Before we get started, we'd just like to congratulate Phil Dyson and his team for being
the seated Eastercon. Reclamation 2022 will be our next British National Science
Fixing Convention and you can go and join now. There is a link in the show notes.
Alison appears to now be eating a bagel with jam on.
There is a long explanation for this. Is it that Steven toasted a bagel and put jam on it?
That's like the last 8% of the long explanation. So if you'd like the rest of it, you can have it,
but we do have a lot to get through. If you want the other 92% of that anecdote,
please come to Octa Thought Live, which will be on 25th April 2021.
And when we will have nothing to talk about in fandom.
[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome to the 29th episode of Octa Thought. A podcast for science fiction and
science fiction fandom. This episode will be going out on the 15th of April 2021. I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty. Today we have two letters of comments,
which is probably because it was Eastercon in between last episode and this episode. And so
people have been busy partying and conventioning and other things.
I would like to say that one of the things that happened at Eastercon is that people
kept coming up to us as saying that they were enjoying the podcast and they thought it was good,
including people that we had had no idea were listening to it at all. So if you're out there,
A, thank you very much. And B, this does not prevent you from writing us letters.
Yes, thank you very much for the compliments, but why don't you write to us? We're very needy.
Now, and there were actually quite a few people who said that they had not realised we were doing
a podcast and have now started listening, which is kind of pleasing because I assumed that, you
know, we had hit our absolutely peak listenership. So it is bewildering that apparently we had not.
But DC wrote to us and said that they were feeling sad at the lack of opportunity at
Eastercon to acquire delicious bits of chocolate late at night from Malcolm. And so they have
attached a photograph of nine bars of lint chocolate to an email to us. And I am very jealous because
I had Reese's peanut butter eggs for my Eastercon experience, which were great, but were not nine
bars of lint chocolate. One of the things about lockdown is that my husband has to service a
greater variety of needs than he might have been required to in pre pandemic time. Family show,
Alison, family show. So as well as his normal requirement to provide me with an Easter egg
over Easter, I let it be known before Easter that it would be very helpful if he also had a number of
boxes of slightly cheap chocolate of the sort that Michael Amorthan's round and also a number of
bars of the sort of chocolate that Malcolm Hutchison hands round to hand and provided me with some
single variety, a couple of different single variety of chocolate. So they were very nice. So thank
you very much, Steve, and you're your age. But this is what I'd recommend. We did go through
Eastercon ago. What does what things do we normally have that had heart-sire Eastercon that we won't
be getting unless we get them ourselves in advance? DC also says in the West Ring reference that they
see me more as a Josh, but that's mainly because they envision me wearing little more than waders
and bleerily asking what's happening. So thanks, DC. Much appreciated. And then they also say best
wishes for the live podcast of OptaThorp, the tech that works. So yes, thanks, DC. We are going to be
doing our live episode next episode, which will be on the 25th of April 2021.
I don't think I have much to add except that obviously John, any time you would like to
answer the podcast wearing only waders. That is totally fine with us. Please don't.
Two very different opinions from my co-hosts on that, interestingly.
And I would also like to highlight DC's tweet to us where they say they're still unconsciously
saying Pete along with John at the end of the podcast. So listeners, you can all join in at home.
Yes. And then other people who tweeted at us were Peter Sullivan, who agrees that having an
overarching ed of communications for a convention is a good thing. Thanks, Peter. I'm glad you think so.
And also volunteered, which is obviously a dangerous thing to do in here sort of John right now.
That is true. That's very true. Jersey Griffin tweeted at us to say ambassador with these
episodes who are really spoiling us, which I think is a chocolate reference. And when tweeted at us
to say that they've just started listening to our podcast, and it's awesome looking forward to your
chat on Father Ted, it will definitely one day happen. Just it might be like, you know, a couple
of years away. We keep recording episodes, which you'd think would be a positive thing.
Yeah, we should explain the Father Ted is our break glass in case it's well, it's part of the
debate on our break glass in case of emergency podcasts, which is ready to be deployed. Should
any of us not be available to podcast one fortnight, but evolving quite reliable so far.
Yes. That's because two of us have not gone anywhere for a year. And that one time I did go
somewhere I did make you podcasts at a different time. Yeah. And basically it's for when me and
Alison are on a beach and Liz is in lockdown, which appears to be the trajectory in which things
are heading, which is a bit weird. I have some beaches in mind and we should book that.
Oh, just be me having a solo podcast. They're just being extremely grumpy while you guys send me,
you know, pitch to the ocean. Fine, it's fine. Margay, Alison Margay, let's get this done.
Oh, I love Margay. Oh, Dreamland, I can take you on the one of Britain's oldest rollercoats,
one of the world's oldest rollercoasters except that the day that I went to Margayate,
specifically so that I could ride the rollercoaster, it was shut.
That is always the way. I will ride on it one day. I'm excited. We did also have a comment from
Duncan McGregor on the diversity of gaming panels. I will say the gaming panel has got a lot more
diverse when the program was finished. So that was good. The program was finished, I would say,
at about noon on Saturday of EasterCon, maybe. But at that point, there was a lot more
like different voices and stuff, which was very good to see. And if anyone is a member who didn't
watch, I really recommend the accessibility on gaming podcast, which has some really interesting
insights from the particular accessibility in games, which was really good.
And then finally, we have a letter from Claire Briarley of Groiden.
So, Claire says, "On your records, John claimed his bowling ball is a round black thing with a
hole in the middle, but anyone who was a teenage reader of smash hits in the 1980s might suspect
that Roy's got there as a licorice also. Taste, offensiveness and legality, well there's another
comedy trio for you, but only you can decide if that's in the right order for you. I wonder if
anyone got confused by the beeps and stopped the podcast before Alison's first hits.
I don't know. I hope not. That would have been 1975, so you know, that's that.
So, if it was taste, offensiveness and legality in order, I'm taste Alison's offensiveness and
Liz's legality. And that doesn't. I don't know. I don't feel it's the worst match up of the three.
Alison's making eyes at me, listener. Not the sort of eyes you're thinking of.
Like googly eyes. Paddington hard stare eyes. No googly eyes. I'm telling you.
And then Claire says, "I am safe from Jerry sending me more weed to mix," says John.
Famous last words, worth repeating. Well, I have just repeated them, so well played Claire.
But also, Jerry, please don't send me weed to mix. I would feel bad about the carbon footprint
of that wee mix. We're going to talk about a topic in which we all sincerely and deeply believe.
And that is Esther's Cat, Badger. Badger the cat is obviously the best cat in science fiction
fandom. If you are listening to this thinking, "My cat is better," you are wrong. Badger is better.
He's best cat. I have no skin in this game because unlike some of my co-hosts, I don't
personally have a cat. So I can say that Badger is absolutely magnificent. He is a cat amongst cats.
He is peerless in his majesty. He's quite the cat. He is perfect. He is excellent and handsome
and high virtue and in need of praise. And he has given his name to a very, very, very tiny kitten,
who hopefully can spend its life hoping to live up to the badgeriness of Big Badger.
Yes. And as Esther notes, Badger is probably licking his bum right now, and he will be doing
so in a glorious and fantastic way. I'm sure he could give lessons to other cats in how to lick their bottoms.
I think we would all agree that if T.S. Eliot were still with us, the cat he would be writing about
is Badger the Cat. But alas, he is not with us and so I have had to compose my own ode to Badger.
Oh Badger Cat, you are so large and fond of sunbeams to recharge your energy. So when it's late,
at Esther's jigsaw's lie in state, you sit on them with mighty weight because you are the best roommate.
Badger, we love you. Badger's the best cat. Thank you very much to Esther for giving an enormous amount
of money to the fanfons at the fanfon auction. Esther is as good a fan as Badger is a cat.
Right, so launching in to the topics. We have thought about confusion. For those who don't know,
confusion was the Eastercon of 2021, which occurred at Easter, which is last weekend as we record.
We went to Eastercon. It was very like Eastercon. No, more like Eastercon than I was expecting.
Yes. I got too drunk every day and stayed up till 2am.
Yep, I did too. But it was also like Eastercon sufficiently much that I do wonder when the
committee sat down and said, "It's not going to feel proper lie-like Eastercon unless we have a
mad panic trying to get everything working in the first day of the convention." We have thoughts
about confusion and what went well and what went badly. And we're going to kind of tackle them in
kind of theme by theme and go through and say kind of the things we liked and the things we
didn't like so much. So the first thing we're going to discuss is Eastercon's communications.
So I think Eastercon's communications strategy was idiosyncratic for an Eastercon. I think it
relied on video and social media to an extent that we have not seen from previous Eastercons.
In some ways that's a very modern take on how to convey information and in some ways I think
that's to be applauded. But in other ways I think the reliance on video as a medium
did frustrate some people, especially those people for whom video is not an accessible medium.
And that was an interesting choice. And one I think that if I was going to do communications
for an Eastercon I would probably not be doing it by video as a result. The other kind of hallmark
of the Eastercon communication strategies I saw it was a desire to keep things very close to their
chest. So we didn't find out until quite close to the convention that they were planning to use
GAVA and kind of a lot of things like program items started to be trailed in the two weeks before
the convention which was quite close to the convention. And that was again that was a decision that I
think they made to kind of stoke anticipation. But I think in some quarters that I was seeing
discussion it was actually stoking worry which I think was not what they were trying to achieve.
And so I think my two takeaways from their communication strategy is that secrecy is I
think probably overrated. I think it's better to have people getting excited about all the cool
stuff you're doing rather than getting excited about all the cool stuff you might announce eventually.
And it's also probably better not to focus on methods of dissemination that are
potentially accessibility issues. I think I broadly agree with you. I think that where I disagree
about video is that using video would be absolutely the right way when they had for example videos
introducing like GAVA as a platform. And those kind of tutorial videos I think are really helpful.
Like I know for punctuation we did kind of very sort of text and screenshot heavy instructions on
how you are going to access our different platforms. But it was maybe the video introducing things
that was the most useful for people to go and go and watch. But I agree that if you're going to do
that one I think you need to really try and have a transcript up at the same time because there's
nothing worse than having a video playing and finding that everyone else is kind of you know able to
look at this video and get all the information out. And if videos are not accessible to you then
you're sort of left in the dark and you don't want any. If you want to get people excited you don't
want them to be sad because they can't be excited with long with everyone else because you haven't
provided the information and media making access. And yeah just to sort of general overline some
video and also kind of the expectation that we're going to do weekly videos and then it was sort
of there were three videos and then they stopped. I think it was a bit of a problem because you're
sort of waiting for the next video and thinking oh well I'm sure there'll be more detail in the
next video but there wasn't the next video. And maybe if you had an easier sort of more text-based
strategy it's less effort. You wouldn't have to be waiting to try and make a video and it's
good that some of the people who are making the videos were also the people who were trying to do
the rest of the convention. So I think there's ways you could do videos but do them in a slightly
different way that would be more helpful. That's actually a phenomenal point which I hadn't considered
which is the point about if you're going to make videos which are quite difficult and quite
intensive I lack the skill to do them which is why we did not do them for punctuation. Having
someone do them that is not also either trying to run every part of the communications or trying
to build the tech stack is probably a good thing. So yes very very good point Alison.
So I ran social media for Mankynicon which was six years ago now but we actually had to stop our
social media strategy before it really got going because the convention was clearly going to fill
its space but one of the reasons that was was the social media strategy which was basically
we won't think about it too hard but we will keep tweeting out and and sharing interesting things
with membership was was actually generating all the buzz that we needed and the convention would be
full. This convention didn't do that so you talked about them relying on social media but they
they hardly tweeted at all or made any posts in the first five months of running the convention.
So there's about one post a month until you get to the point where they say we're going virtual
and then there was nothing more after that for about three months and I this is the point where I
go if I had done it I would have tried to do it differently and I think part of what went wrong
for them there is that they were being very concerned about controlling the message so that
they didn't give the I'm surmising I don't know how to talk to Zoe about this if you're listening
Zoe please get in touch and tell all or to actually don't tell all just tell the nice bits.
I didn't feel that they had a social media tomb who felt empowered which is a very crappy
management word but didn't feel able to just have that slight frivolity that you need in order to
do social media well that you need to be able to go with whatever the flow of this is happening
at the time and you need to be quite regular about it and you don't need to make sure that
every single word has been cleared back through the committee and chair because it's quite easy
to take things down and apologize if you stuff up obviously you don't want to do it too spectacularly.
What that led to was partly it it reflected this kind of sense of secrecy that we weren't being
told because they actually didn't want Eastacom members to know what the Eastacom was going to
be like which is weird especially if not if you're trying to build membership they were kind of like
we're desperate to get more members it's going to be great but without actually telling anyone
anything about anything it's very hard to make that happen but also when they do kind of go
we're not telling you anything but the theme is fun and whimsy and you've just had eight months or
ten months of a social media strategy that has never once showed the slightest
twinge of fun or whimsy that that provides a kind of disconnect in the in the readers and the
members that make them go fun whimsy is that is that what you're about that's not what we get
and in fact they did have their actual branding was quite fun and whimsical they had like rocket
ships and cute fountains and all of that cuteness that was that was doing that but but I think
unless your communications reflect that all the way through people aren't really going to believe
you and I think that's what happened I think people didn't believe they were going to have fun
if they came to the convention and a lot of people didn't come as a result so so I it's not how I
would have done it yeah I think that all seems fair and I think this is one thing when people
think they've got an excellent thing that they need to surprise people with they forget that actually
secrecy is not the most important thing the most important thing is excitement and there is more
than one way to generate excitement and one of those things is by telling people why they should
be excited and I think that is almost the antithesis of secrecy and they're both valid
ways of doing it but when it becomes people if it becomes clear that people are more
aggravated than excited about your secrecy that might be the point of which you switch
tack perhaps and I think what you were saying Alison about the lack of flexibility and responsiveness
in social media is slightly I think touching on that and I think I think it's probably fair for
me to share this on the podcast now so I I actually approached Eastcom before we ran punctuation to
set up the discord and I did most of the initial work on their discord but I eventually left the
team because I was working under Zoe as the kind of head of social media but I I was not able to
have discussions with her at which decisions were made because decisions had to be passed back
up the chain so it'd be a week between me suggesting something and me hearing from Zoe whether or
not that was something we could do and I just found it so frustrating that I eventually left
because I was like I can't I just feel like I'm moving through treacle and I'm not used to that
kind of thing in a in something like running a discord or a social media thing where I feel
like responsiveness is is an incredibly key component of doing that and that's not a slight
on how they did it necessarily but it was definitely something I felt was not fun for me.
I have one more point on surprise and then let's get have a go which is that there are some sorts
of surprise that are lovely like when I left the United States when I was 18 my friends can try
to give me a massive surprise party on my last night and I was not expecting it at all and that's
a lovely surprise. When I am thinking about how to attend an event I haven't attended before the
information about how you're going to get there how you're going to park what the arrangements are
for meals where you camp or in this case how you log on to this exactly what services you're going
to be using exactly what sort of computer you'll need these are not part of a lovely surprise
so they should have been extremely much more open and earlier with things like these you'll be
doing it in a browser you'll need a computer that's got these sorts of specs to make it work here are
the problems that other people sometimes have with these programs and the ways in which you
can solve them lots of lots of that I've just been past a link that I haven't managed to follow yet
for a convention that used Gather that that has a single page with very clear instructions for all
parts of the convention on it and I'm like oh that's good and and and Easter can't have these things
but I don't think they released them until like the Friday a lot more different if we'd actually
handle that material one week earlier and this isn't again it's not the fault for the publications
lead because it was the fault of decisions not being made early enough because so many
decisions had to be made at committee level the next thing we're going to talk about is
technology at the East Com so we're going to segregate this into two different technologies
we're going to segregate into streaming technology so the stuff they use to deliver their program
panels and then we're going to also discuss social technology basically the discord and the Gather
so let's start with the streaming technology East Com was very quiet about what tech stack
they were using but I had a couple of meetings with Keith Smith who was the head of tech just a bit
a few days before the Easter Com where he surfaced quite a lot of that in the meeting and also
Zoe mentioned that they were using one one element of that thing which is is red B which is a very
high-end content distribution system that like the BBC uses and things like that they were also
using a program called VMix as the kind of front-end mixer and overall there were many I heard
22 Keith said 22 to me different programs in the stack that got you from you in your house out to
the person on the stream and they decided I think this was a committee level decision rather than a
decision in tech that they were going to use this stack for all of their programs so essentially
every program item apart from a few readings in Gather was going to be done by running it through
this stack and that meant that it ended up getting used for quite a lot of events that would have
been much better with a more interactive technology and this is partly because the convention had a
huge vision the committee had a bit vision of what the convention would be like and how it would
operate that meant that they then didn't always make the right decision for particular program
items about how they would best run and this is effectively mostly with the fanfans auction where
people had stream lag of up to two minutes which made it very difficult for them to bid on things
it was a very successful auction the tech crew and prog ops worked with us incredibly hard to make
it good it was you know and as did as did the actual fanfans teams but the they should not have
had to do that amount of work and it would have just been much better running zoom it's just
about an example of something where the tech stack was far too ambitious for the thing that was being
was being streamed and it would have been better if it hadn't been streamed at all other conventions
have dealt with this by having everything on interactive technologies like zoom or by having
much simpler streaming stacks i think this is the most complicated streaming stack that any
virtual convention has tried and i think the result was that nobody was trained so once it
worked it worked pretty well for most things not the fanfans auction but for most things it worked
really well but that nobody was trained i think the mistake they made was that they bought an
awful lot of technologies that were paid for by the minute or by the hour rather than buying
technologies that were bought by the month for instance and then they decided that it would be
a waste of money to pay for those far enough in advance of the convention to properly onboard
volunteers with how those technologies worked and i think one of those two decisions was a huge
mistake i don't know which one and i wasn't privy to the discussions in the convention
but certainly i think if your tech stack and your budget for your tech stack requires that
the first time you start training people on it is the day of the convention then that is a tech
stack that is not going to work well with the net effect that the convention effectively started
a day late because the program items on friday and saturday morning just didn't really work and
i'm sympathetic so i asked a question in the feedback session about why didn't you use something
like stream yard and keith very reasonably said well stream yard didn't offer everything we needed
and i will say that i'm sure that is true but the advantage they would have
the advantage they would have had with stream yard is that it is paid by the month and so they
would have had the ability to familiarize their staff and so i am wondering and the question i
asked is is the features that you got from this tech stack that you couldn't have got with more
simple tools worth the human cost to your volunteers and attendees because there was one and it seems
like you're prioritizing bells and whistles over stressing people out on the day they're trying
to get their program to work and that i think is something we've seen spill over onto for example
the anonymous claire discord and in a lot of the discussion of what was happening at the convention
i think i agree both you and you have stolen some of my talking points um i think i want to say that
there's nothing wrong with being ambitious like they are right in that you know certainly
some conventions have used very simple methods you either have a big zoom room or you have one of
the simpler simpler streaming methods like stream yard or so on and they are limited and they do
have issues and particularly they identify i think that you can't really play long videos within
stream yard you then have to go and you know play them off another basically off another tab
which works okay um but not always and and it's things like you know we can note a punctuation that
one of our items basically got dropped from youtube because we were trying to play short video clips
off something else and they got pulled which is not a not going to be a problem if you're running
your own content distribution but yeah i think it's obvious that there was kind of a big mismatch
between the ambition they had and the actual amount of person time they could afford to budget to pull
it off and then what is interesting is i don't know when they chose to use that tech setup and it
feels to me that either they needed to put more money into the tech setup in order to have more
time to familiarize themselves with it but that again would have made them an extremely
expensive streaming only convention or they need at some point to make the decision of
okay we can't do all these things we're going to have to say no we're going to run things
slightly differently and cut some of that out and i know that's really hard to do especially
lay on but you've got to wonder sort of are you so committed to doing this thing that you keep
carrying on even when it's becoming obvious that it's not quite going to pull off and i should say
also that from about saturday afternoon most things were working perfectly well and if everything
had worked that well from friday morning it would have just been you know the occasional hiccup the
occasional stream that needed restarting or rebooting and it would have been fine it only became so
obvious when you know we got saturday morning and i was doing program ops on an item which was not
being broadcast live we were just doing it on the assumption that we could record it and then some
people might watch it later which meant there were no questions because that people would have
to ask questions without seeing the item and things like that in case this ever happens to you in the
future i have a tip which is that i went into the discord halfway through my item being recorded
without the chance of everyone for anyone to be asked questions and i went into this
court and said obviously you can't see what we said so far but does anyone have any questions and we
came up with half a dozen really good questions so you know i mean i did ask for them but that was
a slightly different item like you can't ask for questions on a it was the item about like um
what is punk in fiction and it was an extremely sort of free form wide range discussion and there
was no way to predict like from the description where the panelists would take it and what
be sent for questions to ask and then i think it would be even worse if i'd said well we have a
question here is a question it relates to nothing at all you said on the panel what would you like
to answer anyway you may be better off not even having the questions at that point yeah and like i
say this all comes back to their decisions the decisions that they made not to have that day of
training which would have made it all fine and it's something we were telling them up to the convention
and i was doing my best to stay optimistic and sort of saying you know we're being very critical
but i'm sure they've got it under control and then it's after the convention and they didn't and
you know that is a problem and i don't know whose problem it was but i think it think it's worth
coming back to and saying yeah that that is something you can't do that does make the beginning of your
convention full of argument stress and bad feeling instead of full of excitement joy and happiness
which is the feelings i associate with her convention and the feelings you should be aiming
to instill um a really crystallizing moment for me was when we were in the newsletter on Saturday
morning and they just decided that they were going to not run program on Saturday morning
and i said well you know what it seems like an odd choice to say we're going to take the program
down completely when it would take 200 quid and about 20 minutes to get to the entire thing set up
on zoom and uh lina there's been a lot of discussion about there's been a lot of fallout about
easter con and the sorts of decisions that were made and why all over my smeads and in one of them
lina thane clark said and i thought this was very wise um it's all very well um members coming up
with buckets of water but sometimes from the point of view of the committee they're just coming along
with buckets of paraffin to throw on the fire and i feel that my suggestion that i could pick the
whole thing up and put it on zoom in 20 minutes might have been one of those buckets of paraffin i
think it was a bucket of water i feel like they got into a hole and they carried on digging out
that hole rather than going oh no let's get the convention up and running and then we can and
then we can sort the the whizzy stuff out in the background while we just meanwhile run the
convention using a less good system but you know that's me and not them so obviously i do respect
their right to decide it was better have no program at all and one that wasn't perfect i also have
one point about the particular tech stack that they ended up with which is that it was possible for
random people on being given a link by saying overtired program ops member of staff or because
tech ops are given the wrong link to program ops or because they just clicked the wrong link in
their email and find themselves parachuted live onto a totally different program item
thereby bumping off someone who was on that program item and for me that was not fit for
purpose you should not be able to do that is that okay yeah i think i think that's all fair and i
think ultimately it's very difficult to second guess the decisions they made in the heat in the
moment and i don't want to i i don't want to nitpick decisions that were made kind of on Saturday
morning when they were trying to put all the fires out because i i do want to say i think i think
they should have done things differently in terms of the lead up but i don't want to say that
i know what they should have done then because i think that was an incredibly difficult thing
because obviously the counterpoint to well you could just do it through zoom which is possibly
true is that then you don't get on holodeck so i think you've got a um it's a difficult question
right and one we're talking about um for punctuation to washermat that was hope um he's like is it more
important why don't you get you just record the zoom i don't know how difficult that would have been
and you don't either it may have been difficult to do it across all the program items we know they
managed it for the bid session but they may not have been you know there to snap into action have
seven people record them and ready yeah yeah they did of course take a very long time to get
stuff onto holodeck anyway so that's another thing that it was not because of all the other
problems attack it it it didn't cut up get up and running as fast as ideally you do want stuff on
holodeck within a couple of hours i think probably so the next thing that we're going to pull out
and discuss in a little bit more detail is gather which was the conventions primary kind of virtual
space slash social space um i know we've discussed this on previous shows but it's basically sort of
looks like a little sort of uh top-down 8-bit video game style uh layout where you pick a little
avatar and there's a physical space that you can wander around and as you wander close to people
their video is an audio pop-up so you can hear them and as you wander further away they get
quieter and drift away and confusion has set it up with a really kind of nice big elaborate sort of
space space station setup um and it had lots of cool little things it had all the rooms where you
could watch the program in in gather if you wanted to you know and go and find like the art show and
a little dealers room but it also had cool things like uh there was an observation dome um there
were as an alboretum where of course we all kept leaving our avatars hiding under trees
there were hidden things like hidden rooms and mazes and shortcuts and teleportation and just
generally like clearly an awful lot of effort had gone into producing it but i'm not sure i used
that much of the stuff they've made yes i think that's probably a fair point i have things
okay so i i really wish proximity chat worked it almost does there's quite a few different
place things in the space i've been told about a new one i need to go try gathers
not quite there yet but that i loved you know you could wander past somebody in the corridor and
stop for a conversation and and that feels that feels like an experience i have hugely missed for
the last year and i loved being able to do that i mean i do like gather a lot and i liked gather here
but gathers primarily a social tool and so therefore when you're designing and building the gather
i think the energy should go into designing the social spaces i don't think most people care about
tardis isn't his and major mazes and you know things like the arborita was very nice
so so scenery i think is is probably quite useful but i think a lot of the easter eggs
didn't work as well as they thought people didn't make us spend as much time exploring the gather
because people are mostly there to see their friends and i think i would have liked to have seen
more energy put into thinking how you engineer social spaces in gather so that you can so they
work as effectively as possible and and i don't feel that that was the and i guess this is very
much a personal choice rather the conventions choice but it's um i don't feel that didn't feel
to me to be where the center of the energy in designing the gather went that's yeah i think that's
fair um i really enjoyed the gather space in general um i think that i i was always i think the most
optimistic of the three of us about the use of gather because i've used it professionally and
usually enjoyed it in that context but i think the moment at which it kind of crystallized for me
that actually i really enjoyed this was when i was going from newsletter to the dealer's room to
ask someone a question and i bumped into um mark and come with the other person was but mark plumber
and someone else were talking in the corridor and i bumped into them when we had a chat and i said
hi and we all kind of chat for five minutes and then someone from the newsletter pinged me on this
go to be like oikox and where have you gone and i got on with what i was supposed to be doing um
and but i think that it was that kind of thing where i was like this is the sort of thing that
happens at a real convention that has not happened to me in any zoom or discord i've been on and i
do think that that mode of interaction is a good one and and having a tool that can capture that
is wonderful i now want to launch into the pessimistic bit gather needs to sort out their
accessibility story and it's bananas to me that they haven't done it kind of made sense in april
2020 that they hadn't done because they were very new and everything was moving very quickly but
look at how much work zoom has done to substantially improve their offering in the last year and
compare and contrast together and you're like what are they doing there are key low hanging no not
low hanging fruit there are key requirements for members of our community to be able to access
services that gather just have not bothered to implement and that is and i think they need to
he said as an able-bodied white guy but like it really frustrates me because i want the whole
community to feel able to partake in this tool that i enjoyed using and it really i feel uncomfortable
suggesting it for conventions i want to run because i know that i'm being exclusionary if i do so
despite the fact that i enjoyed it for me i really really wish that it was accessible to everyone
if you're out there listening to octa thought and you know of a proximity chat system that has a
good accessibility story to tell which would certainly include working on mobiles and tablets
please um can you get in touch because i am actively trying out every one i can find at the moment
yes that would be very good of course i too love i love proximity chat i think it's really good
i think i think my final thought and gather is that i also think it's very difficult to design a space
where you intend there to be sort of several hundreds at max little avatars running around
when you're trying to design it probably with a very smaller set of people to test it so i mean i
like the big spaces in the gather but they are horrendous for slowing down my system such that i
had to put on quiet mode so i didn't see everyone's proximity videos or i just couldn't move around
but then when i got in some of the smaller spaces it felt a bit like oh now is now actually a little
bit small and everyone's trying to squeeze around a table so i'm not sure that you know i think we
say it would have been nice if they could have done different things to it but i think this
was very much a sort of first experiment and i don't blame them for trying what they did and then
i'm sure if they had to redesign it they would do things differently and i will just very quickly
note that part of my um screed about accessibility should have been i do wish gather was not a
web app because i think it would be much more accessible to people on less well-spected computers
if it was being written in kind of native code and not being done in a web stack because at the
moment it's very CPU intensive and then there was the discord and the discord was good it wasn't big
enough and what this led to was every time someone said oh hey i wish you had this channel i posted a
link to anonymous claire which had that channel and then people joined anonymous claire with the net
effect that we have about 50 new members over the weekend so if you're listening to this because
you've seen me link it on anonymous claire hello welcome we're happy you're here we like to the
hoyland uh watch along isn't it fun having all these people here oh boy oh boy oh golly i i just had
a word with somebody who's worked on nine world's tech and i said anyone else who's ever worked on
nine words tech would probably be very welcome on an anonymous claire so it's possible that
anonymous claire is just going to kind of generally grow now until it becomes a focal point for uk
fandom and i for one would be very happy about that um we're not going to put a link in the
show notes but if you don't yet have an invite to anonymous claire get in touch with one of us
and we'll see you straight i'm very happy with that except i realized i started being a waterway
term anonymous claire when it had like six members and now i need to consider the fact that it may have
uh i don't know 250 members i will say that while i feel the anonymous claire discord
definitely filled a niche for what people wanted at easter con it was a shame that it couldn't have
been provided through easter con it feels a bit like they got a discord and we know from
punctuation that you have to work quite hard to get your members onto discords a lot of the time
and so you'd only have part of the membership there but then felt that actually during easter it
would be too hard to try and keep the discord running as well and so they wanted people to move
together except that then the discord did keep running and it seemed like the easiest way to
get any sort of tech problems or other issue solve was to come and mention them on discord so
it felt a bit like it was sort of an official but unofficial space it was it was the formal help
test for the convention they didn't really have an ops room that you went to get help with they
did have that but as i think Liz noted when john dod said people aren't coming to the ops room and
we've got loads of people who could help you there and Liz quite rightly said yes but if i'm watching
a program item in program room one that isn't working i could either walk to the ops room and
ask you about it or i could copy and paste things into this box that is here while i am in that
program room and i do wonder i think this is one of the very good examples of where the easter con
did not correctly assess how they could use the fact they were virtual in ways that did not limit
themselves to the like physical space limitations they would usually have because one of the great
benefits of virtual is that the help desk can be like disconnected from the physical space of
the convention in a way that makes it more accessible and i think the fact that we saw the discord
so full of people asking ops questions and the ops room was apparently according to the manager
of ops always completely empty for the whole weekend really shows that this is one way in which
people are quite happy to take advantage of the fact it's virtual and not limited to physical space
i think the other thing that they tried to replicate sort of a physical easter con in gather was by
having ops rovers so there were ops rovers i think wandering around the gather the problem is because
gather doesn't let you kind of sort the list of people there in any way the only way to find the
ops rover was sort of to scroll through this list of names and find out who would tag themselves
ops rover and it was nowhere near as useful as if you're at an actual convention and you can go
and find a person carrying a radio and wearing a sash and figure out who is in charge of things
so that i think was a physical thing that just doesn't carry over and and didn't feel useful you
could just have the ops rover hanging around in ops and if you got a message through saying
you know help someone stuck it in a tree in the arboretum you could then send their little avatar
over i don't think you could get stuck in a tree in the arboretum but wouldn't it be cool if you could
it was clearly a design choice from the convention to replicate the physical convention
as far as they possibly could and this worked well for me in some ways because it meant that when
we asked them if we could have a newsletter room they were like oh yeah yeah you could have a newsletter
room and that turned out to be quite useful for us because it was quite a nice place to to hang out
and do newsletter and talk to people with newsletter items and so on but it also meant that they made
some decisions that were frankly really terrible like paying for i assume a program called zello
which implements walkie talkie functionality between staff now most staff i mean walkie talkies have
been a bit of a an unpleasant essential at least comes for some time but if you have a discord where
you can type things you you don't really need a walkie talkie system because you can just check
the discord and then one other thing on discord which is there have been a lot of different virtual
conventions over the last year and they've run in lots of different ways but one thing that's I think
almost everyone would agree with is that having text threads that collect all the thoughts that have
the people have during and after program items and that you can go in later and go
oh that looks like a good program item i should catch it on replay um i mean those those are
incredibly positive and i've i think easter con not having them when they could perfectly well have
them was i think a kind of a monumental goal and and i think they thought that gather chat would be
reasonably a good reasonably good alternative to discord chat but gather chat isn't persistent
it only kind of happens when you're ready to then the only thing you see is your chatter that it
only saves so many messages so so you can't actually go all the way back through your chat so it doesn't
create a record of information on a topic um so i think that was a bit of a mistake and i think they
didn't need to make it it's not very hard to moderate discords for easter con type people i think
big discord servers with ordinary people on them not ordinary people thought again big discord
servers with teenage gamers on speed on them can be quite hard to moderate because they can be an
awful lot of kind of spammy threads and meme threads and people posting completely outrageous
stuff and i think if you've come from discord from that direction you can be quite surprised by how
sedate convention discords tend to be so um let's talk program and art show um so i liked the program
uh the bits that i saw kind of after saturday morning i thought good and i enjoyed um some of
the program items very much um and i thought the art show was fantastic they used a piece of
software called const matrix um which was cool um and let you kind of imagine that you were in a
real art gallery uh my one criticism of const matrix is that i think it introduced a disconnect
between viewing the art and buying the art that i think um especially my my wife was a bit curious
as to how well the popularity of the art show had converted into sales for artists i do not know
how well it did that so if you are an artist who exhibited and sold things or didn't sell things at
east con please do write in and let us know how you feel that went because we'd be very interested
um the program i thought was very good the panel items i saw were very cool you could watch them by
going to the room in gather and kind of watching them in the room there um but what actually happened was
if you are on a Mac and you watch things as a video in safari you can pop it out and have it as a
little window that like hovers over all your other windows in the corner of your screen and so i was
kind of wandering around uh the gather or doing the newsletter or whatever with the program item just
kind of constantly playing in my upper right hand corner and that was amazing i really liked that
we'll just call you chris gossier chris didn't even lock us this time allison so frankly he's
persona non grata until he gets back on the horse you know who did lock us clair bryley of croydon
right anyway so um yeah but in general i really like them i have no real criticisms of either thing
other than that very small question about um comparing into art sales so i would say that actually
how i watched the program a lot of time is sometimes i had it open on the second screen on my desktop
because i've got a laptop and desktop setup oh fancy um i actually discovered that if i
logged into program on the browser on my amazon tv stick that worked perfectly well it wouldn't work
on my playstation for some reason and it wouldn't work on my chrome cast for some reason but it was
quite happy with the random amazon browser anyway so that that worked fine um so i did that quite a
lot uh a few items i will call out for being particularly good is oh i really enjoyed the hay
lecture which was about sort of um forensic archaeology and about burial practices and it was really
interesting and there is a horrible analogy about popcorn i recommend you go and look up
uh this is probably alison and john because i should say the program is only available till the 12th
of april and we'll be down by the time you listen to this podcast but you know they also had a couple
of panels which i'm not sure where the panelists were but they may have been difficult to pull
together so many experts at an easter con i think they did make good use of the virtuality of the
convention by getting some people to pop in for a panel or a couple of items who you would definitely
not normally see at an easter con and who very much enhanced the easter con so i thought that was
pretty good quite clever good choice good good choice of panelists on lots and lots of items
the one i was specifically pulled out that i i watched later on actually and enjoyed was panel
about jinnyong works in place in chinese literature which is about hong kong's most famous novelist
who i was not aware of before the convention um but now might go and try and check out some
translations and there are yeah there were just generally quite a few good program items there
are also fun ones i watched the one which is like is it about 80s pop lyric or a warhammer 40k
space marine uh line and uh yeah it was very cleverly done because obviously some of them were
were one only that are both sometimes and also included ones that the people on the panel
had written and occasionally forgotten so that was quite fun um
excellent and they all work fine it also may realize it's so that you can do a sort of virtual
fun quiz show because you don't need to have like buzzers you can just have everywhere on the
panel has like i think they had little um like ray toy ray guns that made a noise and so you could
use that to be like your buzzer and you could just have them at home and you just suddenly hold
up your little buzzer and buzz in so that was neat um i did really enjoy the art show i mean i wasn't
in the market for buying any art this year because art car i'd have to get the art ship thousands of
hours from me which seemed impractical so i didn't really notice the lack of linkage between art show
and being able to buy the art but i i really enjoyed the way you could just kind of go to an artist's
site and just you know enjoy clicking through and have a sort of guided tour of all their art
and i did enjoy that um yeah for Alex Stora who designed the gatherer and also had an exhibit in
the art show he does a lot of music and so you can just play the music and there's absolutely no
problem with that and imagine trying to do that in a regular easter con art show it you know you'd
have to have like three people sharing pairs of headphones whatever it would just be terrible
whereas in the virtual one it's like yeah you want to show videos you want to have music go for it
so that was really nice
i think it's the alice it's the alice and segment of the podcast i think now
i want to talk a bit a little bit about how to cherry stecons but i did that actually i've i've
it turns out from a few weeks before the convention we were talking here about it in octa thought but
because i do a lot of different things in fandom and therefore i i get involved in lots of different
areas of convention i kept asking different areas of conventions about things that included things
where i was working on the convention and i needed support from the convention to do what i wanted
to do and didn't want to be interfered with um and also areas where i was bringing things to the
convention and so wanted some information about how the bits of the convention i was bringing things
to would work and areas where i had information for them and i was like do you want to do some of
this stuff on your social media and what what i was finding was that there's a lot of work in
an easter come particularly in the last four or five weeks and what i was finding was that
every single decision no matter how tiny had to be made at committee level and that doesn't mean
that a committee member made the decision what you would get is you'd be in conversation with committee
members and they'd be going i cannot make that decision it has to be made in full committee
we didn't have a bid for 2023 but it wasn't really a terrible problem if we didn't because
it's only 2021 now so we could bid next year but then about three days before three or four days
before the easter con somebody asked if anyone knew anything about a 2023 bid and Vanessa said
yes and i formed a think and my think was i don't think Vanessa should get another
turn at this just because um just because she wants it because she hasn't had a chance to
chair a physical convention yet i i'm not totally reversed for Vanessa running the easter con in
2023 but i thought she should take to where to have a little think about it and so i started
sounding out other people um about their experiences of working on this convention about their
experiences of working with Vanessa and um and i started thinking about the possibility that we
might need to say at the bidding session oh you know what you should take some time to reflect and so
i asked i think two days before the convention how you'd go about um expressing the fact that you
wanted to speak at the bidding session and i didn't get an answer and other people started asking on
by behalf whether this was going to get answered i didn't put them up to it they just kind of asked
and that we didn't get an answer and then during the convention obviously they were too busy on
Thursday and Friday but by Saturday they were i was kind of going how are we going to speak at the
bidding session they were kind of like an eventually we found out that it was going to be a secure
zoom where you could type in a 160 character um comments and i felt well actually that's not the
way our community works and and that caused me to coalesce around the notion that i really need
to speak up and say something on behalf of all the people who weren't getting to speak and when i
asked the convention if i they could make provision for me to speak they said no you can only speak
if you're a bid and this at that point i thought that was just plain wrong so i wrote a speech and
i bid for 2023 and the speech is on answerable so you could go and read it because that seemed like
um nailing it to the church door of fandom was the comment that somebody else used about their
rant which is not like my rant but it was it's a speech about what you should do if you're
chair and obviously i was coming at it from the point of view of it felt to me like i was not seeing
evidence that vinescent was doing enough of these things but it's a general speech about what i think
a convention church do and i think it's pretty good which is why i've left it lying around despite
the fact that it has had its purpose which was to push the east to come bid off for another year
um i feel like a lot of things that i felt didn't go well about this convention were down to not
doing the things i talked about in that speech and a lot of this podcast has also been um it was very
uncomfortable to do that because i felt like i was standing up and plunging all fandom into war
she was um my friends have been very kind but i'm sure my enemies are not being very kind so if this
is you i all i really wanted to achieve was to just put off that decision and i think
so i just want to jump in here and tell you what your speech was in the true manner of a white
vanish male go on i need a mansplain oh it was more in my opinion it was more than you just explaining
why the bid needed to be pushed back it was a neat summarization of all the reasons that people
had been disgruntled with this east con in the last year in a easy to understand package which
made people think oh like from from my perspective anyway i had been feeling frustrated annoyed and
disenfranchised by this east con but i i don't think i could have put quite my finger on why and i think
if you listen to the last ooh 26 episodes of octa thought you can probably hear that although i talk
about it a lot i'm not sure i'm particularly good at saying it's these five things that they're not
doing and when i watched you give that speech it just all clicked and i'll say yes that's exactly why
that's why i feel dissatisfied that's why i feel disenfranchised and that's what i want the east
con to be and so i think it wasn't just a speech delivered to explain why the bid needed to be
pushed back to 2022 but it was also a statement of i would say that it would be a very good foundational
document for what it is we hope to achieve as a community and that's why i think the analogy of
nailing it to the church door is so apt because i think it is the sort of document that deserves
to be nailed to the church door of fandom and so i i do think in fact you are selling yourself
slightly short because i think it was a very good encapsulation of a lot of things i feel about east
con as i said my friends supporters would be very kind to me okay so i mean i i'm sure that there
are people who don't feel that way i if you think at this point i am a quite grumpy person who was
just being grumpy and and Vanessa absolutely deserves another shot right now without a period
of reflection then why don't you in the after times by me a drink and i'll tell you why you're wrong
the other thing is although i am sure and i think this comes down to um whenever you get people
who are disagreeing with you i think it is very difficult for anyone not i'm not i'm so i'm going
to say me personally if i say something and someone i know says no you are wrong and i am annoyed and
here are the reasons i think you're wrong it is often very difficult for me to tell whether i am
at the edge of the bell curve and i am very unusual in thinking what i think and they are very typical
and thinking what they think or the reverse and i think that's true in any disagreement you don't know
how widely felt um either viewpoint is and i think so when we were criticizing east con in the run up
you could plausibly have said that the loudest voices in the chorus of people criticizing east con
were people who are us or people who are friends with us and so i think if you are running east con
you could quite plausibly have said well yes but this is just ten people with like a stick up their
ass so we probably don't need to treat their opinions as representative i think what the bid
session showed quite neatly because 16% of people voted for Vanessa in 2023 10% of people voted for
you in 2023 and 69% of people voted to hold over and i think what that shows quite neatly is that
it isn't a case that it's 10 or 15 people who are very loud in east con fandom who had these
reservations but it is a large segment of fandom who felt this disenfranchisement and i think if
that wasn't the case then 2023 would be settled now and and your um and people would not have voted
to hold over the vote until next year so i think the fact that people did vote for that means that
although i'm sure that like there is a component here of your friends are being very kind to you
and your enemies are probably not i do think that indicates that on some level a large segment of
of the people in that meeting did sympathize more with the way you framed that and i i do think it
is important that we don't be too um self-effacing about that because i think it's an important point
which is it's not that you made a speech and everyone just ignored you you made a speech that resonated
i did pull some skills that i gained in my previous professional job to do that um that have been
lying dormant waiting for a suitable outlet for quite a long time um so you know that was quite nice um
i think i was i am serious i mean i joked about i'll tell you what i'm wrong but i am very up for if
you're listening to this you're thinking allison is full of beans i am full of beans and also yeah
i am very very happy to to have a chat i think what i will say is that was probably one of the
strange easter-comped sessions i've been to um not that i've been to that many used to
combin sessions but it was unexpected and that's it i think like it's not something i would encourage
people to to do at bid sessions is to to stand up and bid in order that they can kind of pin their
personal philosophy of easter-con to a church door but you were left with no other way to do that
because of the way they'd done it and i think that you know if i think there were lots of ways
they could have headed off you ending up at the point where you felt you had to actually bid for
an easter-con and pledged to be run more than necessary in order to make your point and i think
that maybe just comes across again the the fact that everything seemed to be quite tightly controlled
and communications quite tightly controlled and part of that was obviously not really wanting the
bid session to turn into lots of random chatter and try and keep everything neat and tidy and
and questioned through one channel where there was like a character restriction um and so yeah you
ended up basically standing up and pronouncing with philosophy of the easter-con and i was a bit
tense because i was like i don't know because in a normal bid session i could gauge the audience
and i can see who's there and and who do i know and who are these people and do they seem to be
like yeah yeah going along with it or are they like what is this woman doing once you just get
off the stage so we can vote and you don't have that feeling in a virtual one and so when it came
down to like actually okay 70 70 percent of people have said yeah let's hold it over think about this
and come back next year and and really bid in it i was like phew because that made me feel like the
community is supporting Alice in statement which i also very much support and i think
sorry Alice i'm just going to tell you more about how you did um i think but i think what Liz just
said there what Liz just said there is is also i think something she said much better than me but
which i also felt which is and i think it comes back to that thing of like these two uncommitted
didn't know whether it was just ten people who were very loud or whether it was widely felt thing
and i think this is something we've had for the last year which is we're not seeing each other in
pubs so we can't gauge the mood in order for you to make your feelings known about this you have to
deliberately write it down in a place where people can see it you can't just nod along to a pub
meeting or or something like that and so i think i think this is actually a problem of lockdown
generally and i think in some ways because i was very tense in that meeting as well i was by no
mean sure that you were going to come out of that meeting with the desired effect and the fact that
it was like 70 percent of people voted um hold over was a was a very big relief to me um and so i do
want to echo what Liz said which is i was glad that we had that opportunity to take the temperature
of the room in lockdown because i think it is very difficult to take temperatures of rooms virtually
yeah and also it was the first contested bid in my time in fandom this is my 14th east common
it was the first time there's been a contested bid in all that time so it was exciting so it was
not my first contested bid and my first east con was a contested bid it is true that contested bid
in the year 2000 BC when dinosaurs roamed the earth pretty much but in fact dinosaurs ran the
east con which was why we had a contested bid which we won um anyway sorry that that line probably
used to cut out because those dinosaurs are mostly my friends now keeping it in keeping it in i don't
think it's fine but i mean you know it says the thing which is that the reason you have contested
bids is not because two groups of people want to own the east con it's because there are fundamental
differences of view about what the convention is and what it stands for i was not expecting
not to prevail i was slightly worried that i would end up with the east con seated with me
which i as you know didn't particularly want
listeners if you have ever wondered what unbridled self-esteem looks like you can hear it here now
but yeah no but i'm going to explain why which is that i had talked to a lot of people and i
hadn't just talked to them i did a thing where i got talked people who i knew had the ear of people
who are not particularly my friends in fandom but whose opinions i trust and i got those people to
sound out the people who i'm on not such good terms with and in fact i in at least one case some of
my mates came to me to tell me that they'd had a very worried conversation with one of the people
who i don't it is not is not one of my intimates and um and so so this is just kind of how basic
politics works and i am not actually a hugely political animal but um i did actually i had
actually done my homework i would have been extremely surprised um if the east con if that
meeting had gone the other way i wanted just tiny tiny moment on management and organizational
design which is that i don't i think they need to do a lot of it because i think virtual
eastercalls are very different which conventions are very difficult and i'm not sure they really did
any of it so we ended up with teams that reflect the teams you have at
physical eastercalls and i think they kind of got in each other's way quite a bit and that that is
i think absolutely down to chairmanship as well and finally a lot of this a lot of what's
is said was focused on Vanessa but that was because Vanessa had just bid for a convention for which
she had no announced committee so she was literally standing up and saying let me have the easter
con and i'll i'll run it my way and and i think that was that was quite easy to to counter
in a way that if she'd had a good team around her i think i might i might very well have
have not persuaded people to hold over i think a really useful skill in an easter con chair is
being able to do this thing where you can go okay i'll go and ask this person because i know they
can take the temperature of these other ten people who don't necessarily know me it wouldn't
necessarily speak up directly to me and in that way you can get an overview of what people are
thinking and that's actually really effective skill if you're going to run an easter con so
as Liz mentions alison is very good at working with and talking with members of the community
in order to build up a view of what needs doing who needs to do it and when and it is for this
kind of tireless invisible behind the scenes service that she has won the doc weir reward so
congratulations alison very well done um yeah no i was very pleased to win the doc weir um
thanks to my octaphor co-host because i think i kind of got it not for nailing things to church
doors but because i've done a load of stuff for the last year about keeping fandom connected in the
keeping uk fandom connected in the pandemic and i think that octaphor has been a big part of that
and i am also i think there might have been the ones that put the fix in don't know what you mean
i am very pleased to have won an award for for massive humility and i am intending to
play on this every time i feel like i want to say in my humble opinion i know that i am in fact
expressing a humble opinion because i just want to make a humility award so there we go
the reason i vote for you and all weir was mostly not because of your um nailing things to church
doors but mostly because i think you have done more than anyone else in the last year to keep
British fandom a community and i think that deserved recognition and that is exactly why i voted and
i think i as a lot of people also voted before you nailed things for church door um which makes
it somewhat awkward because i don't think you should win for laying things in church door that's a big
obvious visible thing i think you should win for the fact that you have basically been keeping a lot
of people going socially and you know keeping their mental health uh good free ear basically
i've been trying very trying
oh the old jigsaw the best yeah you've had your head your moment of humility now let's go on it
i have right yeah thanks a lot guys
we are going to collect together con reports of confusion and we are going to put links to them
on our on the octothermic show notes page for this show so if you have written a con report
we will if you get it to us we'll make sure it's there for people to read that could be a positive
report a negative report a bit to report we've got a few so do tell us your con reports
yes and we will link that we will link to the ones we know about at the moment in the show notes
and we will add to the show notes to the ones we receive um and we will also mention them at
octotherp live so i don't know if we remembered to mention octotherp live but it's happening on the
25th of April 2021 um and it will be on zoom we will put advertisements in anonymous claire
and on our twitter and facebook so keep your eyes peeled for those but what about our members who
aren't on facebook or twitter and or anonymous claire so if you would like to come to octotherp live
and you are not on the anonymous claire discord or following us on twitter or facebook please do
feel free to email octothecast@gmail.com and we will sort you out with the link but until next time
it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
[Music]
we were going to talk about other topics i don't think we are we've been recording at the time i say
this i believe for around about an hour and 40 minutes the theme music for this episode was
fanfare for space by kevin mccloud at ncompetech.com used under a creative commons attribution 3.0
license this podcast will end at the beep beep