I was very happy with many of the winners.
I was very happy to many of the winners.
And I was very happy with many.
Shall I try?
No, it's John's turn to go word and edge.
Right. So he just has to think about which words he's going to gain.
I was very.
I liked it.
[Laughing]
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 47th episode of Octa Thorpe,
the podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom,
which is coming to you on the 23rd of December 2021.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Betty.
And we didn't read any letters of comment out last episode
and people may have noticed this, but this time we have loads of letters of
comment so we can read them all out.
Verbatim.
That's a good plan.
I think that's a good plan.
Everyone in favor?
Well, it's verbatim.
Oh, OK.
Yeah, you do that and I'll come back in half now.
It's good.
Farah said that Novacom didn't enforce masking and Farah said it was the worst
farah has seen so far and farah then followed up by saying it needs to be
compulsory in the corridors, the dealer room and the program room.
And Fran Dowd commented saying that they were OK with Novacom's policy of
masks pretty much everywhere except the bar area until Fran realized that by bar
area, they didn't mean the bar, but any social space in the hotel where you could
sit down with a drink.
And I think Fran's point is well made and quite thought about in those terms.
That kind of follows from the discussion we were having last time.
I also got a comment from my brother saying that it was his favorite episode
of the podcast we've done so far.
So I'm glad that some people enjoyed it.
And Jonathan Badley also wrote to us and said a long comment about masks and
the worry of deciding whether or not to go to an event that you might be turned
away from the door from if you didn't have the right paperwork and I have to say
flying to Portugal felt a bit like that.
We also had some locks from listeners, Farah, Joe Lindsey Walton and Alan
Stroud about the BSFA.
Thank you all very much for coming on our Facebook group and having a good,
good old discussion about that.
If you are a BSFA member, you can download PDFs of all the BSFA's publications
from their website and we have discovered something about BSFA membership,
which Alison will exclusively reveal.
It turns out that you can get, even if you're in the UK, you can get a digital
membership of the BSFA just by filling in the membership form, but putting not
applicable in all the mandatory address boxes on it.
And that way you'll get a digital membership because they won't be able to send
you anything.
I just recommend you don't try this with Wussless.
And that's a joke that will make more sense later in the episode.
We also heard from listener Dave who commented that the sound on the last
episode was a little bit iffy.
I think I put it right as Alison podcasting from the bottom of a well.
We apologise for this.
It's basically because now we are allowed to leave our homes again.
We have to get used to doing some recordings in one of our optimal usual
podcast spots.
So we are working on it for future episode.
I need to correct Liz there where when she said now that we're able to leave
our homes, what she meant is during the brief interregnum when we were able to
leave our homes.
Do not think about the event.
Chris Garcia wrote a wonderful episode, lots of Chewiness, which is good.
We're glad that you chewed on our episode.
We hope that all episodes will be equally nourishing.
Chris says on the topic of Covid in cons that he
thinks there's a lot of danger with having in person conventions and he says, so
John tell us by the way, she's right.
I try and avoid telling us by the way, because it gives her leverage, Chris.
But she might hear this podcast is one of my best efforts.
And he also notes that it's hard to do test at the door in the US because at
home tests cost 15 bucks for two, which seems too expensive.
I mean, it would seem too expensive, even if it was 50 cents for two, but 15 bucks
for two is is daft.
Yes, free testing.
It's a basic of public health.
Who knew?
He also says that he's had by his count more than a dozen
concussions since he was two.
He almost certainly has CTE.
What's a CTE stand for?
Liz.
Oh, I need to look it up.
It's, but I think it's, um, it's what everyone in the NFL has, basically.
It stands for chronic traumatic encephalopathy.
Fair enough. And he says they can only know for sure if he does by dissecting his
brain. So he's going to wait to get that done.
He thinks sorry to hear that Chris.
It's basically my fear is I hit myself on the head until I can no longer think
or do anything.
Um, but hopefully that won't happen.
Hurrah.
He doesn't have a recorder for tapes anymore, but he'll run Oct thought through
his voice to text converter, a mail, John Hurt to copy.
So thank you very much for that.
Chris, that would be very helpful.
I'm not sure John Hurt is going to thank us for an auto transcribed version of
Octa thought.
It's going to be very confused.
Chris then says at the end, got to say it's an interesting time to be a convention
fan. And that segues neatly into worse, first and world cons site selection news.
At Smothcon, I think people still thought that Cheng do and not got that many votes
in and it was all going to be fine.
And what happened after that was that the Cheng do bid helped by the biggest
science fiction magazine in China ran a live stream for eight consecutive nights
where they got every science fiction celebrity in China and then also some
recordings from people around the world on their live stream and had thousands
upon thousands of science fiction fans in China, mostly students watching it
and chatting all the way through and saying how marvelous Cheng do was and
voting and those people bought supporting memberships of the world con and voting
tokens and voted and in total, there were a lot of votes and Cheng do one.
And this is the bit where Liz can put in.
But in the meantime, yes, 106,000 views on this stream on the SFW magazine house
did one when people think, well, that's a lot of votes.
Emilie Arrow said, and I thought this was very pertinent that when Helsinki was
bidding, they got 200 fins to join and vote.
And that was about 20 times as effective as the Cheng do bid was when you compare
relative populations of China and Finland.
So I'm going to also have to probably explain a little bit about how
site selection works if you have not voted in world con site selection.
Essentially, so you can vote before the con and those votes were emailed to the
site selection admin and you could pay through the discount website, basically.
So on the first evening before world con, traditionally, the bids will send
in some tellers who will start looking at those votes in order, usually to declare
whether the vote is a valid vote or not, separate the address from the actual vote.
And then those votes can be counted later with all the votes that happen on site
where this separation happens during the voting process.
And the first interesting happened here was that Kevin Stanley, who was one of the
Winnipeg bid representatives, posted a breakdown of the country of origin of all
the voters in the pre voting, which was an unusual step.
It showed there was a huge majority of Chinese votes and then votes were about
17 other countries.
And there was some basically can fuff around this because this was not normal
practice.
And so the numbers were actually taken down because you could you could
invest in two ways actually.
I mean, you could infer that it would give Winnipeg a very strong kind of get out
the vote rationale, but you could also interpret it.
The people would then go actually China has a massive lead.
There's no point me voting.
So I don't need a sporting membership in a Chinese welcome, but they got taken down.
But I thought the interesting thing then was that they did not split the address
information from the votes at that time.
So when all the stuff about Kevin emerged, at first people just kind of, this
seems a bit off, especially people from from Europe.
But when the full ramifications emerged, Kevin was released from his roles, both
as one of the official tellers for Winnipeg, but also as the chair of the
Wusswuss business meeting for the convention, which does raise the question
of why somebody who's working for one of the bids was the chair of the business
meeting, though he wasn't planning to chair the site selection section of the
business meeting.
But still, there is an issue about how you separate these roles that I think
Wusswuss would do well to consider for future World Cons.
Then anyway, there's a part two to the story.
Yes, there is a part two.
So I should say like, I have no reason to disbelieve that Kevin who said he would
recuse himself from any site selection business would do that.
But I'm not sure if there is a mechanism by which that can actually happen to the
chair of the business meeting.
And so it all relies very much on kind of goodwill and trust.
And that may also have been a problem with what happened next to business
meetings. So then at the Friday business meeting, a motion appeared.
So I was sort of, I came into business meeting, I was watching it virtually a bit
late and I came in and they were debating a motion.
And I eventually saw the text of the motion on Twitter, which was essentially
business meeting believes that site selection votes should have membership
number, name, signature and address.
It really said, or and then was amended to and the one that went around on Twitter
has the names of the Winnipeg picture and vice chair on it.
Although I'm told that when it was actually introduced, it was introduced by the
site selection administrator.
And it was just a very strange moment because these are people who are, you know,
intimately involved in site selection and in wanting their bid to win,
introducing a resolution, wanting the business meeting to rule on how the vote
should be counted, kind of in the middle of the actual voting process.
But it was in the middle of the actual voting process, but at a point when it
massively favored those who could still vote in person, who were mostly going to
be in favor of the Winnipeg bid, the arguments for and against at the business
meeting, no one seemed to have a good argument for why it had been introduced.
Now, I never stepped up and said clearly, this is why we need the business meeting
to take a ruling on this.
And then in fact, I'm not sure why the business meeting should be taking
ruling on it anyway.
And eventually it's sort of, you know, there were the debate happened.
At one point, the chair of the business meeting got the vice chair of the
business meeting to take over so that he could speak in favor of the
the motion, which also seemed extremely strange.
And then it was voted through.
But it's a non binding resolution, which did not find the site selection
administrator to follow it at all.
So it was just a very kind of strange half an hour.
And I still don't really know what they hope to accomplish with it.
I believe I have an explanation from that for having had several
conversations with Smoughs, who I like and generally respect quite a lot, but
think might have been somewhat misguided, or their friends might have been
somewhat misguided in this case.
And what it was was that quite a lot of people having realized that there were
all these Chinese bids that had only email addresses and not street addresses,
which we now discover is completely 100% the norm in China.
Thought it was important for this to be drawn to the attention of the
business meeting.
And then they did it in this way that was not necessarily very clever.
But the head of site selection wanted to get a sense of the view of the
business meeting before making a final call on that.
And I think eventually he also got, well, they also got a view on the, the
feeling of the internet.
And that's not.
When I say the feeling of the internet, I don't mean Twitter went bananas,
but Twitter did go bananas.
But also a lot of the people who would have been in that room, but can't,
because let my, what I remind you was for still has no arrangement for
remote participation, even though it's obvious that they need one, even the
people who would dearly have loved to be in that room, but were prevented from
say, not having their visa accepted or having, or being worried about plague,
couldn't participate in this directly.
But so those were a lot of the people who were pitching in.
There was an extremely good post, which I'm afraid is friends locked by Colin
Harris, for example, where he, he went through a lot of his feelings about this
resolution.
And, and there was a lot of informed comment there and in a number of other
places around the internet.
So it wasn't just everyone, everyone lost their collective.
What do we say when people are losing collective things and we're a family
family podcast?
Everyone got a little bit cross.
A number of people got a little bit cross on the internet.
But it was also a lot of very considered reaction from people who, who thought
this was really way out of order.
And then eventually the site selection head meant, yeah, no, I've decided
that these, these votes are valid.
And it all came out all right in the end provided that all right in the end
includes having a Chinese Worldcon.
But I mean, I mean, I voted for Winnipeg.
I campaigned for Winnipeg.
I didn't want that to be a Chinese Worldcon by preference, but I, you know,
they, they did win.
I feel like it's okay.
They've got the Worldcon.
We just need to make it the best Worldcon it can be now.
Yeah.
So I think, I think in general, one of the things that got said was the reason
that this resolution was brought was not necessarily because the site
selection administrator wanted to be bound by the business meeting, but because
they wanted a steer from the community.
I think the other thing that is relatively apparent is if you read the
relevant part of the was just constitution, it is not in fact designed to
exclude votes that do not have all of the contact information on them.
And I generally think if that clause in the constitution is going to be
interpreted thusly, we probably need to take postal addresses off or make it
clear that they are an exception because I don't necessarily see the benefit of
everyone giving their postal address to a Worldcon.
So I don't necessarily want the Worldcon to be able to mail me.
I think in the end, it became apparent that the Chinese votes for Chengdu
were real votes from actual science fiction fans and should probably have
been counted.
It did come out at the site selection meeting that if they had followed the
resolution passed by the business meeting, we're going to pay a good of one
because the majority of the votes from China had not got complete address
information on, but it turns out that may well be a cultural thing because
apparently telephroad is a big problem in China.
And one of the ways to reduce your risk of that is not to give your address
out to people via PDF emails on the internet.
Yeah, I have a couple more points here.
The actual point that they were relying on in the constitution says site
selection balance should include name signature address and membership
number spaces to be filled in by the voter.
I don't know about the people in the was was business meeting, but I live in
2021, and I don't think many people on the planet think that would have
automatically assumed that the word address means mailing address.
I mean, I think it's a bit like saying phone means a device that it has
attached to the wall and makes telephone calls.
I'm also concerned that although the instructions for filling in the ballot
were in Chinese, the ballot was in English and the Chinese instructions are
very unlikely to have specified mailing address, I think I suspect.
And of course, the was was constitution is not in Chinese.
And this feels to me to be it would have been deeply unfair to have concluded
that what was required there was full mailing address, which seems again,
makes me quite surprised that the business meeting did.
And again, I think it's it's it just speaks about how monocultural the
business meeting is, especially this year.
This year in particular, when a lot of people from around the world who
normally have been in that room couldn't be there, you do have a group of people
who are mostly white, mostly elderly, mostly American.
And I think that was what caused that outcome.
And props to Ben Yellow, the guest of honour at Discon 3, who spoke
loudly and determinedly against the motion.
Go Ben.
Yes, I will also.
So just one other thing I've got an anecdote, which is I asked my friend.
I said, what's your how do I send you mail these days?
And he said, his magime address.
And I was like, I did I meant post.
I didn't mean email, but he read the word mail and interpreted it to mean email.
And he is like older than me.
So I think that is a shift that is happening.
And the fact it doesn't specify address.
But also I will note there's nothing in the was first constitution that says
here is what makes a ballot valid.
There's nothing at all that says this is the criteria.
And so if the ballot says this is what makes the ballot valid, as far as I can see,
the was first constitution doesn't say what the convention has to take as that.
So making arguments based on the constitution just seems silly.
And if the ballot says here is what makes the ballot valid, then you go with that.
You don't.
I just don't see there's a leg to stand on here.
I think the only thing you achieve by lodging this is that it looks like you're
trying to fill the vote.
And I think that, you know, that's bad.
So I was glad that it did not work.
Yeah.
So my thought on all of this is, you know, it sounds like there may have been
some good valid intentions behind it.
In the end, it has worked out because those votes were not eliminated, which I
think is the correct move.
And so Chengdu won by having more votes.
But it just strikes me as, yeah, again, like we have burned another massive
amount of goodwill.
We have looked like whispers kind of have to, you know,
finger on the scale and are trying to swing ballots.
I think we really need to be aware of kind of how this looks to the outside
world looking.
It's not just important to kind of discuss it with those 80 people in the
business meeting because there might not be people participating virtually,
but there are sure are people watching virtually.
And I think it's, yeah, it's just important that you and you're going to
bring these motions, which look very much like you are trying to say, will the
business meeting approve of me throwing out like all these votes and therefore
when it ends up winning?
I think you just have to be very aware of how this looks for people viewing
virtually who may also not be able to turn to their neighbor and say, what is
going on in this business meeting?
Because they don't quite understand the procedure, which is what I have done a lot
in the very few in person business meetings I've been to, you know, things
like it was a resolution, but it was not at all kind of clear what the difference
is to the average viewer, maybe between a resolution and a constitutional amendment,
things like that.
Yes.
And I think all of the British people heard the words, not binding resolution and
had a kind of sudden shutter to their souls.
I did want to make one more point about this, which is this is how indirect
racism works.
You do things that you do not think are biased, but nevertheless, you introduce
a massive amount of bias.
In this case, that you go business, the business meeting did not know the
balance of votes.
So they did things in a way that they did not believe was biased, but it was.
In general, I am quite happy that the bid that attracted the most votes was the
bid that was the seated world con.
I think that is good.
And I think that is how it should work.
I am a little bit concerned about some aspects of China hosting a world con.
And I think I try to thread this needle because there was a point of which at the
third Thursday, where I was like, well, I was very pro widder peg.
And then everyone on my side turned out to be a little bit of a giant racist.
And now I'm a bit like, Oh, no, am I a baddie?
But I think in general, it should not be the case that people interpret our
gladness that the wisvers procedures worked in a sort of democratic and fairway
as gladness that the world cons States of China.
And I'm not going to talk about it too much because I think probably at this
point in a Western country, everyone's very familiar with the reasons.
We're a little bit nervous about, you know, to Chinese government and et cetera.
But I am going to link to Jeanette Ng's Twitter thread.
Jeanette used to live in Hong Kong and therefore has a quite personal
perspective on this as a British SF fan who used to live in a territory, which
is controlled by China.
And so I will link to that in the show notes.
Yeah, I went.
I have also moved on this issue because I went from being a firm Winnipeg
supporter who was really worried about China getting the welcome to being
some of the viewers met and chatted to quite a lot of Chinese fans and is now
quite excited about the idea of all of those incredibly excitable students who
are amazed by science fiction and thrilled by it, getting a world kind of of
their own to go to.
And I think that will be great.
And I understand that that may mean that some of the people who regularly go to
Worldcon can't go and that's a shame for them, but you don't get to go to
Worldcon every year and they never get to Worldcon.
So, you know, yeah, Liz, do you have anything on, you know, the Chinese state?
No, fair enough.
Yeah, I think I've been, you know, interacting a little bit with the
Chengdu bid on Discord.
What I think is actually more obvious to me now and that I didn't realise is
that it was phenomenally hard for them to vote in site selection.
Because this con had to stop accepting their main payment method.
They don't all have credit cards can use internationally.
You know, the ballot is not translated.
So you've got to basically try and fill in an English language PDF and sign it
and send it back.
And that might be the reason as well why they're apparently 917 voting
tokens that were bought, but no votes associated with them, which isn't
unusually high number.
I mean, that is a lot of money that was spent on voting tokens with no vote.
So it'd be interesting to know kind of why those voting tokens were bought
and then never voted.
Is it that they were bought and people thought they'd sent their vote in, but
actually they hadn't managed to vote at all or they managed to double buy tokens?
It's kind of interesting that obviously something was going on there that meant
a thousand people tried to buy tokens and vote and didn't manage to vote.
I mean, I think it is quite likely that other people were buying tokens in the
end because of this thing about the students not having any way to buy directly.
I mean, I'm assuming that Chengdu will sort it out.
I think so.
My final thoughts on site selection are that every kind of previous overseas
WorldCom bid has had to do a lot of outreach in order to get people to vote for it.
And what is clear from Chengdu is that they just have a sufficiently large
group of fans out there, but actually they don't really need to do any outreach at all.
They can just win a Chinese WorldCom entirely with votes from Chinese fans, which are
in a different situation than we've been in before.
At the site selection business meeting, when Chengdu won, they announced their guests of honour,
who were Liu Sershin, Sergey Lukianenko and Robert J. Sawyer.
This has attracted some comment because obviously those are all male guests of honour.
And some people have wondered why there may not be a female guest of honour.
And I think it is true that they could stand to invite a female guest of honour later down the road.
Yeah, I mean, I expect they'll have more guests and I'm sure there'll be women on that list.
It was either very clever of them to have a Canadian guest of honour, or as a kind of olive
bratch to Winnipeg, or it's just luck.
But I think it's quite a good move.
There have also been some criticisms of the choice of Sergey Lukianenko as the guest of honour.
It's not anything I was aware of personally, but there have been some criticism of his
opinions on Russian sections in Georgia and the Ukraine.
And the only things I've seen are now quite historic.
So they're kind of from 2008, but I haven't seen anything further on whether these are kind of,
you know, opinions he still holds.
So this came up instantly after he was selected as a guest of honour raised by fans from the area.
It's a concern across a broader area than just Ukraine.
Our friend, friend of the show, Marcin was pretty horrified by that announcement.
They've got a very cute panda bid logo and panda convention logo.
And I do look forward to seeing all the different kind of varieties of their panda logo we get over the next couple of years.
I'm looking forward to their branding.
I believe they are currently having discussions about what the name of the convention should be.
I'm kind of like, maybe they should have those discussions before winning the bid.
[Phone ringing]
The Hugo Awards were announced.
We don't have the full statistical breakdown yet, so we can't go proper nerdy.
Expect that next week as we are all proper nerds.
But we did get the actual list of who won and Liz went to the ceremony.
So Liz, do you want to talk about that?
Yes, I could watch the ceremony.
It was actually delayed by an hour for either some smoke or a fire or something.
They said there was no fire.
And then they said there was, however, an electrical fault and quite a lot of smoke.
And you know what they say about smoke.
So, but they own.
So the Hugo started 75 minutes late, but it was fine.
Yes, I mean, that seems reasonable if you had electrical fault.
And I'm quite grateful because I woke up what would have been about 40 minutes into the Hugo's.
And it turns out that it was like half an hour before they started, which was perfect.
So yes, I watched the Hugo ceremony, which was emptied by Shirei Renee Thomas and Andrea Heston,
as Malca Older had to unfortunately withdraw.
And it was pretty good.
I mean, yeah, it was just a very competently done Hugo ceremony, basically.
It ran roughly to time.
It had some jokes.
It had some excellent moments from Thomas and Heston, who they referred to, EG, the renaming
of the astounding award and how that reflects our future.
There were some good speeches from some of the winners.
I really like seeing the fire magazine team on stage.
Maria Devana Headley did a great speech for Beowulf, including saying how she was wearing a necklace
that she could not have worn in person because it would get tangled up.
So she had to remotely.
They segued neatly between live acceptances, pre-recorded acceptances, and live acceptances over Zoom.
I think there were live acceptances over Zoom, and that worked really well and very smoothly.
You know, we had some music.
They had a choir singing during the in memoriam.
It basically was all just kind of very smooth and very nice.
And then I enjoyed watching it.
The only slight hit was they accidentally didn't play the recorded acceptance speech
from Best Video Game until later.
But they just came back and tossed it in.
You know, no fuss.
Yeah.
So I enjoyed watching it.
I'm pretty happy with all the winners.
It was a pretty good Hugo ceremony.
And it was kind of what was needed because last year's Hugo ceremony, you know, we were all
sitting there.
Those of us watching it live going.
What's going on here?
Is this really what I think it is?
And, you know, those were watching it live this time.
We're pretty much like, yeah, this is pretty good with the exception of, you know, some
Albrecht eyebrow raising when they said it was sponsored by Raytheon Corporation.
But apart from that, I think everything was was pretty good.
I was very happy with many of the winners.
I was particularly happy to see fire when best semi-prosine.
I think that's very richly deserved.
And I also think it is good when you have different things winning in a category.
And I think unbroken streaks of many years are perhaps a bad sign.
So particularly happy see that.
I was also generally very pleased with the other winners.
And yeah, I in general was very happy to read read the results and congratulations
to Cooed Street for winning Best Fancast, eight time finalist and first time winners
and richly deserved.
And I do think that their work in 2020 was some of the best work they've done.
So I think richly deserved at the moment as well.
They were my top pick and I was very pleased to see them.
But and congratulations to Alison for her victory because Hades won.
Oh, yeah.
And she must be over the moon.
I tweeted out to Greg this morning and said, Oh, I could not say in all those
emails about the Hugo Boat packet.
Oh, it incidentally, I've played your game for 300 hours.
But I think it's OK to fess up there.
So I was very pleased to see Hades win.
I would have been pleased.
I mean, I was generally pleased that obviously not everything I voted for one.
But there were several categories where I was extremely pleased.
I was very pleased to see Beowulf win because whether or not you think it was
eligible, it was at least a thing that is a work.
You want to say something about it?
It's nice to see a long substantial work win because we've had a run of blog posts
and shorter things.
Yeah, no, I kind of what I am concerned by the trend for things that are kind of about
conventions, winning, invest related work.
And so it's quite nice to see something that is clearly a best related work, winning it.
And also Beowulf, that translation of Beowulf is unbelievably fantastic.
And if you have not read it, if you have any interest at all in the history of fantasy,
it is well worth your time.
I was also pleased to see the old God win for the simple reason that it was the
first time that the full that the full length best dramatic presentation, long form
finalists has been included in a huger voter packet.
And so I don't know whether it was correlated in any way, but I was glad to see it win for that reason.
So if you're out there and you make movies, put them in the voter packet, it works.
We have clear evidence.
I noticed that because I just assumed I'd go and watch on Netflix.
Ah, interesting.
I will immediately counter that with the news that the only thing in the packet
from best dramatic presentation, short form, did not win.
So, you know, sorry.
John, get out here with your logic.
I will also say, apparently Eurovision song contest did better than Tenet.
And I think Tenet has many flaws, but I am not sure I think it deserved to come
behind Eurovision.
OK, can I give you a theory on this, which is that a lot of Hugo voters are quite
old and Tenet is impossible to understand in the cinema and was not available on
streaming during the voting period.
Yeah, I mean, you probably probably both of those are very big contributing factors.
You have to have subtitles.
It's not comparable to old people without subtitles.
I mean, I think it's also an effect of the, you know, the way voting works to determine
second to fourth, fifth place is that, you know, often the thing which has, you know,
a very big number of first place votes and then becomes one of the last two in the
run off, then doesn't end up in second place because of redistribution.
So, you know, Tenet could be, I'll just actually go and find the numbers because
I've got them right in front of me.
I mean, in Tenet's case, actually, it was like at the bottom of the pile from the start.
So it never looked like it had even a chance.
There are more people who put the original song contest actually in this first
preference than Tenet.
So it was never in the chance.
I think it is noticeable that the total participation in the Hugo's this year was
two thousand, three hundred and sixty two ballots.
And there is a clause in the Wussfuss Constitution, which says you have to get at
least 25% of the total ballots to vote in a category for that category to be awarded.
And I think it is worth pointing out that some categories are actually running
quite close to that number, that bottom limit of ballots, in particular, some of the
fan categories.
And I guess particularly relevant to Octa Thorpe is there were 643 632 votes in
fan cast this year and 25% of that total ballot is 590.
So if 42 fewer people had voted in best fan cast, it would not have been awarded.
So I think this does speak to some need to try and raise the profile of the fan
awards a little bit, because I think, you know, they're good awards.
I think that the investment of time you need to look at the nominees and decide
which one to vote for is not huge, especially compared to something like best
series, for instance.
And maybe we can try and raise a little bit more interest in that and get a little
bit more votes going in those categories, just because I think that fan cast,
especially, was starting to come close to the lower limit.
And that segues tidally into the other thing I want to say, which is that I was
absolutely thrilled that Sarah Felix, one best fan artist, for many reasons.
She's done fantastic work on many fanzies this year across a whole spectrum of
different sorts of fanzine.
And she's the bid artist for the Glasgow in 2024 bid, but more than anything else,
she has done the artwork for my for the next issue of my tiny fanzine, which we'll
put a link to in the show notes. And you can't see the bit she's done yet because
it hasn't come out yet.
But when it does come out, it's an exact evocation of why she is the right person
to be winning the best fan artist Hugo.
And I was absolutely thrilled.
Jon, do you have a lot to say on the hugas?
I don't think I do.
I do.
Sorry.
Someone gave me a spreadsheet full of statistics.
Obviously, I have things to say.
I was just also going to say, I was also going to say that, you know, best video
game was, you know, discons, choice to award this year as an experiment.
And I think had, you know, a very credible list of finalists as we've discussed before,
but it also had, you know, it had 40% of ballots that were cast filled in best
video game.
So this is not something that has been chosen by a tiny number of voters.
There was also a reasonable voting contingent in this category.
So it all bodes quite well for future conventions or future business meetings,
which we still introduce a best video game Hugo.
The best video game Hugo is currently in the Hugo Awards Study Committee,
which was described to me this weekend as where Hugo Awards go to die.
Didn't we send best audio book off to the Hugo Study Committee?
Oh, yes.
So it might be a few years.
Pics, do you want to start?
Me or who?
You.
Or whom?
My pick for this episode is the Psychopath Club by Sandra Bond, which follows the
adventures of Daryl Martock, who is a kid living in a small American town and
very much not enjoying himself.
The tagline for the book is he's a good kid.
He just wants to kill you.
And I think the touchstone people might be familiar with that will get them into
the right frame of mind for this book is probably the wasp factory by Ian Banks.
It reminded me very powerfully of that, but I think I probably enjoyed it a bit
more than the wasp factory and it's definitely more genre than the wasp factory.
I really enjoyed it.
It didn't do any of the things that I expected it to do at any point.
And I was very unsure where it was going at most of the points that I was
reading, which I really thoroughly enjoyed.
And yeah, I would recommend everyone go read it.
It is available on Kindle for not much money or for about 12 in paperback.
If you don't have a Kindle, but you want an ebook version, you can convert
the Kindle version in an app called Caliber and just ping me a message and I
can walk you through how to do that.
But yeah, I think it is fantastic and everyone should read it.
So maybe Sandra is a great new voice in science fiction and everyone should
read her book.
So my choice is a book, I think we're all doing books this time.
I booked a recent read, which is The Witness for the Dead by Catherine Addison.
It is a sequel of sorts to the Goblin Emperor, although I think it would stand
alone reasonably well, although you're going to be confused about some of the
world building.
And it follows one of the characters who's introduced in the Goblin Emperor,
Merselahart, who is a witness for the dead.
Essentially, he's a religious man who's kind of calling is to be a witness for the
dead in that he can kind of commune with the dead and he called and pawn a lot
for things like investigating possible murders or suicides to clear up issues
with wills to this kind of thing.
Anyway, it kind of follows him in the town he has now moved to, where he's
investigating several different cases, sort of some murders, some wills.
And also he's dealing with his status and how he fits into the power structures.
And I very much liked it because I like the Goblin Emperor and this gives us a
kind of totally different view of that world because the Goblin Emperor follows
the new Emperor, as you'd expect.
And this one is much more kind of on the ground and is someone who is living
essentially sort of lower middle-class life in a working town.
And a lot of his investigations kind of do follow the class structures,
places he can go essentially because maybe he crosses class boundaries as
his member of the priesthood.
He's investigating the death of an opera singer who had kind of upper-class
patrons and lovers and what was going on there.
And the character himself is pretty great and fun to spend time with.
So yeah, I really enjoyed it.
It finishes a little bit kind of precipitously, but I think actually there
is another book coming in the same series also about Muh Salah.
So I will be reading that one.
And my pick this time is Sibilant Frickitive by Adam Roberts, which is a
collection of his book reviews from New Compress.
And what do I like about it?
Well, I like that he is awesomely erudite and uses examples from literally
everywhere to bring to bear in quite a clever, critical way on all of these
different things that he is reviewing.
And yet nevertheless, he's reviewing things from a great many different genre
in a great many different genres and styles and kind of appreciates them for
what they are.
So he's quite good at actually getting into things and going, this is good
despite the fact that this is a piece of popular culture or this is bad
despite the fact that everyone thinks it's excellent and it's very thought
provoking and interesting and also extremely funny.
Roberts is quite a funny writer and this is a good example of it.
He's more funny, I think, when writing criticism and commentary and tweets than
he is when he is writing novels.
So I liked it a lot and I would recommend it and it is from New Compress.
Yes, I think I think I read most of those kind of when they were on his
blog.
Yes, it is a collection of articles from a blog, but I did not read them all
when they were on the blog and they are not on the blog now because he's put
them in a book.
That's how it works.
Exactly.
Cunning.
Capitalism.
Authors eating, John.
Authors eating.
I'd unlike some people, I know I'm broadly in favour of authors eating.
Pay for art.
Art is good.
I mean, I'm not sure he's making a million dollars off his small press book of
criticism here.
More people should buy the book.
And the book is only technically available on Amazon.
So I wrote to, because we have a kind of anti-adam Amazon ebook thing going on now,
I wrote to Ian Waitsa said, it's only on Amazon, he said, "Oh God,
73 pound 99."
And that's what we've done.
So I have an e-pub.
The psychopath club is also only on Amazon, but I bought it and then
converted it into a different format using calibre and that meant I could
read it on my preferred platform.
And then we're going to do picks for SF Christmas songs listeners.
I'm not actually, do you have to pick an SF Christmas song?
I thought it was just Christmas song.
No, you just had to pick a Christmas song because yours is a Christmas song,
isn't it?
It's a song with a great story about it.
I just read out what was in the bullet points, which says picks for SF Christmas
song.
But all Christmas songs are SF know because they presuppose the existence
of either God or Santa.
Oh, no, goodness, you have such a very limited range of Christmas songs in your
life. In the show notes, I will put a link to a playlist of 100 Christmas songs,
either of which, none of which presupposes the existence of God or Santa.
Well, that is, they're not as F know, Alison, and they don't count.
And we could start with Deck the Halls with Bows of Holly, which is a completely
pagan song with no mention of Christmas.
I mean, there's only about three words in Deck the Halls, and they're all
fallalala.
See, this is what John was complaining about.
And now we don't do you.
No, it there are lots of words, including Don, we now are gay apparel,
and I am going to put a link to the T-shirt in the show notes to make up for that.
So my pick for SF Christmas song, which is an actual science fictional Christmas
song, no doubt, absolutely right nailed it, is Caron Bater Prime by Jonathan
Colton, which is a very, very good song.
And we're going to link to the YouTube because that also includes a very good video.
So there you go.
Nice.
My pick for best Christmas song is I'm going to pick two because I'm some sort of a
bell and no.
One of them is California Christmas time, which is from crazy ex girlfriend.
And I like that a lot mainly because my wife lived in California for like 20 years
and like I have lots of friends there.
So it makes me smile every time I hear it because I think about California and all
of the good times I've had in California.
And I like that a great deal and it's also very funny.
The second word I like is Oh Santa by Mr B, which has not safe for work lyrics.
And I can't play it in front of my parents, but which I love regardless.
And I've been a huge fan of Mr B ever since I saw him play a small coffee shop
in Southampton.
And so I very much like his Christmas Ditty.
Doesn't everyone have a Christmas playlist and then a second Christmas playlist,
which is a subset of the first Christmas playlist that you can play in front of
grandma?
No, that's mostly because I don't really have often have family over to visit
during Christmas because we go somewhere else.
So I rely on the fact that there's somewhere else will have a family friendly playlist.
I think my playlist is family friendly.
It's just it's also full of extremely obscure Christmas carols.
So therefore it's not really family friendly.
Yeah, so so my my pick is a fairly obscure Christmas carol.
It does presuppose the existence of God.
John's therefore is a s f naught.
Oh, it is the carol Bethlehem down, which I love because it is a very beautiful
carol with gorgeous four part harmony.
You know, it changes the harmonies in the third verse to emphasize kind of what
will be coming at Easter for the baby Jesus.
And it's this kind of lovely sad carol, but I actually love it even more because
of the story behind it, which is it's composer Peter Warlock and the lyricist
Bruce Blunt.
They wrote it and submitted the carol to the daily telegraph's annual Christmas
carol contest back in 1927.
And they did this because basically they were short of money.
And when they won the carol contest, they took the money and had essentially a big
piss up on Christmas Eve. So I love that kind of something so beautiful came out
of essentially wanting to go and have a massive vendor on Christmas Eve.
Nice.
I like massive benders.
There's a form of words, something like a majestic carol or something.
There is like a they called it a really an immortal carol is what Warlock said
about it.
I should say that I got, you know, I've heard this story a few times and it is
referenced in the online magazine of a church is where we could be to get
the reference from, but it could be total bollocks.
But it's a good story.
That's probably did win the carol contest.
I would like to address one further issue, which is John.
Can you let us know your future plans for the protection of Marx?
Oh, yes.
Yes.
Now this is very good.
So I have rotated off the Mark Protection Committee for those who don't know the
Mark Protection Committee is a group of people who are on a committee who look
after world-contrade Marx, but it is much more fun to go up to Mark Plummer
every Easter con and ask whether he is protected because, you know, you've got
to find your joy where you can.
And Mark sent me an email or two over the weekend discussing Wussfuss site
selection business.
And at the end of his last email, he wrote, "PS, as I am now unprotected,
I am wearing armour."
So I am glad to report that Mark Plummer will still be safe and he is taking matters
into his own hands.
But this clearly shows a tragic lack of trust in Wussfuss's ability to protect
Marx in my absence.
So Wussfuss, how do you answer these accusations?
That you will no longer adequately protect Mark Plummer.
We are not going to give you a right of reply, but let us know in a lock.
And Nicholas White, who I'm sure would have been extremely capable of
protecting Mark Plummer and other Marx, applied was a candidate in this
election, but they had nine candidates for six places on the committee and he
was not one of those elected.
So Nicholas White will not be protecting Marx in the future.
But I'm sure the people who have been elected will thoroughly protect
Mark Plummer and other Marx going forward.
Well, they'd better Alison, they'd better.
Or they'll have us to answer to.
And that was the Octa Thought Podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
[Squeaking]
[Music]
If I, if I thought it was going in the podcast, I would have been polite.
No, no, I agree.
We shouldn't have that in there.
The theme music for this episode was "It's Christmas Time" by Frank Shurter,
used under a simplified filmusic.io standard license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.