Can you turn off your virtual background just because I like to see the cat?
1, 2, 3...
*clap*
Okay, that'll do.
*laughs*
Right.
John, the cat behind you, which everyone is, like, when we did the clap, the little head came up.
And then they were like, "Oh, nothing's going on, I'll put my head back down again."
*music*
Hello everyone, and welcome to the ninth episode of the OgtThought Podcast, a podcast about science fiction and SF fandom.
I'm John Coxson.
I'm Alison Scott, and I'm Liz Batty.
And this week we have letters of comment that have arrived since the previous episode.
And we actually have three letters of comment, a comment of comment, and a reciprocal letter of comment sort of.
So, firstly, Helena McCallum writes in to say that you can set locks if you're not called Mark Orandrew.
I like this as in it's a sort of meta letter of comment, in that it's telling us a thing and also doing that thing at the same time.
So I prove.
But we had in fact already had letters of comment from Claire.
Yes, that is true.
Who is not called Andrew or Mark.
But we had a lot of marks and a lot of Andries.
I think there are now an equal number of letters of comment from people called Mark, people called Andrew, and women.
And that may be something we want to address at some point.
Maybe we need to be diversifying our relationship.
We're like the board of directors of accompanying, aren't we?
Yeah.
Graham Chanuk used to braid his female readers every episode about their inability to write letters of comment to his fanzine vibrator.
Yeah, that seems.
I tell you what, there are some clueless people out there in the world.
I think we will be coming on to that later.
Mark, someone called Mark did also set us a letter of comment to keep us in letters of comment from people called Mark.
And he says that he is most disappointed that we had omitted letters of comment from people called Mark.
And he accuses me of having transitioned from the Mark Protection Committee to the Mark Neglection League.
So I would like to publicly apologise to all marks and to admit that I have not done a good enough job of protecting their feelings and their opinions.
And I will rededicate myself to the Mark Protection Committee from this day forth.
Well said.
He also says that he thinks I'm wrong about the Wussfuss Business Meeting.
And perhaps a bare minimum business meeting is the right way to go given the state of the world at the moment and the amount of work the Conzeland Committee are probably doing to make Conzeland happen.
And that is a good point.
Um, yes.
So basically he agrees with me on that.
Yes.
He says, he says, "Allison and Liz, I don't mean to neglect you, but you seemed pretty clear that you're holding.
Doctor Hugo Award finalist Mark neglecting the boy Cox and responsible here keep on casting.
So props to you to all of the criticism directed in my direction.
Correctly.
Yes.
I mean, I can't say it. I can't say it's not reasonable.
However, I had some vitriolic criticism directed this, my way, this fortnight from one Lillian Edwards who accused me of accused all three of us of not mentioning her new podcast.
This never happens, which she is doing with Christina, Lakerdy and Sorenson.
And there will be a link in the show notes.
It's very good. You should go and listen to it.
And we are not, we are completely unapologetic about the fact that we did not mention this podcast last time because we recorded our previous.
Episode on the 17th of June and she released the podcast of the world on the 18th of June.
So we would have to have been more than usually prescient to have mentioned it.
So Lillian, tough. We are mentioning it now. Is that good enough? I claim my five pounds.
I mean, what I like about that is that you address her criticism with tact and kindness in a way that definitely won't stoke any fires.
So that's good.
Isn't Stoking Fars what it's all about?
It could well be. It could well be.
So, and also, I think the other mark asked us to say when we're recording it.
We're recording this one on Sunday the 5th of July and it'll go out on Wednesday the 8th of July unless it doesn't.
Yes, all being well unless it doesn't.
Why this podcast is not late? It turns out to be easier to get podcasts out on time than Fansies, which is something I had not realised.
I mean, so I'm just going to say, and obviously this comes from a place of love, but I suspect it is also easier to get podcasts out when you have your co-host do the editing of the podcast.
On time.
How many podcasts? How many Fansies have you done? Professor the boy, Coxon?
Me?
Of the top of my head.
On time.
Twenty.
Maybe on time.
What is time?
Time is an illusion.
Fansies is doubly so.
Time is fleeting.
So Claire wrote us a letter of comment.
Claire Broily wrote us a letter of comment to commend us for pronouncing her surname correctly.
And said she was going to be quieted this week also.
So yes, thank you, Claire.
Please send your Claire Hughes on the topic of Claire Broily to octathookast@gmail.com.
Oh no, that's such a terrible joke.
Or in fact, any other regular correspondent.
Finally, two of us were at the first Thursday meeting on the first Thursday and Crazy Dave
told us that he listens to this podcast at two and a half time speed.
So we are curious to know whether he is the fastest podcast listener in our audience.
So if you are listening at greater than two and a half time speed, please write in and
let us know.
And also tell us how an earth you managed to make sense of what's going on because I
tried it.
I just, I know what we're saying and I can't hear it.
So.
Whenever I listen to podcasts, I listen at normal speed or sometimes 1.1, but normally
normal speed because I feel that podcasts are designed to entertain it.
If they're not entertaining at regular speed, I'll go off and find what it is.
Don't tell people that.
They'll stop listening to our podcast, Alison.
They could listen.
You're very welcome to listen to this podcast.
It's good though.
Imagine if you could listen to like rambling chats in the bar at 2.5 times speed.
There would no longer be sort of like four hours of rambling chat over a point.
It would be like a breezy one hour discussion.
Yes, and you would be taking shots of vodka to replicate.
I feel that Zoom is Mr. Trick here.
Well, because it doesn't come with vodka.
No, no.
Zoom needs smart speed.
I'm in this zoom chat, but it's really a bit boring.
Let's speed it up a bit.
The details for my guff-tripper all taking shape, and I will be on it next time.
So we may have to organise when to record in a way that ties in with my virtually swimming
off the Great Barrier Reef or something like that.
I've got lots of plans to go spend time in bars with people who are not socially, not
required to social distance.
So I don't know to what extent things are really back to normal in Australia and New
Zealand.
I think they are more back to normal, except in Melbourne, which is one of the main places
I'm going, which has had another outbreak.
So who knows what's going to happen?
And anyway, you see, we'll get my next report from not Australia, but virtually Australia.
And I will tell you all about the exciting things I'm doing there as part of the first
part of reporting on a virtual guff trip.
So when does your virtual guff-tripper begin, Alison?
It starts on the 11th, which is really not very long.
Oh, wow, that's the week.
I've got, yeah, less than a week.
And normally I'd be like panicking and packing at this point, but in fact I'm actually doing
all the stuff I didn't get around to earlier because as it's virtual, it's easier.
I hope to get it all sorted.
Fair enough.
And on your...
So you're starting on the 11th.
When does your virtual trip come to a close?
Well, I finish with Conzeland and then I will be not flying home.
And I think that's the time we actually have to sort out a recording because I think I'm
going to not stay with this on my way home and we're going to record Octa Thorpe as if
I was in this living room.
So that won't be the next one.
It'll be the one after, I think, after Conzeland and you'll be going, "What were your impressions
of virtual Conzeland?"
And I'll be going, "I am completely connected.
I'm completely knackered in my eyes square now."
Yes, that's fair.
So there will be more firm details about our live from Alison's trip home recording in
the next episode.
So keep your eyes peeled for that.
Shall we talk about Conzeland?
We often do, but yes, let's do it again.
I saw a tweet several weeks ago, which I have now lost, but it was that Conzeland were looking
for people to help with access.
And specifically, the issues of access which would come up when you are a virtual convention,
which I think is quite interesting because it feels like we're starting to get a handle
on what conventions can do to make themselves more accessible to people who are actually
at the convention.
But obviously moving online is going to bring a whole new set of issues.
And I'd be interested to know if you have any thoughts on them.
If you've been to any virtual conventions or meetups, which did think about ways to make
them more accessible to people who find it difficult to access virtual conventions and
any other thoughts on the matter.
Well, it's funny you should say this.
So I've been doing first Thursday meetups for London fans.
When we started, we very quickly noticed that we were getting quite a lot of people attending
who could not attend the first Thursday in person, sometimes for reasons of distance,
which is not actually a primary accessibility issue for what we think of as being a local
London pub meeting.
So it's nice that these people can now come, but it's not what I think of as the most important
accessibility issue for the thing.
But we also have had people visiting who cannot normally attend the meeting either because
they do not like crowded pubs or they cannot get up the stairs.
And so having those people there is very welcome.
We have then, since then, been trying to do outreach, and we've done this on a very
individual basis, and we've done outreach to the people who we know normally attend
the first Thursday meetings, but have not been attending the Zoom meetings.
We've had a range of responses.
So some of them have come and tried it, and some of them quite like it.
Some of them have tried Zoom, but concluded that they don't like large zooms, even if
we do the breakout room thing, that they are preferring there, even though they might quite
enjoy conventions.
They are preferring to do the interactive meetups in smaller groups.
People are still struggling with technology.
Most of this virtual life that we are living now, it is much worse than a regular pub
meeting would be, and often also than the formal panels and presentations at conventions,
they are finding it harder.
It is harder to lip read.
It is harder to manage the complexity of conversation where several people are in a
room.
Some people don't like Zoom, some people can't manage Zoom, some people have disabilities
that are more or differently disabling in a Zoom environment.
But you know, it is something we've given some thought to.
And actually for a lot of the older people, just helping them individually get into this
way of working is the thing that is most useful.
So the thing that popped into my head immediately was the problem that you would have if you
were hard of hearing with this kind of technology.
And I think one of the reasons I got quite annoyed at the Hugo ceremony in Dublin because
they had the automatic subtitles people were laughing when they got it wrong.
But the problem with that is that it means that they said, "Oh, we should not have used
automatic subtitles because they were inviting people to find them funny."
And I kind of thought that maybe when we see automatic subtitles that are inadvertently
saying the wrong things, we need to shut the hell up and remember that these subtitles
are there as an accessibility feature for deaf people and not laugh in a way that means
that convention committees want to take that away for the deaf community.
So my thought, Sisson, is that one, you are quite right, that if we see something on automatic
subtitles, we do need to remember, look, these are here for a purpose there to help
people and we shouldn't, you know, we should try not to react in that way because it's
not helpful.
And that I can see that when you're doing an all online convention, there are auto-subtitling
options that might help.
But my second thought is that for big events like the Hugo's, you should really be paying
for a live captioner because these problems will not happen.
And we know that is possible.
It takes money, but it doesn't take enormous vast amounts of money that world comes, cannot
allocate to it.
And that would have solved that particular problem.
I think in smaller groups, that is less of a problem because I think the problem with
the Hugo's is one person finds it a bit funny and then everyone around them starts to realize
what they're laughing about and that spreads.
So maybe that's not a problem if it's only 30 people watching live captioning of a panel
or so on.
But I was slightly surprised that they use the auto-subtitling option for the Hugo's
instead of going with a person in the auditorium or else we're doing it for them.
That's fair.
I think that's a good point.
I think that's less relevant to a virtual thing because the people who need automatic
subtitling will use it.
I also feel that laughing at automatic subtitling is the equivalent of laughing at a presenter
whose first language is not English or who has a spasticity that means that they can't
form words or move in a normal way and it's completely reprehensible.
And if all you need to do to stop it happening is to say we're having these captions to help
people who have poor hearing hear the thing and I understand that some of you are finding
it funny but please keep that to yourselves and people would have shut up.
I think your argument, I think the problem is that if you laugh at someone on stage who
has a problem speaking or problem communicating, you're clearly laughing at someone who has
feelings whereas laughing at an automatic transcription doesn't have a victim and doesn't have as
obvious a victim and so I think it is much easier to laugh at that because it doesn't
feel like you're being cruel.
I see why people might laugh at one or not the other but yeah and I think Liz's point
about the hugos especially being able to afford a person to do it which would not necessarily
run into the same problems.
Especially as a word ceremonies often have a lot of text which is pre-written and can
just be spewed out, you don't have to live caption anything except the acceptance speeches.
Yes and it means you can send them the names of all the finalists in advance.
They could have put that into the automatic transcription software too just saying.
I actually had another subsidiary point about the other thing Alice has said.
I was just going to say that obviously the first Thursday mechanism of individually contacting
members who are having trouble and helping them in a one to one setting scales poorly
to world's cotton levels of attendance.
Okay here's how you do it.
You ask people to talk to their friends who are having trouble and you also encourage local
things like the first Thursday to happen because if those things are happening in lots of
different places that is a way to preload lots of people.
So you encourage the grassroots activities that's required.
In fact Conziel and I think are doing training sessions to get people familiar with their
platforms before the com which I think is a great way of doing it and that is also going
to open up access so you can log in, you'll be able to log in I think to their Discord
and things and check them out ahead of time to make sure your chosen device is going to
work nicely with everything and so you don't spend the first day of your convention trying
to fiddle with Zoom I guess.
Have they announced this or have they just, is this just one of these we are intending
to do this stuff because I've just, I've finally got around to filling in my program
participant form.
Sorry Jenny, you had said it to me and I am just terrible.
You are the bane of program, you are the bane of program heads everywhere Alice and
it has a thing saying would you like to moderate a panel and I said if you insist because I
know that although I'm not the world's best moderator there's always a shortage of female
moderators and I think that it is better to have less good female moderators than better
male moderators controversial opinion and so and then they said would you be happy to
attend a training session and I'm kind of like yes of course but they do have to fit that
training session in around my virtual guff trip and so time is getting tight, touch the
unusual I feel for the world con.
There are a few things where I'm kind of like oh you're cutting it a bit fine now.
I thought they had said this but now I mention it of course I cannot actually find any of
the information on it or did they email it to me that might be it.
It is interesting since we have started podcasting I have become much more interested in conventions
official lines of communication because that is how I try and find out what conventions
are doing and so whenever there is something I know about a convention that is not in their
official line of communication I'm like why have you not put this on your website in a
place that it is easy to find?
Conventions often put quite a lot of control over their official communication routes in
a way that makes it hard for say area heads to actually get in there and amend the things
for their own area rapidly so you can often have a area heads who are very happy to keep
the information for their area up to date who are prevented from doing so by the broader
controls over what goes on the website and that is not it is not a stupid thing to do
there are arguments on both sides of this but my view is that if you trust somebody to
be an area head you should probably trust them to update their webpage too.
I have now found the announcement and it was in my email and it probably says something
about me that I immediately tried to find it on Facebook and Twitter and their official
page before I just went and read the email which I read this afternoon but yes it does
say you can ask if there's a form to fill in if you would like to have some live training
on Discord which I think is a great initiative.
I think it is a great initiative I will point out that anyone who has not joined New Zealand
because they feel they cannot use the technology is perhaps in need of this being announced
more widely than emails to people who have joined Conzeland.
I'm not technically a Conzeland member I'm just on their mailing list of people who have
expressed interest at some point so it may be is going to a wider group there.
Yeah and I'm well taken I'm actually interestingly as a Conzeland member why does it not get
that email.
So you know I think that all of these things make sense in terms of how World Con divisions
are put together and they are all volunteers doing these jobs and like you know I completely
see how all of this has happened but I do think at some point that needs to be a little
bit of a thought about whether or not these are sensible structures and whether or not
there is a better way to structure these things.
I realise that as someone who is identifying this problem and not volunteering for a World
Con not that I definitely part of the precipitate in this regard in that I am not part of the
solution but.
Shall we talk about Hugo voting?
Yeah it hasn't started yet.
I have had informal conversations with people who may not be connected with the people who
have to actually count up the hugas who are like we think the time is now getting quite
tight for the management of the Hugo vote.
So this is my question because I well I agree that the time is getting very tight for Hugo
voting since it is not open yet and they are going to present them at the end of the month.
But also I do not know how many people actually vote throughout the voting process and how
many people try and log in 10 minutes before they end the voting and frantically vote for
everything. So I don't know whether this delay will actually be lowering the number of Hugo
votes or just compressing everything into a two week window when it would probably be compressed
into anyway.
This is my question because when people were discussing this I was like I can see that having
fewer votes is a problem but it was less clear to me whether or not this would end up in there
being less votes if that makes sense.
So yeah I completely see your point.
It also prevents you from doing neat little things like having the best novel Hugo presented
by a female astronaut and other tricks like this.
It's quite useful to have the hugas in the bag well before the welcome.
It used to be that this would have been completely impossible because the process of Hugo voting
involved a voting phase and then a counting phase that was long and extremely complicated
and I believe that now that we have very few postal votes the counting phase is very quick
but people are still entitled to vote by poster they cannot do that so they can.
They can. The paper ballots have been up since the nominees were announced.
It is only the online voting that is not available.
Sorry that that ruins the run.
In that case ignore me I'm talking about but it's still impossible because you can't actually
post anything to New Zealand with any confidence it will arrive at the moment so you know.
Oh yeah I do I do sort of think that if you're casting a postal vote across the Pacific Ocean
during Covid-19 that may not be the most reliable mechanism but yes.
I like that Covid-19 is this kind of like the 2019 Hugo's in the Tits voted in
awarded in 2020. Okay.
So this is an interesting this is an ecumenical matter. The 2020 Hugo's are awarded in 2020 for
works in 2019. That's right sorry these things vary quite a lot but I think it's 2019 Oscars isn't
it? I never know these things. Everyone does it differently there is no consensus.
It is it is quite interesting in that it is it is clear that they will get it together
we think but if they don't get it together it's going to be spectacular. I think there's
quite a big risk that they get it together in in between when we record this and when the
show is released so well done guys that was that was well timed mess up our podcast.
They have announced the voting will open no later than Wednesday the 8th of July so it should be
open by the time this podcast is released. I'm not sure it's um it's going to be a problem in
practice because I don't think really you need a 13 period that's longer than a week um it'll be
fine they'll develop all the hugos. I do feel a bit sorry for the guys who have to engrave the
days on the basis as well but they're probably used to this sort of thing. But that's actually fine
because all the hugos will be being shipped around the world and so they don't necessarily
have to be ready and engraved on the day of the Hugo ceremony. The introduction of the
e pluribus Hugo um let's make the Hugo voting quite complicated uh amendment also means that
you absolutely have to do the whole thing digitally anyway and like have software that you've run
seven or eight times to check it actually works. So I assume that when you just close your
go voting and then you push a button and then ten minutes later you have the results but maybe
that's hopefully optimistic. Fingers crossed. That also presumably means that the paper votes are
transmitted uh our data entry into the digital system. I'm pretty sure that's certainly how I
would do it if I were on the Hugo um a missed a group of Hugo administrators and that is not in
any way a job application guys. Um I've I've now listened to all the best fan cast so that I can
write an article for um for um the Glasgow 2024 bid is running some articles on um on hugo slates
and one of them is Best Fan Cast and I'm writing about it um so we can talk about that next time
if you like a crossover but I will I will be plugging this podcast there obviously and I
I can plug Glasgow 2024 they're going to be a great convention. Glasgow's a wonderful place to go
to for the Worldcon you should vote for them. Does that mean I should listen to all the best
fan casts? At 2.5 speed obviously. Yes it does make me laugh that next episode will be the only
episode we record um other than this one before the close of voting so we gave an hour
to Best Mac presentation log form and then we're going to give an hour to all other
Hugo categories which is yes that's our topic for next time all the hugos in an hour starting
from here yeah all of them we can probably do it we just do like a minute per categories over a
minute per finalist or we could have like an extra or we could have an extra log episode
where we talk about all of the categories and people have to add crazy Dave has to run it at
4.6 speed how much of our like uh Star Wars Marvel debate did you go out of the episode jump
because if you think about it I don't think the rest will be as contentious I think we all agree
no if you can find a topic on which we all agree we have failed in our podcast setting up a rage
with the other thing we need to talk about with regard to New Zealand is the colonized marginalized
and historically underrepresented people inclusion initiative which Liz knows about
so Conzeland had a previous scholarship which was for people from marginalized communities to tend
Conzeland in person and so it was aimed at people who were in New Zealand specifically those who
identified as Maori, Pacifica, people of color um LGBTQI or disabled and I I'm wondering if this is
now an initiative to expand that given that they're now an online and an online convention where you
don't need to be there in person so presumably adding people to the virtual convention um is
less of an issue because you don't have uh limits on your venue capacity and also your your kind of
marginal costs are minimal it's just kind of expanding your online activities and making sure you have
the people's support for them um and so they have a new membership upgrade initiative to include
support the inclusion of colonized marginalized and historically underrepresented people are at
welcome uh which I think is great because that will hopefully allow a lot more people to attend
virtually um from a lot more different places even more so than when it was actually going to be
physically in uh New Zealand so I think this is a great initiative it sounds like a good initiative
um like obviously um I think inclusion in conventions is a thing that um is it really important and
we've talked before about how virtual conventions can be a way to achieve that and it sounds like
this initiative is kind of putting putting that into practice in a in a way which I think is really
good um it's pretty exciting actually and as I've had numerous conversations with people who are
unable to attend Conziland because of the cost of doing it um some of those people are marginalized
or from groups that will probably be represented by this and we should put a link in the show notes
and we should let everyone know that it's happening because this might be you is there a is there a
deadline for applying for these scholarships nope they're going to say at least weekly as long as
upgrades last I don't know how long upgrades last but there you go
recently there has been a new wave of stories concerning abuse and harassment in the community
and a common thread between many of these is the need to be aware of two factors um firstly the
power dynamic that can exist between more established and less established members of the community
and uh secondly the fact that conventions are professional environments for professional members
of the community and there needs to be more awareness of that so this has been on twitter I think
mostly although obviously it has bled into other discussion venues um and I don't think we're going
to try and link to much because it's very widely distributed and it's very difficult to keep track
of um but we have thoughts I thought this was interesting because I don't have this mindset of
thinking about conventions as professional spaces because for me the conventions are not
professional spaces and I do have you know I do there are professional spaces that I go into
that are conferences in my own field and for me they feel sufficiently different from science
fiction conventions that I don't really think of conventions in that professional way and so
I've been thinking about where this might give me um blind spots in particular I think because I
don't think of them as being professional events for me I don't think of myself as really having
any power in them when maybe I should because if I am say working on program convention and I
have a lot of power over who does and who doesn't get lots of panels lots of readings lots for
cafe clutches how much am I projecting my own biases on there and kind of rewarding professional
names I know and not rewarding professional names I don't know things like that um is what I think
of as just being a hobby of setting these things up actually something which can make a difference to
maybe to the careers of quite junior people who would really like the platform that they can get
at a convention to try and develop their professional careers and also in that a lot of the issues
that have been talked about seem to involve interactions in convention bars this gets us back to the I
think well discussed previously a problem that a lot of interaction does take places in bars and
in particular places with alcohol consumption which obviously is fun for a lot of us but may lead to
extra problems of how do you keep things professional if you are drinking in the bar with people who
may have the power to help or hinder your career that seems remarkably reasonable I think I want
to go slightly further obviously conventions are for some people a professional space they are not
I think primarily a professional space um we I think we would probably most say that the most
most possible degree that the most successful conventions um certainly the most successful
larger conventions are a weird hybrid between personal professional space in that although they
were originally set up by fans as a way to spend social time and they are almost exclusively run
by fans um volunteering to do the organizing it is certainly true that professionals who
are attending the convention professionally enhance the convention in many ways and as I've just kind
of started in a tiny little way attending a conventions professional is valid as well as personally
that I do feel that kind of strange the edge of well I would do this but I will not do this because
it is a it is a professional barrier from your or here is this thing that I can I may be able to
provide a professional service to a convention but is it right for me to provide a professional
service to that convention while I am also a fan attending the convention um I I feel that it is
not reasonable to expect everybody in a convention bar in the evening to behave as if they were
at a professional event and and you would not necessarily want that to happen I think that
I've seen some calls for alcohol and bars at conventions to be um but banned or relegated and I do feel
that that those people are missing the point or certainly the point for me because I am although
I do do some professional work at cons I am primarily there to um have fun with my mates um I feel
that at least one of the stories that I've read has arisen out of somebody believing that they
were engaging in a professional relationship where it's quite possible that the other people involved
in this primarily saw the relationship as a personal one that didn't contain a professional
component and I think there is the issue the one where the issue of how much power as a as a
and a very established writer or he did even as a quote big name fowl I am putting big name fan in
actual scarecoats because these things do not actually exist and and it has always been a joke
I think except obviously it isn't a joke in some ways so and whether people like that do have more
power than they realize you say about big name fans being a joke and and and I see where you're
coming from I I don't feel um I don't feel that the fact that I have been in fandom for longer
than some people gives me any power but it might be that that's because I haven't thought properly
about it what professor hugo nominated mark protector or neglector um the boy um major podcast
editor the coxern yes this this neatly encapsulates the problem which is if you asked me are you
powerful I would probably not immediately rush to say yes and I think that means that I
haven't thought properly about it because I think I do have a I have obviously acutely aware of many
of my axes of privilege um but I think that is an axis of privilege I have not properly thought
about and I think the problem with saying oh you know there's not really any such thing as a big
name fad like I do completely understand where you're coming from but I do wonder whether that is
because we don't properly think about how those power dynamics are actually um in effect in fandom
because I think if you meet someone I remember the first time you know meeting some fans I
don't really heard about you do I remember being scared to meet Greg Pickers Gill right you were
right I'm not necessarily saying he is powerful uh but in some ways he definitely is he had a
power over me when I was a new fan and it's also very easy for me to forget that I've been fandom
for 15 years now so I'm not new anymore and I think it's double easy to forget that because there
are people who have been in fandom a lot longer than me who think I am still new so these are all
really interesting um overlapping power dynamics which are I think quite easy not to think about
which is bad but you know but there are people there are people there are quite a lot of people
at the EasterCon who are not very established in their careers who believe very strongly that
it's very important to be there and I've been on panels with people who I I think were very
introverted writers who almost certainly write very well but who who honestly I think would rather
have been in a bucket of of live crabs for an hour than on an EasterCon panel having to say
things about things and I did feel very sorry for these people and then again who felt that that
was part of professional development for a writer yes I mean what I would hope actually is that
going to EasterCons and other conventions is fun but I would like it if it didn't have that much
impact on careers yes I would agree with that because I do think it I think it is a bunch of
the underrepresented people even further because they're not the people who may feel that they are
able or feel safe in going into a convention bar and you know having a few pints and trying to
just moves with publishing professionals because also as we've seen it's those people who are
taking the bulk of the harassment in situations where it does go wrong and it is not all kind of
nice fun and games and there are power imbalances and and the question there is whether the harassment
or not seriously harassment but whether the unfortunate some of the unfortunate outcomes arise
from a situation where people who are marginalized to begin with feel that they have to go outside
their comfort zone in order to gain acceptance in in the community and as a result
do things that that they probably wouldn't do if they weren't doing them for professional
reasons and at that point you're into a very difficult situation very difficult situations that
you know as we know from other industries lead to terrible abuses and I think it's we should be
clear that convention should be aware of the potential for problems and try and have
good codes of conduct good harassment policies and things to try and mitigate against all these
problems and and obviously listener services and systems so that people who are finding something
is is amiss but at least one of these things that's come out the the incident may happen now and it
may only be years down the line that the ramifications of that come to light I think that's that the
sort of thing and there's only so much the conventions could do there you know if you're in a position
of power try not to abuse it try to realize that the person may be talking to you not because they
like you and think you're marvelous but because they think you may be able to help your career
adapt accordingly that has been the ninth episode of octa thought thank you very much
for listening and it is goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me the theme music
for this episode was spamfare for space by kevin mccloud at ncompetech.com used under a creative commons
attribution 3.0 license
so before we leave you we're going to talk a little bit about staying sane in the apocalypse
so allison what have you been doing to stay sane in the apocalypse the the country seems to have
decided that we all have to go out to pubs and restaurants and i have not been doing that but i
have come to visit my parents which is legal as of yesterday so we're here for two nights which i
believe is allowed within the law and obviously they are getting on so it's quite nice to be
able to come up and help them with symptoms most of which involve operating systems and i feel like
it's back to being it's the first time i felt that i've done anything that's felt like my normal life
for months on end so that's quite nice but i still think in general i'm not that sane and we are
still in an apocalypse oh and if we're greetings to all our american listeners who are really just
kind of at the beginning of an apocalypse right now so i'm very worried for america
i mean i think we're actually in several apocalypse is simultaneously but there is one main one but
personally this week i went to work for two days i worked for my coffee shop one day because all
the power was going off for the annual electrical check in my apartment and i forgot about this
until the air conditioning went off one morning um i have also been to a bar although all the bars
here are already like table service and someone brings you your drinks so i did not like have to go
and cram up at the bar trying to retrieve my pipes they bring them to you it's obviously civilised
so it it does feel more like i am doing the normal everyday things i would do them before but i am
doing them all while wearing a mask so that's obviously a kind of reminder of what's going on
oh my other thing is that um i happened to be reading the anthology new suns original
speculative fiction by people of color but edited by niecesheull i haven't reading that this week and
it is very good it's it's it's not a themed anthology it's just an anthology of like excellent speculative
fiction and it it's got a very high hit rate for me and while i was reading it happened to win the
local award for best anthology so it you should go out and get that i have this day saying in the
apocalypse um by uh it will not surprise anyone to learn playing board games um i recently discovered
the joys of print and play board games i have found a website called docs direct dot com
you could put your beautiful game cards in the show notes john because they really are a thing
of beauty i was very impressed i purchased i purchased several 300 gsm satin prince various board game
print and play stuff and i bought a corner cutter which makes square corners round and i got my
craft knife and my i would i would say cutting board but i actually use a cardboard envelope
because i am pro and i got on with it and now i have print-a-play board games to play even more
board games um also it's like kia like kia's still there had to cute again wasn't that bad
social distancing was fine um most are very good well like kia's always had to go all the way
around the shop on a one-way system hasn't it yes actually this is one of the things that really
made it difficult which is the bit immediately upon getting in was very crowded but as soon as you
got through that bit it was all fine um and the other thing is that my parents are coming to visit
next week which i am very much looking forward to and there's day in a hotel they're not staying
with us because our house is small enough that it might be difficult um to do social distancing
in our house um but yes uh looking forward to that very much
hurrah for people i haven't seen people in so long i'm still not going as far as going to iKEA
iKEA can still bring stuff to me on a truck as far as i'm concerned yeah i'm only going into
shops when it's absolutely essential which means when they sell almond croissants
that's fair no i mean so i would have gotten we have been mostly getting delivery um i will say
the problem is that iKEA's delivery is not um priced if you're just buying like a couple of
odds and ends for your bathroom the delivery costs are exorbitant if we would be getting like you
know several bits of furniture i probably would have done that but i just needed like a toilet roll
holder and a mirror and other things like that so so yeah oh it's a good point because iKEA here
will deliver mine a bit some pieces for about three quid so yeah they just put them in the post
i've certainly got odd things delivered from iKEA without i think there was one thing we tried
that they wanted to deliver for the full whack and that's the problem it's if you're bigger than
whatever could go it it like it's but it'll be your towel rail or something yeah well like it
might have been the bin oh yeah bins i'll get you the bin might have been too big but yeah like
but it was fine i wore my mask um i walked didn't didn't use public transport um so yeah it was fine
i am not sympathetic um oh and i'm taking part in a University of Southampton um
southlinson NHS uh covid 19 testing pilot program where i spit in a small vial and they tell me if
i have coronavirus they don't tell me if i have had coronavirus they tell me if i currently have
coronavirus and i think this is part of them trying to get set up for city-wide testing and
kind of instantaneous timescales or as near as you can get when you're doing this kind of thing
so yeah i'm helping yeah we cannot tell you if you have had coronavirus from your saliva we need
your blood for that john so so we can actually so i can't do blood tests at home i pass out so
spit test is good enough then because an awful lot of people have been stuffing things up their noses
and and it seems like if a spit test was adequate for this wouldn't they just be spitting so there
are various papers comparing the utility of uh an asiparangial swab to saliva and saliva does
seem to come out quite well but i think there's some slightly contradictory results and the other
problem is that i think trying to get people to swap their own noses and throat successfully at home
is quite difficult because really needs a swab you know that you need to like swab your tonsils without
like touching the rest of your mouth which is quite complicated and possibly just spitting in a tube
is better i can spit in a tube successfully but i cannot do any of the other things and i got i
got a blood test at home once and it was like prick your prick your thumb and put blood in the thing
and i have a phobia blood but i was like i could just prick my thumb i can't i can't as it turns out
much easier to get the trained with different city to have the blood test that is to do at home
for john i'll just come around with like a diamond pen and write blue on it for you john and i will
charge you only 20 quid i didn't say like in what time slot i would come and visit you john yeah in
fact john if if i promise to do that will you quarantine me for 14 days in your house oh hello
hello uh why is she unhappy