And I have to, unfortunately, I'm going to have to cut all of this out in case I want to rest Liz,
which is always awkward.
Hello everyone and welcome to the 40th episode of the Octa Thought podcast,
which is coming to you on the 16th of September 2021. I'm John Coxson.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
And we have three letters of comment. Also definitely planning to keep that pause in the final edit.
Don't do that.
Just to illustrate lack of caffeine on the part of one co-host.
So we are recording earlier than normal today because John is off doing actual things in the real
world. So yesterday everyone was like, can you record at nine? And I was like, absolutely,
I'll be wide awake and full of beads at nine o'clock. And this turned out not to be the case.
I mean, I was skeptical.
So we got some letters and tweets of comments and one of the first tweets of comment we got was
from Brigitte Bradshaw who proposes that a Garcia is a billion units of exuberance.
And thus a milligarsia is a million units and a killer Garcia.
I just don't want to see a killer Garcia. That seems like a terrible, terrible idea.
A very exuberant and very dangerous.
And also Bug is hungry for traybake.
Well, now I'm hungry for traybakes again. So you're hungry for traybakes?
Yeah.
I could go for some fridge cake.
I've had a very nice friend Japan tart. I'm not really hungry for traybakes.
You're a very nice friend Japan tart.
Did we not get a whole pile of letters about the traybake nature of 15s?
No, literally no one commented on that. So apparently we nailed it.
Thanks listeners. Thanks for, thanks for approving of our take on 15s.
Or maybe we just don't have very many listeners.
If you disapprove of our take on 15s, please write in.
Even if you're listening to this episode like months later,
please still write in. We feed on your approval and disapproval and basically interaction.
Shouldn't that be we feed upon your approval and disapproval?
As speaking of alchem horror.
Mark Plummer wrote in saying, "Sorry for the silence from these parts.
I'm several episodes behind now and I've decided to skip ahead to the current one.
We encourage people to do that if they get behind.
Please don't let Alk to become a source of stress in your life,
unless you're innocent in which case it's basically unavoidable."
Mark does say that he got behind with his listening because he's been struggling to get
to grips with the latest version of alchem horror.
And I know what Mark means because I picked up the latest version of alchem horror yesterday
from my friendly local game shop and it's got a lot of cards in it.
And I really did have to take my time to sit down and properly digest them all.
So I'm right there with you, Mark. I did like the sled dogs though, big up to them.
Is there a new version of alchem horror?
Well there's a new pack that came out like on Friday. It's very good. I like it.
Oh I see. But there are new packs that come out every Friday, isn't that how they get you?
No, they've actually moved distribution models so they're only releasing about two packs a year now.
I was getting it confused with Eldritch Horror.
Oh Eldritch Horror. There was an advert for Eldritch Horror on the back of the booklet that came
in my new alchem horror card.
Is this the time to talk about how I'm grinding legend in Hearthstone?
It's a family show, Alison.
I just want to say that I got to the very top of level one and had a game where if I'd won the game,
I would have got legend on three separate occasions yesterday and I lost all of those games.
And now I'm back at level four and I'm very, very, very, very pissed off.
Good time for a podcast, yeah.
Mark was surprised by the hard line nature of the discount policy, but he does see a logic to it
because he does sort of agree with Alison that it does mean some parts of the community are
effectively barred from the world con. But he says that he thinks the counter to that is there
were obviously still in exceptional circumstances. And he thinks that it's good for events like this
to have a clear and unambiguous policy lines as it makes it easier for the convention staff who
have to deal with the policy on the day. And it kind of, but he says, well, I understand the
policy does feel like a recipe for no fun. And I think that kind of, we had that discussion
last episode. I did a coin of where we ended up coming down where we had to say why. But yeah.
Yeah, I think I think fundamentally I do think that conventions will feel slightly less fun for
a while while there is the whole masking and vaccination and indeed like all events at the
moment feels like you're like, oh, maybe it's just me. Oh, but we had fun last weekend and it felt
like majestic fun because we haven't had enough fun recently. So even small amounts of fun feel
fantastic. So I'm not, I think objectively people will probably have just as much fun as they always
did. They will have an amount of fun, which is as much higher as the background level of fun as usual.
It's just that we've adjusted the background level of fun. Write in with your explanations
of how fun scales work and whether a logarithmic or a linear scale and
set appropriate measurements of fun. We could definitely go there.
Now, now I'm a bit sad that we've already assigned the Garcia as a unit of exuberance
because we really could have tied these two things together if we'd known we were going to say them.
Exuberance and fun and not the same thing, John. I could understand that you might, from your
point of view, see it that way. I know. That was literally the point I was making was that it was
a shame we couldn't use the Garcia for units of fun. So I already made that clear in my statements.
Okay, so readers, what is the SI unit for fun? Do please tell us.
I believe it's Newton's Permita squared. I'm sure that's not fun. I am not. Anyway.
God, I feel old now. Mark also says he's been looking at the Discon membership numbers,
which is excellent. He thinks that they've had about 900 people joining as attending
membership since last November. But he notes that there's only about 280 virtual members and
there are about 2000 supporters. And he's wondering why more supporters haven't paid the relatively
small extra amount for virtual access. And I am one of these people because I haven't got around
to it yet. So I should probably do that because he says it could just be down to, as we've talked
about before, the general tendency to join virtual convention late because there's no need for the
attendee to plan their attendance. But he wonders whether the Discon is going to know how many virtual
members they're going to need to cater for. And that's an interesting problem I thought of.
So yeah, I don't know how that's all going to shake out. I think a significant
proportion. I mean, I think actually we do have walking stick curves for, we have membership curves
virtual conventions now. Discon could reach out to other virtual conventions and get a pretty good
idea of of how that's going to work. My guess would be that they'll have double the number of
members they have a week before the convention starts. And that's just that's what they should
plan for. My estimate would be given they've got 280 now they're looking at at least 600. But that
is assuming the punctuation curve applies to a Worldcom. And I have no idea if it does. But it
seemed like the best guess you could make at the moment. I mean, I can't remember whether was it
contested bidding for 2021? I cannot remember it all. But I mean, a lot of those sporting members might
be people who voted at Dublin, but then absolutely cannot go because they cannot get to US. And also
not really interested in a virtual membership because of time zones. So you could have a lot of people
in that situation. I mean, I signed up for virtual membership, but I don't know how much I'll actually
get to watch. That's an interesting point, Liz. But in fact, DC was an opposed at Ireland, as is
mentioned on the excellent website, worldcom.org by first time call that Kevin Stanley. Yeah, but lots
of people vote. Yeah. There's a lot of things going on here. I think Worldcon has thousands of
supporting members, probably somewhere between one or 2000, who are people who never go to Worldcon
or might go to Worldcon if it's in a city very close to them, but would not otherwise go to a
Worldcon, but who are readers and who are essentially supporting now to be part of the voting community.
Now we don't know necessarily whether that's something that's good or bad, but I think it is
out there. People do buy memberships just so they can read the stuff from the voter packet.
I think also, did you say they've got 2,000-800 attending members? I think Mark's bringing facts
into this conversation, which is quite strange. So Mark said that there were 2,500 attending
members of which 900 have joined in about the last year. Yes, I think those 2,500 attending
members, I think quite a lot of them will not attend, but will not ask for refunds because of
the whole community support thing. So they could downgrade to virtual. I think there's probably a
limit for when they have to have done that by. You could downgrade to supporting member by the end
of August. You can still downgrade to virtual membership until the beginning of December.
Yeah, so I think that there will be people who are still watching and waiting and considering
whether they might go. And there will also be people who are definitely not going to attend,
but either don't get around to downgrading or who downgraded at the last minute because,
you know, it's the last minute. That's when you do things, isn't it?
So I think quite a lot of their virtual members will already be attending members.
And so they're probably, I assume they're accounting for all of that stuff.
I think it's easier to scale up a virtual convention at the last minute than to scale up a,
well, it depends how complicated your tech stack is. You'd hope. Yeah, I don't know how easy it is
to scale up a hybrid convention, but I don't think they're doing proper hybrid. They're doing
two conventions, one of which is impersonal, one of which is virtual rather than doing a single
convention, which is hybrid, right? What is the distinction between those, John?
I think I am right in saying I might be wrong, but I got the impression that virtual attendees
would not necessarily be able to watch panels which were happening in DC. They would be able to
watch panels which were being put on virtually by DC. And so I think the distinction between a
hybrid and a hybrid convention and a physical and virtual convention happening at the same time is
that virtual members will not be able to interact with the physical convention.
Is my belief I could be wrong there, right in if I'm wrong listeners, because I might be.
I don't know. I don't know if it's going to be purely virtual things happening that presumably
will be streamed somewhere in the convention as well, or if it's actually going to be streaming
off certain streams from this con. I mean, my suspicion is going to be a mix of both,
because then you get to include people that can't be there in person. I don't know if you're going
to have say, online panels with online participants which are streamed to the physical location,
or even the most difficult thing, panels which are part online and part in person mixed together.
I don't even know actually. I'd also like to give respect to Mark Plummer for managing to
find the membership numbers on the Discord site, because I cannot do that. I'm very impressed.
Mark Plummer regularly impresses me. I should make that into a ribbon, often impressed by Mark
Plummer. Mark might not enjoy that. He might. I won't do it if you don't want me to, Mark.
So, I am going to say I have to give a factual update to something I said earlier. I said I was
only a supporting member, but I have on the very podcast upgraded to a virtual membership for
the princely sum of 25 US dollars. See how easy it is to do to do it now. I'd like
there to be lots of people at virtual discount though, because it is the weekend before Christmas,
I'm not 100% certain how much time I'm going to be able to give it. Christmas involves a lot of,
you know, faffing about, and I'm normally pretty busy that we can before Christmas, so, you know,
I think I feel like that'll be a thing. Well done for posing a direct question to Mark on this
podcast so that he is forced to send us a letter of comment, even if he hasn't caught up on the
previous episodes. We should get, we could scan the IP addresses of all of our regular listeners,
and then write questions to all of them for next weeks. Questions to octa-thong podcast,
where we ask each of you a direct question tailored to your needs and abilities.
Can we do that? I don't think we should do that. I would like to say I'm not sure we know the IP
addresses of all of our listeners, and listeners, if you're currently panicking that we do, I'm
pretty sure we don't. I've been watching Mythic Quest and apparently that's an easy thing to find out.
Yeah, I'm not sure Mythic Quest is 100% factually accurate, but I think maybe we'll get to that
later on. Well, and also in Mythic Quest, they're not using a podcasting platform that they haven't
built, which is another key differentiator. But yes, and also Mark finishes by saying that he
thinks conversation is the most Caroline Mullen convention name imaginable, and I don't know what
that means, but I'm happy that he thinks it. I do know what she means. How well do you know Caroline,
John? Not very. There you go then. Chris Garcia wrote in to tell us that he is only giving his
letter of comment, 0.36 Garcia's, which is 360 million units of exuberance. Oh, I've just understood
Bugs tweet. The one you read out, 20 million. She's not. She's not proposing the Garcia is a unit of
exuberance. She's proposing that the RCA is a unit of exuberance, and therefore a Garcia is a
giga RCA. I had not appreciated that. So I say yes. So 0.36 Garcia is only 0.36
giga RCA's, which is 360 million RCA's. So that's quite a lot of exuberance.
But does Chris giving us 0.36 Garcia's mean that he's only giving us like 36% of his regular levels
of enthusiasm, or I don't know. Well, I'll tell you, I've only given you 36% of my regular levels
of enthusiasm. I offered multiple times to podcast at a different time for Alison's benefits, and I
was like, no, no, no, I'll drink some pint of coffee. It'll be fine. I am fine. I am fine.
I am so fine. In fact, I'm I'm definitely at least a bit. What was it? At least a bit,
Garcia. You're so fine. You're now making jokes about it. We understand.
Oh, I've just worked out the Briarly. A Briarly is the unit of how many coffees you need in the
morning before you're awake, measured in points. And that is very, I think, very in keeping with
Claire's approach to coffee, because I've seen her caffeinate and she takes it seriously.
I believe my normal level is 0.36 Briarly's. I mean, I'm surprised just to live because that is a
large amount of coffee. So Chris says that losing Earl was a massive bummer and kind of expresses
some reminiscent about that. And yeah, I can imagine like, obviously, if a friend of yours goes,
then that is always going to be a huge hardship. And sorry, sorry, sorry about that, Chris. But he
also writes in about COVID policies. And he says it, he thinks it's illegal to require negative
testing for attendees. He's basically saying that you can't do negative testing and you can't do
exemptions because of US privacy laws. And I am curious about that. I don't know much about US law.
There'll be a lot of there's also going to be a lot of state and local jurisdictions. It seems
very likely that DC took advice on what was possible in in the place that the planet told the convention.
And use that to inform the policy. And he also says he went to a historians convention,
which was done in a hybrid model, where everyone wore clear masks, but all of the masks were mic'd.
So if you wore them, it miked your voice underneath the mask. And that is magic. And we did not
consider that as an option last time. But that is like the idea that you might have. But then I
guess you'd have to have a mask for our tendees. I can't imagine that's cheap. But that is that
is clever. It's definitely clever. Or a sanitation sanitation system that works for those for those
mics. If we have a sound engineer in the in the audience, please please let us know your thoughts
on miking under the mask. And incidentally, miking under the mask is the name of a new reality TV
show and our superhero expose. I would also note that Chris says they sent mini bottles of
Scotts to all attendees, which is maybe an excellent tradition for hybrid conventions.
I do quite like that. When we did a leaving party at work, my boss got tiny bottles of
champagne sent to everyone for the leaving party. And that did feel much more like a leaving party
than other zoom leaving parties I have been to, where I did not have a tiny bottle of champagne.
I say champagne, prosecco. Fizz. Phil Dyson tweets as to say that he thinks the greatest high school
movie ever is Heathers, which I have not heard about, but we will put a link in the show notes.
Alison is laughing quite a lot, and I'm assuming that there's something happening here that I
don't know about. No, no, no, you've not heard of Heathers. No. Oh my god. Oh my god. I understand
that people are young, but oh my god. How can you not have heard of Heathers?
Liz, am I, is this, have you heard of feathers? Am I, am I sorry, Heathers? Ah, for enough.
Yeah, I think I think you are actually an outlier for people, even people of your age, but I might
be wrong about that. So yeah, no, Heathers is an extremely influential movie. If you have any
interest in the history of, I guess, outcast culture. I think, I think Heathers is quite an
important movie, and it's also very good. And yeah, and it's kind of, of its time a bit, it doesn't
necessarily hold up as well as it did when it was new, but yeah, maybe the greatest high school
movie. It's a real counterpoint to a lot of the other things that were around at the time, because
yeah, because it's different. That's great movie. Yeah, and it's something that often comes
up on those lists of the best high school movies ever. But I mean, John, have you heard of things
like, you know, the Breakfast Club and 16 candles and that kind of thing? Because it feels like
it's of a contemporary of those. I've seen the Breakfast Club, and I've heard of 16 candles,
and I've watched various Bueller's Day Off, which looking at the date was like about four years before.
So like, I think I'm familiar with other films that were in that way. I just haven't heard of
this particular one. Yes. But looking at the cast, I think there is probably an argument that I
really should have done because I don't think that just don't, we don't think else about it.
In fact, don't even look at the pack cover. Oh, no, it's too late. Yeah. I read that there's a blurb
and it tells you like, he went to Wikipedia 10 minutes ago. Yeah. Don't read a synopsis, just
watch the film. It'll be good for you. You like movies. You've been watching great movies. This
is a movie that you should definitely have watched. If you have any interest in, Heather's is a film
that is very much in your wheelhouse. You'll appreciate it. From the synopsis, it sounds amazing.
I'm very, very, very surprised to discover that you do not already seen Heather's.
Go, go. Is the Spaniard around? Yeah. I text her. Yeah. Go, go, go, go and ask his Spanish. Say,
"Allison is surprised that I've never seen Heather. Should I, should she be?"
The typing you can hear listeners is me texting my wife to, uh, to ask her this question.
Well, while you're doing so, I would like to say that, um, while Heather is great,
if we are allowed to count it as a high school movie, I would like to put forth the proposition
that Billenteds excellent adventure is the best high school film. Uh, it's a stoner movie. Is that
a high school movie? I feel like most of it doesn't take place in a high school. I may be not remembering
but then again, Ferris Bueller's day off almost entirely doesn't take place. Yeah, no, that's right.
So something like, I mean, there's a sense of which gross point blank. I've heard of that,
but I haven't seen it. It's a great high school movie. Right in listeners. What's your
favorite readers? What's the best high school movie? Yep. Anyway, and then we have one final lock.
So Roman thoroughly enjoyed episode 38 and liked the surf sound and the pleasant chat around the
table and notes. There was no problem with sound balance despite the warnings, but added a little
note to me saying that there's a wonderful tool called the levelator, which is very good. I'll put
link in the show notes for anyone who is making podcasts. Good tool to have in your arsenal.
And indeed, I did level the sound. So a secret. Um, and also, um, he's notes. Uh, while Celsius
may be foreign to the Americans, the rest of us have no real problem with it. Of course, you could
meet at Denali, Alaska, which is also called Mount McKinley, where the average temperature is
apparently minus 40 degrees. And therefore, there's no argument about Fahrenheit and Celsius. But
there might be an argument about whether or not it was a sensible place to go given how bloody cold
it is. Yes. No. I mean, the arguments we have at the moment is me and Alison saying all 21s
are a bit hot and Liz being like, no, it isn't. Uh, so, but I think we would all agree minus 40 was
quite chilly. One member of our podcast voluntarily lives in Thailand and the other two don't.
I would just like to say that every minute we record this podcast is a minute that I'm not
in the swimming pool. So, you know, there's upside. So Liz did send a lovely photo of her
summer office, which had sky and plants and sunshine and palm trees. A very relaxed feeling to it.
And it did look very good.
Last week, we didn't go into any detail about the NHS COVID pass, which is a thing that the NHS
offers through the NHS app. And that is not the NHS COVID app. That is the central NHS app. Instead,
in order to get an NHS COVID pass, you have to have had a full vaccination with the COVID vaccine
used in the UK. And you can get the past two weeks after your second dose. You can get a pass if
you've had a negative PCR or rapid lateral flow test within the last 48 hours and you can get to
the pass as soon as you have your result. And you can get one if you've had a positive PCR test
within the last six months. And you can get the pass after you've finished self isolating and up to
180 days after the test. And it notes that none of these are things you can do in the Isle of Man.
So conventions and attendees for conventions from the Isle of Man should take all this with a large
pinch of salt. And I believe Scotland, you use the NHS Inform app and then in Northern Ireland,
use the N.I.E. direct app. And they may have different stuff. But that does mean that if you
are a convention and you're thinking, how can we offer a way of making sure that our convention
attendees are less likely to have COVID than they might otherwise be? The NHS COVID pass is a good
way of doing that that incorporates people who are vaccinated, but also provides options for
people who cannot get vaccinated for different reasons. And basically just means you have a thing
on your phone that you wave and it handles all of the things you should have to look and be like,
yes, that is the NHS COVID pass. We are happy. Hurrah, which takes a lot of the deciding what
counts as proof parts out of your convention planning. And it's something that convention runners
possibly should look at as a good thing to do this sort of stuff. I'm going to put a link in the
show notes. And the stuff I said about Northern Ireland Scotland is at the bottom of the page
that I have linked. Also in terms of feedback from our last episode in the UK Easticon group
on Facebook, which we recommend if you like that sort of thing, Fran Dowd said, there's a very good
discussion about conventions, COVID policies and the latest octa-thorpe. Thank you, Fran. And Nick Whitehead
responded to say, that's very useful because we're currently discussing this for Bristolcon,
which is one of the conventions we mentioned last time as not having announced their policy. So thank
you, Nick. Thank you, Fran. And Bristolcon, I did email in between the two episodes to ask whether
they had a policy and their policy is very much. We would really appreciate it if you could wear a
mask and not have COVID, which is I think a good place to start from. But I would encourage
conventions to look at the NHS COVID pass, because I think that does more than just politely asking
attendees not to have COVID. Obviously, see, discussions last episode about, you know,
you can always, whatever you pick, if someone's really determined to attend your convention with
COVID, they will be able to do that because you can forge all of these things. The thing you're
hoping to do is instill a level of compliance in people who are not trying to be actively
malicious, but may not have thought properly about the safety of everything before going about their
day. I mean, I was just going to say that I think there is also difference to things like Bristolcon,
which are basically as big as like a medium size wedding and things like potentially
a fancy conno-easticon who might be getting into the high hundreds of members. I think if you're
sort of a smaller convention, like the risks and issues are a little bit different.
It's so good to have a policy, obviously, but I can see why they've gone for a slightly sort of
softer, yes, please wear masks and so on. I don't know. I mean, is that an artificial distinction?
I just feel there is a difference between, you know, this conwear would say, well, you potentially
will have 2,000 people in Bristolcon where you probably will have 100.
Yes, I think it's a big difference. I have a very mathematical feeling to this, and although in
practice you probably do hang around with your personal mates, no matter how big the convention
you're going to is, I think that's the thing about mandating mask wearing in public areas and
when moving around the convention, because those are the times that you're likely to have close
interaction with people who you're not just generally hanging out with.
Ta. So, I will say, although I do understand where both of you are coming from and I do
understand there's a difference in risk, I do think that most, I find it difficult to imagine
a convention where I'm like, yeah, but it's fine if people turn up with COVID, right?
And so I think still I would say use the NHS app because that gives you a good way of saying this
person probably doesn't have COVID. And that seems like, that seems like my minimum like
requirement from any event is it would be nice if they were just double checking that people
don't have the owner. Yeah, in the last festival we went to, they were basically checking everyone
for either an up-to-date NHS app or the text from the NHS say you'd had a lateral flow in the last
24 hours, because obviously that's very fakable as we know, but I don't think anyone necessarily would.
I should say this lasts for as long as free lateral flow tests are available,
at which point this system breaks down a bit. It would be a great shame if the government
stops allowing free lateral flow tests, but at the same time, if you are not doing something
at your convention to say we would actually quite like to have some measure of control over
people arriving at our event not having COVID, that is the point which I start saying, I might
just not go then. And so I do sort of take your point, but if people do go that way of, oh, well,
we can't demand this because there are no free lateral flow tests, I can go that is a great
shame, but I will stay at home. So I do, I think I actually 100% disagree, you know, sorry.
I'm hoping the government won't do that, but if they are stupid enough to do that, that will be
a shame, but it will, I don't think it will change my mind. I mean, I hope they don't, but it does
make it different to me because I can't get an NHS COVID pass. So, I mean, I'm not looking at
coming to any UK conventions in the future, but if I do, I can't get one. I'm very much talking
about like, I think convention needs to think quite carefully about what proof they'll accept from
kind of overseas attendees. Sorry, I should have said that. So I don't want to rehash the
discussion we had last time completely, but my main concern with this gone was there,
they didn't have an exceptions policy. And I feel like you need to have an exceptions policy.
You need to say, if there's a reason you cannot do this, let's talk. And then you can say, no,
you're in, you're out. I think that is also very, yeah, because like you say, Liz, like if you can't
get an NHS COVID pass because like, that's not possible, then then I do think like, you've been
double-japped. So that should be something that can be sort of coped with. And I kind of understand
that the DC as a 2000 person convention may not have the bandwidth to deal with the exemptions
and stuff. But like, if you're a convention that's going to have like 100 attendees, you can probably
talk to the one or two people for whom there needs to be a conversation.
Lastly on convention COVID-19 policies, Corflu have updated their website basically along the
lines of the Novocon website to say, we are going to have a policy, but we're waiting a little bit
longer before we decide what that policy will be. And I heard from Peter Sullivan, who is on the
Corflu Committee, that he is now the Corflu Committee member whose job it is to listen to Octa Thorpe.
And that that slightly terrifies me. So, hurrah, thank you to Corflu. Thank you to Corflu very
much for doing this because I think this is a fantastic development. They all should be. This
is a brilliant post that every convention should have on its staff. Are they listening to us for
advice or in case we say anything, you know, scandalous? No, I think they're listening to us.
So that if we say every convention should do X and if they don't will be grumpy, they can be
like, oh no, we should do X. And that is a level of responsibility that frankly terrifies me.
I mean, I think there's a lot of things you can do that make Octa Thorpe grumpy and you're never
going to avoid them all. Because you can do things that will make one third of Octa Thorpe grumpy in
two thirds very happy. We just do that one. That's another podcast. This podcast might or might not
be based on said, it's a job to be grumpy about conventions. That's what we do. But I think it's
also important to be happy about conventions when conventions do good things. And so I think
Corflu has done a good thing. And they're also spooling up their discord. And that's very exciting.
I don't know if that's public, but I saw a sneak peek as British fandom's chief discord opinion
have her. Discordian, we might say. Yeah, no, I might like to tap into your discord knowledge for
a discord. I might or might not be setting up. Would it be a discord on which people could have
conversation? You can't see listeners cannot see John's look, which is the look of
that bird that looks like that. There's a GIF. John is being a reaction gift right there.
Yes, but yes, good stuff. Thank you to Corflu for having basically for putting something on
the website. I think that is important. I note that fantasy con still hasn't segueing neatly into
fantasy con, which is before our next episode. So if you're listening to this episode,
fantasy con will be before you listen to our next episode. Unless I mean, that is always true. But
obviously, if you're listening to this episode in like 2024, you definitely missed it. But yes,
so it is on the weekend of the 25th and 26th of September 2021. And Farah Mendelsohn is going to
be there representing East con 2024. And I think other East cons may also have people there to chat.
I think there's going to be a shared table. Yeah, I think we have somebody there, but they're
on the committee. So they're not exactly going to be chatting. Conversation will have someone there,
but they will be on the committee. So they may not be super free because they may be having
important con runner type conversations. But equally, if you see people you think,
oh, they're probably involved with an East con, check it up and ask them. Never goes wrong.
It is fancy con. Is it the first like UK in person con? Yes, that was far as arguments for
why the East con should have a table. I really interested to know like what the vibe is. Is it
going to be like, yes, we've all been released from released from COVID prison? Or is it actually
going to be slightly like, I don't know, we're all now bit cautious and be very interested.
I mean, obviously I'm not going. It's it's fantasy con. It's going to be a succession of business
lunches. I've never entered fancy con. I thought there was world fancy con though. I thought like a
UK fancy con was slightly less so. Farah con is also happening before next episode, but it's sold out.
So none of us can go. Liz is a bit sad that she missed out on tickets. Me and Alison are less sad.
No, I'm going. I have a ticket. I'm attending. It's next weekend. Yeah, I don't know if it's sold
out or just they closed memberships and I forgot to buy one. It's closed. Never mind. I mean,
they're probably busy anyway and I would have only gone to the fringe bits. So it's fine. Although
they're not the fringe anymore. They're called bonfire, but I'm not like super sad. Just I was
going to pick one up and then I forgot and then it was like, oh, they're closed. Oh,
fire con memberships have closed. And so if you're hearing about fire con for the first time now,
then unfortunately is too late for you to attend as Liz found to her peril. But Alison has secured
a membership so she will be a roving octa thought reporter. I will. I think most of the stuff remains
at a time zone that is is not perfect for me and I don't know how much hanging around in bars.
There'll be that being my primary interest in conventions, even virtual ones. But I'm looking
forward to it. And that is next weekend. Yay. Good stuff. And then the beginning of October,
we have octacon, which is virtual. Yes. And the last virtual octacon was very, very good. We
liberally borrowed ideas from it for the first punctuation. So if you attended punctuation and
you quite like punctuation, you may quite like octacon. So I'd recommend giving it a look and
we will put a link in the show notes. It is the weekend of the first to the third of October 2021.
I will be on the Isle of White. We're going to do pics listeners. Pics is where every episode we
talk about a thing we liked that was genre in the last two weeks. Every episode? Yes. We got this
right. Because if we're not, if we're not able every two weeks to be like here is a thing in SF
that I like, we might want to consider that we need to read more SF that we like. Or watch or play.
Or watch or play. But I think if you, what, what, what if I read and watch and play lots of stuff
for it's all shit? I probably do, but they're not necessarily science fiction thing. Like,
I haven't actually read any science fiction books for a while. I think it's okay if you're
picked not to be genre. Obviously prefer genre. Essentially, I kind of go, I don't really want
to talk about something that's mediocre in genre over something that's fantastic in genre.
If you're, if your choice, if your choice is between something crappy in genre and something
great and not a genre, I'd go for the great. But Liz doesn't want to do pics every two weeks and
I think we probably should do pics every two weeks. I think actually, oh, we can try to pick
three weeks, but I mean, I think thinking about it, we can always say I have no pick this week
because I've been lackadaisical. Yes, or we can always chop them out if we are running long
because despite having basically no topics this week, we have just talked for an hour.
Are we going to do pics? So we're going to do like a thing from the last two weeks that we've
enjoyed or interacted with and we'd recommend to our listeners, usually genre. But if the thing
we've listened to is, or the thing we've interacted with is not genre, then we might recommend non-genre
things listeners prepare to have your horizons broadened. My pick this episode is the case of
Charles Dexter Ward. Now, I know Alison has opinions about BBC podcasts and we will get to those
in a second or two. But the BBC has done a podcast called the Lovecraft Investigations,
where they've basically been adapting Lovecraft stories as true crime podcasts, fictional true
crime podcasts. And the first one they did was the case of Charles Dexter Ward, which is a
10 episode podcast you can listen to on iPlayer or I've also put the RSS in the show notes. And
it was my first exposure to the story of the case of Charles Dexter Ward, and I really enjoyed it.
And I've been reading the thing on the doorstep and other weird stories by HP Lovecraft, which is
a penguin book that I've put links to in the show notes. And that contains the original novel.
And so I have read the original novel. I find Lovecraft difficult to read because he never uses
one word where 14 would do. And usually it's quite dense. I can't read it when I'm sleepy because I
just fall asleep. I am glad I read it because there are a couple of bits from the podcast adaptation
that I felt were a little bit unclear and made more sense having read the book. But I am glad I
listened to the adaptation first actually. And yeah, I really enjoyed the adaptation. The book is fine.
I think it's probably one of Lovecraft's better stories. I can see why it's one of the ones that
kind of caught the public imagination. But at the same time, it is very Lovecraft. So, you know,
take that with a pinch of salt. And it has all of the racism you'd expect. So, hurrah. But yeah,
that's my pick. That's a thing I enjoyed this week. When I say I have opinions about podcasts,
I think the I prefer in general to listen to unscripted podcasts. So the problem with
podcasts from big media organizations is that they're never really unscripted. Or they go
through multiple levels of editing for tone, which I think takes the edge off them. But actually,
that sounds like doing a true crime version. Another fiction story sounds like exactly the
sort of thing that they might be quite good at. So yeah. No, it was good. No. And I think
you're right. Like, because the other BBC podcast I really liked is 13 minutes to the moon. But that
is like, and that's nonfiction, but is much more scripted. And I think most of the podcasts I
listen to tend to be more discussion unscripted. And the BBC doesn't really do that. Alison, do
you have a pick? I do. So the otherwise award was announced this week. Again,
Chovwe Donald-Eckpeke has won the otherwise award for Ify Yoku, the tale of Imadiyouaga Bon.
The author who was actually a Facebook friend of mine, and who has been nominated for tons of
things over the last year or two. But this is the first, first big award that they've won. And I'm
pretty sure they're thrilled. And I'm very pleased. And it's a very interesting story. And
when you read it, some there are places in it where if you're reading with a kind of UK or
probably American accessibility, you go, Oh, there's some editing that didn't happen here. This is,
this is not this doesn't this bit doesn't necessarily fit together with that bit in the way that you
would expect. And I am telling you that you should ignore the fact that it is not copy edited perfectly
because this is a great and interesting novella. And I'm very pleased to have read it. It's basically
about a community that's kind of like Wakanda in that they've hidden away from the West.
Well, the rest of the world in a post-apocalyptic situation that's very bad.
Yeah, and it's good. Really liked it. Where can I read it? It's in an anthology, Dominion,
an anthology of speculative fiction for Africa and the from Africa and the African diaspora,
which you might have to buy. I'm afraid it's the thing, but you can buy it. It's easily available on
all good electronic bookstores and bookstores near you. And also morally questionable ones.
Well, you wouldn't want to buy from one of those, would you? It depends if you've got a Kindle or not.
I do buy from the more unquestionable books, because yeah, it's a good place to buy books.
Good pick. I will look that up. It looks like it costs somewhere in the region of...
Is that 7 quid? It costs me about 7 quid.
Yeah, 7 quid for the ebook or about 20 for the physical copy. And I will put links to those in
the show notes. Liz, do you have a pick?
I have been catching up on season two of Star Trek Lower Decks, which is an animated series
about bunch of vensons on the USS Cerritos, which is the Federation Starship that gets all the
really crap jobs to do. And it is funny and it is a chop full of Star Trek references, and it is
not afraid to poke some fun at itself and all other Star Trek series. There's some very funny
jokes involving a Tom Paris commemorative plate. You got a love boy. I do love a bit of a
referencing. Yeah, it's basically funny. The voice acting is great. I would say it's a good solid
bit of Star Trek, and I like that it kind of co-exists alongside Discovery, which is kind of
the more serious cousin as something which is like, yeah, we're going to have a funny show.
And also, if you've watched lots of Deep Space Nine, there'll be some extra jokes.
I quite like that, I think it's really good. Every time we finish an episode on Amazon Prime,
which is where it is in the UK, it recommends I watch Future Armor, and it does kind of feel
like a Star Trek-y Futurama in a way. I think the humor is a bit more closely aligned with my
humor than Futurama was. And yeah, if you'd like funny sci-fi, I would highly recommend giving it
a shot. I think it's a good pick. Yes, I would say it is pretty Futurama, which for me is very high
praise, and certainly like some of the background gags and things like that, and going to Futurama
levels. Just needs more songs. I was concerned that I hadn't seen enough Star Trek to enjoy
Lower Decks. I don't think that is too referential. I mean, I've seen like, movies and quite a lot of
original Star Trek and various other bits of Star Trek here and there, but I'm not really
much into Star Trek, so... I don't think... I think if you are heavily into Star Trek,
there are a lot of references that will make you happy, but I don't think any of the...
I don't think you need to understand the references to enjoy the show, because I think most of the
actual jokes are not requiring of a high level of Star Trek expertise. They will be funny any...
I think if you know the general tone of most of the Star Trek shows, which tend towards the
tend towards the serious end of things tend to have quite a lot of worthy goals and moral dilemmas,
then I think if you know that's kind of the tone of most of the live action shows,
then you will get why what Lower Decks is doing is funny, even if you don't know the specifics.
And just before two things before we go, firstly, File 770 reports that the UK has a new national
film and science fiction museum, which James Bacon wrote a review of in File 770 and is located in
the beautiful Milton Keynes. So if you are located near to Milton Keynes, you can go and have a look.
I say science fiction, it's actually sci-fi. Some people get very annoyed by that sort of thing,
but personally I don't. And then secondly, I texted my wife to say, "Should I have heard of Heathers?"
And she said, "Only if you're a Gen Xer." So hello, Liz and Allison, come here, Gen Xers.
I'm the young one. I was still the young one.
It may be. I mean, I'm slightly too old to be a Gen Xer, but it's, I mean, I'm clearly Gen X
because I'm too young to be a baby boomer, but I just didn't get between those two.
But it is kind of quintessential Gen X movie, yes. So if you want to understand how Gen X feels,
Heathers is a good movie to understand that. And I would like to say I'm not in fact Gen X.
I am an elder millennial, John. She wears a cape and a hood,
listeners, and she chants, chants, "Eldrich things."
I think I'm basically a millennial, but less f*cked over than some of the later ones, basically.
I don't really believe in generations.
And that was the 40th episode of the Octa Thought podcast, and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me, and it's goodbye from me.
[Music]
What will you be doing on the Isle of Wight, John?
I'm going on holiday with my parents, and we're going to have a mostly outdoor
holiday, and it's quite well timed because I'm moving away from Southampton.
And so exploring the Isle of Wight properly before we go is something that is good.
And for those who are space nerds, which may have some overlap with science fiction nerds,
the Isle of Wight is where the British rocket programme when it existed was
based, and so you can go and see the old launch sites and stuff like that.
And so that is one of the things I would be doing.
Oh, I thought it was based in Wumara.
So the actual launch sites for the Black Arrow, Black Arrow is the Needles, which is in the Isle of Wight.
What, what's to be launched for?
Well, because I don't know, it might be that they also launch from Wumara.
Obviously, Wumara is harder to get to from the Isle of Wight than the Isle of Wight,
being as it is in Australia.
But Alison has committed to go there on her guff trip, so she can report back.
There was a test launch.
I mean, it may well be, it may well be that there were, there were nuclear tests, so Wumara.
I didn't think Black Knight, it was tested at the Needles, but they were,
they were launched in Australia, they were launched at Wumara.
I mean, I, I, I was like, oh, really? Not Wumara?
Let me, let me give you a link.
So the rockets were, um,
they were obviously not, I think we'd know if they'd be launched from the UK.
I don't think, don't think we've ever launched any, and people will know.
Yeah, but they, we did launch ones from the UK, it's just that they were not where the
satellites were launched from, but there were rocket launches from, from the Needles.
It's just that they didn't have payload, because that's how you test a rocket,
you launch it and see if it blows up, and you hope it doesn't.
The Black Arrow was launched from Wumara.
If it's not too much trouble, they were live tested.
Can we conclude a podcast and possibly our go over rocket launches at a late date?
Yeah, how do you live test a rocket without launching the rocket?
No, we cannot.
No rocket, no rockets ever left the launch pad at I down, but the ship took Wumara in
South Australia for launch.
That's much less exciting.
Us are really, and as they say, Britain is the only country in the world to have developed a
successful satellite launch, but never actually, but then abandoned it, because that's a very
British thing to do. But this was why I was determined to go and see Wumara at,
as part of my guff trip. I mean, I was...
Wumara is significantly harder to get to than the Isle of Wight.
Not on a virtual trip, it's not. In fact, it might be easier to get to on a virtual trip.
I don't know how easy the Isle of Wight is to do virtually, because they haven't
got electricity on the internet yet. Anyway, go to the Wight.
I love the bit about Wumara and the Isle of Wight, so please keep as much of that in as you can.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod in
Competec.com, used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.
[BLANK_AUDIO]