I definitely don't want to go off topic, but congratulations to Australia for kicking the
Tories out. Well done.
Yes, now this is good.
You absolutely just did go off topic.
You can't say I don't want to go off topic and then go off topic. Just do it.
Hello everyone and welcome to Octa Thorpe, the podcast for Science Fiction and Science
Fiction fandom, which is coming to you on the 26th of May 2022. I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
And we have some letters of comments. Firstly, we got an email from Phil Dyson, the chair of
Eastcon, the previous Eastcon Reclamation 2022 and he writes with his official chair of Eastcon hat,
he tells us, "Stricky Bacon is the worth of Satan. Proper Bacon consists of unsmoked
backrashes grilled not fried, said rashes must come from a good butcher all other attempts
of bacon are unworthy of the name. That is all."
He doesn't like American bacon though, obviously.
He does not specify whether or not he likes American bacon and therefore we cannot.
Well, he clearly doesn't like American bacon because what he's talked about is backbacon
and all other bacon being an abomination and that includes American bacon, which does not
include any backbacon at all because it's all you cannot sell something as bacon in the United
States unless it comes from the pork belly.
Ah, in that case maybe.
So, only streaky bacon.
Well, I mean, Phil sent us a follow up email which says, "Alice in is wrong."
Yeah, I'm feeling very picked upon. I feel like we've got
Liz doesn't want any podcasts, not since Alison is very be wrong.
And John is sitting there with waffles.
No, waffles was yesterday. It's pancakes today.
Okay. John is sitting there with pancakes.
John always has pancakes.
Yes.
And I suspect you just need to set up a better pancake delivery service.
Because John has one. It's called a spania.
But do they have bacon with them?
No, because pancakes should be sweet, not savory.
Octa thought the podcast of arguing about food a whole lot.
Yes, that is true.
Yeah, pretty much.
Chris Garcia has officially given Liz permission to say yawl.
Thank you, Chris.
As a Texican.
Do you think she needs that?
I did say I wasn't sure about saying yawl.
The modus sounds weird when I say it.
But I have got official permission now, so we're good.
Chris says that Alison is right about bacon.
Yeah, but he says that John is also correct that American bacon is better than all bacon,
which is clearly wrong.
So, you know, I'm right about bacon.
John is right about bacon, but Chris is wrong about bacon.
So, you know, he says he will support our Patreon where we talk,
where we talk nonsense about American food.
So that's quite useful. That's one person.
He says he's going to see us at Chai-Kon and he's got his hotel and his flight,
but he doesn't have his membership.
And he talks about the amount of gigantic spiders in the hotel.
So that is interesting.
I don't remember gigantic spiders in Chai-Kon 7,
but maybe I was just like having too much fun partying.
I don't know.
We face as the gigantic spiders are outside the hotel.
So maybe they're just for some reason gathering outside Chris's room.
Chris, what were you doing?
Also, Chris, will you take us for gluten-free pancakes?
Yeah, he writes in to say he's got his locations out for where he's going to be having
this gluten-free pancake breakfast near the hotel, but then unaccountably fails to tell us
the name of the restaurant.
So Chris, write in and let us know.
We will keep it under our hats if you're worried about it being full of fans.
And also he fails to tell us at what time he's booked the table for the five of us to go and
have breakfast.
Sorry, seven of us.
Seven of us to go and have breakfast.
So Chris, get a reservation in please.
Let us know.
Usual channels.
Good man.
Mark Plummer wrote to us and he said how much he loves getting distracted and talking about
video games, but only almost as much as he loves hearing you, especially John,
talk for 15 minutes about Arkham Horror.
And now he listens to Octa Thorpe on headphones whilst in his office and says,
Octa Thorpe, the perfect accompaniment to tedium.
Yes, and I feel very strongly that this is right.
This is what podcasts are for.
It's when you're at work and you've got your headphones on and you're like,
ugh, you know the podcast and then make it better.
So hoorah for Mark.
On the subject of video games, I've been playing Horizon for Bidden West and it's quite good.
I'm now a bit shortly after where I went down a hill.
Are you going back up a hill again?
No, do you have to go back up a hill?
Whoa.
I don't know.
I've played this game.
I have played the little chess substitute thingy which I quite liked and I beat a nice woman who
taught me the rules and that was good.
And there's a man and I don't like him.
But there's another man who's all right, so hoorah, bounce out.
I played one game of the chess substitute and then decided I am not playing Horizon
Bidden West in order to play a chess substitute.
I am here to shoot machines and stopped.
Top tip jump.
Mark also says, love the chapter art and it would be nice if more of you said that.
Just saying.
Please like us.
It's also possible the most visible place for our artwork is not like buried in the chapter
art of the podcast because I don't know about you guys but I don't look at the chapter art
on podcasts.
Sorry.
Oh, it's kind of the episode art, isn't it, rather the chapter art.
It's um and it does appear on when we distribute the Fazid people and it will appear at some
point we're going to put a fancy with all the artids so you know it's getting out there.
But when it's kind of when people talk about the podcast on things like um
file 770 and E-Fazids they do put our chapter art.
They put our episode art up with it.
Mark also says that despite the fact that he would have expected it to come
embedded behavior he found it very interesting how easy it was to forget to remask
when you were moving between environments at Easter Com.
So like the thing he says was you know he'd come out of an environment where he didn't need to
be master would be struggling on a corridor master and seemingly not really registering all
the masked people who are walking past him and probably thinking he was some sort of COVID
denying rebel.
And yeah no I know what you mean Mark.
I did definitely have similar things so it is a good point and well made.
He also says that he quite likes the film of mortal engines which I haven't seen but I think
Haslam and Will Miranda in it.
Am I thinking of the right one?
I don't think you are.
I'd like to say that I do not think of Mark Plummer as a rebel so they go Mark.
You're okay.
Oh I think of him he's absolutely a rebel.
I don't think he's a COVID denying rebel but rebel yes.
I've done a control F for Lin-Manuel Miranda on the mortal engines film page and it doesn't come up
so I think you have invented that entirely in your head John.
Boo!
"Venturing things in Talya was said the best way."
Are you just putting Lin-Manuel Miranda into every film?
Is this your thing now?
No I think I was looking at Lin-Manuel's filmography I think I was thinking of Mary Poppins
because they both start with M.
I was wondering if you were thinking of Mary Poppins and I didn't want to say
righto.
Because I don't think they've got that much in common except obviously they both set in
a steampunk London.
One of which moves.
We also have a little look from somebody who's volunteered to help me with a secret project
with Bradley Harris who says "I've listened to some of your opt thought podcast and I love the way
you British people sadly didn't say that I'm paraphrasing" and I agree with John that Detroit
pizza is very good.
I have food recommendations for Chicago so you can look forward to them.
Look up Jiborito and I have now looked up Jiborito and I am very excited because that is
right in my wheelhouse.
I am generally very up for any food that is kind of from Spanish speaking countries I guess.
Like I've never had a papusa I didn't like and I've been thinking about it and I think I do
actually think that this might be nice so I'm looking forward to trying it out.
They link to Flanderkeso and assuming that that is similar to Flanderkeso you get in Spain I am
really well up for that.
That's just quiche right?
No.
I mean but it isn't just quiche because it's sweet it's much more like cheesecake.
Oh okay.
So I guess it's like quiche in the same way that a cheesecake is like quiche.
Okay that's good though.
It's in the family you know deep dish pizza, quiche, flanderkeso all of these foods have
similarities but have different contexts.
Basically what you're saying is that if you have a suitable combination of cheese and carbs
everything is good.
I am saying that.
You're not wrong.
[Music]
So I've had an interesting experience which I've described in the show notes as I've seen
Hugo VertiPackits from both sides down which is the last year I coordinated the Hugo VertiPackit
and had to collect and everything for everyone.
This year I've submitted a thing to the Hugo VertiPackit with the help of Joel and Liz.
So it turns out that when we got an email saying "oh congratulations guys you're a Hugo finalist"
what we should have done is that of squeaking for an hour and texting Liz 47 times
was immediately start working on a Hugo VertiPackits submission.
Because what we actually did was a couple of days before the VertiPackit deadline go
"oh it's a bit time to get about time we got this together isn't it?"
Yeah I had a really torrid three days.
Thank you for the extension Cassidy.
We didn't look at it as kind of a few days before.
The problem is that we looked at it sort of seven to ten days before and that was not enough time.
Yeah that's right.
We should have, we basically there were things we could have done earlier that might have been better.
I think that's fair to say.
So what went wrong is that we decided we'd better have some transcripts.
We've been kind of not having transcripts for two years and it's probably time we started
having transcripts and so we have put four episodes into the Hugo VertiPackit and we have put some
transcripts for those episodes in and you will be able to download them if you're a
check on member when the Hugo VertiPackit comes out but we'll also release it we'll put it somewhere.
I suggest we'll probably put it on efanseed's so you can go get it there and of course you'd get
the actual podcast from the podcast site.
Transcripts are hard, who knew?
Yeah it turns out even with the help of you know an automated transcription service
it gets sufficient stuff either completely wrong or slightly wrong that it still takes a very
long time to turn the rough text into an actual transcript.
Hmm yeah and they can mostly tell the difference between me talking, John talking and Alice
in talking but not always.
They're very bad in particular at the times when one of us says something and then the other one
says oh no or really or pancakes or something and then and then the first person goes on so all
of those had to be fished out and made into separate paragraphs.
Oh no really pancakes.
Like that.
It'd be much better if the podcast was actually just a series of monologues and not a conversation
so we should consider that for easy transcription.
It turns out that the podcast is quite often a series of monologues as well.
Do you want to expand on that point Alison?
I was looking at the transcripts for some other conversational podcasts and it appears that
those podcasts might not have somebody go off or one and talk solidly for five minutes in the way
that ours does from time to time.
This is only if you look at the front of the thing we've put into the Hugo Verte packet
it just kind of says octa-thorp Hugo Verte packet submission but if you look at the back
into the colophon the colophon is something that old-time fanzine fans
printing their fanzines to tell you who's done it and when and why
so that you can find us information out later.
It describes the document as an immutable artifact which it is but meanwhile in the
interim jollers worked out that we are mutable after all.
Yeah because mutable being a word which clearly means something you can mute.
You can mute octa-thorp try it now lower your volume to zero I go away I come back
what crazy magic.
Ah it's yes we are mutable but the transcript is not no volume
and and it's immutable and will never change that might be a joke.
True unless we upload a new PDF which we're going to and it's also an e-pub so you can now
read octa-thorp on your e-reading device.
I'm not sure why you want to do that really.
I mean I really like reading e-books or by e-reading device and even I am not doing that so
please write in if you decide to.
Alison did occlude something which is early statistics suggest that Alison talks roughly half the time
on octa-thorp although it does change from episode to episode but it is quite interesting to see
the the divisions it will not shock long-term listeners to find that Liz talks usually the
least of the three of us because she only says things when she's got things to say.
Yeah I mean this is partly because I like to you know reserve my participation for making
short pithy and funny statements ideally but it's also because I shirk my duties of introducing
any of the letters of comment and leave that off the chat.
Oh I mean that is oh no hang on this is a life hack gosh darn it.
And also I am also prone to monologuing it's just that I tend to find my monologues less
interesting than other monologues and cut them out preferentially.
Yeah I think I did I transcribe your uh android netrunner monologue that was uh I don't know.
Oh it's quite the monologue.
It might be a villain origin story.
The other thing about our immutable artifact is that we started doing the transcripts and Liz
started on we agreed which episodes were going to go into the Hugo VertiPacket and Liz started
transcribing episode 26 and she wrote several times about how she was transcribing episode 26 so
I finished episode 26 and then when I'd finished all of the episodes I went to check that we'd got
the episodes in the drop box for the Hugo people and observed that episode 26 was not one of the ones
that we put into the Hugo VertiPacket and I had one of those ghastly sinking feelings that you get
when you go oh oh no so we've actually transcribed five episodes so far and we have in fact transcribed
six episodes so far because we've also done episode 57 which will really release
at or around the same time as we do this we have to work out where we're going to put the transcripts
of things like that.
Sorry about my brain fart but in my defense I did mention the title of it several times
and I've been noticed.
Disc on three have translated their souvenir book into Chinese which I remembered
while we were recording this and I thought it was quite cool I mean I don't really have
any idea to say on it beyond I think it's quite cool so you know I just thought I'd drop that in there.
I hope that means that the Chinese supporting members of Disc on will get it and read it and
find it interesting. Yeah I feel like they might get to the WILK on long list and go
this is not what I got into satisfaction to read but you know.
I mean I think it's interesting because like so Disc on have kind of retrospectively translated
their souvenir book as far as I can see I don't think I kind of translated anything including things
like the Hugo nomination form and so on in 20 other languages which is interesting because
should we be routinely providing them in the languages you know of the hosts of the WILKons who can vote.
Disc on ended up with quite a commitment to getting like auto translations of their events
into Chinese and things like that so this is something Disc on to take quite seriously.
I just thought it was really interesting that they'd done the souvenir book I think that's really cool.
My guess is that if you deal with a set of auto transcripts or auto translation and then have to
turn it into real translation that's probably not that dissimilar to transcription. It's the same
sort of it's the same sort of unpleasant finicety task.
I have a suspicion that my sister who is a translator would would disagree with you
extremely strongly because you don't have any of the nuance of the language if you convert it.
You'd have to be better off because idioms don't translate. It's not like in a transcription where
the idioms would yeah I have a suspicion that it might not be right. I don't know if you are a
translator right in. Yeah I mean I do think that spoken language is very different from written
language and the reason that I find transcripts so hard is that I want the written transcript to
make sense and it the transcription of the Batum speech doesn't always make sense so that's not
that dissimilar. Oh no really pancakes. I would also say that if you're going for like auto
transcription then you know Chinese is one of the harder languages I think to do the auto
transcription into so. Auto translation but yeah. So I had a translation yet so I suspect it
happened on that. I mean it's also worth noting that you know Chengdu already have a
translation services division and division head so I'm sure they're already thinking about
what they're going to need which is a lot of translation. I have not been looking at Chengdu's
organizational chart but that sounds like an extremely interesting thing to look at.
Did you not see that they released his turn Estercon? No because I spent Estercon absolutely flat out
over over committing myself so I mean I've learnt a number of valuable lessons from Estercon.
I will say listeners and Liz if anything happened during Estercon please tell me what it was and
you know right in because I was not paying attention to much. Now this is really good thank you for
the link Liz there's a very interesting picture. I'll put a link in the show notes listeners.
Tchaikon launched their portal for expressing interest in being on programme
a while back and the deadline was in the last few weeks and all three of us applied to fill in the
programme questionnaire and then all three of us filled in the programme questionnaire and then
I think some of us have heard back although I'm not sure whether all three of us have.
I think all three of us are confirmed on the on the list of programme participants on the
Tchaikon website so we will all three be programme participants but we don't know what
programme items we'll get yet. I was down as a programme participant virtually so I've
emailed them and let them know I'm going so I don't know what that's going to do to which programme
items I was put on or not because it might mean that all of the ones they thought oh he could be
on that one they're like oh no that's a virtual one and vice versa no idea sorry programme team
of Tchaikon 8 that must be very annoying. Do we know anyone on the programme team?
I don't think so. Liz is shaking her fist. I'm not I'm not a signing panelist so that's okay.
And the way that Tchaikon's programme participation worked was that in the expression of interest
you gave like a little bit about yourself and then when you filled in the actual programme you
the actual questionnaire you got like a list of all of the things that they were planning to do
and you could choose ones that you were interested in doing. The way it worked is that you could choose
five that you rated a one and one is like I really really really really want to be on this
panel and I think I'd be great. You could choose five panels which you rated a two where two was
kind of I have relevant expertise to this panel and I wouldn't mind not being on it but equally I
think I'd be good on it and then you could choose as many as you'd like to put three which is basically
yeah I could do that and you could like filter the programme down by various categories. I found
the filtering slightly annoying because you couldn't filter for instance to programme item type so
you couldn't filter between workshops and panels when I looked at it and I was like I don't think
I want to volunteer to do a workshop so I would quite like just to select panels but I don't think
that was an option but you could do it between kind of different areas of the programme so I
looked mostly at areas that I was interested in obviously and so I've signed up for a couple on
fanning podcasting because I am a fancaster and I have signed up for a couple of things like
Star Wars and other things that I'm very interested in as a fan so yeah we'll see what happens.
I can say I'm not sure if there were workshops in there to sign up for I think like it was mostly
things where there would be other people on there as well. I can't remember what I signed up for
some of the same panels as John sorry John I'm going to fight your forum so I put some fan casting
panels some con running panels some science panels. I did like how the system was like you could put
things as number one but you can only have like a certain number as number one because I think
that does sidestep people saying here are the 27 panels I would be enormously great on
you have to actually select and you also have to explain why you would be great on them which
is good because if you can't plausibly write a sentence saying why you would be great on it
you probably not great on it. Yeah I didn't answer fair. It is quite a
effort though. In the list of things I hugely disagree with that's one of them but I feel I have
a problem with this entire system which is it is going to make it harder for people who struggle
with big forms of whom we have quite a lot in tandem to get themselves onto programming and it
is it preferentially suits people who are who are quite methodical and systematic about the way
they do these sorts of things so I feel like there is a considerable risk that the people who have
carefully assigned themselves to 75 panels will get more programming than people who are
absolutely fantastic but can't be asked with forms like this and I think I don't think the
system is wrong but I think it probably has to be combined with a certain amount of oh we know that
X is great at Y but they have to be persuaded to do Y or it won't happen they're never going to fill
in a 200 page form. Over on the Hugo finalists discord somebody said well I have a Hugo finalist
who I've been helping to complete that form but they could not possibly have completed it without
some support from another person and there is an access issue to forms that require people to
write a lot of stuff about themselves for people who have trouble writing which this person does
or for people who have trouble with forms so there's this basically there's a problem with the
people who are too busy and can't be asked but nevertheless a good one program and there's a
problem with people with the access issues so there's kind of both of those are in the category of
problems with the system I have another set of rants though which I'm happy to do later
I could do as many rants or this as you like. I think the thing isn't you don't you so you're
looking at this system in isolation and you're not comparing it to the previous system and so
this system does have a couple of things that are bad about it which you're very neatly elucidated.
I think in terms of people who have trouble filling in big forms the previous system also has big
forms so I am not wholly convinced that this system is worse than that but I do think it's
something we do need to think about and especially from the access perspective when you said about
people we know would be good I think one of the massive strengths of this system
I think it's very easy for program to reflect the people that the program team know and I think this
system does an enormous amount to remove that and to broaden the pool of people out and so I do
think and if you know there's someone coming who hasn't filled in like I don't know if Chris Evans
is attending and there's a Captain America panel and he hasn't filled in the form you might gently
know Jim would be like Chris beyond the Captain America our panel please but I do think one of the
things this model is clearly trying to achieve is making it easier for the program team to tell
who would be good on panels that they might not be aware of you know I have big support for all of
that so I mean I am quite supportive of the aims of some of this stuff yeah I think I am
you know more persuaded by one of your points than others you know I think the access issue is a big
one and I don't know whether it needs to be in bigger letters look if this form is a problem for
you if you cannot you know easily fill in this form you know if there are no you know getting
in touch with those because I'm pretty sure they would have said okay someone will like work through
it with you or we'll you know we can send you the panels in a different format they might be easier
for you to read for instance if like there's a problem with signing up from on the website and
you could do them that way so I'm a bit more sympathetic to that one than to the people who are too busy
to fill in big forms because then again it becomes like okay so this person is too busy to fill in
the forms but we know they're good and they should be on program as opposed to this person is maybe
two busy fill in forms but we don't know their names so we wouldn't use them for program even though
they're great no no I think you're preferentially selecting against bestsellers and people whose
books people actually read in favor of wannabes and I think that is not a sensible thing to do
I mean I think it's fine to say oh yes we want to broaden the range of people on the thing and have
participation from more groups and particularly from underrepresented groups and people who we
might not know about but I think saying oh we've got somebody who's consistently on New York Times
bestseller list but we're not going to put them on program because they can't be faffed with that
form is just stupid for the Worldcon I think it's stupid and can you tell us which authors you
have seen that have been in that category um it's good question because I suspect this is wild
supposition there might be and it may be that it's true but I think that Worldcon is a big enough
deal to most of the authors in our genre that most of the authors in our genre do do this and the
ones who don't are the ones who aren't bothering to come to Worldcon and are going to drag and con
instead it's possible yeah and you could say that there are probably a small number yeah I would
say there are probably a small number of incredibly high profile people who you would like then assist
because but in a way it feels like the ones who come to your convention when they could otherwise
probably be doing like you know personal appearances and signatures for thousands of dollars that
weekend maybe we do put a bit more effort into making sure they get some some panels without
having to put too much effort in but the other thing is that those people also tend to have
a person who works for them who can fill in forms for them oh that's true indeed
Chai Conum Chai Con is on Dragon Con weekend isn't it it certainly could be I know Chai Con 7
was because they had interlinked programming it is indeed Dragon Con is at the same time as Worldcon
this year and Worldcon speak kind of avoiding Dragon Con well it's interesting because
because like I say like because I think I don't know the extent to which that was true
like a decade ago because obviously I was new and shiny then because Chai Con 7 was my second
Worldcon I know that Chai Con 7 had like video had like hybrid content where there were program items
that were shared between the two conventions which was like I have no idea how well that worked
but I remember thinking it was interesting I don't have a good feel for what the Venn diagram
between the two conventions is like in terms of potential attendees like because obviously the
state is massive so I don't I don't know to what extent you hurt your attendance by going up against
Dragon Con whereas like if there were two big cons in the UK you might be a bit more wary because
the the potential pool might be lower I don't know as an example Metropole Con which is the Berlin
Con next year has just is just in the process of moving because a large literary festival has
launched on the same weekend as them and they're like oh no we can't do that interesting interesting
the problem with Dragon Con is not splitting the membership it's splitting the authors
hmm knowing that is fair it's that and it's the guests of all kinds professionals in the
science fiction and fantasy field feel they have to go to Dragon Con because it is it is now a
bigger deal for them than Worldcon also if you're a sad puppy you go to Dragon Con right that's
my understanding because they're less angry with them I assume so but I don't know and then when
Scolzy got nominated for a Dragon Award everyone was like what are these Hugo Award winners doing
in our Dragon Awards it was very much like the Fan Awards but for Dragon Con instead of for Corfloo
is my impression I mean the Dragon Awards are you know they're kind of like I think they very
much like to over time be more prestigious than the Hugos I'm not sure that's likely to happen
because I think awards have a huge first move of advantage and that's why the Hugo's a sad
procedure yep do you want to do your second rant yeah no my second rant is that I didn't think
very much of the panel choices and I think that might be because the the program team didn't
doesn't necessarily reflect all of the different parts of Worldcon programming you might want at
the point where they put the panel choices together and some of the people on the program team were
proactive about getting panel ideas in there but that meant that for me it felt quite unbalanced
and there were also panels that were very much like each other and for example there were like
14 podcasting panels and despite the fact that I am I am a fancaster I feel like having 14
podcasting panels and almost no panels about the actual things that fans do in terms of writing
and art and I don't think I think there might be like one fan art item and there aren't very
many art items altogether and I felt that there was a clearly clearly I'd not enough thought
had been given a sorry list yet to the balance of things that were on that on that thing so a
lot of things that I'm interested in in fandom you know that just wasn't very much on the on the
program about it there wasn't a lot about creating social spaces which is something that I think
is incredibly interesting and I ask about every single time and it wasn't there and there wasn't
very much about there's some stuff about quite a lot of stuff about making money but not very
much about kind of turning your fan hobby into into business and things like that so yeah it was
just lots of different you know I felt my personal interests were not very well represented on the
on the program and it wasn't because they were too busy with all the fantastic science serious
science fiction and fantasy content or science content it was because there were a vast number
of panels that were very like each other on what I thought were quite narrow areas there were I
don't think there were 14 podcast panels to that why we just like is our duration I think there might
be more like six or seven and I do think in general podcasting because because casting like takes
under its umbrella podcasting in the fashion we do it which is currently undergoing a huge
explosion in popularity especially with companies like Spotify getting into the space
but it also encompasses stuff like TikTok and YouTube both of which are hugely popular
and so I suspect that fan casting is by far the most common expression of fanak currently in our
genre and so I do think if you're gonna wait your program to what people are doing and experiencing
that probably makes sense for most people but I might be wrong I do I don't know I didn't think
the panels like there were lots of panels I was like oh you know I wouldn't be good on that but
I'm not sure I thought that there were lots of very similar panels but I don't know Liz what do you
reckon yeah so I think before we start this we say I am on the Shikon program team although I think
I only had input into like a handful of actual panels on there I'm not actually working for any
particular area yeah I thought it was quite nice actually because I think in a way it feels like
we've had very few panels on podcasting I think we've had like how to start your first
fanning podcast and a lot of maybe technical things and it felt it was digging into the area
in a way that you can if you have 10 items that you can't if you have two items and the rest
it felt quite balanced to me but maybe that's just because it has more things you know about my
particular niche interests and it does about Alison's particular niche interests I would
also say there was a big form where you could suggest items so I don't know if you did suggest
items and they've not taken into account or whether you did you know you didn't suggest it yeah I
mean it is possible that I did not do enough work at the earlier point but I kind of thought that with
Jo and Edie as guests of honor of the convention there would have been
significantly more about well there's loads of fanak history no there's there's a very
small there's a load of stuff about 1946 which isn't really fan history in the sense that fans
today would think about it because it's 80 years ago but it's exactly the sort of thing that Jo
and Edie would be really good at talking about um they probably will be good about well they
might be here but I mean they do a lot of other stuff as well and I didn't think that was
there was as much as I would have liked to have seen I think it's worth being aware that the
things you can sign up for are just items you can sign up for and obviously there will be other
items on the program which have already been you know designed with people in mind and I bet
there are quite a few of those for the guests of honor and so on um that that may not be there
for open sign up and so you can't judge the entire program just by the things that you personally
can sign up to be on oh that's quite useful to know actually yeah that makes sense
I'm just assuming this but just because I don't see things like guest of honor you like the guest
of honor interviews are not in there so if they have things specifically like the guest of honor
said you know I would like to do a conversation with this particular interesting person it's
probably not there so you don't waste your time signing up for it I think I just kind of have
an idea of a sort of panelist I think is very good which is that you take a chunk of
you take some topic in the field and then you take people who come at that topic in the field
from different perspectives and you get a lot of paddle together and and those topics are quite
broad so a lot of people could sign up for it but there were very few panels on the thing that
felt like that they felt much more narrow in general and focused in general oh I mean so this
and this comes back really neatly to an argument we've had about Easticon program where you're like
we need more better program items and but the thing is that what you regard as better program items
what you just said sounds bad to me I'd much rather have focused items that actually delve
into something in enough detail to be interesting rather than just a plethora of super vague items
where I'm like could be about anything probably not going to go and so I do think that is and I
can entirely understand why someone would disagree with me don't get me wrong like I am in Thailand
and this is a subjective thing for me but I much more prefer that kind of program to a very kind of
sort of high level not really delving into any crunch program and it goes back to what Liz was
saying about the podcast panels which is that I think she's right that having more panels on the
subject lets you get into that subject better than having a couple of very high level program items
does and that resonated with me as well so so I think yeah I think this is a perhaps a subjective
thing I will feel a lot more convinced about this the first time I go to a podcasting item no
matter how deep that does not contain a discussion of which microphone you should buy so so what I
feel is they say they'll delve in but every podcasting item is podcasting 101 and this is why when I
suggested items to the east con just gone a couple of the items I was like and I would like to moderate
that because if I had not moderated them I think they would have gone into very very
points and I did not want them to I wanted them to be specific discussions about specific things
that are interesting and this is something that Esther and Emily were on a panel with me about
board games and they both read the thing and went oh that's going to end up being tabletop gaming 101
and I was like it is absolutely not going to end up like that it's going to be a discussion of the
modern canon it's going to be a discussion of like the modern kind of historical context of the hobby
and that is the discussion we actually had and I think it was really good but I think I think the
flip side of that is you've got to have moderators who are willing and able to read the panel description
and deliver that panel I went to a panel at Dublin which was a really interesting sounding
panel about animation but there had not been there had been some glitch in the program set up for
that panel where it was not clear to the panel who the moderator was so I'm all stepped in and
basically moderated a very vague panel which was entirely dis satisfactory to me rather than the
interesting panel I had read about in the description and I thought that was a great shame because
the panel as described was fascinating and a panel which is what is genre what is animation is just
like no I've heard this before I'm leaving I agree with you however I agree with this I agree that
the moderator has a job to do which is to deliver the thing on the sheet though obviously you have
some scope for digressions like the one we're currently having when they get into an interesting
gritty topic but I also feel that in general if I am creating a program item for a room of size
x I would like to think that it's going to appeal to approximately point x eight of x people at the
convention and the problem with some of these quite crunchy panels like the excellent one on
on gaming over zoom that you moderated at least con that I really enjoyed being on
is it attracted to an audience about 10 people and really you could just do those in the bar
or this question about is it worth really digging in deep into topics to get to get a
panel really only a very few people will be interested in but they will have a final time
if alison has a full proof algorithm for working at how big x is prior to the convention you know
if you can predict the number of people who will come for a panel within like two or three times
the number of people who actually end up at that panel no not at all absolutely not no chance
that's the problem because you can say oh I think this might only appeal to 12 people and I'll put
it in a small room and then you end up with 50 or you say oh this will appear to loads of people
and then there's 10 people in it so we can do better than we typically do though because we don't do a
very good job of collecting the data at conventions to then inform future conventions for example
we felt octothor filled its room at easter con and I don't suppose anyone was expecting that
including us lots of program items that he's to go to not fill their rooms this is something that
I would have thought would be useful for future convention committees to know about live podcasts
in general I don't think it is unique to us I think podcasts have audiences and we know from
folk clubs that if you if things have existing audiences and you program them people will come
to them we filled our room at easter con but we were like what maybe a third full at no over con so
even if you take those two data points I don't know which way you extrapolate from those two I
just say we filled a room at you know like the item just before the closing ceremony when there
wasn't very much on if you would put us on you know maybe at 2 p.m. on the Saturday I don't think
we would have filled the room so again it's like a very complex arrangement of things I probably
would be better if we had better notes of how many people there were in rooms but we need an
organized way to do that because the basically the volunteers are too stretch kicking people out
of rooms at the right time to count how many people are in there no I think you require the
moderator to report back yeah and most of them would Alison is entirely right because I do think
one of the things we're very weak at in con running generally is analytics I like you have
arguments about so many different things where people are like I assert X and someone else is
like I assert Y and you're like is there any data to give us any perspective on which of these
assertions is more valid and there is none because we don't we don't collect that data and part of
that is because it's difficult it's difficult to collect data and that's why like market research
firms are phenomenally expensive and well out of the reach of like anyone running a convention or
maybe not a WorldCon but definitely like at an East con level it's difficult because most of the
data capture would be being done by volunteers and I think you're right that most
moderators would report back but like there is a weak link there but it's also difficult in
that most of the analyzing the data would need to take place quite soon post con and we know that
people tend to be very burnt out post con and I think the longer you leave it the more risk you
have of not realizing you need some number that you haven't collected and then being like oh no
and I've had this experience from public engagement data analysis where you do your analysis sort of
a year after you wrapped up the engagement and then you're like oh it would really have been helpful
if I had thought of taking that number at the time so I do I do think this is a weakness in
fandom but I understand why it's a weakness in fandom and I don't have any useful suggestions
for things we could do about it well you need a specific team to take charge of it and know
that they're going to do most of their stuff after the convention so preferably a different set of
people are not working pre con I think would be the way to do it the more data you gather during
the convention the better if you gather the raw data during the convention and then store it somewhere
it's it's there when people want it um it can be really simple things like the number of points
of beer we sold today nobody ever wants to do this after the convention they want to do it
during the convention well I think Liz might be right having like a specific team of people that
don't have any pre con responsibility and just work post con might be a good way of kind of
sidestepping the burnout problem a little bit and and and maybe this is something like we should
be you know looking at doing I don't know maybe this is a thing that people could think about
our con-running knowledge base which is the thing that requires people to work post con is way out
of date and I've had some things about what we can do about improving that and indeed it is to
find people who want to do the work and want to do it off to the call and make it their only job
but it's it's so far down the list of projects I want to get into that I haven't really done
anything else with it but if anyone listening with this and thinks oh gathering this information
would be a really interesting project they should get in touch I would like to volunteer whoever
chairs the 2025 e-stick on come and talk to me after 2024s over because this might be something
I'd be quite interested in getting involved but I'm not going to do anything before it's 2024 so
so I feel like a bigger problem is getting a team together to bid 25 oh yeah I mean I'm definitely
not volunteering to take a leadership role in that and I wanted to just say have right Liz is about
room size estimates being a dark art because that clearly even if we got fantastic data forever
it would still be impossible and I do accept that I mean there is the the alternate approach
to room size which is to just have a convention where every room isn't I for because you've got
too many people very simple we will call that the loncon model our loncon model Helsinki model
I was about to call it the anti-covid model but then it might actually be pro-covid in all the
wrong ways so uh I think we should be getting better at this now it happened because we started
publishing programs in advance of the convention and it turns out that if you program publish your
program in advance of a convention people read it and identify things they'd like to go and see
and go and see them and the uptake of program is vastly higher than it traditionally wasn't at
UK convention certainly where traditionally the program was something that very many people
ignored was in the bar and it is much less so now people go to program items in larger numbers
because the program is more public oh no I don't know if it's because the program is more public I
think it's whole different conversation about the fact that people tend to go to more program now
possibly more program when they've only been to a few Wilcons so but we might be drifting too far
off the topic of program like software model um well thank you very much for this discussion
since I have volunteered for at least one item at Chicon about convention programming
and so we'll see if I get on that and then can recurgeitate all your opinions as my own thank you
no worries if you need um any panelists for program items listening if you need us to do your
homework for you write in with the name of the panel you need to pre-chat for and we'll give it a
good go preferably things we know about but we're not proud when you was like I assert this and I
assert that but there's no data and I'm kind of like well it's probably good thing there's no
data because we had data we wouldn't have a podcast would we no I was also thinking about that but
no I was thinking about like in terms of modeling it is so difficult to model stuff like this even
when you have good data like there's there's like the whole field of machine learning where you're
basically just trying to predict stuff like this like using enormous amounts of data so trying to
do it with literally no data is phenomenally difficult so if you're a convention out there and you're
trying to do a machine learning model where you put all the audiences for panels into your machine
learning model and then generate panel names that will get a lot of people to go along to them um
do let us know because I know that somebody's done the first part of that where they put all the
panel names in and identify a node of new panels like things like cake in science fiction discuss
so the way that you do machine learning clarification is you like give everything a tag and then you
develop an algorithm that can basically spit out like what tags are associated with what trends
and so that would let you say like if I have ex guest of honor who I've got data from previous
conventions and if I've got ex subject matter so say fan casting or fan art or science can I then
predict like what the likely what the likely attendance of a science panel with this guest of
honor on it is for instance and that that starts getting you into kind of interesting things but
it also means you can be valuable judgments about how many fan art panels do we have will that capture
enough of a audience Liz are you going to tell us do pics no I was actually going to digress even
further hey excellent have you seen a video from a youtube channel defunct land about fast pass
the disney system essentially for trying to minimize people's wait time in line for rides because in
order to do that extremely lengthy video they basically set up a model of a theme park you know
in which they could give the guests different behaviors and you know model all the attractions
and the activities you could do and then have this sort of each person is therefore like a different
model of behavior and what they like to do you know do they want to go on as many rides as possible
with minimal waiting or do they really want to do the three rides they want to do and they don't
mind waiting and basically set up as a model of an entire theme park so maybe we need that look
for a convention and it's probably something it's on get we can nick it oh yes excellent no i'm
i'm suddenly very excited about this yeah no we're crowdsourcing this guys because we're not going
to do it at least not till 2025 i mean to be fair genuinely if i was not on an easter
con committee this would be my next project but i am i know i'm gonna have to say no because um
oh that sounds fascinating it's quite good yeah sounds good but that's the other thing on the
trycon on the trycon program and i'm not just trycon like i've not seen any discussions about
how to try to improve conventions using data like i don't think that's a conversation anyone's
having and i think did you suggest it john i did not because i only just thought about
alison but i will suggest it can you suggest it to 2023 please for the easter con thank you
picks so um who wants to go now alison and i you're having a fight and i'm staying out of it
we both want to pick the same movie we had a we had a we i was like i i did cause dips on this first
and john was like i saw it first and then john was like well i've been doing hugo reading so what i
am showing the camera is i'm showing the camera a paper cut in between my thumb and my forefinger
which i believe means i can transition to the multiverse in which i win this argument oh
whereas i'm like going this is a film about a harried middle aged businesswoman with
who is distractible and overworked with a with um a dependent and irascible parent and
aimless but bright lesbian daughter and um and uh extremely devoted and kind but perhaps
slightly dull husband and i felt seen not as much as your family do now
but my family have all heard this joke at least once already actually might have mentioned
uh so for the listeners who haven't worked out we're talking about everything everywhere all at
once which is great i quite liked it i thought it was really good i like representation of movies
and there aren't enough movies about middle aged women who are michelle yo that's true i mean not
even tomorrow never dies because she's quite young in that yeah and she's she's older than i am and
she is vastly more flexible than i am i think it's safe to say
more flexible than any of us i think it's safe to say i think and i'm the subject of representation
this is actually something i said to i would see it with uh friends of the podcast Neil and Nick
i said afterwards i thought one of the things i really liked about the movie was that waymund
really neatly encapsulates my basic like perspective on life and i very much liked that because
it's not often you see that perspective presented in movies but it's really not
often you see that perspective presented as not the easy choice and then there's a real
i really liked having someone say like it's good to be positive and happy all the time but it's not
easy and i i very much resonated with that i like that an enormous amount in terms of representation
but i suspect you felt more seen than i e allison i did there's also there's also some of the topics
of the movie about i don't think this is spoiling too much one of the big themes of the movie is
whether you could make different life choices and and experience better or a different life as a
result of them and also whether anything has any purpose whatsoever and i am a stage in my life
well obviously i do grapple with that sort of thing i think that i think this comes and goes
throughout one's whole life i don't think it's just that i think evilin is is meant to feel like a
very relatable character for a lot of people i don't think it is just people like me well and is as
as john says an amazing character as well and i thought he was fantastic which is probably quite
good for my marriage because i do have a somebody who evokes many of wahman's ways of living as a
husband which is good and i really liked all of that and i don't want to spoil the movie too much
but i did i'm going to tell you another funny story which is that i wasn't spoiled for this
movie going in at all really so all i knew about it was that it was a movie where
michelle yoh has adventures in the multiverse and saves the world and so i basically said a
text to john saying i'm really looking forward to a seagull movie where um there's a bat
mid-laged woman that's not all about her relationships with her parents and children and her husband
and john was like spoiler i said spoiler and then in spoiler text i said in fact the movie is entirely
about that and then allison said oh i i would have worth that hour if i thought about it and i like
but i felt really bad because i was like i don't want to harsh your i don't want to harsh your
squee and i don't want to spoil the movie for you and but i really feel well like but i am gonna need
to warn her that maybe it's not pure escapist fun uh in in some aspects yeah there was enough
escapist fun that it didn't it wasn't all it wasn't it wasn't too too dare beat for me it will be your
next year's hugo ballad you heard it here first i mean i did not hear it first this now i heard
it in other places also two other things on the letterboxed page for everything everywhere all at
once the little reviewed icon is a little googly eye that follows your mouse around the page which i
thought was brilliant uh lovely attention to detail googly eyes are sort of a motif of the movie
les i'm going to pick a young adult fantasy geology which is ray bearer and redemptor by
jonnie fueco which are low sound omones from uh 2021 and 2022 and i've read these recently and
really quite enjoyed them i'm struggling to start with where to describe them because there is just
so much in them but essentially the idea of the ray bearer is in this fantasy culture which is
very heavily derived from west african uh cultures i think the ray bearer is kind of the emperor figure
who has the magical power of the ray this allows him to essentially speak psychically to a council
that he picks as a child and once he's kind of bonded them to him with this psychic power
he's also immune to many methods of injury and death and all of his council are linked together
and cannot be apart from each other so that's kind of the premise which is that the the main character
charisai is brought in to be one of the new young emperors council but she's actually been raised
to be an assassin who will who will kill the the young emperor before he ever takes the throne
but it turns out that the actual origin of the ray bearer has been shrouded and hidden and changed
and actually it's a lot more complicated than that and by the end of the first book kind of the
situation in the world has changed substantially the the redemptors are children who are essentially
sacrificed into the underworld in order to placate the demons who live there and a very few of them
basically make it out again and are the redemptors i really only got into kind of like half of the
stuff which is in these books so also i forgot so that all the council have like a special power
called the hallow her power is to kind of read the memories from people and objects and this is an
absolutely crucial part of the story it's basically just two books absolutely crammed with stuff all
around the central character of charisai but i think even though it is crammed with stuff it's
still very well focused on the central character and the kind of journey she goes on and a lot of
questions about where does all the power and privilege come from in this empire who has it
and what can you do when you are given power and can you know choose to radically reshape the world
or not and we know what happens if you try and radically reshape the world but the toll on yourself
is too great and then the toll on the people who love you and the people around you when you take
that on yourself and so yeah i just i really enjoyed both books i think they're kind of in a way
that antidote to our early discussion with allison about books being stretched out over a trilogy
and that i think this possibly could have been a trilogy there was enough stuff in there and it
feels like a lot of things happened from page to page and there's a lot you could go more deeply
into and characters who sort of you know prominent in one book and then fade out in the second maybe
because as even more characters are introduced to take their part in the story there's not enough
room for them but they were just they they felt like an incredibly fallen realized world in a way
that maybe you don't always get no i agree with all the things you just said i liked both books
and enormous amount um i really like so that the idea is that there are 12 ways to die other
than old age and you have 11 members of your council so you're born with one immunity and
then every member you appoint you get another immunity and when you complete your council you are
impervious to to death except for from old age uh which i thought was really cool concept
i very much like the i like it and always thought about things i can't really talk about here
because they're spoilers um but i very much liked uh various parts including a lot of discussion
about how how power manifests and how sometimes it's important to wield that power in different
ways that aren't always through the proper channels i think i think the book especially the
second book has quite a lot to say about kind of protest and about um power structures and how
tying into existing power structures isn't always the way to affect change um and i agree with you
like i i do think that could well have been uh three books um the first book kind of ends at a
point where a lot has happened to change the world and then the second book kind of explored the
ramifications of that which i quite liked um and i i think probably this is my favorite of the two
load star finalists i've read so far i think it probably just about edges uh snakes that felt
at earth although both were fantastic um so yes i'm very much enjoying the load star slate so far
yes i haven't read all the load star um all the load star not many's yet i've only read um the
last graduate and i think i would pick redempt a wave of the last graduate at the moment yeah i
should say it could be it could be a trilogy but i'm quite glad it's not i think i preferred reading
two books that were stuffed full of energy rather than and they felt like there was still enough time
for the characters to to breathe and for all these kind of big questions to be considered um
and yeah it did feel like it was the right length still yeah i i think i agree i like duologies okay
yeah no i quite like duologies um we'll talk about that more when we talk about hugo books i think
and that was the octa thought podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye
from me
you won't see it in my old stomping ground oh yeah and i saw it at a john cox and shrine which was
quite interesting which is the showcase cinema in petebra it's not a shrine it's just a place i
used to work it has lovely seats i did not recline my seat all the way because i'd had quite a
strenuous weekend and we were we were squeezing the movie in by kind of driving down the a1 going
where is the movie showing between here and London that we can get to at the right time which is how
can we ended up in petebra and i was very worried that if i reclined by seat all the way back i would
fall asleep for three hours and that would be a bit of a shame allison did also say that she should
in hindsight have asked me which cinema in petebra to go and see it at and i did point out that this
is a very London centric view of how many cinemas there are in any given city there are more cinemas
in waltland state of the petebra now the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by
kevin mccloud in com peteck.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast
will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]