I was doing that thing where it uses all my CPU and then crashes.
So if that happens, I'll see you in a minute.
Uh oh.
Okay, well we'll see you in a minute.
He just managed to say that before it used all his CPU and then crashed, didn't he?
Yeah, he's frozen.
This does not normally happen, viewers.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 30th episode of OctaThaw, being an installment
of OctaThaw Live.
Pause for ooze.
Ooooh.
There it is.
Oh, you met from us.
Well no one else can talk.
Uh, this episode will be going out on the 29th of April.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
So we have a myriad of letters of comment today.
We have tweets of comment, discords of comment, Facebook messages of comment, emails of comment,
many other forms of comment are available.
Please check your local comment vendor for details.
Chris Garcia writes in to apologise for not locking us last issue.
Yeah, Chris Garcia notes that he's sorry for not locking the last episode, but he was busy
being fired.
Um, which is very sad.
Sorry Chris.
We hope you find employment soon.
Chris also says, congratulations to Hugo nominated, fanzine editor, John the Rock of
England Coxon.
Much deserved and I hope you win.
So I, I suspect that Chris is hoping that I will win is linked to the fact that if I
win Chris will also win.
So I think it might not be an entirely altruistic expression of hoping of winness.
Okay, I know I was told that there was a subject I was not allowed to snuck about on
this podcast, but you were really trying my patience at this point, John.
And then he says, congratulations, Alison on the doc we are, which is much deserved
and that certificate you shared on the social media was phenomenal.
You're awesome.
That's very nice.
Thank you.
And then he says other things.
Hurrah.
And then he signs it yours.
John Coxon.
Wait, no, I meant Chris Garcia.
He's working very hard at it.
I want to read out Mark Plummer of Croydon's Lock in Full because I thought it was very
funny and I will try to read it out without laughing while I do it.
Claire and I were playing Arkham Horror earlier.
Things started getting interesting around the fifth turn.
I rolled a six and advanced my Charles Dexteward figure, the appropriate number of spaces.
Excellent, I thought.
As I rummaged in the papers in front of me, handed over $100 and positioned by little
green plastic house on the square.
Next time around I'd be able to build a hotel on Dunwich.
Fiendish indeed.
Claire picked up the die and rolled a two.
Hmm, not so good.
She moved her Nathaniel Wingate Peasley forward and decided to try a theory.
Was it Naira Lothotep in the Miskatonic University with the blast from a cycle?
That's pretty horrifying, I said.
And this is Arkham Horror and the objective is to be horrifying except no, that's not
the answer, my turn.
I picked a card and read it out.
Damn.
Go to the mountains of madness.
Go directly to the mountains of madness.
Do not pass in's mouth.
Do not collect the sport of the forgotten.
Claire sensed that the tables had turned and went on the offensive.
E3, she said triumphantly.
I threw down my card's infrastration.
Blast, you've sunk my shop digger-ath.
Thank you Mark.
We thought that was very good.
It made me kickle quite a lot when I read it.
What's really interesting is that I know that you have not in fact played the Arkham
Horror card game but that is pretty much what it was like so, you know.
Hmm, right, okay.
Yeah.
I, hmm, it makes me wonder whether you were paying as much attention as I was when we played
it together but maybe that's unfair.
Don, I'm never paying as much attention because I know you were paying attention.
That is why I like, I asked you ten times yesterday whether I'd used to pull my actions
and you had to be like, I'm not actually tracking every single thing you were doing in this
game, Liz.
Alright, so...
More letters.
Mark did also raise another lock in which he doesn't talk about Arkham Horror almost
at all.
He mentions it a little bit.
This is a lovely glimpse of, you know, life into a certain, Croydon-Fanish household.
Um, but I think, I think he, I think he raises a good point which is that when he goes to
it in person he's gone, he's essentially going on holiday with his mates, most of whom he
doesn't see otherwise.
I think, and he says, as such, he thinks the quality of the convention is only a contributing
factor to the experience.
I think that is, um, basically true in that, and it's something I've been talking about
a little bit since confusion wrapped up which is, I had fun at confusion and I think it is
worth bearing in mind that it would have been very impressive had I not given how many
of my friends were all in the same place that weekend.
I think it would be very difficult, uh, not to enjoy yourself in some ways.
Um, so I do, I do think that is something worth bearing in mind that we are always kind
of grading on a curve, I guess.
Yeah, but also I think, I even a really terrible Easter con is fun because you're essentially
on holiday with your mates and confusion could not fall back on the fun of being on holiday
with your mates because we were not on holiday with our mates.
Yeah, he talks about the experience of being in gather and finding himself talking to a
couple of unexpectedly interesting people and then, and then other unexpectedly interesting
people turned up, which I think is right.
But also having the experience of, um, trying to talk to someone in gather and they ran past
a hundred miles an hour, which does happen at conventions too.
So, you know.
Well, that's a story where I remember it because it was me who ran past.
So I noticed Mark was in the cantina.
So I went up to him and I said, "Hi Mark."
And by the time he had managed to unmute and video himself, I had already gone back to
newsletter.
Uh, but you know, I was, I was, I was, I was in a rush to get back to these letter, uh,
because I owed things to the newsletter, like my soul, my blood, my sweat and my tears.
On the subject of confusion, DC also writes in and they say that they think it is important
to note explicitly with regard to confusion that there were not just potential accessibility
issues with the platforms used, but there were issues, um, which impacted negatively
all members and which led to people in the community not joining, uh, confusion.
And they kind of know that some of these are things that affect people with visual hearing
or neuromotor problems.
And I think, I think, um, and they say that they know we weren't trying to minimize those
things in any way, but it would be a wrong to overlook the extent to which various groups
of people felt actively excluded.
Um, yes.
We are, we didn't intend to minimize that.
And we are very sorry, uh, if it came across that way.
Um, we did, I think spent quite a lot of time in the run up to confusion, discussing how
their pre-con decisions were, um, uh, making those groups of people feel disenfranchised.
And I think, um, uh, that's one of the reasons we didn't touch on it as much last, uh, episode.
Uh, but yes, it's a very good point.
And, uh, we thank DC for bringing it up.
Yeah.
I think it's a, also a good point that, uh, you know, sometimes if I, uh, complain about
conventions, communication decisions, it's merely things that are like slightly inconveniencing
me or annoying me a little bit, but for other people, they can actually be deal breakers
about whether they can attend the convention or not.
So it's good to be reminded of that.
Pat McMurray wrote in, now this is very good because Pat is kind of taking us on a tour
of our back catalog in the medium of locks, which we are enjoying hugely.
So Pat wrote us a lock, which, uh, he titled Octa Thorpe 2, and it is a lock which deals
with Octa Thorpe's issue 21, 26, 1, 2, 27 and 29.
Uh, and so this is, um, we, we, we thoroughly enjoyed, uh, this kind of, um, thoroughly enjoyed
this kind of thing.
Uh, and thank you very much for writing your pat.
We, I'm, and I have seen a few other people, um, on Facebook been talking about something
about earlier episodes.
Um, and having gone back to listen to them, um, we apologise, uh, so Alison's first recording
studio was a well, uh, and mine was a sort of muffly scratchy haystack that I was embedded
in and Liz was obviously on the beach the whole time.
Uh, so we have, uh, substantially reworked our recording environment since then.
We apologise for the, for the less good audio quality of those first episodes.
Um, but we glad the people are going back to them and enjoying them.
Um, and thank you for the lock.
That is nice to, to read.
I enjoyed Pat's lock because it's a bit like turning Octa Thorpe into some kind of like
time loop podcast.
It occurs in a non-linear fashion, which I think is fun.
Maybe you should do a non-linear podcast one day, but that will annoy everyone.
I'm pretty sure that mentioning the fact that it's a time loop is a spoiler.
I'd also say to those of you who are watching on Octa Thorpe Live, you can see how John
and Alison have, you know, gone for upgraded and more impressive kit, whereas I'm still
using the same 15 quid headset that I got for free, that I was using on Octa Thorpe
one one day I will buy a better microphone, but much like an iPhone, I have not yet been
pressured into it.
Yeah, my microphone comes courtesy of Chris O'Shea.
Thank you very much, Chris.
Um, I, I, at some point I too will buy a better microphone, but it doesn't happen yet.
My microphone came from a place called Argos.
Tara Mendelson wrote to us on Facebook Messenger to say that Robin Hobb is a huge Jigsaw fan
and at LungCon 3 they made three of her book covers into Jigsaw's for the social space
in exhibits and then gave them to her after the convention.
So this is, I think, a letter of comment based on an early episode of Octa Thorpe, as I was
just referencing.
Yes, unlike, unlike Pat, Pharah is listening to Octa Thorpe in numerical order.
I don't think it makes any more sense that way.
It may even make less sense to listen to it in the order we did it.
It might be that Pat is discovering hidden themes that are not visible to the normal
listener.
Bridget says, "Opportunity for a whole new trench of rhyming poems."
So Mike, my thought was really what there were three giant Robin Hobb book cover jigs
alls in the social space in exhibits.
I never saw those and then I remembered that so I didn't see anything at LungCon apart
from the inside of ProgramOps.
Yay!
I saw some other stuff but I did not find the jigs source.
That's fair.
I explored the exhibits hall vigorously and thought it was fantastic and well done to
everyone involved in putting it together.
But that's because you were 17 at LungCon and that's how it works.
That's an outrageous lie.
An outrageous lie.
I was 25.
Yes, 25 because I was still a young person for the purposes of paying for membership.
Just.
Oh god.
And we've also had a couple of tweets of comment.
There's one from Androsan who says there is one thing she's fairly confident she could
do with its cross-platform accessible instructional video and she says send anything you need doing
her way.
So anyone who wants accessible videos, her Twitter username is A-N-G_G-R-R-R.
I think she meant us.
Oh did she.
I don't think she read everyone in the world.
Oh no.
Not everyone in the world is listening to this podcast.
It'll be fine.
Yeah, but you have to count all the people in the future who go back and listen to it
either in numerical order or in random date order.
And Peter Sullivan tweeted to say a killer feature of Gather that we didn't mention was
the ability to find anyone else in Gather using the magic red line on the floor.
I would gladly consider giving tech ops whatever tech budget they need to be able to replicate
this in real life.
I am also very fond of the Stalkure mates option in Gather.
And actually in fact if you'd like to talk to Alison about giving everyone at the Convention
and Oculus Quest 2 and setting this up, I'm sure Alison would be very interested in working
with you on it.
The third way to use a name is B-O-H-E-M.
But also, I mean when you said that I was like, oh I wonder if you took the EasterCon
tech budget, how many Oculus Quest sort of that have bought?
Is this a bit like if you look at the Test and Trace budget in the UK, you could have just
sent everyone in the country an iPhone and had them switch tracking on?
That's actually true.
That's how much they spent.
Very very large amount of money.
That's not, that's because the actual job of Test anyway, sorry that's definitely off
topic and we are definitely not talking about it.
Don your iPhone cannot yet do a PCR test.
Lies, maybe.
I'm sure Apple will, you know.
If I shove it far enough down my throat, Liz will see.
Okay, where anyone would like to suggest where we might shove John's iPhone far enough,
I should mention it in chat.
Things now said that when we were discussing the problems of an ops room trying to hard
to replicate a physical convention, it struck him that there's an extremely useful point
of reflection here.
Not only did they fail in trying to replicate a physical convention in the use of a walkie
talkie apps in an ops room, but in fact they seriously dropped the ball in normalizing the
use of additional channels and providing support.
And he basically says he thinks that future conventions should promote use of tools like
Discord so you can easily report problems from around the convention to ops without needing
to travel to the ops room.
And I think this is something that future conventions are thinking about and is a good
idea and I'm looking forward to seeing that kind of thing being taken up by future East
Cons.
And it's actually very good to do it in Discord because I've seen this kind of thing happen
on Twitter, but then if 10 people all send you a message on Twitter saying this thing
is going wrong, then you have to reply to all 10 of them say, "Yep, we're aware we're
going to fix it."
In Discord you can do that once and then everyone's like, "Yep, all right, they're
on top of it, sit back, relax, except they're not because I found this will probably send
other 10 messages."
But in theory that would work.
The chat's going wild.
If they want to set up a poll, but I wasn't paying enough attention to know what the poll
they want us to set up is.
So, you know.
We're definitely not setting up a poll guys, we're recording a podcast.
Wait for chat afterwards.
Can we set up a non-legally binding consultative referend?
We are going to do that more later.
We are.
For shadowing, and then lastly and bestly and PhD-resistant-slee, it is Claire Breyerley
from Croydon, who says, "Thank you very much for the compliments, but why don't you write
to us?
You really are living the closest a podcast can get to the fanzine life, aren't you?"
That is a fair comment.
Lots of you wrote to us this time and you will know because next, if we carry on getting
this many letters, we are going to have to institute a, we also heard from section on
our podcast.
They wanted to do a poll of where you stick the iPhone.
Yes.
For God.
Okay.
That, yes.
Family show guys.
Family show.
Thank you.
Thank you for other details and comments.
Thank you, thank you to Andrew January for the bugle reference.
And also said that she thinks I'm Will Bailey in the West Wing.
I haven't seen the West Wing, so like most of these references are for the enjoyment
of other people, but I'm happy to let myself be used as a tool for other people's enjoyment.
I'd go to, is it a good reference?
Bear that in mind for future reference.
Claire also notes that she enjoyed that Liz's Badger poem, and most significantly though,
you've previously talked around various ways in which people multitask while listening
to the podcast, but she thinks Badger has won that topic.
If anyone wants to claim they were also licking their own bum while listening, well, it's
really up to you whether you want proof.
We do not want proof.
Oh, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no,
we don't even want to be informed really.
Oh, no, we want to be informed.
We just don't want you to prove.
No, no, just, just informed John Coxon is, is, is.
And my Twitter handle is J O H L. Right.
Yes, but thank you all.
As we say, thank you all very much for the lovely letters of comment.
They were very nice.
We have a new feature this week, which is called Ask OctaThorp, our segment.
And for this first time, if there are questions you'd like the OctaThorp trio to answer, you
could do it in, in chat.
You can ask them in chat.
And at some point we will collate them and then answer a couple of funny ones later in
the show using a patented back chat method to decide which one we're going to do.
Oh, you want me to make the announcement?
Well, I want you to do the, I want you to do the joke.
You said you do.
We have decided that we are going to run punctuation to dot dot dot.
That was a joke.
That was a joke punctuation to be on the 80th to 20th of June and in traditional style, you
can't quite join it yet.
You'll be able to join it quite soon?
Yeah.
In late spring, as some of the surfants would say.
So yes, it's going to cost a fiver again, but this time it's going to cost a fiver if
you'd like to pay a fiver, or a tenor if you like what we're doing and would like us
to support us a bit more, or nothing if you like what we're doing, but you don't want
to pay a fiver.
Or if you think you don't know, aren't sure if you like it or not, and want to just pop
in for an hour.
Yeah.
So yeah, we will let you know how to do it soon, and we will also let you know how you
can help.
In fact, when you join, you're going to get a note saying, here's the link to tell us
how you'd like to help.
So we currently have on our website a big blue button, which says sign up for an email
when we open registrations.
And if you type in your email and click that button, we will send you an email when we
open registration.
If you were a member of punctuation one, we will also send you an email when we open
registrations.
And if you are in the discord for punctuation one, we will put in the discord when we open
But that will be the only thing we post to the punctuation one mailing list, and it will
be the only thing we post in the punctuation one discord.
So don't worry about getting inundated with messages you're not interested in.
We just want to let people know that the second one is open if they'd like to join.
And yes, it's going to be good.
We're going to bring back some old favourites like breakfast and the beer tasting and the
not a park run.
You too can listen to me run five kilometres.
Hopefully the weather will be nicer this time because it's June and not November.
If you've ever wanted half an hour of John doing heavy breathing, this is your chance.
Liz has not ever wanted that.
So Liz will not be taking me up on it.
I regret to inform you that the parks here are currently closed.
And so if they open reopen by June, I will go out and show you some live video of Komodo
ever monitor Liz.
If requested.
One of the reasons for choosing the dates 18th to 20th of June was that on the 21st of
June, all restrictions on behaviour in England will cease forever.
No, no, no.
All restrictions on behaviour in England will cease forever.
Some very specific restrictions will cease forever.
I really hope.
All restrictions on Covid safe behaviour in England will cease forever.
And so it would be quite, I don't know what the word is, ironic.
So this, if at punctuation two, we were just about to celebrate the very end of lockdown
forever.
And Liz was stuck in her flat unable to go out for coffee.
I mean, let's not.
I mean, we all hope that Liz will not be stuck in our house for ages.
Ah, but yes.
So punctuation two is basically the dead dog party of lockdown.
So come and have one big last hurrah before Covid goes forever because Boris Johnson told
it to.
I think it might be quite sarcastic at this point.
I don't think we think this is the end of restrictions forever, but it might be the end
of restrictions for a while.
It might be the start of a nice, mostly unrestricted summer.
And so let's do that by, you know, also indoors on our computer for weekend.
But yes, we want to hear, you know, we want, we like to hear from people, what did you
think worked really nicely punctuation one and we should do again?
What was we should never do it again?
Yeah.
And, you know, we'll be asking for ideas of fun things and especially since it will be
June and not November, there may be exciting things you can do outside your house.
And we are working on a couple of things which will be strict upgrades from the first
punctuation, but we're not going to tell you what they are yet in case they don't work.
And we will be doing a non-legally binding consultative referendum on some different
options we're throwing around with regards to exactly how we run our tech stack and what
people would find the most accessible slash the most usable.
So and again, that will be going out in the same email as the announcement that we've
opened our registrations to punctuation one members.
And we will also be posting to that in the anonymous Claire Discord.
So if you would like to join the consultation, you will see it when it is ready.
I think that's everything on punctuation too.
Ah, yeah.
Come along.
It'll be fun.
Yeah.
We're going to have fun.
We're looking forward to it.
Start planning your breakfasts now.
Yeah, start planning your meet.
So one of my big takeaways from virtual conventions was the big takeaways are good at virtual
conventions.
So you should definitely start planning your big takeaways.
I recommend kibab.
Yeah, I also recommend kibab.
And this recommends some Thai thing that we can't get here, which is very tasty apparently.
Yeah, probably.
I mean, probably multiple options to that.
But I was a bit jealous because fried breakfasts are not a huge thing.
And it's much harder to get like nice bacon and sausages.
So I would come to the breakfast thing, which to me would be a mid-afternoon and everyone
would be like tucking into the delicious full English and I'd be drinking a cup of coffee.
No player, no.
Banana humus is what caused that spontaneous outburst from Liz.
We still don't have a chair.
Oh, we should say we have extra people on the committee this time.
We definitely should have said that.
This time we have a committee of six people, all mad gaming fans.
The centre of gravity of the punctuation committee was not sufficiently based in South London.
And to rectify this, we have added two people to address the balance.
And that is Claire Briley and Mark Plummer of Croydon.
You may recognise them from their locks.
We're happy to have them on the team.
They have good ideas and they will make punctuation too better than it would be without them.
So thank you very much to both of them for volunteering.
They will certainly make it better punctuated.
They will.
Doesn't that mean that the central gravity of the convention is now somewhere about western
Greece?
Yeah, but that is more South London than it was before.
I'll calculate it.
Yeah, this will calculate it.
Oh god.
There are Python scripts to do this sort of thing probably.
So on the subject of virtual conventions, Swankon has had to cancel their convention the
day before it was due to start due to a three day lockdown.
For those who don't know.
Swankon is the convention of Perth in Australia.
And we would like to note that Swankon announced the day before that they were not going to
be running a convention and they had time to do some online programme items.
Not every convention has found that they have had time to do online programme items with
a similar lead time.
I am hugely impressed by that because I feel desperately sorry for them, especially if
you were doing all that planning and then literally the day before you have to just...
Yeah, I think they're postponing.
They'll be able to run it quite soon I think, but it must be an important shot for them.
We're very sorry.
We hope that the rescheduled Swankon is amazing and we are very sorry to anyone who is going
because that sucks.
And on the subject of postponing conventions, look at these seamless segues guys, "Disc
on three are changing their dates to December for my birthday."
Yeah, we'd have talked about this two weeks ago, but we were too busy talking about these
two gone two weeks ago.
So yes, "disc on" is now a live action convention in December.
I think this says there may still be some hybrid elements as well.
There will be some hybrid elements.
And it's the weekend before Christmas, which I have to say guys, removes any lingering
chance I was going to be able to get to it.
Yeah, I'm also not planning to attend, I don't think.
Although if I hear a sad noise from a spandere in the other room, maybe I will change my mind
to life on air.
We'll see.
I mean, right now it's moot because none of us are allowed into the US right now, I think.
Anyway, so really given we don't know when that will shift, I'm not sure whether August
to December makes a big change to that.
I think people who don't like hot weather will be much happier with the December date.
Yes, I think you might be right.
It would be that cold.
It would probably just be quite cold.
But I calibrate everything on a different scale now.
That's not really the most important.
I think, oh, they've even got, actually there is a frequently asked questions about what
is the weather like in mid-December.
So I'm cleaning up the only person worrying about that.
And the answer is bloody awful, right?
Now the answer is high of seven and low of one on average.
That's fine.
Which is, you know, chilly, quite cold.
Couple of jumpers.
It's bringing my proper coat weather.
Yeah, there's no such thing as bad weather, there's just bad clothing.
So you'll be inside all we can, so, yeah.
And this has raised questions about the deadline for site selection, says Kevin Stanley on
Dreamwidth.
We've put a link in the show notes if you would like to read about that.
I, um, yes, I had thoughts, but I forgot them.
Or more accurately, I decided they were too tedious to say out loud.
Yeah, I think Kevin's basically said they should reopen site selection and everyone else
has said they're there, Kevin.
I think that's, is that right?
I think that's right.
So I think I can see where he's coming from on a principal stand basis.
The other thing that's happened while we were talking about Eastercon was that Baines
Bar returned with all of its odd posts intact.
And with a note from Tony Vyskoff saying that she'd reviewed them and didn't think
there was a problem with them.
So that's a thing.
I feel like this is now sitting around being a issue for fandom that is unlikely to go away,
that it's going to continue to cause us trouble.
But we'll see.
And Mike Gloyer wrote about this and we've got a link in the show notes, but I do think
that, um, I don't know if Liz and Nalison agree with me here, but I do think that now
that she's been like, Oh, no, all of this was fine.
She's like, yeah, you should not have been the discount three guest of order.
And that was probably the right decision.
I know it's said to horrible precedent.
And I know it's like very much not something we've done traditionally, but dang.
Yeah, I suspect the Discon committee who had to make that difficult decision are probably
feeling better.
Yeah.
I think that's about it.
I think that's fine.
The other thing about the about Discon moving its dates to December, look at our amazing
segues, is that it means that we've got much longer for our Hugo reading and watching and
for the very first time playing.
So reactions to the Hugo finalists.
Congratulations to John for his Hugo finalists spot for Journey Planet.
We're very proud of him.
Thank you.
Hey.
And congratulations to everyone else who was a finalist or is a finalist or was a finalist
or will be your finalist in the future.
Oh, no.
Okay.
In that case, I was in the past, but who knows?
No, so we have a couple of broad thoughts.
We're not going to go massively into the weeds or the Hugo Awards, because, you know, because
we're going to do that next episode or maybe the one after there will be an episode when
we go massively into the weeds.
Yeah.
At some point, quite a lot of episodes, really.
We've got we've got time.
It's not so December.
We've got ages.
Yeah, we could just fill the entire podcast with Hugo, Nerdary from now until December.
An episode per category.
I could can I have an episode just for Hades, please, because I can fill an entire episode
with Hades, Nerdary.
Um, yes, possibly.
Octa-thop, it would be less och-thop gaming corner and more just och-thop at that point.
Um, so, um, so some top level thoughts about the Hugo's.
Firstly, I did a lot of reading this year in preparation with the Hugo's with the net effect
that I'm quite a lot further along with my fiction reading than I am usually, which is
nice.
Uh, and in general, I've been enjoying that.
But my two overarching thoughts are, um...
Sorry, can I have a poll, please?
Because I always say overarching.
Oh, overarching?
Over-arching.
And because of arches, but I understand that it's one of these difficult prefixes because
obviously it's arkin, archangel, and arkin archaeology, but arch in archbishop.
And in archive.
Archbishop, or...
But they're just called that because they're very sarcastic.
And so I don't know what the...
Archum.
You should see, yes.
That's what happens when we are reading the chat while doing it.
I would say overarching with Alison.
So, Hugo, John, out of it.
Okay.
I'm gonna have to just say overarching a lot and then Eddy Stitihin, where you two have
said that to make it sound back for Alessa.
That's annoying.
I think the best game category is really good.
And the reason I think this is because it is six games, none of which are all indie darlings
and are all AAA games or are all big old PlayStation games.
You know, there's a huge breadth in just the six titles that has really shown, I think,
how much there is in the genre from the massive remakes of beloved games for your kind of
hardcore PlayStation gamers.
And then also a nice little browser game where you bet on baseball with black holes and there's
like a whole narrative around that, which is a bit strange.
And I really, I'm playing Spirit of Fair as the moment, I'm really enjoying it.
And yeah, I'm super impressed with how broad the best game category is.
And it's already more vibrant than several of the categories that have been around for
a lot longer than it.
And I have a beef to pick with the Hugo's because I had been avoiding buying Hades ever
since my son said to me, "Oh, Mum, you would really like this game.
It's a persistent roguelike of the sort that you drop into and then neither eat nor sleep
for weeks on end."
And I was like, "Yeah, yeah, you're quite right.
I'm just not touching it with the barge pole."
And then it got turned up on the Hugo ballot and I was like, "Oh, this is an excuse."
And so if I owe you anything, if I haven't done something I said I'd do, if I've been,
if I missed a major organizational meeting for your convention, if I did any of these
things any time in the last two weeks I'm very sorry.
Whatever she said, whatever she did, she didn't mean it.
I did.
It's, I'm really, really enjoying this game there.
Ha ha ha ha.
Allison's doing the Hugo voter pack this year so I'm looking forward to her giving me
a free copy of this game later in the year.
That's not part of my responsibilities.
Boo!
Um, is it possible to pay for, pay for Blaiseball?
Have I?
No, I don't think it is possible to pay for Blaiseball.
Yeah, so, so, so we actually have everything from a, you know, a, a triple-a game on a
playstation through to a game you play in your browser for nothing and I, I think that's
quite good.
I am similarly pleased to see a wide variety of stuff on there.
I was slightly surprised not to see Cyberpunk 2077 which despite all the bugs seem to have
been a quite well received game but maybe it came out quite late in the year and people
didn't own it.
I'm a little bit, I'm a little bit sad because I would like to play all these games but I
actually only have the hardware to play four out of six and I've never played a Final
Fantasy game and I'd be quite interested in playing it but it is still extremely expensive.
Jon is waving a hand at me.
I think you can play five out of six.
Can I?
Yeah, because I think Spirit of Eris and Hades are both on playstation.
Hades is not on playstation.
What?
Oh, but it's on Steam.
The more general point is, very few of the Hugo voters are actually going to have the
kit to play all six of these games because it does require you to have both a Switch
and a playstation 4.
True.
And that's quite a big ask and I think that's something that separates it from most of
the Hugo categories where we can expect most voters to be able to access all of the games
and I think there was some suggestion when we suggested this before that let's plays
might be the solution to that but I don't think they are because they're not the same.
I think they might be for a couple of them not naming the last of us two explicitly.
I just wanted to come back.
So you mentioned Cyberpunk 2077.
I'm not sure that in the Hugo voters wheelhouse you know, I'm not sure that the Hugo voters
are historically known except for certain bad actors for supporting works which are quite
as undiverse as that game turned out to be shall we say.
And so I am entirely unsurprised that Hugo Electric chose not to reward it.
And to be fair, I think that was the right decision.
But as always it will be very interesting seeing the other things that were nominated
when the full when the long list comes out in December we have to wait till December.
Oh I am told about that.
We do it's so annoying if Kevin Sandley wants to have opinions he should have opinions on
releasing the full list in August anyway like I happen to need his stats.
I'm sure that's enough games chaps otherwise we'll start losing our audience won't we.
Hey Mark's already written us a lock during the recording so.
He did that before we started talking about games though and it's about games so you know.
It is about games.
I've got a tiny tiny tiny bit more on games sorry because not only would I have to have
like all I basically would need a playstation and a switch to play this but also the last
of us part two is still I think better part 45 quid.
The final fantasy remake is still 40 quid so like it's not an hour we need these but the
investment to actually play the games in this category is about 100 quid it's it's a big
thing.
I am going to tell you how the young gamers play these games which is that they buy them
from their local second hand game shop and then they sell them back to their local second
hand game shop so you know for a total cost of about a fiver so I don't think that's
a I don't think that's insane.
Yeah I hadn't thought of that but I might have to get myself down to CEX once once lockdown
eases a bit more and see if I can pick up cheap copies.
I understand it's pronounced sex.
On this podcast it's not this is a family show a family show family show Alison.
It used to be that if you phone them up you'd get the person answering the phone would say
you've reached the sex helpline how can we help you something which has irritated me
ever since I discovered it.
So it pleased me to see a place ball on the list actually because that's one of the games
that I've heard described as basically the game is one thing but really everyone's playing
for the emerging emergent narrative around it.
I think that is very interesting because we had discussions about emerging narratives
and things in games on previous episodes.
No and the current season of of plays ball is sponsored by a convention that focuses
on Ludo narrative and I think yes it is clear that an awful lot of the enjoyment of the
game is not actually the mechanics of the game which is really interesting and it kind
of reminds me of the Marble Olympics but like I think a lot of that to do with emergent
narrative as well rather than it yeah there's a lot to talk about there I think and also
like some novels and stuff got nominated.
Oh yeah who tells stories by writing them down on paint like what like come on guys it's
2021 strap on a graphics card let's get this baby going.
A quite novel just in case anyone is about to write in.
Yeah I'm also trying to watch the all the best dramatic presentation nominees because
I should manage to do that despite not paying a lot of attention to television generally
some of them are the short fixed the short form ones are kind of episodes of things so
that probably requires me to watch quite a lot of things to get to the relevant episode.
I've already seen all of the best long form contenders except for Tenet and if that is
still the case when votes close I won't regard it as a huge problem.
Everything I've heard about Tenet makes me reluctant to spend the amount of money to
actually like purchase it so if it doesn't come on a free streaming service between now
and then it is unlikely that I will watch it in time for the Hugo's unless it's in the
Hugo Voto packet and Alison gives me a free copy.
I think it's most unlikely to be in the Hugo Voto packet.
True.
Doctor who might be was last year.
I think there is a chance that some of the short forms will be better don't think any
of the long forms will be historically they have not been.
Richard says that her old job they had fire assembly points hopefully labelled on the maps
as FAP in reassuringly large letters.
Okay, what's next on the show notes?
Are you done with games?
Are we ever done with games?
I think Mark Plone would argue no.
But yes I think so.
I was going to say Tenet is the only one of the long forms I've actually seen and I
mean I did enjoy it but I did go and see it in the cinema having not been to see a film
in the cinema for many months because they were closed so I did enjoy it that way.
You do have to turn your brain off a bit and I missed about a quarter of the dialogue
I think because it's very hard to hear and I'm not sure if that helped or hindered my
enjoyment of the film.
So I might watch again just with the subtitles on to see if it's any more enjoyable.
That's fair.
If you are interested in watching the best long-form Mac presentation finalists then you can come
along to the snark-long channel on the anonymous Claire Discord where there are discussions
of such things and you can discuss them with us.
We've been with Watcht Palm Springs so far.
I don't think we've watched any of this have we?
Not a snark-along no.
I mean snark-along has watched other things but in true snark-long form where we have
chatted over the film whereas for me at least I'm going to watch the BDP finalists without
having people talking over them at the time.
Except for you and Stephen.
I mean I think it's kind of okay still to have one person on the sofa going "What's that
about?"
Is that the same character as that one earlier and you go "They're both clean-cut white American
men in their early 20s and are therefore indistinguishable?"
The Warhammer 40,000 movie Ultramarine is an animated movie where everyone is exactly
the same white guy and that was enormously difficult to follow.
It did not find its way onto the Hugo Ballot for some reason.
Shockingly.
Has there ever been a good game based movie to discuss?
Or we should talk about that sometime in...
There has.
Golden Eye, the James Bond film.
Mm-hmm.
Wasn't the game afterwards?
Some people have argued that.
Yeah.
But what even is time?
Okay.
So apart from Minesweeper the trailer which I would argue with.
Ah yes now.
We really are off topic.
I'm so sorry guys.
The detective Pikachu is quite good.
In actual fact.
I know it sounds like I'm trolling but I genuinely enjoyed that movie.
Yeah no, people say that's very good.
Firecom.
Doing things.
Alison's bought a ticket.
Lizzamy bought a ticket.
Yeah I could go last year so I have because they sold out by the time I tried to join.
So this year I have joined.
I will probably go to it.
Um.
Yeah.
I think it's worth saying that last year they had limited tickets.
Um and so I didn't buy one last year because I would not have been able to attend which
is a convention.
I did buy a ticket for the fringe which is explicitly in my time zone which was very
good and was free.
I might buy a ticket this year because since they're unlimited this year I don't feel
I'm taking away a ticket from someone who could make better use of it.
Um.
That makes sense.
Yeah.
Do they do programming in your time zone which is not adorated?
Sorry.
Programming am I?
I said it was explicitly in your time zone.
I was just wondering if there's any non explicit content in your time zone.
What I love about this is the audience finally gets to see your reactions to my jokes like
on your faces and they get to understand why I have such a good time.
Yeah.
Um we have many people in the chat saying that they love Detective Pikachu so I will try
and watch that at some point.
And DC says in reaction to my joke tumble read which is fair.
Is the reaction to a many of George jokes?
It's true.
I love being me.
As has been noted the last time FireCon did a convention they had a much smaller pool of
tickets.
I mean, definitely because this time it's infinite but also small enough that it's all
out very quickly.
This time you can donate memberships but we believe they have hit their donation target
for that but you can still donate to the general fund.
And this is something that Reclamation in 2022 are also doing and we very quickly mentioned
Reclamation last episode at the very beginning.
We haven't talked about it a great deal.
So yes.
So Reclamation when you sign up the membership is 70 pounds for our attending and different
prices for other categories which are not the ones I fall into so I didn't look at them
in great detail.
But it asks you when you check out whether you would like to add a donation.
The recommended donation is 10 pounds towards letting less able fans, letting fans attend
who would be less financially able to do so.
Obviously if you can't afford 10 pounds there's no pressure on you to do so like it's entirely
up to you.
But I think this is a really good idea and a way of kind of letting the more privileged
of us in the community support the less privileged when it comes to wealth.
So yeah, well done Reclamation.
I think this is something that all East Con should be looking at doing.
I would say that I believe it was a Turbium that had this as well.
I'm being a bit vague because I can't exactly remember but I think it was a Turbium who also
had a Bursary Fund that you could donate to.
They had some issues around the bursaries though and I think Reclamation is doing a
simpler let's just donate memberships rather than granting bursaries with strings attached.
Yes, I think that just is a much simpler way to implement it.
I was noticing I think Dublin had the fantastic Dublin Fund which had some similar aspects
and Discon and Chicon both have funds for this as well.
So I think it's clearly going to be thing World Cons do in the future.
I quite like the way Discons Warner has basically two aims.
One is getting underrepresented fans into World Cons but the other one is specifically
for local fans who might enjoy it but basically can't come in on a World Cons membership.
And so it will let them come in and have like a taster of the convention or people who live
locally so they don't need extra funding but just a membership is too much for barrier.
I think that's quite a nice sort of dual aim especially for a convention that moves around
every year.
Yes, no and I think I wasn't aware that Itobium had to try to do something similar but I think
like you say having it right there on the Redch Form is really nice so I think that's
really positive.
And in general very excited about Reclamation in 2022.
Great guest of on the list.
In 2022 has a great guest of honor list.
They have Zencho who I love and they have Mary Robinette Coel who I also love and they
have Philip Reeve who I love and they have Nicholas White who I love.
So this is a solid roster in my opinion.
Yes.
It's very good.
Well done lads.
Yeah, it's very very very solidist.
And I mean by lads I'm using lads and it's British, gender inclusive form.
Very sorry.
Yes.
And also FireCon did publish details about their costs and platforms.
If you want to know how much it costs to run a virtual convention there will be a link
in the show notes.
I think FireCon published details of its platforms and it costs shortly after the previous
Varkon and it was one of the things that I took into account when I was enthusiastic
about the idea that punctuation would do the same.
We have not done it any in quite as much details they did but it's good.
I think it's very useful for conventions to do this to give people who are planning other
conventions a sense of what the really exciting things that they saw actually cost because
sometimes those things are very expensive and sometimes they're not, they're just clever.
So FireCon also announced the nominees of their Ignite Awards which I believe are a set
of jury nominations from a committee from FireCon which I think this year included some of
the awardees from the previous year and then they put all the nominees up for a public
vote.
So we put a link in the show notes.
There's some really interesting nominees on there.
There's some crossover with the Hugo's but there's also some really interesting things on
there.
They have more categories as well because they have categories for poetry, a specific year,
critics award and some community awards.
So it's worth going over there and checking out all the nominees and then you can vote
until the 21st of May.
Right, so I have just read all the way through the chat looking for Ask Octathorb questions
that have not found any so that maybe didn't work.
Look, right, have we tried checking out Twitter?
There were at least two questions which I spotted and I really should have copied the
post.
So we had one for Jerry which is what is the average airspeed velocity of a laden swallow?
Would that be an African or a European swallow?
I am able to make the correct religious forms here.
Unlike John who had no idea what that reference was referring to.
I do have an idea, it's Monty Python.
I always preferred the series to the movies.
God I sound like a...
Really?
Because the series has loads of really crap stuff.
If you actually go and watch it, you go, "Oh, this was a sketch show on the BBC so one
joke in five is very funny."
What I should say is I'm a fan of the three disc best of the sketch show set which solves
an awful lot of that problem.
And Claire Brierley from Croydon also asks us, "Where should we stick the iPhone if we want
to send you the proof you don't want?"
To be fair, that was the one that I decided we wouldn't actually do some last copy of
the book.
And I did post in the chat because people were clamoring for a poll of where I should
stick my iPhone but I discovered I cannot do a poll of my own orifices so apologies to
all of them.
Okay, so let me set up a poll of John's orifices.
No, not right.
Family show guys.
It doesn't work if I'm the one making it less family, does it?
That was the 30th episode of the Oxford Hall podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
I'm using lads wrongly.
Yeah, okay.
I suppose well done chaps isn't going to do me any better is it?
Well done everyone.
No, we need to launch a campaign that makes it clear that chaps is gender neutral because...
Well done guys.
Guys is less...
I think chaps is definitely more gender neutral than guys or lads.
The two I've been using are folks and peeps, both of which are absolutely gender neutral
but I want chaps to be come gender neutral because I like calling people chaps.
I always use chaps in a gender neutral way until people started saying, "Oh no, do you
realize it's not gender neutral?"
I was like, "It really is for me."
But obviously it's not always interpreted that way so I will try to do better.
Folks and peeps both are but peeps is a trademark so I have to be a bit careful about that.
Roman suggests team as in the reclamation team which is a good one but I also think
I try to always use chaps in a gender neutral way is maybe the title of the podcast.
Yeah right, that works.
I like that.
Okay.
I shouldn't say stuff like that now because now John can't cut that bit of complete nonsense
from the podcast.
Yes!
This is what I feed on.
Bridget suggests leather chaps which does solve the problem of people interpreting it
to me.
Men but...
Mini Figs.
Nice.
Okay, Mini Figs.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod at Ncompetech.com,
used under a Creative Commons attribution 3.0 license.
Ha ha ha ha ha!
I don't have the same beep in chat now.
We don't actually recall the beep but every time.
Beep.