Are you suggesting that was not gold content that is going in the podcast, John?
No, but I am going to say that that was the 25th episode of the Octa thought podcast.
Hello everyone and welcome to the 25th episode of Octa Thorpe, the podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom.
This is the episode for the 18th of February 2021 and I'm John Coxon and I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
Hello everyone, it's John here just interjecting very quickly to tell you all that this weekend,
Saturday the 20th of February, is PicoCon 38, which has gone online and is called Automata.
There are details in the show notes and the guests of honor are Jeffrey Somers, Dan Morrin,
S.J. Kinkade and Brian David Johnson. I'll be there as I believe will Alison and so we might see you in the bar.
Now back to the episode and we are recording this on Valentine's Day.
I love you both. Love you both.
I better say I love you both or it's going to sound weird if I didn't say it, didn't I?
And we've also had some letters of comment.
We have lots.
No, no locks.
And we have a lot of different, proud locks.
Yeah, Bridget Bradshaw, right?
To say that she used to log all her films on that box and she thought she had only kind of full off the wagon in the last year.
And then she went on her little box account and it's actually been since 2016.
So she's back on the wagon. Yes, I too am on the wagon.
I have been logging my 2021 film watching, which is the vast majority of which has been genre,
but there's been some comedies.
So if anyone wants to follow me watching best dramatic presentation,
eligible films, then I am John Coxon in a fit of imagination.
And I am Bohemian coast.
Yes, and Liz is not on letterboxed.
What?
Great.
Do you watch movies?
They don't have films in Thailand.
We we have films in Thailand.
I can in fact go out to the cinema and watch a film right now.
I think we do have films, but I just don't tend to log them.
I think logging book this is about as far as I can get.
And really, I don't want something that loves just movies.
I would like something that just logs like all TV I watch and all movies.
If you want that, then you want a service called Tract, which is T-R-A-K-T dot TV.
But in effect, you don't want it because logging all the TV you watch is incredibly
tedious and takes ages.
I used to log the TV I watched, but you watch so much TV that you watch way more
programs of TV than you do movies or books.
And so logging all your TV just like very quickly becomes this never-ending,
grinding, tedious thing, whereas the other two I feel less so.
I need to say at this point that when John says you in this context, he means John.
I mean, I watch maybe seven episodes of TV a week, but that is still far more
than I watch movies or read books.
And I suspect that's true for most people unless you are a very quick reader,
or unless you almost exclusively watch movies.
To be fair, it's Spanya Whitewatch more movies than she does TV episodes.
But I think it's Spanya is at the edge of the bell curve in that.
If you are somebody who prioritizes movies and books because you tend to think
that a lot of TV is extruded entertainment product.
Yeah, that.
When I say log my TV, I don't necessarily want to log every single thing.
What I want to be able to say is like, oh, I finished watching the expand season
five log that whole thing.
Ah, no, that is not no Tract as episode by episode.
Yeah, no, I don't want that.
I may want episode by episode.
This is complicated that I think TV tracking and people can write to us about
this. I think TV tracking is interesting because you kind of want to log that
you've started watching a series and you want to what log when you finish
watching a series and you don't necessarily want to log that you gave off
on a series, a episode seven of season two because it really wasn't going anywhere.
And there are 19 seasons of it and life is too short.
Yes.
So listeners is taking us less than five minutes to get a cast
offically off topic today.
We hope you're enjoying the podcast is almost entirely my fault.
Footrobe, I apologize.
Bridget also mentions the Bosco fan fund auction and we're going to mention that
later listeners.
This is foreshadowing, which I think they do in TV and movies and books and maybe
other media. Next lock is from Chris Garcia.
He titled his email lock on the episode, whose number I've forgotten.
The context should reveal it in due time.
So it was 24 Chris, just, you know, Chris writes another strong episode that made
me listen with only two of the sound sources going.
So clearly what we have to aspire to is that one day Chris will give us half an
hour of complete attention and we will ever taint vanish, Nirvana.
I I thought this was a very revealing lot because I think it is true that people
believe their ability to multitask is much better than it actually is.
While I think most people can listen to a podcast whilst also doing a thing that
is using a different part of their brain, like I don't know, knitting or walking or
whatever or being Chris Garcia.
I am not convinced that you can listen to multiple sound sources at once and get
full benefit from all of them.
And I think that Chris might kidding himself and I feel that I would be interested
in other people's views on this.
I think that if anyone can do it, Christopher J.
Garcia Esquire is the man.
I think if Chris really was listening to two of the things at the same time and still
managed to write a lot, which basically covers everything we covered in the last
episode, then I'm pretty impressed.
Go for it, Chris.
He's a clearly a wizard, but we knew this.
Also, you say you have a friend who runs a serial podcast party that is another
concept, please write to us about how a serial podcast party works.
And indeed, anyone else running weird format parties, please write to us about how
they work and by write to us, I think we mean invite us.
I mean, yup.
Chris also mentions his nominations for Best Chameck Long Form, which is going to be
welcome to Night Vale, Palm Springs, The Mandalorian and Wonder Woman 1984.
I think we mentioned Palm Springs and Wonder Woman last episode.
But I don't think we mentioned The Mandalorian as a contender for long form.
So thank you for mentioning that, Chris.
But I think it clearly is.
And I'm interested by the reference to Welcome to Night Vale, which is something
that I started listening to and concluded was not moving.
Interestingly or excitingly enough for me, but people do seem to like it quite a
lot. It has a lot of fans.
It does.
The Vast of Night, which I'll talk about later, has a lot in common with Welcome
Tonight.
Mark Plummer wrote to us
that say that we should extract the sound by of Liz saying Jesus at 49.
33 or thereabouts for future use.
And he says he's sure that we can monetize it.
He could use it two or three times in every work conference call.
So Liz has a huge and sparkling future as a voice over.
You know how you can like pay a fiver and someone bring a goat to your zoom call.
What?
OK, have you ever seen that?
Oh, hang on though. This was on the news quiz, wasn't it?
Yes. No, OK, yes.
But explain for the listeners who are not familiar.
There's a farm and you can pay them a fiver and they will bring a goat to a zoom
call for you like to liven up your weekly zoom calls or whatever.
If anyone would like to pay me to turn up to the zoom call, just like log in and say,
Jesus and then leave, I'm available.
Mark also sends us some statistics.
I like this.
And I mentioned statistics that I would like to see, try and think of one for every
episode and then Mark will magically do the work for me.
The sort of listenership I like now that you've revealed that that's your strategy,
Liz, it might backfire.
In return for this, I will turn up to your zoom calls.
And see.
Brilliant.
Mark has run numbers for us of those numbers.
4,624 members as per the long list,
including attending, supporting and to some degree a day members.
I'm not sure I can see them.
They've had day members, but I might be wrong about that, including some members
who don't have voting rights because they joined too late.
I would I would say that my experience of virtual conventions is a lot of people.
This is me, not Mark.
A lot of people join right up to the last minute
for online conventions.
And I assume that those people will generically not have voting rights.
So that might be quite a large number.
Two of those 2,221 people voted in at least one Hugo category, which is slightly less
than half. And the most votes in any category was 1,873 for best novel.
So of the people who voted about 80 percent vote for the best novel.
For Dublin, those numbers were 8,430 members of whom 3,097 voted in the Hugo's
slightly pure as a proportion.
Most in a category was 2,540 for best dramatic presentation,
longer get around about 80 percent.
Yeah. And then there are many other examples as well.
Did not really say I'm off to play Arkham Horror now.
There may be a typo in that sentence.
Yeah, a pyjima typo is I'm off to play Arkham Horror now.
Yeah, I think that's right.
I think we so so our target for I think this podcast should have 21 targets.
It's like that, but our target for 21 should be to get Claire
about play Arkham Horror with us.
Mark is less into games than Claire is.
So I think if I was going to guess which person we would be able to entice more easily,
I think I would guess that Claire was more
enticed than Mark.
This may spur letters of comment from both disagreeing with my take.
But yeah, I feel we may have to leave this one till 2022 and the distant future
and we can all gather together and play it in person with some beer.
Beer.
Big this will be a more appealing prospect than seeing for a different computer for four hours.
And then Claire wrote in, she mentions a mistake we made that we're not going to go into.
And then she also notes that if she started, if her and Mark started shuffling all
of their Nova Awards around for our amusement, the cloud of dust stood up would
make us cough a lot and that's a bit too worrying at the moment.
So yes, that is a good point.
Thank you, Claire, for catching a properly embarrassing era.
And I've said we should say what the era was and John has explained to me why we should not do that.
I'm probably just being paranoid.
And she has also said that everyone should read all of the murderbot dairies,
which I have taken away as a target.
Yes, well, I've got them.
I've got them on.
I've got them on order from the library.
I believe the third one is on my device now, but we will get on to that in a minute.
And Christina writes in to say that she
learned a lot from the mask on panel on podcasting and
she sort of talks about some of the stuff she learned about microphones and whatnot.
But she does say that she'd like to add that she never said that Lily and love
laughing very loudly caused problems with editing bad Alison.
No, I think I might have said that.
So there we go.
Whenever I hear Lillian laughing on the podcast, it makes me miss evenings where
Lillian laughs on my sofa.
Oh, yeah, that's fair. That is very fair.
OK, and my red wine bill is way down.
I mean, tell him to cheer up.
We don't want a sad red wine bill.
Fine.
She says there's one benefit to you having a regular recording schedule, which is she
knows when to get her comments in.
And that's true because we received this yesterday evening.
So thank you very much, Christina, brilliant.
And Rosin tweeted us to say that she's moved her desk into her living room because
it's got a nicer view.
But she then attached a picture of a cat hogging said desk.
And I think that might really be more of the reason as a good
man, having a desk somewhere where there is a cat is always preferable to somewhere
where there isn't.
Fuse expressed by John Cox and may not reflect all of the members of the Octa
Thought podcast.
They reflect two thirds of the OctaPod podcast.
Yeah, I understand the time and outlier in not wanting furry, furry creatures wandering
through my workspace.
Oh, God, we're going to get somebody letters now.
I know.
I mean, firstly, you've got a son and a husband and we were listening to your
opinions on that earlier.
So all I've got is a cat and much easier to deal with Alison.
My husband is not particularly furry.
My son, I will grant you his pretty bloody furry.
I've got a gecko again.
Yeah.
I think it's a different one.
I bought some anti geckos, Ray.
You should tag them.
Can you please quantify how furry is your gecko on a scale of not furry to furry?
I think it is very much on the not furry end.
You've bought some anti gecko spray.
Look, I mean, OK, so I have not got to this extent of buying anti cat spray.
OK, yeah, but to cut regularly into your house and the hide in the skirting boards.
Anyway, back on topic.
Yes.
So DC wrote in to DC tweeted to say that the perils are reading well tired.
He looked at the info for last episode and thought it said, please let email your
letters of contempt.
So if anyone does have any letters of contempt, please send them to this.
Never happens.
And then finally, Duncan McGregor tweeted to ask whether we are going to discuss
the we to bits and beans thing.
So for those who don't know, there was some tweets in which we to bits suggested
you could have we to bits with beans.
This is baked beans for a non-British listener.
And then there were a lot of funny follow ups.
And then every British band, every British large brand posted, I think it must
be the coordinated effort to say to make some quite funny and some rather less
funny jokes tying their brand into the concept of like spec savers said, let's
take our glasses off and that sort of thing.
They had tweeted the day before about Marmite on we have it, but that had not
quite that had not quite captured the zeitgeist as effectively.
No, that's because my my time we to fix is perfectly normal.
My time we to fix is normal.
Not sure that's it.
Marmalade on we to fix is normal.
Bait beans on we is not.
I'd like to just say normal on we mix is milk and everything else is pretty unusual,
I would say.
But it's not unknown.
The reason why we beans on we to bits doesn't work is that in the time it takes,
I've explained this to people and they're kind of like in the time it takes to heat
beans, you can also make toast.
So there's no point using we to bits as the substrate field.
But when I explain this, people were like, oh, you mean people heat up their beans?
So cold beans on cold we to fix does make a certain amount of sense.
But probably only if you've had a certain amount of alcohol, which is a lot.
So no, do not do this.
Do not send us beans on which books.
Yeah, because I would say that the only thing worse than beans on we to fix is
beans in general or possibly every social media manager in the UK trying to think
up a funny comment to make about beans on we to fix.
I got no sense to humor.
Speaking of which, bigs, I have a milkman now.
Hello, because I was like the problem.
So you don't want to cater a gecko, but milkman, sons and husbands, they're all fine.
My milkman does not wander thoroughly through my workspace.
Yeah, anyway, right.
So on to the topics.
So firstly, Alison is at Boscone.
I am.
It's possible the reason I've been detached this weekend is that I've been at Boscone,
which is using the new Grenadine single sign on system to run where you log in
to Grenadine, which is a very easy pro.
It's got the kind of password free login where you type your email address in
and they send you a link logged in and then it is remembered my login across all
weekend on my main device, which has made me very happy because lots of things don't
do that. And then you're into everything and everything in this case consists of a
lot of kind of web pages and documents and things and also zooms for the individual
program item.
So it's kind of hooking into Zoom's API and that works pretty well.
And also chats everywhere.
And this is sort of instead of discord, but it's not been for me working as well as a
discord does because every individual item and every individual fan table and dealers
table and so on has a chat area.
But you can't kind of look at all the chats and go, ah-ha, those are the places
where chat is happening.
You just have to kind of look at this huge convention and go.
I wonder if there's some chat around here.
So Henry Bailey, if you're listening to this, I'm going to I'm going to give you
this feedback in a very precise way.
I'm going to wrap it around a brick and I don't think it's as good as discord,
but I think it could be as good as discord if Grenadine kind of shifted up a gear
in this direction and actually single sign on is lovely.
It is clearly it is clearly the future, but at the moment it's not quite there yet.
But just got the Bosco and obviously has its its great Bosco and programme and we
have fan funds auction at which we auction many things, not including wete books,
but including a box of rocks, which I thought was a very creative use of the
United States Postal Service's flat rate boxes, which mean that you can take by a
box of a given the size of $50 you can fill it with rocks and send it to anywhere
in the United States.
And lots of other stuff and we raised $1000 for fan funds, including guff, taff,
duff and the otherwise award, which is the award formerly known as the James
Street Junior Award.
And it was a lot of fun.
And then I went to a party and that is why I am completely
discombobulated this morning as we record because I did not get my normal
gentle, peaceful night's sleep before an octal recording session.
I stayed up late and parties instead.
Yeah.
Is that what you want? Was there anything else you wanted to know about Bosco?
Yeah. Are they specific rocks or just generic rocks in a box?
So I believe that when Jerry sends you a box of kipple, that you have won in a
fan fund auction, she has a discussion with you to ascertain your interests.
And then she sends you things that align with your interests from her very large
collection of rocks and other things.
Oh, I see.
No, that sounds nice.
It sounded like literally someone was going to go outside, scoop up a pile of rubble and ship it to you.
I suspect some of the rocks are going to be more interesting than others.
So and the fan fund auction raised a thousand dollars.
That's right. Pretty good.
Yeah.
Nice. Very good.
Very good.
And you were able to auction because you have had problems with your voice at real life
or options, but you don't have those on a microphone.
I understand.
Yeah.
I mean, I feel like I am wondering whether I need to.
I've asked Eastacon whether we can have a fan fund auction at Eastacon and I am
going and obviously we'll be able to do it for this.
For future Easter Colin, for future fan fund auctions, I am going to start to say
to conventions, could you please sort out all of the auctioneers with throat mics
as you do have those things at Eastacons these days?
And I think let's actually take care of ourselves in the future because I was.
Yeah, it was very destructive to my voice.
Now I really used to love auctioning and I had to stop and now I can do it again.
So that's quite nice.
And Marchin and Gillian helped me and Jerry Sullivan put it all together and I am
Martin did all of our backs back of the house account and see and it was great.
We're also running the dead dog for Bosco.
And so this hasn't happened yet, but but the dead dog party at Bosco will be a
fan of his party later today.
So I will be back partying tonight because I'd like nothing.
I like nothing better than partying in the dead of night with people who were five
hours behind me.
So they're all just getting up to having really good fun at the point where I
absolutely positively have to go to bed if I'm to get everything done on Monday.
Liz will probably be familiar with it.
Yes, welcome to my world, Alison.
But if you're very good, you can get up and party with them again in the morning.
Liz can icon.
I think that's the difference between being five hours behind and being seven
hours behind, actually.
Yeah, it does make a difference, although I think I prefer it when it's six because
of the shared daytime hours and we will we will be six again by the time we get
to con which will help.
I believe significantly.
Anyway, that's not really interesting.
Podcast I did not go to Boscon or Capricon precisely because of these time
zone things. Oh, sorry.
Oh, God.
Can we just redo the entire last segment with Bosco?
No, but it's not Boscon either, right?
So Liz said Boscon, but it's definitely not Boscon as a Boscon.
Oh, sorry, because it's got an E on it.
This is why I don't like ease on the end of things.
I'm like in San Francisco, Moscone Center is pronounced Moscone.
So I assume Boscone was pronounced Boscone and then every little I really
thought it's Boscon, but then people say Boscon and it's like make sure that
your cons call the thing that people can pronounce and spell.
Easter con.
Everyone can pronounce and spell it.
That's a plus in branding.
I'm telling you.
I'm really looking for yes to cone.
Yes to go.
Yeah, the problem is that I have only ever seen the Moscone Center written down.
And so I thought it was the Moscone Center.
So here's part of the problem.
OK, so Boscone is called Boscone because it's a reference to the works of E.
Doc Smith. Oh, and he was that old man, which is why they also award the Skylark
Award, which is an award with a very funny story attached to it, which is read out
at the beginning, which is now read out at the beginning of every Skylark Award
ceremony, which was on opposite, which I didn't get a chance to hear yesterday
because it was on opposite the fanfon's auction.
But but but there is a very funny story about the Skylark Award, which is shaped
like a giant lens because it reflects the works of E.
Which are I think fading into obscurity at this point.
And I would have to say rightly so.
I think it's a very good example of work that is definitely worth reading.
If you're interested in the history of science fiction and probably not otherwise
worth your time and fun fact.
E. Doc Smith got married in boys Idaho, which I'm pretty sure is pronounced
boyzy. Boscone happens in Boston, right?
That's why I was thinking they rhymed, but they don't rhyme.
It should be called Boscone. Yeah.
You're you're 100 percent right that it should rhyme. OK, and it doesn't.
OK, so here's what they will have got.
We're a convention in Boston.
We should call it Boscone and someone has said would have said, oh, no, we should
call it Boscone and that's that that will have been very funny at the time when,
which is about 150 years ago, when everybody at that convention would have
been familiar with the works of the E. Doc Smith.
But I just I found it funny that he got married in a town that has a trailing E.
And if we applied this logic, it would be boys, but it is definitely Boise.
OK, I also didn't know that.
So this is the thing we're trailing E's.
I'm just pronouncing all of America wrong.
This is the thing we're trailing E's trailing E's make things hard to pronounce.
They're there and it's it's an unforced error.
It's a shame it is the sort of both Boscone and Capricon are the cons where, you know,
I've heard they are fun and I would have liked to attended them.
But the timing was just not going to work.
So I will they're fun in very different ways.
Oh, yes.
I know they they they they are at the two opposing ends of where
traditional science fiction fandom is at the moment.
My only rant about it is is this it's not good enough.
It's not good enough to have chat attached to items and fan table.
You have to have somewhere we are still failing at the job of helping
people see what what all is going on right now.
Yeah, what you want is to be able to replicate that feeling of wondering
around the con, seeing what's going on.
Yeah.
Easter card.
They've announced they're not using discord or zoom.
Yes, to Kone.
Yes, to Kone have announced that they are not using either discord or zoom, which is
quite funny because they are already using discord.
I have some thoughts about this, which I'm going to quickly outline before you to
get onto this topic, which is when I was going through the punctuation surveys
sent out, which I am currently tidying up for publication, one of the things that
was said by someone was that they felt that they had needed to go to punctuation
in order to be able to attend punctuation.
And one of the things they talked about was they found it all very overwhelming
at the time, but at the end of the convention, they were like, oh, if you did
this again, I'd know how it worked and I'd be able to do it and it would be fine.
And we were aware of that as a problem going into punctuation, which one of the
reasons why we started the discord early and things like that to try and mitigate
this as best we could, but we were aware that that wasn't going to be enough on its
own to mitigate it.
So we were aware that there was going to be an element of this.
But I will also say that one of the reasons I personally was excited to run
punctuation was because I suspected that this would be true of British fans going
to other big British conventions running a similar way.
And so part of why I wanted to run punctuation was to get people used to online
convention platforms so that when they got to say a big convention like an Easter
con using these platforms, they would be less taken aback and more ready to do it.
And so we get on to East con not using the same platforms, which is fine because
I don't think these platforms are perfect.
And I definitely think there's room for improvement.
But what I will say is that no platform in the world is so good that you don't have
to learn how to use it.
There's always some learning curve and it can be a very shallow learning curve,
but it's still there. And so the worry I have is that Easter con is now six weeks
away and they still haven't announced what it is they're using.
They haven't announced what platform is going to be available on.
They haven't announced how we're going to get used to using it.
And I'm a little bit worried about that.
And I think this is a problem.
And I would like to note what extent you to think I'm being a nervous nelly.
I have a point where I start worrying about Easter and the state of the East
con every year, which is Shrove Tuesday.
And it's made easy for me because I the government tells me to eat pancakes.
And so I eat pancakes and start panicking about the Easter con.
That is not till Tuesday, so I've not started panicking yet.
But by the time this episode comes out, I will have started panicking.
So I think it's OK to already talk about panicking.
And when I eat we to fix it.
But I when you eat we to fix it.
Wow.
Damn. Let me try that joke again.
And my tradition, of course, is that I eat pancakes on a show of Tuesday with
filling such as chicken and Nutella, but
and we to fix.
Yeah, now I'm not going to eat we to fix pancakes on Tuesday, but I am going to
consider the matter.
It is a chicken Nutella.
Classic chicken moly pancakes.
It's a very basic chicken moly.
Sorry, a chicken mole.
I'm now wondering if I can make a chicken mole pancake using chicken, using
Marxist, but says Chuckie chicken and Nutella, whether that will actually work,
which it might welcome to the after four pay podcast in which we discuss how best
to abuse trailing ease or words.
I think my point of which I get weird about the Easter con is probably about
like the Tuesday of Easter week, if I'm not otherwise involved.
So it's not a code to me to start being concerned about the Easter con.
You know, this con can stand its own two feet, but I do take John's points.
So I think there's two points.
One is that they are using some other technology, which is not discord or zoom
based, but is going to be good.
This is perfectly possible, but
and it's also possible that since I we last looked around at technologies to use,
which I think I lasted before punctuation, that a bunch more good technologies have
come out that might actually be really great for this kind of thing, because when we
looked at it, a lot of them had, you know, flaws of one kind or another, which meant
they were not really suitable for punctuation.
So it is possible that something else great out there, but I do want to know what it
is. And I think there's a point about a learning curve is very true because for
me, discord has like almost no learning curve.
I logged on to discord and I was like, oh, it's like a modern IRC fine.
You know, you get on with it.
And a day later, I've got the hang of it apart from working out how I could get like
animated emoji or something.
But what punctuation made extremely clear was that not everyone, not everyone
finds it the same, not everyone and found it straightforward to use.
And it was quite off putting to some people.
So I think you're right and that we do need some lead up to know how things are
going to work. And the earlier you get it, the earlier people can start, you know,
working out if they can even log in, working out if it breaks on their phone,
tablets, you know, Unix box from the 1970s, whatever they might be using to log into
it. And the early you tell people what you're using, the early they can sort of
fix all their teething problems because whatever platform we're using, I assume
there are going to be some teething problems.
I just really said what John said, but in more words, right.
So I'm going to say a few things that are different, I think.
So one of them is that there is a thread on Joth, which is the journeyman of
Joth, which is a Facebook group, which we'll link to where somebody whose name
temporarily escapes me, asked, Hey, guys, what's the state of the art in?
I'm paraphrasing here. Hey, guys, what's the state of the art in con running
platforms? And in the subsequent discussion, about a dozen platforms that I
had not previously heard of are mentioned.
So at some point, it's probably necessary to go and have a look at what all of those
are going to do. My experience of Boscode is that the single sign on is lovely,
knowing that there is one place you go and it goes, Oh, yes, your Alison, you're
registered. It's great. Love that bit.
It's not quite doing what I wanted to do for chat, but I feel like that getting
the chat working is an easier problem than getting the video conferencing working.
So that feels quite good. I would like to.
I do think there's a lot further to go in this direction, but trying to making
making the point where you enter the convention seamless clearly solves a whole
big set of problems. And I think that's quite nice.
And I would like to know what Easter comes up to, but I'm sure everyone would.
And we've been promised a video, which if we're lucky might come out before before
we see this. So, so that would be good.
I they did have one.
They've had one video already, which is a discussion between
Vanessa May and I guess head of tech, Keith Smith.
And they kind of told us how marvelous it would be and that we should all join.
But they didn't actually say anything about the technology apart from that it
wasn't zoom and discord, which kind of worries people who've been using zoom
and discord and kind of got the hang of that.
So, so yeah, so I guess that last bit was yes, I also agree with John.
It's going to take time to get people used to this.
But there's probably a discussion about this going over in their discord, which I
confess I have not been to recently.
So I should probably check there.
I asked in the information desk on their discord kind of when we could expect to
hear more about this platform.
Mostly like, you know, I am excited to see what they're doing because if it is
something that does let you do things that is better than the zoom and discord,
then that is fabulous and I am really looking forward to seeing it in action.
And they did in that response say that the next video will have more concrete
details and I think the intention is for that to come out before we release.
So, so yes, hopefully by the time you listen to this, we will have found out and
it will be it will be clear and we can discuss that on the next episode of
Oct though. It's very nice to just put these videos out.
But, you know, if they put the videos out one at a time, then it generates lots
of content, fault to thought. So that's very, very nice.
The really yes, and we can discuss all of their decisions in detail and what we
think about them, which is I think good for everyone for us.
May not be good for everyone.
I can hear some little meows.
Yeah, sorry, Quentin is, Quentin is pretty convinced that people should be
playing with him. And so if you hear meowing on the on the podcast listeners,
then that is a very sad cat who is resenting the fact that both of his
cat parents are doing fanak at the moment and not doing catak.
That was East Carolina. We've done Bosco and we've done baby beans.
So it's on to the hugos, I think.
So last episode, I went away from a recording fully convinced that John and
Liz both watched The Vast of Night, which is a low budget science fiction
movie on Amazon Prime that was that got a kind of selection into the.
There's a thing in the hugos where
works which were technically released in the wrong year, but only got a very
limited distribution, get kind of bumped into Hugo.
Eligibility through a special clause at the business meeting and there were a set
of items that this was done for that included the Vast of Night.
There is a digression here, which is that I think that the Hugo people who do
Hugo things should be thinking about how that can be made automatic.
So that rather than say we have to have a list of these things, so something has
been noticed as falling into this category by the time of the Worldcon.
We can automatically say that something that was only available to a very small
proportion of the world's population automatically gets a second shout if nobody
had heard of it until Amazon picked up the distribution for it.
All that sort of thing.
So the Vast of Night got picked up by Amazon
distribution and is available on Amazon Prime and cost $700,000 to make.
And as a result, it kind of gets a bit graded on a curve because there are a number
of cases when you're watching the film where you think if they had had more money,
this would be a slightly better film.
But I went away thoroughly believing that John and Liz had watched it.
So I watched it and then I listened to the edited, but not quite ready to put out
version of OptiThump and realised that they had not watched it.
And I was completely wrong about that.
So it's a great example of the syndrome of false memories or as or Alison not paying
attention, as we call it.
It's quite a good film.
I would not be unhappy to see it on a Hugo ballot.
I think it is quite slight.
I think it's a subtle though.
It is obviously a science fiction film.
It's actual science fiction content is quite small.
It is using the trappings of science fiction to tell a story that is not about
science fiction.
Primarily, it is primarily a story about
alienation in ways that are not necessarily science fictional and it is it is well
watching, go and see it on your Amazon.
If you have Amazon Prime, if not, go and watch something else.
Don't get Amazon just to watch this movie.
Yeah, agreed.
I have also watched it since last time.
So and so we have started our Hugo eligible watching.
And I am logging them, as I mentioned earlier, on Letterbox.
So so far this year, Fast Might is the only 2020 SF movie that I've seen.
I thought it was good.
I gave it three and a half stars and I gave it a heart.
We all know what that means.
It means I liked it listeners.
I will say, I think that it is sorry.
I'm just doing a small visual joke.
Yeah.
Now listen to making a heart with her hands and Liz is making an atomly accurate
and that's an atomically accurate heart with her hands, which I did not know you
could do and is amazing.
I'm doing I'm doing mini hearts with my thumb and forefinger mini hearts.
I thought you were doing the two chambers with like the pipes coming out and like
ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba ba.
None of this works in a audio medium.
No, it is it is a good shoestring
SF movie.
I did not think it was amazing, but I thought it was solid.
And ultimately solid original SF in the genre of movies is not something that
happens often enough for me to set my nose up at it when it does happen and is
fairly well done.
I don't think the last night is as good as Palm Springs, which is the other 2020
SF normal movie that I have seen and which I will be enthusiastically nominating.
And I am going to watch the color out of space later this very day.
So I will have thoughts about that next time.
Yes, Palm Springs is coming to Amazon Prime later this year.
So if you want to save up your Amazon Prime free trial and use it to watch two
Hugo eligible movies both at once, then you might be able to do that.
Although I don't know whether Palm Springs comes out in time,
denominations, I don't think there's an actual data attached to it yet.
So what was the other film?
The color out of space, which is the Nicholas Cage Lovecraft movie is eligible.
It was extended at the business meeting.
So we will be watching that later today.
It's supposed to be very good.
And what and what streaming service is might we get that one on?
I believe that's also Amazon Prime.
I think as usual outside the UK, your mileage may vary because a lot of stuff,
which is on Netflix or Amazon Prime is on the other service in different countries.
And that's all I really have to say because I haven't actually watched the
best of night or the color out of space or Palm Springs.
Oh, and I've watched Wonder Woman 84 as well.
That's eligible.
We haven't watched that either.
But we did discuss that last time.
We did.
I will say if you but also if you subscribe to Amazon Prime, then you can watch the
Expanse, which is also Hugo eligible.
Although I don't know if you still have to subscribe to Netflix to watch the earlier
seasons, if you haven't already caught on them.
Yeah, I have a problem with the Expanse, which is I have to watch five seasons as
this, don't I?
See previous episodes and TV.
Yes, this is this is a this is a thing we can
relitigate until the cows come home.
But yeah, I think I think it is very clear, Alison, you don't wear
a much lighter version, which is fine, but like we quite like
television.
So that's different.
The expanse is that my friends list has been I nobody spoilt, but my friends
this has been full of oh my god, the end of the fifth season of the expanse.
Oh my god, that's amazing, which I think is I bought it.
It's a hot spot because I'm so clearly there is something about the end of season
five that is that has astonished and and amazed everybody.
And I'm like, that would be like 60 hours.
Yeah, it would be 60 hours to get that point.
So I can see a problem.
I assume the end of sea I send I.
But I assume the big thing that happens at the end of series five is what I think
is I'm not watched series five, I've read the books, which is obviously cheating.
Oh, so there are books like so I could like read books because that would not be 60
hours. Well, there's nine very large space opera books.
Who wrote the James S.A.
Corey, who is actually two people and one of them is Daniel Abraham, whose books
you may have read in terms of reading since last time I have read The Doors of Eden,
which is an Adrian Tchaikovsky book, which is eligible for a Hugo Award.
And I enjoyed it.
It was a little bit long, but I don't think that's necessarily a bad thing.
I have less patients for long books than some other people.
But I still enjoyed it despite the fact it was quite long.
It does take a while to work out what's going on, but in a kind of pleasant,
I wonder what's going on sort of a way.
So that's quite nice, actually.
What else have I read that's eligible?
I've read Harrow the Ninth, which is the sequel to Gideon the Ninth.
I really enjoyed Harrow the Ninth, but it was not clear to me what on earth was
going on until about 70% of the way through the book.
That does seem like quite an adventurous choice, like to have it just really made
not a lot of sense for most of it.
And I kind of want to go back and reread it now that I know what was going on,
but equally I've got a lot of other books to read.
So yeah, but I did enjoy it.
I'm not sure it was as good as Gideon the Ninth.
I don't know whether it'll end up on the ballot.
And I'm currently reading The Ministry for the Future, which makes me very angry
in the way that Kim Stanley Robinson does when he is at his best.
It's an odd book, but I am enjoying it.
I don't know if it'll end up on the ballot because it is an odd book,
structurally, very strange.
I would say I do have a soft spot for books that you read and then, you know,
something happens late on in the book that would put the whole of the beginning
in a different perspective.
I kind of like books where, you know, you there's a value from rereading them
because you get something different out of them, but you do have to temper that
with, yeah, you can't be completely opaque and mysterious for 70% of the book,
or I am going to be annoyed by the time you reveal things unless it's really,
really good.
I mean, like I said, I did really enjoy it.
So yeah, there is that, but I don't know.
Your mileage may vary.
Yeah, because I quite enjoyed Gideon the Ninth, but I wasn't completely
out by it.
And so everything I've heard about Harro the Ninth makes me not want to
immediately rush out and read it.
That makes sense.
Unless I would really like it because it's different than
the Ninth.
This is very complicated.
It is different because it's all from it's from Harro's very different point
of view character to Gideon.
So yeah, yeah.
Yep.
Anyway, what books have you guys read?
I read the space between worlds by Micaiah Johnson,
which is really interesting premise.
So it's set in a world where we have discovered parallel universes and we can
travel to the parallel worlds which are closest to our own in terms of kind
of divergence from our own.
But the twist is you can only travel to a world where your like
doppelganger in that world is not alive.
And so the people who travel between worlds are essentially the people who
have been most likely to die in their other lives and send it with this kind
of interesting set up where there's a rich city and a much poorer town on the
outskirts of the city and it's people from that much poorer town who get pulled
through the traveling between worlds and because a lot of their other selves have
died.
It does really interesting things about like privilege and how in fact the most
privileged in the society can't travel between worlds.
It goes into a lot of stuff about kind of your other selves that have taken
different paths and what they could have become and what people become with
different opportunities.
It took a bit of getting into because it does quite a lot of telling you what's
going on at the start, I feel.
But then there's a few sort of little reveals about maybe 25% the way in that
had me going, oh, that's what's going on.
And then it gets really interesting.
And I think it's kind of it's a standalone book that is very satisfying
ending both in plot terms and also kind of in
kind of in character terms or the characters get to a point which is really
satisfying and interesting.
So yeah, I liked it.
It is probably on my Hugo ballot at the moment.
I still got a lot of other books left to read, but I think I will probably
eliminate that one.
I am reading a lot of books and only a few of them are genre and none of them
Hugo eligible and none of the books I've finished in the last two weeks are
Hugo eligible.
I kind of go must do better, but I think probably because I'm reading
primarily from the library, I'm never ever going to be able to read books
early enough to nominate them for Hugo.
So yeah, well, I've just in TV terms, I have finished the Queen's Gambit,
which is definitely not eligible for Hugo.
It probably gets the nominations anyway, but is based on a book by Walter
Tevis, who is, of course, a genre writer or was a genre writer as well,
and which like the dig is one of these things that loads and loads of people who
are science fiction fans are also watching because it it's kind of genre
adjacent in a weird sort of way despite actually having no genre content whatsoever
apart from, you know, chess, science fiction fans are interested in chess.
Because it's a game for those more interested.
Check out Shut Up Sit Down's recent chess month, which was very interesting.
There's a link you can buy expansions for chess, though.
I think it was Steve Jackson games who wrote an expansion for chess that adds
you have a hand of cards and they let you make your pieces do strange things.
So that's good.
That was the 25th episode of the ultra thought podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from more.
And it's goodbye from me.
You haven't mentioned the letter of
commentary received from Basgar who centers his uncensored bodybuilding newsletter.
And so thank you very much for that, Basgar.
I have clicked unsubscribe with great prejudice.
So sorry, do we have to unsubscribe from
Basgar's uncensored bodybuilding newsletter?
I mean, it's a spam email.
So I think unsubscribe, which just means you get more, doesn't it?
But I don't know.
No, I'd so I so I did unsubscribe and it's MailChimp.
And so he's abusing MailChimp.
And so I clicked on subscribe and clicked the we did not sign up to his mailing
list in the hope that his MailChimp gets limited or something.
Hey, sorry, Basgar.
I'm slightly worried about this because I
I am forever unsubscribing from MailChimp email mailing list because I didn't sign up
to them and it's not it.
They are legitimate mailing list where somebody in America believes that their
email address is my email address because I have a very common name.
Yes.
And if you are the American listener listening, whose name is OctaThaw cast,
please do stop using our email address.
It is not your email address.
It's very annoying.
So what what I assume will happen is if you know,
0.1% of Basgar subscribers click, I never signed up to this.
It'll be fine if 50% keep saying I never signed up to this.
Then yeah, they might tell him knock it off.
So we'll see this podcast will end at the beep.
beep