Hello everyone and welcome to the very 66th episode of Octa Thorpe, the podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom, which is coming to you on the 15th of September 2022.
I'm John Coxen and I am bringing to you a series of recordings we made at Tricon 8.
We didn't have time to record while we were travelling and so we've put this together as a sort of taster of the fanzine lounge for people who couldn't be at the convention itself.
The audio quality is therefore not quite up to our usual standard.
I've cleaned it up as best I can, but there are still some audio artifacts and I will entirely understand if you listen to the first few minutes and decide to wait for next fortnight's episode.
But sit back, relax and enjoy.
[Music]
So I'm here with noted podcast and previous Hugo Award winner, Alison Scott.
I'm so glad you invited me to be on Octa Thorpe today John.
I have been a big admirer of Octa Thorpe ever since, I'd say even before the first episode.
Now that is true.
What I want to talk to you about was the fanzine lounge, which is not so much full of fanzines, but it is not so much lads, but it's still significantly full of fanzine fans.
It has a good, a good watch of fanzine fans in it and we're hoping that will carry on for the whole weekend.
And I'm hoping that I could introduce new fanzine fans to the idea of making fanzines and doing fanzines on our paper.
Oh, bugger.
We have the beads of production.
I've got to make my good thing.
And we have to make our work, yeah we're going to do, I've told.
When is that happening?
I've told Nigel, well, Sunday morning to 11.
I said, so therefore, Nigel, when do you need my contribution?
I said Sunday morning to 11.
So you'll be doing your contribution at half past ten on Sunday.
So if anyone, if anyone was at Worldcon at half past ten on Sunday and saw Alison,
Matt Lee typing, you now know why that was.
So why, what is on your head?
Oh, on my head right now is.
Because you are the hardest friends.
I've learned from the best.
I'm an incisive interview.
How am I supposed to talk?
Because I cannot see the top of my head.
Yeah, that's bad.
I have to.
I could.
Yes, you could.
You could look at your phone.
But I have.
Well, tell me first what's on your arm or what was just on your arm.
Indeed, indeed.
This is our.
Oh, wow.
Is it extreme?
It's kind of like a smack bag.
What's the product type?
I was a bottle.
Yeah, so so Alison is holding a Google grey polyester fleece tote that we got because we are Hugo award finalists.
Oh, yeah, we got the Hugo one finalist got all over smack this year.
Yeah.
And the swag was very excited.
This was came in this big bag, which is the bag that I'm currently holding.
It says that's very useful for cutting your shirt around the Worldcon.
Yeah.
And inside that bag, what was inside the bag?
Inside.
So inside the sort of sturdy, fairly rigid polyester feast tote bag was a non sturdy.
Actually, no, probably steady, but not rigid.
Google branded gym bag made if I would say cotton.
And what was inside that bag, Alison?
Inside that bag was a kind of very compact nylon bag that falls out to be quite a useful bag size with zips.
But it's actually very small inside.
And so that was another bag inside the bag that was inside the bag.
And inside that bag was only trite-based, stressful.
Yeah, and a flask.
And a flask.
And inside the flask is coffee if you're just excusing it.
For the benefit of the recording, Alison is abandoning me for coffee.
It is quite nice.
It's not actually not looked at the flask.
It's solid solid.
I haven't opened the box.
It's like, and it's also cold.
And yeah.
Yeah.
No, I mean, actually I recently broke of that.
So having a replacement is a good thing.
And I don't know whether so.
So for those who don't know, the Hugo finalists sometimes get,
or often I would say get a party favor from the next world's con who traditionally hosts the post award reception or the Hugo Losers party.
Chengdu is hosting that reception.
I don't know whether they will do party papers.
They may well.
I think it's too likely given that they've done party favors for everybody at the convention.
I think the chances there won't be a party favor for us is quite small.
Taff delegate, Fia, has just brought up.
Taff, Fia Carlson.
She has blue hair and a blue top and has several ribbons.
I recognize some of these ribbons.
Would you two like to have a ribbon pissing contest?
I know.
I celebrate all ribbons.
It's not a competition.
But obviously, I ain't clogging.
Hold them up, back to back.
Only two.
Fia is applying another ribbon.
All she's applying a Glasgow ribbon.
And a Seattle to a Twitch fan.
I haven't got the Seattle ribbon yet.
I asked Chengdu if they had ribbons and they said no.
So I have not got Chengdu ribbon.
Chengdu don't have ribbons.
No. They have ribbons for being a Hugo voter.
I put that on my badge.
Fia, would you like to say things into the microphone?
We are.
So you can be on book to thought.
Book to thought.
Sure.
How has your Taff trip been so far?
Oh, it's been amazing.
I have seen almost all of the East Coast and I've seen Wales.
I've seen the Minnesota State Fair and I am very, very happy
with everything that I've done.
All the people that have met, you know, it's been amazing.
And you have tinsel in your hair.
Yeah.
Which matches your hair, which is lovely.
Yes.
And we have Jerry Sullivan, who is taking a picture of Alison and Fia.
Jerry also has tinsel in her hair.
There was actually a Estonian band that put the tinsel on.
Are we podcasting as we speak?
Yes, Jerry, you are now on octopole.
I love being on my picture.
The science fiction and science fiction fandom.
And I should probably give you a ribbon if you are on the board.
So ribbons will happen.
That's probably me.
Fia will overtake me when I give her this ribbon,
which I think tells you how much I value.
Whoa.
Thank you.
There we go.
So yes, what is on my head, I remember now, is a...
Jesus Christ.
I thought you were being funny.
I didn't think you genuinely forgotten.
LAUGHTER
Is that that?
Which a friend of Jerry's who I don't know, gave me?
Jean Mealy.
Yes, Jean Mealy.
He gave me.
Which says bison fuddy and has...
Metal kind of bison conservation herd.
Yeah, and it kind of has bisony bits.
I mean, it's not quite like a moose, but it's definitely kind of horns.
And I love that stuff, Matiara's.
But...
Elizan is a bit horny.
LAUGHTER
Bison is very horny right now.
Listen, if you could see her, you'd know how horny she was.
I think you might want...
Are we going to put some photographs into this?
Can I go up the look?
You chapped her out.
I feel like...
Is there anything else you'd need to tell us?
Would you like to be Baudie too, Fia?
Yes.
I grew up acting as a man.
Elizan is currently making Fia horny.
Um...
L'etel, do you feel to tell what to thought about what Consilans got going on at World
Con
We plan to show some of the panels that we've recorded virtually so you can relive the experience.
Um, we'll have posters of all of the exhibit space that we had.
We'll be providing at least in some cases some of our famous chocolate and we're hosting
a thank you party.
It's just really a kind of a taster of the things that we would have done.
And there will be this throne of key we use on which you can sit.
The throne of key we use.
Yes.
You know, in the same style as Game of Thrones.
So like the throne of swords.
Yes, like a throne of swords.
It's a thing, it's this one, softer.
And it's a throne of key we use.
Yeah, no, I definitely want to sit on the throne of key we use.
Yes.
And what's more is that key we love to travel as you can tell by the fact that I'm here.
At.
Go on, you'll remember there.
I got it.
I'm sorry.
I'm not going to be doing three hours of sleep.
There is nothing left in this thing.
That's amazing.
Thank you ever so much for the bell.
But what I would say is that yes, the throne of key we use on which one can sit is that
because key we use love to travel.
You can take one home.
Please, please take one home.
Right.
They are they human New Zealanders.
Kiwi birds or Kiwi fruit.
Kiwi birds.
They are soft Kiwi birds.
They are.
Okay.
So you.
That is very tempting.
I will be doing that.
Well, just sit on a soft Kiwi and then take one of the Kiwi's home.
They're being attached or wires.
So they can be removed and taken home.
Excellent.
I think I have a Kiwi from a previous convention that was like to cling on to your lanyard.
I think we've still got one of those at home.
Somewhere.
I saw it recently.
It was definitely around.
But you moved recently, didn't you?
No.
I think we took it with us.
I don't think it went.
Look, I mean, some things did go, but not that.
Yes.
That was special.
And they, Kiwi's are special.
Yes.
You do know that they only come out at night.
I did not know that.
No, they are not too.
Ah, okay, okay.
And you have to be extraordinarily quiet in order for them to come out and.
So where is the throne of Kiwis?
Ah, the throne of Kiwis will be in the Konsieland, Connor box tomorrow.
Is that during the day or during the night?
During the day from one o'clock to nine o'clock tomorrow.
So all the Kiwi will be asleep.
Yes.
Okay.
That means that I'm glad that I won't be sitting on an awake Kiwi.
No.
I feel that would be, uh, disrespectful.
Disrespect.
Indeed.
So, Chuck, you are a Hugo Award Finalist.
For the sixth time.
A nice.
And so you have been nominated for your work on Journey Planets.
Yes.
For, uh, some co-editing with our friend Mr Garcia.
So for those who don't know, Journey Planets is a fan-zine.
If you've heard the song Old Fan-Zine, you're familiar with some of the folk tradition around
fan-zines.
So which, uh, issue did you co-edit, Chuck?
I was co-editor on the King Arthur issue, which led me here this year.
Oh, I really love that.
I also did some reviews of, uh, different modern takes on the King Arthur legend.
Oh, yep, yep, yep.
Once in future, I looked at once in future.
I looked at, um, Libby Tedars.
Very, very twisted interpretation of the Arthur legends with quite wonderful.
And, uh, just basically concluded that, um, Arthur is going to morph, uh, to suit his
purposes to specific times.
Yeah.
And things within specific times.
Historicity.
Yeah.
Two different Arthurian things, or maybe three on the ballot this year, right?
'Cause Tracy Dion is nominated in astounding for her.
Oh no, maybe...
Now I think it's astounding, but maybe loads that I can't remember.
Sorry listeners, uh, for her Arthurian kind of urban fantasy series.
And, um, obviously there's the Green Knight starring Dev...
It's out.
Not...
Yeah, Dev...
There was at least one last year or two, I think, in the YA, right?
Yes, yeah, that was Tracy Dion again.
Again, so yeah.
Um, but yeah, seems to be very popular, so I like it.
We're contemplating maybe doing a follow-up about Robin Hood.
Oh!
Looking at that from the counseling.
For Americans who don't know, Robin Hood is King Arthur's son.
Ah!
The one he doesn't talk about.
Yeah.
Who is one in the Green Knight?
The one that should have got the attention other than the one that did.
You know what I'm saying?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
He's, uh, King Arthur's other son was Jesus, and he gets a lot of the, uh, a lot of the
raves.
I think I've got this right.
Yeah, I think you're...
There's no mythology, so weird.
I think your scholarship is dead on there.
Yeah.
Uh, emphasis on the dead.
Uh, but yeah, no.
Jenny Planet, so you're gonna win?
I hope so.
Aang!
One of these years.
Yeah, you know, really, really my philosophy is I'm just having fun.
Yeah.
I'm going to collaborate with Chris Garcia.
And, you know, you and I have gone to parties together many a year now.
Yeah, yeah.
For these things.
We've been co-finalists together a couple times, even though now we're in separate camps
I guess this year.
But no, competing.
Not competing.
We're in different categories.
That is correct.
Um, but for me it's just a, it's just kind of good fun to communicate.
Yeah.
We're gonna talk, Alison and I are gonna talk about that tomorrow afternoon in five fanzines.
You know why people can get involved in them, why they should get involved in them.
Uh, how it helps facilitate communication and fandom.
Yeah.
And, um, yeah.
So I'm just, I'm not really award minded.
I'm really kind of right in on Chris Garcia's coattails to tell the truth, you know.
Because Journey planned as you know is one huge village and they're very insistent on
including everyone that provides editorial content during the year within the general
umbrella of finalists.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
No, and like working with Chris and James is amazing because they have so many ideas,
so much energy.
And it's nice to kind of like tap into that.
It's almost like, I feel like it must be like when you hook a house up to the national group
for the first time and you just get like all that electricity.
That's a fan.
Well, spend you did a cover, did a cover for one of our, really, our drink tank.
Cause I also wrote them on drink tank.
And she put both, she did very nice illustrations of the both of us.
And Chris was hovering in the air and having grand plans about taking over the world.
And I'm standing down on the ground going, no, no, something like, no, no, I need to bring
him to earth.
I need to concentrate that energy in a very much described relationship.
So she's been paying attention.
Ah, yeah.
So you know what people sometimes say, where do you get your ideas from?
The answer is, Chris and James.
I mean, they have a lot of ideas.
They have a lot.
They do, they do.
They do.
And they often ask us for ideas and we go, what do you think?
Yeah.
Well, that's how I got to edit my first study plan.
Like Chris and James were like, we want to do a Star Wars issue and they brought a couple
of people on for someone like, had to bow out and I ended up doing layout because Chris
had some stuff going on.
And then because most of the time Chris does layout, but the ones I've edited, I've done
layout to give him like some time.
And also because I like doing layouts.
He loves doing layouts.
Yeah.
And he loves doing the art.
He doesn't love doing the copy editing and the wordsmithery at all.
And he just came to me and said, work with me, you know, because I think our skills with
the mesh wall together, you can do the wordsmith and the copy editing and I'll go do the
stuff I like, you know, so quite a deal.
Yeah.
Well, that's kind of how collaboration works really.
Absolutely.
That's how the collaboration works a lot to look.
I took bollocks and John edits it.
Yes, that is correct.
And Liz gives us accurate content that is, you know, worth listening to.
And we basically fill in around Liz's golden nuggets.
I think.
Wow.
I'm pretty sure.
So Liz, when you hear this, let me know if you agree with that analysis.
Because you'll be hearing this in the edit.
Hi, Liz.
So you're John Clarkson editor to the bolsters.
Something like that.
Edit so much to the what?
Bolsters.
Is that a bullet?
Well, he is one of the bullet providers, I think.
Yes.
I provide both of the bollocks of.
So you're both a provider editor.
I'm like, they are just one of the blokes.
Okay.
I'm one of the blokes I have been referred to by.
But he is seeming more than this one.
As one of the blokes.
And I don't know who the other bloke is.
But I'd love to meet him.
Other bloke, if you're listening, please get in touch.
Show up for a podcast.
Yeah.
Other bloke.
God.
This is the first time we've had multiple bollocks on our own.
No, this is the first time we've had more than two bollocks on our own.
Oh, you'll get nothing but bollocks for me.
So you're in good shape today.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think that's right.
Because we've had every.
Yeah, we've had one.
Oh, no, one Nicholas Williams appeared in the background.
No, no, no, no, no.
And we did have quite a lot of interjection from the audience at Easter.
I think you'll find we had quite a lot of ejaculations from the audience.
I think that might be right.
You're lowering the tone again.
No, I wouldn't.
Yeah, you won't.
To be fair, we did start with you being morning, so long.
Expectioned, a noted podcaster has arrived.
Have I arrived?
I mean, in my heart and in my vicinity, yes.
So you haven't mentioned the fact that in this era of COVID, we don't have to worry
about plosives or.
Yeah, we're all wearing pop filters.
Yeah, it's great.
Everyone is so audio ready at this invention.
I don't know what.
But every time I meet anyone, it's like you're already wearing your pop filter.
It's pretty on so many levels.
I should have happened years ago, although I haven't ever done recording a podcast.
Although I did get interviewed by Chris Garcia for the hard copy podcast, which was only
available on cassettes.
Yes, I have some more.
I ripped all of them to MP3s to make a boot there.
He hates that.
I know.
And then I sent them to him to spite him.
Over and over again.
Oh, you're big.
I am.
He keeps them all too.
Hi, Chris.
No, I was just waving at the microphone, which in this case is Chris.
Rick is also a fan cast person.
And you have a panel this week.
I'm out on a podcast called fanboy.
Yeah, fanboy.
So I really feel like you've still each stolen parts of my podcast.
So can you tell me about your podcast?
We've been doing it for about 700 episodes.
And for a while, we were doing it along with the BBC, actually.
Oh, no.
It's the late license show over here on the BBC.
That was my-- the owner of fanboy's line, the other in chief, Derek McCall.
And we basically-- you start off by just getting together and doing a live podcast in a comic
book shop on the drop day of the week when we moved to Mutsra.
Oh, that's a really good idea.
Yeah, yeah.
It's a really good idea.
I really did.
I did 700 episodes ago, John.
Yeah, yeah.
We don't do it that way anymore.
I love ambient sound.
I love background sound.
It makes it a little hard to edit because you can really tell where they come.
It really does make a difference, especially things about context.
But if you're listening to something where you expect the background noise and it isn't
there, it's very, very off-putting.
So it's weird.
And that's why at the beginning of this episode, we have like the warnings saying there's ambient
noise because I'm sure some of you listeners are experiencing that in reverse right now
because usually we are in pristine recording studios.
We all have an extension to our house, which is--
You have like baffle boards all over the place.
I'm sure there's strategic like ways to--
Yeah, yeah, definitely.
And obviously later we'll go to Walgreens and get a bunch of egg boxes and like staple
them to things to like further dead in the noise.
I know they'll be plastic in the US, won't they?
I don't know if that would work.
I once saw a guy who had to do voiceover work, he was in a hotel room and he couldn't
find a good place to record his voiceover stuff because you want nothing in the background.
But he ended up taking a sofa, standing it on its end, putting the cushions up against
the walls we had like this little concave fiber box.
Yeah.
And it worked.
I mean if I need to record in a hotel room, I feel like I would just get a duvet and
drape it over myself.
But like I think the sofa solution is more elegant if you have a sofa.
Yes.
So John, how thoroughly do you get to customize your lightsaber?
Do you get to customize every little bit of it?
Or is it just like there's like 10 different lightsabers and you get one at once?
Have you done it as well?
I know.
Yeah.
So you get Liz Barry noted podcaster has joined us.
Liz, do you want to tell us a bit about your voiceover?
A bit about yourself?
Hello.
Is Darcy your question?
I'm Liz.
I'm going to get closer to Mike.
I've got a terrible microphone.
There's a blend.
Sometimes I do a podcast.
What's your podcast called?
It's called Octa Thor.
I don't know.
That's the same as ours.
That's the microphone when you say that Liz.
Come on now.
Don't you just get, don't just days at John.
Look, I've got to tell, I've got to tell the listeners that I'm basically being very distracted
here because Alice and is wearing a vise and hat.
She is horny.
I've remarked to fond this for the podcast.
But Alice and then made fear horny.
Would you like me to make you horny as well Liz?
I'm good.
It's a thank you.
This is going to be a brilliant edit job for you.
I'm just going to let you know that's fantastic.
But yeah, on the subject of lightsabers, you choose one of four themes and they are protection
and justice, power and control.
Is this sort of spoiler for the lightsaber experience?
Well, not really because you have to choose it themed before you go into the room.
I can't remember what the others are, but there are four.
Basically, they can be roughly split into a prequel type blade, which is a very old
public art deco style, an original trilogy/sequel style, which is much more kind of industrial
looking, and then a kind of dark side style, which is blacks and very, very sleek.
And then a kind of elemental style where you can, if you want, have a rank or two on the
end, which is dope.
And then you choose from pieces from that theme.
What's really awesome about it is it's very authentic to the Jedi culture and that you
go on a web page ahead of time and choose all these side unseen and they deliver all
the pieces not unlike that you would get your food into cafeteria set before you and
then assemble.
Yeah.
And it was fun.
I liked it a great deal.
I mean, I assume, so like, did you do it at Orlando or at LA?
We didn't know our essentials here.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
No, that makes sense.
I assume it's like, I don't actually know because I've not been to both yet, but the
attentive listener will notice the use of the word "yet" in that sense.
But I assume the parts are carbon copies of one another.
I assume that they're...
The same.
Every reason believe what they are.
So by an interesting scene.
But yeah, no.
And you kind of like get a man at the front in our case who does a kind of almost like
a one man show and it's all very well acted and set dressed and there's music and lighting.
Very special and safe route.
Yeah, it's very good.
And he said with, what did he say?
We tell that our eyesabers and he's like, "These are weapons and they are powerful
weapons and with great power comes a need not to drop great power on the ground."
Yes.
And we were like, "That is a good point.
So you also get a very, very phone case to put your basically 36 inch light bulb attached
to a heavy bit of metal on so that it does not break."
You wear it on your back all the way the rest of the day in the park and who looks like
they're going fly fishing?
Yes.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And you get a pin?
You get a free pin?
Great.
And it's a strange new meaning for what I was not previously familiar with.
How much do we cost in Orlando?
That's 220 plus tax.
Whoa, it's gone up.
But that's why you should do it in Orlando because sales tax is low.
Well, it's okay.
It's like, with my buy nothing it has to hold you.
Oh no, it's a wall decoration.
So it'll take almost no room.
My son got the dark saber.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, because you can get like free-built versions that are actually from the cannons.
Yes, sir.
I'm sat here with Perry Minow is noted Australian fan, podcaster, past WorldCon chair and wearer
of excellent t-shirts.
How are you, Perry?
I'm very well, thank you very much.
On the live.
Hey! Which is a bit of a shock after 29 hours.
And for those who don't know, Perry is one of the two co-hosts of the two chairs talking
broadcast.
Yes, poor old David's not here, but he's not travelling very much these days.
So there we go.
I think we've mentioned it previously.
We have definitely mentioned the class don't stop, yes.
Yes, you have.
Thank you very much.
Much appreciated.
And it's a really good format because it's like kind of a very kind of world-comprospective
on the science fiction canon and kind of what's kind of coming out and things like that,
which I really like.
And Perry also does a fancy.
Yes, I do.
You can probably get hold off by, I don't know, googling Perry Middle and it's a following.
Well, it's all on the tour on Efansines.com, of course.
We should choutefansines.com.
Yes.
One of the great, fan-ish websites in history.
Yeah.
So Bill Burns isn't at this convention, but if we do the Sogality's to come, which doesn't
sound like a totally different idea, Bill will be there and we can do it.
Oh, yeah, just talk to him.
Yeah.
You'll be there for his.
He's very good.
And good as they would be.
Yes.
He stays in my house every year when Bill and Mary come to UK and they stay with us
in the week.
And we absolutely love it because I kind of sit bill down and I go, "So what's new is
it's called?"
The class of the tables.
And he tells me like, "There's just seven fascinating stories about the way in which
fits the metal, the managed of the ocean."
Well, he's got the whole lot.
He's got, he's a central point.
Just saves all of us massive amounts of time and energy being able to deposit it if you
want to use that term.
At the fans' hands, he makes it all available.
People can just download it for free.
And at the same time, he's like, "I quite like the software, port and our transcripts."
And I quite like the use of the word deposit because I feel like Evandines is in some
way the library of record for San Spectrum Bandum.
So you deposit your artefact with them in much the same way you do with the British
Library if you're a novelist.
So that makes me happy.
Well, one of the things that is interesting about Australia is that if you produce a publication
like a small fanzier like I do, I have to deposit a copy of it into the National Library.
And so I have to put a copy in there.
And once it goes into the National Library of Australia, it gets spread around to the
other state libraries as well.
So they can all pick it up.
So there's extra copies there.
The good thing about this thing is that back in the 70s and 80s, everything was very ephemeral.
It all disappeared.
And now it's all available forever.
Yeah.
Noted fan and Fandy Van James Baker has arrived.
Oh, another ex world god chair.
Hello James.
Ex Worlde.
And Fandy editor and Hugo Award finalist.
Thanks, John.
Thanks, Alison.
And how are you?
Very.
Great to see you here at the Worlde Khan in Chicago.
Indeed.
We do a load of VoxPods that we're going to register to a podcast later.
That's fantastic.
And James has a medal that says, "Try on a committee."
That's right because I'm on the committee here, unfortunately, for my sins.
I volunteered.
I have not yet learned not to volunteer.
You've done your time.
Yeah.
You've been a chair.
That's it.
I mean, it's time to come back and do it twice.
Yeah, exactly.
And that's it.
I'm not doing it anymore.
I've done a couple of people who have done it twice.
So, bin stockety, very middle miss.
Yes.
Nicely used to crack.
Yeah.
Colin Harris.
Two older people.
I mean, when I say older, I mean going back for a...
Way back.
Yeah, for like a little cotch.
No, I don't think so.
Oh, I remember I just remember I just remember this four.
There was one guy that did it twice on his own.
His chair.
His old chair.
Mine.
And what did one chair on my own and one cotch chair?
Yeah.
OK.
So that's a great anecdote that you can better...
If you can round that and get the right decals.
Listen, it's a hook for comments.
It's a great hook for lots.
It is.
So James, why don't you next one then?
Yeah, so I would have liked to have chaired at a little roll time because the first one
is very existential.
You know, you approach it learning so much and not knowing.
Yeah, yeah.
So it's quite an interesting challenge.
You're deploying new skills every 10 minutes and you're trying to learn and understand and
comprehend and, you know, reflect on your own mistakes as you proceed ahead at such high
speed.
Yeah.
And I think the second one next will be based on experience.
But what Vincent Daugherty has said to me is that, you know, also you're experienced
and therefore you sort of realize that the effort, time and energy it takes is not in
substantial.
No.
You know, there were certain things I did to be a World Cup chair for me.
So I lost weight.
I tried to be fit.
I tried to make sure that my fitness levels were fine.
They're not sort of at the necessary pace.
OK, thanks.
That's kind.
Not that in any way this is about me.
So this was about me becoming fit because obviously I had known some people previously
who were unwell and my own father had his first heart attack when he was 38.
Yeah.
So bearing in mind that I was past that threshold and I was approaching the age where he had
a quadruple bypass, fitness was important to me, which is mad.
But when you're working on a World Cup for maybe 16 hours in a day, you need that sort
of energy.
Well, it's good to have that extra bit in the back pocket and I was in charge of that
so it was good times but hard work.
Would I do it again?
Yes, I would love to this week.
No.
That's fair.
I mean, that is reasonable.
See, I told you, if you do a World Cup, you become a World Cup chair, send your man.
So mad that you think you could actually approach another one.
That's how mad you become.
It does remind me of the way people talk about shoulders, actually.
Probably right.
So, but there is a WN-239 bit.
Yes.
So you must be very excited about it.
Oh, super excited.
And I think that's one of the greatest things about being a World Cup chair.
It's not that the World Cup was a good time.
You know, we got a few things wrong.
We got thousands of things right.
It's the way it works.
But I hope that the team who were very full of enthusiasm and who really enjoyed running
the World Cup go on now and I can maybe give them a couple of pointers, at least tell them
not to try to make the mistakes I made and watch them go on and succeed in 29.
And Brian Neswitt and Marguerite Smith are running down at the moment.
And basically, it's early days.
It's a long way away.
But they're following the similar path that 2019 had.
So they're, they've obviously got a timeline in mind.
And I'm really enjoying watching on and not really doing too much.
Yeah.
And it's great for everyone in Europe to have more European World Cups.
Like I think it's really good to have Ireland and Finland kind of joining the community
of countries that can kind of, you know, run a convention maybe every decade.
And then you get that kind of much more international flavour to the convention.
So it is amazing.
And it's really, really good.
Yeah.
So it's really quite interesting.
As a smart con, we did a little exercise to see ten other venues around the world which
could work including Lisbon.
And you know, one of the venues we didn't look at was the venue that Capcom were looking
at.
And that was quite amazing.
So the idea that there could be a Ugandan World Cup which in its Rome right will face
challenges.
You know, they will have their own challenges to deal with.
But the idea of the concept of an African World Cup is very exciting.
And as we know now, we have a number of beds hopefully coming from the continent which
is vast.
It's a huge place.
Like Ireland is the same size as Maine.
And then alone, you know, so you know, there's a wonderful potential there.
So yeah.
I think that's great.
And I look forward actually to watching helping a little bit and watching Albert Glasgow.
Watching people develop and it's really fun.
And then Brisbane is bidding for 2028, Perry.
I believe so.
Yes, that's correct.
And you're not caring for a third time.
You're not going to be becoming the third first person to do.
I am absolutely not cheering.
I would not have a life nor would I have a marriage left.
I think I decided to go down that path.
So no, I've done my dash, I think.
Time for other people to do that.
Plus, I'll be in my 70s and two or more.
It's one of those things that it's not necessarily a really young person's game.
But you've got to be, as James was saying, you've got to be in that period where you're
not only physically but pretty mentally fit as well.
You start getting up in your 70s and now you start to fade.
And you know, you're...
It's a bit like a game.
Yes.
You need the experience and managerial experience with people and projects to be able to do
it so you need enough level of that.
Yeah.
But you don't want to go so far that you're so stuck in the mud, you don't want to change.
And that's where things...
My aim is to go from being too young to chair a world con to too old to chair a world con
without ever going through the middle bed.
That's an interesting...
I think it's an excellent choice to do everything.
Am I allowed to say damn you?
Thank you very much to Harry and James to chair Storke.
Hello again everyone.
It's John back in England again with his Good Mike and the lack of audio artifacts.
I hope you enjoyed that short taste of Tricon 8 and I will see you next week for the next
episode of OctaThorp.
But until then, it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from everyone else who talked to us
in this episode.
[Music]
Stephen has very kindly brought coffee for which I'm very grateful.
Thank you Stephen.
He'll hear this later when it goes out.
Because we didn't say thank you when he actually brought the coffees because we were brought
up badly.
Sorry mum and dad.
You raised me better than that.
I kind of nodded at him.
Which is, you know...
Surely being married to you is thanks enough.
Like I feel like I should have said thank you but you probably imply...
Wait, look at him in a small drink.
A smoldering.
I was horny, look.
Oh yeah, for this is what I'm doing.
That's what I'm doing.
And now the chronology of these recordings.
Alison is still horny.
She was up going off bison on him.
Yup.
Indeed.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod in Comprotec.com.
Used under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beat.
[BLANK_AUDIO]