Hello everyone and welcome to the very 77th episode of Octa Thorpe. This episode is coming
to you on the 16th of February 2023 and if you're on the way to the UCU picket line
solidarity comrades. I'm Jon Coxon, I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty and we have some
letters of comment. We've got a toot, a tweet and an email. What's the difference between
a talk and a talk? I don't know Jon what is the difference between a talk and a talk?
It wasn't a joke, I just think we need different acronyms for toot and tweet. A talk and a
talk, a toot and a tweet. And we need them toot tweet. Oh dear. That wasn't where I was
going with that but staying in the edit. Boom. It's fine. Raj messaged us to let us know
that they are going to write a proper lock later but they loved the episode art for number
76. That was done by my wife, Ispania. I will pass on your compliments Raj. And it
was a very good picture of three groundhogs which look suspiciously like us looking at
their shadow and I did not get it at all. I did not understand it. I had to look at it
several times and eventually ask Jon what it meant and he told me. Oh I also didn't get
it till later but why I very cleverly put the title and the alt text in the show notes
so that people would read the show notes and be like oh I bold of you to assume that people
read the show notes Jon. That is true. It's true. But all of you just assume that I read
the show notes Jon. Also it provoked Alison to come up with a joke because it is said
that if the three of us see our shadows on Groundhog Day it means we'll have to talk
about China on the podcast every fortnight until the end of the year. For shadowing. But
don't fish. We also heard from Hugo Girl. Firstly Hugo Girl mentioned us in their most
recent episode or possibly the second to most recent episode depending on when you listen
to this listeners about weird crisps and Amy and Haley have volunteered to try full haggis
so that's exciting. They're like we love some awful and I'm like cool that's good.
And also I mentioned to Laurie who does their audio transcripts that we have started doing
transcribing with whisper and you can do this as well. I will put a link in the show notes
to the GitHub repository that I'm using. They got into a discussion on Twitter about
this so it's worth noting we're using the C++ port of whisper which means instead of
being limited to transcribing it to X speed you can do a full 45 minute episode of Octo
Thorpe in like three minutes which is quite useful so I tuned through all of our episodes
and now we can like search when we said things like China or Guff which is useful. I've used
it at least once already but if anyone wants any tips on how to use this software do to
me. Sounds rude than tweeting you for some reason. Yeah two me listeners. We'll get used to it.
It's like the fart signal. We also heard from Christopher J. Garcia who signed his email
Chris who is also apathetic about things having meaning so that was like the best end off
to an email. Chris says that there is both haggis and vegetarian haggis in a can. We
Mexicans are not barbarians Chris says we eat our brains and lungs in soup which fair
he also says I'm wrong because gurps is the one true way. When are you running a gurps
campaign then Chris get on it. You told me why gurps was rubbish and it was completely
compelling I totally agreed with you. Yeah you were right I only liked gurps because it
was the 80s then. Also it rhymes with burps. I wasn't sure if anyone would have one in
the tank. Oh I'm glad you did. Always always. Liz must remember not to mess with the time
screens as the clock is running at both ends. So Liz don't do that. I will not do that.
Having started burping I can't stop so I may be a while. What have I done? I would like
to pull out some random quotes from Chris's letter James Mason is basically a beard that
delivers lines from a script. And I'm also creating a museum about things of my life
Thank you Chris. It should be good. I would go to the Museum of Christopher J. Garcia.
I've been to Chris's house which I imagine would be similar. I bought tacos. There's
a good taco place near Chris's house. There used to be good Chinese food near Chris's
house but firstly that Chinese restaurant went away and secondly he moved and those two
things conspire to mean that is no longer true but the peanut dumplings were the best
Chinese food I ever ate in my entire dang life. I was very tired I was on my tough trip.
It was great.
Shall we discuss Chida because we saw our shadows?
Specifically we're discussing Chengdu right we're not discussing the entirety of China.
That is true we're discussing Chengdu. Did you hear this light note of worry in Liz's
voice there that we might somehow get comfortable? We don't have much to talk about China this
week. What we do have is a post by Dave McCarty on Facebook that Liz found.
I mean my point is if we're talking about you know if we're talking about like you know
the Denver Worldcon we don't say this week we're going to talk about America like it is not a monolith.
Would you like me to do my joke again?
But this is my point I don't know it just feels a bit weird to say we're going to talk about China
when we know we're not going to talk about a billion people we're going to talk about the
Worldcon. Yes no fair enough. I will now proceed to tell you about Dave McCarty so rather Dave McCarty
on Facebook here's the Hugo Administrator for Chengdu and he said they're in the process of testing
nomination page should be readied by the end of February and given that the dates have moved
October nominations will stay open through the end of April and then voting on the ballot will
happen in June so that all sounds well and good. Why is this announced on Dave McCarty's Facebook
page and not like the Chengdu official Facebook page or any other any other forms? Who knows but
it is nice to have some of you so thank you Dave. I guess it would have been as accurate to say
that we were going to discuss Chicago. For those who don't know Dave McCarty lives in Chicago.
It's not a funny joke even if you know that but it's much less funny if you don't so
might go to negative fun. Well done. I'm rocking it this week but yes thank you very much Liz. No
I mean it is good to know however I agree with everything Liz said. I'm going to snip that out
and keep that on a soundboard for later. Yep. So yes we should have nominations opening fairly soon.
Fingers crossed. And from that we can seamlessly segue into discussing what we're going to nominate
for the Hugh Goes. Now this week we're going to mostly focus our best dramatic presentation
short form on account of how we're all under red crocodiles. Is that fair? It's fair I feel I need
to I have a wider selection of you know stuff I have read to think about then I have things that I
could plausibly nominate in dramatic presentation I think. So yes basically yes. Liz is less
troggler.ie. It's not less troggler than you. I haven't started my pre-dobulation reading yet but
I have watched them telling. Thank you Renee and the many volunteers who put stuff in the big spreadsheet
of things that are eligible for the Hugh Go awards. It's really helpful when it comes to try and
remember what year anything was released in and how long things were and whether like queering
whether things are actually eligible or not. So thank you very much. Who wants to go first?
John pick one and then I'll pick one how about that and we can go round for a lit. A draft!
A draft! Alright we're going to draft listeners. The way this works is we're all going to pick one
and we can't pick one that someone else picked and we're going to put the draft picks in the show notes
at the end. Okay. Ah and I go first. Fuck this is a lot of responsibility. Well I've got to pick
something that is good because I can save my crap picks for after Liz has gone because she won't
pick any crap because she's Lady of discernment. I've only got like three picks as well so. So do I
go for what I think is the slam dunk? I'm going to go for one that I think I think this might win
and I don't know whether I think it should win but I think it's got a very good chance of winning
and that is Babylon's Ashes from season six of The Expanse which is the finale of that season and
is a 2022 work. I think it will be on the ballot even if I don't nominate it and I think it has a
very high chance of winning this category as the Kappa 2 basically six seasons of Delhi and also I
think the Expanse has done okay in short form previously but yes I will pick Babylon's Ashes.
Has it won? Has it the Expanse ever won a Hugo? I think it has but I might be wrong.
I thought did it not win last year? Nemesis Games won in 2022 and that is the only other
Oh and Leviathan wakes won in 2017 and those are the other two times the Expanse won in best
dramatic presentation short form. So Leviathan wakes was the first season finale and Nemesis
Games I think was the fifth season finale. If you give the Hugo I'm getting all philosophical here.
If you give the Hugo for best dramatic presentation short form to the final episode of a six series
television show are you really giving it to a short form item at all really or are you in fact
celebrating a long form item? We have neatly encapsulated a debate that has been had for about
the last decade and a half. The best short form dramatic presentation award has gone to a standalone
short form piece of science fiction twice. Oh when? Gollum's acceptance speech at the 2003 MTV
Movies Awards and Dr Horrible's single long blog. Okay that's not a strong argument for giving the
Hugo to standalone short forms. The Gollum's acceptance speech was quite clever. I think the
thing is that in practice short form has never been about short form science fiction it's always
been about TV. I mean and I think like it depends right because we have seen TV win in long form
and that will come up again as a discussion later and like I do think all of the things that have
one in short form have been astounding standalone pieces but like it's real tricky because they're
part of longer works but we award novels that are part of series all the time so I don't know.
I think this could be a future episode. Yep yep. But I think yeah Babylon's Ashes is my first pick.
Yeah I feel like there should be a place to reward good episodes of TV. If you don't think
Babylon's Ashes is particularly good but you like the last season they're expanding too much to
put it in long form. I think working against it might be that you know the Expanse finished
very early in 2022 it is a long time kind of outside out of mind there so that might work against it.
True, true, true. My first pick is it's going to be an episode of Andor. I'm just deciding which one
I might pick as my top one. And this is interesting because one of the things I thought was quite good
about Andor was that it did manage to do some distinct episodes while being serialised.
I would probably pick one way out from Andor as my top pick which if you have seen it is basically
the one with the prison break and a succession of great monologues. So that would probably be my
first pick there. So that's the prison break episode with Gollum's acceptance speech in it.
See what you did there. Yes. So Andy Serkis is extraordinarily fantastic in that episode as far as
I know he is not wearing a motion capture suit. No so I would have picked one way out as my first
pick except that I knew Liz would pick it so I was like but yes I think it is. So one way out is
amazing it is one of a series of sort of amazing standout episodes of Andor and I think it would
be a worthy winner. Yeah no I also think that I think it's probably my favourite single episode
of Andor and yeah. So my first pick is going to be the final episode of Severance and you guys are
going to have to tell me what it's called because I'm not doing any heavy lifting
ass at this episode. Somehow disconnected from Wikipedia.
I still have disconnected from reality in a big way. It's called The Way We Are. The Way We Are.
So it's quite hard to talk about the last episode of Severance without spoiling it which I'm not
going to do but what happens in the last episode is that the various things, well I suppose always
happens in the last episode of series but the various things that have been happening come
together in a really spectacular way which is not like anything I've seen done in television before
and is both very entertaining and very thought-provoking and just generally wonderful and it's a brilliant
piece of television. Definitely the best piece of television short form I watched in 2022 and yes
it was the final episode of an extremely tight series so we'll get back to that in long form.
Yes so it is I mean obviously very good, directed by Ben Stiller and I find Severance, one of the
reasons I find Severance very interesting is that I think that if you look at Ben Stiller's career as
like what he's done outside of acting he's clearly had an interest in science fiction for a very
long time but he's also had an interest in very weird science fiction so like he was the person
who gave Rob Shrub and Dan Harmon money to do Heat Vision and Jack which was a TV series about Jack
Black and a talking motorcycle and so Stiller's obviously had like a slum or offbeat sense of SF
nor humor for a while and Severance seems to be like a very good vehicle for that and so yeah I
have enjoyed Severance greatly and again we will come back to that later. But also you say humer,
Severance is a very funny show but it's also an extremely unsettling and scary show in lots of
ways it's doing a lot, a lot of different, a lot of different things going on there.
I think humor can often be very unsettling. Well when you do it,
that my second pick therefore is going to be I am going to go with Defiant Jazz. Defiant Jazz,
it's a bit boring because we just talked about Severance but I will pick Defiant Jazz
because it's the best episode of Severance and I loved it. Just great. Just the very episode title
sums up everything I love about Severance so much so yes I'm going to pick Defiant Jazz and I guess
I might be the one I nominate if I only nominate one it might be that one instead of the way we are
but it's the one with the music dance experience which is very good. So I get to pick a mix I think.
So again it's quite sometimes quite difficult to pick a particular episode so basically I am
trying to pick one episode of what I think was a bit of an up and down season but I think I might
pick here or trust nothing from Star Trek Lower Decks which is the one where they go to Deep Space
Nine and it's lots of fun. Yep that is entirely legit. I mean there's really no really not a great
deal else to say which is it's loads of fun and it uses the Deep Space Nine characters well and
it's nice to see them again and they're in Garden Form and it's just fun. It would either be that one
or the one which is called the Mathematically Perfect Redemption which is the evil robot
peanut hamper. That is bloody great. Which is also a solid one so I might in fact go for that
instead but I did it but it would probably be one of those will be on my ballot I think. Okay I will
take the Liberty Liz of putting both of those in the giant Hugo Spreadsheet because I don't see them.
No I don't know they are in there so yes go for it. And they probably ought to be because they are
both solid solid picks and I think this kind of I don't know I think comedy and animation are both
parts of the genre that are treated less well than their cousins so I do think it's good to
recognize them. I mean there's also an aspect of gaming what I think will be on the ballot in a way
and I do think that Lower Decks having been on there before has a good chance of being back on.
I mean to be honest I'm not sure I've seen anything obscure enough that it's not going to have a
lot of support from other other areas but it's true there are a lot of Star Trek episodes in the
Spreadsheet right now but not the ones from Lower Decks so we'll put those in. I think that episode
would have landed much better for me how do I see Deep Space Nine? I loved it anyway but I really
wish I had seen Deep Space Nine before. Yeah if I had one criticism of Star Trek Lower Decks it's
the way it shows up my inadequacy as a Star Trek watcher generally. I'm just too much of a
dilatante to really get the most out of the series. So then it is over to Alison. I am riffing off
the Spreadsheet but I think I'm picking something that's not actually on it which is the Christmas
special of ghosts called It's Behind You because I am a terrible hugo nominator and I think that
ghosts is a great series that really ought to get more science fiction love for what it's doing
for what it's doing in fantasy and and the space and again comedy I like comedy I want to see more
comedy on the short form ballot because I think that comedy is something that science fiction
tends to do quite a lot better in short form than it does in long form. I'm not sure I've heard
of ghosts. It's a TV series about a couple who buy a house that's sorted. Oh yeah you have it's
done by the horrible histories people. Is it? I should probably say that. Yeah have you not
have you enough familiar with ghosts at all and then it's been remade for America with quite a lot
of the funniest jokes taken out. I think the thing is you haven't mentioned it on the pod.
Ghosts? Whatever. Nope. I don't think so. Okay right. I don't remember but Don can in fact
transcripts. Oh he can. Is it good? Should I watch it? Well watch it to see if you think it's funny.
It's about a couple who inherit an ancient house and they discover that it's inhabited by a load
of ghosts who are the horrible histories team and they're and all the ghosts are very funny because
they've all died in in terrible horrible histories type gruesome deaths at which you gradually
discover you to gradually discover what it is that's causing them to haunt this mansion and
one of the couple can see the ghosts and interact with them and the other one can't and and humor
happens. It's just a funny show. It's just a funny entertaining show that's been running for I guess
three and a half seasons but slot was beginning. Watch the first few if you don't like it stop.
I will also say I feel like I would have remembered you mentioning it because having just read the
cast I am excited. It has Lolly Adafrope and it has Katie Wicks as main cast and it has
Jeff McGivin, Jessica Knappett and Bridget Christie's recurring cast and I'm like I am here for these
people so yes I will look this up. Thank you and because it's British there's only like 24 episodes.
Yeah it's not going to take you long. Hey oh shoot it's background to me. What is Liz going to pick next
and can I snipe it? Probably not. Oh hello interesting. Now why does Liz think I can't snipe it?
I'm going to pick a Strange New World episode and then the question is which Strange New Worlds
episode do I pick? It's tricky. There are a lot of good ones. We have been recently watching Strange
New Worlds by which I mean we have watched the first eight episodes in the space of our week
and have been enjoying it quite a lot. I'm going to pick Spock and Muk. I think probably it's supposed
to be pronounced Spock and Muk for the rhyme but I usually pronounce him mukkamuk so um but
basically it's great. It's just hijinks. Hijinks in space in all the ways that discovery doesn't let
itself be silly anywhere near often enough. Spock and Muk really embraces the silly side of Star Trek
and I bloody loved it. So yeah I'll pick that one and also Nurse Chappell is the best and I love her
very much. So don't you you're correct that that does not snipe me on account of your past pick is
falls into the genre of things I cannot legally watch because they're not available anywhere.
I think ghosts might also fall into that. Oh I thought you'd watch Strange New Worlds. No
Paramount Plus limited limited market so far. Haven't bothered rolling out to kind of watch it
so yep I haven't seen that at all. Okay so I'll have to go with something else. So I am going to go
with some more comedy because I'm going to go with what we do in the shadows episode go flip
yourself. I don't know there's a episode in season four I felt were a little bit uneven and some of
them have great moments but also some less great stuff going on but Go Flip yourself is done like
in the style of a sort of home renovation show. So basically Laslo the vampire has been obsessed
with a home renovation show and he thinks he has got the home renovation show in to come and renovate
their mansion and so the first put is done as though you know you are watching the home renovation
show where all the crew are getting killed kind of you know behind the scenes and so on but it all
turns out that it is more of a plot to bring back in a character from previous seasons which is very
funny because they just ran the whole character incredibly funny and so that's probably my pick
of the fourth season which aired in 2022. I have not seen I could not have picked that because I
have not seen well I've not seen what we do in the shadows. Yeah I figured you hadn't so you
wouldn't pick it so I was pretty confident you weren't going to snipe me you probably should
watch it though it's good. I watched I watched the movie and I loved the movie and I watched the
first episode of the TV show and I was like this is not as good as the movie and then I didn't watch
anymore but I have heard from many people that it gets better so maybe I should give it another
try. I was really like I'm not going to watch it because the movie was so good this all just
be rubbish and then it's got Matt Berry in so I do love Matt Berry yes I can hear you Clem Fandango
as Panya has that on a mug. Right Alison your next pick. Right my next pick for best dramatic
presentation is short form is the first episode of season three of Mythic Quest across the universe.
We left the Mythic Quest people at the end of season two really scattered to the four wins and
and they're not all doing the same thing anymore and they're not all working on Mythic Quest anymore
and they've gone off doing all sorts of different things so they had to find a way to bring them
all together at the beginning of season three because this is basically an ensemble cast it's a
comedy about an ensemble cast and they did it very well and they did it in a way that was quite
science fictional actually. I mean I know it's technically is it genre it's a it's kind of
quite close to genre is Mythic Quest it's a comedy show about a bunch of people who make video games
so you know one of whom has been a science fiction writer before writing for video games.
And it's a good episode I really really enjoyed it and I was kind of like sitting down going
oh don't know how Mythic Quest is gonna cope now it's all gonna be bad and then at the end of the
episode I was like oh no it's gonna be great it's gonna be fantastic so I loved it there are some
spoilers which I'm not going to again not spoil if you haven't seen Mythic Quest it's good it's on
Apple TV so a lot of people haven't seen it um in general you know you want to get Apple TV plus
to watch Severance and then you should watch Mythic Quest as well and then there's a few other
things you should watch I probably watch for all my kind haven't watched it yet but you should do
and I will do but haven't yet um there may be a reason why I've been watching a lot of comedy
so far I think all my short form nominations may be comedy apart from if I short form
nominate Severance which I'm not intending to do because I'm planning to love form nominated
anyway spoilers for shadowing so I have a question for you with that foreshadowing which is if you
have a spot left on your short form will you still not um nominate Severance or will you be like
or nominate the best episode two cracks of the apple I don't know what happens doesn't it all get
transferred and discounted um Liz Bat I was gonna say I don't actually know because like you can't
you can't end up giving yourself six nominations in best short form by transferring everything from
best long form or vice versa I don't think but I think if you left a space if I give you put
long let's say you put an episode of Severance in best short form but you haven't filled up best
long form I think it will get transferred so I think I think like they won't if you've nominated
it in both they won't they will treat that as a nomination in both because it's very clear what
your intention is but if you've nominated it in short form and then long form like two nominations
off I don't know whether they'd get transferred if they weren't enough to get on the final ballot
yeah I think it's quite possible then that my short form ballot will include what I think is the best
episode of each of Andor and Severance which we've already talked about but we've already talked
about both of them in fact so we've each got two picks left I haven't seen Star Trek Discovery
season four so I can't nominate from that I haven't seen the Sandman and I haven't seen I haven't seen
the latest season of the of For All Mankind sorry and I know what I want to basically is between
three and the next one I'm going to pick is Asylum from Moon Knight now not everyone loved Moon
Knight but that is because not everyone was correct because Moon Knight was amazing
it was my favorite empty-youth thing basically I've always had a soft spot for Moon Knight and
seeing them actually fucking do it in all its weird glory on a big screen with Oscar Isaac was
just like what's going on it was amazing I can't can't adequately state how amazing it was to see
like something I love that much like done so so seriously I'm not no seriously because it had
jokes in as well but like it wasn't ironic I think it would have been very easily easy to do it
ironically and they didn't and I respected that a great deal Asylum is I think the best episode
but I loved all of them very very much and as I put it to my friend Ian when I guest start on
become the teapot imagine that they'd made an iron fist tv show and imagine how good that would
feel Ian because you love iron fist and imagine imagine when or if they ever make an iron fist tv
show how good that will feel and for some reason he seems sad that's my pick yeah I mean I think
I like I like Moon Knight less than you which is not difficult I mean I basically thought it was
pretty great whenever it was doing stuff with Oscar Isaac but a lot of the stuff that wasn't Oscar
Isaac less good I like Ethan Hawke a lot as well I liked him I thought there was some interesting
things but he didn't I don't know I didn't feel he got a ton of great stuff but just basically
Oscar Isaac was so good at portraying the different aspects of Moon Knight that I really enjoyed that
bit so I think you're right thinking about that that is the best episode yeah it's probably a solid
pick if you're gonna pick anything we have not picked a lot of stuff from Marvel haven't we
no I mean I think they had a week year but like I don't think I'm gonna put any particular
episode of like spoilers Ms Marvel or She Hulk on there because they just did not quite reach the
top of my I don't think I'll nominate anything for She Hulk I do think I was dithering so like
spoilers for my final pick I was dithering between the partition episode of Ms Marvel which I do
think was really good TV like even though I don't think Ms Marvel as a longer piece was amazing
that episode was pretty damn good but I am going for a different one I might go well we'll see
you can leave them to Spence it's Liz's pick it is my pick I was thinking what to pick I mean
it's possible that I will end up with multiple episodes of Andor on there it's possible I also
haven't watched Station 11 which is supposed to be great yeah I haven't seen that either but I think
it is quite possible that I will end putting an episode of For All Mankind on there the problem
is that in season two the episode that got nominated was like absolutely this season was not the
season was not always great and then the last episode pulled it all together and then I think
series three well not quite as good but I guess it would probably be if I nominate anything it would
probably be Stranger in a Strange Land which is the final episode of the season again because it
pulled some stuff nicely together and set up some interesting stuff for the last series and
yeah when they basically the resolution of Margot's plotline in that sets up some really
interesting stuff and I thought she was really great so I would go with that one Margot is
amazing I haven't seen season three season four season three but Margot is just so great and I
love the way I mean I don't know whether this holds season three but in season one and season two I
love that both seasons start with Margot in exactly the same way but in different circumstances
I thought I was a really nice touch I am looking forward to seeing that season of For All Mankind
but we were busy watching literally all the other TV there's so much TV
it's like I can yeah I mean I'm not sure I agree in you know you you have to kind of
believe that maybe Margot was a little bit more naive than you actually think Margot as a character
is to I'm trying very hard to do this without giving a big massive honking spoiler but like she
is a little bit naive to not see what's going on but you kind of believe that she thought it would
all work out okay right and then doesn't work out as okay as you would like I'm gonna be so sad at
the end okay for our life yeah I was thought I'm gonna say then John can go and be sad and send
me messages about how sad he is when he gets to that point I do do that every time I'm sad I send
Liz like infinite texts Liz I'm sad I should do that maybe I should start doing that Liz is
give me a look you find John but just don't just don't get sad anytime after about like 5 p.m
because I'll be asleep so that is your problem there and he gets sad during specific times
you can send me infinite texts say you're sad after 5 p.m we could kind of type sub-time share
arrangement and I in return will send back bad jokes how the turns table it's true I won't send
you bad jokes that is Alison's domain no it's John's domain hands off my domain we're not when he's
when he's sad he cannot be a joke creation machine that's the thing Alison is your pick
when we have five picks each that's really a huge number because of course we're not repeating
each other's picks we're a reality we are a tightly honed automaton who will absolutely
replicate other each other's picks in the actual ballot so I'm really starting to think for things
that definitely won't be all the ballots my pick is going to be Harry Josephine Giles reading of
Deep Wheel L'Ocadia at the Edinburgh Book Festival which I found very interesting and very affecting
and I loved hearing her perform the poem or parts of the poem obviously she didn't perform the entire
thing and therefore I was very excited to see how it ended I haven't actually read the entire
novel yet okay so I don't think anyone agrees with me on this and it's not going to be on the ballot
the genre as a whole does not agree that this should be on the Hugo ballot in that it has not yet
been on the Hugo ballot however I think is that only show or perhaps one of two shows that I can
think of that is directly trying to talk about the current state of politics in America and talking
about Trumpism and talking about the Republican Party and the way that corporations are distorting
American freedom and that is the boys I think like for all its faults and I know that lots of
people have problems with it it's extremely graphic and it's extremely colorful but it's also not
trying away from actually talking about this stuff in a way that I don't really think anything else
is doing and so I am going to pick Herogasm in the latest series of the boys which is just
horrific episode it's the episode where it becomes clear the depth to which some people will sink to
do what they think is right it's an episode which highlights all of the excesses of power and wealth
it's an episode that highlights how those excesses end up ruining lives and I loved it I think it
was amazing I mean I was a big fan of supernatural before kripkey left so I've always been a fan of
Eric Kripkey stuff but the boys is like so so much better that supernatural but it's not funny
and in some ways supernatural is the love letter to America where the boys is the savage criticism
of America like a supernatural is a celebration of everything that kripkey loves about america and
american history whereas the boys is the utter pelereing of all of the huge problems in modern
american culture so yeah that would be my fifth pick I thought the boys have been nominated actually
has it I did a control F for the boys on the dramatic presentation it hasn't but I'm surprised
because I thought it had um no I think it and I really think it should have been because like
even though I know not everyone gets along with it I don't know I just I feel like it is doing
stuff that nothing else is doing even if you don't like how it's doing it I mean I've only watched
season one so that's why I'm not gonna snipe you I mean I don't have a particular I mean I don't
have a particular issue with it I didn't really I really didn't get along with the comics at all
but I thought the the comics are terrible yeah that's why it took me so long to pick it up because
the comics that I read I really didn't like at all and so that was why I was a bit like okay yeah
the the comics are edgelordy nonsense in my opinion I think the comics are trying to talk about the
same stuff but do such a bad job and also they're they're much more the comics are much more trying
to talk about 9/11 but they're just not very good whereas the it's a really good example of a show
taking the fundamental it's a bit like the kickass movie the first one it's it's it's a work taking
the fundamental idea behind a comic and then like actually making something much better out of it
than the comic managed and I think there is it's not a coincidence that both the examples I've given
are very edgelordy comics that were less edgeldy in their adaptations because I loved Preacher
but even that had like bits where you were a bit like really yeah I mean I was face basically
yep yeah okay I am not yeah I mean it is ultra violent but I'm not I wouldn't be surprised if I
did see it on the ballot but I wonder also if it had its heyday kind of in series one and series
two especially I heard good things about but then maybe not so much season three series two is really
good series two is really interesting because there is a do you mind spoilers either you're gonna
watch the boys I can't imagine it'll be Allison's cup of tea at all it's probably a bit violent for
me I mean I am but I know that I know that like there's a particular character in it if that's
what you're gonna smile I was gonna talk about Stormfront yeah I have not managed to avoid knowing
that so yeah and like I like how it's the only safe it's the only science fiction show on tv that
openly says that the modern republic party has Nazis in it and no one else is doing that and I
do think saying that out loud in fiction is probably good and I think it's something that the genre
is shying away from which understandably so or no not a shying away from that's unfair but I think
the boys is one of the only things that's like obviously enough about what we're living through
that it can make statements like that which can't be misread if that makes sense and that's why
everyone who liked Homelander from season one got really angry with later seasons I mean like
Tom Landers no but there were people who were like Homelander's great right and then it's like
no he's not oh why do you think that I mean they're watching the same tv show right where you're
basically oh yeah oh yeah that's kind of why I think it's useful to have a character is like oh
here's a character and then two seasons they should be like no he's evil how do you not get it
his performance is so creepy that every time he's on screen with a baby you start worrying yes he's
so good the actor is so good like either the actor is literally evil or the actor is a very good actor
and I'm not ruling out either but like oh my god that portrayal was amazing he's so unsettling
yeah anyway okay yeah so okay that's my pick Liz last pick last pick oh yeah I'm trying to think
do I have any like totally left feel exciting picks and I don't think I do so I mean I think it
probably is it might be just looking at the spreadsheet I mean things that I've they're on there that I
think were pretty good and would consider nominating is slightly surprisingly I probably would nominate
the episode of Stranger Things that is on there because no strange things was quite surprising to me
in that I looked at series four and you know I was a bit like you know it's been going a while
they keep getting episodes keep getting longer and longer they've basically got a kind of entire
plot strand that really should be kind of done away with because they don't know what to do with
the characters but they don't really want to do that so they just keep them off doing an entirely
separate thing and I get bored with it so it's got lots of flaws but the episode which is nominated
which gets Kate Bush back to the top of the charts is pretty good so I can't listen to Kate Bush
because she gives me flashbacks to first year revision because I had a friend who basically just
played Kate Bush songs and rocked for a solid two months and I have severe Kate Bush based PTSD
so I've been sitting here for the last five minutes going what can I do for my last pick what can I
do for my last pick oh what can I do for my last pick oh oh wait I know I haven't watched any of
Stranger Things since season one because I thought it was a bit pants but but Kate Bush there's an
episode that's got Kate Bush in I can do is my last pick the one with Kate Kate Bush in because
because Kate Bush could do no wrong and running up that hill is my favorite Kate Bush song so
the notion that it basically reinvigorated brought her music to an entire generation who had never
heard any of it and and she's been completely revitalized that makes it a perfect spot for my
fifth pick what I love about this is that you have somehow managed to you have somehow managed to
sign each other on pick five not on pick like one or two five you both waited to the very end and
then it got personal totally yeah but can't have seen it yeah that's why I don't feel guilty about
taking the pick from you because you have not seen it but I feel very aggrieved to be
to be sniped on pick five that was really shocking Kate Bush is in multiple episodes so you could
just have one of the other ones that has the Kate Bush song in because you won't understand the
emotional resonance of the Kate Bush song because you haven't seen the episode no I understand the
emotional resonance of the Kate Bush song because I understand Kate Bush because I listened to it
when it was new and it's really good in the but you don't understand the context of the show why
the Kate Bush song is so good no I think basically the show has fundamentally jumped the shark and
decided that the way it's going to get emotional relevance is by stealing us a piece of music that's
far better than anything in the show you probably don't want to give it a hugo then do you oh I
definitely don't want to guess as you go look right I think I speak for all three of us when I say
that using music to elicit emotional responses in dramatic presentations is wrong and any show that
does it should not be on the ballot I want entirely silent except for dialogue it's about the ideas
people it's not about the feelings hashtag proper science fiction fan don't want to be nominating
the wire if it was more science fictional then I've never seen the wire it does not seem like it
would be my cup of tea so it famously has only music that occurs during the during the show there
is no instrumental music oh interesting it is Alison's pick and she's gonna pick Kate Bush's
discography yes and my last pick is all the other episodes of severance pick one any of them I
think that is really like I think that is very very fair because severance was great that is
what I'm going to do if I run out of that's what I'm going to do if I run out of nomination slots
um okay so that was our picks shall we do picks I'm going to pick the Arthur C. Clark award
shortlist from 2022 I read them listeners I read them and I am glad I read them do you have
opinions John I have some opinions some more disclosure I did not finish reading a river called
time I'm sure it was very good but I think it's got some interesting ideas in it that are perhaps
ideas that would have been better explored by someone who was better versed in the genre and also
I think the author says that they have decolonized their writing which I think is very admirable but
all of the female characters exist to be there for the man I like I like books that have women
and who are not just there for the men so that was that I also read Skyward in by Alia Whiteley
which again I did not like I am not familiar with the Daphne de Morier book which it is in
conversation with and it may be that if I have read that I would have liked it a lot more I
thought the science fiction idea was interesting but I thought the characters were not people I
wanted to spend time with and I think it would be much better as a novelt where they properly
explored the science fiction concept because basically the first two thirds of the book
build up to the last third where all the science fiction happens but because I fundamentally
didn't care about the characters the last third is also like emotional payoff for the characters
and I'm like but I don't care about them so this just feels very flat so it's a rare
comment from me that I think it'd been better had a bit less character driven
which is unusual but there we are I loved Vergen and I loved a desolation called Peace
we've discussed a desolation called Peace on the podcast before but it is very good
Vergen the alien love war is amazing it's a very good way of making you think oh no humans are
the worst which was very fun and I liked the way it does that plow it and the sun was good
again from the literary fiction angle but I enjoyed it I didn't enjoy it as much the other two that
I mentioned but I did think it was quite good and then Deep Will Arcadia is very conflicting
because it is a poem or as it refers to itself in the blurb a verse novel and it is clearly a
work of genius and it is clearly incredible however I found the experience of actually reading it
was difficult because I have ADHD and because you have to keep switching between the poem and
the translation if you don't speak the Orkney language which I don't I found the actual experience
of reading it was very difficult to get into and so I have no idea how to talk about it like
clearly a work of genius but approach it more like you're in an art museum than you're settling
in for a nice novel I think but it was very good but I didn't like reading it but it was very good
I think it's a prose poem that probably repays study rather than a rollicking good read
would be my guess but it was very good to listen to with it because of course you're listening to
it being spoken in or cadian but with English translations at the bottom of the screen and that
did help a whole lot I think it in some ways reminds me a lot of reading Shakespeare as a kid
which is I found reading Shakespeare fine but watching Shakespeare is a lot better and in some
ways it reminds me of reading the script like to good omens or something where like we're probably
just script book and it's like why would I read a script book or I'd like to read the thing that
originated from the script and not the script itself and so I do wonder whether as with many poems
it works better as performance than it's writing John do you want to make joker's guide script book
yeah but that's mostly because the stage directions are funny
excellent pursued by a bear yeah Shakespeare occasionally has funny ones but John did you
enjoy your six stealth picks there or rather three picks and two anti picks I think or three
anti picks yeah yes well I'd buy a whistle to throw it yes you did whistle through it um but yeah
for anyone else who hasn't read vergan highly recommend buying it and reading it is extremely
good and I think it was much less talked about than many of the other books on the clerk's short
list so I highly recommend giving it a look if I if I had to have one pick it would be that one
Liz I am going to pick the most recent issue of Strange Horizons which is one of the criticism
specials they did one in 2022 and they've brought out this one in 2023 it is also a tribute to the
late reviews editor there Maureen Kincaid Speller and so basically it's got a few tributes to Maureen
along with basically criticism that she would have liked to see and so it's got a great essay
from friend of the podcast Neil Arison about his concept of overshoot novels which you must go
and read the essays so you can find that one overshoot novel is and then completely misuse that term
as a critical term forever yup it's got a good essay or essay I enjoyed on Becky Chambers Wayfarer's
books which I think gets to some of my issues with their Wayfarer's books and even John enjoyed
the essay even though he likes the books more than me so good because I think it's very I mean
it's not a like a hatchet job I think it's not it's not doesn't end up being particularly positive
about the novels but it really digs into kind of why why they are popular but why they why why the
the author of the essay kind of feels they maybe fail to do what he would you would hope this kind
of fiction can do that fair yeah like and the author convinced me of their opinion which is I
think the hallmark of great critical writing in that they argue I think very well that the Wayfarer
series is an expression of sort of current American liberalism and are not really sort of doing anything
that can further us towards progression because they're reflective and not predictive and not
trying to move towards a better state and in that way because of the way they're written it
basically portrays current American liberalism as the ideal and I think and I think he really neatly
hits the nail on the head why I'd really dislike the second novel because he's like this is an
expression of the American dream and I read it and I thought this is wank and I really don't like
novel number two I thought no one of three was confusing I love novel number one and I quite
like novel number four but novel number two I really didn't like and I think putting it in that
framework helped me understand why and I did I loved that essay I thought it was amazing I think
yeah great critical writing does two things firstly it can convince you of the author's point of view
and secondly it can make you think oh so that's why I think that and I think the second one is
actually in some ways like the holy grail right like if you can identify a thought in the reader's
head that they have not previously been able to articulate and render them able to articulate it
that is a very good it was just it was very good even though it is incredibly negative about something
that I do enjoy part of yeah I think ironically John has just expressed much better why I enjoyed
the essay by picking out the things that I would have said about it so thank you John sorry Liz
in a good way yeah Neil Neil's essay on overshoots is amazing firstly both because I think he's
identified a thing in the genre that didn't have a name and given a name which again hallmark of
very good writing and obviously Neil is genius anyway but also because the number of people on
Twitter who haven't properly read the essay and are using that word in ways that he doesn't
think it applies is truly hilarious so 10 out of 10 on both fronts so last week I said that my life
had taken a dramatic turn for the worse and I had got deeply into um printed play games so in the
subsequent fortnight my life has taken a dramatic turn for the worse again and I really upped to my
lekken print and play games now um to a phenomenal degree I'm still not allowed to spend money
apparently I was told I was told it was a hyper focus by John and he said you must not spend money
for a month it's a hyper focus yep and Alison sent me a text message saying has it been a month yet
and I sent a text message back saying no it has been 15 days which underlines what I say these things
it has it has I think been the longest three weeks the last three weeks have been the longest three
weeks of my life by some considerable margin except me you know so it's been it's been quite a shock
guys yeah but any print and play games still good hey if I'm still doing printed play games in two
weeks I'll try I'll try to do a proper pick sometime in the next two weeks I should get some time to
read a book or watch some television or watch a movie that'd be good that was the old thought
podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me
for listeners who are wondering I don't know if this is going to come out in the edit but if it is
obvious how long my picks are taking after Alison is gone it's because whenever Liz and Alison say
a thing they have invariably not added it to the show the the big spreadsheet of Hugo eligible
things and so I am doing that before it gets round to me you're a good you're a very good friend I
have not been paying a lot attention to the great list of Hugo eligibility thing because I just care
about data unlike you two apparently I was gonna do it later when I'm not also doing a podcast
job well look right we all know that I have bad impulse control the worst yep true the theme music
for this episode was fanfare for space by Kevin McLeod and Competec.com used under a creative
commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep