Hello everyone, it's John here just letting you know we're aware that Alison has some music
bleeding through in the La Half of the podcast. Alison very kindly recorded while she was at a
festival in a field but unfortunately we hadn't quite grasped what that would mean for the audio
scape. Hopefully it doesn't impede your enjoyment too much but we'll be back to a regular service
next episode. See you all after the music.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 87th episode of Octa Thorpe, a podcast for science fiction and
science fiction fandom. This episode is coming to you on the 6th of July 2023. I'm John Coxon,
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty and we have some letters of comment. So sometimes we have
tweets of comment, Twitter broke. So if you sent us a tweet a comment please try sending it again
on a different social network. Thank you, we love you all, we love hearing from you.
Christopher J Garcia wrote in as he usually does. A day late, I swear I will speedily listen next
week. We will be watching Chris. Chris says lots of things all of which are good. He saw a moose
in person once, it was about eight feet tall and it was in chill mode and that is about the opposite
of Alison in both respects. Because Alison is not eight feet tall and is perhaps not as chill as a
moose. I am pretty chill, I do not, I very rarely stampede at people and flack them with my giant
antlers. I would also say that a moose is considerably more deadly than Alison that is another way in
which you are differentiated. Oh you just crossed me. Listeners, if you could write in and tell us
whether you'd rather have a fight with Alison or a fight with a moose and we will read out the
best responses next episode. Would you rather have a fight with 100 Alison sized moose or one
moose sized Alison? Chris, Chris did pick us up on some pronunciation. He says never call it Los
Angeles, it's Los Angeles. And also if we need stunt versions of ourselves Chris volunteers to
portray John Coxon. He might be able to pull off a reasonable Liz but he's been working on his
Coxon delivery since 2009 and he's awesome at it. What I now want to see is whether Chris could
do all three of us. Well we know that we've done it on the cover. Well that was all three of us
doing Chris. No I was just going to say about Chris's letter that I think Chris Garcia I think
is the man with the most energy who could do all three of us convincingly during a live episode and
I would like to see that. Yep and I'd like to see that at a Californian convention but obviously
in Eastercon I'd want it to be Tobe's. Ooh I think that would be funny. Yeah I'm okay with that. We
also heard from Anne-Gell Nussbaum who writes in and apologizes for confusing Alison.
Adliss I think. Would you rather confuse Alison or confuse a moose?
No no I knew what was going on. I knew what was going on. I just let you finish before I
pointed out that you got the wrong end of the sick. Oh my god that's so much worse.
I don't like to interrupt people John. No I don't listen as may know I don't have that
character character as a judge described. Yes but Abigail would like to clarify that the most
recommended Francis Harding novels are Gullsford Carlin, Skimfleshadows, Verdigree, Deep,
and a Facelight class and I've read three of those and they're all good so go for it. Which ties in
very nicely to an email we got from Karen Shafer thanking us for our recommendation over Facelight
class and they read it just before listening to the discussion just like a book club. It's just
like a book club except we get to pontificate for like an hour and then you get to write as a
letter of comment that we extract the bits we like from. So it's not quite like a book club.
Maybe we should announce more often that we're going to do like a book episode and then people
can read it. That might be a good idea. Maybe we should. That's a good point. When we record,
so the next episode we will be doing a book club about will be Six Weeks by Merlafferty which was
a Hugo Award finalist in I think 2018 which is my pick that I get to make Liz and Alison read
and I don't know when it will come out. We haven't yet read and recorded the episode and you'll be
able to do some behind the scenes cryptography because if it comes out in like August 2024
you now have an indication of timescale. But we'll let you know when we do record it.
Well we'll let you know, I guess we'll let you know when near when it comes out so that people
can read it closer to the time. But yeah foreshadowing. Something that happened this week is that one
of file 777 throwback novels was Grass by Sherry Tepper which is my choice for the book that I'm
going to make John and Liz read. So I thought it was quite funny that given all of the books in
all of the world they will pick that one. Of all the books of all the world you had to walk in a
mine. Yeah like that one like that. We heard toots. We had toots of comment. Firstly Peter Sullivan
says that he's beginning to catch up with the backlog. So obviously he said that and then he
probably isn't going to listen to this episode for a while. But when you get here, hi Peter.
And then Raj says he loves Alison's episode art. This is the cricket episode art. It feels like a
1930 seaside murder mystery where Alison is murdered. John is innocent but is framed for her
murder because he looks shifty and lizzes the Ditzy but very sharp lady detective who has saw
everything out. I don't know if that's how it would unfold but we could do it as a play.
I'm happy to be the Ditzy but sharp lady detective. I think I do get off lightly here.
I don't want to be murdered. Thank you. I don't really want to be murdered even in the play.
I don't know how that's so funny but it is. If you were murdered would you want me to investigate
your murder or jump? Is this hypothetical too far? I wonder if neither is an option if I could
pick a detective who is not either of you. All of the rights who would it be? Any fan who's
investigating your murder? Chris Garcia. Chris Garcia. I mean he does have, he is writing a book about
true crime I think. Yeah speaking to the skill set. I feel like he'd investigate my murder with
considerable energy. On the subject of cricket Malcolm Hutchison told us on Facebook,
"What do you mean cricket is an SF no a game created from my racial memory of being attacked by cricket
robots?" I did think that when we were discussing it and I didn't say it but thank you very much
for writing up writing in Malcolm that was very good. And also Fara thanked us for the discussion
of COVID ventilation. We have news. We have been nominated for a Hugo Award. Yay.
So thank you very much. Which answers one important question which we had at the time of recording
which is will there be any English language finalists on the ballot? And the answer is yes
because we are. So we're very pleased. Which makes conversations that are being had in theory
about the Hugo is very difficult because people are loudly asserting there won't be any and I'm
like I know there will be but I can't tell you why. Oh no I have heard elsewhere on gossipy grapevines.
I heard before we learnt that we were a nominee. I heard that there was at least one English language
nominee through the grapevine. At time recording we don't know anything else that's on the ballot.
We're recording this after we receive the you know super secret email. Oh no we do we do we do we do we
do we do we do we do we actually know two other things that are on the ballot Liz. You know two
other things on the ballot. I do not know two other things on the ballot. Well I have been nominated
for my role in a fanzine called journey planet. Congratulations John. I did not know that you did
not tell me that. Yes I do not obviously do not officially know these things because no one would
ever you know break the Hugo and Bargo to tell them eight stuff. No well it's tricky I feel like
you two are good at keeping secrets and also I feel like it would be weird to have this episode
going out celebrating our Hugo norm as a podcast without mentioning our other Hugo norms.
Yeah it would yes. I edited the and or issue of journey planet and that was very good.
Oh thank you. I'm a journey planet did absolutely fantastic work last year and
they were definitely on my ballot and I'm sure lots of other people's and I'm very glad to see
that they're on the thing. So congratulations John and the and or episode issue was fantastic
even though it had the same joke on the cover that we'd use for octalope and you must have known
at the point where you commissioned it for octalope and you did not tell me and I was only a bit
annoyed and by a bit annoyed I mean absolutely fucking furious. You underestimate how joined up
the journey planet team is. But you edited that I blame I blame sharing competence.
I guess I guess a little bit of a look behind the curtain but it's actually usually James who
does the cover art commissioning. Oh right. Like like so so for all of the episode all of the issues
of journey planet I have worked on it has been James who commissioned the covers except for the
matrix issue which I commissioned. James needs to commission a cover for me then doesn't he?
Because as we know Bob. So on the subject of people who were on
nomination ballots from other people on the podcast so what else is nominated for a Hugo
in our company? I am also eligible in best fan artist and I have been nominated for this my first
aye this is my first finalist place for best fan artist and I am very happy because I have
been doing fan art in Fansies and in other places since 1996 so I'm kind of like oh this is amazing
I didn't think this would ever happen so I'm very pleased. I've sent them a note saying
here's my eligible stuff and about 13 of those pieces are octa-thorpe covers so thank you guys
for not only providing me an outlet for my art but also insisting that I do it every two weeks
because that is what we call good discipline and I'm pretty proud of some of the covers that I did
in 2022 so do check them out if you've never looked at our cover art we do have cover art
most issues episodes and most of that's me but some of it's by our other excellent artists
like Sue Mason and Spanish Shove and Brad Foster we've had it had in 2022 and is that everyone?
Oh Sarah Felix and if you are a fan artist and we have no invited you to do fan art for our
podcast please write in because we're very British and coy and what that means is you have to kick
us to get us to ask you to do things. No no no we will yeah we'd love for you to do us art.
Yes. We have an art specification but you're welcome to ignore all of it it's only there so
that you can have ideas to bounce off. Yeah I should say how the process normally goes for the
fortnightly octa-thorpe artist Alison goes do you have any art prompts guys and I try and come up
with the most ludicrous one possible like saying can we all be mouse detectives or can we have
a commemorative plates and then Alison somehow makes them into something amazing. It is very good.
On the subject of being nominated for Hugo Awards the Hugo Award finalists are out but at the
recording time we do not know what they are because they weren't when we recorded. I'm gonna say that
I worked on the Hugo team a couple of years ago for the Disc on 300th Hugo vote packet.
This entire area of Worldcon work is tedious for nickety hard work that takes ages even if you don't
theoretically have a load of nominations in a language you don't understand with a lot of
different conventions for how titles are portrayed so I mean I feel like they've probably had a
bucket load of work to do and we should cut them a load of slack and the people are not cutting
them a load of slack yeah should take a chill pill because I'm sure it's going to get sorted out
and the hugas will be awarded and it will all be lovely but they did say that they would have it
done by the end of June and it's now the second of July as we record. So and I would say I mean
my experience of Worldcon deadlines is generally you have a deadline you set an advance and then
like it slips by a couple of weeks and then sometimes it slips by a bit more but most of these
deadlines because they're not as public facing as a Hugo's no one really notices or cares about them
as long as you actually get it done in time and you build in enough slack into the system that
your deadline is always well we're going to do it now and then if it slips by a couple of weeks it
won't actually you know cause any massive problems it will just tighten up all your timescales so
hopefully they will get them out and still give people a good couple of months to read everything
um I guess the timescales for the Hugo packet do get a little bit tight if that slips well
assuming there is a Hugo packet if that slips as far as the nominees have that might be a little
bit difficult if people are relying on that to read things but yeah I would just urge people to get
on with getting books out from the library and reading what fiction is free online and you know
engaging with whatever else they can get their hands on before the Hugo packet if they're worried
about running out of time. Three of us know that there are finalists out there uh the file 770
comments Paul Weimer notes that he knows that someone has been notified they're a finalist so they
are clearly going through so like it's not like no one has heard anything so presumably it's just
taking longer than they thought. So two days ago um Chung Do announced on their Facebook page 114
lucky emails have been sent we have now sent the emails to all of the finalists for final
confirmation and the official list will be announced once all the finalists have confirmed by email.
Chung Do is a shower we're recording a little pick up a little bit after we recorded because
since we recorded the Hugo finalists were announced and then were unannounced again.
I think announced is a strong word. They were not really announced were they they sort of
they were they were put on the website in a kind of by somebody who clearly didn't think that anybody
would ever check you know Chung Do Worldcon.com/Hugoes. I believe there's actually Hugo Heifen Award which
is clearly very obvious. Is there any thoughts? Yeah I mean I can kind of see how it happened and
I suspect that Chung Do are having to put more effort than many conventions into making sure
their Hugo voting site is accessible from lots of different locations but I think just don't put
the actual data in there to leave an empty awards. But apparently they were using they've been using
fake data for weeks. The thing that happened was that people noticed when it changed to
data which Tammy Coxen assures us is not correct. People who follow these things have
pointed out numerous ways in which it cannot be correct because things are in wrong categories
or there is double dipping in the best dramatic presentations. But why would you even like ever
take a set of data which is wrong and put it in there instead of dummy data? I just yeah.
It doesn't make any sense right? Because you hadn't noticed it was wrong at the point where
you put it on and it took putting it on and having it around to cause people including people who
should have known better to actually look at it and check it. No obviously then it was wrong
because Tammy said this is the incorrect list like why did they get the list from the Hugo
administrators in the first place if it was not the actual list? Yeah that's my question as well.
Did they realize it was wrong until people pointed out it was wrong? Like did the Hugo team
think to put the categories in alphabetical order for example? There's incompetence here
from at least one group right? Either the Hugo administrator was incompetent because they
let an incorrect list into the wild of the rest of the convention which should absolutely not have
happened. It should have been the correct list and there should have been no list and then the
correct list and they should not have been an intermediate stage and the web team were incompetent
because on no account should you use real data when you're testing. Ever if you need representative
data use the 2022 Hugo finalists which would be fine from the perspective of making sure like all
your line wrapping is worked but we clearly not the actual ballot. These things do happen and I don't
want to be mean but at the same time this should not have happened. Oh yeah no matter how many
how much slack you are cutting the Shagdo team for having to do a very good difficult job in a
very difficult year they absolutely should not have done this and the number of the number of
lead so so when you're thinking about health and safety and risk management you have this model of
the Swiss cheese where you have layers of protection none of which are perfect but the idea is that
things don't get through because a lot of imperfect barriers is as good as a perfect one or it feels
like you had to have made a cascade of stupid mistakes in order to have this happen in this way
and they should have not have done that. It's a little bit annoying because when we posited a
binary when we first recorded this episode of they will announce it or they won't announce it we
didn't imagine the third option where they would do both. So sorry listeners we've let you down
we've let ourselves down. Yeah and we're not going to talk about the people who we now expect to be
on the ballot and are thrilled to see on the ballot that we shouldn't have seen but we are thrilled
to see them all well done everyone. There are no Hugo finalists at the moment there are only past
winners and that's finalists. So my favorite my favorite comment on this whole thing is the
person who's busy saying oh so when we see the final list if there's anyone who wasn't on the
redacted who was on the redacted list but isn't on the final list they are necessarily the people
that the invidious forces of the Chinese government have deemed cannot be on the Hugo list and I thought
that was amazing. Oh god I hadn't occurred to me until you just said it and now it has occurred to
me and it makes me sad. I think it's very unlikely guys I don't think I don't think the Chinese
government cares that much. Oh no I 100% agree with that but there will definitely be people who
don't appear on the ballot because they'll have like recused or something and then we're gonna
have a massive argument about whether that may or I just I'm not here for a listeners I can't be
out. Yeah I mean well I listen so as did they only I'm going to give them not much benefit of
the doubt but I don't think they can possibly realize that the list was not the correct list
until they saw it on the website because it had dramatic presentations in both short and long form
and we know that they always put them in one or the other category and that is a really easy thing
that was the instant thing to spot. It's not like an edge case like did someone you know self you
know self-publish their you know fiction on a tiny website in 2019 that makes them ineligible
for astounding it's like a big thing. So my my personal theory is that it's just the top five in
every category so top six in every category on the website before they do this kind of eligibility
checking and so what I hope is that the only people who disappear are those who actually decline or
are ineligible or are in two categories and then we only get new people. Are we very sad if there is
anyone who is actually on the list and then gets taken off because it was a colossal error that would
be a big shame. Especially if it's us. Anyway next segment.
The Locust Award winners have been announced recently there are a whole load of them actually
because they break down novel into multiple categories and they also award for short fiction
and short story anthology and collection and magazine and so I'll link them in the show notes
and you can go and read through them. I think the ones I would pull out are the winner of
novelt is if you find yourself speaking to a dress god within formal you which I think was one of
John and I's picks for best novelt for the Hugos. The winner of best short story was rabbit test
by Samantha Mills which again was one of our picks and I don't think I've read any of the other
winners actually so it's hard for me to pass comment on those but they do it like a solid list
of stuff. I will say that Best Publisher winner was once again Tor. So I will also pull out that
in the category of Best Publisher which was previously awarded under Best Book Publisher
I think it has been Tor since about 1988 as far as I can tell although it has been split into
it's been Best Publisher or Best Publisher Test imprint or Best Book Publisher at different times
as far as I can tell they've all since 1988 gone to Tor so maybe I mean I'm not saying Tor out good
but I am saying maybe it's time we thought about whether there are other publishers who may have
published something good in the past 35 years. It is tricky to look at because I've looked up on the
ISFDB and it's sort of split into five different awards at different times but it looks like
previously it was mostly Valentine Delray and then passed seriously onto Tor or Tor,
St Martin's and I think those are the only winners. Probably represents the you know the
makeup of the voters and that they're probably predominantly American and probably do read a lot
books from Tor but there's a number of you know British imprints on there in the the long list
angry robot glance orbit and also small presses like Small Bit Press so yeah. Having said this I
bet next year that we're not just going to be Tor.com instead. I said that. Oh do you think you have
that much power over the locus fetus list? No I don't I think it will just be to spite me basically
anyway the the the long list I think we mentioned the long list the long list do all look pretty good
I've read some of the fiction of the short fiction lists while I was reading for the hugos and I
liked pretty much all the ones on these lists I've read. So as always locus is the locus awards
long list is quite a good survey of the fields and has loads of good stuff in it. It does and I suspect
it's going to have some crossover with the Hugo nominations when we see those. Yes probably.
Finalists. Finalists. There was a tempest in a teacup on a social network no one can get on
where some people were unhappy that John Scalzi won for best science fiction novel and John Scalzi
was unhappy that those people were unhappy and that went about as well as you'd expect. There
is an interesting bit from the July 2023 issue of locus. Decide you preservation society by John
Scalzi won with the smallest winning lead this year just 17 points ahead of the equality by Emily
St. John Mandel which had the most votes and first place votes and would have won without the
doubling of subscriber points and this is because if you are a locus subscriber your vote
counts double in the locus awards so if you were annoyed by any of that it's all locus readers fault
is that accurate is that is that the line we're taking is that good I think that's good
dear's passionate I mean I didn't really follow the slap fight because I'm not on Twitter anymore
I just hear about the snap slap fights third hand which is I gotta be honest much more fun
it no one's on Twitter anymore it's true I tried clicking the link you put to the tweet in and it
just said no error so I'm like okay this is good
I am a member of the BSA and the BSA sent me their June 2023 newsletter I read in the newsletter
that there are proposals for new awards categories which reflect the expanding communities of science
fiction the BSA are connected with and then they are detailed in the minutes of the AGM now they say
that these will be put out in more detail in the July newsletter so maybe there will be more detail
then but as far as I can tell from the minutes there are going to be some new BSA awards and that's
exciting so we're going to talk about it here so there is going to be a split they are splitting
non-fiction into short non-fiction which is under 30,000 words or under 30 minutes and long non-fiction
which is over 30,000 words or over 30 minutes and you will notice listeners that that has the word
minutes in it as well as words and therefore I believe it means that podcasts such as ours will
be officially eligible rather than under the radar eligible because I assume the intention is to
encompass well and also it says non-fiction any platform which is the other key clue there will
be we will be eligible again which is cool because long-time listeners might remember we were nominated
in 2021 but we weren't nominated in 2022 and I suspect part of the reason was that we pointed
out we were not technically eligible so so to try to try to what we we were nominated and we got
a got into our gladrags and went along to the awards ceremony and a lot of people came up to us
said you know that we've read the rules and you're not actually eligible which was true
well no it wasn't people didn't come up to us they read the description of the award when they
were awarding the awards and I noticed that the description did make it very clear it had to be
written down which I just assumed that because we were nominated we were eligible but that is as
it turns out bad assumption listeners don't make that assumption necessarily but anyway this is
good I think and they're also introducing original audio fiction they're introducing best collection
and they are splitting the short story I believe into novella and into short story although I am not
100% clear about that so yes there's also I believe a new one for best translated work of short
fiction but that's going to be a jury award not bs-fay award in the same style as the others
did you mention the one for collections I did mention the one for collections and so this is
all very interesting in a vacuum I think several very good ideas here my worry is participation in
the bs-fay award is not always as high as one might ideally like it to be it's lower than you
like it to be it's lower both at nomination stage which means that things sometimes get onto the
final ballot with very small numbers of nominations and it's also lower than you'd like to be at
finalist stage considering what a large member organization the bs-fay is and the fact that
east econ members can also vote in the bs-fay awards it would be nice if there were more people
I mean basically a lot of you guys out there are eligible to vote in these awards at both stages
please do that it's good because broader participation is better so I should say I am the one of us who
is not a bs-fay member at present do we get much detail on how many people actually voted
or nominated no I'm relying on insider gossip here yeah so it is it is quite difficult to know and
I think if I was at the AGM I might have wanted to have a bit more detail on that so I'd sort of know
maybe I've been into this but I would want to kind of know how many people you've you got
that seem to be part of your sort of active nominating body but you could also you could argue that
the way to get more people engaged with your awards is to give them more categories of things they
really care about and so maybe with more categories you will get a more engaged voting body so that
that was like what I was going to come back to which is that's the counter argument I think is that if
you recognize more categories that people care about you might find that there's an uptick it might be
that this is the first step in doing that I would also say that this was based on a committee they
did look at the viability of each of the things they proposed so presumably this has been discussed
at some point I will also say and it's interesting because I hadn't read this until just now but
one of the reasons stipulated in the report from the committee is that the reason this is happening
now is because the award booklet is no longer being printed it's only going to be a PDF which
means that expanding the award doesn't cost extra money for printing and I had not really thought
of that as like a consideration but I guess that is that is another consideration happening here
that's an interesting thing imagine if they got rid of all their other print publications
well so yeah BSA awards interesting stuff I have a slight worry about that because although
increasing the number of reward categories doesn't it doesn't cause them actual cash problems because
of printing increasing the number of awards materially increases the amount of admin work
and as we know from the Hugo Awards the the admin award for the the admin work for awards can become
overwhelming yeah I'm I'm slightly surprised they did so many at once rather than kind of doing
you know doing maybe doing these changes one at a time but maybe there's a
I sense you're just doing them all at once and seeing how they go and then you can drop them if
it turns out there is no appetite for particularly ones I said I could have sworn that the BSA
had an award for best translation or best translation work that was a jury award but am I barking up
totally the wrong tree was non-fictioned jury for a while someone who can like remember the 2010s
please write it. Karen Mark you know everything about the history of the BSA
A until they decide they didn't care about the history so please write it. Also anyone who can
tell me why I can no longer remember the 2010s also please write. Oh it gets so much worse
Liz you have no idea that was the BSA award
I have a pick and somewhere I have some notes because normally when I pick books I have the books
but the books are so heavy I was like I'm not taking them camping right so my pick this week is museum
catalogs and in particular the museum catalogs of two of the museums I went to last two of the
exhibitions I went to last year which were science fiction, voyage to the edge of imagination at the
science museum and in the black fantastic at the Hayward Gallery and I think both of those got picked
as picks on the podcast. Now museum catalogs used to just have pictures of everything that was in
the museum and some text about the artist that more or less duplicated the material you could see
in the exhibition but they have worked out that they can limit the amount of information in the
exhibition and put it in museum catalogs instead for the nerds and charge a lot of money for these
books so being me and a massive cheapskate I went to my library as soon as these books were published
and said please get me copies of these books and now almost a year later I have them both at once
so they are large very interesting hardbacks and they do they address the subject in two different
ways so voyage to the edge of imagination um glim organ has collected contributions from a range
of different academics to write chapters about the topic and this is illustrated with material
about the exhibition as well so it does it would represent it would be a great souvenir of the
exhibition if you wanted to keep these sorts of things in your house which I don't um and that's
kind of explore the themes of the exhibition in more depth through a variety of different perspectives
and in the black fantastic has the author echoation actually going into more depth on the topic and
the themes of the exhibition but pulling in some contributions from other people but not with the
sense of it being an academic work in chapters in quite the same way I think the thing that struck
me most about this is that several of the reviews of voyage to the edge of the imagination have
suggested that the edge of the imagination of what is essentially odd visual science fiction
of the last 50 years we're not actually all that imaginative that the edge of the imagination
is not that far away because of the limits of human imagination and then you look at it in the
black fantastic where echelon is playing with essentially the whole of black culture not merely
afrofuturism but also lots of different sorts of um black art and um and the whole of the myth of
all of the african peoples which is an enormous range of culture and has and of course it's
it's massively more imaginative than the relatively narrow um robots and spaceship stuff that is
it there's most of the stuff of science fiction edge of the imagination these are two very good
books and I recommend them both and both books made me think again about what I've seen in their
relative exhibitions and think about what they were telling me in different ways and I'd strongly
recommend them and you can get them from your library by pushing your name down and waiting
for a very long time. I'm going next so my pick is a book I read basically in one sitting while on
my uh some holidays it is a novella called Stealing for the Sky by Adam Roberts which
it seemed to sort of sneak out I mean Adam Roberts writes a lot of kind of well regarded science
fiction novels many of which have ended up on award shortlist and Silling for the Sky I think
is by a different press than his novels come out and it just sort of like snuck out it seems and
it's it's quite enjoyable all the reviews say is in the style of Donald Westlake and all that I
have never read but it's basically like one of these sort of it's sort of a science fiction thriller
with a kind of very a very violent and gory edge I mean if anyone who is planning to read this does
not like kind of a protagonist who is not afraid to deal out a lot of violence in the cause of
doing the um fevery that he does but it seems it's quite entertaining and it ends up with him
basically stealing a mystery device kind of in the course of another like high steers pulling
um which has some really odd momentum effects and then he ends up he mostly still satellites and
he steals a strange orb and then he ends up getting chased by the authorities chased by Russians
going out to try and heist an obsolete rocket in the middle of the Russian winter and it's just
quite a fun kind of techno thriller near future you know in the the protagonist whose name is
Starman slightly unbelievably but it's his nickname is um essentially stealing things to try and get
enough money to go into space and probably get away from people so it's it's it's quite short I mean
it's a novella I don't think it's going to win any awards but I did find it kind of an entertaining
thing to read while I was in transit because it's quite pacy and keeps your keeps your attention
nice I had a moment of cognitive dissonance because you said Donald Westlake and I was like
what isn't that the chair of the Wussfuss mark protection committee but that's Donald Eastlake
yeah wrong one so uh completely different lake Adam Roberts is one of the authors that I do
keep dipping into because he does normally write quite chewy stuff that is trying to expand my
horizons I mean he doesn't necessarily always succeed and it does sound like you've just described
a Adam Roberts novella which is just kind of cheerily pacy and entertaining and I'm sure it's
the same Adam Roberts so one thing I would say is that I read quite a lot of Adam Roberts I haven't
read all of his work but you know I've probably read at least 10 probably more of his novels but
I do think he you know there there is some kind of common ground to them but I don't think he writes
the same book twice yeah no I'd agree with that which you know I applaud him for even when it's one
that doesn't quite work for me I do applaud him for what he's doing I would say this one has some
commonalities with yellow blue tibia because he goes back to the sort of it's in Russia and
there's always sort of the slightly slightly comedically done Russian accent kind of thing of like dour
Russian heavies so there's that in it but I think because it's so short and because it's basically
kind of pretty tight perspective on this warm hardball protagonist who is just going around doing
kind of a couple of heists and that's basically the whole thing I think it does manage to be quite
pacy maybe pacy than a lot of his regular novels but I mean I went into it I think I picked it up
picked up of Amazon because it's very cheap on Amazon like I think it was under a quid and so I
thought well I'll give it a go and I didn't really have many expectations for it because I hadn't read
any of the comparator things and yeah I just found it to be a good little you know two-hour diversion
Adam Roberts is one of the people who I would be absolutely delighted to see on next year's hugo
ballot when um the Worldconners in the UK so we might get more British stuff on the ballot
so therefore write some good things in 2022 Adam what is this book eligible no this is a
it's a 2022 book oh boo so you need so he needs to write a 2023 one get your skates on Adam I honestly
don't expect Adam Roberts to end up on the Hugo shortlist I mean he's been on the BSA
shortlist but I don't know if these books kind of have enough mass appeal to get on the Hugo
shortlist I think they are one thing always very different for each other they are sometimes
quite difficult reads quite philosophical and maybe they've never quite passed that threshold
of being on the Hugo ballot I also don't know if he has a high readership in the US whereas for
instance I know let's say Adrian Tricowski now has like a US publisher and gets more attention in the
US and that might be part of why he's starting to turn upon on Hugo ballots but like you say 2024
is going to be 2024 is going to be an incredibly odd year for Hugo nominations because it's going
to be anyone who joined to vote in 2023 which could be a lot it could be and we'll see the Chinese
influence on there which may be persistent at 2024 plus a whole load more Europeans than you might
have had for the past few years plus the Americans who are still joining to come to Glasgow or just
to have voting and nomination rights could be really odd next year I look forward to it
I'm going to pick I'm going to not pick something and then I'm going to do my pick
so I'm not going to pick every clerk award finalist that as I read them because I think that would
get tedious for everyone but I have just finished reading Venomous Lumpsucker by Ned Bowman which
I've put in my Goodreads review that it felt to me like in some places the Ministry for the
Future by Kim Stanley Robertson but in other places it felt like Ready Player One by Ernest Cline
and it really distresses me that like I can see how this book could have been amazing
but there is just so many bits where it isn't and there was one bit where I did a full body
eye roll which I didn't know I was capable of oh could you can you do want to demonstrate what
a full body eye roll looks like John for the for the audio podcast it's like ah it's like
some of it's very insightful and interesting and some of it is extremely crude and uninsightful
and sort of very unfunny and unwitty you know in a part of it feel very incisive and cutting and
part of it feels zany in a bad way and I found that incredibly frustrating. Can I just check
is it the bits that were like Kim Stanley Robinson that were the insightful ones and the bits that
were unfunny and forced like Ready Player One by any chance? You have successfully you have
successfully grasped the key yeah it's tricky I do wonder whether someone more grounded in the
genre would have avoided some of the zanniness but I don't know whether that's fair I don't know
whether that's fair or not really because I get the impression this comes from the literary angle
as did the anomaly but yes I didn't hate it but I and I wanted to like it more than I ended up
liking it which was a frustrating experience. Does it at any point have chapters where we just
like list a whole bunch of shit? There's a lot of info dumping and there's a lot of I'm very clever
and have worked out the I'm going to tell you things in the guise of what are the characters now
which is yeah in that same kind of way that Ready Player One does. This is of course not my pick
I'm just explaining why it's not my pick for the for the listener. My actual pick is
Across the Spider-Verse which I went to see with friends of the
Friends of the Pod Neil Harrison and Nick Clark in the Jamdrah Cinema in Willie Bay which
lovely little cinema and it's very good it is interesting I believe it is spoiler half a movie
yeah but I don't mind that I mean it became very clear it was half a movie when I looked at my
watch and I was like well it feels like we're about at the end of act two and we have been in the
cinema for over two hours and I do not understand how they could do a compelling act three in the
next sort of 20 minutes and then there was a 2B continued and I was like oh yes that makes sense
in the in the sense of what I know about the structures of movies. I don't think this is a
problem at all if you know it's happening. I didn't know it was happening and I wasn't bothered
and you know I've seen lots of good movies in the cinema where well I really like the first
half of June but I went into that clear-eyed believing I was getting the first half of June
I think if I'd gone into the cinema believing I was seeing the entire plot I would have been
pretty pissed off because it really it really just does film the first half of the thing.
Dune didn't market itself as a part one right all of the posters just said Dune.
I think if you were paying attention to Dune you knew Dune was part one of a two-part story
and if you're paying attention to this you probably know the same but both movies have not
marketed themselves as part one which it like you know is not great but I've noticed a lot of
people talking about this in ways that I think are slightly okay so people have been
commending the art style which I think is great and obviously the first one did a lot in terms
of animation techniques which was very fresh. One of the things that's been repeatedly kind of
praised is the art style of Spider Gwen's universe and it's slightly frustrating because no one is
discussing that. Everyone is discussing that as if that was something the film did and that is
just straight from the comics and that is something the comics have been doing since Spider Gwen was
a character in the comic so like I do find it slightly frustrating that a lot of people are
giving Miller and Lord the Crayard it for that in a way that I think is weird because I think it
betrays a lack of knowledge of the source material. Not unusual for comic adaptations in movies.
No no probably not. It's very common for things that are straight out of the comics to be
hailed as as fresh and innovative in movies because one of the things that you could do in comics is
explore cinematographic styles at low cost. Much lower cost than making movies which is an
expensive thing to do. Yes in general I think the pacing is weird in the start because it starts
by telling Spider Gwen's story and then kind of cuts to the title sequence and takes us back to
Miles probably about 20 minutes in which is quite a long time to basically do an act zero and that
was it didn't feel the structure is slightly weird as a result and I'm glad they did that but
certainly at the beginning I was a bit like this is not quite as well paced as the original which is
probably about as perfect as you could structure a movie but when it gets into things it's really
good and I also find it interesting that they don't use the characters from the original movie as
prominently as they might have done. Like obviously Gwen's in it a lot of Miles's in it a lot but
the other characters are like not featured as much which I was a bit surprised by by assuming that
they will come back in the third installment but in general I really liked it and I think it does
a good job of doing something a bit different with the series than you might otherwise have done
and also I really like how enthusiastically they've embraced the complete lunacy of the
Spider-verse because like they were just growing stuff in the film and I was like I cannot believe
that they are putting all of this in the movie because it doesn't really be kind of hard to
work out what's going on in the comics and there you can reread the page but this is like the web
of destiny and you're like oh my god it's all here which is fabulous but kind of mad.
That was true the first one though. Oh but the second one have you seen the second one?
No should I? No so the second one rams it up to like 11 or 12 I think. They fully embrace well
because I think the first one the first one does have like the multiverse stuff in but it doesn't
go anywhere near as much into like the mysticism behind it that's in the comics and the second one
I feel like is starting to touch on all that more and I think is kind of I like it a lot but I'm not
necessarily I don't think I would have guessed that that was the way they were going to go.
Maybe that's the best way to put it. So yeah. It sounds great. I liked it a great deal I would
highly recommend seeing it in the cinema even though it is a part one. For most of the
reason I regret not seeing Dune in the cinema despite it being a part one although Dune I didn't
go and see not because it was a part one but because it was too long however rule about
long movies. Well that was the Hold To Thought podcast and it's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me and somehow while we were doing that every Lebanese restaurant on my
delivery app has gone offline. Probably because it rained while we were doing podcasts.
I think we're getting through it. I think we've got some stuff here this is good.
I think we're done apart from pics aren't we? Probably that out of a pic.
Yeah you do you've got a pic Liz. Search your feelings you know it to be true.
I did watch Rogue One. Pick, pick the beach. I've been to the beach. You went to the beach last time
we recorded right? Yeah I mean I'm not gonna pick like Indonesia it's my pic. That is very nice.
Let me see what books I've read someone else go first. Why what's wrong with picking Indonesia?
Is it very nice should we go? I'm not going to pick a country for a pic. It's not science fictional.
You can because it's the summer of fun. Well we're going to pick the summer of fun then I'm
picking sport and you probably don't want that. Oh do it do it. You need all sport or a specific
sport. No specific sport. No I've got something it's all right. Pick a sport pick a sport pick a sport.
No we're good I've got a book. Pick a sport that's not cricket because I feel like we should have
equal representation for other sports that are played in summer. Well I feel this is like
just escalating the off topic cricket mentions of the pod. The theme music for this episode was
Surf Shimmy by Kevin MacLeod and Combetech.com used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.