Hello listeners, it's John here. I just want to let you know that Liz's microphone sounds very
slightly different in this episode. We need to get on because Liz is starting to make
I need to get to bed soon because I've got another club meeting noises.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 57th episode of Octa Thorpe, which is coming to you on the 12th
of May 2022. I'm John Coxon, I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Bassie.
And we are recording our first episode after Eastercon, but before we get to Eastercon,
we have some letters of comment. So we had a letter from Malcolm Hutchison that said that in the
episode before last, the sound I made at the start of the episode made him visualise me as a
muppet in a good way, which is nice. Well, there's the chapter art. Oh yes, I'm well up for that.
Well, it may need to be all three of us as muppets, so that might be a bit hard.
Can my muppet have a glittery octa-thorpe on its forehead? Yeah, I should think so.
Thank you very much to Meg MacDonald, who did a letter of comment in the form of a
glyph on my skin, which is the first time we've had a letter of comment on that medium. So thank you
very much Meg. She also decorated me. Chris Garcia sent us a letter saying, "I don't like live
episode usually, but this one is really good because it's y'all." And I don't know if I could say y'all.
Is it y'all? And y'all didn't try making it into a live show, any different from the regular show.
Maybe that's not normal. So I think that's a compliment, but basically when we're live,
apparently we sound exactly like when we're not live, which is... Well, no, I think when we're
not live, we sometimes do have show notes and preparation. So thank you Chris for that.
He also says that streaky bacon is the only true bacon, which is another example of when Chris is
wrong about things. Yeah, it's sad, isn't it? It's just, I'm much prefer what he's right about
things. He still hasn't told me which author wrote me. Oh yeah. I'm still waiting Chris. Sorry Chris is
right about streaky bacon. No. Certainly not right about British streaky bacon. American streaky
bacon is very nice. No, it's not American streak. Americans don't understand how to do streaky
bacon. In fact Americans don't understand how to do bacon, but British streaky bacon. No, American
bacon is better than British streaky bacon. 100%. Because? Because it's crispy and nice,
as opposed to sort of limp and sad. No, it's crispy if you cook it properly in Britain. This is a
matter of how you fry it, right? Get good bacon from a good butcher, fry it. Sticky bacon turns into
the most marvelous thing, and then you eat it on bomb cakes with brown sauce. It's bad you won't
eat bacon in the UK because she fundamentally thinks that our streaky bent bacon is complete crap,
and she just waits to go back. You need to get a decent bacon. Get better bacon. We've had it from
a decent butcher. It's not a problem with butchers. It's not a problem with provenance. It's a problem
with our country, Alison, our country. So problem with the pigs? I don't know, maybe streaky bacon in
the UK is not quite the same as American bacon. I think it's the problem. No, no, it's a different
cut of bacon. But streaky bacon is the best bacon because fundamentally, fundamentally,
I just like lard. Sticky bacon has its own lard in it, right? So it literally cooks itself in lard.
Backbacon's better. You're overruled. Yeah, I'm a john. No, so wrong. Official opinion of the
Oct thought podcast by majority vote that backbacon is best, and that's going to be the episode title,
and you can't stop me. Boom. I love nobody likes middle. Maybe in hindsight, listening to all the
bacon chat is a good thing. We did not actually sit down and have breakfast together at East
Oh, Chris also wrote to us with a lock on the previous episode. He says the fan awards and
coffee was late shows how much are outside of fanzine fandom he is at the moment. He still does
scenes, but he's not quite a part of the core flu community, which he finds kind of sad because
he loves scenes and a bunch of the stuff the core flu regulars do. And that kind of ties into
stuff we were saying in that episode. And that is interesting because I think Chris is one of the
fairly prolific old school fanzine editors. Roman wrote to us on Easter Sunday when we
were scoffing chocolate catching COVID and preparing for our live show to send us greetings from the
Easter bill be, for which we're very grateful because we do not have Easter bill be's in Britain
or Thailand. I have a question about what is an Easter bill we well, it's a bill be at Easter.
So a fundamental question here is an adorable Australian animal which I've already drawn.
So I'm going to try and draw the bill be muppet now.
Excellent stuff. Thank you Roman. Oh they're cute. Sorry I look but you don't know,
bill be's are very cute. I looked at bill be's they've got adorable giant ears.
They have adorable giant ears and also glasses at a silly beard.
Oh yeah that is a daft looking animal. It really is yeah. So it looks like I don't know what it
looks like. John the bill be muppet. Oh that's my art task for the week isn't it? Yes.
We have one more lock which was from Jersey Griffin who says that the Hello Internet podcast
did a vinyl episode before jumping the shark and doing a four to five minute wax cylinder episode
and that is interesting. I'll try and find a link and pop it in the show notes.
Oh a four to five minute wax cylinder episode. Sorry I thought you said a 45 minute wax
cylinder episode. Now it's like it's a lot of wax. What was the wax cylinder episode?
Someone else did a wax cylinder episode that we have been alerted to by one of our listeners
as well as false light.
Well we all have fun at EasterCon. Obviously we talked about our impressions of EasterCon last
week but this time we're going to talk about what happened after EasterCon which is that quite
a lot of people went home and discovered that they are caught COVID at the convention including
me. I'm all better now thank you very much. That's the bit you could edit the coffin to John.
Let's help you another one along in a minute. What buses? It's interesting because the west
con happened the same weekend with the identical COVID policy to EasterCon and did not have very
many cases possibly because there was much COVID in the area but also possibly because
people at North Westcon behaved slightly differently than people at EasterCon.
I went around the convention. I mean I mostly did follow the conventions COVID policy and I
masked up except when I was eating and drinking in bars. How much time did I spend eating and
drinking in bars? I mean a lot. Until 7 a.m. on the only 6.30 and I didn't spend all of that time
in a bar. I spent so that time in a corridor and I didn't spend all of that time. I just
spend all of that time on masks. One of the things that España said on the way home was that if we do
because España stayed up late on the Sunday night and we both agreed that in future conventions
we might go to bed sort of 1 a.m.ish on purpose because the masking dropped noticeably after
about midnight every night that I stayed up that late and that's like a mixture of things like
people up that late are generally drinking but also like as you get drunker your ability to
remember to put your mask on between so it's a bit of a decrease and so I think the convention
got riskier after midnight than it was before would be my guess. Conventions are normally
riskier after the midnight. I'm not sure I would pick that at midnight. What I would say is during
the daytime when people were in panels or in the dealers room or even in the games room they seem
to be mostly masked. Of course there were exceptions for people with medical exemptions. People on
panels often were not wearing masks because of the need to read and there were a few notable
exceptions of people I saw like in panels who seemed to be slowly sipping a drink for the whole
hour and I get made and recently cranky by this and I saw you and I know who you are but let's
move on. But then basically what happens is you know the program the program dies down people start
going out to dinner or go out to dinner and then come back and sit in the bar and then you're
drinking and you're fairly continuously drinking from your pint of beer or your glass of wine or
eating your pizza and you tend not to put your masks back on and then basically you end up with
a large room either in this case the the real L bar or the hotel bar which is full of people who
are not really masked and then you know I was I put mine back on for things like you know making a
quick trip to loo or going to the bar to buy another drink but fundamentally I'm spending a lot
of that time without a mask on and I think that's my guess is that's where quite a lot of the transmission
occurred and the later it got the less people had masks on but also the later it got I think
you know once you get past one or two a.m. there's a lot fewer people still around so that probably
does help a bit yeah I mean I'm not sure that the actual number of people in the bar after 1 a.m.
was the problem here though it's certainly true that the people who were up late were more likely
to be people who catch COVID but they're probably more sociable people generally I wanted to single
out two events that were not just hanging out in the bar the first was a disco which was a program
item and the COVID policy was completely clear that if you're in the disco and dancing you should
have been wearing masks and as far as I could tell from the many many photos of people singing along
in the disco and having a great time nobody in the disco wore a mask and that's probably an extremely
spready sort of an event and the other event I want to single out was the voxel party which obviously
was not a good official program item but was in the same room that we had Octa thought live in which
was one of the less well ventilated rooms in the convention and it was quite crowded and obviously
a lot of drinking was people were actively drinking and obviously if you were actively drinking you
do not have to wear a mask because you know active drinking is what we do and I think that was probably
quite a spready event but you can't tell. I shown a categorizable what I said about my
Eastcon experience as one woman super spreader event Alice and Scott has absolutely no regrets
and I don't on my account and I'm catching it and I've not been very sick but I you know I have a
friend who spent an art in hospital and I have another friend who went home to with COVID to be
the sole carer for her her aged parents so I think there's cases like that where you do have to go
well maybe we should be a little bit more careful and see if we can't reduce the transmission further.
Yeah it was it was definitely not great I think we ended up you know the number of reports
suggest about 10% of the convention reports at a positive test in the kind of 10 days at the
convention or in the sort of 10 days following it which is I would say pretty high and you know
still higher than I think than things like Novocarne which we thought had quite a few cases last year
and definitely much higher than NorwestCon. So there are things you could do but I struggled
to find ways that you could do things that aren't fundamentally you shouldn't all sit in the real
little bar or in a path you're in a disco with your masks off for five hours and it feels like
everyone was sort of willing to if you're looking in those spaces I presume you're willing to kind
of take the risk of being in those on mass spaces because they enjoyed chatting and drinking with
people. I did actually circulate in bars less than I normally would and I don't know whether that was
a deliberate thing or accidental but I spent the number of people I actually spent a lot of time
chatting to is it was much smaller than it might have been at the average EastCon.
I had kind of a couple of long conversations each night rather than Melly.
Yeah I think I probably kind of flitted about from group to group less although I think I do that
less than Allison anyway and definitely there's one night where we sort of sat in a corridor
and around a corridor away from the real elbow rather than sitting in the real elbow all that
was wanted to do with the availability of chairs. Oh that's my favourite space in the park in
for sitting and chatting. Is that little bit round the corner from the real elbow?
I mean obviously if I tell everyone then everyone will want it.
Yes, sorry but I definitely think not getting covid was a case of I was very recently vaccinated.
I was quite diligent about mask wearing and I wore quite a good mask and I just was lucky not to
catch it when the people I had prolonged on mass conversations with. I definitely had prolonged
mass conversations with people who were positive at the time but I guess we won't know for sure.
I put in the show notes. Turns out beer sharing is not as dodgy as all that and this is quick to
be up on that. Well I mean yeah there are photos of obviously me, John and Allison sharing one beer
on the Upstalk Live at EastCon at a time when unknown to us all Allison had probably got covid
and we seemed to have escaped and that she didn't pass it on to me or John. But I mean I think there
were at least three or four people in that room who probably had covid at the time. So...
It seems likely right like given that 10% of people tested positive after the event if you
assume that was proportionate in all of the panel items and there were about 40 people in the room
I would have expected of three or four. Obviously like I'm not an expert but Liz is an expert and
she just said it and I'm agreeing with her so I'm definitely right. I really wanted to
Liz to read out the thing she said of the show notes which I thought was very funny.
I mean I buy that I mean that specifically I noticed three or four people in the room who then
reported positive tests so I'm not basing it on any mathematical thing I'm saying oh those three
people who are my mates who I saw were then like oh I'm positive. No no it was it was the thing
where you were like I was like beer sharing is that dodgy and you were like not compared to
turning your head to spray aerosols on your canvas. Yes so we also discovered at OptiThult Live
that one thing that Alison cannot refrain from doing on panels is turning her head to look at a
fellow panelist even when that means taking her mouth well away from the microphone which I thought
was a major problem at the time but it turns out that may you know pale and it's significant
compared to fact that Alison was therefore stewing aerosols directly and being John for an hour.
But we had both taken the sensible precaution of topping up our antibodies pre-esticon.
Liz with a jab from Thailand and me from getting Covid from movers and so you know one of those is
a more sensible approach than the other I think but it did stand a thing good stead for the
convention. I mean Mark and I so when Mark Plummer came down with Covid he sent me a text saying
you know at least this is well timed for e-sticon and I did it was one of the things that I thought
when I got out I was like oh thank goodness it means I'm very unlikely to come down with it on my
holiday to Spain and my trip to Eastcon and that so it so it turned out to be.
Yeah I think we both took the more readily available way of getting antibodies in our
countries at the respective times yeah. Yeah so probably I should have gone for a few part
to a few parties a month before Easticon or hung out with Mark Plummer more.
Just move house Alison. So the other thing I wanted to pick up is that I've heard some people
saying well you know actually a lot of a lot of people took a calculated risk here they knew what
they were doing they knew what they were getting into and a lot of people have reminded us of the
Chester Easticon which is about the same size as this one where about the third of the convention
came down with Noravirus afterwards and I have to say my experience of Covid has not been as bad
as many people's I didn't catch Noravirus or that occasion but many periods people's experience
of post Eastcon Noravirus so if I if there hadn't been a pandemic going on I wouldn't have
noticed this this illness as being anything untoward. I mean I've never had Noravirus so it's a difficult
craving. Do not recommend it. I think Chester was slightly smaller by I take your point.
Do we want to talk about Noravirus-Con's case three and case five? Yes so I was first
alerted to this by a tweet from Shonna Maguire but Noravirus-Con published you know their own case reports
of people who reported Covid positive tests after Noravirus-Con on their website and it turned out by
positive tests after the con they also mean positive tests at the con or before the con and in
at least two cases positive tests after before the con and symptoms and continuing to go to the
convention. So yeah I'm just sort of I just look at it and I'm staggered like even if you did that
why would you then go report it? I guess your conscience doesn't prick you that maybe oh I have
Covid I shouldn't go into it in the games room but it does prick you that you should then tell people
later on that you're in the games room with Covid? Yeah it's just I can't get my head around the mindset.
So I am fairly certain that there were people in this position at Eastrecon. I don't have names
or other things this isn't like I so is so but I think that we almost certainly in a convention of
600 odd people had people who knew perfectly well they got Covid and were keeping their mouth shut
about it and go to the convention anyway. And those people are absolute rotters and I think they
should sod off. I'm abandoning all balance or pretense of diplomacy if you are one of these
people stop listening delete the podcast I don't like you. No no no carry on listening if you're
all these listeners right in so we could roundly mock you. I think it's reasonable to assume that
there were there was a lot of infection around but you know we didn't need a lot of infection there
were plenty of people who tested positive during the convention and there's plenty of time at
least to come to spread the infection and we are one community everyone socialises with everyone
else. I also don't know because obviously the other thing with Eastrecon is that we were not
the hotel we used Eastrecon is also a hotel used by a lot of people who fly with airlines and so
it might also be the case that like even if everyone even if Alison is wrong and no one at the
Eastrecon was attending suspecting they had covid you know there were vectors probably.
There were a lot of sick people in the in the breakfast room on Friday morning I think not going
if you're thinking about things you simple things you could do to reduce your risk at Eastrecon
travelling on the Friday is probably one of them because because there were a lot of non-fans in
the hotel on the Thursday night and obviously those people weren't following the convention's
mass policy at breakfast. Although I will say the masking at Eastrecon was better than the masking
at the hotel Liz and I stayed at when we visited Reading with Alison last summer because my god
that was more crowded and less masks and that was I mean that was in summer so I guess the cases
were lower then but I will say Eastrecon did a pretty good job of the Eastrecon was better than
other hotel breakfast so I have been to lately so that is good well done Eastrecon committee
and I think in general the Eastrecon committee should be applauded I think they did about as
good a job as they possibly could have done maybe with the exception of better enforcement in the
disco what do you what do you two think is that reasonable statement do we reckon?
Yeah I mean I think you could have been stricter you could you could say something like okay
the real Elba or some social spaces are designated like eating and drinking spaces and in other
places you must remain masked except for you know to take a sip of your water or something so
basically try and encourage people not to take points into panels and sit there slowly sipping
them and things like that and then in a way it would let attendees choose if they go into the
social spaces or not but it is difficult because if they said okay you know real Elba we want you
to try and mask up between sips and make sure you mask when you are moving around and mask when
you are going to the bar there is still the hotel bar which is not a convention space and so they
cannot really enforce people masking there particularly as there were non-convention guests in the hotel
bar you know acting in you know in complete accordance with the you know the current state of
things in the UK which is that people don't habitually wear masks at all so yeah I think there are
you know there are possibly a few things you could have done but it would have been quite
difficult to actually practically implement those the convention was also under volunteered
and one of the consequences of that was especially during setup when volunteers were working very
very hard there was a lot of not being masked whilst getting the work done going on and I think
if you had a convention where you had enough volunteers including enough volunteers to
account for people who came down with covid um you could say but we are going to require you to
mask while working um in setup we're not going to actually allow you to have pockets where you go
well we're working on the convention in this space and you're not masking and I think we could have
done that and I think we could have done better because for program items the rule was you can
bring a drink in but you have to just raise your mask have a sim remask not everybody was doing
that and I think we could have policed that sort of thing I don't know and I will say sorry tip
button before lizards had a turn but I will say one of the other things is banyan I said on the
train home was a few drink of edges I do wonder whether there needs to be a rule around you
not allowed to be drinking panels because as much as that would be slightly annoying I do wonder
whether the bonus would be worth it I mean I very rarely take drinks into panels because I always
spill them um so this would not really affect me negatively very much so maybe I'm wrong I don't
want to restrict people being able to take water in oh well yeah no I mean I think that's fair when
I say no food and drink I'm sort of doing the because lecture theatres often say no food and
drink but there is an acceptance that water is pretty much okay um so yes good point Liz do you
want to get a word in uh I think I've had quite a lot of words on this one but I will take the
opportunity for another I think you're right but I mean when I'm drinking water from a bottle of
water I'm not drinking it like I am from a pint I'm like I will really just have a drink and then
put my mask out and that's what I was doing in all the panels I didn't take any beers into panels
this time um I thought it was able to leave my mask on because I was surrounded by people that I
probably basically I was sitting next to different people in every panel and there might be people I
didn't know was at least in the bar I was sitting next to usually the same people consistently so
you may have been unmasked but maybe that kind of limited my exposure to that smaller group of people
I would also say that uh isakon actually didn't say you had to be masked they said you had to wear
a face covering and I think you could be stricter about was as an acceptable face covering I mean
it's it's still kind of surprising to me because I come to the UK and like to me there's still a
shock to it because my expectation is if I get on a train everyone on the train will be wearing a
mask and they're almost all well-fitting surgical masks or you know kf94 and 95 masks at this point
with very few cloth masks you know and this is just kind of what what I expect so it was quite
spicy people with sort of like very loose masks or bandanas or face shields or things that probably
not really having much of an effect I don't know if I you'd just get that little bit of extra safety
by saying people have to wear an actual face mask which is well fitted I will say like and obviously
I'm not an expert but I would I have moved to using FFP2 and FFP3 masks not everyone will find
that they fit their faces very well but there's also the N95, the N99 and various other countries
standards and I would encourage listeners to explore the options because I find I find the FFP3s
especially are actually much nicer to wear than a cloth mask cloth mask because they don't fog my
glasses up so I have found that to be an enormous quality of life upgrade generally but certainly
at this point I think it's probably time to make the switch because they fit you John people were
seeing the praises of KF94 at Smuffcord and it was a it was completely revelation,
being so much happier. Yeah that's so much more comfortable but I mean I guess two more things
I want to say one is you know we can suggest things around the edges they could have done but I don't
think there is anything that would have fundamentally made the difference from 10% got infected to you
know one person got infected or zero people got infected apart from you have to mask up everywhere
and even then people still going to eat hotel breakfast so maybe this is all like fiddling
around the edges of the problem. Can we can we get into the bit that you had in the show notes about
the um are you on my Norwegian Christmas party and it goes? The other thing the question here is of
course we don't have a control easter-colm we don't know how much spread there would have been
if we'd had no cover policy at all apart from you know don't actively spit on people. Yeah so I
I found this an interesting paper which is from the very early stage of the Omicron variant really I
think before we knew a lot about it and this has probably become written up as a paper and become
noteworthy because it was a large outbreak but it's basically a Christmas party where all the attendees
were vaccinated and asked to test beforehand and they still managed to spread to I think 74%
of attendees so if you think of that as being like the upper bound of what is possible in a super
spread event then EasterCon is doing poorly but clearly not as poorly as we could have done if
we had had no masking rules whatsoever maybe. Yeah so I have to say there's a caveat here because
a lot of people in Britain have had COVID in the last six weeks so which is probably not the true
of the Christmas party yeah well at the Christmas party cooked very early on in the Omicron spread
no one had had Omicron crucially so that was the that was the issue. I would also say there was
some discontent on Discord in the run up to the convention people mostly I think people who were
not attending the EaseCon grumbling about the fact that people were reporting the people in the hotel
weren't wearing masks and weren't complying with the convention mask policy I do want to say that
I think those complaints are a bit I actually know I think those complaints were a lot unfair
I think the convention controlled as much of the masking policy maybe with the exception of the
disco as they possibly could have done and like we can't blame the convention and it's not fair to
get snooty at the convention if other guests in the hotel or hotel staff the day before the convention
staff starts are choosing not to wear masks I am annoyed at the government and at Britain as a
culture but I'm not annoyed at Phil Dyson and his team. The convention couldn't do more than
they were legally able to do and they probably overstepped what they were legally able to do
by requiring vaccination from every member so but nobody has a problem with that sort of sign.
Yeah I would say what we can clearly see is that even with what seemed to be
pretty reasonable COVID precautions it's absolutely not possible to have a convention which is totally
COVID safe and like I said all the things but we're doing a kind of like trying to like you know make
a policy slightly stricter but they won't reduce it to zero and that just says basically that
there's no way we can make in-person conventions at this point safe for everyone and so we just
have to make them as safe as possible but accept that unfortunately at this point we can't have
in-person conventions for everyone. Although a lot of the people at EasterCon who got COVID were
people like you know party animals and dealers who were talking to a great many different people
it is also true to the ton of the people who got COVID were people who were not spending any time
in unmasked eating and drinking spaces who will blast the full time who being extremely careful
and so I think that really underlines the fact that we we just don't have a safe option here for
people at the moment. So which is why we have to have excellence in hybrid conventions all
join conversation please. Hand levitation. Yeah but conversation is definitely going to
have a convention for people even people who don't feel that they can come and people that's in person.
And so is levitation. Is this going to be dueling EasterCon for like the next year?
Yeah no no absolutely. Oh no it's not dueling I'm just making the point that we are all so aiming
for this excellent. Yeah the next two Eastercons are both very committed to hybridity it's going to
happen. Yep 100%. This is one of the things that annoyed me about NovaCon because I had a few
people at NovaCon say that it was privileged to have had online conventions because not everyone
has the technical access. I think one of the things that NovaCon and EasterCon have shown in spades
is that it is also privileged to have inversion conventions. It is a different privilege but you
can't attend an inversion convention if you are at high risk and that is a privilege that those of
us who are not at high risk have. And obviously you can't attend a virtual convention if you don't
have the technical skill and so that's a privilege that those of us with the technical skill have
and that's why doing hybrid conventions is good because it means that you open that net to as many
people as you plausibly can. I can't see I can't see many ways we can significantly reduce the
privilege through hybrid conventions more than we are doing. I am going to repeat my offer here
which is that if you have somebody who cannot get on to online conventions I can send them a Mac
and show them what they need to do. I can do a hybrid convention and a box kit. I'll probably
did crowdfund if a lot of people probably would say yes this is the thing I need but you know I
was trying to sell a Mac that will do an online convention for you for £60 at EasterCon and I
did not get any takers so you know and that wasn't by any means the lowest technical kit that
that'll do the job. I will also say that next episode if we announce our Patreon that's a signal
that lots of people took Alison up on her offer so do keep your eyes peeled for that.
There are all these Macs are going to have sponsored by provided by Octa thought
of the spray painted in purple on the side. Spray painted in purple yeah I had one more thing to
say about Norwescon which is that Norwescon commented favorably on the example of a panelist
who left the convention because they had been pinged as a close contact and if EasterCon had
done that the entire convention would have left by Monday lunchtime. Did I don't think I got
anything more than EasterCon? I got pinged afterwards. I got pinged so often Monday and she'd say
that my phone was like a fruit machine. No I didn't I don't think I got pinged on Monday I got
pinged on Tuesday. No I got pinged on Monday lunchtime just pinged just before Octa thought actually.
Then we drank the beer. Oh no it was just after Octa thought. Oh good. Because it was between
when we drank the beer and they were like I hugged Liz to say goodbye I was like Liz I've been pinged
and she was like half a fuck sake. So anyway if anyone was thinking I walked
through up a good on Covid I should listen to their advice. I like that we've rounded off this
discussion with a great anecdote illustrating the dangers of believing what you hear on the internet.
Do as we say not as we did at EasterCon. Yeah I was going to say there's a very famous
fan scene called daysnade so yeah do as we say not as we do. I do not regret hugging either of you
at at EasterCon that was good it was nice to see you babe. Well neither of us got Covid so
it didn't get Covid so therefore I don't regret it if I got Covid so I might have been
written it I was quite worried about my PC artist. I don't know and maybe I don't know if you agree
with me Liz but like it's very difficult to tell whether I would have behaved differently if I
hadn't recently had Covid. I don't think I would have done I think I behaved much the same but like
it did reassure me like I was like I was I was fairly convinced that unless there was a new
variant like a BA3 or a BA4 or a BA5 that was very prevalent at EasterCon I would probably not
get it because I had already I think had BA2. I don't know whether you think that your recent
booster affected your behaviour much. I don't think it affected my behaviour it just made me feel
that little bit safer and specifically in my case because there was a mandatory PCR to
get back home at the time and so you know failing that would have been quite annoying and potentially
quite expensive. I was very pleased when I heard you got that. Yes I was also very pleased.
That was the bit that was most worrying me is oh god. Yes I think in hindsight it would have been fine
and that has now been abolished so it's not a big issue. I mean I was said don't want to get
Covid but I also didn't want to have to deal with um you know trying to arrange isolation and so on.
But my booster was five months ago and I have been sitting in a house for two years so I was
pretty certain I was going to catch Covid over the weekend. I would have been quite surprised if I
hadn't especially if there would have been 75 reported cases and I hadn't been one of them.
Not them we do. Yeah I would have been phoning up the are you immune to Covid we want to know about
it people. So I was I was expected to get it I got it it was less bad than I was expecting so it's been
okay. I think we may have done I'm going to suggest that we have done far too much fighting on
about Covid and let's get on with some other. Congratulations to fear for winning TAF.
You sure that's fear and not fire? Yeah 100% sorry that's a well conché. Oh I thought I thought
you yeah no I'm um you know it it was. Sorry I thought it was funny I'm sorry I had a push to
the show that's my fault of it. It's not it's not bad. Great race run very well more
more voters than at any time since 2006. That's good for TAF good for the fanfans generally
helps people know about fanfans. We're looking forward to seeing um fear in Chicago because we're
all going to be there. Yep um we would like to encourage yeah we would like to encourage
everyone who didn't win TAF to run for TAF again so that they can win next time all of them three
way tie. Yeah I mean great candidates would still I mean I was very honored to have nominated and
as I would love to see him run again and win next time that would be very good um and yeah I had
some very hard choices in voting I would be happy to see that the moving candidates run again things.
It's very disheartening to lose a race but you mustn't think oh no that means people
don't think I'd be a good candidate I think everyone would have been a great delegate this time and
and um it's just only one of them could win and that was fear so.
Yeah we're all going to strike on. I've booked my flights at my hotel and my travel insurance and
um and I've got my not a visa whatever it's called. Esther and here and so yeah we're definitely
going. What about you John? Uh I've got my flights and I've booked my hotel which was eye
wateringly expensive and I haven't yet got around to doing the travel insurance I should probably do
that and I've got membership have you got membership? Oh yeah no we've got membership yeah so yes the
entire thing was eye watering expensive the entire thing was like oh my god it's a good thing we have
an offset mortgage. It's like what do you spend your mortgage what do you use your offset mortgage
for an extension? No we're paid to go to Chai Con and worrying about paying off the mortgage some
other year. I have booked nothing um but what membership? That was why I went around this line of
things I was fairly sure this is where we get to. Yeah I just haven't got myself organized.
Yeah I bought membership. A very kind person uh sold me their uh unwanted attending membership
and I swapped it for my sporting membership so it works out for both of us so that was very nice.
Yeah I'll get around to doing it I just have not actually kind of figured out any of the logistics
of the horrendous 24 hour journey that I will have to take to get to Chicago so yeah might be
putting that off you so to think about it. Um we Chicago is supposed to be lovely.
Isn't it lovely? Um yeah I've never been to Chicago I'm very excited.
Are you not? And I keep getting more excited because people keep saying oh Chicago is kind of like
New York as if it had effective city planning and a socialist government and that's like oh that
sounds good. I don't remember you know the giant Trump tower on the Chicago waterfront giving me
a very socialist value. The specific thing they said was unlike New York and I think also London
though London is getting better about this um Chicago has treated its waterfront as being a
public good for over a hundred years and um and so therefore it has lots of lovely parklands
and it has lots of good stuff and it's all very near the hotel and everything's very walkable
and that also sounded good to me apart from it's going to be as hard as the furs of hell but
probably not for Liz. No it'd probably be quite a nice temperature for me.
Yes I mean one reason the hotel is I want to be expensive is because uh it genuinely is in the
middle of Chicago unlike you know long come where we're like come to London maybe zone three and
this is generally right in the centre. And I think when you say I want to really expensive I think
it's about the same price as satellites hotel which is also I want to really expensive. Yeah I
accept that if you wanted to put four of you into a room at Chai Con you could do in which case it
wouldn't be expensive at all. I mean there's obviously an opt to thought sitcom hijinks sensual
there. All five of us are in one room and Liz has the path yes. They are big hotel rooms though I
mean I've been to went to the world come there in 2012 and we did put four of us in a hotel room
and it was fine fine but I was younger then. Yeah I mean I did yeah it would be it would be much
cheaper than Niestcon hotel. At the previous Chai Con I had four people to my room and we also had
a deep dish pizza in there which basically counts as an entire person on its own so uh yep quite big.
I ate cold because pizza for lunch one day and I felt so ill don't do that.
No we had a breakfast it was that absolute best like 100% recommended would do again.
Last time I was in New York my New York friends said we have to show you what pizza true pizza is
like and it turns out the true pizza in New York is very like true pizza in Walthamstow and was not
at all the sort of pizza I missed terribly since leaving the United States in 1982 which is Chicago
pizza and I am really very much looking forward to eating some Chicago pizza. This actually segues
very neatly to picks. So in today's picks my pick is Detroit style pizza. I live in a city now
listeners that has Detroit style pizza and I can order it whenever I want and it is bloody
glorious. It is basically a large square which is deeper than most pizza but less deep than a Chicago
pizza and you get like this delicious kind of almost but not quite burnt cheese crust around
the edges and it is incredibly nice and the place near us does it with sort of ricotta cheese and
fennel sausage and lots of other lovely toppings and I've been enormously enjoying that.
But I'm looking forward to Chicago deep dish as well very much. I mean it's a pie basically isn't
it's like a quiche in a pizza I had a baby. A very cheesy baby. Yeah and the baby favoured the
quiche more than the pizza except with less eggs. Tune in to our new podcast British people explain
American food every other Thursday on this feed. Our transcripts have a whole thing where we try
and explain cookies. I don't see why we couldn't have a whole British people explain American food
segment most weeks actually. When we're in Chicago we're going to have a pancake breakfast did we
say that already? We're not on the podcast but we did say it to ourselves yes. No we're going to
have it I think we could have say this on the podcast we're going to have a pancake breakfast.
At least one pancake breakfast maybe six or seven. At least one pancake breakfast together.
Oh yeah I've also got like six or seven pancake breakfast with that probably. Yeah I mean I'm
going to pose here and now that instead of doing a live octa talk at Chicago we just go around
eating various American foodstuffs and making mini podcasts about them and by the end of the
convention we might be hunted down by every American. I mean by all means do write to the
Chicago program team and demand not to thought live that would be quite funny. No God don't do
that because I'm on the Chicago program team and it'd be slightly embarrassing. Yeah please all
tweet at Liz demanding octa talk live listeners. I don't have that sort of power John.
So my pick while I had Covid I got to read some books that are purely entertaining and not informative
or improving in any way and several of my friends have suggested that you could do this all the time
but it's more fun than reading the sort of highfalutin stuff but anyway I've really enjoyed
Mortal Engines by Philip Reeve a bit late for Eastercom. If I had read it a few weeks earlier I could
have go up to where the Eastercom said I really really loved your book which I did. Thought it was
great looking forward to the rest. I liked the fact that you didn't pull its punches because
it's a kids book but it kind of goes into places that kids books don't necessarily always go and
it did quite well and I liked how inventive it was and I liked how cinematic it was though apparently
the movie is terrible so that's a bit sad but I did like the fact that it evoked cinematic
images in my brain which I like and it was good fun and I've got the second one out of the library
good library. It's great to get rid of reading old books is that libraries have them in stock
and you can read them. So my my pick the week I will have to be slightly circumspected about it
because my pick is a video game Horizon Forbidden West it's equal to the video game Horizon Zero Dawn
Alison has left because Alison has not finished playing Horizon Zero Dawn which is going to hear
what I say when he listens back to the podcast anyway but I know John is also playing Horizon
Forbidden West and I think he's not finished. I have gotten to the point where I'm at the bottom
of a hill and I told Neil this and he went oh your age is behind so that probably tells you that
I'm quite a long way behind everyone I know who's playing it. Bottom of a hill? Oh oh oh right.
Yeah so I've gone down a big rope like lift thing and an awkward man has been awkward at me
and I have told him to get get you know and gone off to do my alloy thing like an absolute legend.
Right so John has played approximately five to ten percent of games so far. Oh I would say less
than that. There's a lot I finished up I mean I was quite completed about it haven't finished
everything but I've done basic here if you quite still could find and I end up on about 110 hours
played so that'll give you an idea of how long it is but yeah if you played I'm trying to think
of a good way of explaining it that doesn't spy either Horizon Zero Dawn or Horizon Forbidden West
too much for those who haven't played them basically you players A-9, a heroine who was an outcast from
her tribe and lives in a sort of this kind of future where humans are living in kind of separated
tribes in a kind of very fairly primitive existence but they're all these giant robot machines
driving about and what's going on with that and what's going on with that is what you're
going to find out over playing the course of both of these games. The first one is spectacularly good
the second one is still pretty good but maybe not quite as spectacularly good because
the novelty isn't quite there finding out kind of the second act of the story is not quite as
exciting as all the stuff that gets unraveled in the first act but it is still great you're still
essentially roaming around this giant open world you know shooting giant mechanical animals and
sneaking up behind them and you know throwing sticky bombs at them and shooting them with different
ammo and you know going around meeting all these different tribes which they do a great job of
kind of having all these distinct groups of people with their own kind of traditions and building
styles and outfits that look really distinctive and I would say that my main piece of the second
one is they put too much stuff in it so we're in the first one I had like six different weapons
and this one I have like 12 different weapons that do 27 different things and I spent way too
long trying to work out okay what is the optimal weapon for shooting this giant crocodile machine
in the face a lot and it also has the very annoying thing where if you kind of pause for too long
Aloy will say something helpful like maybe I should scan for a point of interest and things
like this and it's like no I'm on my way to do what you're just about to tell me to do it's just I
fell off this cliff and have to climb back up again and that gets surprisingly jarring after 100 hours
of it but I did really enjoy it even on PlayStation 4 it looks spectacular the voice acting is pretty
great throughout and it's just 100 hours of fun so if you haven't played the first one and you
have a PlayStation you should go and get it right now and if you haven't played it and you haven't
or bought a PlayStation then you should go out and buy a PlayStation which you say goes very well
into a while or something was about to say I bought a PlayStation to play this game I didn't
realize it at the time I thought I was buying it to play a different game but it turns out that
this is the game I bought the PlayStation to buy and the other thing about the first one is that
it's a game that's so good that it tipped the conversation on best games Hugo from oh well I can
see that there's an argument for why we might have best games Hugo to obviously we need to have a
best games Hugo so that we can give the Hugo to things that are like this and it reminded me very
much of what happened with Watchman back in the mid 80s which was that they had to invent a special
Hugo for Watchman because they didn't have best graphic novel at the time I think that is fair
I think Horizon and Zero Dawn is like the first time I played a game where I was like oh this is
like great science fiction in a game and I don't think I'd had that prior to that point like it's
not like there hadn't been science fiction in games like Mass Effect is an obvious example
but I think Horizon I'm now played Mass Effect and it was okay but Horizon really tickled me now I
will also say that I'm not sure that Sony quite realizes how popular the franchise is and I say
this because they released a Horizon Zero Dawn Lego set and it sold out within five hours of coming
out I went to get it from the Lego shop and they did not have any more there had been a big queue
the time the store opened no so you don't have one and I did not get my tall neck no John I know
but I am kind of happy about this because I think it shows that there is appetite for the
franchise I think that is good yeah what's their first first Horizon thing wasn't it
Sony probably has a very good idea of how successful the franchise is on account of how
they have sales figures they won't know how many people are buying second-hand play stations to
play it but they know how many people are playing it because obviously they're tracking every
minute I spend playing it and things like that they know the thing they didn't know is what the
overlap between Horizon fans and Lego fans is and I think it's probably higher than they expected
but I don't but I don't think it's fair to say that the sales figures of a video game reflect the
cultural penetration of that video game in isolation I suspect there are games that have sold as well
as Horizon that have not got the same level of cultural penetration and therefore I suspect you
need more data than just that one number to work that out yeah it's a very good game though it is
it's so good yeah so good and I haven't played the second one yet but I'm looking forward to it
they'll probably take it I am now something like 52% of the way through the first one so I'm
I'd further on with it than than I had thought have you found out that all of the animals are
robots yet spoilers listeners all of the animals are not robots because otherwise I've been eating
a lot of robot that's not great some of the animals are bloody little rabbits and you have to kill
the rabbit to make your pouch for holding arrows bigger which is the worst mechanic oh yes I
am going to have some a little whine about Horizon and I don't know if this is improved in the sequel
but if I had to complain about things it would be like I am like umptium games in hours into this
game where umptium is a lot I'm still having to wander around picking up bloody herbs everywhere
and that is pissing me off and I also have to keep shooting animals and that is also pissing me off
and I could be doing without that those quite relaxing it's kind of very meditative to sort of
wander around the countryside filling up one's medicine pouch and which I need to do because
obviously all of the giant robot things kick my butt repeatedly because that bit where I suppose
to work out what weapon I should use I'm just going if I stand on a legend hit far arrows into
this it will die eventually and that doesn't seem to be true in most cases so my other complaint
about the game is that actually there's a lot of there's a lot of quests in this game and a lot
of them work exactly the same way and I'm getting a little bit tired of it but I mean I have time
for fun so what I'm gonna do I will look up before the next episode exactly how many crabs
I have massacred in order to make a lot of these rope pouches and so on because the second game
is not any better about that I killed so many crabs I've killed so many owls I killed some
seagulls and felt slightly bad about it yes for any owl feathers okay she's dead to me and I need
like three owl feathers to make a pouch and apparently I'm such a bad hunter that this takes at least
12 owls to get enough feathers to make my pouch and then it's like well done you have a level
three pouch now make a level four pouch with some more owl feathers yeah so one of the things
that's very annoying about the hunting the thing that's very annoying about the hunting mini-game
is that you don't all no matter how effectively you kill these beasts you don't always get the
thing you're looking for that is very annoying like life I'm like I got over this in video games
ooh bring me an iridescent crab shell why'd need a particular iridescent crab shell
well because it's pretty hellous I will also say this doesn't count as a re-pick because when we
discussed it in episode 39 we haven't invented picks yet so it gets off on a technicality
also it's we have got a long tradition of going round it also she
this is talking about the second game that I talked about the first game
I'm talking about the second one and also we have a long tradition of getting distracted and
talking about video games a lot because that's the sort of content that Mark Lumbelowt
and it's midnight in Bangkok so that was the Octa thought podcast and it's goodbye from me
it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
[Music]
yeah well done and we didn't have 15 minutes of talking about Arkham Horror
no the theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod in
Competec.com used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license
this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]