Amazingly creating VR social spaces is one of the things that I am particularly interested in. You never get it.
It turns out I was born to to run parties without having to tidy up the house
before or afterwards.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very seventh episode of Octa Thor.
A podcast about science fiction and science fiction fandom.
We are sponsored this week by Stow shirts. I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
For those listeners who are reading the news and Twitter and Facebook and sort of generally
staying up to date, there have been widespread protests against police brutality and the treatment
of black people in the United States of America for most of the last week.
Here at Octa Thor we are aware that a lot of you may be listening to us to get away from the
terrible and awful news happening out there in the wider world but equally we as a trio feel
quite strongly about social justice and we are very much standing with the protesters as we are all
white. We are not necessarily the best people tell you where to go to educate yourself.
So if the listeners of Octa Thorpe have any suggestions for literature or for places to donate
money then please send us locks and tell us where we can donate money and what we can recommend
to our listeners in order to help them educate themselves about everything that's happening at
the moment. If you want to start educating yourself about black writers of speculative
fiction you could go and look at Fire Magazine and we'll put a link in the show notes to that
too and there's also the Black Spec Fic Report which reports on kind of the state of the industry.
The writer survey I think is quite American centric. I'm not sure about the contributors to
Fire Mag but I believe it is based in the USA so if anyone knows of any equivalent
initiatives in the UK I'd like to hear about them.
And I should say I've had a couple of people as always happens when there's anything trending
getting in touch with me and saying have you made this badge or this t-shirt or this thing and I
would suggest that you should go and get your protest gear from black and minority ethnic owned
businesses. In Letter of Comment news we had a conversation of comment with Lillian Edwards
at the first Thursday pub meeting in which she told us that Ian Sorenson says that my microphone
is better now which is true it is. Hoorah!
Last time we recorded was in the middle of Bulticon which was being held virtually. It is the
Baltimore SF Groups Convention it's held every year and they did a variety of programming and
social spaces on the internet and we decided not to talk about it last week because it was still
happening but what did we think of Bulticon? Did we go to Bulticon? Liz it's rather a
wrong time zone for you I understand. Yes really everything is in the wrong time zone for me but see
many many podcasts previously complaining about this so I didn't it's like I keep meaning to go
to things but it's one that they're in the wrong time zone but also that every time there is a
convention I have to then work out what is its local time zone and how does that compare to my
time zone and what time actually is it and usually I never get to the third stage so I had to say
one thing I would implore virtual conventions to do is to maybe put somewhere in small letters their
time in like UTC or something just to make it easy for us all to work out what time it would be
in our own time zone. That is a good idea actually that should be a thing that happens.
I'm sure people from Conzil and listening to this podcast I am not sure people from Conzil and
listening to this podcast. I was intending to spend quite a lot of my weekend at those conventions
both at Wiscan and Bulticon and it mostly didn't happen and I'm not entirely sure why not I kind
of dropped into the discord's a bit and they were fine but I never found like the buzzing zoom party
of my dreams or anything of that kind and I didn't go to any program items because I have a problem
with my life at the moment which is that for all the time lockdown and can't do any of the things
I would normally do I am incredibly busy all the time. I have no idea how this has happened but it
clearly has happened and I'm surrounded by things I should be doing all of the time. Yes and so I
didn't get to a lot of it. I did talk a little I understand that Bulticon was an enormous success
and I talked a little bit to some people who had had a good time and they really liked lots of
things about the way that it worked. My wife, Spania, also attended Bulticon and she wrote a
very excellent blog post about it and she basically sent me a text message saying I didn't lock but
here's a blog post so I will include a link to the blog post in the show notes and you can go and
read her thoughts on everything. Spania did an awful lot of socialising on this board in the
text chat so she had quite a different opinion of it than me and Alison did which is interesting.
She I think thought it worked very well but she also went to some of the zoom parties and she
thought that that was good. Right and I also talked to the Glasgow in 2024 team who said it was a
lot of fun but not very many people came to our room party so we're now worried about room parties
at Conzeland and will you run them all and I said no I would not run them all but I will run one
and they said it won't be very difficult because only a very few people will come and I'm like
not if I'm running it so I'm telling you now I'm going to have an awesome and enormous room party
at Conzeland and it will be timed at like I don't know eight o'clock in the morning UK time but you
know just day drinking it's the best. I will say that the problem I think the Glasgow in 2024 room
party at Bulticon had was that I did not know it was on so I did not attend and I feel as someone
who is a pre-supporter of Glasgow in 2024 and man who was at Bulticon I perhaps should be in the
middle of the Venn diagram of people who heard about this room party so I do think there might
have made a slight problem with the communication there because I would have been there with bells
on had I realized it was happening. I think you had to look look down a long chain of information on
Discord to find the Discord channel that was Glasgow in 2024 and then go to that and I think there was
an issue with multiple nested Discords possibly rather too many of them. I think part of the
problem is that like I don't know why they didn't advertise it on the Glasgow in 2024 mailing list
for instance which I subscribe to yeah if it's a virtual thing that anyone could come to you can
make it buzzing by advertising on your mailing list and then people will come. I do think that
there should have been and I don't know if there was I suppose I could double check as we record
there should have been like a room party/social um notice board equivalent on the Bulticon
Discord if there was one of those I'm not sure I really noticed it but that probably should have
been like quite prominent. I will say so I went to Bulticon I did not go to any Zoom parties because
they all started after I went to bed and I am some sort of lame person who goes to bed before 2am
but I will say that generally speaking I enjoyed the panels I went to I went to three or four panels
I went to a panel on Star Wars the end of the saga which I thought was going to be a super great
panel like looking at the nine part thing and like how it went and what they should have done
differently and what they could take away and actually devolved into people just talking about
their favourite parts from their past strikes back which if a modest wasn't quite the angle I wanted
from the panel and I eventually gave up I do wish that panelists would read the panel description
like it's my biggest bugbear just guys there's a description of what the panel's about please
discuss that because that's why I clicked um the other two that I went to were both on tabletop
games and they were actually really really really good um I really enjoyed the way that the Zoom
kind of webinar mode lets you ask questions and stuff and then people from those panels were hanging
out in the discord text chat after the panels and you got to talk to them a bit more there
and you also got to see people talking about other gaming panels you might not have been to
and that actually worked really well so I think I think from my perspective I kind of mostly ignored
the dealer's room the artist Sally and the fan tables on the discord but the little gaming segment
with the different channels worked quite well I think next time I would probably um I would
probably advise condensing the discord channels for the dealers and artists of anti-ables a little
bit because I think there was just way too much variety there um but I can see why they did that
but I'm not sure it was what they should have done um but I think these things will be things
that we get better at over time and I think baltz college the first place I've seen do this with
what I would say was quite a high level of success so um I I thought it was quite good I was quite
encouraged I will say harking back uh several minutes at this point Glasgow in 2024 did put it on
their twitter feed and I wonder if they're trying to do the sort of thing where they keep their
mailing list low volume announcements and announce things like an upcoming party in two days on
their twitter feed so that might be part of the issue okay so so twitter's a terrible way to
announce anything unless you announce it every half hour for because how people use twitter is
that when they're on twitter they dip in and a twitter stream rushes past them nobody's actually
reading everything that the 9 000 people they follow um posts every single time it's it's even
worse than facebook for that um and at least if you put something on facebook and lots of people
say they are going then eventually facebook will go oh yes that's an event I should probably show
you well and the other thing is that I like the Glasgow in 2024 page on facebook so if they had
made it into a facebook event presumably they could have invited me and I would have seen it that way
but I will agree that twitter is great and I think it's very good for many things but the thing I
think it's absolutely awful for is announcements because as as Alison just said like the algorithm
means that I don't see posts in the order they were published anyway and if twitter doesn't show
me that tweet then I there's no way for me to see it and the thing I love about mailing lists is
that when someone says me an email I read the email and that is a one-to-one correspondence which
which facebook and twitter are sadly algorithmically eroding uh which I get I fully understand why
they're doing that but it does it frustrates me when stuff is announced on twitter and I'm like but
I never could have seen that because I have run mailing lists I now know that when you used to
send things to people in the post you never really understood how many people were reading them
but when you email people you do learn how many people are reading them because mail chimp or
whatever you're using will give you a read percentage and if you're doing well that read
percentage is somewhere in the margin in the order like a convention mail app will probably get a
40% open rate and that's the reason why conventions are kind of going will mail you less will will
not use the mailing list as people just aren't reading their email no I understand I do think
it's probably better not to pepper people with email so I do I understand the tensions but what
you actually do to announce things is you have multiple channels you get in touch with the people
that you want to be at your fantastic buzzing party and say will you be there and they go yes of
course I wouldn't miss it for the world and you go can you tell all your friends on your podcast
or whatever yeah and you actually you know it's like any any other event would be that you do have
to market things a little bit more aggressively than just sticking up your hands saying we are
running a room party at bolticon and of course you busy people all over the world who are overwhelmed
by the amount of stuff you have to do on the internet at the moment will immediately think of
our party as being the first thing that you want to do it's become clear that that in fact Facebook
marketing for conventions is quite effective at has been effective at pulling in people who would
not habitually have got the easter con the easter con the makeup of the easter con has changed
extremely dramatically over the last five years and although long con gets some of the credit for
that it's also the fact that we accidentally reached out to a broader community by just doing very
basic social media stuff and and also by the people who go talking about it and and raising
bells for it and i don't see any reason why you can't do that with the online conventions
as well you just have to make sure that you've got a a value proposition that is compelling at
times when people have a lot of other things on their plate
on the topic of value propositions consieland have announced that they are also going to use a
mixture of zoom and discord to run their convention and one question we had when we read this is
what is the value proposition of this given that bolt con has done this seemingly free at the
point of use so um uh listen did you want to start talking about this and then me and Liz can jump
in with our excellent opinions i wanted to 100% make clear that i am pontificating from a
complete state of ignorance here and i wanted to say that i guess that bolt con probably wasn't
free um that they will have had there a convention that doesn't that runs every year so they will
have things like a corporate structure and a bank account and a set of and and they would have
been able to put some money into this in the knowledge that they will have um future physical
conventions in a way that conventions that only run once like a world con may not be able to so
it is possible that it was not as free as all of that um these will all be tied together with a
single sign in point for authentication so so i feel like conzeland is planning to wall off its
garden and i i guess that bolt con because it was free didn't need to wall off its garden and i i
guess is that the the process of saying only con see on only conzeland members are going to be
inside the loop here will make this more expensive uh and if you can spot the floor in that reasoning
i think you're right i think that bolt con almost certainly as a continuing convention has a reserve
that they can probably call upon because they are an established organization that has been going
for a while and will have a continuity the disadvantage in this sense that world cons have is that each
world con for those who don't know is a separate organization uh and so there is no um continuity
in the amount of of money on the organization that you have available to you other than what other
world cons have been able to donate to you and i don't know how much Dublin did in donating to
conzeland but i wouldn't be surprised if it was relatively low because i suspect Dublin spent
quite a lot of money on running their convention and so it might well be that this is mostly driven
by the father bolt con might have a source of stability that conzeland doesn't and so it might
well be a slightly unfair comparison to make in some ways if you look at the easter con easter cons
pass along money between easter cons and these pass alongs can often be quite large um compared
to the relatively small budget of an easter con um and and they've been getting bigger um and we
intended when running fully con to reduce the size of the pass along deliberately because we
thought they were slightly too large um but we we did end up passing along quite a lot of money
and we will use i think it is likely that most of that money is going to get used up dealing with
this year's easter con refunding where it needed to and the incurring the expenses it couldn't get
out of and then next year's easter con coping with what is likely to be a very disrupted
easter con for a number of ways and i would suspect that between those two we will probably not have
very much pass along at all left at the end of it um so it's kind of like oh yes easter con has
been saving for a rainy day and that is a thing that that it's done now i imagine that conzeland
has an enormous amount of incurred expenses that it cannot get out i think there's also one extra
aspect that conzeland will have to deal with i think bolticon in a way could have sort of open
zoom and open discord and largely fly under the radar and i didn't hear anything about any problems
they had but i think a world con is a much more visible entity and also the world con has had
problems in the past well you know will con is a higher profile thing and it has uh you know had
the whole thing with the puppies and the hugo nominations and it's possible they also feel
that a they need to be a little bit more of a walled gardener to put some effort into making
sure that no one disrupts their higher profile event and also into more people points to do
moderation and to try and keep things as safe as possible um for everyone when they do have the
event just because of numbers so i don't think any of these open events have had problems so far
but it's it's not hard to think of a world in which they could have problems from a bunch of
bored people deciding to disrupt proceedings
i think that segues quite nicely into a discussion about what the relative strengths of zoom and
discord are in this space my understanding is that one of the reasons discord has gotten more popular
recently is because they've recently introduced an awful lot of features to allow for that kind
of effective moderation to be more easily implemented and i saw that there were to get into the bolt
econ you had to agree to a code of conduct before you were allowed to enter the bolt econ discord
and there were moderators who were able to step in but i think you're right that cons elend will
have a harder time with that it will be a much bigger enterprise but i think it's interesting
that the way that do you see the the way that discord can be used to facilitate that kind of
code of conduct might be one of the reasons we're seeing that as the like spokes in between the zooms
which are the kind of panels and room parties um and i think that's a really good use of the two
technologies really playing both to their strengths while minimizing their weaknesses
discourse strength being like the fact it's always there and you can always go and it's got the
moderation and zoom strengths being that the video quality is higher it's a lot easier to get started
like you just click a link and it appears um and you can do the webinar boat stuff which is all
kind of baked in um very much playing to the strengths of both platforms yeah i mean i think
it's quite clear that a combination of zoom and discord is very good for all this stuff i mean i
haven't i've not thought about running a party in the form of um having the having the actual party
going on in discord with a set of video chats but that might be a better way to run big parties i
don't know um i'm still i'm still amazed that nobody has really solved the problem of running
big parties it's given that it's been months now and given that big parties are one of the things
that humans like to do a lot i know i just keep talking about parties all the time um when we get
to what i'm doing to stay set in the pocket it's one of the things i've been looking at is whether
there are any really good vr party apps because it feels like vr parties ought to be totally a thing
that could solve all of these problems but you know what they're not or at least if they are
that i haven't found one yet and actually one of the things that we were talking about um i'm
almost certain it was on one of allesans in terminable zoom parties um possibly after a tap
pop possibly after a tap zoom maybe it's a lot of pop music maybe a thursday uh they're lovely
but there are many of them and they all slightly blur into one which i enjoy about them um and also
i've just googled in terminable and they are endless you are always zooming allison it is 100%
that i i do not believe you will ever stop partying i am actually slightly less zooming than i would
like to um i feel like i i'm not i'm not running fewer events than i'd like to but i i kind of find
i get to the beginning of weekend and goes who's running a party this weekend and they're never
quite enough of those people so maybe there are great parties going on to which i am not being
invited but they probably are but i feel like i mean i never was going to invite me to loads of
things now i'm going to have to go no no but i would like that to be more things out there that i could
just kind of drop into if i feel like it where people will be having buzz but i will say that
jerry was saying that balticon also had a presence on second life where you could go and interact
with people in second life and i was like and it gets better what you were saying about yeah about
VR like party like it's 1999 Liz do you use second life avid second life user i have never used second
life mean either i used it in 1999 i don't know what was it actually 1999 i'm just checking but yeah
no and i think that gets back to what you're saying about like it would be it sounds like what you
want is a VR world where you could go and like more realistically interact and then i heard that
they were doing a second life thing and i'm like oh no because i think that's the attempt to do
something like that but i just don't think it actually works or provides that experience in any
meaningful way and hopefully one day but not not today but kudos to them for trying i don't think
conzeland has announced their aggressive second life uh home utilization yet and obviously i think
i speak for all three of us when i say i'm waiting with baited breath to see what they plan i am
actually wrong apparently you can party like it's 2003
excellent
octa-thorpe is sponsored this week by stow shirts stow shirts makes political,
science fictional and nerdy apparel and pin badges for a whole range of different interests
whether it's a virtual hug badge to tell a loved one you're thinking of them
a shirt with an in-joke for sf fans or nerds a pronoun badge to wear on your work lanyard
or a political slogan for your next protest they're likely to have something for you
podcast host should speak here about their personal experience with the sponsor
um podcast with her every week she's quite nice
what's more they can do custom badges and shirts amend existing designs to suit your needs and
they're happy to work with sf conventions and fangroups to help organize their merchandise
offering and reduce stress on the committee visit them today at stow shirts dot com and use the
code octa-thorpe for a 10 discount
we should we should talk briefly about the nebulous and wizcon which we i think i speak for three of
us did not attend but allison gosson sleeky gossip before the nebulous happened so um
when it wasn't really sneaky gossip steven silvers said he'd been running um zoom parties along
the lines of the ones that i've been running for up to 500 people with a lot of rut of i he'd
been running them for up to 150 people with a plan to run for up to 500 on nebula weekend and
i've heard nothing i feel like if 500 people are gone to a to the nebula party i would have heard
about it but they were probably all american science fiction authors so maybe not but if you
were at the nebula zoom party do let us know how it went so he was using the same system as we do
where you have a lot of breakout rooms people move between them he was doing a thing very cleverly
where he put everybody into a lobby and then he had moderators in the lobby trying to divide people
up into smaller rooms i slightly worry that that leaves you with hundreds of people in the lobby
and he was leaving people in the waiting room until he had a bunch of say six so then he bring them
all in at once and um give them the spiel about how it was going to work and things like that um
but i don't that was all in the practice which is what we talked about so steven if you're listening
then that would be a great thing to know about how it went and um yeah and if you're not listening
if anyone was at the nebula zoom party i really really want to know how it went the one thing i
must say i really dislike about zoom is the bit where you wait for the host to notice that you
want to party and they eventually let you into their party but it's i guess a bit like queuing to get
into a room party as a world con so it's a pleasing recreation of a fannish tradition it's replicating
that bit of the party where you decide to go to party and you get a drink and you sort of hang
around at the edge to want to work out if you know anyone at this party or if you're just gonna stand
around looking like you are a cool loner it's actually replicating the part where you're
standing on the doorstep and your hostess had a has engrossed in conversation and the last thing
we want to do right now is open the door the second
the other thing we did not attend was wizcon do Liz do you know anything about wizcon yes i have
been to wizcon quite a long time ago now uh 2006 and i enjoyed it but i've never managed to go back
so i was sort of thinking about trying to go back when it was a virtual convention but i completely
failed to do so because of inertia and time zones but they i think they were paid as well so i would
have had to make a proper commitment to working out if i could go to things really before you
couldn't sort of dip in and out um but it is the of the ones that were running on memorial the day
what that was the one i would quite have liked to go to registration for wizcon cost $10 you could
pay zero dollars if you could not afford the $10 and they also had membership levels at $25 and
$55 for those who felt able to more support the convention so it wasn't um it wasn't sort of
conziedland levels of money um but it was sort of a small tip i hadn't realized it was only $10
um i think i must have seen one of the higher numbers and decided i need to think about it if
it's only $10 and that is within my realm of yep i'll just take a plunge on that and if i don't end
up going to any of the events well i like wizcon and they can have my $10 yes no that's that is fair
i was i don't know whether baltachon had a tip jar but it does occur to me as well that you you
really need to have some sort of like paper or or drip or whatever other service um tip jar
um on your um on your convention website to allow people to contribute to the costs i think
i'm still very much looking forward to conziedland i am i think part of the thing about the virtual
trip is trying to get myself into a headspace where i really am focusing when you there's a focus
thing when you decide to go to an actual convention in actual life you go right i am going off
if we ever have these again i go somewhere for the weekend and i spend my weekend there and i do
the convention when a virtual convention comes into your life you're kind of like oh i'm doing
everything else i'm doing else and then also there's this convention going on and i think actually
saying no i'm i'm going to block out three days and the convention is going to be what i do for
those three days is a very different way to think about these and i'm not sure how many of us are
doing that just yet did that make any sense that did make sense because i think when i was
thinking about oh should i try and get to any of these uh online conventions over the moral day
weekend i was thinking about it and oh i might dip in and out of some events if they're in the
right time so and i wasn't thinking i will take the plunge and commit my weekend to it as i normally
would for convention yes i think i think that's fair and i think that was very much the
thing i did with um bolticon was i signed up for the panels that i was interested in going to and
were in the right time zone and then i didn't really think i was attending bolticon but i got to go
to some cool panels which is the way i was thinking about it but i think if there was going to be
a convention i usually attend happening virtually i would be taking that as a i will block
the time out and do this as if i am at the convention and the next convention for which that happens
is probably going to be the virtual uk games expo which is being held in mid-August they have
cancelled the physical one and they are holding a virtual one and i will be thoroughly and enthusiastically
attending oh how much does it cost and what are its dates uh so it's the 21st of august
um to the 23rd of august i have found the part on the website uh we've decided to make virtually
expo freely available to anyone who wants to join in so there are no entry tickets but there will be
the option to donate and some activities such as role-playing games and tournaments will still
require individual tickets and will attract a small fee in order to participate so free to attend the
sort of show floor but perhaps small amounts of money to attend some of the events happening
they're using twitch discord zoom youtube um it's being sponsored by paizo and walen games and
wahammer and katann um so big sponsors i i had not heard of uk online games expo and because
gaming conventions are one of the things that i very very much enjoy but have had to decide
or a piece of life that is too much for me um you know i can't manage to squeeze them into my life
i'm actually extremely excited about the idea of a virtual one and um i might walk over long to
that so that's quite exciting it's going to be very interesting to see how some of the tournaments
are run because asthma d which is one of the big big board game companies in the world has been
clamping down on methods to virtually play their games in recent weeks and it will be interesting
to see how you run a tournament for a game that has no official digital client and the parent
company of which has been strongly discouraging online play so i don't know whether those will
actually happen or what they will look like if they do but you know which games are asthma d what
are they what games are they famous for john so they do anything with the arkham horror branding is
asthma d anything with the star wars branding is asthma d unless it's hasbro but there aren't any
tournaments for hasbro games anything with legends of the five rings branding game of thrones branding
katan is asthma d like if it's not if it's not hasbro and it's not wizards of the coast
it's probably aspody it's basically breaks down ticket to ride pandemic uh kakasan small world
misterium i'm not sure they originally developed all of those but they've sort of swallowed up some
smaller companies at this point so essentially huge swathes of games are now aspody they've been
eating companies and then they recently got sold to a venture capital company and you know
capitalism is is great obviously wouldn't hear a word against it but um but yeah slightly sad
oh so the basis they're basically the electronic arts of board games oh geez that is a particularly
good comparison which makes me very very sad Alison so essentially the bit where you're starting
to spend too much money on arkam aura you have no idea how that's going for you uh right let's move
on we should talk about the hugo voter packet on the subject of things which are terrific value
um i signed up for a supporting membership to conziland after the last episode of octa thought
and i have downloaded my hugo voter packet Alison and Liz have you downloaded hugo voter packets?
i have but it took me so long to download my hugo voter packet which is enormous i had to have a
little lie down after that so i haven't really looked at it very much but you have told me that
it has the whole of the wicked and the divine in it and i am very excited about that because the
wicked and divine is an excellent graphic novel that everyone should read yes it has the entire
of wicked and the divine and it also has the entire of monstrous and the entire of paper girls in it
so all of the back issues for those comics are available and i think Liz is particularly excited
well i have already read all of wicked as well so i do not need that from my
voter packet i basically haven't signed up to conziland yet but i am considering signing up for
supporting membership um basically i will sign up for supporting membership in a very
mercenary way if the amount of stuff i haven't read which is in the voter packet makes it seem
like a worthwhile proposition and then i basically get to vote in the hughos as a bonus okay i'm
i'm going to put my grumpy old fart cap on now and go i believe in the world con community and i
think that it is worth buying a supporting membership to the world con each year even for years in
which you could not possibly travel to it because we are we are one if you can afford it obviously
because people have to pay that spend their money on different things because we are one community
and and having the membership every year and voting in site selection and the hughos and being
part of the world con community is a bigger thing than any one world con and you understand that
sometimes the world con will go to places that you cannot possibly get to don't go where i can't
follow yeah like that i do by supporting memberships to the world con every year for exactly those
reasons the reason i bought the cons unit one very late is because i thought i had voted
in site selection at sam house a but i can find no evidence that this thought was actually based in
fact or anything approaching evidence so um having reluctantly conceded i might not have done
that i eventually bought a supporting membership um but yes usually i vote in site selection and
that gets me my supporting membership um without me having to do anything else but this time it does
not appear to have worked which is probably my own stupid fault it's true that sounds so i sound
overly obsessed with free stuff at this point i have bought quite a lot of supporting memberships
in various conventions and world cons in the past i don't know why i never got around to buying one
for cons eland i think it is now clear that the that the hugo that putting your things in the
hugo but voting pack does encourage people to pay attention to them and maybe vote for them and
certainly increases the chance that they will win the hugo but probably is also quite good advertising
for things generally i worry slightly about the tendency for people to buy a by hug by world
con memberships just for the hugo pack because it's not quite that's what gave us the sad puppies
but that's what gives us a group of people who are interested in the world con only for
what it can provide as a reading service and and that seems a bit of a shame yes i don't want to
suggest that the only reason to support the world con is the hugo voter packet but obviously the hugo
voter packet is a pretty fantastic perk that one gets if one is in that community and i will say that
i have oftentimes used the hugo voter packet as a way to try to encourage friends who are perhaps
less in the world con fandom to support the world con and maybe bring them slightly more into the
fandom which is i think also a kind of good carrot to use if that makes sense it's true i also feel
that i am sufficiently embedded in world con fandom and have given quite a lot of my effort in
kind to world cons in the past but i don't feel i always need to support them with my money that's
fair for those who don't know liz has deputy department headed or sorry no liz has deputy division
headed at world cons in the past a job which is very difficult allison has also deputy division
headed in the past a job which was very difficult and i have also deputy division headed in the past
a job which was very difficult so um we are all speaking as deeply entrenched members of world con
fandom who have never been quite daft enough to rise to the position of full division head
which would be insane this is where allison is like i was division head of something and i'm like oh
no why no no i've been area head i was area head at 1995 and 2005 and i was a ddh at 2014 and have
no further intention have no ambitions in that direction at all yes the only one of us who
will ever chair a world con is of course liz i've been going down in responsibility i've gone from
deputy division head to area head to person who hangs around a bit because they know how the
programming database works so clearly my next role will be just hanging around for no reason whatsoever
excellent i think i should say that it isn't a progress so i have been i did area head jobs
two uk world hogs and then a ddh job but at other world cons i have also taken quite dull staff roles
like for example the person whose job it was to inject jokes into the newsletter and that sort of
thing that's a pretty vital role
shall we move on staying sane in the apocalypse aka allison attempts to bring the entire world
to her house so what have i done i've run some more to do parties one of the exciting things that
happened this month is that facebook um included a checkbox on events for this event is happening
online which has stopped the repeated messages that i and all my attendees were getting saying
are you really going to an event with 50 people don't you know that that's not allowed under the
lockdown rules so now it has a little checkbox where you can say my event is happening online
but being facebook i slightly worry that what zuckerberg is doing is trying to because now i get
a lot of advertising from facebook about how wouldn't i be rather using facebook's social media
facebook's video conferencing tools to which the arts reason though i am still using a combination
of zoom and breakout rooms because i've not yet found anything better but i could be persuaded into
discord instead and yes i'm running big resumes i'm running small zooms i'm i've not gone into
the enormous i kind of think once you've got about 20 or 30 people that's probably enough for
for me to have a fantastic time and there's an extent to which i don't necessarily care about
anybody else and i have bought a VR rig that's why i bought an ukulex quest i might my child stopped
working for me on the completely spurious excuse that she was studying for her finals and therefore
did not have any time to make badges for minimum wage they'll notice that she does have time to run a
turnip empire on animal crossing but you know people make their own priorities i mean to be
fair allison you're benefiting from the i was about to say i am benefiting from the truth
from the turnip empire but obviously you're benefiting from the vegetables
all right that's it stop the podcast episode seven were peaked there's nowhere down there
nowhere but downhill from here right um so instead i basically had to do all the minimum wage batch
making it shipping work last month and at the end of the month i looked at what i thought i would
have paid for the number of hours i had spent doing it and i bought an ukulex quest um and also
because i i had said when i decided to buy nothing that i would spend my money on experiences rather
than things and if i still can't get out of my house to do anything then clearly sticking a headset
on and and going and swimming with dolphins or or um playing some vr game is is as close as i can
get to new experiences and they are new experiences it was like utterly science fictional it was
completely sense of wonder for me now i mean i i've obviously used some vr stuff before but
there's something about the fact it doesn't use wires so it's just wherever you happen to be so
you can take a tiny patch of your house from which you've managed to clear clutter and then you put
this headset on it suddenly or in a gorgeous geodesic dome that has been tastefully furnished by somebody
else and in you go oh i can see how we might all be doing this um and um it's equal parts of oh my
god this is a really futuristic feeling and oh my god the world as i know it is going to collapse i
look at what has happened between when i bought my nintendo game and watch in 1980 and the oculus
quest and i extrapolate forward and i'm like we are going to get to the point where real life
does not necessarily have a lot to offer that is better than these systems it is the opinion of
the octa thought podcast that we should all live in small pods plugged into some sort of central
computer where we socialize without risk of pandemic and is this how the matrix starts allison
is this how the matrix starts that was literally where i got to i was like i can see a world where
actually people do this in enormous amount and that's the matrix yeah and that was kind of weird
it was a very weird feeling and and and yet when you sort of go well if say facebook's creating
avatars now and you can see that one of the reasons that facebook's creating avatars is if you want
to do something that's like second life but works getting people to have realistic consistent
avatars for themselves is one of the ways in which you make that happen so you go into your virtual
space and you go oh yeah that's john because i recognize his avatar and yes and this is all
quite the weird thing and but but you know when you're saying well we can't actually go to see
i still can't see my family and i feel like there's a there's going to be attractions this sort of
thing oh also beat saber is a lot of fun beat saber is is fun beat saber is the only vl game i have
played and i like rhythm games because they're the only games i'm actually any good at every
other game i have to put it on easy mode and die a lot and beat saber is just like yep i'm gonna go
for this and it's it's fine although hard work so beat saber is great have you played any other vl
games because do they make and someone should have made this a sort of like matrix crossed with half
live crossed with inception style game where you can do the matrix and run up walls and
reshift reality i think my feeling about games beat saber is fine but beat saber feels to me like
a tech demo rather than a game i feel like we are so there's a set of games that are coming out now
that are set at the star wars universe where you get to run around with light saber um but i feel
like we are only at the very beginning of of exploring what you can do with this game space
there is a game called super hot VR which people talk about where you only move the the bad guys
only move when you do you're in a kind of weird matrix like environment there and you and there
is bullet time so as long as you're not moving the bullets aren't moving and if you start to move
then the bullets move and that is quite freaky and it also is quite intense when they talk about
intense VR experiences they mean they mean roller coasters they mean things that set off your balance
so it's not intense in that way at all but i found it intense in a gaming way i am five foot tall
and it didn't seem to have any height adjustment so these guys that were coming towards me but
only when i moved were much bigger than i was and that was quite freaky i'm not so i've only played
the demo and i'm not saying i won't buy it but it felt like and i've heard other people talking
about VR is saying that some of the really intense first person shooter games are not working for
them because it is just all too much so other people really like that sort of stuff but it's just
early days early days for all this stuff and and there is a game called star trek bridge command
i think that Ming pointed me at Ming has a headset Ming is in New Zealand Ming and i could play this
is a cooperative game where you work with other people on the bridge of the enterprise or some
some federation starship in order to solve problems and i haven't actually played it yet but but
that's something that feels to me the sort of thing that i am actually looking for which is cooperative
games in VR between people who are not located in the same space in the real world
for your you know to make up for a thing like ballgame like i like cooperative game gaming generally
there's apparently a version of keep talking and nobody explodes which is a game which my family
has played endlessly to the death we have absolutely run all the love out all the possible joy out of
this game at this point but apparently there's a VR version of that so that one of you is sitting
with headphones and the quest and the the the VR set on with the bomb in front of you and actually
physically manipulating it and the other people are sitting with the decoding the decoding manual
trying to tell you what to do um so but i'm not playing that either so i've played a bit of
beat saber and i've done a few i've done some things like i have done some VR um i have played
the star wars VR game on playstation 4 and it made me feel a little bit
queasy i had to spend some time looking very fixiddly at a planet in the distance in order to
avoid feeling very queasy um so i am and but i'm very much looking forward to VR becoming a bigger
thing because one of the things i really am finding very difficult about the apocalypse is that i
have a weekly roleplay in which we do quite a lot of highly cooperative storytelling and part of the
problem with zoom and discord and all of these things is that it's very difficult to um pick up
on other people's social cues in a week in a way that means that everyone can join in without
having to sort of go around the room pointing at people saying now it's your turn now it's your turn
because louder voices dominate and quieter voices find it difficult to get a look in
and this can really disrupt the dynamic so i'm very much looking forward to VR as a mechanism
for role playing games because i think i hope that VR will be a better way of doing that that
doesn't fall prey to the same problems that video chatting uh falls prey to so i am sort of
optimistic and hopeful about the potential for VR chatting as a replacement for video chatting
but i i don't know what timescale that's a realistic um proposition on 20 years like uh
like nuclear fusion right it's 20 years away no i think it depends really on how pandemic goes
because if we are still here in a year um not really going to the pub then i think at that point
a lot of this stuff will have happened because there will be so infinitely much money in it
i also did see and i've been looking for the link for ages which is why i've been super quiet
uh someone developed a sort of top down 2d chat room idea where you wander about a 2d space and
you can talk through your microphone and people who are closer to you can hear what you're saying
more clearly and people who are further away hear you less clearly and you can wander around
an actual kind of physical space talking and it replicates a bar in 2d and i am looking for the
link and the name of this and i cannot find it it's very frustrating uh if i do find i'll put a link
in the show notes um but so they've got to get there's a problem with all of these systems at the
moment is that they have to get over the the level of adequacy that we've established now with
with the zoom in the break out which is clearly not that adequate but it's still
a lot better than a lot of these systems are quite managing yet and the other thing about the
VR rig that i was going to say is that although my house is not small really it's got five adults
in it and i've been and i don't think of myself as the world's greatest introvert but when i put
on we don't think of the quest introvert either no you're a terrible introvert Alison yeah indeed
but when i put the quest on i'm alone in a way that i never am in my own house at the moment and i
quite like that it's quite isolating and i have been missing feeling as odd in a type of self-isolation
i have been missing feeling actual time alone to do things i want to do in comfortable spaces because
my house is not so i've made that many comfortable spaces and they're awful at the name of the service
i was thinking of is Calla and i will put a link in the show notes it is C-A-L-L-A is this a thing
you're planning to use on your virtual guff trip Alison i am hoping that i will be able to do some
of my tours virtually i have a really whizzy idea that i am going to do VR stuff whilst streaming
whilst streaming it to twitch streaming both the VR stuff and me using using twitch streaming tools
which i already use a little bit and so that people will be able to come along and watch me
swimming swim off the great barrier reefing real time or something and that will be hilarious
please get in touch for recommendations for ways we can support and learn about the black
lives matter movement and also b-a-m-e people in the UK and in the community in the UK in general
and please also write in with your experiences of virtual conventions we would love to hear from
you thank you to Stow shirts for supporting our podcast this week that was the seventh episode
of the octa thought podcast so it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud at incompatec.com
used under a creative commons attribution 3.0 license
is this the point where i can say that lillian and christina are hoping to do a podcast and
when they first told me about this or rather when lillian first told me about this i said
but you'll have to find someone to do all the work and they have now found in sorenson i believe
so he is investigating other podcasts which is how he's paying attention to john's microphone
so i'm very much looking forward i am waiting with baited breath for that podcast to appear
in my podcast feed i will be listening avidly yes no no pressure obviously the fact that we've
announced it doesn't have any ramifications for whether it has to happen uh and allison's decision
to do that was entirely her own uh well i mean i think you know one of the things i always liked
about fanzines back in the day was that they could be relentless pis takes you know a little bit
edgy about the the community and the things the community we're getting up to
and i feel like we should capture some of that flavor in apocos
more antagonism um i do feel if i was going to pick some adjectives to describe our podcast
edgy would be quite a long way down the list oh okay now i maybe don't mean edgy are you
are you indicating that you think three middle class white people during a podcast are not at the
forefront of edge we talk about things we like liz what could be more edgy than this
my 19 year old son did call me an edgelord this week
right well we're going to come back to that later 100 and i was like what do you mean by edgelord
dear and he explained and i said and i said you mean like kylo ren and he said yes oh dear
oh allison i i i said that that's that's unfair i said what i actually said was that's unfair
quash quash quash quash quash quash quash quash quash but we'll come back to that
i would like to reassure people that allison was miming uh destroying a control console with a
lightsaber and not miming beating her children uh that's important to note the context of the video
was uh key in that particular direction um before we descend the noise is a terrible
yeah everyone knows it goes warm exactly