Hello everyone, it's John here just recording a quick pre episode pickup with some details
of things that we mentioned in the episode.
So firstly, the Chengdu website is back up.
That won't make any sense to you now, but it will do at about 12 minutes in.
Secondly, we mention the launch of all these worlds reviews and essays by Neil Harrison
at Eastcom, but we don't mention it is on this Saturday afternoon.
So do keep an eye out for that on the programme.
And thirdly, we mention that we'll be recording at Eastcom but we don't tell you when and
that is going to be at 1.30 in the afternoon on Monday.
Yeah, it will be a kind of wrap up of what's happened during the con.
Alright, now into the episode.
In the last couple of weeks, the world's first Octopus farm has opened.
So if you haven't already stopped eating Octopus, guys, you need to stop now.
Or if you do carry on eating Octopus, make sure it's wild caught Octopus and not farmed
Octopus because seriously, Octopus is intelligent.
They may be as intelligent as us.
We should not be farming them.
Oh my goodness.
My wife and I do not eat Octopus because although many meats, we draw the line at intelligent
creatures, it's also why we don't eat chat GBT.
Although that's mostly because although it isn't intelligent, it is very crunchy.
Oh, that's so they can.
Liz, completely unmoved by that listeners, Alison, shortly away without making a sound.
This is a good sometimes where jokes land very much with one co-host and not the other.
I'm not sure it landed exactly.
I was just like, oh God.
It's more of a John's Attie to get in, isn't it?
Yes.
John's gone off on a joke thread.
That was, it was that sort of a shuttle.
We were promised jet lagged.
I'm not sure this is noticeably jet lagged.
I actually, I am jet lagged.
The reason you can tell this is because I've only just worked out that when I adjusted the
gain on my mic to make it good for podcasting, because the last thing I did before leaving
for work was podcast, the game was all right and I adjusted it to not all right and I've
just adjusted it back again.
So this will go at the front of the episode to be like, there's not much evidence of jet
lagging here, but the sound quality on my track might be one of them.
Don't know yet.
I haven't listened back.
So apologies listeners, if I screwed that up.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 80th episode of OctaThorp, the podcast for science
fiction and science fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 30th of March, 2023.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And today we have some letters of comment for you all.
First up we have a letter of comment from Mark Plummer and we got Mark curious about
word counts for the same text in different languages.
So he says the top ranked German language book on Project Gutenberg is the critique of
pure reason by Emmanuelle Kant.
And if you strip out all of the front matter and Gutenberg boilerplate, it's about 176,000
words and the English language version is about 198.
It is the Michael John translation, which is a detail he only mentions for obscure fan
historical purposes.
At the Harrogate Mexican, the Friends of Foundation had a copy of the can on our table, of course,
alongside the G-Paton, Wharton, Bakers and Festus, Pregnals and so on.
And I think it was Michael Abbott who noted in the newsletter that it was the Michael
John translation.
Sadly, I can't recall whether or not he thought that was a good thing.
He can also report that all of the world is about 60,000 words, but La Gird de Mons is
about 64,000 words.
And the Gods of Mars by Edgar Rice Bros is about 83,000 words in English, but only about
57,000 words in Finnish.
So thank you very much, Mark.
Some case studies.
Yeah, there is some weird stuff going on there in Finnish, isn't there?
It's interesting as well because Mark points out that the text in English is 360,000 characters
but in Finnish it's 400,000 characters.
So yeah, it's interesting that it's so many fewer words, but those words are much longer.
We didn't hear from Nicholas White, but we did read his Facebook.
Yes, so I think two weeks ago I was saying I was quite confident that nothing in a foreign
language had ever been nominated for a fiction Hugo in a foreign language.
And obviously because I was quite confident about this, I was probably wrong.
But credit to me, I did spot this on Nicholas's Facebook myself.
He didn't write into, to let me know I was wrong.
And that is because the little prince was a finest for the retro Hugo in 2019.
And it's not clear whether that would have been, you know, was it the French original
was nominated or the English translation?
And even if one was actually eligible for the retro Hugo, it wasn't translated until later,
I'm guessing a lot of the nominators had read it in English.
Unfortunately, it was not a problem because with the wiggle room for novella, you could
fit them both into the novella category, basically.
So it wasn't a problem, but that is, yeah, I think one edge case where it has come up.
But I guess that's going to occur more regularly in the retro's where if something got translated
10 years later, it might already be, you know, it might be widely known even if the one that
could be nominated was the original.
So there we go.
I was wrong, but I think that's the only edge case.
And it is the retro's that don't pay any attention to the retro's.
So that's my excuse.
And that's why Liz's rocket's always crash because she doesn't pay attention to the
retro's.
Yeah, I got it.
I mean, I will say everything enough attention is paid in the community to how great a like
name the retro Hugo's is.
Like, even if you don't like the idea of go back and filling in the old, like the naming
on point on the subject of the retro he goes, it does occur to me that there should be a
conversion factors for how books were shorter in the old days.
We should have book inflation.
We should write this into the Wussfuss Constitution.
If anyone wants to co-sponsor, let me know and I will propose it to us first.
I think I think the Wussfuss constitution should have way more trivial amendments taking up
time at the business meeting.
I think that's what we'll need.
That's exactly what I'm at the business meeting for.
I mean, to be fair, if there is going to be, okay, let me be afraid.
Then there is a lot of completely pointless trivia at the business meeting.
It would be at least better if it were funny.
Ian Hillman writes in to say that George Takaie collaborated on a graphic novel called
"They Called Us Enemy" that is also based around the experience of Japanese Americans
in internment camps.
And he says that his understanding is that it was more critically well received than
the musical.
So if anyone is interested in that story but not interested in the musical, then we recommend
you go.
Well, Ian recommends you go look that up.
Thank you very much, Ian.
And after our call for arachnophobes to tell us if they had read works of Adrian Tchaikovsky,
we got a letter from Gwen to inform us that she read "Children of Time" knowing those
spiders and was pleasantly surprised at how much they liked it.
So big thumbs up.
Excellent.
Thank you, Gwen.
I said that she read it.
She speed read the human chapter so that she could get to the spider chapters fast.
I think I read "A Deepness in the Sky" by reading the human chapters as fast as possible
so that I could get to the spider chapter.
So maybe this is a thing.
I mean, the spider chapters are vastly better, I think, in "A Deepness in the Sky."
Yeah, I think that's right.
So maybe there's just something that's excellent about spider chapters.
Right.
I think the human chapters are good as well in "Children of Time."
It's just that if you can read about people or a novel spider people, then you read about
the novel spider people, right?
This is how we know you're a science fiction fan.
And yeah, if you liked the chapters with the spider people in "Children of Time," then
just wait for this equal when there's other stuff.
I have finished reading "Children of Ruin," and there were some people who told me it was
about octopuses and they were correct, but there is other stuff happening as well, which
was very creepy.
I liked the book a lot, but yeah, no, yeah, it was good.
It might be a spoiler.
No, I mean that.
I mean, no, I mean, and it is fantastic.
I didn't know that I liked spiders until I read that book, and I don't like spiders,
but yeah.
We got a letter of comment from a publisher, so we got a letter of comment, or more accurately,
a press release from Brian Dean Books to tell us that all these worlds, reviews and
essays by Neil Harrison will be launching at Estercon.
So we will perhaps have that as a pick when it's out and one of us has read it.
Spoilers listeners, I have already got a copy, but I have not finished.
I'm only about a quarter of the way through, but it is very good and I will pick it eventually.
And finally, we heard a lot about loss isspooky's.
So there was at least one person who didn't get the name from the audio, so it's loss isspooky's.
Regis, that person was me.
You didn't stop me to query.
You just let me carry on with no idea what I was talking about.
Yeah, I think you said it was on Hulu, so I was like, oh, well, I won't be seeing that
for a while.
No, HBO, wrong one.
HBO.
In the UK it's on now.
Yeah, so won't be seeing that for a while.
But it's very good.
It wasn't until I went to look at the Wikipedia article that I realized that it has 100% fresh
on Ron's tomatoes.
So that is quite a high, quite a high reading.
But Karen Shafer wrote in to say that she had watched it on our recommendation and was
thoroughly enjoying it.
So I am very glad and very glad that that landed for someone.
Great stuff.
Oh, and we also heard from a member of the Hugo Girl podcast.
We heard from two different members.
So firstly, we heard from Amy, who says that I'm right about Spock and Muck being great,
I assume, and not the pronunciation.
You're definitely wrong about the pronunciation.
We also heard from Laurie, who said, "Here's a fun Instagram she just noticed.
OctaThorpcast is an Instagram of OctaThorpcast, and we shall have a spin-off show."
And I am down.
I will record my cats and put it up as bonus episode one day.
Large-tooted to us about episode 79, confirming that he is not a teenage girl.
He is a middle-aged Indian man who lives in Glasgow, even though there are some who would
argue that his tastes haven't grown beyond those of a teenager.
He disagrees with me strongly about children of time and says it's very much a book about
spiders.
I didn't think I had said it wasn't about spiders, but I agree with Rod, it's definitely
about spiders.
I should listen back to the episode and see what I said.
Listeners, write in and tell me what I said.
And he also asks about the satellite 8 COVID policy.
So he said, "It looks fine to Raj, but then Raj thought that one about the Easter cold
one too before Liz and I talked about it."
So yeah, fair enough.
No, so the satellite 8 COVID policy is a lot terse, and is, yeah, it seems good.
It's, it's seven, well, it's two bullet points with seven sub bullet points, and they're
all good bullet points, Brent.
So I like it.
I don't know if you've looked at it Liz, but...
I have not, but I do like bullet points.
Exclusive thing, Imajig.
Yeah, it's not really an exclusive reveal that I like bullet points.
Anyone who has said anything I've ever written would be able to confirm that one.
Bullet points are great, is why.
Yeah.
Chengdu.
In the regular, there's not much in the regular Chengdu is a shower segment, except that Chengdu
sent everyone an email saying that they would be a shower imminently.
Well, it just kind of said they did.
Or are currently a shower, but imminently won't be.
They just said they take their website down for maintenance, which is fine, and they told
us they'd let us know again when it's up again.
So as long as it comes up fairly quickly, I think that's fine.
Yes.
And then I was quite snarky about the lack of English in this email, and I was called out
for my angler privilege, which is perfectly fair.
Yeah, I mean, I'm of the opinion that it was clear to me from the email what was going
on, which is the website was going down for maintenance, be back later.
And if currently down.
Basically, if your English is not perfect, but I can get the gist, I don't care.
Is my philosophy on these things.
My philosophy, I think, is I hope is nuanced, which is...
That'll be a first.
Oh, oi.
John's full of nuance.
I mean, I wouldn't go that far.
I'd say I'm half full.
Oh, look at me being nuanced about my nuance.
Wurp.
It's like nuances, seption.
My perspective is basically if I hadn't talked to at least a few people who had attempted
to volunteer for Chengdu and who are native English speakers and who had been resolutely
ignored by Chengdu's voluntary team, I would be more sympathetic.
But I think there is it.
I can see if it's like a small company who don't have native English speakers, I'm completely
fine with them, not quite getting the English right, but I do wonder whether Chengdu could
have solved this by having a better onboarding process for English speaking volunteers.
So like, I think Liz is right, but I also think Alison is right.
Is that a good episode title?
We might have even used that one before, to be honest.
I think that's fair.
But I mean, I also think if what you're having a problem with is having enough native English
speakers, then you may have a problem finding someone to do that onboarding for them.
That is true, actually.
That's a good point.
But again, we really don't know anything about how the Chengdu-Wulcan is running.
So kind of, it's such a mystery to us that we've had a regular, it's such a mystery that
we've got a regular podcast segment on it.
But I really don't know what's going on with internal communications.
I mean, some things obviously are done by Lingley.
I suspect this was just, "Oh, we better tell everyone the websites down," then they don't
worry, and they wanted to get it out as quickly as possible.
Yeah, no, I think that's fair.
Let's do picks.
Liz, do you want to go first because you've just written something in the show document
and I haven't yet?
Yeah, I might just have been putting my picks into the show notes as we speak.
And again, I'm going to pick what may not be like the best thing I have read, watch,
listen to, et cetera, but maybe the most interesting one to our listeners that we used to talk
about.
And that is a 2022 novel by Gabrielle Zevin called Tomorrow and Tomorrow and Tomorrow,
which has been getting a lot of attention in mainstream circles.
It's not because it's not science fictional, but it is basically about the friendship of
two people as they develop video games.
So it's about these two, Sadie and Sam, who meet as children, and they end up developing
video games together.
They make some very successful video games together.
They have a video games company, you know, life strikes them, tragedy strikes them, things
continue.
And I thought it was pretty interesting.
For me, it has some excellent chapters.
Like there's one where it's all told through a kind of game, which is sort of almost across
between Stardew Valley and the Oregon Trail, which kind of is revealing stuff about the
characters as we go along.
It's kind of there's some real video games in there as well, and there's also ones that
are obviously inspirations to them.
But all the video games they have worked on are fictional and it's about kind of the
tension between art and making money and about how two people can both make art the
satisfied them.
I mean, in a way it reminded me of Mythic Quest, because I watched Mythic Quest season three
as well.
And obviously the heart of Mythic Quest is the, you know, Poppy and Iron, and like the
ideas versus the programmer and how you kind of both be satisfied in that.
But yeah, I don't know if I would ultimately recommend it.
I think the ending is a little bit weak.
It's maybe a little bit long.
And I think it maybe feels like, you know, this discussion of people making like a novel
about people who make video games does not feel to me to be like quite as much as a
revelatory thing as I suspect some of the mainstream reviews have thought about it.
But I did, I did enjoy it.
And some of the kind of listening to the process of how they come up with these games and kind
of technology moves on and the games become more technologically progressed and, you know,
some of them are familiar to you from other, you know, you can kind of see how they would
fit into our world of video games, which is interesting.
So I think it's got enough in there to recommend them.
I'm not sure I would say it is the best book of the year, but it is a pretty interesting
one.
Nice.
I've heard about it.
I haven't read it, but I've like, I've seen buzz.
It's like Amazon's best book of 2022 or something like that.
And, you know, it's been immediately the option for film.
And I thought it was fun, but maybe doesn't quite stick it.
And some of the characters feel a little bit, I don't know, they're not ciphers, but some
of the characters feel a little bit underdeveloped.
There's one particular character who doesn't really have many flaws.
I mean, seems a little bit too perfect.
And it's very fun to spend time with, but maybe doesn't quite work.
But yes, it's in the top books of the year.
And I have only read, I've read two actually of Amazon's, three of Amazon's top 10 books
of the year.
And yeah, it's hard to rank them because it's got fiction and nonfiction in there.
But I wouldn't have said it was number one.
So I was listening to Liz's pick going, this sounds just like Mythic Quest.
So she said it was just like Mythic Quest.
I mean, in the time since we last recorded, I've listened, I've watched quite a bit more
of Mythic Quest.
And I've actually got to the flashback episode in season three, which is called Sarion, and
which I absolutely adored.
So I thought that was amazing and a really great payoff for a lot of the things being
seeing a Mythic Quest.
Plus I still haven't quite got to the end, so there's a little bit more yet.
And I don't know if there's going to be any more of it or not.
It feels like they're wrapping up their story.
That wasn't a pick, that was just kind of a reaction to Liz's pick.
The reason I didn't pick Mythic Quest season three, I think I have picked season one or
maybe particular episodes previously, is that it feels like the thing I like in Mythic
Quest is so much Poppy and Iron.
And the things I dislike about Mythic Quest are rapidly becoming basically everyone else
in Mythic Quest who is not Poppy and Iron.
Because I just feel like the other characters are kind of not really going anywhere or in
some cases going around in circles or in some cases going somewhere but I don't really
care.
And they, like the fact that you can take a character like Iron and make him kind of,
make him at times a terrible, terrible person, but also for most of the time not to make him
relatable and interesting and someone I want to see on screen, I think is a great achievement.
I love, I love Rachel and Jo.
And Rachel I think it's going to be very interesting.
I think her arc in season three is very interesting and I'm really interested to see what they
do with Rachel and Dana in season four.
When they renewed it, they renewed it for season three and four so we do know in fact
that season three is not the last series.
Yes, and that's not a spoiler because we did already know it, although we may have forgotten.
And I did pick Mythic Quest season three, episode one as a pick a few weeks ago.
So that's another reason why I probably shouldn't pick it again for a while.
I also love Carol and I love how she's been ratcheted up.
I've basically I love all of them.
Yeah, now I disagree with Liz.
I guess is the point I'm making slowly but surely.
Yeah, that's the problem.
You're like, I really love what the other Rachel and Jo and I'm like, I would be fine
if we excised all scenes with Rachel and Jo from the show.
Sorry.
No.
I love Dana.
And it's fair to say that I really loved Sarion, which just has Poppy and I am.
Oh no, he's Sarion.
Sarion is amazing.
All of the flashback episodes have been amazing.
It was weird to see Sam Whitworth and Robert Piccardo pop up in Sarion.
So I was like, they're famous.
Are they?
Who are they?
Come on.
I just assume I have no cultural reference for the last 30 years.
Yeah, I had children.
Oh, come on, Alison.
Joe, Joe Man-Jennello coming up as the actor they want to play.
The masked man was, I loved those episodes so much.
And I loved David and Jo and Jo, like, I loved all of that plotline, especially because
I've just seen Magic Mike.
So, and also, if you don't know this, Joe Man-Jennello goes to every red carpet event
with his tiny little dog and it's very adorable.
So yeah, I just basically just want to be friends with Joe Man-Jennello.
I mean, you know that Joe Man-Jennello famously has a D&D game?
Yes.
No, he's clearly a massive nerd.
Yeah, he's supposed to go a D&D game with, like, Tom Morello and DBYs.
They're a big nerd.
I'm going to pick peer pressure.
You're told at school peer pressure is bad, but peer pressure is great.
I'm picking it.
You could in some ways say that peer pressure is good because due to the peer pressure of
John Coxon and some other people who will remain nameless for this podcast, I have bought
plane ticket to Birmingham.
Hey!
So when we record a Easter card, it will be the three of us.
Holy, oh God!
We thought it would be fun to tell Alice in live on the podcast and indeed it is.
Look, you swear you guys.
Oh God.
You might have to be that.
Oh my goodness, that's amazing.
That's so good.
Yes.
And so you decided you'd tell me live while we were recording and that's why I'd be like,
"Who's that stunt is going to be?
Who's that stunt is going to be?
Should I flag a membership for this so that she can appear virtually from Tyler on the
big screen?"
Oh God, you guys.
I did wonder if you were going to have to spill the beans at that point.
And then she was like, "Do you want a virtual membership?"
And I was like, "No, which is technically correct.
I do not want a virtual membership."
Have you actually joined the convention?
And it would have just spilled the beans because I see all the memberships coming across my
transtom because I get copied in.
Yeah, I thought it might so I didn't do it yet.
Also, I was seeing if anyone had a membership that they might sell me for cheap fees, but
I can't find anyone.
And I can't leave until the podcast goes out.
So it's a "sell me" membership so I am going to have to go and buy one full price.
But I did think that might spill the beans if I joined so I deliberately didn't do it
yet.
Oh, that is lovely.
Yeah.
So it was partly, you know, I was like, "Oh, I'm not going to go."
And then I talked to John and a few other people and they were like, "Wait.
Nina's a guest of honor.
Why are you not coming to Eastacom?"
And I was a bit like, "Ooh, it's a long way."
Because I'm a cheapskate.
Yeah, that was basically, it was basically, I was being a cheapskate and it was a long
way.
And then I counted my holiday days and so on and was like, "Oh, actually I could do this
and it would be fine."
So I am.
Where we tested the theory that 13 Brits, which was how many Brits in total were there this
year, could drink the, drinks, midi-cons, famous, free beer, dry.
And we did not manage it, but we came fairly close.
So, yeah, now I strongly recommend coming out to Eastacom's support, Neil as guest of
honor.
Let's leave it up and see if that's great.
What else should also come to Eastacom?
If you haven't booked your flight to Birmingham yet, it's time.
I thought I might get the train.
And also, or join us virtually, because there's going to be tons and tons and tons of virtual
stuff.
It'll be great, probably.
So that is half of my pick.
I will also pick a thing.
You get to pick a natural thing, although I thought that would be quite funny.
Yes, no, no, completely worth it.
Oh, you got it.
So...
I was going to, I'm not going to pick a was as guy to defensive breaking because I picked
it at episode 31, which I found out all on my own because I'm great.
Ah, editors privilege.
But the thing I am going to pick is Digger.
So Digger is a comic about a wombat and Digger won the Hugo Award for Best Graphic Novel in
2011 or 2012, I forget which.
But it was in, the entire thing was in the voter packet that year.
So if you download Hugo Voter Packets and you are usually a member of the Worldcon, then
you may already have Digger on your hard drive.
And it was 2012.
But there was a Kickstarter for a new version of Digger, which was, which involved Pat Rothfuss.
He launched a new publishing imprint because he wanted Digger to be back available again.
And so I don't know when that version will be available for people to buy.
But if you don't have it, a reprint is coming soon.
And yeah, it's about a wombat and it's very good and it's very funny and it's very well
drawn and it's just lovely.
So highly recommend seeking out Digger if you have not already read it.
And then it's Alison's pick.
So I have had the huge luck to be able to read it over the last couple of days, an advanced
reading copy of something very exciting indeed.
So you guys can't see it yet, but you'll be able to see it by the time this episode drops
I very much hope.
And that is the programme for EasterCon.
Hey!
Which is fantastic and is full of excellent things, including OptiThought Live, which
as we now know, well actually depends if John's doing some editing, is going to feature all
all three of us live in Birmingham.
Do we have any beer guys?
I have quite a lot of beer.
Right now.
No, I meant special beer for OptiThought Live.
Oh, special, special beers for giving each other the COVID, you mean?
Yeah, none of us gave any of each other COVID.
No, that's the episode title.
And we're all very excited about the programme.
I'm on some programme items.
So I think the programme items I'm on are all the kind of things the committee are on,
and then, which is the opening of Slosie Ceremonies, and then OptiThought Live.
I am going to be at the fanfons auction being the person who checks Discord for bids on Discord
and tells people on Discord what the bid in the room is and stuff like that.
So that's all I'm doing, because I decided I couldn't cope with programme.
I will be back on Convention programmes next year, I should think, or later this year, but
not this one.
Yes.
So I am on.
So Liz isn't on anything because as mentioned previously, Liz does not, yeah, is not a member
of the Convention, but she will definitely be on OptiThought Live.
I am on down the virtual pub, fan groups in the time of Covid-19 and beyond, which will
be 9pm on Saturday with Marchin, Clack, Tim, Mendelies and FranDoud.
I am on future of EasterCon at 9am on Sunday, so 12 hours later, with Phil Dyson and Faro
Mendelssohn, and then I'm on the third row fandom panel on Monday at 10.30.
I have to say, down the virtual pub is the item that I probably would have wanted to
be on if I don't be on programme items.
So I might be the audience for that one, but I might also be in the bar as it's like
P.E.A.V.L. Saturday.
I mean, I'm absolutely going to be on the one about the third row and sit in the third
row and heckle.
I mean, obviously.
Yep.
I assume you're going to, I assume the Convention is aware that the third row in that panel
is going to need to have more chairs in it, because like, there's quite a lot of, there
might be quite a lot of people wanting to sit in it.
I don't know.
It's a state of mind, John.
It's not literally the third row, it is a state of mind.
This will be the schism of the third row one day.
A lot of people are probably very confused right now, so you'll have to come to that
panel to find out what we are talking about and heckle John.
Yes.
The other programme item I'm excited to go to is the book launch of Neil Harrison's
book.
It's the first time I've ever seen a book launch.
It's a book launch that I've ever seen.
WorldCon, this time also used the You Can Sign Up for, you know, we'll give you a lot of
the items and you can sign up for the ones you think you are interested in.
And I see EasterCon as Confront.
It's going to be interesting to see how we think that is working versus the traditional
method of some programmers put you on some stuff.
You decide whether it's actually the stuff you would like to be on or not.
And then an email of varying levels of politeness based on how much we have got your subject
matter of interest wrong.
So I'm interested to see how it works.
I was interested that there was, what was interesting to me is that I went on PlanZ
and I filled in the, I went through the list and filled in the ones I thought might be
good on.
I think I picked out like four or five maybe and like rated one is like quite high.
And then a few others are like, you know, I think I'd be interested on this but equally,
I don't think I'd necessarily have unique insights or if you have someone better great.
And then I went on the list of ones that they'd already sort of earmarked me for.
And there were a couple where I looked at and thought, ah, it might be a good pick for that
but equally am I just like kidding myself.
And I was on them.
And I was like, oh, okay.
So that was kind of interesting because I was like, oh, maybe I'm like being slightly too
like harsh on myself.
It seems like they're kind of approaching it from both ways where you can express interest,
but there's also clearly a level where they're like, well, you know, we know John could be
on a panel about X.
So we will sort of put him on and hope he says yes.
The program items I see look good.
There were a few where I was like, oh, I could be on that one but I'd also quite like to go to it.
Which is nice.
One of the ones I signed up for, but I was like, I'm going to be an arring about was one
on tabletop games where I'm like, I could be on it but equally like, I wouldn't say no to just
being in the audience.
Listeners, if you are in the thing, you can see all of the slots that are open for signups.
Which I think there aren't, there shouldn't be very many of those anymore because we're
tying up.
I mean, I think today is essentially the program gets finalised day.
Okay.
I mean, by today, I mean Sunday, not Thursday when you're hearing this listeners.
Yeah, but people will always, you know, people will probably be dropping in and out quite
a lot through the whole process anyway.
It's always what happens.
But yeah, I am quite enjoying basically just going to conventions and not doing anything.
I mean, I did some stuff at Wilkham because I felt like, um, a finalist, I should do some
things but it's quite nice to just rock up and not do anything.
I have been asked to be involved with Glasgow's program team at a very kind of, very kind of
undemanding level and I have said, all right, on the basis that basically they're at the
just throwing ideas into a mailing list stage, which is probably about level effort.
I'm willing to engage in, but Meg will be listening to this and being like, how are
I a minute?
John said yes to a Glasgow thing and then I will receive text messages being like, what else
will you say yes to John?
And so that's terrifying.
And also Meg can play me with Booze Eastcon, which was also terrifying.
[Music]
Alison, you are hard at work on doing things for a convention.
But my understanding is that convention is at least in part core flu.
So do you want to tell us about core flu?
Um, yes.
So I am very excited about Eastcon and I am working very hard on Eastcon.
But the reason I'm working very hard on Eastcon is that on Thursday morning, I'm going to
be very well fast for one, two, three, four, five days and not do any more work on
Eastcon until I get home.
So, sorry, Eastcon.
I mean, I'm sure there'll be some things, but I'm probably not going to be doing a lot
of Eastcon stuff because I'm going to be sitting in a bar talking to Fazzy and Fazzy.
I was just reminded of core flu very much when Liz was saying how nice it was to go to
conventions and not do very much because I feel like core flu is an entire convention
dedicated to go to a convention and not doing very much.
Um, though there's quite a lot more program than I used to for core flu partly because
some of the core flu team are about to bid to hold the Eastcon in Belfast in 2025, which
I'm also very excited about.
We must have talked about this on the part, right?
Don't think we have.
Yeah.
So, so one of the things we should put on the agenda for Octa Thought Live is my impressions
of the Belfast Eastcon site, which I'm hoping to see on Friday.
So, so yeah, by the time you listen to this,
I will be on a plane or about to get on a plane or more likely waiting around an airport or
something of that kind, but then I'll be at a bar in Northern Ireland drinking, drinking
good beer, I hope.
This is pretty exciting, which is the core flu, which is not a very big convention, but
this is core flu 40 and there are going to be, I think, 12 people at core flu 40 who were
at core flu one.
So I think that's quite good.
Quite, you know, not a bad attrition rate.
Right.
And the core flu has quite an old demographic and it's also got quite a lot of people who
you would necessarily expect me to core flu, who are excited by the fact that it's in
Belfast or excited by the fact that it's a conventionally week before Eastcon or something, things of that kind.
So I'm really, really looking forward to it and I'm not really doing anything for it except that
they keep sending me emails saying, "Alice, I might have a view on this," and they always
involve work.
I am excited by the idea of Belfast conventions.
I think this is good.
I'm very excited about the idea of an Eastcon in Belfast and it just means that Wales needs
to get its stuff together and get the Eastcon and we've had one in each of the four constituent
blobs.
Blobs is the safest word.
And you better be quick while we still have four constituent blobs.
Yeah, come on Wales.
Come on.
You've got maybe three years.
Let's do this.
Look, they got very close.
We will have had one in four constituent blobs because of course we've had one in Jersey.
That's true.
I'm looking forward to the Belfast Eastcon.
Should it be selected, which hopefully it will be?
Will the site selection vote have happened?
Are they planning to go for site selection at conversation?
Yeah, there'll be site selection conversation, I believe, they'll vote.
Yeah, I'm pretty sure the site selection at conversation.
Well, some, I know that, like, for instance, Phil Dyson presented two years ahead but said
like, "We're actually going to go for the vote one year ahead."
So I know that this can be fuzzy.
I believe that was just due to their, like, that was a, we'd like to bid but we are not
yet in the position to be ready to do it.
Whereas Glasgow is more, you know, not Glasgow, sorry, Belfast are, you know, I think more
settled, like, they have a venue and everything.
So.
My understanding is that they are bidding this year and if they're not, could they please
tell us Pronto because I think that's also the chair's understanding.
I'd let you, you'll be able to tell us how cold flu was as well at the Eastcon Live.
Although we might be distracted by talking about how Eastcon was.
I just, I just, good chance I won't remember a lot of it.
You might have to take notes.
I mean, as I recall, last year there was not a lot of actual, like, full-on content at all
but we can, we can aim for that this year.
Oh yeah, now.
This is a good, this is a good point.
We would like to encourage listeners to send us things for us to talk about at Eastcon.
Oh yeah!
If you are listening and you think that there is something you would like to hear, please
write in because we never have any idea what to talk about and we just want to talk about
what you want to listen to.
So.
That's not always true.
Sometimes we like to talk about the hard things that you don't want to listen to but
you need to.
But at the Eastcon Live show, what we want to do is be very gentle and lovely and just
talk about shiny things.
So yes, if you have any ideas, please write in.
Can I do.
Oct-Thorp Gaming's Corner, sponsored by Mark Plummer.
Mark Plummer, for when you need information but in a funny way.
New tagline, Mark, if you need to get that old business cards, I charge no fee.
So basically, I went on a work trip for two weeks and I took a bunch of solo board games
and they make work trips while less boring.
It was good.
And I don't know whether I've ever picked it on the podcast.
And this isn't a pick, obviously, because I would be greedy.
But under falling skies is a solo board game I took with me to the States and I played
that a bunch.
And it was good.
And I also took a print and play of Arkham Noir, which is a solo card game, which I can't.
I'm not sure if it's good.
It's enjoyable, but I won twice out of two games and I'm a bit like it's challenging.
But I might need to play again on high difficulty and see whether that improves it.
But yeah, no, solo board games.
They're nice.
But I'm glad to be back.
And the reason I'm going to a friend's house this afternoon and this is a short record,
that's because I'm going to a friend's house and I'm going to play games with other people,
which I haven't done since before last time we recorded.
I also love solo games and I, in fact, have both of the ones John mentioned, both in print
and play versions rather than I think John has the commercial version of under falling skies.
But the print and play is free and you can go and download it and print it and it's not fun.
And I did a bit of big wine yesterday, which was like, oh God, my entire life is getting up
and not playing games and doing EasterCon actions all day and then falling asleep.
And my daughter came over and we played Terraforming Mars, which is quite a long fuck.
Tony took us four hours this time, which is faster than the previous time.
Are you eventually going to pick Terraforming Mars?
Oh.
Because, you know, that is the sort of thing that on a future episode you could pick because it is an SF work.
It's from 2016, yes.
I don't know if we picked it yet, though.
I'm not sure if we can get it out of the way.
I think I do that. That is quite excellent.
Yeah.
I mean, I would like to see someone, I mean, I've only played the Terraforming Mars card game with Jump,
but I would like to see someone option Terraforming Mars and Tonya Video.
Basically, someone wants to make the Mars Trilogy, but the Mars Trilogy is still under option,
so they're doing Terraforming Mars potentially.
Yeah.
I mean, I guess, but like, Terraforming Mars is like just a game about, I mean, obviously, it's a game about Terraforming Mars, right?
This is not surprising.
But like, it's not like the Expanse is about Terraforming Mars.
They didn't, I don't understand what it is you're optioning.
Like, the concept of Terraforming Mars is something you can make a movie about.
And they said like, "Oh, we want to explore like colonialism."
And I'm like, "The board game doesn't touch on colonialism at all."
I, it's really, I don't understand.
I guess it's so that they can call it Terraforming Mars and get the board game friends in.
But I don't know how much money that's worth.
Clearly something because they spent money on it.
But, um, but yeah, odd.
I was a bit non-plus when you said you could take it as a pick because
nothing I like about it really has a lot to do with the theme, you know?
But that doesn't matter.
Yeah, okay.
Let's, let's take this another time.
I mean, I, I do.
Well, hang on. No.
I mean, I don't mean, I don't mean like, there is the argument artistically that it doesn't matter.
But like, my first pick, this episode was peer pressure.
Uh, and it's not, I didn't pick that for the SF, no quality of the idea.
I picked it for the lulls.
And so I do think it's important that we have a rule that sometimes we're allowed to, like,
we don't necessarily have to pick things for the broad philosophical conversations they unlock.
Listeners will be like, but you always pick things for the broad philosophical questions they unlock.
Obviously, uh, we pay attention.
Okay. Fair. Um, yeah, no.
So a future pick, Terraforming Mars, maybe.
Um, so yeah, I did squeeze a four-hour board game into yesterday.
And watch the second episode to tell us.
That was the "Oltutthot" podcast.
And it's goodbye for me.
It's goodbye from me.
"Plan Z" was the name given to the planned re-equipment and expansion of the Kriegsmder
in order by Hitler in early 1939.
I do not think that is the plan Z that I'm looking for.
Possibly you shouldn't have a piece of software used for your schedule where if you Google for it,
you get a thing about Hitler.
I don't know how to diplomatically put that in the thing.
No, I think just like, if I was naming a thing that is not, I would just like, I don't know anything.
The first thing I do is Google it to see if there's anything else with the same name.
And while I appreciate that this is not in the similar vein that's going to be confusion,
you probably don't want it to be a thing that people Google and go, "Oh, I just did."
No, that is true.
I'm sure it wasn't the intent, but it might be that after this year,
that name could be sort of politely retired in favor of something less, uh, Hitler-y.
I mean, I suspect it's- if it is a fork of Zambia, then that's a reason to use it.
100% that's probably why.
Listeners write in, but did it take us 80 episodes to trigger Godwin's law?
Because that's a pretty good run.
It's possible, yeah.
I really think you should cut this stuff out.
I mean, we can see.
The theme music for this episode was "Fanfare for Space" by Kevin MacLeod in Competec.com,
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.