No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no,
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 18th episode of the Oct Thor podcast, a podcast
for science fiction and science fiction fandom. I am Jon Coxon.
I am Alison Scott.
No, I'm Liz Batty.
Today's going to be a somewhat shorter episode than usual because we are running a convention
and it turns out that that involves work, which I didn't know and Alison and Liz didn't
tell me. Boo.
We so did. I said it wouldn't be too much work and that was wrong.
Yeah, exactly.
I think the amount of work it is reflects the fact that none of us have run a convention
quite like this before because this amount of convention would not be very much work
if it was a real but it's more work because it's a because we're all doing it for the
first time. So none of us have any of the, I guess, muscle memory.
We're not doing anything on autopilot except when we do.
Yes. So before we get into letters of comment, I just want to say if you are listening to
this and if you like online conventions, join Punctuation at PunctuationCon.uk.
You are listening to this and you don't particularly care for online conventions but you want to
give us a favour anyway. Join Punctuation at PunctuationCon.uk and if you just fancy a natter,
then join because they'll be nattering.
Hooray.
This is a great way to support the podcast but well it isn't because we don't get any of the money
because it's all going to fan funds and charity but it's a great way to show your appreciation
of the podcast because as you can see we have no advertising sponsorship.
If you are an advertiser and you'd like to sponsor OctaThork,
absolutely get in touch, we have 67 regular listeners and we do in fact have at least one
convention member who's joined the convention because they like the podcast. So I think that's
quite good really.
I need to caveat that 67 which is, I don't know, is that, did you make that up Alison?
Yeah 90% of statistics are made up of on the spot and that's one of them.
Excellent. Okay, what we do have is, and I believe I'm now using this correctly,
a plethora of letters of comment.
What we have more than we want?
Well yeah because ideally we'd have none and we could just sack this in super quickly and go
back to con running right? So...
No, no, no. The letters are what's providing content for your podcast this morning because
otherwise it would get to Thursday and people would be like, "Oh my god there's another day to go
before punctuation. What am I going to do for entertainment?"
And they would look at OctaThork and we'd be like with three minutes long.
Yes, by the time you listen to this list there will be one day until punctuation.
About a day and a half Liz is making a face into the camera which I think is dread.
I wasn't making a face but yeah I do have a knowing sense of dread.
I would say also if this episode is too short for your simple needs,
if you are a member of punctuation come on the Discord where there's been quite a lot of chat
going on and you can A) work out your happy with Discord and B)
see what everybody's saying and maybe make some friends
if you don't know anyone. Yeah and come and say hello, we like that.
I've just waved, this is a podcast. I need to wave less on podcasts.
That's like 2021 goal. Fair enough. And we will say so we are planning to run,
the convention is mostly on Discord and so if you are not familiar with Discord please do join.
As soon as you hear this, come and join. Then if you have any trouble we can help you through
email or through Facebook Messenger or through other mechanisms and we will be very helpful.
So yes.
Onto letters of comment. Liz, do you want to read Jo's tweet of comment?
Jo's tweet of comment about things she's missing from social spaces is the ability to hear and
understand multi-threaded conversations and the problem is that Zoom conversations all come from
one direction it's hard to disentangle multiple speakers and I can see what she means and that
you don't get those occasionally branching and coming back together conversations in a group
that you can have say if you're all sitting around a table and you know what's going on in
Zoom you just get a bunch of people talking over each other. It's rubbish.
Yeah and that's one of the reasons you can't have Zoom breakout rooms above about eight people
before it gets a little bit chaotic. We'll definitely be trying out some other things. I mean we may do
wonder which is the internet service that used to be called Yodrive and we may be doing a bit of
Gather Town. I mean I think this is still an unsolved problem there.
Yes it is. I think and this is one of the reasons why I think although I do understand
that obviously Discord is not good for audio video in the same way that Zoom is but I do think
Discord text chats do represent the closest to this that I have seen as an accessible platform.
Because I find you can have the different channels so you can have different places to
wander into but like in those channels you can have conversations that are like bifurcating and
coming back together and that is the closest I've seen. But I think it's an enormously difficult
thing to solve in audio video and perhaps easier to solve in text. Bob is he text isn't quite as good.
So yeah it's tricky. We're also going to the other way that you can't solve it is in online spaces
and we are definitely in kind of virtual reality like headset spaces and we're going to have a
go at one of those as well but there's a big problem that so it gives you some of the spatial
stuff and it allows you to move around to different people and it gives you sort of
nearer you are the better the sound is further you are the sound is further away and it gives you
the sense of presence and the only downside is you look like a robot and have to wear a
helmet on your head neither of which are perfect for social interactions. Oh yes true okay um we
also had a I'm going to describe it as a flurry of tweets from listener and and is a new listener
who has listened to our entire back catalog since the last episode of octa-thorpe so welcome
and we will henceforth call anyone who on board by listening to our entire back catalog as and
that will be their nickname it will get enormously confusing and it will be good but she did send us
well she sent us some thoughts she sent us a tweet of comment with a photograph of her
breakfast at the virtual octa-con which will perhaps be the chapter art at the point you listen to this
and we we note the mushrooms she also sent us a tweet saying that she is dependent on the kindness
and others for good poached eggs which um okay so so Gordon Ramsey who's famous for saying the
sort of things you can't say on a podcast I understand you can but we have to put a little
label on the podcast now um does actually have a video on his on youtube about how to poach an
egg and it's very good excellent you can learn to poach eggs it's fine just get fresh eggs it's
very good if you if you know somebody who has chickens the best way to make poached eggs is to
get an egg more or less straight from the chicken and make that your poached egg because because eggs
poached much better when they're very fresh um this might be too much egg poaching information for
a slow podcast but you know oh I don't know I think it's excellent no I agree I have tried to
learn to poach eggs in various different ways you know whisking it little like egg poachers that
sit on the side of the pan and they were all terrible okay fresh eggs yeah but then I'd have to go out
and get eggs before a breakfast and that's just not going to work is it and they don't need to be
that fresh a couple of days it's fine but generally speaking when you get an egg in the supermarket
it may have been it may have spent some time getting from the the chicken or the duck to you so
so it's easier if you get them from someone to keep the chickens or a farm where they they're just kind
of getting the eggs and selling those straight off um we also have we also have a letter of
comment from Andrge who um yes caught up uh caught up with us and um has tested us a a a long
letter of comment basically commenting on every theme that we've had in the past 17 episodes
which is great um but she does um she does write a poem um and it is it is quite good so I shall
I shall read it now Oh to thought poetry corner Oh bugger I forgot I was told to write a rhyme
this is the best I've got in the available time cracking poem there's an egg there's an egg
reference for you yes so another tweet of comment we got is from Duncan McGregor who says that he
thinks it would be off brand if we run an online convention and we don't make a complete hash of
it which is funny because an octa thought is sometimes called a hash yeah no no I think we've
got good news for Duncan he then follows that up with has he asks whether we have pounded this
joke into the ground yet which is funny because an octa thought is sometimes called a pound it's
quite good I thoroughly enjoyed this tweet you can't see but I'm nodding vigorously and I know I'm
fairly sure that we've not yet pounded that joke into oblivion and that our readers will help I
think Duncan's the only one that's come up with it so hats off to Duncan he wins my respect he
already had it but uh okay we also had other letters we also got a letter of comment from Max
which was titled a thought vigorous um and she got the title from gmail's ai
generating email subjects so but it's a good email subject um for a letter of comment
particularly um but she says that she has managed to incapacitate herself with muscle fatigue
caused by playing vigorous VR after a month's break if you too would like to ae horribly when
you try to move your arms laugh or breathe too heavily try the thrill of the fight on oculus quest
so I have done so yes I bought it yesterday I beat the training dummy and I beat like the the
practice game and then they put me in against the first opponent and I had three two-minute rounds
I'd stopped this by because my my thing that tells you how much exercise you do if you play a video
game said you'll be you'll be burning about 15 calories a minute playing this and I was like
god I'll die that's impossible and I can confirm that that yes three three rounds of two minutes did
kill me and also I lost so but I feel like hey today so I'm planning to do it again today so we will
we will see how it goes I kind of I should say I don't really approve of the theme of this video
game which is about beating up men a lot boxing actually ravio too yeah as good as I um so yes
so for those who are the way i thrill of the fight is a VR boxing game and now I have learned that this
exists and now I have learned that a listener and ours and both have it I assume we are going to have
a VR boxing match at punctuation it doesn't have multiplayer that's all these people going
multiplayer would be good oh what that is why ah but also it's obvious I would get beaten up by
max a lot yes but that would be that would be a I would I would come to that program item
so you know when it gets multiplayer if it's a lot of players by punctuation to
and if we do punctuation to then we'll talk I mean I feel because I was like I'm I'm a woman and I
would I would probably enjoy this game more if my opponents were also female and it about 30 seconds
less than 30 seconds about three seconds of thought caused me to work out but in fact I would
probably prefer this game if my opponents were cute aliens I don't really the whole beating up
people is is not quite for me um yeah I I I have low tolerance for video games in which
of the I I can I can have any sort of empathy for the other side um on the other hand you know
boxing games are quite fun and they are fantastically good just um in terms of exercise that you
could do in your house without equipment hashtag other than the asterisk other than the extremely
expensive oculus quest that they're pretty good cheap too is it it I mean obviously
oculus quest is expensive but but the game is eight pounds which seems to me to be very reasonable
and a lot better than a lot of oculus game quest games which seem to be quite expensive fair enough
um Liz if you bought a VR boxing game what would you want your opponents to look like
thing is I don't actually want to play a VR boxing game all I want to be a headset for is so I can
play beats over that's true that's a good point Liz playing beats over is a sight to behold and if
there was any good way of doing that as a program writer we would also do that but there is not
one day listeners one day yeah I feel that this is all this all of this stuff's gonna come
quite soon they're kind of getting quite good at the the necessary tech so that you can film
people while they're also playing on their oculus quest and you can see both things at once um yeah I
um I feel I might actually enjoy this game more if if I was beating on Donald Trump because I'm
not done with that yet oh yeah it's gonna take you a little while and I can also think of some
also current politicians that I could that I wouldn't mind having as my virtual uh right okay
onto Claire Breiley of Croydon who is sent has a lock um she says that no one should actually
nominate weekend we mix for a hugo and we categorically disagree we are all going to nominate for a
hugo we thoroughly encourage all of our listeners to nominate for a hugo um so that's that good
that we sorted that out mark devised and constructed the lego box for sending the
weeabics through the post and she also sends us a poem now I'm hoping Alison can explain this
hang on a second oh Claire sent us a poem yes um Claire sent us a poem which I will read out
and I I confidently predict that four or five of our readers will fall over laughing at this one
and actually knows because it's actually gay four or five of our readers will find this funny
and the rest will go no no I don't get that um I found it funny but I don't understand the
contexts so I thought I thought having you but she's provided she has provided context yes
um so which we will put into the show notes for you online strain can mean physical pain
so you stretch but say ow is that blood you won't hurt your necks if you just enter text in
widow is wonderful mud thank you and and the background for this um is that widow is wonderful
things well widow is things a variety of um sorts have been a fanist trope for many many decades um
I also like the the kind of echoes here of um a flanders and swam because they are also into mud
they're not the same sort of mud wonderful mud though or glorious mud which is very similar and
so Claire also says so Claire says if causing a global volcanic eruption is a sufficient code of
condor violation to justify ejection from the convention um she worries about some of the
behaviors that might be acceptable by comparison I would like to say that when we when we said that
global volcanic eruptions were a kind of color violation we don't mean to exclude any of the
varied um examples Claire gives one example of a thing that would not be acceptable is setting fire
to a lake I don't know how many people learn to sun that joke but it is a joke and if you understood
it you get points yeah if you understood that joke get in touch and you can have a point for your
house at punctuation yes I know Claire will get it anyone else I'm unsure um and she concludes by
saying that she only drinks two or three points a coffee now or when she was civil servant it was
four or five points with occasional espresso's which I took two mugs which is I believe like
maybe one point one and a half point so Claire is more caffeine than woman during my if you read
my trip report cover to cover you will understand the reference there's no charts I'm going to
read you I mean I think I'm pretty sure I've done my ego scan there that's why that's why anyone
who understands the joke yeah that that's why anyone who understands the joke gets a point because
I am not confident it's like PhD theses they do not get read widely is that like how you know when
sometimes like professors will put like a hidden word on their web page that you have to quote back
to them when you email them to prove you've actually read their website this is basically your
shibboleth for whether I've read your tough report isn't it yes something like that oh my god that's
amazing one of the professors at um Lester when I was an undergraduate um taught the
statistical inference course and he was planning to write it up into a book so um in the um course
notes it basically said if you could find five typos I will give you a book voucher for 20 quid
apparently I was the only person in the history of his teaching career to ever find the five typos
and collect my book voucher but I was like free book voucher I'm not an idiot I'm an undergraduate
with no money you know like books if he had done that with Claire Broly she'd have found five typos
on the first page and he'd have been very shocked they'd all have been things like this
comma appears to be in Helvetica 14 not 12 as someone who has had Claire edit him Claire's good
at editing Claire taught me how to use semicolons correctly or no Claire taught me how not to use
m dashes incorrectly are you sure it's not just that Claire corrected all of your I mean I feel
like she made off of actually taught you to use semicolons correctly I'm pretty sure she did if
you misuse a semicolon now I can it's class fault yep okay moving on from Claire's letter of
color before I get into trouble there will definitely be semicolons of punctuation yes okay Mark
Plummer wrote to us saying that he understands Claire had already written to us about this but
the wittabix capsule was his work so I get the impression that Claire is in charge of writing
the fanzines and Mark is in charge of sort of the engineering behind them. Mark's an extremely
accomplished fan writer also as we do I know Mark it didn't yes it is the official position of the
up to the podcast that barca claire are both extremely talented fan writers Britain's greatest
living fan writers to you that's true Britain's greatest living fan writers I believe he does say
that in the very niche area of wittabix related fanzines Claire is responsible for content and he
is responsible for building Lego wittabix capsules yes I will wittabix related fanzines yes then that
makes sense I think we could all agree he also fixed the lid on the recycling bin with an old
rolling pin handle and some string she gets a wittabix for punctuation breakfast shouldn't I?
I've got to I've got to oh yes I've got to read this out verbatim sorry in this fan household I
am responsible for engineering projects such as making little Lego wittabix capsules and fixing
the lid on the recycle bin with an old rolling pin handle and some string as well as ironing
and putting things down in the wrong place Claire is responsible for wittabix related fanzines
list making and putting things in the right place especially commerce that's true and we're
we're in it was very good it made me chuckle quellot but yes and he also mentions that we mentioned
that the wittabix fanzine is eligible in best fanzine hugo he says technically eligible I would
define it as gloriously eligible and then he says thanks to octa the walk he finds himself in the
personally surprising position of how he's something to nominate in the best fan cast category no
you're not going to put that to the podcast john we we do not put things like that to the podcast
we just say something like mark also said some very nice things about octa thought which we're
going to which we're not going to repeat what we really want is not so much um
not so much awards and recognitions as for more people to listen to the podcast and award and
recognition does help with that so and wittabix we're also happy with wittabix uh you know don't
please do not all send us wittabix definitely did not send me wittabix because as previously
elaborated it might be complicated i i don't why people said it would be wittabix on the basis
that it would save you a trip to wittra's it doesn't really though it does if people said enough wittabix
please send wittabix in packages of 108 wittabix too i think so don't do that because mark a clair
might and then you'll be then you feel really guilty oh i won't i'll be rolling around in my
massive bathtub of wittabix okay so what we need now is for somebody to send john 108 wittabix
and he then promises to roll around in a massive tub of wittabix and and fill it for the podcast
my address is so Alex Holden got in touch with me about octa thought and um wants to point out
she is in fact a folkie in this she likes and enjoys folk music even though he doesn't make folk music
though there obviously is he makes concertinas he does make folk music um in that way and he says
something else as well as i was going to say oh yeah and that he listened to most of our podcast
whilst making my concertino which i thought it's pretty cool so he he he has said on his instagram
that he listens to every podcast in the world you know just fast fast numbers of podcasts because
that's what you do if you work with your hands um so just before we wrap up um please do if you
are considering coming to punctuation um come along um we at the time that you are listening to this
will be one day away so don't delay join now if you hear this sort of a week after it drops
don't join it finished sorry yeah there you know send us your send us your reflections of the
convention you didn't get so so next next episode will be punctuation aftermath i i mean we haven't
really talked about what we're doing in the next episode that's that's not we don't
have to do trailers for the next episode of octop do we we're not nearly that organized are we we
don't know what we're talking about in the next episode until five minutes before the next episode
if that all right Liz come on we're very organized that was the 18th episode of the octothor podcast
and we will all see you at punctuation but for now it is goodbye from me it's goodbye from me
and it's goodbye from me
um and she's also sent us a photograph of a full english breakfast at her full english
breakfast at virtual octacon um and she is planning a similar breakfast for punctuation i i think
you should make the breakfast like a chapter heading because it's kind of a demonstration of
what breakfast should be like at virtual conventions have you got this picture didn't didn't we cover
that like two minutes ago in the podcast? it's a great idea Alison and if i hadn't said it two
minutes ago it would definitely go in okay so i've seen all of my brain is fried
i thought you were doing a bit and then i realized you were doing a bit uh anyway but yes
crack it idea Alison i might leave your version in and take mine out i kind of wonder what i did
i think you were probably distracted by um looking up other letters of coit or reading
and i was i was distracted by reading Alison's letter of coit but i mean i think i must have been
more than averagely distracted at that point because that's obviously the thing that caused us
to be talking about poached eggs is the first place yes yes exactly exactly
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud at ncompetech.com
used under a creative commons attribution 3.0 license this podcast will end at the beep