We are recording this as a pick up because something very surprising happened.
It did. We are thrilled and delighted to discover that we are a finalist for the BSFA award for nonfiction,
which was announced after we recorded our podcast but before it dropped so we're doing an extra special bit.
And this is it.
And we are nominated in nonfiction alongside Anna McFarland, Joy Sanchez Taylor, Mark Bould, Francesca Barbini and Val Nolan.
So congratulations to all the other people.
They have all been nominated for writing and editing books and we have been nominated for this.
It's fair to say that this is an outlier in BSFA award nonfiction nominations.
We're quite pleased though.
Bewilded. Is that the word you use, John? Bewilded.
I am, I think Bewilded captures, I'm delighted and I'm very excited and also I was quite surprised when we were on the long list.
So my surprise at being on the short list is quite a lot higher.
I remember I told John when he got back from the pub, I said, "Check your email."
Liz, Liz is on location and so her audio may be a bit more muffled than usual.
Yes, we recorded early because I am on holiday and so this is an unplanned emergency octa-thaw session we have convened to say,
"Yeah, it's very exciting. I don't think I've ever been nominated for any award."
So that's very exciting.
I think we're the first podcast to be nominated for BSFA award.
I mean, I haven't taken every single nominee, but I think so.
And yes, when I looked at the long list, I was like, "Oh, that's a good bunch of serious academic and critical works.
We're on the long list."
And I thought there would be a short list of own.
And so it's very nice for us to be on it, but I am slightly bewildered, but also pleased that people like it.
I'm from John, who is as previously established, John is a novel, so not eligible.
Sorry, John.
[LAUGHTER]
Is John a novel?
Yeah, I'm trying to do a running gag.
It is. No, yeah, we did decide that I was a novel and therefore...
When? When?
Last episode, episode before.
Oh.
You probably weren't listening.
Shh, don't give away my secrets.
It's hard to get running jokes going when...
Well, let's do it. Remember what we said on the previous episode.
But we'll try. We'll keep going.
But it does tie into the running joke where Alison doesn't listen to the podcast, so that's good.
I listen to the podcast repeatedly.
I listen to the podcast where we recorded to that.
I listen to the podcast and editing it, and then I sometimes listen to the podcast when it drops.
And this is very embarrassing, really.
Sometimes if I'm feeling a bit sad, I just listen to a back episode of the podcast and it cheers me up.
I... I... I'm mine.
That's very sweet.
You are just callers, Alison.
It's not the same.
Um...
My colleague, Martin, posted on my Facebook post about this saying,
"Did they read your scientific papers?"
And I... I think he saw science fiction and thought, "Aha!"
But, uh... But even if they had nonfiction,
we've managed to go off topic listeners and we've been recording for a grand total of four minutes
and fifty seconds.
So...
Oh no, I've got one more...
Because we ought to say extraordinary general meeting.
What? Just...
Just as a complete non-sequitur.
Well, this was like it's an emergency opt-of-thought.
And I was... I wanted to say, yes, it's our extraordinary general meeting.
I like to think of it as an emergency holographic octa-thought.
Anyway, we've recorded enough, Alison.
Can I be played by Robert Piccardo?
Well, I have to fight before it.
Who's Robert Piccardo?
We're making Star Trek jokes now.
We've played the emergency holographic doctor in Star Trek Voyager.
Thank you very much to BSFA members for nominating us and the voting openers today.
So do go and read those very good works of critical science fiction and vote.
Members of the BSFA and members of the Eastcon are eligible to vote
in the BSFA awards and the awards are going to be given out at Eastcon at the award ceremony.
Yeah, and it's a good fiction shortlist, so you should also go out and read as much of that as you
can before the voting deadline.
Yeah, lots of great fiction on there.
Yes, agreed.
I'd love to say it includes books I've read, but I'm not sure it does.
This was the octa-thought podcast drop-in.
Yeah, please chop most of the nonsense out of that.
There was a lot of nonsense about fashion, so on.
Hello everyone and welcome to the 52nd episode of Octa-Thorp, a podcast for science fiction and
science fiction fandom.
This episode is coming to you on the 3rd of March 2022.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And today we have a letter of comment all about boxing from Christopher J Garcia.
I feel we brought this one on ourselves, really.
Yes, basically there are lots of boxing organisations.
If you'd like to know more, talk to Chris about that.
He does also say that he likes the games Hugo and he talked a little bit about short films and
says he would like to see more of those on the ballot, but they don't end up on the ballot.
So that's sad.
He makes a recommendation for a short film called The Fantastical Flying Books of Mr Morris Lessmore,
and we will link to it in the show notes.
We will.
I think I have that.
I think it was a free film on iTunes at one point in the days when you still bought
media for it to be on your computer, as opposed to just streaming everything from some sort of
amorphous mainframe somewhere. But he is also on YouTube, so you know, now I can stream it
from some amorphous mainframe somewhere.
Hoorah!
Thank you very much for writing in Chris.
Thank you, Chris, for writing in.
We think we should also add that he did explain all the boxing organisations by
analogies to science fiction and fantasy awards, which is obviously the best way to explain
things to this podcast.
So basically, for explaining anything to us, you have to do it in terms of science fiction awards.
Yes.
How would you explain the hugas in terms of science fiction awards?
Recursively.
Yeah, you'd have to shove them. Never mind.
Peter Sullivan emailed us to tell us where to find the Christmas TAF website,
and we'll put that in the show notes.
And Ming wrote on Facebook to ask how I would want to have without getting the most votes
is this some sort of "fanish first past the post" system.
And Alison commented saying that it's much more complicated than that, which it is.
Basically, there were four people in that race, and in order to win, you had to have at least
20% of the vote on either side of the Atlantic.
So you had to have 20% of the US and Canadian votes and 20% of the European votes.
And I was the only candidate that got 20% of the votes on both sides of the Atlantic.
So Liam Proven and Graham Charnock got more votes than me but did not get.
The right number of votes on both sides.
I had not realised until I went to find that for Ming that in fact,
Liam got vastly more votes than you.
Just enormous numbers more votes than you would have.
I was only shy on the US side by about one or two votes, not for many.
So we're very sorry, Liam.
But look, look, look what a great fan John has turned out to be wearing.
You just, you know, pissed off to Prague and have babies.
Just the one baby, actually.
I was gonna say plural.
No, Liam needed one more North American vote.
And I believe I'm right in saying, I might be wrong about this,
but I'm pretty sure at the time someone noticed that one of Liam's North American nominators
does not appear on the list of people he voted.
So, you know, when you're running for TAF, get your nominators to vote for you.
That is a wise campaign strategy, regardless of opinions or self promotion.
I should say I have voted for Anders for TAF this week and would suggest that all of you do the same.
I have also already voted for fear.
I got my very nice and early.
So yes, recommended.
Yeah, so do vote for TAF this week.
Remember your second and third and fourth place votes, because all the candidates are very good.
The rules have since been changed such that the 20% rule is only applied when there are
three remaining candidates on the ballot.
And so if that rule had been in place in that form when I was running for TAF,
I suspect I would not have won, because I suspect Liam would have achieved 20% in the second round
of vote allocation, and Liam would have gone.
But, you know, these things happen.
Liam could just stand again at some point.
Liam, if you're listening, which I know you're not, run for TAF.
Yeah, we can discuss separately the practicalities of running for fan fans when you have small children.
There was a tweet from Peter Sullivan as well that said for a really serious challenge,
try and get a five-way tie in TAF and get all of them to meet the 20% rule on each side of the Atlantic.
That's not so much a challenge as a fix.
And actually, I'm not sure how that would intersect with the 20% rule doesn't get applied until
there are three candidates, because if no one's eliminated, how does that work?
I assume it's solved by a football match in the gardens of the Birmingham Hilton Metropole,
and if you know otherwise, you should write in.
We also heard from Duncan McGregor, who wrote on the subject of the Games Hugo,
"In the grimdark future of the Hugo Awards, they are all games, and I desperately tried
to decide whether to vote for the latest Tilaris expansion, thousand-year vampire,
or the next Warhammer 40,000 Tyranid Codex or something.
This seems tricky. Thanks for that vision of Hell, Octorp."
And, firstly, you're welcome.
I responded saying Necrons all the way, and Duncan revealed that he has
a Necron Christmas jumper, which is 10 out of 10, and should definitely win some sort of Hugo.
"For the benefit of our less connected listeners, what's a Necron?"
It's a race of beings whose souls were harvested by the Catan and distilled into robots to do their
bidding, and they worship a god who's probably buried on Mars.
And so the Adeptus mechanic has probably actually worked,
worshiping the same god, and that could be a bit tricky if it ever wakes up.
"In what universe?"
"One forty thousand."
So they're basically sort of, I've just saw some good-ling,
skeletal robot zombie warriors.
"Yeah."
"And maybe Alice and Chadros won with a Christmas hat on?"
"What we need is a Necron with an Octo-Thought Christmas jumper."
"Ooh."
"We do need that."
"I will do that."
"I used to play Necrons when I was a nipper."
"Saying ever more elaborate fanart challenges for Alice and tune in next fortnight to see
what we come up with."
"I love the fact that we're talking about Christmas jumpers in February,
rather than say October when it's commercially viable."
"Ock to Thorpe, the podcast of commercial viability."
"Readers, if you want, you can email me and Liz and place bets on what we can make Alice
and draw, and we will try and get her to draw it without telling her what it is,
and that will be very fun for everyone."
So if you have any ideas, do get in touch, and we can have some fun.
Sorry, Alice, in advance.
"How are they going to get touched?"
"They're going to email me or discord me. I'm around."
"Yeah, this is not- this is the sort of thing that does not work when I podcast scales to people
who do not know us personally. Then we have Twitter accounts, you can tweet us."
"You can probably DM the ock to Thorpe account, because I'm not sure if Alice and remembers password."
"I get forwards, though."
And finally, we heard from Laurie from the Hugo Girl podcast,
whose To Be Redpile has been sidelined because I mentioned six weeks on last
Friday's podcast, and sorry, Laurie. I hope you like it.
I found out that Liz and Alice and have not read it, and so at some point in the future,
I was about to say near future, but you know, what even is time?
I will be encouraging them both to read it so we can discuss it on the cast.
So keep your ears peeled.
And also be cool if Hugo Girl discussed it on their podcast,
because it did end up as a Hugo finalist.
On the subject of Hugo Award finalists, the deadline for nominating for you goes is the 15th
of March, which is just under two weeks from when this episode will drop.
So you should all nominate things.
Nominate the things you like.
I will be nominating things.
I like one of which we may be discussing later.
Ooh, foreshadowing.
We put a list of some of the things we like on the fan categories in Corlobulot's blog.
So for instance, I will be nominating the fabulous banana wings.
I will be nominating the excellent Sumason.
I will be nominating the incomparable Become the Teapot,
and I will be enthusiastically getting behind.
It's Banya.
I'll be nominating Sandra Bond.
So those are, for examples of fans I will be nominating in different categories.
So yeah, do get on and nominate.
Who are you nominating, peeps?
Well, I'm definitely nominating Sandra Bond now that you mention it.
And I'm nominating Claire Brawley and I'm nominating Mark Plummer.
I am going to nominate for fan artists, as well as the people on that list.
I'm going to nominate Olarika O'Brien.
And then, like science fiction books, I'm definitely nominating the actual star,
but I still haven't read enough science fiction books published in 2021
to fill up my nomination categories.
I am going to nominate the Unraveling by Benjamin Rosenbaum,
which is a 2021 novel.
I am going to nominate something from Mythic Quest,
and I am torn as to whether nominate to nominate,
like the whole of season two in best romantic presentation, long form,
or whether to pick my favorite episode of season two,
or whether to pick the episode of season two,
I think everyone else is going to nominate.
So I have to do some thinking there.
Because my assumption is if there is one episode which appeals to Hugo Voters,
it will be the one about young Carl Longbottom becoming a writer.
Oh, is Alison's gone fingers in her ears because she hasn't seen it yet?
It's not really a spoiler though.
No, no, it's fine, it's fine, it's fine.
I didn't hear it anyway.
So I think I'll probably nominate that episode, yes.
But I did also like the one where they have to decide if they're wolves or sheep.
That was great.
And it's like a bottle episode all in one episode,
and it is a great episode.
But maybe not the one which will appeal most of the Hugo Voters.
Maybe not.
It seems likely that if Mythic Quest got a Hugo finalist spot,
they'd be quite excited about that given that they've got a nebula in their show, wouldn't it?
Possibly.
Oh, I just want to tell you, John, while I was looking up the name of the episode of Mythic Quest,
you can apparently now read the tears of the Inarron story.
It's presumably terrible, so I might have to look at that.
[Music]
Ch icon are planning to be hybrid, but the exact details of that haven't been announced yet.
They also haven't announced things like platforms,
and whether they have a virtual membership or any of that sort of stuff.
They have, however, appointed a virtual program lead, which is Eddie Louise.
I had a chat with Eddie a couple of weeks ago that was very interesting.
Eddie led tech for both the firecons, so she has very good chops here,
and she also has been involved in the nebula weekend.
That's where her background in running virtual events are from,
that she's very excited about the possibilities of virtual,
and all the other decisions have been made.
She's kind of talking about all the sorts of highly engaged virtual programming that
we try to do, the sort of things we try to do with punctuation,
and the sort of things that I particularly like.
So I'm quite excited about that.
I ended up talking to her because I had volunteered help on fanzine lounge,
and if I'm not going to be at Ch icon, then I'm very happy to kind of run the virtual
fanzine lounge for them.
If I am at Ch icon, I guess I'm going to be doing some stuff on fanzine lounge.
And I've promised a note on what a virtual fanzine lounge might look like,
which I very much need to get on and do.
I will be going to try conz hybrid stuff if there is any.
I have a Ch icon supporting membership, so hopefully there will be something included in that.
I quite enjoyed the discount virtual stuff, but I have to be honest,
probably not enough to pay an uplift to a virtual membership,
if it's more than a supporting membership.
So I do kind of hope.
It was only $25.
I didn't get $25 of value out of it, and so if it costs that much again, I would not pay it.
I don't think.
And I don't really see what the 25-pound boards, or $25 boards, but maybe I'm just not thinking
about it properly.
It was mainly the right podcast for this argument, but I mean, you could say,
what does $50 for a 14 membership get you?
It essentially gets you at this point, sort of voting rights, nominating rights,
site-section voting rights, and the Hugo packet, which is all free stuff donated by the people who
made that stuff.
So I can see an additional monetary cost could be involved in the virtual program,
but I think the $50 you pay for a supporting membership,
if I'm trying to put a dollar value on what I get out of it, it's like,
I'm sure you could actually do a feasible sporting membership for much lower,
if it weren't for the fact that you have to set it to a certain number because of the
multiple of supporting rate conversion or whatever it is.
I take your point, but the number of books I read in the last Hugo voter packet,
I think I thought it was well worth the money.
Yeah.
So I appreciate it doesn't cost the worldcon that much to do it,
but I definitely get that much value out of it.
I guess I'm drawing my argument a bit here, which is unhelpful.
But no, I mean, and I'm sure lots of other people did get the value.
I'm just not sure I did really, but that's fine.
Different strokes.
The one of the things people point to as the cost of the virtual membership
is actually the stream out and stream in costs of the physical convention.
And I am beginning to argue more forcefully that the virtual members shouldn't be picking up
those costs, that it's actually part of the cost of putting on the convention,
or they shouldn't be picking up all of those costs.
So, and certainly that was the argument is that you have to have better IT
in lots of different ways to do the stream out and stream in,
than you do just to have people in their own homes using their own equipment.
One of the things that we're going to discuss today is what you want from an
Eastercon bid. So those who are listening in the states, or those who are more familiar with
Worldcons, will be familiar perhaps with the thing called the Fanaging Position,
which is a kind of standard list of questions that sent out to Worldcon bids.
But we don't really have an equivalent for Eastercon.
And I was curious what Alison and Liz and the listenership that you thought are the key bits
of information you would like to know about an Eastercon when you're deciding whether or not
to cast a vote for it. So, full disclosure, Alison and I obviously have horses in this race,
because we are both involved with upcoming Eastercon bids. Liz is currently listening,
you can't see, but she has leaned back. Her hands are on the back of her head, her elbows are wide,
and she looks like the most relaxed person in the world, and I'm very envious of her.
She looks so smug listeners, you don't understand, so smug.
She does look like a person who is not bidding for an Eastercon and feels like she might have
dodged a bullet. And I think as I feel like somebody who actually threw myself in front of the bullet.
So Liz, do you want to start? Do you want to kick things off with what you look for in an Eastercon bid?
Can I put in something that's only slightly relevant here, which is that in a search to find
out what other people put into their Eastercon presentations, John asked for previous Eastercon
material, and so far that has turned up as well as some serious presentations. The bid video for
the 1988 Eastercon, which is hilarious, and which I suppose that's no reason I couldn't put on
YouTube for the delight of an edification of what to thought viewers. Well, and I just really liked
that because it was nice to see what Eastercon bidding was like for the year I was born. Yeah.
Oh, it was the year before you were born. This was done for 1987, but it also turned up like a
kind of script with timing details for the second Jersey bid. What do I look for in an Eastercon
bid presentation? I like to know who's doing it and why they might be good at the jobs they have
chosen to do. I like to know where you're having it and why it is a good place to have it,
and if there are significant drawbacks to that location that you can't avoid, it's nice to know
those upfront as well. I don't think I want you to necessarily show me that you have a fully
fledged code of conduct and harassment policy and access policy, but I want you to tell me that
you are committed to having those things. And then I would like to know why your Eastercon
will be particularly fun. Essentially the way I'd like to know what your Eastercon is going to focus
on, what you think is a key part of Eastercons, and what you're going to do to make that happen.
Oh yeah, and I think also if you're planning to ditch any massively significant bits of
Eastercon tradition, it's possibly good to mention those in the bid session. Like if you're not
planning to have any guests of honor, you should probably tell us. If you're planning to do it in
a campsite or butlins, then you should tell us. And also you should be short and sweet because
it's Sunday morning and I'm probably hungover. That, yep, that's all very fair, brilliant stuff.
You've got to disagree with me now, John, are the podcast no fun?
Oh, I'm going to let Alison go next. Children's agree with me.
I think Liz has covered most of the main things, but under who's running it and why,
you do kind of want to get a sense A that they're covering the set of work that has to be done.
There's something about financial probity because there's some assumptions about
Eastercons being not for profit and the committee not benefiting from it. And it's all very assumed,
but I think, and we tend not to say it out loud, but one of the things we do is we look at the
people who were running it. And if it wasn't a group of people that were already in that network,
I think people probably will be saying, well, why you, what is it that you're hoping to get out of it?
Something about Eastercon philosophy, maybe, but I don't know if people really care. People just
want to know that it's going to be in a nice place and they'll have a good weekend. If you're
going to be not on the UK mainland, I think you probably need to say quite a lot about why.
So one of the things that they say in the Worldcon vanishing position is for what dates are you bidding?
And generally speaking, for Eastercons, we're bidding for Easter, but it's not absolutely guaranteed
that will always be the case. There's a reason why Worldcon moved off the Labor Day weekend,
and those reasons also pertain to Eastercons, to some extent, which is if you could only get the
site you want some other time, people might do that. If you actually go and look at the
vanishing position, it's all full of things like what's the nearest airport to your city and what
the airfare is like? And I'm like, oh, for God's sake, can people not use Google?
I think that probably is covered a little bit under Liz's Eastercon traditions,
proviso. But yes, no, I think that is a good point. The one thing that stands out to me that neither
of you have mentioned is price. I like knowing what the price of the membership is and what the price
of the hotel is. One of the reasons why, although I know going back to your point about the vanishing
position and flights to nearby cities, I think having an idea of how much it costs to get to
the location is good, which kind of folds into your point about offshore Eastercons as well.
I haven't not been to any of these concerts they started, so I've never been put off by the price,
but I think it's something I look for. It does, but if we were to decide to hold Eastercon and say
Bristol or Aberdeen, I think there would be quite a lot of criticism about the cost of getting there
from London and I think there probably shouldn't be, you know, or getting to Bristol from Glasgow
or whatever. So, you know, I think it's right that the Eastercons should move around the UK.
You could obviously say, "Oh, it's cheapest for everyone on average if we always hold it
in the Hilton Metropolitan Birmingham, plus it has an excellent garden suitable for football matches."
I think you've got a counterbalance, considerations of cost with the considerations of access,
and I for one would love to see, for instance, an Eastercon held in Cardiff or in Northern Ireland,
and although they would be more difficult to get to than some other venues, I still think
that would be fabulous. So, yeah. So, there's a thing about beer as well, which is that if you
do not say anything about beer, people will ask you if you're going to have real ale, and
we have just discovered that at least one recent Eastercon covered its entire food and drink spend
requirement on taking over the real ale bar over the weekend. So, so it's not marginal. We start
to get people going, "Oh, the beer thing is marginal," but it probably isn't marginal. There's a real
question of whether if you don't have beer at your convention, you could possibly satisfy the
square the circle of making the convention work. And there's a load of questions that people will
ask you whether you say anything about them or not. You should probably say something about
children and how you're going to deal with them, because although there are not that many children
at Eastercon, it's really important that people with kids can still get involved in Eastercon and
are not expected to just leave their children with their other partner for the weekend and go
off and have a jolly. I would also say that at the moment, I would probably like to know what your
plans are for virtual and/or hybrid conventions. Should you need to go for that? But also to say
that there's another thing I judge off your Eastercon bid presentation, which is not necessarily
the content of your presentation, but can your bid team put together a good presentation and
present it and, you know, have slides and do it all in the right order? Because if you can't manage
to put together a five-minute presentation to tell me what you're going to do in two years time,
then I have a lot less faith that you will actually put together a good convention.
I guess fair. Yeah, I remember when the Hugo Loser's party was being run by the subsequent
WELKON, somebody explaining to me that it was the first major event that the winning team
organised, and it was used as a sort of prior warning by the Shadowy Cabal that actually runs
the WELKON, because if the sitting WELKON couldn't manage to run a party, then you knew there was
a major problem. And the bid presentations like that, you want to see that they could do a bid
presentation. One thing that Liz touched on that we haven't talked much about is obviously
access policies are important, but discussions of the accessibility of the venue. And Liz, you
did say like, where is it? But obviously, I just want to highlight that that doesn't just cover
the geography, but it covers kind of whereabouts in the city, is it, and how easy is it to
navigate? Is it two minutes walk from the station, or is it all sedatively on a motorway junction
miles away from anywhere? Liz, do you want to pick first? So my pick is Deep Breath,
the 50-year mission, Colon, the next 25 years Colon, from the next generation to JJ Abrams,
Colon, the complete uncensored and unauthorized oral history of Star Trek. It's a very long title
for a very long book, but it is exactly what it says on the tin, basically. It goes from Star Trek
next generation to the JJ Abrams films, and it's all done by essentially accepting interviews of
nearly all the major players in the entire franchise. So it's basically a deeply nerdy book for people
who like Star Trek. If you want to hear a lot from the writers, and very candidly about what
they thought went well, what they thought went badly, they interviewed a lot of people who
spent a short time working on Star Trek, and then left the interview everyone through Deep Space
Nine, an enterprise and Voyager who were quite candid about what worked, what didn't, what kind
of the network wanted them to be, and also at the end of enterprise, how they really thought they
were finding their feet, just as they got cancelled, and then it goes on, and you know,
just to say about the JJ Abrams films would also talk about kind of all the different attempts to
reboot it in the intervening time, like different film proposals and so on. So yeah, it's a very
long book, I haven't read it in one city, but I sort of been dipping in and out of different
chapters and reading about the different sections, and yeah, it's made me want to go and watch
some Star Trek again. Excellent stuff. I am sort of in the middle of a original series watch, but because
my television platform of choice merges all of the videos I'm currently watching from every service,
except Netflix, so I forget the things I'm watching on Netflix, and then I forget to go back to them.
So I've been about halfway through series three for about a year, so yeah, I need to go back.
I particularly like the episode where Kirk punches a thing and gets it sorted, and I dislike the
episode where Kirk is a bit sexist, but the lady wanted it really.
I bought the whole of the original series planning to do a rewatch, and I managed about three and
half episodes. I've been a bit glib there, but I do find the approach to gender of some of the
episodes is, oh my goodness, it's hard. This was a very progressive show of its time. Like the one
where Kirk is accused of sexual impropriety, and the solution is, oh yeah, but he wouldn't do that,
because we know him, and he's good. And it's like, oh no, that's not how it works. And I get that
it was a different time, but blimey. It's just hard to watch. There's some interesting and,
you know, occasionally, hair-raising stuff about this in the 50th mission. I should say there is a
previous book in this series. One of the reasons it's got so many colons is there is a first 25
years book, which is all about the original series and the original films. But yes, there are some
stories of the costuming of who can we bring into this show to bring us in some sexy babes.
And there is a constant thread going through of how they complain about they can never find any
stunningly attractive women who can act, because stunningly attractive women are never able to act
or something. And it's very strange. So you can see some of the behind-the-scenes stuff that
was still going on, and I guess next generation is going back to the mid-80s when they were starting
up. But you can see some of that. But it's also quite interesting to hear about when they got
Voyager and they were determined to have a female captain and they cast the original,
an original actress who they realised very quickly was completely wrong for it, and she realised as
well. This was completely not what she wanted to do, and then they just kind of flipped it entirely
and put a new actress in there. Hmm, interesting. I feel that we need phonetic punctuation for
titles like that. We did have big phonetic punctuation. Liz said colon a lot. Yeah, but like, colon.
*gibberish* Sorry, can't do it. *bop* *bop* Sorry, did I burst any ones and he had drops?
*laughs* I don't know where to go with this. You just made some funny beeping.
Oh, can I, can I give you one quote that I highlighted from this book?
Yep, yep, yep, go for it.
Uh, it's about, you know, enterprise being constantly says, in England they loved enterprise. I've
done a couple of conventions there, and people are like, 'why did you cancel it?' They were
baffled because they were successful and popular there. What's here? English people
write in and tell me if this was you telling one of the enterprise producers how much England
loved enterprise because I do not remember that being the case. If you go to a convention that's
about a thing in Britain and you're a representative of that thing, then all the people who like that
thing will come up to you and tell you how marvellous that thing was, and all the people who didn't
like that thing will sit in the bar drinking pints or not come to the convention.
That's how Britain works. I guess, I suspect in America people who didn't like your show and
more likely to tell you so at a convention, but that's not going to happen here.
That could be true. Interesting point. I also at some point need to finish next generation
because I've been about two episodes into series seven for ages.
I am in television bankruptcy. However, I have watched one more episode of the Expanse since we
last spoke. So obviously, the reason we do picks is to tell you all about the great things in the
community that are happening and encourage you to go and experience them. So naturally,
in line with this, I'm picking a decade old out-of-print card game called Android Netrunner.
Android Netrunner was a game published by Fantasyfly Games between about 2012 and about 2017.
It was designed by a man called Lucas Litzinger and it's based on a Richard Garfield design
that was originally published by Wizards of the Coast in the mid-90s, just after Magic the Gathering.
For those who don't know, Richard Garfield designed Magic the Gathering and so is well
regarded in the space of card games as a result. Netrunner is a particularly interesting game because
firstly, it's set in a cyberpunk dystopia, which I prefer to a fantasy setting because I prefer
lasers and robots to magic. And because it's asymmetrical, so you are two players and one player
plays the corporation and you are protecting your servers with ICE, which is intrusion countermeasure
electronics from the Neuromancer terminology, and the other player is running on your servers,
trying to get past your ICE and into the servers. The twist is the corporation installs all of
their cards face down, so the runner doesn't know what they are until they encounter the card.
And so there's a real bluffing element to the game, which is unusual in that kind of competitive
card game. Not many games have that bluffing angle. And so it was really good. It was good as well
because it wasn't collectible. It was, well, they call it a living card game, which is a thing
fantasyfly I've come up with. And basically, if you buy a pack of cards, you know what's in the
pack of cards. And for those of you who are not super into games, you might be like, surely that
makes sense, but you would be surprised how many popular card games do not follow this simple model.
So this would be like when you buy a pack of football cards, you could like choose which
teams cards you wanted, or you could buy the cards that you didn't have yet for your
Phonini album rather than spending many hours on the playground trying to swap.
Exactly. Where would be the fun in that?
Ah, well, the fun is in the game rather than the collecting.
Pretty sure the fun is in the loot boxes. Right. So, um, Netrunner was fantastic,
and I loved it for a long time and I've still got a bunch of cards, not all of them. I sold a lot,
but I still got enough cards. I've made some decks. I'm very happy with playing it recently
in Casa, Cox and Sheriff, and it has been great. The man who designed the modernized version of Netrunner
went on to make a game called Star Wars Destiny. The problem is that these games went away,
and it's very sad. But then there was a game called Arkham Horror the Card Game.
And Arkham Horror the Card Game is interesting because it borrows things from the Netrunner core
design, the kind of DNA of Netrunner lives on, uh, through Arkham. But me and Espaa have been
playing Netrunner with some of my pickup decks, and they are enormously good fun.
I've never played another card game like it, which has that kind of bluffing element and that kind of
uncertainty if you're playing the runner of not quite knowing what's going to hit you,
when you're trying to get into the opponent's servers. And so I really do,
I really do think Netrunner was fantastic. And I'm very sad that it went away. Yes,
if you find it on eBay, it's good Android Netrunner. Highly recommend. And the artwork's amazing.
Like on the cards, the arts just so pretty. Mark's going to write, you know.
I hope so. There's a point where you got to Arkham Horror and I was like, oh no, he's just
put it around to Arkham Horror now. But if anyone's ever in my house, I have some decks and we could
play. Which house would that be? My new house or my old house, but basically the house in which
I am in. Don't go to a house I don't live in. I'm going to turn it but John's old house and
knock on the door and be like, Netrunner and the new occupants are going to be like,
actually the previous occupants of this house did also play Netrunner because that was one of
the things we chat to them about when we were looking around.
That is interesting. We were actually recording six days early, which is only like eight days
after we last recorded, as a result of which I don't really have a new and interesting genre
pick for you. However, so my pick is, an anti-productivity book called I Didn't Do the Thing Today by
Madeline Dor, which is all about how you shouldn't worry so much about fitting the things you do into
arbitrary structures of what needs to be done on a particular date, like having a pick ready
for octa thought recording, but instead you should find where the mood takes you and build your
creative and professional structures around what is exciting and speaks to you at any given time.
And there are much more important things in life than checking a box like having a pick ready for
octa thought. So it's pretty good. I've been listening to it as an audio book. It is full of quotes from
other productivity writers. So if you are a productivity junkie like I am, you will be familiar with a
lot of what is in this book, but it's very soothing. It's full of stuff that is very reassuring about
the fact that it is 4.30 in the afternoon and you have only done one of the 19 things on your
to-do list today. And in particular, you've not done any of the things that had to happen today.
Do I sound a bit worried? But I'm soothed because this book has reassured me that my creativity is
more important. Yeah, I am not sure my employers would agree that it's okay if I have today thing
on my to-do list by 4.30 because my creativity has been fulfilled. She does explain how to do
some stuff as well. Unfortunately, creative fulfilment is not the thing I require in my
employment. Just in case you are someone to whom Alison currently owns work, the address of the
author will be in the show-pounds. So, listeners, we're going to talk about a book that we all read.
Yeah, we've all read it really recently and it is a book that you can nominate for The Hugo.
If you like, this basically never happens.
Oct-thought book club. Oct-thought book club though. If it was Oct-thought book club,
really we would need red wine and also cackling. We've got one out of two.
So this is also a book that if you read it, you will be reading a work by an Easter Kong guest of
honor because it is The Jasmine Throne by Tasha Sieri. So I always or I always used to try
to read a book or two by each of the Easter Kong guests of honor and that did sort of
fall off my priorities list at some point and I'm sort of trying to get back into the habits.
I think it is a good habit to have. So Liz read it the least recently of the three of us,
by which I mean that Liz read it on time. She had us as a pick two weeks ago, didn't she?
No, I specifically did not have it as my pick because I was going to have it as my pick and
then you all said, "Oh but we're going to read this. You can't have it as a pick." So I had another
thing as my pick which you briefly complained about because you were also going to read that
but then we decided getting us organized enough to read one book all at the same time is really
as far as we can go. So yes. It's fair. So I quite liked it. Do you want to tell us a bit about the
book John? So the Jasmine Throne by Touch the Siri is a book about a country which is a colony
of another larger country and it's about two or three characters in that country and their
interactions with its colonial relationship with its parent country. At the start of the book,
a princess is imprisoned atop a hill but in a more interesting way than it that made it sound
and we follow her and we follow someone who is from the country in question and we follow a
couple of other characters who are kind of either related to the princess or to the second character
and kind of explore the tensions in that country and explore what it is to be in power
and also what it is to meaningfully reject power and kind of the difference between
violent revolution with no goal versus quiet sedition with an actual end game in mind.
And I really liked it. I thought it was good. I thought it was very interesting the way that the
book handles many of its themes. I very much liked the two central characters. I really liked the
world and it made me very angry in a good way about colonialism and about how countries come to
subjugate other countries. That I think is my kind of, that's the things I took away from it.
What did you take away from it Liz? Yeah I would agree. I mean what I think is it's a really
impressive and interesting world into which you put some fascinating characters. I do really like
the idea. I think you get a lot of fantasy series where you've got sort of an alliance of city
states or an emperor who has conquered another country and so to really focus this on the kind
of conquered country and about the kind of colonization of that country. And it's very soon after it has
been colonized as well so kind of it's a really recent wound for everyone, everyone who lives
who lives there. I thought was interesting and there were some parts I really liked about it because
you get you know these three temple children who were brought up together in Iherania the
colonized country and they really between them show kind of three different ways in which
you know you can try for revolution and for regaining your country and I think it kind of does a
great job of discussing kind of the different aspects of how they go about this and kind of
what their vision is for the future of their country. And yeah there's a great thing where they
say that the, you know, the project, the conquering country, they say it has reshaped us, it is not
a conversation but a rewriting. So I really loved about how it you know rewrites their history from
the you know perspective of the oppressors. And yeah it is the first of a trilogy so you know it does
kind of you know end a little bit abruptly to give you a hook for the next book but I probably will,
I definitely will pick up the next book and read it and hopefully the third one as well. I'll let
Alison get a word in anyways. Yeah I quite liked it. I am looking forward to the author saying a bit
more about it. I probably didn't like it quite as much as either of you two did. As Liz says it's
the first book of the trilogy and I feel like if they had cut out two or three hundred pages of
wafting around in the middle of it it could just have been a standalone book in which you put all
the rest of the plot in as well. I understand that I am not the target market for fat fantasy novels,
this is a fat fantasy novel. Every paragraph is quite nice though it's very lush to read,
it's very well written, the characterisation is good, all of the major female characters were
interesting and quite complicated and I quite like that. It has a really badly drawn one note
villain which is not good and is given this absolutely no explanation for why this person is the way
they are and it just kind of sits there like a kind of clocked in the middle of the story. I
think it might be intended as a metaphor for Empire but it's not a very good one. A lot of the
other stuff about Empire and colonialism is pretty good. It uses Indian culture as the basis for
its world building and that is very much underused as a way to build fantasy which is good. It then
does it in a way that I felt still felt like it was hitting the beets of a western fantasy novel
though I didn't feel oh yes I'm reading something that is about an alien culture as much as I
would have liked to. That's alien in the sense of alien to me and I thought that was a little bit
of a shame that she maybe missed a trick there and the other trick I think she really missed is
right at the beginning she kind of introduces the rot as this disease of of breading plantification
that kills people and she doesn't really she spends most of the novel not going anywhere with it
and this is a 520 page close typed novel there's a lot of words here something like 160 000
and you kind of get at the end of the book oh wait that's one of the plot points I'm saving back
for next time and I was like well that was that that doesn't leave me feeling very good about this
book I would I feel like the the notion that oh I can make more money if I write if I write my
stories longer I really struggle with you know I don't I just I think that's honestly I think it's
utterb I know we have this argument all the time but I don't think it's fair to say that the only
reason to write a trilogy is because you want to make money right okay so this is the thing that
really interested me the thing that really interested me about the novel was the way in which the
colonialism or the colonization of the country is directly linked to the idea that the magic
consists of the country asserting it of the earth and the water and the fabric of the country as
well as the people reasserting its nature and rising up to fight back against colonization and
I feel that the that this was introduced and then artificially left to one side so that the
story about the people could be expanded for the entire novel but the story tells like the story
is about the initial stages of that rise up right I'm not sure I think you could have I'm not sure
you could have taken two thirds of this novel out and had it land the emotional punches it lands
in the places it lands them and maybe I'm wrong but I mean at least I think you'd need to do it as a
duology okay because I just don't think I just don't see how there's enough space like I thought
there was some bits in the middle where I thought oh you might be able to cut a little bit of this
out but I'm talking like you could have made it 140 instead of 160 000 words I'm not saying you
could have made it 50 000 I don't think this could have been a novella oh no no but you would have
had to have been a novella for the subsequent two installments to fit in a single novel yeah I mean
you know I may be overstating this I did think that I did think it told its story in a in a very
gradually paced way and I think that's fine and I think that's fine for people I mean you know
I'm probably being a bit mean here I did quite like it I think people who are looking for
worlds in which they could kind of fall into and spend a long time will find a lot to like yeah I
think it feels deliberate that the kind of pacing of the stories of the characters and how you know
the the reveal of what is going on with kind of the land of the earth and the waters you know they
are going together so I think you could only speed up kind of the telling of the story as a whole
rather maybe refocus on one but the other I mean I would also say yeah it's a little bit long I
think you could probably have it be a hundred pages shorter possibly not by having fewer things
happen but maybe just by you know there's a lot of kind of paragraphs which have a lot of space
to breathe and you could probably tighten those up a bit and also I think like near the start of
the book you have Princess Malini who comes to be imprisoned and meets the maid servant who is
also part of this revolution and it kind of takes quite a long time to get them kind of into the
same space which is really one of the driving catalysts of the book because what you know the
relationship between them which turns into a romance is one of the kind of the main I think
things driving the book because you know the agreements they make with one another and you know
how they're going to help each other and get their mutual goals like I think you could put them
together a bit faster and it would maybe you know Malini feels like she has no agency for kind of
quite a big chunk of the first part of it so you get things moving a bit faster there is how I felt
and then near the end of the book there seems to be quite a lot of basically wandering around in the
forest I found the last two-thirds of the book very well paced for me I thought it really went
along and I really enjoyed that I found the first third a little bit slow and I think that is because
of what Liz just said I think if you had had Malini in pre-air I think it's a classic thing of the
first maybe 50 pages are set up for the book but we could have had that set up implied I don't
think you necessarily need to start right at the start of where all the pieces start moving
you can start at the point where the pieces have got to the point where the story is starting
and so and so there are a few bits right at the beginning where I think oh you could probably
make that a lot quicker and especially there's one character in the book that about a third of
the way through I said to Alison and is like oh I'm not really sure what rail was doing in this book
and they said aha you will find out what he is doing in this book in the next two-thirds of the
book and they were right but I think you probably could have spent less time with him I think
those bits in the first third drag I'm also curious I quite liked the baddie but I don't know
because I liked how personal I liked how personal her relationship with him was but also how
completely her brother couldn't see why I liked that dynamic of he had never I like the other
brother a lot the other brothers are really interesting character the other brother is a
character that you actually meet all of the time in real life and I like that you know I like to
think that people in books exemplify the kind of complicated characters that humans that I know are
and they often don't and for the most of the people they do they're just complicated people
living their complicated lives and doing what they think is best and I like that novels should
have that fantasy doffles often don't have as much of that as they need so that was good yeah they
feel like it feels like none of them fit into particularly kind of stereotypical fancy
archetypes they'll have you know some other things of interest about them and I like the kind of
contrast of the you know familial relationships between Princess Malini and her two brothers and
between Priya and the other temple children essentially have the same familial relationship
and upbringing but in a very you know in the very different environment of um
herania I was really interested in the relationship between Bumika and Vikram I really liked the way
that's depicted and the way that you find out more about Mika through the book and it becomes clear
that certain things are true but also the way that Vikram is much more complicated than he could
have been I think he's not super deep but like I found it interesting enough to kind of get my
teeth into and I take I take the point the chandere is quite he is he is a bad man bad quite like
that and I wonder whether that'll get expanded on in book two because in this book he's kind of the
he's kind of the boundary condition he's not really the main character he's a thing that everyone
else is reacting to and I and I think as we encounter him more as a character it might be that he has
some depth or might just be that he's a bad bad man in which case I'll probably also enjoy that
I think I will probably nominate it for a Hugo award unless I read suddenly a lot of extremely
good books in the next four weeks which what was the one you said you were going to nominate Liz?
The Unraveling by Benjamin Rosenbaum. So that is after I'm just about to read a
desolation called Peace which I strongly suspect I will nominate because I love
D'Merecle Empire the Unraveling is the next on my list after that. Yeah next up for me is
Far From the Light of Heaven by Tardotomson which is you know which is right about to get started
now and then the next one after that for me is the Catherine Addison Witness for the Dead.
Oh yes the follow-up or not quite a follow-up but same world as the Goblin Emperor which I did
really love. And that was the Octa Thor podcast and it's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
You've not even got your video on this.
Alright let's I will turn my video on briefly and wave.
It's so pretty you've got like crazy geometric like Moorish almost thing behind you.
Yes there's like a sort of mosaic thing on the wall. No nice I like it.
Is your are you holiday? I don't know why I asked Liz if she's holidaying so well.
Oh look at the bath. The bath's like a buddy. Listeners you can't see it but the bath is like an
altar to baths. Like imagine that there was a church of baths and then imagine what the altar
would look like and that is what Liz baths look like.
Because basically if you've got a bathtub like this and I don't live in a house with a bathtub
I'm going to take as many baths as possible. That makes a lot of sense.
Yeah I think we may have gone even further off topic and John should cut this down to just a
minute and a half. The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod
and CompeTech.com used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.