So John, you've just devalued the value of John Cox's nomination in my eyes.
How can I take them seriously now?
Also, are you eating a mini-quass hunt?
Yes!
You may need to cut that bit too to the chewing noises.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 85th episode of OctaThorp, a podcast for Science Fiction
and Science Fiction fandom, which is coming to you on the 8th of June 2023.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And we are in the summer of fun!
Summer of fun!
I guess it will be June by the time this is out, which counts as summer.
The summer has already begun, Liz.
Yeah, I mean, summer of fun is the period where everyone is having fun and scheduling
becomes impossible, right?
Yes, the summer of fun started on the 25th of May 2023.
And you can tell where the surf music.
Because I am in a covered garden outside of barn, in the bits of whales, where I've managed to find some wi-fi.
I am in Glasgow, in the Crown Plaza, attending Satellite 8, a convention.
And Liz is in Liz's house and is not such a coffee festival.
So, sorry Liz.
Correct.
What do you do?
What's a coffee festival like then?
Well, I don't know, I'm not there.
But I believe it would have lots of stalls from different coffee shops and coffee roasters
and lots of coffee to buy and I could get super caffeinated.
Because I understand what a beer festival is like, but I feel like I could not do what I do
at a beer festival, at a coffee festival.
Yeah, you can't do that unless you can drink infinite amounts of coffee,
but you can try a few different coffees and there are more opportunities to say,
buy nice beans and take them home to make your own coffee than at a beer festival,
where you might be able to buy like a growlerful, but it's not going to be good forever.
It's okay, there will be more coffee.
Coffee will continue.
So we have some letters of comments.
So we haven't done letters of comments since EasterCon, or sorry, since we did our
EasterCon Roundup episode.
Tharra Mendelssohn writes in with a photograph of the International Centre
of Telford, which reads, "Wales Comic Con Telford Takeover 13th to 14th May."
So, yay, Wales.
Sandra Bond writes in to say, "So much from my intention to write you a lock on your
fan fun discussion in the previous one."
Sandra, there's never, there's never not a time where we wouldn't love to get a lock from you.
I did say that if you wrote us a lock in the next 48 hours after you made that comment,
it would get into this episode. Another time, Sandra.
You can write locks on episodes as old as you like.
There's no statute of lock limitations.
Yeah, they don't even have to be very closely related to the episode.
It can be very tangential.
Just write to us, guys.
We're very lonely and we like to hear from you.
We have some emails.
We have a letter of comment from Chris Garcia.
Another excellent episode, entirely focused like a laser with patents,
with quite in particular expectations.
Thank you very much, Chris.
And contributes some recommendations for things to nominate for Hugo's.
But the nomination deadline has been gone.
So, we're not going to read the about Chris.
Also, if you want to know what Chris thinks, you should not know if Hugo's.
I suspect that there is an issue of the drink tank you could read that would have a lot of detail.
So, I encourage you all to go and read the drink tank.
All of it.
If you start now, you might have finished by the next episode dropping.
Although, maybe not.
Alex Holdren wrote in and Dave Mansfield wrote in.
Now, Dave wrote in in the form of a link to an Instagram reel,
which I am reliably informed by Liz's what happened,
because from my perspective, he wrote a DM with no attachment that made
absolutely no sense.
And that is because apparently I have to check my Instagram DMs every day
in order for reels to still be there when I check them.
So, listeners, if you send me a message in a medium that requires me to check it on the same day,
you may find that that doesn't work.
Because I am an enigma.
I am in the night.
Also, I'm very disorganized and sometimes quite busy.
So, yes.
Sorry, Dave.
Did not see the thing you posted, which Liz says,
"Was you doing the astral pole?"
And that does sound great.
And I wish I had seen it.
Because I mean, I assume it was real, but now I'm wondering,
did Dave really send me a reel or did I just hallucinate Dave
doing the astral pole?
It was very impressive astral pole by I hallucinated, though.
I regularly do that.
I got an Instagram DM from Dave,
but when we tell this to Alison, Alison was like,
"Hang on, do we have Instagram now?"
Which tells you how reliably Instagram DMs get through to Alison.
But yes.
No, he's then a DM with astral pole challenge,
laughing face, which I assume he had listened to our episode
and just decided that Instagram was the medium
with which he would comment on it.
And I was a bit confused, but I was like, "Oh, that's nice."
But no, apparently now that I know there was a video there,
that I now just can't see, it makes way more sense.
Yeah.
No, I check Instagram once a week and I don't normally bother to check my messages
because they're all gentlemen who tell me the time lovely
and would like to get to know me better.
And I'm not interested in any of them.
So, sorry, sorry, Dave.
Mine is mostly scantily clad ladies with a lot of numbers
after their names being like, "You could get into crypto."
And I'm like, "No, thanks."
And that is segmenting marketing.
I don't get any of these.
What the fuck have you done to your Instagram saying, guys?
Because I'm not getting all this kind of shit.
I don't get many spam DMs.
Like, I would say I probably get one a month,
but they are all of the DMs I go on Instagram.
So like, even though the quantity is not high,
the ratio is very bad of content to nonsense.
Fair enough.
All right, on to Alex's.
Alex sent us an email.
A traditional form of DM.
About a YouTube video.
Yes, Alex said he put an email of him doing self doing the astral poll on YouTube 17 years ago,
but has now unlisted it and very harshly didn't send us the link.
So you'll have to imagine a very young Alex Holden doing the astral poll.
I think that will be excellent content for your Instagram channel all about concertino's Alex.
Can you use the concertino's to do the astral poll?
Probably not very good idea with your precious concertino, is it?
I mean, I do check Instagram once a week and it's nearly always,
nearly entirely so that I can check out Alex's hot pictures of concertinos.
That is an entirely different sort of spam DM, I listen.
So if you're looking for hot pictures of concertinos, I recommend Alex's Instagram.
But unfortunately not Alex doing the astral poll.
We got letter from Chris Garcia, where he, I think, is on the John end of the COVID spectrum.
He writes, "I find it odd that España is the calm, rational voice of reason.
I don't know this world anymore.
And Chris, she would say the same thing about you.
But he does say he doesn't like going to green rooms because it might be his improv training.
And I'm like, I feel like you can improv in a green room, Chris.
We did get quite a lot of locks saying that I was totally wrong about COVID.
So, you know, I might have been.
We got a variety of locks, which we're not going to go too much into detail because
I feel like having seen this unfold of various forums, it could go on infinitely.
That idea fills me with dread.
Yeah, I don't think, we've had a lot of people's thoughts,
but I'm not sure we're adding a lot of content to the debate at this point.
I do think I want to pull out one thing from one of our letters of comment,
and not because I encourage Abigail to put this in an email.
We got a letter from Abigail Nussbaum and specifically she was saying that
Hugo Award-winning fan writer Abigail Nussbaum.
Indeed, Hugo Award-winning fan writer Abigail Nussbaum who points out that the conversation
used to come mask policy ended up kind of abandoning panelists on panels a bit,
and that she really did not like the option of allowing panelists to ask people in the room
to mask, which I think we covered, but I think it's worth noting, you do not want to
have your panelists a con feeling like you have kind of abandoned them for COVID.
So, I think that is something kind of future.
Future policies need to take into account, which is like your panelists are showing up
and basically doing a job for the con, and generally, if they can't do the job for the con
without feeling like they might get COVID, then they're not going to want to do that job for the con.
So, it is always a balancing act, but I kind of put a bit more weight on the feelings of the panelists
than kind of the feelings of the audience watching them in this field.
I'd agree with that. I mean, the panelists were well spaced from the audience in large,
well-ventilated rooms, but we were expecting, I think, people to mask more than they did,
as we said last time. Abigail also said that she really enjoyed conversation.
I thought it was one of the best conventions she's attended in every other respect apart from this,
so, you know, that was kind of nice, but still, sorry, Abigail.
I'm going to raise one thing, which is we keep saying large, well-ventilated rooms, but
I think, as we said before, we don't really have a standard for ventilation or any good way of
doing this. So, I think at some point, fans are going to have to work out what we mean by
large, well-ventilated rooms, and does that mean going into those rooms with the CO2 monitor at
some point or asking for specs on the ventilation of the venue, which hopefully venues are going to
get better at providing, because, you know, we could say large, well-ventilated rooms,
but I don't think we actually know how much the air is recirculating in there, and so on.
I like big rooms, and I cannot lie. You other brothers can't deny.
We also heard from, I can't remember if he's written in before, Christopher Garcia,
who wrote in saying that he liked the special episode, and a face like Glass is the kind he'd
loved to read, but never seems to get around to, instead it bumps up against me on audible.
I quite like what he says about, it sounds like a book that pumps ideas into the air,
and then he spends a week thinking about them, and then kind of they infect his brain, and I know
what he means. Some of the stuff in a face like Glass, when I was really listening to the conversation
when I was editing it, I was struck by like how much it had made me start thinking about like
the power of people to inform the conversation, and how biased the media is towards the powerful,
and those are all thoughts that are still bouncing around in my head.
And so I do think there is something there with the infectiousness of the ideas in that book,
that I don't know whether we touched on last episode, because we record that quite quickly
after finishing the book, I think. And like that was, oh god, when was that? Like a while ago,
listeners, I don't want to take you too far beyond the curtain, but suffice to say, it was like
months, and those ideas have been bouncing around in my little cranium for a while since, so
yeah, no, I think he's got a point there. Oh, and the mastodons, we got two.
Tammy Goxon wrote in to say that it was an excellent octop, thank you.
Zambia programming software came out of Erisia, and they had a registration system that was called
Congo, as in Congo, and then Zambia was the system they made to fit into it in a sort of,
you can see how that ended up happening, but yeah. On the naming of things.
And so yep, no, that is that is fan history we were unaware of. Thank you very much, Tammy.
I still think Ariadne is good, and then you could rename the registration system like
after a different spider, like Boris or Charlotte. We got a letter from Randy Smith, and I'm not sure
Randy's written to us before saying that when he stood for TAF, around for TAF in 2015,
he chose nominators based on who do I think I can get? That is a model.
No, I think that is very reasonable. I read a new fan scene by a new person. Martin Petto.
Martin Petto, just the other day. Yes, so Martin has done a fan scene called Moon
Moot, and it has the return of fanboys and Alison has spoiled my pick, but oh, sorry, shit.
No, that's all right. I've said to have a letter of comment. Andrew Hogg has
redone some fanboys books, books, comics, which is very good. And no, it's very well designed.
It is its landscape. Yes, it's designed for reading on iPads.
Oh, it is. Yeah, I approve. He says a podcast is a fan scene made of talking,
and Nick Fairey would have issues with that, Martin. But anyway, yes, so there are new fanzies,
and one way, one of the best ways of getting your fan scene into in front of the eyeballs of
people who read the old fanzies is to send it to Bill Burns to push it on efansy.com,
which is what Martin Petto did. I don't think I know Martin. He made us some lovely slides for
Eastercon. Yeah, no, I mean, part of the fan scene is about your lovely slides. The last thing I was
going to say on nominators is so, guys, if you're thinking of running for a fanfunk, get in touch.
We will, we may not nominate you, but we will put you in the direction of likely nominators.
So we heard from Raj. Raj agrees with Alison. He's got his first con since the before times
coming up soon, which is the con I am at now listeners. And he says he thinks he's coming down
more on the Alison side of the argument than mine. Fair enough Raj. We are now nemesis.
And he says, I raise a good point. I know with friends again about getting boosters from boots,
which yes, if politicians keep comparing COVID to flu, they need to explain why we can't get the
same projections as the former as we can against the latter. There's a very nice point Raj.
I liked that sentence a lot. Yeah, 100%. Yeah. And also they love the private sector. Why can't
the private sector sell us a load of COVID jobs? In the show notes for the last episode,
or no, sorry, in the show notes for the episode before last, we said there are no picks this
episode. What have you been reading? And Raj was the only person who wrote in. So Raj is going to get
to have his pick on October. He has picked the very secret society of irregular witches by
Sangumandana, which is a cozy fantasy that melted his heart. So, I might look that up. It sounds
interesting. It's a great title. Yeah, I'm going to say I've not heard of that. It sounds good.
Thank you, Raj. Soon we will be obsolete because soon the podcast will just be locks.
I say soon. This episode listeners, this episode DC wrote in saying that they enjoyed the last
podcast and they agreed that conversation did the hybrid convention thing. Excellently
is also reminding themselves to read more Francis Harding. She's so good. And she also seems to be
lovely person. Agreed on both fronts DC. Oh, that was a lot of locks. Yeah.
This morning, while I was at breakfast at the convention, I got an email from Chicon 8
announcing that they are doing partial membership reimbursements. So, if you volunteered or were
on programme for Chicon 8, keep an eye on your email. They say that you will, they are offering
a standard reimbursement amount to all qualifying staff, volunteers and programme participants as
follows. And it's between 60 and 80 dollars, depending on how many people choose to take up this offer
for adult attending. And if you have virtual attending, it's 40. So, hurrah.
I think it's very nice of them to include the virtual attending members as well. I mean,
obviously it's not really been a decision previous cons for to make, but it's nice to reimburse them,
especially as you know, lots of volunteers and programme participants would be doing a lot of
work virtually. Mm hmm. Oh, it's good. It's good stuff. Yes. Tell us about the convention.
I am at satellite eight, which is the eighth convention in the satellite convention series,
which are held at the Crown Plaza Hotel in Glasgow. Guests who honour Christopher Priest and fan
guest of honour, Michelle Cuddles, Dreeton Harald. Chris Priest is being very Chris Priest on all
of the programme I have seen him on, seen him on, which is very good. Meg McDonald managed to persuade
him to give a reading at the start of his guest of honour interview, which he introduced by saying
I hate doing readings. And then Meg was like, but I did ask very nicely. And then he stopped. And
then he said, I'm going to stop there because I hate doing it. And I'm like, fair enough.
It was good. But yeah, lovely little, lovely little relaxer con. How many, how many people
are there, would you say? Mm hmm, 100 maybe. Also, it's tiny. Yeah, it's nice. Oh, and there's
a scavenger hunt and more conventions should have scavenger hunts. If you're running a scavenger hunt,
and you haven't got a convention, no, wrong. If you are running a convention, you haven't got a scavenger
hunt, fix that now, now. So basically they've hidden, it's not really, I guess it's not really
a scavenger hunt. So treasure hunt. They've hidden pictures of astronauts around the hotel and you've
got to find 42 astronauts. And there's a prize. Don't know what the prize is. Don't care. The
point is filling in the list. The prize is the satisfaction. But yes, found the last three
yesterday in between karaoke. So it was good. And yeah, so the satellite conventions are all themed
around like space exploration, or kind of, well, fastest space exploration. So they're kind of my
bag anyway. And I volunteered for ops. Oh, do you get like a walkie-dockie and a shiny vest? No.
For 100% conventions, that would be excessive, I think. You get it's a badge. I get a badge that
says ops. Oh, I get to sit behind a desk and people come in and say, can I sign up for a thing? And
I'm like, yes. Except for if they want to sign up for the cheesecake tasting, in which I'm like,
no, because it was full. I went to the cheesesteing. It was bloody brilliant.
How was the cheese? Good cheese. We were driving to the middle of Wales on Friday. And I noticed a
size saying cheese making next right. And so we stopped doing what we were doing and drove to the
place of cheese making. And they were not cheese making, but they did have a lot of their own
cheese. And they said, would you like some lunch? And I said, what sort of lunch do you have? And
they said, well, we have a cheese platter for two. And I said, that sounds very good. So there was
so much cheese. I had to bring cheese away with me. So I have, I have cheese tucked into the fridge
here, despite the fact that they're also feeding us a lot here as well. So cheese, cheese is good.
Yep. But it was cheese as I've never, cheese as I've never had before that I made it this one
dairy that just makes cheese, local cheese for local people. It's practically on their mission
statement. It's like we will make, we will make cheese and distribute it within herrifucher.
I was like, okay, that's, that's fine. That's a take. I like herrifucher. Speaking of cheese,
I just want people to know the types of the last, the cover for the last episode entirely on my
phone on the train, which I think is a first for me. I was so proud of myself. And it has cheese on
it. Imaginary cheese. Does have cheese. Good. Cheese. It's, it's kind of a relatively small
convention. There's two or three program tracks, depending on how you look at it. And there's nothing
opposite the guest of honor items, which I kind of love. At 11, there is a program item
about moving to Scotland. So, you know, it's a recruitment drive. Scotland does seem nice.
A data point, Liz. I went to a bar in Glasgow that was selling beer for £7.20 a point.
Yeah. This has been beer price roundup with Liz. We're going to need a chapter art,
Alison. Beer price roundup, right? It's very high.
Bredeemer the crown plaza. Is it a venue for Glasgow in 2024?
It is. I mean, Bredeemer will be a hotel for Glasgow in 2024.
It is both. I don't know how much of the space is being used for conventionally things.
They are. They are, in fact, using all of the spaces in this hotel for Glasgow in 2024.
I don't know exactly what they use in the fort. I don't think program have gone on the tour of the
venue to work out what is being used for what yet. So like, I don't know. I don't think areas
have been bagzied for specific uses yet. But I know I think they have the entire SECC. And I
think they have all of the space in this hotel except for maybe one of the big halls which they
have an option on but they haven't committed to yet. I believe is the case. But yes. So lots
of program space in this hotel, which is very nice. I mean, there's an Easter cons worth of
program space as long as your Easter cons quite small in the crown plaza.
Yeah. I don't know if it's had any change or updates since I last went to it in 2006. But I
mean, I know the area has because they've obviously built like the Hydro and I think some more hotels
in the car park. But I would assume the crown plaza is largely the same. They might have painted it.
Well, and also you get free stuff. I mean, free are users of term neglecting the price of the room.
But it's nice that you get like loads of light bottles of like water and a couple of
bottles of beer and a couple of cans of wine and stuff. So that's been quite cool.
Which means you can dip up to the room and like have refreshment, which is lovely.
And the breakfast is very good. It doesn't have mushrooms, but it does have haggis.
Wait, wait, wait, wait. Is it cans of wine?
Yes. Are you sure that's not a mini bar and you'll discover you'll be in charge for the
ball at the end of your stay? Rang down a nest. But yeah, no. I can't remember. The cans of wine
have a pun on them, but the cans are wearing no longer in the fridge on account of how we drank
them. So I can't trade what the pun was, but there is a pun. I mean, like it's not fantastic.
I mean, obviously the tea cakes, which are great. I don't know how much of this was here
when I was here for satellite four, because when I was here for satellite four, I was a PhD student.
And so my like ability to go out for dinner was less than it is now. But there's like a lot of
restaurants on our Gile Street, which is like a 10 minute walk away. And there's just like so
much good food and drink there. It's really nice. I mean, for the world con, I guess you're going to
need to like try and book and make sure that you have a table planned. But that is really,
really good. We went to a place called the Tap House. Was that what you had? You said
£7.20 a pint of beer? Yep. It was very good though. Local brewery. I think it's bad to say that
they also did pines for like £5.20. But that was if you wanted like a pint of Blue Moon or a pint
of like something equally generic. If you wanted good beer, it was more. But that is kind of the
that's kind of the way of nice beers unfortunately. Yes, it's like this lovely pub in Paddington that
Claire has found. It's like a pub except perfect in every respect. And the one respect to which
it might not be absolutely perfect is that everything is very expensive. Yes. Yeah, I, the only satellite
I've been to is the Eastcon. Every single time I think, oh yes, that would be good. We should do that.
We've never managed it. I don't even make it to the Eastcon because that was the year of Worldcon.
And so I was spending all my free time and money on Worldcon. Yep. I mean, I really did enjoy the
Eastcon that there was there though. It was fantastic. I'd be very also bought a house. So
that took up a lot of my time and attention rather than a thing to come.
Mm-mm. There has been some discussion about whether or not people think that the Hugo award
nominees will be highly skewed towards Chinese language works or not in the last few weeks.
We are recording this before the lists are up. We are mindful of the fact that the episode might
come out after the list has dropped. So we're going to do some discussion of that without knowing
what will happen listeners. Oh, oh, oh. Octa thought pontification corner. Basically,
we're either going to look super smart or completely opposite. So let's do it. Alison,
what is your view of this? My view of this is that there will not be any or maybe one or two,
but almost certainly no Chinese language finalists on the Hugo ballot. And my reason for thinking this
is that I don't think the vast majority of Chinese SF fans have any concept of what the
hugas are or what they do. I don't think they're very interested in it. And I don't think they are.
I'm not seeing any evidence that there's any sort of science fiction world magazine
right could have could have run a campaign to get Chinese fans to nominate. And I think if
you'd have done this, they would have done. And we would we would know it was happening.
And we have not seen anything of that kind. And so I don't think it's going to happen.
So I think I agree. And part of the reason I agree is that there have been two previous years,
the Japanese Worldcon and the Finnish Worldcon have both occurred in my time in fandom.
And obviously I suspect a lot of Japanese Finnish people do speak English. But what we didn't see in
either of those years was a lot of Japanese or Finnish language science fiction on the ballot.
And now I don't know whether that's because those countries just don't have as much science
fiction as China does because I don't have a good view of international science fiction listeners.
But I do it would it would be interesting if China is the one that proves the exception to the rule
because so far the Hugo has been remarkably resilient to being held in countries that
are not first language English. And like I don't know. Maybe that is a fool's extrapolation.
But that is just kind of where I'm at. I wonder whether the same thing will happen this time.
What do you think Liz?
Well I mean it would be quite easy for me to at this point say I think there will be at least one
Chinese language nominee on the ballot. And then since you guys have picked zero I will look smart
if there's any. So I'm going to do that. Yep. But no I think I think it's might be the year. So I think
in the year of Helsinki the thing is I think because all the Finnish fans firstly the Finnish
fans were still a minority of the people nominating you know because there were huge numbers of
British American fans who had signed up for the vote and not and they many of those voted for
Helsinki. It wasn't purely Helsinki fans whereas in Chengdu it was a lot more. The Helsinki fandom
as far as I know basically when I met at the convention was through in English and while they
were reading Finnish language and Swedish language science fiction they're also reading a lot of
English language science fiction. And also I will say for Chengdu I just don't really have any insight
into what's going on because I just cannot read any of their social media. I can't read any websites
so I see any discussion. So I think given the number of them who are fully signed up as members
thanks voting in DC and given that some of the categories have incredibly low numbers of
nominators either they just have a very low number altogether or they have a really really broad
spread like in short story where you have a lot of nominators but a massive spread. I think there
will be some categories with Chinese language nominees or Chinese people who blog or podcast
or write in the Chinese language. Possibly in things like short story where I don't think it would take
a lot of votes from China if they coalesce around a small number of stories. You know if there are
3,000 votes from Anglophone readers but we pick 300 stories and then there are 200 votes from
Chinese members who pick a small number even with the purpose you go still in effect I think that
would still get them a nominee. And then when you get down to categories like best fan artists,
fan cast, fanzine, fan rights and extent where you don't need a huge number of nominations
then I can easily see that they might might only need 100 people to get you on the ballot and that
seems completely possible. So I think there's going to be more than what. What I can't explain
really is why in 2007 there were not any Japanese language nominations but I don't know enough about
the situation then and you know how many of them had joined up to vote in site selection and things
like that to really know if it's going to be a big difference but I will stick my neck out and say
there's going to be some Chinese language nominees on the ballot. Okay so I have a question for you
Liz. Why were there none last year? Because there were lots of Chinese fans who had joined for site
selection and who could have nominated Hugo's and there were no Chinese language works on the ballot
then. So what do you think has changed in the intervening year? Is it just that the ratio of
Chinese to American fans? Because I think we know that there were more Chinese fans who had signed
up to that Worldcon than American ones for site selection but I don't have a feel for like what
the absolute ratios were. Yeah okay you do have a good point there which may undermine my theory
but my other theory would be that as far as I know when Chai Khan sent out you know email communications
and opening nominations and so on. So what I don't know is whether the fact that Chengdu will
have been emailing all its members in you know their native language will have made a difference
of their kind of awareness about being able to vote in the Hugo's being able to nominate stuff
and whether there is a set of fandom who just weren't aware that they had those you know nomination
rights for Chai Khan. I sort of agree with that but in the last five minutes I have been checking
the internet and have also checked the nomination lists for the two Worldcons that were non-anglophone
countries before John's memory which were Python in 1970 and Confiction in 1990 and none neither of
those ballots contained any non-English language works as far as I can tell. So that's true but I
think it's also like I think the landscape has totally changed since Worldcons of the 1990s
in terms of how many people nominate and I mean also the voting vote counting has changed.
And also I would say I don't know I mean I know there is like a thriving kind of you know there is
a German language SFC and there is a Dutch language SFC but how much of that is there and how much
crossover is there between fans of that and also fans who are reading in English language as well.
Like I can believe there is a big segment of fans who are signed up to Chengdu Woken who do not
habitually read any science fiction in English and I suspect a lot more of the German and Dutch
fans were reading things in English. I think all of them were maybe not absolutely all of them but
the vast majority of Dutch fans at Confiction and almost certainly also the German fans at
Hijkon of whom there weren't actually the old not many were reading English language SFCs
even in 1990 remarkably little SFC was available in Dutch translation this was one of the things
that the Dutch fans complained about a great deal. I mean there is a thing on
on file 770 just to remind me is that there was no like Chinese language ballot for Shikon and
apparently there had never been one previously so when they're in Germany in the Netherlands they
also didn't translate the Hugo ballots and I'm pretty sure they didn't do it for Helsinki either.
So I think this Worldcon maybe the first time they've actually had a bilingual ballot could be
interesting. I thought that was a Finnish one. Finn's right in. Yeah I did think there was a Finnish
language one but I don't know I mean so much that Helsinki was done in English it almost felt like
there are like Worldcons which have had the program tracks in other languages but it's always been
very much a kind of minority thing and I think most of the people you know on the
banish or Polish or Irish language tracks have also been taking part in the English language one.
Yeah Pics he wants to do their first pick. So you would think I would have a good pick at this
point but apparently I've spent the last month and a half reading non-science fiction books
watching non-science fiction television and films playing non-science fiction video games or
doing all those things but not wanting to actually recommend them. So you're going to get a podcast
recommendation which feels very cheeky so it feels like I'm piggybacking on everyone else's
podcast recommendation but essentially lots of people last year recommended the Going Rogue
podcast by Tanzi Garden who did a podcast all about the making of Rogue One which I have not listened
to yet because I feel I need to rewatch Rogue One before I listen to it so it's on my list but she
has a new podcast series currently running which is called Striking Out and it is all about the
2007-2008 writer strike through stories of the shows and films that were running at the time so
it's obviously very timely given we're in the middle of another writer strike and the first few
episodes are out and there's no about you know Quantum of Solace the the bomb film and how the
writer strike affected that and then also about the office the US one which is very interesting
because I hadn't realized it was such a big thing in the very early days of streaming and it was
really interesting to hear about kind of you know how they felt getting the the right residuals for
streaming episodes of the office was a big thing in 2008 and obviously has paved the way for what
is now a massive massive thing is an entertaining podcast Tanzi Garden is obviously very well read
well informed and fun to listen to and I recommend you give it a go I may be nominated for Hugo next
year now I'm going where we use on my list of things to listen to but I'm a bit behind on podcasts
ever since I discovered that you can watch all of Durham County cricket clubs matches on YouTube
because then I do that instead of listening to podcasts and there's bad I listen to them on my
commute and my commute is very short so that's the problem now actually the problem is that you
know during cycling when tours I try and listen to like two and a half daily podcasts so that's
the problem I mean that does sound like a very interesting podcast it is go and listen to it okay
shall I do my pick so I am going to pick another Apple TV show I do I do watch other TV that's not
Apple TV sometimes but anyway this was recommended to me by Abigail Nespam who said this is Sunk Below
Trace it is Shining Girls a eight part series based on Lauren Buke's book and starring Elizabeth
Moss as a woman who some years ago was attacked by a psychopath and survived and is now trying to
piece together what appears to be a series of quite strange serial killings I think it's not you know
I'm picking it so it is genre it sounds like it's not genre but it is it is science fiction as well
as being a thriller obviously it is all very beautiful and very put together and all of the
performances are marvelous and I have a slight hesitation about it because A) I haven't quite finished
it yet so this is another pick where I am halfway through a series and picking it but B) it does have
quite a lot of emery-drating content about dead women and stalking women which is not my favorite
topic but everything about else about the show is so good to the time colour letting it
off a bit but it's very good and almost nobody seems to have mentioned it it's sort of come up
it came up in Abigail's Hugo List but that was the first I'd heard of it and I don't think I've
seen anything else about it on any of my socials so so I feel like yeah this is this is something
that you might be interested in especially if if you like that kind of thriller science fiction
crossover genre thing which you might I was surprised you liked it because you are a
confirmed wuss which is a word you have used to describe yourself and this yeah wait till we get
to me talking about six weeks Boiler you never did six weeks oh wow okay you are more of a
but hang on okay so you your finalist but China goes way worse than six weeks I mean I've only read
the book I haven't watched the TV series yet but like um China goes it's like really creepy yes I
think the TV series is quite careful right yeah no China girls is super creepy six weeks is not
so creepy but no so China girls is is incredibly creepy we're having to watch an episode of Lower
Decks immediately after it every time so that it is not sitting in my brain at bedtime so so it is
like it's a kind of guarded pick right it's right at the edge but I think they've been careful I
think they're kind of they're trying to make prestige TV and so they've been quite careful
about the ways in which they're doing all the really scary stuff and I know that some people
have bounced off the novel for this but for this reason as well that they found it too too horrible
yeah I read Moxieland when it was it was the free book at the Eastercon in 2009 I can't remember
going back a while and I read it and then when Zu T came out I read that and then when China
goes came out I read that I am I am but I knew they were doing a TV show of it
but Aaron is like not bubbled to the top of my two watch list yet yeah same for me I
I read the book I'm aware of it I just haven't got around watching too much stuff not enough time
yes so I don't know how it finishes yet so though I have a I have a guess I have a
spoilery prediction for how it's gonna all unravel I am gonna pick so an anecdote I went to the house
of noted critic Neil Harrison and noted critic Nick Clark and noted critic Mosker the Cat
and breakfast and we watched movies we were stormy Monday with sting and a very young Sean Bean
which is very good ah and we watched the menu and we watched a random episode of the West Wing
and over breakfast the conversation turns to how we haven't picked all these worlds reviews and essays
by Neil Harrison yet on this very podcast in fat listeners you may not be aware that Neil
Harrison has written a series of reviews which is then collected into a book which is called
all these worlds reviews and essays by Neil Harrison and I have finished the book it's quite good
and this is the sort of incisive criticism which is why I do not have a collection of my criticism
written into 161 000 words of genius but no it is extremely good don't you find you want to argue
with him on every single page because that's what reviews of critics criticism do for me generally
I go oh yes well there he's so wrong about all this stuff no I think good so I think this is the
difference between good criticism and bad criticism which is I think bad criticism makes me want to
argue and I think good criticism introduces me to a viewpoint I hadn't considered before
if my first instinct is to argue I think it means you haven't properly explained your point
because it means it's not in my brain enough because I think I would have to be and I think
trying to think of a way to say this nicely I think I would have to be very sure of the
primacy of my own opinions for someone very wise to say something and then for me to be like oh
but you haven't considered it properly and argue with them okay so the very first thing I would
recommend to you for reading non-fiction with a critical eye to start to develop your critical
skills is to always be thinking who is this person and why are they lying to me you know what is
what are the holes in the things that I am reading where can I find the holes in this argument have
they been patched why have they not been patched this is like this is like what critical analysis
is it's like the number one thing you do is go right what this is a point of view so I listen I
don't know if you know this but I've been a scientist for 11 years now and I read scientific
journals so I am aware of this thank you you don't need to explain it I think that a good critic
doesn't make me think that they are deliberately including part of the discussion in order to try
to light me I think a lot of critics do do that and it drives me up the fucking wall the thing I
love about Harrison's criticism the thing I absolutely adore about it is that he actually admits the
parts where he is taking a line and he thinks about all of these books as a holistic whole and
instead of trying to sell you his opinion of them he talks about them in a way that's full enough
that he can explain what his opinion is but he can also explain why his opinion may not be your
opinion and take other people's opinions into account as he does it and he does that fantastically
and so I don't need to do that when I read Harrison's criticism because Harrison is doing it for me
and that is what makes him one of the preeminent voices of his generation I mean I have not read
this book yet there are two copies of it on myself uh waiting for me to read it I'm very
sorry getting around to reading books on paper nowadays maybe I should just buy the Kindle copy
as well then I will read it why have you got two copies one of them is is me um shuffling one to
the opposite side of the world on a planet trip later this year there is a reason for it one of
them is not technically mine this is a book mule the fur zat yeah and bookmule fur zat I mean in
some ways it'll make sense but I know I will see him in a few months time and so it made sense for
me to take one at the time get it signed and hand it over to him I thought we were going to have a
podcast where all three of us picked but I have the I have three copies of Neil's book so I outrank Liz
I have the ebook and then I have the paper book that's signed and then I have the paper book that's
unsigned you've got the rare on side copy yes well I bought it well no I didn't buy it I've
bought one copy but I have three copies because I did the type saying so I got a contributors copy
and Neil gave it to me in his house I forgot to come to sign it and then at east to come we bid on
the one that came with the free review or more more he's reading ijedi by michael staepole oh yeah
okay because we are bad bad men is that not a particularly good book
that was very good laugh john loves it very much so there's a thing here which is that my
star wars fandom is like partly the films like the original trilogy and it's partly the new
the sequel films but then the other strand so like I got into the original trilogy when I was like
a kid like like you know it must have been what a seven no nine I enjoyed the very much
and then like you fall off the wagon a little bit and then when I was a teenager I read the
rose quadrant novels by michael staepole and they kind of re-ignited my star wars fandom and ijedi
is kind of the fifth book in that sequence but kind of not it's kind of part of a series of books I
loved very very much but I can't pretend it was good I strongly suspect it's bad but Neil's gonna
read it and it's only 200 000 words long 200 000 words yeah well because it's because it's the
sequel to a four book sequence and it's also telling the same story as a trilogy of books which
are happening at the same time but it's telling it from a different perspective so it's a good
self-contained novel to get Neil to read we're basically just very bad friends
or good friends but he hasn't started reading it it's on his um table
well does he have like a succession of to be read does he have a complicated to be read system
don't know actually he like I don't know but I think yes well so they've just recently decluttered
a lot of books and like I know several of those books are books that were on the 2b read pile
and are now on the this will never get read pile which is why they're being decluttered
so I think their 2b read pile is like definitely non-trivial but I haven't asked
Neil if you're listening write in with a detailed explanation of your 2b read system
it's also a very fetching shade of green yeah no I'm sorry for setting you off John
that's right I'm sorry for being set off yeah but you did you had just gone said yeah it's good
I like it so you know well it is good Alison I do like it
well I mean I would agree with you that Neil is one of the foremost critical critics of our age
I was so you should say um on the pod because I think I mention it in the third row panel
but I should say it somewhere like out loud which is the reason that this book exists
and the reason I think a large part of the reason I don't know if it's the whole reason I don't want
to speak for Neil but I know a large part of the reason that Neil has returned to write a column
for Strange Horizons and has returned to criticism in recent months is the fact that
conversation invited him to be a guest of honor because I think he felt it was a very great I
think he felt it was like a validation of him as a critic and a validation of his place in the field
and in an external way where he he said to me one of the reasons why he decided to do a book is
that being invited to be a convention guest of honor felt a bit like a publisher expecting interest
in a collection he was like this this shows the community interested in my criticism so like
it shows that I can do this book and then I think but all this to say I don't think we would have
the book and I don't think we would have Neil doing more and more criticism now if it wasn't for
the fact he had been a guest of honor and so I will say I want to say thank you to conversation
for doing that because I think it is for the good of the field that that has happened but also I
want to say to conventions who are considering the guests of honor this is something you might
want to consider when selecting guests of honor is selecting guests who might find the honor
invigorating in a way that will mean that they return to what it is they're known for in a way
that does benefit everyone and I think that is a very that is a very powerful thing to be able to
do if you are a convention committee and it is a gift you have that not many do and so yes thank
you to conversation and perhaps who's thought for others ties neatly into my kind of philosophy on
what being an east con guest of honor should be which is that it it should be an honor that it
that we should be picking people who who we honor by by having them as as our guests and and then
the convention should work with the person so that they're what they do is is brought out in the way
in which they are celebrated as part of the conventions program and I hope we did that with
all of our guests but I think we did do it particularly well with Neil as it happens and if you are
interested in hearing Neil's desert island books then you can go and listen to the sixth episode
of the critical friends podcast which is the strange horizon's criticism podcast which has an
edited version of the interview and if you're interested in the third row fandom panel it is
now up online on youtube as part of fanak.org's fan history events because it fitted absolutely
into their um rationale so they were very pleased to have it and thank you to everyone who's on
the panel for letting it go up there so that's those are two examples of stuff from conversation
that's being preserved um there there will be more but quite a lot of it's sitting in my intro
which we sorted out at the moment so that was the art of the podcast and it's goodbye for me
it's goodbye for me it's goodbye for me
[Music]
I don't mind we could we could touch on Hugo we could do like 10 minutes on Hugo's and then do picks
do you want to do i got an idea do we all want to make a guess as to something about the Hugo's
let's make some kind of guess that can be then easily falsified before this podcast comes out
yes i'm down all right all right so let's do a little mini Hugo prediction thing i have a Hugo
prediction which is that it's not going to have any or more than one or two Chinese language
finalists in any category i'm very glad that we go john allison liz because that's also my
prediction enemies i can go first and us is going to have to predict a different thing
fucker i think we could all discuss that once that's fine i i kind of agree but i kind of
disagree it's an interesting one are we doing are we doing this now because i disagree as well or
do we want to like so are we doing it in the other kind of back editing it or do we want to
properly do this segment and have this discussion which i think will fill five minutes 10 minutes
and then we do pick and we're done so let's okay so let's discuss let's should we just discuss
whether we think there will be lots of Chinese language um nominees on the ballot and let's not
do predictions let's just discuss that question the theme music for this episode was surf shimmy
by kevin mccloud and combatec.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast
will end at the beep beep