Oh, I'm also going to say that I forgot to turn the air conditioning off.
So the first half hour of this one has some air conditioning.
Sorry.
That'll be the cold open.
Da boom tish.
Sorry.
And the reason it will be the cold open is because Liz had the air conditioning on.
I got there.
Sorry Liz.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 104th episode of Octohorpe.
This episode is coming to you on the 29th of February 2024.
I am John Coxon.
I am Alison Scott.
And I am Liz Batty.
Happy Leap Day, folks.
Oh.
So Liz, who are you proposing to today?
Huh?
Looking blankly at me.
Yeah.
It's an old thing where Leap Day and April Falls Day are the two days where women can propose
to men for marriage.
Oh, I see.
And by some old thing.
You mean something that has not really applied in my lifetime?
I think it's a custom.
According to the patriarchy, Liz.
Yeah, I'm definitely paying tons of attention to that then, aren't I?
Right then.
This episode listeners, we are going to talk about what we enjoyed from 2023 and what we
might nominate for awards in 2024, including but not limited to the Hugo Award.
So if you're wondering why we're all being completely silent on the amazing things that
have happened in science fiction and science fiction fandom in the last two weeks,
that's because they haven't happened yet.
I think we should say a little bit about the fan categories.
We probably won't say too much because I tend to think that people who know and love
these categories also know some of the things they want to vote for.
But I really wanted a chance to shout out Geri Sullivan's idea, which is a fantastic
fanzine that had an issue with December 2023.
It is eligible for the Hugo and is I think the fanzine I have enjoyed the most in the
last 12 months.
That's the only thing I had in fanzine and you sniped me, Alison.
You bastard.
You asked me to introduce the category?
That's what you get.
I did.
This is what I get.
I should never, I should never do it again.
I don't know if Idea is on the internet yet.
All of Idea is online.
The recent type of issues are at e-fanzines and the previous ones are at fanac.
I would like to say this is very good.
It has a great article by one, Alison Scott.
And it also has Sandra's report from Pemmi-Con, which will give some context to why we were
saying that the Montreal bid would need to have answers for some of the things that
happened there.
If you are unfamiliar with what happened at Pemmi-Con.
I advise you go and read Idea number 13.
I am just briefly going to shout out in this category the Ancilliary Review of Books who
publish a lot of book criticism.
And the reason I'm going to shout them out is because I assumed they were a semiprozine.
And in fact, they are unpaid and so they are a fanzine instead.
So anyone thinking of nominating that, this is a category it should go in.
Ooh.
Hm.
Intriguing.
So I would like to mention noted fan artist and noted wife.
More noted for being a fan artist, I would say, España Sheriff.
I will be enthusiastically nominating her for fan artist.
And Alison won't tell you to nominate her, but I will.
You should nominate Alison as well because she's great.
I will also say we would obviously nominate Hugo, Girl, but they have recused themselves.
So we cannot.
We had muted nominating Ersatz Culture for best fan writer, but I believe he has said
somewhere that he would recuse if he was awarded it and he wants people to nominate Chinese
fan writers.
Yeah, it is.
Ersatz Culture has said that he will recuse if you nominate him, but also that he's going
to put up a list of Chinese fan writers who are worth looking at.
So when that pops up, we'll mention it so you can go and take a look at those.
I'm hoping quite a lot of reports from Chengdu will start trickling out and being translated.
For fan writer, I'd quite like to see, I'm sure other people will think of this, but please
nominate Paul Weimer.
This might be something that comes back up through my nominations.
Yeah, please nominate Paul Weimer who was unjustly.
I think we could agree.
Left off the Hugo ballot in 2023.
And I would also think about Camestros Felapton who has done a lot of great work.
Yes, I would agree.
I might nominate some of the Nerds of a Feather crew.
My problem is that sometimes I read Nerds of a Feather and don't pay 100% attention
to who is writing which bits, but they have some great writers there.
So we can just nominate Nerds of a Feather, yes?
Well only in Fanzine not in Best Fan Writer, yeah, but I might go and have a look at the different
bits.
We're lumping all of the fan categories together at the moment.
So Nerds of a Feather is a good fanzine rec.
Paul Weimer is a contributor to Nerds of a Feather.
As is friend of the pod, Haley Zapal, who is one of the Hugo Girl hosts.
Another fan writer we should mention is Sandra Bond and she has been posting.
She is just generally a very good fan writer.
Her work from idea makes her eligible for a fan writer as well a vast corpus of other work.
I will also say if she continues to write excellent poems about Dave McCarty in the Anonymous
Claire Discord, then I shall be definitely nominating her next year as well.
And I shall be hoping that they make their way into the voter packet.
She writes excellent poems on a wide range of things all over the internet.
So I think actually that's another reason why Sandra Bond might deserve your fan writer
vote.
I've got a Fancast.
As I said last year, everyone should nominate Going Solo by Tansy Gardam, which is an incredibly
deeply researched podcast that did a series on the Solo film, a series on Rogue One, and in
2023, this is the end of the solo series plus a series on the writer's strike with a lot
of historical stuff about the past strikes and how they affected things and also standalone
episodes on The Creator and How to Train your Dragon and it's really good and it's really
funny and it's really well written and yeah, you should really really nominate that one.
You nominate one podcast, nominate Going Solo.
I believe it is still called Going Rogue.
Oh sorry.
That's quite like, well I think that, because I think that season, podcasts with seasons
confuse me because like, why are they even?
Oh god, it is called Going Rogue.
Sorry.
We’re an evergreen podcast.
Alright, nominate Going Rogue by Tansy Gardam not Going Solo.
I've got confused and it's also wrong on the Hugo spreadsheet.
So please nominate Going Rogue.
Game apparently.
Yeah, something called Best Game or Interactive Work.
A new category.
So the two obvious ones in this category are two games I have not played which are Tears
of the Kingdom and Baldur's Gate 3.
I didn't like Breath of the Wild enough to want to play the sequel.
Baldur's Gate 3 is on my list of things to play but I haven't got around to it yet.
Do you want to do your actual suggestions then now?
The thing I enjoyed very much from 2023 was a game called Star Wars Jedi Survivor which
I think was amazing.
It took everything I loved about the first game and then basically just made it all better
which was great.
Which was the first game, John?
Jedi Fallen Order.
I will be enthusiastically nominating Star Wars Jedi Survivor for a Hugo Award.
I will also be nominating a couple of board games.
I do not expect them to arrive on the ballot but equally I feel I would be remiss if I
did not nominate them.
First things first, I can't nominate Arkham Horror the Card Game on account of how it
didn't have an expansion in 2023.
It's very sad, will be enthusiastically.
I will say that the 2022 expansion was an absolute masterpiece and everyone who doesn't like
it was wrong.
I will also be nominating Earthborne Rangers which I really like.
I've only played a little bit of it but I think it's really good and it's basically
if.
It's the gameplay of Arkham Horror the Card Game with the setting of Horizon Zero Dawn
in a way and so it is very up my alley.
Oh that sounds good.
It does doesn't it?
A little bit of Seventh Continent dashed in.
I've seen a lot of people saying lovely lovely things about this on the internet over the
while I've been in a while I've been under a rock.
The rock I've been under has had a lot of board games in it.
The other games I will be nominating are Moon and Star Wars the Deck building game both
of which I thought were great.
I was skeptical that Star Wars the game would be great and then it turned out it was great
so that was pleasantly surprising.
But yes those are my picks in games.
There is also a game on the giant spreadsheet of Doom that I have not played but really
really really want to so I don't know if either of you have played it called Apairy where
you play Space bees.
Yes that has that has it is all my list of things to play but I have not yet played.
I would very much like to play it.
But I looked at that like oh yes that's a good choice.
Despite the fact that I haven't played it.
Just on the buzz of all the people who have.
My favourite game from 2023 wasn't genre which is sad it's about economics and it has no
SF2-led elements at all.
Which games that?
Hegemony which is basically a model of class systems and economics and is absolutely wonderful.
It's just so good.
Long time listeners will note that the weight on BGG that it has of 4.18 would not usually
be in the Coxon range of acceptable weights for a board game and yet I love it.
And the other one that's on there is Chants of Sennar which someone called Liz likes.
I did please go back and listen to whatever episode I chose it as a pick.
It's pretty good.
I'll probably nominate it because I've literally played two eligible games this year I think.
Because I only just got a Switch and I don't have a PlayStation 5 and I haven't played
many board games so yeah.
It's probably Chants of Sennar, possibly Dredge which is this sort of atmospheric fishing
game.
Yeah otherwise that is about it.
I'd like to play Baldur's Gate 3 but I haven't you know forked out the cash for PlayStation
5 yet.
Which means I also can't nominate Horizon Forbidden West: Burning Shores which is on there but
I haven't played that.
I haven't played that either.
I own it but I haven't played it.
Baldur's Gate 3 is available on the Mac but not the PS4.
This seems very ludicrous to me.
Will also say another thing that's eligible in this category is the Galactic Star Cruiser.
I didn't go on the Galactic Star Cruiser but I just think we should note that, because it
was very ambitious and I've read so many articles about it and I'm just like oh I would
have given a kidney well I wouldn't have given a kidney.
I could have given a kidney and I didn't so clearly I wouldn't have done.
What was Galactic Star Cruiser?
Three day long LARP.
It was an interactive yeah Star Wars Hotel/LARP.
Yeah but so this is basically saying it's a convention right?
It's a convention.
No it's not.
It's like Phantom Peak.
No it's a larp.
There's a story line and you can affect it and change it and your decisions have meaning.
I think it falls under interactive work.
100% in the same way that I think if you went to Phantom Peak that would be eligible
for this category because it's a repeatable thing where it resets every time people enter
it.
Unlike a convention where a convention is unique and you can never go back.
Did they run it multiple times?
Is it like a...
Yeah.
Oh yeah so it's like a thing...
It was basically a three day long escape room.
And then we go on to the category of Best Dramatic Presentation Short Form.
Ooh.
Alison you watch TV.
I do.
Have I watched any of this TV?
Have I done any thinking about this?
I am bewilderingly behind on my 2023 television.
I will say that Strange New Worlds has a number of episodes on and I think I basically could
nominate any Strange New Worlds.
I think it'll be great.
But the ones that are on the Hugo spreadsheet of doom are Ad Astra Per Aspera, Under the
Cloak of War, Tomorrow and Tomorrow and Tomorrow.
Those Old Scientists and Subspace Rhapsody.
I think of those I would nominate Those Old Scientists because I thought it was absolutely
wonderful and it would be a very worthy winner.
Ditto In a Fight/ Old Friends New Planets from Lower Decks.
I think would also be very very good.
And there is an episode of the Mandalorian on there which was episode 20...
Sorry episode 7 of season 3 which is The Spies which I did also quite enjoy.
I really want to nominate For All Mankind but I feel like I want to nominate it in long
form rather than short form but I think it might be a bit difficult to nominate in long
form because of the way in which the seasons overlap the year and I'll need to do a bit
of finding out what everybody is doing.
The episode that is mentioned on the giant spreadsheet of doom is Leningrad so I guess
I probably will put it in a nomination in short form as well.
The thing that people are mentioning here that I have not watched and feel most guilty
about is another Apple TV show called Silo which I think is probably very good but I have
not got around to watching yet.
Have heard very good things.
I'm still... I'm nearly all the way through season 3 of the Expanse guys.
We are halfway through season 3 of For All Mankind and it is very good.
I will say that the previous times For All Mankind has appeared on the ballot it has been
nominated in short form for a specific episode so I would imagine that would continue but
I do not know for sure.
But none of these episodes make any sense whatsoever unless you are familiar with the
overarching story arc so you know.
Both The Giggle and The Church on Ruby Road are on the Hugo spreadsheet of doom.
I have enjoyed... I did enjoy the run of Doctor Who specials recently but I am not sure I
was planning to nominate any of them.
I'm sure they will be on the ballot but I'm not just really sure I think they deserve
Hugo awards.
Maybe that is very controversial.
Maybe that is a hot take.
I would also say I'm not nominating For All Mankind because I think its fourth season
was not very good, so no nominations for you.
Also on the... you know people have been talking about Blue Eyed Samurai which I have started
watching but not finished so I can't tell you which episode is best yet but that from
the first three episodes is pretty great.
I enjoyed Foundation a lot more in season 2 than season 1.
I don't know what episode again to nominate but probably not the season finale which people
put on there because I thought that was a bit weak.
It will be one of the later episodes leading up to us.
I'm going to put Strange New Worlds on but I like Tomorrow and Tomorrow and Tomorrow which
is the time travel one with Kirk.
Full disclosure Liz, I'm probably just going to nominate five episodes of Strange New Worlds.
No sorry, four of Strange New Worlds and one of Lower Decks.
I genuinely think Strange New Worlds is one of the best things in science fiction television
at the moment.
I just I would love to see it win a Hugo award.
Most of the other things we're discussing I'm like I think it would be fine if it won
a Hugo award but it wouldn't excite me.
John, you need to catch up with For All Mankind so that Liz and I can have a big argument.
I mean if I had to pick For All Mankind or Strange New Worlds, it's Strange New Worlds.
Oh should I be watching Strange New Worlds?
Were you not just I just said that Alison, like just now.
It's it's sort of TV service I don't have is that the reason I'm not watching it?
Yeah it's on Paramount+.
Oh god.
So I need another TV service.
Yeah but just get it for a month watch all of Strange New Worlds and then cancel.
Okay that's what we'll do but we have to finish the, do we have to finish The Expanse
first?
You can finish The Expanse whenever you like.
Strange New Worlds doesn't rely on any story from the expansion.
It won't spoil you.
Yeah but we normally only watch one television TV show at the time right?
Wait wait wait you've been watching For All Mankind and the Expanse or at least you took
a pause.
Yeah no so we watched bits of the Expanse and then we then we watched For All Mankind
and then we went back to the Expanse as a bit of a For All Mankind methodone.
Because I mean For All Mankind demonstrates what it is I want in my science fiction that
the Expanse doesn't have but nevertheless the Expanse you know I've kind of got the
hang of it now.
I would also say that I have not watched Gen V which is The Boys spin off so I don't
know if it was any good but in general I am still bewildered that the Hugo electorate are not
nominating The Boys which I think is like one of the most savage criticisms of modern
day.
For those who don't know the boys was developed by Eric Kripke who was also the showrunner
on Supernatural and Supernatural is sort of a love letter to America in the same way
that The Boys is a savage tearing apart of America.
Like Supernatural is a celebration of everything that's good about it and The Boys is a quite
cutting critique of everything that's bad about it and I think The Boys is great and
I will be paying attention to the 2024 season with great interest because the previous three
seasons were amazing.
And once again where can I watch it?
Amazon which you have if you're watching The Expanse so oh yes it is.
I have I have I have you know I have the Amazon if I Amazon if I want to get print and
play components delivered to my house twice a week.
Obviously The Last of Us was eligible and I don't ever put the whole series in long
form or just put the episode in short form that made me cry a lot which was Long Long
Time which is basically a standalone so there you go.
Poker Face which I should watch and I have not watched.
Oh it's great I might try and put some of that in short form.
In Best Dramatic Presentation Short Form listener Raj recommends The Wonderful Story
of Henry Sugar and The Church on Ruby Road from Doctor Who.
Thank you very much listener Raj.
I would also like to shout out whoever has put on the spreadsheet.
Superconductor PB 10XC UX showing levitation at room temperature and atmospheric pressure
and mechanism which is quite a funny science burn.
What, oh because it’s science fiction.
Yeah because it's not actually superconductor.
But shout out to whoever put that on the list. I'm not nominating it but well done.
I think I am the person who has done the most Long Form so I might introduce Long Form go
through the ones I've seen and the ones I think might be worth seeing before it all
wraps up.
Good oh yeah fair enough.
Agreed.
Asteroid City
Wes Anderson movie
Absolutely phenomenal.
I am not.
It does have an alien in it.
I was about to say I wasn't sure if it was genre but it does have aliens in it so I guess
it probably is really.
It's very close to the world but also if you have things like Oppenheimer and Hidden Figures
and sh*t like that you definitely get Asteroid City, it's more science fiction than Oppenheimer
obviously.
And it is also a masterpiece so I will be enthusiastically nominating that.
Barbie was very very good.
It's technically genre.
I'm not sure I think it's primarily good for its genre elements so I might nominate it
but equally if there is a lot of other very SF-nal stuff on my ballot I might not which
is not to say I didn't love it.
The Creator was very pretty but was also awful so it will not be going on my ballot.
D&D movie was great.
Not sure it deserves, I'm not sure it needs a Hugo it made more money than God I think
but it was very fun.
It's probably going on my ballot because I don't see a lot of movies and I really enjoyed
that one.
That is fair I mean it is very good it's basically it feels like a movie that's in conversation
with the first Guardians of the Galaxy movie in terms of like its whole vibe.
In that way I really enjoyed it and also Chris Pine is just brilliant in everything he does.
Even things that are not good.
Chris Pine is good in them.
I feel like one of the things about the Dungeons and Dragons movie is that it had a lot there
for people who had played a lot of Dungeons and Dragons in about 1980 and it had a lot
there for people who played Dungeons and Dragons in 2023 and it had quite a lot there for people
who had never played Dungeons and Dragons.
And I think that's quite a good trick to pull off in a tie-in movie.
Yes it also had a female lead with armpit hair.
Tons of armpit hair and sensible armour.
That was good.
And also Hugh Grant hamming it up beyond hamness.
Hugh Grant is living his best life and I am here for it.
He really is.
Guardians of the Galaxy Volume III which did make me cry will be going on my ballot.
The Marvels I loved the Marvels some people didn't like the Marvels but those people
I politely disagree with.
That might go on my ballot.
And then there's Polite Society which is the British Indian genre movie which was absolutely
phenomenal.
I am slightly surprised that I was the one to put it on the spreadsheet of Doom.
I would very very much like to see this movie on the ballot.
No chance.
Oh I know there's no chance but that's why I'm trying to use my platform Alison.
I would very much like our listeners to go and watch it and nominate it.
Look it up.
It's really really really really good.
And then Poor Things which I think it would be astounding if it wasn't on the ballot which
was also really really really good.
I feel like poor things should have a following wind for a Glasgow Worldcon it really should
despite the fact that it didn’t end up being set in Glasgow.
And then Spider-Verse 2.
Spider-Man across the Spider-Verse which will definitely be on my ballot.
Yeah.
It was a masterpiece even more than the first one was a masterpiece and the first one was
a masterpiece.
The only problem with it is the ending but I don't think that mars it enough for me
not to want to nominate it.
Has anyone mentioned Indiana Jones and the Dial of Destiny?
Indiana Jones and the dial of destiny is not on the Hugo spreadsheet of Doom which probably
tells you a lot about his chances of getting on the ballot.
It is a major genre movie of 2023 which I watched on an aeroplane.
It's terrible, it's a terrible film.
I really quite enjoyed it but it is terrible.
In Best Dramatic Presentation Long Form, listener Raj wrote in to recommend the D&D
movie and Across the Spider-Verse as we've mentioned but also recommended Nimona which
I don't think I know what it is and season 5 of Ghosts which we have mentioned before
but we have not mentioned just now.
So yes also one's to consider.
Oh Nimona is the Netflix film based on the webcomic and graphic novel.
Ooh that has passed me by, thank you very much for writing in Raj that's good.
Alright shall we do Best Related Work?
So there are multiple things for best related work.
Some people have been mentioning All These Worlds, reviews and essays by Neil Harrison.
I wanted to do that!
Please nominate All These Worlds reviews and essays by Neil Harrison.
It is fantastic, I still haven't finished it but the essays that I've read which has
got a few of them now are all great and it is jolly good and thought  provoking.
And we are totally biased guys, 100% biased podcast on this matter.
The other book that I will be nominating is A City of Mars which I thought was extremely
good and really enjoyed.
Oh that is getting a lot of buzz.
Yes it is.
I think I've seen people mention that the best fan writer/best fanzine packet that was
done unofficially before Chengdu released it is eligible but I would much rather recognise
the people who did that in Best Fan Writer.
Oh you mean, does he mean that that stuff from... hmm that's tricky because surely that
fan packet is a re-publication of stuff that was from 2022?
Yeah that's the thing, I think it's primarily notable for the fan effort rather than the
contents and therefore I would rather reward the people for their effort than the contents.
I don't know who wins the Hugo if all of the fanzines win a Hugo… I don't love it.
Excellent, how about this?
A Traveller in Time: the critical practice of Maureen KIncaid Speller edited by Nina
Allen.
That seems to be to be like an excellent, absolutely the sort of thing I would like to
see on the Hugo ballot for Best Related Work.
Yes I would agree.
It's a shame that there are two really good collections of criticism from UK critics who
knew and worked with each other coming out in the same year.
Let's get them both on the ballot and then  they can fight it out for first and second place.
That sounds good to me.
Another fantastic book about genre that came out in 2023 was the book 50 Years of Text
Games by Aaron Reed.
It started as a substack but that it was much revised and produced for the book and
the book is amazing and it is a really... I absolutely love it when really thoughtful,
comprehensive books about gaming history come out because there are not that many of them
yet because it is still quite a young genre in that sense and this is a wonderful book
and nearly all of these individual... nearly all of the individual games are genre but not
all by any means but overall it's clearly relevant to best related work and I would like to see
that on the ballot even though I know it's only me.
So if you have any interest at all in the history of text games, this is a book you should read.
I'm about to put it on the...
And that, I mean one of the articles from that went viral right?
Which one was that?
Oh I'm just finding it.
It was the one about the...
Female commune?
Nuns?
Yeah.
Nuns making text games, something like that.
I can't remember if they’re Nuns.
Yeah.
Women?
Women in some sort of context.
Yeah, I forget.
We'll put a link in the show notes listeners.
Yes, I found it.
It was the one about St. Bride's School which turns out to be...
Yeah, like a school which was putting out text adventures but I remember to go viral
and lots of people presumably read that and then became aware of the 50 years of text adventures.
Yeah, it ended up going to call 50 years of...
It started out as 50 years of Text Adventures but the book is 50 years of Text Games because
obviously the games included ended up being very much broader than just text adventures.
I've also heard good stuff and this is going to link a bit of foreshadowing here.
I've heard good stuff about "I Am the Law: How Judge Dredd predicted our future” by Michael
Mulcher so I may try and get out to that before the nomination deadline as well.
And that dovetails very nicely into Best Graphic Story.
I will be nominating a thing.
The thing I will be nominating is Moon Knight Volume 9 by Jed MacKaye and Alessandro Capuccio
and Rochelle Rosenberg.
It's really good.
I've never seen...
I've recommended Moon Knight on the podcast before and I love Moon Knight as a character
but I do not think all the Moon Knight comics are good.
I think that is important to say.
This Moon Knight comic is great.
It is weird.
The art is superb.
I cannot overstate how good the art is.
Sometimes I just look at pages for like five minutes and be like this dope.
The way in which it discusses the character is really nice and the way in which it embraces
some of the weirder aspects of the Marvel Universe including one comic where he fights
a house.
Which is the sort of thing I love in comics because you can't do that elsewhere.
It's got vampires in it.
It's just all of the weird bits of Marvel and it's great.
And it wrapped up in 2023 in December.
I don't think I've actually got to that issue yet but I've read the preceding 27 issues
and they were all issues I thoroughly enjoyed.
So yes, I will be nominating that.
I suspect it will not be on the ballot but I will nominate it.
Presumably the way to get hold of that one is to take Marvel Unlimited for a month and
read it all.
Yes.
Is there still a delay between stuff popping up on Marvel unlimited.
There's six months normally so you might not get all of it that way.
By the time you've read issues one to 27, issues 28 to 30 will probably have popped up.
I would say but I might be wrong.
I believe you can also just buy it.
I will put links in the show notes to where the collections are available.
Alison, you were going to recommend some comics as well.
I was going to say one more time.
Why Don't You Love Me? by Paul B. Rainey but I think we have mentioned that multiple
times on the podcast now.
I have read it.
Did you like it?
Ah, it's very bleak.
I think I liked it but Jesus Christ it was bleak.
It's very bleak.
It is pretty bleak.
And people talk about the ending being optimistic and I feel like they've read a different graphic
novel to the one I read.
I'm just going to say it's got one of the bleakest endings I've ever read I think.
I feel like they did not understand the ending.
Yeah, like maybe it's tricky right because they don't want to cast aspersions on people
who interpret art differently to me.
But I did not feel uplifted by the last page put it that way.
But you know, it is clearly very good.
But also there's a lot of stuff in graphic story that comes around is quite, I don't
have to explain it.
Sh*t.
I don't mean sh*t but I mean kind of quite basic entertainment.
You know, when I was saying how much I liked the Dungeons and Dragons movie, I mean I liked
it because it made me laugh quite a lot for a couple of hours.
Yeah.
But I feel like when I read graphic stories, including some quite well thought off ones,
quite a lot of them don't really do a lot more with the form than that.
They entertain me for a while and then I'm done with it.
And I would like to see graphic stories that have the use to have the same sort of weight
and texture as novels do and all too often I don't see that.
So when one comes along that does do that, I want to celebrate it.
Is that fair?
Yeah, I think that's fair.
It's not like many other things I have read.
So from that perspective. I would like to see a bigger range of genre graphic novels,
please.
What I will say, and this is tricky because it feels like I'm criticizing it for something
it wasn't true.
One of my core criticisms of it is that it didn't do what I wanted it to do.
But I don't know if it wanted to do it and I am historically a bit hesitant to levy that
kind of thing.
I wish it had been bleaker and funnier.
I think I would have really liked it if it was a if it had hewed more to the style of
old school newspaper strip where it was like Bam Bam punchline.
And I did I just I think I would have liked it more if it had been more parodic, parodic.
But equally I don't think that's what it's trying to do.
So I'm not sure if that's like a helpful thing to say.
I think it hit its intended tone bang on over and over again.
So I think I have to I have to say you are criticising it for something the author
wasn't trying to do.
Yeah, I think that is right.
Probably.
Best series I will be enthusiastically nominating The City of Last Chances slash House of Open
Wounds series for Best Series.
Ah, is it 240,000 words already?
Probably they're quite big.
It must be.
Yeah.
See my problem with that John is that I will be enthusiastically nominating The Final Architecture
by one Adrian Tchaikovsky and therefore we are arguing.
Has Adrian Tchaikovsky written enough extra words in five series for us to nominate a
lot of them?
I mean any other author you'd be like surely not, but Adrian Tchaikovsky perhaps.
I'm thinking about it.
Yeah.
Yeah, we can nominate The Final Architecture series, which is the one Liz just mentioned.
We can nominate the Tyrant Philosophers, which is what the series with city of last
chances and house of open wounds is.
I don't know what else he's written in 2023.
This is just our equivalent to the sort of people who nominate five Star Trek episodes
in 1967, isn't it?
Star Trek in 1967 was a groundbreaking and great as Adrian Tchaikovsky is in 2024 and
I will be fighting anyone who disagrees.
I mean, I would say for bonus entertainment, I'm pretty sure both of the tyrant philosophers
books are eligible in best novel due to it only getting a 2023 release in the US for
the first book.
So you have a chance to do something very funny.
And looking it up on Kobo, House of Open Wounds is 186,000 words long.
And so as long as City of Last Chances were more than 60k, which I think it was, then
I think it's eligible.
I mean, I think it is worth noting that because Ann Leckie wrote a fourth Imperial
Raj book Translation State, it is possible to nominate the whole thing for series again.
I'm not sure I will because I did particularly like the fourth book and I feel like the
first few got enough individual awards, but it is eligible.
So I think listener Raj wrote in and we'll get onto this in novel.
So a few people wrote in with their favorite thing from 2023 and I solicited some opinions
as well listeners.
But I think Raj mentioned Translation State as one of the favorite five things from 2023.
So I don't think Ann Leckie has ever been nominated for the Hugo Award for Best Series because
it post-dates her most well known series.
What else is a eligible, a bunch of stuff I haven't read.
Cool.
Dune!
You can nominate Dune for Best Series listeners because they've written another one for some
reason.
What?
Why?
Oh there's tons of them.
If this is true, this has a very good chance of winning because allegedly the Culture series
is eligible because there is a work of drawings from the Culture which eligibleises it.
And if that's true then a British Worldcon giving Iain M Banks a Hugo Award for Best
Series is not.
It's not unlikely but I don't know whether that counts and I had not heard that.
I feel that is against the spirit of the award in a big way.
Yeah I'm not sure I will be nominating it.
You know it's not like, like Elric was properly eligible last year because Moorcock had written
a new Elric book.
Spoiler is written another one, it's eligible this year.
Goodo, let's get Elric a Hugo, that would be good.
Yeah but it's going to be really difficult because I won't nominate The Culture but
if The Culture is on the ballot it was a very good series.
I don't know what I'd do then, that's tricky, we'll have an argument if it happens.
It's going to be a really tricky one there isn't it?
Because someone's going to have to make an eligibility call.
Yeah that would be down to Hugo UberChef.
The Hugo, Heston Blumenthal, Nicholas Whyte?
Yeah Hugo, Heston Blumenthall
Nicholas Whyte.
Shall we move on to short fiction?
Yes it's just going to be me.
I don't actually, I just, I find that short fiction has quite a low hit rate for me so
I did read a bunch of stuff which was either off the Locus recommended reading list or
things I had collected over time from recommendations on Bluesky or whatever or you know things
there's also Rocket Stack Rank that does ranking of stories and things and I read a
few of their top ranked ones and I didn't like that many of them.
So yeah I've got a few suggestions but not as many that kind of really made me go oh
this is amazing so I'm hoping that the Hugos, the nominations will draw some more stuff
up especially in Novelette I've got nothing in Novelette yet.
For listeners who are listening to the edit the reason Liz now sounds fed up is because
I just made that terrible air conditioning joke from the start of the show here.
I was on a roll and John is making terrible air conditioning jokes.
Serious science fictional content coming up.
I'm going to nominate some short fiction for the Hugos.
So in Best Short Fiction I have a suggestion which is a piece called Spring Woods Spring
by B. Pladek which was published at Strange Horizons and the premise basically is that
the trees have started glowing and it's a kind of nice meditation on climate change,
on aging, on families, on like the end of civilization in a way and I just really enjoyed
the tone so I'm going to suggest that one.
That's cool.
Yeah that's not on the giant spreadsheet of doom.
Oh well I should put it on the giant spreadsheet of doom.
I've read a few more of the things recommended but I haven't completely fallen for any of
them but there is good stuff that might turn up on the ballot.
My other recommendations are all novellas.
Somehow I've read three novellas, none of which are from Tor.com which is unusual for
me.
I didn't even know that was possible.
Oh yeah, well I read A Theory of Haunting by Sarah Monette which is in her series, the
Kyle Murchison Booth series which I have read none of the rest of actually.
But there are all kind of mysteries starring this Kyle Booth who is a kind of archivist
and goes out to solve various mysteries and ghost stories.
It's a ghost story in a haunted house but it's a good one.
I'm also going to pick Walking Practice by Dolki Min as previously picked by me which is
quite long so I'm worried it actually crosses over into a novel but I'm going to pick it
for novella.
And the last one I'm going to pick is called On the English Approach to the Study of History
and I almost don't want to style what the English approach to the study of history is
but it's basically a novella.
It's a novella all about academic history which is performed in a certain way originating
from Queens College, Cambridge.
And so it's about kind of, you know, it's about academia, it's about hierarchies, it's
about young women and non-white people and how they get along in academia.
It's about kind of how the same methods get used over and over and people don't want
to challenge them but it's also kind of a horror/ghost story.
The whole thing does take place in a college where I spent an awful lot of time in an undergrad
so that's probably why I like it but I still thought it was good.
And that is by E Saxey and it was published in Giganotosaurus who I think generally have
pretty good fiction until I might nominate them in Best Semiprozine as well.
I vote all of those sound really interesting, I will look them up enthusiastically.
Giga Notosaurus I think is a good shout for Best Semi-Prosean as is Strange Horizons.
Which has been nominated 11 years in a row at this point and never won and gone very,
very close.
Vote for Strange Horizons.
Yeah, it's probably about time to celebrate Strange Horizons, should be their year maybe.
I have unsubscribed from Uncanny so I have not really read any short fiction this year.
So I will be throwing myself on the mercy of people's recommendations.
I mean I do think Naomi Kritzer’s The Year Without Sunshine from Uncanny is a dead cert
in Novolette.
Fair enough.
Yeah so The Year Without Sunshine is a story about kind of communities coming together
in the face of difficult times in Apocalypse and I think it will really, I don't know,
I thought it was fine but I think it will really appeal to people who want that sort of story
about having a sense of community and coming together and people working together to solve
problems.
Listen to Raj wrote in and recommended the year without Sunshine by Naomi Quits for Novelette.
So thank you very much Raj.
I mean do send us your recommendations guys.
I am looking forward to seeing the ballot and then reading some short fiction.
Can we talk about novels before we run out of time?
Yes.
I read some novels.
I didn't read many though.
Liz read all the novels.
Yeah I read a lot apparently.
I was going to do some last minute novel reading and I solicited some opinions on what might
be good to read from various people and then when I went to look at them on Goodreads to
see whether Alison or Liz had read them.
Alison and Liz had read all of them except one so I started reading the one that they
hadn’t
Alison or Liz because there's no way I'd read all of them.
That you haven't read all of them but there are a few where Liz hadn't and you had.
So between you you are quite good on 2023 fiction.
Well done both.
Yeah.
Right well I started doing some emergency reading for this podcast and I was going to
read Julia by Sandra Newman which is a book that a lot of people have talked about who
are not necessarily in our regular thing.
It is a book that is in conversation as they say with 1984 by George Orwell and I read the
first eight pages and thought oh shit I need to go and read 1984 by George Orwell so I'm
just here to tell you that's quite a good book that holds up way better than you might
think it does but is perhaps not eligible for the Hugo.
So Julia is an interesting novel but I'm only halfway through it.
I think it's probably not as good as it thinks it is but I think there is plenty of space
to think about some of the other characters who exist in the space of 1984 and what's
going on in their lives and that is what Sandra Newman has tried to do here whilst also saying
something quite interesting about the philosophy and the kind of meta story of 1984 which is
always of course a huge thing but I'm not sure it entirely succeeds as an all but I think
it is a shout.
I have not read Hopeland but if I had a pound for everybody who had told me that Hopeland
by Ian McDonald is the best novel of the year I would have had enough for about 20% of
the money I spent in games shop yesterday and I think I would love to see Ian on the
ballot at a Glasgow Worldcon so.
Everyone should nominate Hopeland.
That's outrageous whether it's good or not but I hope it is and I will definitely read
it before nominations come around.
I have read Some Desperate Glory by Emily Tesh and I picked it as a former pick and
I think it is quite a good book and I have read The Saint of Bright Doors which is not a book
like any book I've ever read before and I think that is quite an interesting book but
I kind of slightly like it a little bit less once I learnt just how much the amazing central
city is just Colombo and just how much it borrows very directly from a major creation
myth of Buddhism but I think probably it is still pretty good and that is a very interesting
book.
I think that's probably about all of the ones that I have come to my attention that aren't
all but also going to be on Liz's list.
And indeed some of those are on my list.
Alright, I'd like to see Him by Geoff Ryman on the ballot as well and that's another one
that I have to confess I haven't actually read.
People who have read it tell us me tell me it's very very good but this will be a good
year to get some excellent British novelists on the list guys let's do that.
I'm going to pick some books that I have read and also weren't published many years ago
because I think that's probably a good starting point.
Yeah I was about to say only Alison when I asked what should we read from 2023 could
go on a digression about 1984.
Sorry guys.
So I am probably picking some desperate glory.
I'm in the middle of the Saint of Bright Doors and unless it's terrible in the last half
then I'm probably picking that as well.
My other possibilities are Cahokia Jazz by Francis Spufford which is an alternate history kind of
20s noir.
So it's basically the setting is that it's the 1920s and there is still like a huge native
American population that is thriving and has not been completely wiped out and they have
this city state called Cahokia which is home to a mix of Native Americans, African Americans
and Europeans and it's about a murder that is investigated by Native American who was
fostered as a child and so he does not speak the local language and his European partner
and he gets entangled with the politics of the city.
Yeah and I really liked it.
The closest thing to it is, sorry I can't remember the name of the book it is closest
to.
Oh, The Yiddish Policeman's Union.
So it feels a lot like The Yiddish Policeman's Union in that it has kind of a murder mystery
and the main thing is that it is set in this alternate United States.
So it did feel a bit like that but in a really good way. I like The Yiddish Policeman's Union
but it's not maybe quite core genre in that way.
What am I going to nominate? I'm thinking about In Ascension by Martin Macinnes which is this
really nicely written book about going into space and investigating a mysterious signal.
Yeah and it's kind of about this, I'm trying to say how I should want to say about this.
It's kind of about a protagonist who has kind of thrown herself into sort of marine biology
and the study of that in a way to get away from the difficult family relationship she
has and she ends up kind of deciding she's going to go to the stars.
And I read this quite a while ago but I really enjoyed it.
What else am I thinking of nominating?
Basically then I've got like an extra slot or maybe an extra two slots that might contain
City of Last Chances as mentioned on this podcast previously.
The Reformatory has recommended a couple of episodes ago by me, Titanium Noir as recommended
by me probably a few episodes ago and Our Share of Night by Marianna Henriquet.
I'm not sure if this is actually 2023 or 2022 because it's a translation of an earlier
novel but that is sort of a very long novel about people with sort of supernatural powers
and investigating the kind of other worlds set in 1980s Argentina.
According to Kobo that's 2022.
Yes but I think it might be 2023 in the US.
Ah hah.
Which I guess counts.
This is the last year, this is the last year it does count but it would this year yes.
Well we'll get into that again when I've bothered reading that one.
Yes you are right it is eligible through the US publication.
But I think it sounds very little chance of being on the ballot and but then it feels
like 700 pages and quite dense so I don't think it stands a chance then either.
I read I can't remember how much I've read this eligible.
I'm told by my learned co-host Liz that the City of Last Chances is eligible because it
was only published in the US in 2023.
What I will say is that the Hugo spreadsheet of doom has the sequel House of Open Wounds
on it instead.
So I wonder whether that is the one that people will get behind.
But I will read House of Open Wounds before the nominations close and I will probably
nominate both if they're eligible because I love Adrian's Tchaikovsky novels.
The book I have started to read but not finished I'm about halfway through I was hoping I would
tear through it and it turns out it's an incredibly difficult book to tear through because it
deals with loads of like hard stuff is Bridge by Lauren Beukes which is about there is a
woman and her mother dies and she has to go through her mother's stuff.
So it's probably maybe content warnings for anyone who's had to recently go through that.
Trigger, trigger warning.
Yeah.
And she has a memory that when she was young her mother used to take drugs and let her
take drugs and go to parallel dimensions and her therapist has worked on this with her
and explained how this is probably a false memory that's repressing something.
But since I'm really.
But this is a Lauren Beukes novel.
So since I am recommending it on the Octothorpe podcast one may be able to discern that this
perhaps might not be the case.
Part of the reason it's so difficult is because large parts of it deal with like if you're
doing a thing that to someone else sounds absolutely insane how do they process that
and how do you process your grief and if you're doing this while you're processing
that grief does that make it look worse to the exterior person and why did your mother
not talk to you more and there's a lot of really really hard stuff in there.
But I am really enjoying it so far about halfway through.
So if it doesn't completely screw the landing I would confidently recommend it and like anyone
who's read Beukes’ previous novels like it it seems up there with all of them maybe
even better.
So yes I am.
I haven't finished it yet so you know the last half might be rubbish but I strongly
suspect it won't be and I might pick it properly once I've actually finished it.
Sounds quite scary.
It's really good.
I'm not sure I would recommend you read it because of how it might be quite triggering.
He also heard from listener Raj who recommended some books we haven't covered.
Well we covered translation states in best series but Raj recommends that for novel.
He also recommends Meru by S.B. Divya, Descendant Machine by Gareth L. Powell, Starter Villain and
by John Scalzi and Book Shops and Bone Dust by Travis Baldry.
I'll be astounded if that latter isn't on the ballot.
I wrote to Niall Harrison to ask what he would nominate and most of his picks are ones that
have already come up as Liz and Alison have been talking but his favourite five books did
include Orbital by Samantha Harvey which we did not yet mention and which he really
enjoyed.
I wrote to Abigail Nussbaum to ask her for her opinions and she recommended The Terraformers
by Annalie Newitz and The Mad Sisters of Esi by Tashan Mehta both of which we didn't
mention and also recommended some others that we did.
I also wrote to Graham Sleight and he recommended some we haven't mentioned so he recommended
Conquest by Nina Allen, Biography of X by Catherine Lacey, Prophet by Helen McDonald and Sin
Blasheh, Dryland by B. Pladek who we mentioned in short story and Airside by Christopher Priest.
So this is the last chance to get a Christopher Priest book onto the Hugo Ballot for a UK
Worldcon, possibly our greatest British science fiction author, just saying.
I will definitely read it before nominations close.
Graham excerpted his picks from a Locus article so that was very handy because I can just
link you all to the locus article where he talks to that topic.
That was it, that's all of it, not bad.
Shall we do picks?
No.
And that was the Octothorpe podcast and it's goodbye from me, it's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
So when I go to, oh this is a clone of eFanzines that I've found through Google, how strange.
That is weird.
I just saw that the URL was not actually eFanzines.com and that'll be why.
Fair enough, okay good.
Yeah so what you want is eFanzines.com/idea.
Some sort of weird bootleg eFanzines, why?
Yeah I know, it's bizarre, oh yes, cool.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod at incompetech.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.
[silence]