I really am going off track now. Um, the stinks have a sport called golf, which was a vegetarian Scotland.
Hello everyone and welcome to the 61st episode of Octa thought the podcast for
science fiction and science fiction fandom. This episode is coming to you on the 7th of July 2022.
I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott. And I'm Liz Batty. And we have some letters of comment for you all.
Chris Garcia sent us an email. He thinks we need more Hugo categories. He is probably not correct in
the opinion of the Octa thought podcast. Sorry, Chris. I think the Octa thought podcast believes
in Hugo non-proliferation over brackets except video game. Liz Brackett.
Yeah, I go for a one in one out system. Well, like the hokey-cokey.
Except that's how would you decide what goes in on the one in one out system? And if it was by
number of votes, it might ditch some things I quite like spoiler for later in the episode.
I was going to say you foreshadowing again, Liz.
Generally, I just don't want the Hugo ceremony to take any longer than it already does, I think.
He does mention that they did a whole drink tank. So for those who don't know, the drink tank is
Chris Garcia's fanzine. And they did a whole drink tank about audio dramas. And that is true. And we
will put a link in the show notes. And he also thinks the idea of best critical work sounds good.
And basically also talks about short film discovery and says that there is a YouTube channel called
Dust, which is our friend. And I have not explored this yet, Chris, but I intend to.
He, along with I think a few other people also pointed out that when we were discussing
ABBA and their magical hologram technology, we failed to talk about the president of having
Tupac as a hologram at Coachella, which I did know about, but had forgotten.
When I think I assume it's the same technology that the gorillas used to perform at Glastonbury,
because they were holograms as well. Being cartoon characters. The hologram cartoon is
probably easier to pull off than a real looking person hologram.
Ob 3D nerd, none of these things are holograms. They're all pepper's ghost.
You know, you cannot actually do holograms at that sort of scale. I'm sure we would do if we could.
But people do talk about them as being holograms. So this might just be a kind of change of,
of language. They are literally holograms. When people say that something is significant,
there's always a little voice at the back of my brain that says, and have you done your p-test,
but I don't let it out because that voice inside my brain is very annoying and not helpful.
That's also foreshadow, but for the next episode.
Yeah, we'll name that little voice in your head.
Chris mentions, as I said, short films and so did Fran Dowd. Fran on Facebook sent us a list of
lots of short film festivals in the UK. And there is one in Sheffield. There is one in Sheffield.
There is one in Sheffield. And there's one in Manchester. I'm sensing a theme. Fran lives in
Sheffield listeners. So thank you very much for sending those in. Fran, if you are a British
person listening to this and you know of a short film festival that focuses on genre films,
please do let us know because we would be interested to hear about them.
And honestly, there probably are quite a lot we don't know about because if all of fans are in
Sheffield, then either they're on Sheffield or there's an awful lot more that we didn't mention.
And on the subject of the things that we wrote last time, Roman Orzansky wrote to us to say,
I think your suggestion of a best audio drama Hugo is a great one. That is not what I suggested.
I was drawing my net a great deal wider than that for all sorts of audio. But he also says,
there's a lot of audio you hadn't thought of and sends us some suggestions of what that might be.
So thank you Roman. He also encloses a slideshow he created, which we will try and put in the show
notes somehow. Thank you very much for doing that Roman.
Farah Mendelssohn wrote a Facebook comment to tell us about the Science Fiction Research
Association or SUFRA, which is the oldest professional association dedicated to the
scholarly inquiry of science fiction and the fantastic across all media, which is very good.
Doesn't say on their website where they're based because they're in the US and I assume they just
assume that you know there are 501(c)(3) or no, sorry 501(c)(6) non-profit, which means that they are in the
United States and therefore you don't specify that because that's the default, right? I'm not bitter.
Well, it might be registered in the US. I mean, I think their last conference was
in Oslo and it was this week and there's been lots of stuff from that on Twitter and it seems
quite international. So, I mean, I think it's one of those things where it's not like a thing that
calls itself the world association of something and then exists only in the US.
Yes, but it might be the dead hand of empire.
They do have on their website a list of country representatives, which does have a large number
of different people. I note that it doesn't have a country representative from the United States,
which adds to my theory that it is based in the United States. But they do have from Australia,
Austria, Brazil, Canada, Czech Republic, Estonia, Germany, India, Israel,
Moscow, Norway, Russia, South Korea, Spain,
slash Catalonia. They're not the same thing. Switzerland, Turkey, and the United Kingdom.
Quite an international group of people. I'd never heard of them. I had either review heard of them.
Yes. Yeah, I just forgot when we were doing the podcast.
Definitely forgot. Thanks for providing us for our.
So, we got a comment on Twitter from Duncan McGregor saying we have ignored the possibility of a
Hugo Award for Best Hugo Award. And Dave, to say we have missed the idea of a Hugo Award for Best
WISFUS Committee. And yes, we did not mention those on the podcast. Thanks.
What I love is that Duncan responded to Dave with a gift of Thanos saying I am inevitable.
And I was like, that is what the WISFUS business meeting is like, the end of Avengers Endgame.
I'd never put it together before in my head, but I think Endgame might be a metaphor for the
WISFUS business meeting. You heard it here first.
Can I choose which half of people to evaporate?
On another forum, we had the opinion that what we need is a Hugo for Best thing,
and that is the only Hugo. And therefore, we can get rid of all of the Hugos and just have a Hugo
for Best thing, which is of a certain kind of elegance to it. If you are a Hugo maximalist,
then this is the Hugo minimalist approach. So thank you for that comment on Discord in.
I think we should have that as a proposal at the WISFUS business meeting.
We did also get a Twitter from Raj, who is Lord of the Moon on Twitter, who is listening to our
back catalogue. And yeah, thank you very much for writing in Raj. Really enjoying reading your
comments on our previous stuff. And please do keep writing in. And anyone else who's going
through the back catalogue, and he's on episode 60 now, 61. Yeah, also writing.
You won't hear this for ages, Raj, I realise. But hello from the past or from the future.
Times weird. And Andrew January wrote to us, and he has run our transcripts. This is why we did
transcripts to see through a machine learning generator and has generated an episode of Octo
flop. Now this is scripted, which we never do, but I think we should read it out anyway.
And he's given it with voices. So right. So this is a machine learning generated episode of Octo
flop. Chris Garcia, yeah, gonna get round the table once you're a smaller gully.
I mean, I think it's now a big showing for the then. The show that I voted back at is that we've
put it on the internet. So if you go from the podcast thing, Gimmery, and for panels like these
fan tables. Although I did not, because they recision that they've already already, I want to
met especially that they're only alical nominees and you must leaving the power in your abover.
Yes. Why do I get the one with all the made up words, did it? Boo. Boo. I very rarely use
made up words. But I feel like I use much play to English that you, Alison, I feel like you should
get the made up words with your flowery words. Like, I don't know. That's fair. Indeed. And I
can't believe it didn't put that's fair in there. Or 10 out of 10. I mean, I feel like there are
lots of words which I if I have been being a machine learning generator of an octo podcast,
I'd have put in. Sorry, I did identify that every episode we do say the words Chris Garcia though.
So that was fair. Yeah. So thank you very much for that, Andrew. And we will give you some more
transcripts. And the particularly good thing about this is that you'll be able to insert this
transcript with all those machine learning generated words in to kind of create kind of
octothor perception. Oh, you're gonna have fun transcribing this one as well.
Transcribing this podcast is always a joy. But you can cut, you can cut and paste the bit we just
did because we did it scripted. There we go. Only if we did it right, which we won't have.
Yeah, John messed up.
On the subject of only doing things right, shall we talk about Wiscom? That was a segue listeners,
flawless. We're going to talk about Wiscom in a very specific way, I should say, since all of us
were at Wiscom or, or I don't know if you go to any virtual bits of Wiscom? I did not. Nope.
Nope. But the interesting thing is that Wiscom did a very detailed post-com
COVID report about what they did to try and keep the convention safe in the time of COVID. I mean,
they also do discuss about how, you know, is it actually unsafe to have a physical convention at
all? But they were basically forced into this because they had a contract with the hotel and
it had a big penalty clause for cancellation. And, you know, they weren't allowed to cancel it
in 2022 because there were no restrictions on large gatherings where they are. So yeah,
they basically were having a convention. And so this is what they did to try and keep it safe.
They did things that a lot of other conventions have done, like having a vaccination policy,
although it sounds like there's a quad you also to have a booster dose if you're able. But they
said they do the checking on a separate floor. So that basically if you were under vaccinated and
you were going to be turned away, you were in a separate place, rather than being with everyone
else in the main space. And they also had that policy on kind of everyone who was in the convention
spaces, including things like childcare providers and their captioning providers. They had a masking
requirement. They encouraged people to test by having free rapid test kits in the space. They
lowered the attendance cap and given that they use the same space every year, they will know very
well kind of what it looks like if you put, you know, 800, 900 people in that space versus what
you do if you put 600 in and they in the end had 407, they say. So that's kind of like half the
size of those will physically fit. You know, they had a bunch of other stuff, including changing
air filters, you know, prepackaged food, not having the zits along in the same way and things like that.
But I thought the interesting bit was that they managed to do air purification basically by buying
some big commercial air purifiers to put in the space and then essentially making a load of
small air purifiers to put them all the way around their space. And so basically they did the best
they possibly could to try and clean the air space while people were there. Yeah, so I thought there
are a few things they did that yeah, I haven't seen it at the conventions. I mean, one is that they
had the masking requirement extend to hotel employees, which I think is very difficult to do
unless you have a very good relationship with your hotel. If that's not mandatory in the place
where you're holding the convention. And also the idea of basically the day before assembling a bunch
of kind of DIY air purifiers cheaply so that you can have them all over your space is quite
interesting as well, because I don't know any of the conventions that have tried that. Anyway,
despite that they still had 12 or 13 cases, but they say a lot of those are linked possibly to
what's called the governor's club, which has like an open bar. They're not kind of convention
exclusive spaces. They probably had other hotel guests in them, whereas they didn't in their
convention exclusive spaces. So yeah, I thought it was quite interesting. A few things that you
might be able to do that other conventions have not, especially the one about like having
cheap air purifiers in all your spaces that might give you that little percent or two extra
safety. I think, yeah, I mean, I agree with you on the air purifiers. I think that was quite good,
and they use the kind of model for a cheap one that's been out on the internet. This is a thing
that other conventions could do, because getting fans to build stuff is one of the things that
conventions are normally pretty good at. They didn't have any alcohol in any of the convention
spaces, and the few cases that they did have were clustered around the places where people
could buy and consume alcohol. I don't think it's an accident that EasterCon, with lots and lots and
lots of cases, has a culture that is built around a bar that almost everybody hangs out in,
and Wiskon, which has a culture that doesn't really involve any drinking of alcohol whatsoever,
didn't have very many cases except for the people who weren't ahead and drunk alcohol anyway.
So I think we may need to think about the effects to which people get drunk and then spread covid.
When I think like the other thing here is that EasterCon let people take drinks into panels and
things like that. So I think there is potentially a point at which EasterCon is on one end of this
Spectrum and Wiskon is on the other, but I do wonder whether the ideal position for EasterCon
would be a place where you can't drink alcohol in panels, for instance. I would not particularly
have a problem with doing that. I don't want to take the bar away, but I don't necessarily think
it would be a bad trade to sort of bring it a bit closer in on that Spectrum.
Yes, I think this is going to be a big question for next year's EasterCon, which of course I'm on
the committee of, thinking about whether we could just say, well, if it's a program, then you can't
have open alcohol in the program, that you have to drink it in food and drink accessible areas.
But it's complicated. I think it does raise quite a lot of questions because I think what we see
there is that the people who went to the bar did maybe catch it anyway and Wiskon's a shorter
convention than EasterCon, which is in turn a shorter convention than the WorldCon. The reason
EasterCon had so many cases was not just because of the bar culture, it was because people had time
to catch COVID at EasterCon and then spread it, which you probably don't get in a type weekend
convention and you definitely do get at the WorldCon maybe even longer. But yeah, I'm running a
mask required space at WorldCon, so hopefully that will reduce the extent to which people catch
COVID. Great, I think it is four days. I mean, I think it's people arrive Friday morning and people
leave Monday evening, kind of similar to EasterCon and some people arrive on Thursday and some people
leave on Tuesday. So it's not a whole lot different. I'm trying to remember, I think the last thing I
saw about like Omicron incubation times was like somewhere between two and five days as this sort
of median. So, you know, I think the difference between three days, four days, five days, it just
really depends if you've got someone or a few people there who are, you know, you might just
have time to have an extra round, but don't think there's a lot in it kind of going from three days
to four days. I think it is interesting to see a convention that has come out with a fairly
comprehensive post event analysis, which is really nice. And the sort of thing that it often
doesn't happen because there's a lot of effort. So thank you very much to WISCOM for doing the work.
That's very good. So I also saw a tweet from Andrew Plotkin. Now Andrew Plotkin is a well-known
person in interactive fiction game designing. I don't know whether every listener will have
heard of them, but basically like they've done some really interesting stuff. So I follow them
on the Twitters. He went to a convention called scintillation and was like, there was no COVID
and it was great. And the thing is that scintillation was 75 people and also core
flu didn't have any COVID and that was great. Or at least no confirmed COVID like Caroline had a
cough but kept testing negative. Probably not COVID but maybe COVID. Who knows. And like yeah,
that is very true. If you have very small conventions, your risk of getting COVID goes down. I did,
I think we probably already knew that number of people was a key factor in how much the COVID
might be around. I mean, I guess that's another thing to consider is maybe it would be cool to run
some very small kind of Teledoo sized conventions in the pandemic because you know they would be
less risky and I had a lot of fun at Teledoo. So maybe that would be good. So I don't know.
It's an interesting one. I don't know whether there's much you can take away for bigger conventions
from the news that a very small convention didn't have much COVID because it kind of makes sense
to me in my head that that was true. Yeah, yes, smothcon. Smothcon also had no COVID.
So I guess what I'm saying guys is we need to run punctuation three.
I mean, they did do some other stuff that you know, similar to whisk on of having masking
vaccination and air filters. I mean, I would say the other thing is if you have like,
say you did like a 40 person convention or something, it is totally feasible for a 40 person
convention to like set up a room on site and say, okay, you enter conspace. Here's your rapid test.
Do it now for, I don't know, I don't know how much rapid test costs in the UK, but I mean,
you know, that's what, so it equated expenditure? I don't know. I haven't actually ever still
working through my NHS stockpile. Yeah, I had to buy a box or I know I can get them from a ACP.
I mean, I could definitely provide tests for a 40 person convention from my stockpile.
Well, we know we know the 37 billion pounds spent on tests and trace went to
good use in Alison's stockpile. Hey, I've got a stockpile too. Well, I mean, I'm sure,
I'm sure there are other people with stockpiles as well, right? I don't think I'm the only one.
I think the general state of play now seems to be people who have no tests left and people who
have a big pile of boxes. I should say I'm being flippant, but I mean, I do think it was quite
wise to do that, but it has led this situation where we do have people who have stockpiles.
I was just going to say I've been to a sort of many hundred person event where they did require
you to either provide proof of, you know, proof of a recent ATK or to take one on site. All
of the proof was, I think I showed a picture of mine, you know, in front of a dated newspaper or
something. So it's not completely like without loopholes, but you had to actually show the proof
for those who haven't been following us closely. An ATK is a Thai LFT. I think that actually is
everything up for everyone. And an LFT is a British RAT. Yep, an RAT is a small rodent that used to
get a ship's cat to deal with, and that doesn't make any sense to anyone. For shadowing. The other
thing Andrew Plotkin says in his blog is that he ate all of his meals either with one other person
or on his own getting takeout most of the time. And that is something that wouldn't
Portwell to an Eastercon because yeah, I've generally eaten quite large groups at Eastercons,
especially breakfast. And not just eating as well. I mean, I think we've been talking about the
possibility of going to a bar at Chaicon and things like that. That means that unless you're
very careful about the way you live over the weekend, you might still find some exposure. Yep.
[Music]
So, Olaf Rokney wrote a reform proposal for the Hugo Awards. Now, actually, no, this is a case for
nananana nanana nanana lisbat to the Wussfuss Constitution lisbat.
I'm not prepped now. I'm going to open it. I just like, how has this become my personal brand?
I'm very happy to introduce the Olaf Rokney stuff because I care a lot.
Why don't you introduce it because I'd have to read it and do it on the fly and you'll do a big
job. So, I am temporarily handing over the, I don't know, baton. Wussfuss gavel? I think you'll
find it's a gavel. No, it's the lisbaton. I'm handing the lisbaton to Alison because she knows
this one better than me. What's the difference to the lisbat and the lisbaton?
I don't know, Alison. What is the difference between a lisbaton and a lisbaton?
One of them belongs to opt to the quicketing corner.
I thought Alison had a joke and I played long and then Alison just looked very confused.
No, no, no, I didn't have a joke. I was just saying that the baton a bat.
No, a baton isn't a bat. That's why it's a baton.
A baton is for like twirling.
Yeah, like in a relay race.
You were at an American high school, weren't you?
Yeah, they don't do baton twirling in American high schools. They do baton twirling in Scottish
high schools and Scottish secretary school, primary schools and secondary schools.
Right, all Scottish people, please write in.
Apparently a baton is defined as a staff or truncheon used for various purposes or an object
transferred by runners in a relay race, which is the sense in which we were using it.
Yes.
Octa thought words corner.
Yeah, word using it as the truncheon.
No, I was using it in the relay race sense.
I mean, Liz will beat you with her other Liz baton if we don't get on with it.
So come on, Alison.
So one of the little known provisions in the Wistvers Constitution is what is called the 25%
rule, which says that if any category doesn't get 25% of the overall number of votes cast in
the Hugo's as a whole, I might be quite slightly wrong about this. We'll put a link to the exact
wording in the show notes. But if any category doesn't meet that threshold, it's not awarded.
And this isn't nominating votes. This is voting votes.
This is obviously terrible. It might not be obviously terrible, but here's why it's terrible.
What it means is that you could have a bunch of happy podcasters say to pick a random category
as an example. Turn up at the Hugo Awards in their posh togs, very excited and then have them
announce. Oops, we've decided not to announce this category because we didn't get quite enough votes.
So nobody's won. Off you go back to your podcasting hole that nobody cares about,
because 25% of them didn't vote. This is kind of odd because podcasts and critical works generally
and fan works don't have the same sorts of reach or spread or marketing budgets as say novels and
in particular dramatic presentations. And it seems a bit odd that this is some kind of model as to
whether it's worth awarding Hugo's to them or not. I think quite a lot of people agree that even if
this is a good idea in principle, this probably is the way that you would want to do it. You
could create drama just by the way that the way in which you do it, which probably isn't how you
would want to. So people have been thinking about what you might do about it. The original
provision existed because there weren't very many Hugo votes at the time. There were maybe kind of
500 or 600 votes for the Hugo's overall. So the 25% threshold was 150 votes or so. And it felt like
if you couldn't get 150 votes for something, then maybe there wasn't a lot of interest in
that amongst Worldcon attendees. But that's not the case now because we have thousands of votes
for the Hugo's. They're very popular and that's great. One of the things that the
proposals on the file 770 blog in which they talk about it note is that the 25% rule would have been
591 at discount. But that is more votes than any category received in the
Hugo's in which this rule was first proposed. And while I'm not sure I disagree that some
consideration of that in the Constitution is what is, I do think that without carefully doing it,
it will basically just end up with the fan categories going away by default. And because I think the
fan categories are actually an important part of the Hugo Awards, I disagree with that. I am
obviously wearing a hat in which I have been nominated in those categories. So perhaps I am
biased. It also means the best editor long form is at risk because that gets about the same number
of votes as some of the fan categories. And so it could go away under this as well. And so,
yeah, I think it's wise to make sure that the Hugos are not given out by a tiny number of people
just voting for their mates. But I do think that kind of, I don't know, I think anything above about
100 or 150 votes probably meets that. So I'm not sure that a 25% threshold is necessary.
And striking this and kind of seeing what happens and how we could introduce new rules to prevent
sort of small number statistics going forwards is probably the best way of going.
I think my general view is the sufficient people still voting in the fan categories. They don't
feel like they're being voted for by 12 men and a dog. So the simplest solution seems to be,
let's just ditch this 25% rule and then see what we get. And you know, you'll, this still might
mean hundreds and hundreds of people voting in these categories. And so that's fine. I guess in a
kind of devil's advocate way, you could say that, you know, there are a lot of Hugo's and as things
become more and more niche, should there be some way that we, you know, do decide actually this has
become too niche for the Hugo electorate to really have an opinion on only a small proportion of them
have any sort of opinion on it. And maybe that's a sign that they should not be
Hugo's. And so looking at number of votes might be one way to to kind of assess that. But actually,
I think if you do want to do something where you don't award in the lowest popularity categories,
then the way to do it would be to look at the number of nominations rather than
the number of votes because it's much better to say, okay, we're not having, you know, this category
this year because it didn't get many nominations than to say actually we're having this category.
Here are all the nominations here are the finalists. You know, they've got dressed up and come ceremony
and now they don't get an award. I'd much rather did it earlier on. It seems much, you know,
kinder to the people involved. So if you, if we did want something like this, I would support
bringing it back at the nominations side of things. I think that probably makes sense.
I don't think popularity is the best measure of how important a category is. I do think it's one
measure, but I do think, you know, the fan categories have had a long tradition in the Hugo
voting. And also, there's not, there are other awards for fan endeavors, but there's nothing that
has the sort of reaches even the 25% of Hugo ballots. This is a much more comprehensive assessment of
what fans think is good than anything else we've got in the space.
I don't want the fan categories to go away because they're unpopular relative to novel,
but if they became so unpopular that it was 12 men and a dog, I would rather see them retired
than just be a joke. I think there is a consideration here of you need a minimum amount of investment
from the Worldcon community in order for the award to make sense as a prestigious award
awarded by the Worldcon. I don't think that number is 591. I think it's quite a long way below 591,
but I saying like every category must have at least, I don't know, 100 nominations. I think that
would be fair. I think below that you do run the risk. Do you mean 100 across, you mean 100 nominations
or 100 nominating ballots across a category? The latter. Yeah, we get much more than that.
There were 274 fan cast listed or something lost here, something like lots, lots, lots.
So yes, I think bringing it back at the nomination stage is not a bad idea. Whatever happens,
the earliest such a change could take effect is 2024. So if you're on the
Chicon committee, I mean, I guess I mean Cat here, if it turns out that Best Fan cast isn't going
to be awarded, do you think you could tell us at the Hugo reception or even earlier in the weekend?
So that we can just kind of drink all the vodka instead of having to come to the show?
If it is going to be kept in the voting, it should be announced like the day after voting
closes, right? Because it should be relatively obvious if like I know that doing the count is
hard, but how many ballots actually filled one of the categories in should be a relatively simple
database query, right? So you could announce that very quickly after the deadline, I would have thought.
I hadn't thought that about our tour. It's a very good point from Liz, because I do think at the
moment it does seem unnecessarily cruel. It's just fantastically cool.
I'm actually just looking at it. Best Fan cast, for instance, had more nominating ballots than
Best Editor Short Form, Best Editor Long Form, Best Professional Artist, Best Semi-Prozine.
I mean, I do think this is about marketing budgets. I mean, the overall number of ballots is driven
by Disney being in every household in the world. That's the thing. Not sure it does, right? Because
Best Novel is the leader and I'm not sure Disney are pushing any of the novels all that hard.
I think Best I thought Best Dramatic Presentation was normally the lead. It probably varies.
It probably depends how much you've got to the Hugo packet, guys. So better Hugo packets mean
more votes for Best Novel. We're at nomination phase here. Oh, a nomination phase. I know,
but I thought I thought Alison was making a point about how the number of votes in those categories
being proportionately larger than the votes in Fan cast, despite the fact that it's not represented
at nomination phase is because after the nomination phase, there's more money to spend on that.
It's both nominations and it's familiarity. Oh, in that case, I disagree with you. Sorry,
because I don't think the data supports that view. Okay, so Liz, you told us you'd crunched
the data. Could you crunched the data? You're going to have to give me better specifications
than that. I can tell you that Best Novel got way more nominating ballots than either of the
Best Dramatic Presentations last year. But it's votes that count for this at the moment.
Yeah, but we keep making the argument about nominations as well. So you're going to have to
specify your data query and I will do it. I think I can see an argument and if this isn't the
argument Alison was making, it's my idea. So I'm making it and I'm very clever. I think I can see
an argument that the fact that some things get much more nominations compared to others in the
nomination phase, but then that's not reflected in the vote is due to the fact that if you get
something nominated for a Hugo, you might market it based on that and that might increase your
number of votes. And I can see an argument that the nominations reflect much more the level of
interest in the community in various categories and then the votes reflect kind of that combined
with the marketing considerations of these companies that stand to benefit from this.
I think that is a coherent argument. I thought that's the argument Alison was making. She's
still shaking her head. So it's my idea and I'm very clever listeners.
Right. Any comments from the crowd. So one of the things about human conversation is that it
often goes in areas that neither of the participants, none of the participants expect at the point
where you start the conversation. And then sort of the things are so good about it. This is also
foreshadowing for our next episode. Yeah. Do you want to make a comment on how can I make a comment
on John's actual proposal? Because I don't think it's marketing. I think where's his marketing
budgets, but it's not marketing budget in a specific way. It's just that if I look at the ballot and I
see five fan casts I never heard of and I see five films and I watch them in the cinema. Of course,
I'm going to vote in best dramatic presentation and not vote in best fan cast. Yeah. And the reason
you've seen them in the cinema is because they're huge projects with huge budgets. And a fan cast
is just like a fan cast. On the obvious solution is we need cinemas to be screening afterthought.
No. Agreed. Fan activity is worthwhile even if it's a minority taste. Criticism as well. I think
we had the best nonfiction Hugo that you were talking about last week, then I think you would
see that get lower votes as well. Because it's not what everybody wants. It's fine. It doesn't
mean it's not important. Anyway, so one of the ways to deal with this is to try to find convoluted
ways of solving the problem. But I think Olav has gone for let's just scrap it and see what happens
and that would also be my preference. Yeah. I mean, has it ever actually been used? I don't know
actually. That is a good question. I don't believe so, but I think it's come a little bit worryingly
close. This also means guys, please vote in all the minor categories and get your pals to so that
we don't have this problem of not awarding. Yeah. Not awarding an award when there are massive numbers
of votes. I think basically if you have a rule that was enacted in 1964 and has never actually
come about, then it might be time to get rid of it and say actually, do we really, if this really
doing what it was proposed to do. Hugo stats nerds write in and tell us whether this has ever been used.
Picks, picks, picks, picks, picks. Liz, do you want to go first? Yeah. All right. I'm going to go first
with my pick, which was going to be, you know, some TV or a book or something that you could also
engage with. But actually, it's going to be the best purchase I've made for at least several weeks,
which is a Roomba. And I have called him Kevin. Kevin the Roomba. I called him Kevin because at the
moment, there's lots of adverts for the million, million film on the train I take to work in the
morning. And he got there's a minion called Kevin. So I call him after that because he's just
delightful. Basically, he hovers my house. I hate hoversing. So I'm very happy to have a robot who
sort of bumbles about hoversing my house, but he's also just a little bit incompetent. He's second
hand. So I think he's, you know, his state of the art technology was probably state of the art in
about 2015. And so he's both brilliant at hoversing and also just a little bit pathetic. I pressed the
dock button, which is supposed to send him back to his little charging dock to dock. And despite
him being about five meters away, he went in completely the opposite direction and spent about
10 minutes kind of wobbling around my office, bumping into things before coming back to the
correct room and then managing to dock. And when he gets to dock about 10 centimeters away,
he slows down and goes incredibly slowly. So he doesn't bump into anything and just kind of goes
click and gets his little charging socket someplace. So basically, he's great. I'm going to buy him
some googly eyes. And when I put the googly eyes on, I'll show you all a picture.
Yes, yes. I'm very excited about this pick because I am going to buy a Roomba. I'm probably going to
wait for it's it's prime day coming up and there might be a sale. And if there isn't a sale, I might
wait for about Friday and get one then. But yes, I want the Roomba i3. My Roomba is a Roomba 620,
if you want to know kind of what sort of technology I am dealing with here. The i3 is one of the ones
that you can put virtual walls in your house and you can control it by Siri. So I'll be able to ask
the air to do the hoovering and the air will hoover, which is a 10 out of 10 innovation.
Oh, that's that's the best thing though. There's no there's no virtual walls on this one. It would
do virtual walls if I built like little things to mark the walls. But I'm not doing that. I paid
40 quid for the room, but I'm not spending 40 quid in a virtual wall for him. So I closed the door
and then he just sort of like the sort of some sort of terrifying thing on the other side of the
door. And it was kind of like, or a cat. I think I think he's heavier than a cat is the thing or
certainly he like drives forward with more force than a cat would when presented with a closed door.
I guess this depends very much on your cat. But it'll sort of like come along and bump on the door
and then like, you know, spin around and wander off again. It's like, when's he gonna come back
and bang on the door again? Yeah, it's science fiction, the future.
I have a second hand Roomba, which was given to me with the instruction that I would need to buy
a new battery for it because it was battery was shot and I would need to give it a good clean.
And so I have bought a battery for it and I have not given it a good clean. And the next stage was
going to be to get our bedroom clear enough of crap on the floor so that we could reasonably
use a Roomba in it. And there this project has stalled to speed a year or something now.
Oh, it is also great incentive to not leave like shoes lying around everywhere.
We are relatively good about not having crap on the floor. So I'm not sure that's going to be a
huge problem. Getting to know, I mean, I'm not saying that this is a problem for other people.
I am merely saying it's a problem for me. So this is my explanation for what I have a Roomba,
but I have not given it a name and and it's just kind of sitting in a carrier bag waiting for me
to get my act together. But I mean, mine also can't cope with my coffee table because it's got like
these cross like these legs in the sort of the shape of a cross. So they're a slight slope.
So we can get up on the slope and then get stuck and then it just makes us sort of sad bleeping
noise until you come and put them back down. So it's quite a high maintenance pet really.
It's also what I needed in my life a high maintenance pet. I mean, you should get a cat, Alison.
My pick is also technology and my pick is a stream deck. Oh, that's exciting.
Now, whenever Alison goes off on one, I can press a button. I have a little automation that tells
me the timestamp at which she went off on the one and then the timestamp at which we got back on
track and that is going to be listeners you don't understand. Those of you who've been to live shows
do understand, but this is game changing, I would say. But it's really good. I've pressed buttons.
I made a little icons. I've made a little icon that has a little hashtag with this purple and
then it has different little logos to tells me which thing it does for Octa-Thorp and I have a button
and Alison, this will make you happy. I have a button that when I press it, it opens the show notes.
Literally, all it does, just show notes there. Instantly one button, 10 out of 10. Yeah, I really
like it. It's good. I've got 40 pounds off eBay because second hand things are good.
I think I told you that, didn't I? Yes. Can you reconfigure one to pop up the show notes and then
put it in the post to Alison? That's something that doesn't make sense to people who are the
three of us, but it is very funny. So we'll be staying in the episode. Thank you, Liz.
Last week listeners, I was recording at my parents' house, which is the first time I've recorded
the podcast away from my desk. So episode 60 was an experiment and no one has written in, say,
John sounds weird. So I think it's an experiment that went relatively well.
Hurrah. Let's move away from boring chat and talk about the cricket. Oh, the cricket. Liz just
made a lack of a face, held up her Kindle, and started reading. My pick this week is cricket.
And the reason for that is that I have not been watching anything or reading anything apart from
Hugo Books because I have been watching and listening to, in particular, the cricket.
I think I was just spending too much time hanging out with people who kept
incessantly talking about the cricket. And they kept going, oh, cricket, and saying cricket is fun
to listen to when you're supposed to be doing other things like working. And I can confirm that
this is true, that cricket is highly optimized as a sport for listening to when you're supposed
to be doing something else. And there's an entire massive infrastructure has been built up around
providing ways for people to experience the cricket without their boss realizing that they're
experiencing the cricket. But in my case, my boss is me. So I can listen to the cricket if I like.
And just to help me along my way, England decided to have a period of 13 consecutive days on which
there was a test match on every day, which was quite exciting. We're still in the middle of that.
Hasn't quite finished yet. However, England did not do very well yesterday. And also it rains a lot
in cricket. Who do you? I will say that's not quite true. Because if you watch the cricket that's in,
for instance, Dubai, it does rain quite a lot less than the cricket that happens in England for some
reason. So I think it might be country specific rather than cricket specific. I feel like the
rain's part of it because part of one of the things you have to take into account when judging your
strategy is that it might rain randomly all the way through or a bit of the time. And that might
affect how you choose to play the game. Fascinating game. Also, it's been very interesting. The last
couple of weeks of cricket have been extremely interesting. Is that enough back cricket? I mean,
Alison, how would you feel if I told you there was a sport where they went for like 21 consecutive
days, they never got rained off and you know, no one wins until the end. They go every day.
And also there's hours of it where nothing happens. Oh, cricket. Liz refers, of course, to the sport
of cycling. I do. Oh, no, no, cycling also very, oh, cycling is great there because
there really is where there's nothing happening because there's lots of things where you can kind
of watch what's going on and the way in which people are gathering and cycling's also good. I
have, I'm definitely up for watching cycling too. I've been watching the Formula E but I'm only
halfway through, so please don't spoil the result for me. You too. I have to deliberately look it up.
So, you know, it's unlikely. And that was the Oxford Thought podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me.
I do need to say one more thing about Andrew Plockkin.
Yep. Which is linked to, because I almost said in the locks bit that my previous
fanzine plotter got a lock this week, which is quite good. It is never too late from somebody
who was working on the archives of the things that they'd done when they were a much younger man
and discovered that Plockkin had written about it once and so he tweeted out about that and
somebody drew it to our attention. But also Andrew Plockkin, of course, I've known for a very long
time because Plockter had an ongoing correspondence with him because of the, initially because of
the similarity of names but also because of some collective interests around gaming and interactive
fiction. Plockkin wrote a great interactive fiction game in which the narrator is unreliable
called Spider and Web and it is bloody amazing. It is so good. He was my favourite
interactive fiction writer when I was into IF. I mean, he is amazing. But just the idea of having a
video game in text where the texture being shown isn't the world that you're seeing is, oh, so good.
If there had been a Hugo Award for Best Video Game in 1998, it might have won.
Technically, interaction fiction is not video games because there's no video in it. It's a
text adventure. But that's one of the reasons why it has to be Best Game Hugo because interactive
fiction is still a vibrant category of gaming in which you could well imagine something might
turn up for the Hugo. I've got a question now. Sorry, we went off of one. Yeah, I'm now also
wondering, like, since Plockter is presumably dormant, maybe to rise again in our hour of need,
but not imminently. Does that mean that any future Plockter lets a comment will get
read down Octothop instead? Probably not. I only did it because the Plockkin stuff came up as well,
so. So that was two Hugo, two Plockter shout outs. I will just confirm that the interactive fiction
referred to would have qualified as a video game under the rules of the Discon 3 video game Hugo.
Find it as games available on personal computers. So, yes. Yeah, what if I have like a
choose-you-run adventure book and I read it kind of as an ebook to then become a video game?
My core argument for why you can't differentiate is because there are many examples of games which
have both a physical form and also being sold as video game form.
And my assertion is, unless you are playing interactive fiction through a device that has no
GUI, you are playing a video game. Okay, so am I the only one of the three of us who has played
quite a lot of interactive fiction through devices without GUI? No, because I had, well,
I don't know. Does it count as a GUI if I could load the menu up on my BBC master?
I played all of my interactive fiction on Windows and Macs PCs.
Yeah, okay. But basically, these games played on computers that did not have GUIs.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod in Com