- Well, do follow up.
We'll mention what Hogg said.
We'll say that Alison got lots of supportive comments
that can't be printed, which sounds filthy.
(laughing)
- It does, yes, but let's do an actual podcast
no more than an hour, 'cause then I need to eat my dinner.
So.
(soft music)
- Hello and welcome to episode two of Octa Thought,
the podcast about science fiction.
I'm John Coxon.
- I'm Alison Scott.
- And I'm Liz Betty.
- We are riding on the heels
of a phenomenally successful episode one.
We have had a letter of comments.
We've actually had a couple of comments.
So Andrew Hogg criticized my metaphor choices.
He said that sticking plasters over hurdles
is not a thing that happens in athletics,
but in my defense, I was always terrible at athletics.
So that may be why.
- Alison, I believe you also got some comments.
- I did, but they were all in a private members
only mailing list, so I cannot repeat them here.
- Yay.
- But they were all very nice.
Everyone was very impressed by the podcast
and was like, do more of that.
It's just what we need in these great times.
- We also had an email of comment from Murray Moore
who told us all about what he's reading,
A Sour Apple Tree by John Blackburn and Bunts,
which is collected columns about baseball,
which sounds very good if you like baseball.
- But not science fiction.
Not science fictional unless baseball
is present in the future, which it may be.
We don't know.
We have not been there.
He also mentioned that we haven't mentioned mailing lists
in our discussion of virtual fandom last episode.
So would either of you like to talk about mailing lists?
- Well, I could talk a bit about fan history
and say that virtual fandom is a bit of an old concept
because fandom was always virtual.
It started as a way for people to keep in touch
with people all over the world
who shared this same weird interest.
What's happened here is that the rest of the world
has caught up with the sort of things that fans do
rather than fans necessarily changing what they do.
So they're all over the world.
They're a pocket of science fiction fans,
keeping in touch in much the ways they always have done.
And a lot of those ways are through emailing lists
where somebody sends an email
and sometimes later somebody else replies
and confusion reigns.
- Confusion does often reign.
- Yes, well, I have a long-standing mailing list
of me and some fan-ish friends.
But actually what's happened is
that the mailing list traffic has dwindled
and being replaced with WhatsApp and Discord.
And in fact, what happened is we keep starting up
WhatsApp channels whenever we're at a convention
in order to coordinate sensible things like eating
and are there any more seats left in room two B
for that interesting panel?
And then we just keep it going
because we kind of enjoy talking to each other.
And in this time more than ever,
so those are all sort of back we activate again
and we also have Discord and so on as well.
So the mailing list is actually dying a little bit,
but I'm not sad because it's been replaced with other things.
- Yeah, and I think I'm on various fan-ish mailing lists.
There is a top secret mailing list full of fan fund winners
and most of that is very good-natured.
That has been a flurry of discussion
in light of recent events,
but we will get to that a bit later in the show.
Liz mentioned Discord and there is also now a BSFA Discord.
If you are a member of the British Science Fiction Association
or if you are not,
but you would like to talk to people who are,
you can join their Discord
and it's reasonably low traffic at the moment.
I don't know what they're planning to do with it,
but I will put a link in the show notes.
Are you on a Discord, Alison?
Have you been doing much Discording?
- I have not been doing much Discording,
but I am on many Discord.
So what I find with Discord is that
I'll be doing something, some activity
and a Discord will pop up around that.
And for a while we will have a flurry in activity
and it will be very useful,
but I'm not using Discord at the moment
for any part of my social life, I don't think.
I do use Slack a bit
when we're talking about things like that
for a group of people who I work with.
So it's not necessarily a science fiction or thing at all.
In fact, not, but that's only a social space,
not really a work space.
We talk about things like how to make money,
which at the moment is, yeah, don't.
- Yeah, we have a Discord and we have morning tea
or afternoon tea for people in the wrong time zones
every morning and that's really nice.
And for me, Slack is mostly a workplace,
so I don't usually check that outside the work day.
How are you finding Discord?
So you, a member of lots of Discords are only a couple.
- I remember only one Discord
because I think I'd previously assumed
it was sort of for gaming mostly,
but actually it's just like IRC,
which was a key part of my social life
in the pre-discord times,
except as much easier to spontaneously
have voice conversations with people.
So I'm really enjoying it, yeah.
And I use Slack only for work.
So it's nice to keep that division of Slack is for work.
Discord is for non-work situation.
- Yeah, I think Discord and Slack
are very similar in some ways.
Discord started as a way of letting gamers do voice chat
and has kind of grown beyond that.
And Slack started as a way to let work colleagues
talk to each other in serious text conversations
and has grown beyond that.
And they have kind of slowly been moving towards the middle
from opposite directions,
which has been quite interesting to watch.
- The other big technology that has been used quite a lot
recently is Zoom.
So Alison, you have ran a first Thursday pub meeting on Zoom.
And I was curious to see what your thoughts about that were
and how it went.
- I think I should start by saying
there are a great many video conferencing options
and Zoom has emerged, I think pretty well everywhere
as having probably the best combination of ease of use
and ability to deliver quality audio and video
over quite small brand width in a lot of cases
for quite a lot of people.
So it's just got the sweet spot of the package.
I looked at, I wanted to run a virtual first Thursday meeting
for people who don't know that London fans
have been meeting on the first Thursday of the month
ever since 1946 in a variety of London pubs.
And we couldn't do it this month.
And so I thought it would be good to have a virtual thing.
And the people in the first Thursday Facebook group
thought that it would be quite a good thing.
So I set about exhaustively testing
every video conference a solution available,
try and find one that would help us do that.
And what I didn't want was something where the 50 or so people
who might turn up on a Thursday night
would all cram into one video conferencing space
and have it go, oh well, I can't have 50 people
all talking at once.
If you actually go to a real pub, you go and sit at tables.
And what happens at the first Thursday
is that people mostly go and sit at the same table
every time.
So there'll be a table that mostly has zed zed
and dyed people on it.
And there'll be a table that mostly has old farts on it.
And there'll be a table for people
who want to talk seriously about science fiction.
There'll be a table for people who want to smough the Eastergum.
And what we were trying to do was recreate some sense of that
in the zoo by using Zoom's breakout rooms
to essentially act as these tables.
And it turns out that video conferencing for business,
they don't think that people are going to want to move around
between the breakout rooms regularly
or dash away from their breakout room
because somebody started to be boring and nip off for a smoke.
Though actually I've been at work conferences
where that has been the case.
So it turned out to be quite complicated to set up
and I did it by getting a paid Zoom account,
making everyone in the meeting co-hosts.
And then after that,
they could move themselves around but to do these rooms.
We had no password.
Our security strategy was,
if anyone tries to do anything naughty, we'd boot them,
which is not the most elaborate security strategy.
And it worked fantastically and everyone had a lot of fun
and we had about 40 people or so
and we had a really good evening,
except mostly my fun was mostly the fun of sorting it all out,
which so it felt more like con-running type fun
rather than sitting around in a pub type fun.
But I have been having a lot of sitting around
in the pub type fun on many video conferencing services.
So I don't want to suggest that I'd be missing out on that.
The only thing I've missed out on is that the hangovers really
and tried to get back from London and the tube
at two o'clock in the morning,
having not entirely worked out what I was doing.
I've missed that.
There's no reason you couldn't recreate the hangover experience
in the comfort of your own home.
It turns out that there's a,
the amount I want to drink on Zoom
seems to be lower than the amount I want to drink in the pub,
which is quite good really.
I mean, we do have beer and it's quite nice
and we've been buying beer from local breweries
and that's good.
It's not quite such a drinking experience.
The beer is vastly better.
We had two notable groups of spies on our chat.
The first was the Yom's Vikings, trying to work out
whether this would be effective for a virtual Yom's thing,
which is a book discussion where traditionally
one person holds the speaking object
and speaks at any time.
And the first Thursday group,
the Vanguard group in Seattle turned up
to see whether they thought they would be able to run
a Seattle meeting using the same technology.
So it's kind of spreading.
- And I think it's worth noting that the Toronto Faddo
also has a first Thursday meeting,
which I think started because people from London
went over to Toronto and introduced it.
So I think it is not an accident that is the same day.
But it's kind of nice to think that there are fans
all over the world who meet on a first Thursday.
One of the reasons I didn't come to the first Thursday
is 'cause I don't usually come to the first Thursday
and I thought going along, if everyone who doesn't usually go
had clicked on the button, I was a bit worried
it would get overwhelmed.
So I did not go.
- In practice, it was fine.
But also one of the things that happened on Thursday
was that we got some people who have been to the first Thursday
from time to time, but because they live in Australia
or Canada or Seattle or wherever,
do not habitually get to it.
And in that included at least one regular
who's just moved to New Zealand.
So obviously it was very nice to see them.
The other group of people who got there
were people who would love to go to the first Thursday
and who are London fans,
but who can't manage the stairs up to that back room.
And so any fans who can't manage stairs,
this is actually enabling for them.
- Do you think you will do it again next month?
- Yeah, well, we'll certainly have some form
of virtual meeting every month
that the pubs are closed, certainly.
- Technically speaking, I believe as we record
that it is two weeks away from the government's proposed
see whether everything has gotten better
and we can relax the restrictions, deadline.
- Yeah, would you like to make a small bet?
- I mean, given how much things changed
in between us recording and the episode going out last week,
I'm very hesitant, but yeah, propose your battleism.
We'll see, we'll see.
- I bet it won't have.
I do not think that the pubs will be open
for some considerable time.
- I think you might be right about that.
- Certainly not May, probably not June.
Let's hope on July.
- Well, I think we might get quicker
than that is small gatherings.
- Yes, well, yes, maybe.
I don't know.
Liz, you're an expert.
- Yes, but there are also lots of other experts
who are more expert than me who've given their opinion on this.
So I will cowardly defer to them.
But also I think when they release the restrictions a bit,
people are going to stay local.
So I think like gatherings where you go and see someone
nearby that you can walk to, maybe things that are
regained earlier than ones where you have to go
and get on public transport and go to a pub
on the other side of London.
So I think it's all going to kind of go in, in waves perhaps.
But it's also, I don't know if they've reopened
sort of restaurants and bars and things in Shanghai
and Wuhan yet.
So that might be an interesting path to look at.
- My understanding is that restaurants and bars
are open in China with some restrictions,
but the cinemas and theatres have not reopened.
They tried to reopen them and then change their minds
particularly, but again, I'm not being following
this in great detail.
So I might just be totally wrong about that.
- I would like to urge our listeners not to take
medical advice from us.
Please look at what the NHS and the government are saying.
We are, but people discussing interesting things.
- What I would say that science fiction all about this
is that if I ever read a science fiction book again,
where society has dramatically changed in the way
that personal interactions work or work works
or things of that kind, unless it gives me a trigger event
for that change to have happened,
I'm just going to say no, no, no,
these things don't happen by gradual change.
It turns out that they are in fact triggered by event.
And what we have seen here is a big old trigger event.
Lots of old people are now doing video chats
because we had a trigger event.
- Yeah, I mean, my grandmother has worked out how to text
which may be the first time that she has successfully done that.
And my parents were already relatively comfortable
with video chatting, so that is not a huge change.
But yeah, I've noticed some changes in behavior.
- I think many people were already comfortable with it
just because of the globalised nature of things
before the trigger event, as to put it.
There are a lot of parents and grandparents
who are not necessarily living in the same country
as their children, their grandchildren,
and they have all learned how to video chat
so they don't miss the important life event.
- Yeah, there are lots of disabled people
who have been asking for the ability to work from home
for many, many years and have been told,
"No, we could not possibly do your very important work from home."
And they have been very angry
that the world has suddenly worked out
that a vast majority of jobs can in fact be done from home
perfectly well.
- Again, it's trigger events, like you're saying.
As much as I think the impetus should have been there earlier
for accessibility reasons, you're right that this is the big push
that people needed to make that actually work.
Last episode, we used to just cancel
and we were discussing the reasons why that might be.
We haven't yet gone into lockdown in the UK.
In the intervening three days, we did in fact
get a lot closer to lockdown.
We were advised to shelter in place
and hotels were advised to shut by the government.
So, Eastacom would have been canceled either way.
It's amazing how much things changed in three days.
In the couple of weeks since the last episode,
Conzeland have announced that they are also not running
as we predicted last episode
and are going to do a virtual convention.
So how do we feel about the idea
of a virtual world con?
- That is one of the issues here,
which is when I pay for a world con,
which is a reasonably expensive proposition
just for the membership.
I'm paying for physical, tangible things,
like because I know that my money is going towards
essentially the rental of a large expensive venue
and all the associated costs with that.
And when you get to a virtual con,
apart from the costs of managing to host it,
which will be probably considerable,
but nothing like as much as hosting a physical venue,
a lot of the work that will go into it
is the work that people were already doing
as volunteers for the world con.
So I think it's going to be very difficult
to try and get a pricing structure that will work.
As for refunds, I don't know how much money
has already been spent and cannot be recouped.
So I can see why they might not be doing refunds,
but I'd be very interested to see
where they pitch the rate for new memberships.
- They have said that they are going to refund
the difference between attending and online memberships
when the price for online membership goes live,
which I think at the time of recording
is supposed to be the 15th of April.
- I am not persuaded yet of the value proposition
of an online world con.
I think that this is a very hard task to manage.
We manage our existing world cons
by having a lot of extremely talented volunteers
who work in areas they always work in,
know how to do those things and make them work.
An example of the sorts of difficulties here
are that a friend of mine having listened to our podcast said,
well, that would be a great model for the world con.
You could record a panel and then do it like that.
And I was like, but John will have put in many hours of editing.
I mean, a thousand hours maybe?
I don't know, many hours of editing on OctaThorp1.
And there's no way that's going to happen
for the hundreds or thousands of panels
that you have to work on.
You know, that volunteer resource just isn't there.
- I was thinking about this.
I mean, I think it could work.
You'd have to treat every panel
as a sort of Zoom style breakout room
where only your panelists are on video and audio
and everyone else is forcibly muted.
And then at the end, you let them selectively
unmute themselves to ask questions.
But you need the person who is normally sitting
at the back of the room fiddling with the levels
on the microphones to be the person who is in that room,
like enforcing that with an iron fist fit to work at all.
- At the last EasterCon, they had a model
where they passed a book around the audience
and people wrote questions in it
that they wanted to ask John Scalzi
who was the guest of honor.
And at the end, they chose questions
from the book and read them.
And I think that had two very big advantages.
It meant that the person who was doing the interview
could scan through and find the next interesting question
while John was answering the previous one.
And it also meant the person scanning through
could look for sentences that had question marks
at the end, which completely brought to an end.
This is more of a comment than a question phenomenon,
which I don't know about YouTube,
but it is my firm opinion, can die and go in the sea.
I don't know if you think that would translate well,
but that's how I would do it if I was going to,
which of course I am not.
- Unlike running a virtual pub meeting,
this is a problem which is very well established
in professional video conferencing uses,
and they do both of those models.
So it's normal for professional video conferencing,
setups to have a number of people who are allowed to speak
and everybody else be auto-muted.
And then I've seen both of those other ways work.
Either you have a text chat that everybody has access to
and people type things in it,
or you have a text chat that everybody has access to,
but only the moderators can read
so they could be reading what's coming in on it,
or you can have a thing where people just click a button
if they want to speak,
and then those people are called on internal.
I've seen all of those systems work.
I've seen the system work where people type their question,
but then the moderator calls all that person to speak.
And so all of those things are fine.
As well as the moderator who's allegedly
the moderator of the panel,
you almost certainly need two more people.
One managing the audio for the panel
in the way that the tech person at the back of the room would,
and one actually managing that text chat
and making sure that any actual bad actors are booted.
So I think it's interesting because the problem is
that the panels are only one part of the experience,
and I cannot see myself sitting at my laptop
for four or six hours a day watching online panels
in the way that at Worldcon
I would actually physically go to those panels.
So I think we've got to take that into account.
I think you're right.
And I think that's one of the things I want to bring up,
which was a criticism I saw on various mailing lists
I'm a member of, which is a real division
between people who wondered to what extent it was not worth
having a virtual Worldcon,
because the social aspect of the Worldcon
is really the primary motivator for them.
And to what extent it's worth putting on a Worldcon,
because obviously having something is better than nothing.
And it's not like there's a mystical option
where we just have the Worldcon anyway,
and we all get exactly what we want.
So it really is a choice between having nothing at all
or having some online offering.
I don't think I would pay as much as I would pay
for a normal attending membership
in order to attend a virtual convention.
But equally, I can see an argument
that it's better to have something on
rather than just completely abandoning it.
- If they run a virtual con,
at what time are they going to do it?
- That's a really good question,
because you don't want to isolate,
you don't want to exclude the local fandom,
but you equally don't want to exclude the US fandom.
I don't know this for sure,
I haven't looked at the membership numbers,
but I strongly suspect the US contingent
was the biggest contingent.
It usually is at any given Worldcon.
And so it's a very, very good question.
- I think in some ways it's not the US,
which is a problem.
So I'm just looking at the Hugo finalist announcement,
which will be on the seventh or the eighth,
depending on your time zone.
And it's starting at 8 a.m. New Zealand time,
which is 9 p.m. in the UK, 4 p.m. on the East Coast
and 1 p.m. on the West Coast.
So you can actually manage to find a time
when I think New Zealand and the US are awake,
but you cannot find a time when New Zealand
and the US and Europe are awake.
And those in between New Zealand and Europe,
I think will just stand up, give it up,
'cause I'm not sure there'll be any time
that suits everyone.
- Somebody has told me that as a result
of everybody's lockdown,
we now have two time zones globally,
which are coffee and beer.
(laughs)
- Yes, I've heard that too.
And it's worryingly true.
- So you're either in coffee time or beer time.
- Yes, that is, I think, a very good point.
I think that is a very good question
of how they're gonna do it.
My guess would be that it will be bad for Europe
and I will not get to attend much of it.
But then again, I was not planning to go to New Zealand
and would not have attended a bunch of it anyway.
So perhaps I am not the person they need to be prioritizing.
- So now I can say something temperate about Guff,
which is that they haven't,
the Guff races due to end next week.
And I was gonna do a big push on,
the Guff races due to end,
please everybody vote for me,
though I can't say that
because I wouldn't dream of being the campaigning type.
But they haven't really said what they're doing.
They've indicated privately that the plan is
that the winner will attend the convention virtually
and take their trip at a later date,
which seems completely fine to me
and I would have thought would be fine
to lots of other people as well.
But it raises that question.
I mean, I'm very happy to attend the convention virtually
in those circumstances,
but I certainly wouldn't be able to attend
in the same way that I would in person.
And it would mean me almost certainly going on tonight's shift
for a week in order to make it work.
And that's kind of slightly weird.
I mean, it's not impossible, but it's slightly weird.
- Obviously, you're in a position where you miss out
on Conziland being the destination World Cup,
which we touched on last episode is a great shame.
I think that rearranging the race for a future time
and having the delegate get enthusiastically virtually
involved is the best solution.
But it is a solution that does have a lot of logistical
questions, as you say, and I'm not sure what the answer
to any of that is.
I am very glad that I am not the administrator
of a fan fund at this time,
because it must be a nightmare for the administrator
to decide what to do.
- But I would like them to decide what to do
because there are sometimes when it's appropriate
to take a decision.
And I think this is an announcement in time for the race
to either be canceled or to finish.
- I suspect the race will not be canceled
because I suspect they will want there to be a delegate
for the virtual convention that occurs,
because not having Duff and Guff candidates
when there is a Australasian World Cup would be a great shame.
And doing it this way means you can at least have some
fan fund candidate involvement in the World Cup
even if it is virtual.
Maybe they'll listen to this and write us a letter.
- Yeah, they don't have a lot of time.
(laughing)
- You get a little bit of time.
- I'll do a faster editing job, it will be fine.
- So the Duff winner has been announced already,
which is Erin Underwood, it's a great choice
for anyone who hasn't heard.
- Fantastic choice.
- Yes.
- And it doesn't say anything about Erin going to Conziland.
It just says that she will try and travel in 2021.
But I assume that is also the goal.
- I submitted my bond and a guarantee
that I would attend the convention if I won.
(laughing)
And travel, it's really weird.
And then of course when all this kicked off,
I went, oh, that's interesting isn't it?
- So you have guaranteed that if you win,
you will stay up all night
virtually attending Conziland.
- Yeah, definitely.
Yeah.
Like I wasn't gonna do that anyway.
These two corners announced that they're going to run
the bidding session for 2021 and 2022.
I was going to be the fangest at concentric,
so I'm gonna be holding a Zoom party.
I don't know if I should say this.
People who are interested in this
should get in touch with me.
If I know you, I'll give you the details.
It's not gonna be super secret.
Because if I was at the convention being fangest of honor,
then one of the things I would do is hold a definitely,
definitely not official room party.
- I think that's a good one.
- And I think you'll find that other people
who might have done things at EasterCon
will be doing those things over next weekend.
But this otherwise, what are we gonna do?
Like, I don't know, what do people do at Easter?
Is that not at the EasterCon?
- This is a hashtag privilege problems.
But because I am an academic,
I get two extra days off around the Easter weekend.
So I've got six days of not having anything to do.
And it's just, oh, it's gonna be tricky
with how EasterCon there to kind of fill up with stuff.
I think doing a Zoom thing or something
is a really good idea.
And I also think that having it so that it's only people
who would have been there anyway is a good idea too.
I really don't want to suggest that only people
who go to the EasterCon could come to my party.
But I think I am going to suggest that only people
who know me can come to my party.
I don't think that's unreasonable.
- That's good, 'cause then I can come to your party.
So I approve.
- You definitely can come to my party.
Yes, you two are both invited.
- Liz, you would fall under both criteria
because you currently have an EasterCon attending membership.
- I do, but that's because it got to the point
where I was trying to sell it
and then I realized it was going to be canceled.
And I felt that I was selling someone a membership
but then they would be on the hook.
- How many hours ahead of us are you, Liz?
- So this is the problem.
I am currently six hours ahead of you,
which means while I would very much like to come to your party,
it will be like the early hours of the morning for me.
It will be the early hours of the morning.
I mean, I suspect that the drinks of the party
will just be as you're getting up.
- It's that time that I cannot get to
from either end, basically.
I cannot stay up late enough, I get up early enough.
- As yet, the only thing the EasterCon committee
have announced they are doing over the Easter weekend
virtually is the bid session,
which probably means that there's not going
to be much programming happening.
So to what extent do you think British fandom
are going to do any programming sort of as a grassroots effort?
Do you think that there will be lots of room parties popping up?
Or do you think that it will be very ad hoc
and we'll see Facebook posts at the time?
- I mean, I've announced I'm doing something but I,
and part of why I did that was to encourage the others.
So I'm doing a thing and there's a bit of accession
that I was trying to hope by saying,
"I'm doing a thing," then we might see some virtual book launches
or virtual author readings or things of that kind
because I think that would be quite fun.
- There's a lot of virtual author readings going on right now.
Anyway, I see quite a lot of them pop up on Twitter and Facebook.
But I wonder if part of it is also that the committee
have been understandably quiet,
but if I was organizing things,
I might not want to jump in enthusiastically
in case they were still planning something.
And as it gets later and later,
then becomes even less likely that anyone will jump in
enthusiastically.
So that might be part of it.
- Last week, we talked about giving the Quitty Space
and letting them work out what they wanted to do
and not having a big discussion either way.
But now, given that it's a week until Easter,
as we record, if they were planning to do something,
I think they would have announced it at this point.
And I think that it's completely legit that they don't want to
because I think it is a very different thing.
And they must be completely gutted
that they can't run the convention they were planning.
But I think at this point, it may be time
to start trying to get the ball rolling
on organizing some grassroots stuff.
And I think Alison's impetus to do that is a good one.
And I've got some ideas about things we could do.
We could do a live podcast recording.
- It's only been a week.
Would it be okay to have a third octave thought?
- Yeah, why not?
- In only a week after the second.
We don't give the impression this is going to become a habit.
(laughs)
- No, we could do.
We could have an octave thought Zoom party.
That could work exclusive.
We each get two plus ones or one plus two,
depending on how that works.
I'm hoping that there will be stuff happening next weekend.
There was something that happened this weekend.
Yesterday was Wi-Fi sci-fi.
Did either of you hear about Wi-Fi sci-fi?
- I did not.
Tell me about Wi-Fi sci-fi John.
- So I saw this on Glen Morgan's Twitter feed.
I saw it after it had happened
because that is how all the best parties get heard about.
You hear about them after they've finished.
But it was a Zoom convention which starred various luminaries.
It had Gareth Powell, Ezra Walker, Michael Carey,
Tarda Thompson, Ann Corlott, Patrick Edwards,
Jonathan Piddock, Allie DeBodard, Kim, Lake and Smith,
Michael Rowley, Kevin Henny, Anna Chapman, Dave Hutchinson,
Derek Kuntzken and Premier Mohammed.
But it had two paddles.
It had cafe clutches and it had a quiz.
And it, I believe the two panels are on YouTube
for people who couldn't make it to the Zoom
because the Zoom was 90 people
and there were more than 90 people interested.
I believe you can go and watch both of those on YouTube.
It looked like it was quite good.
The tweets I saw about it seemed to be people
having a good time.
I'm a little bit annoyed.
I didn't hear about it when it was happening
as opposed to hearing about it the day after.
But I think that's often the way with a convention
you see people tweeting while they were at the convention
and you did not see the marketing
push leading up to the convention,
which is distressingly common.
But it sounds like a really good idea.
I think two panels for a one day convention
virtually is probably about the right number
'cause I think Liz's point about
not being able to sit for six hours in panels
is probably right.
I think something like that next weekend,
if anyone puts it together,
I would enthusiastically get involved with.
- It is interesting that I think everyone you listed
who was on those panels was a science fiction author.
One of the things I do like about EasterCon
is it tends to have fans and scientists
and historians and people with non-writing expertise
on the panel as well.
So it'd be nice if we could put together something
that included all of those people.
- I agree.
- I'd obviously agree with that.
- We've been talking a lot about video conferencing software
and I think that a lot has been done over the last few weeks
to really advance fandom's engagement with these tools.
Zoom has come under fire over the last week or so
for various bits of bad practice to do with privacy.
I don't want to give the impression here
that I don't think people should use Zoom.
Zoom is an incredible piece of software
that's really helping people keep their mental health
and their communication lines open at the moment.
And I think that is fantastic.
I do think it's worth being aware
of some of Zoom's potential pitfalls
and protecting yourself against them
if it's something you mind.
And if it's not something you mind, obviously go wild.
But recently there have been a few bits of controversy,
notably they had some Facebook data
in their iOS app that was sending data back to Facebook.
They had said that their chats were end to end encrypted
but it turned out that their encryption is not end to end
and is in fact based on a slightly different encryption method
to the method that they had said they used.
Their Mac OS installer abuses pre-install scripts
to install itself without letting you see
what's it going to install.
And a few months ago, I think actually maybe a year ago,
they had installed a local web server
on every Mac they installed on
which let them reinstall their app even
after you've done installed it.
It is worth saying that they have published a blog post
in the last few days that outline a 90 day plan
to address a lot of these privacy concerns
and that they are working very hard to address them.
And I appreciate those points got more and more technical
and less and less understandable as time goes on.
I will put links in the show notes.
And as I say, I want to emphasize that I am advising
people be careful rather than stop using it altogether.
But both of you, to what extent do you think
this is a thing we need to be super concerned about
and to what extent do you think that this is something
that we just need to be mindful of?
- I think that a lot of the people who are making
the most noise about Zoom use either A, Facebook or B,
emailing lists, both of which are notably less secure
than Zoom.
So they started, they assumed they're clearly a bunch
of wide boys, honestly.
They started this company, they made a good product,
they did not care about privacy,
they clearly failed in three different areas.
The first is that they have a load of kind of corporate
spying stuff so that your boss can spy on you,
which is I think fairly normal for corporate software.
They didn't care in the sense that other people's
security things, they just kind of worked around
if that way they got to make a better product.
So they basically went, ah-ha, can we make a better product
by entering operating systems by the back door?
Yes, we can, we should do that.
And the third is they left great gaping holes
in their security accidentally
while they were busy trying to make a better product.
They ended up with a better product
and now they're going, okay, so clearly everyone's
using our product 'cause it's better,
we should probably go back and fix those holes
we left in it, which I think is fair.
It's not the best way to behave, but it is better.
It is noticeably better for any video chat over eight people
and it's probably better for most of the ones under that,
except possibly Microsoft's E.
People think Microsoft seems very good,
but everything else is definitely worse.
- I will agree with you, I think that they have clearly
made a good product and now they are fixing it.
I think part of the reason they are fixing it
is because there has been so much criticism.
So I do think, I do think strong.
- Absolutely, absolutely, they wouldn't be fixing it
because they weren't forced to.
- Yeah, I think strong criticism is an important part of that
and that is the spirit in which I criticize.
- So I've been using Zoom for ages
because it just worked better than all the alternatives.
So I mean, I do a lot of video conferencing anyway
and I do a lot of video conferencing
with people who have pretty terrible internet connections
and Zoom was noticeably better than any of the alternatives
for that, it was better than WebEx,
it was better than Google Hangouts,
it was better than Skype, I mean,
we didn't try running workshops on Facebook Messenger
but I suspect it's better than that.
- Oh God, Facebook Messenger's awful, oh my God.
- So I'm quite, I think I feel I'm quite relaxed about it
in that I know it does some terrible things
but I sort of assume all software is doing
some terrible things unless I'm using one of the real
like good open source ones that have been built
from the ground up for that kind of thing.
So I'm glad people are aware of these things,
I'm glad people are pointing them out
and that they fix them, but otherwise I'm not too,
I'll end up about it.
I should say I do use Microsoft Teams a lot now
because all our work,
all our work, well everything basically
is moved to Office 365
and Microsoft Teams just works really nicely
and it just works a lot of the time.
We haven't run a really huge event in it yet
but we are swapping our weekly seminars to Microsoft Teams
and they will be, you know,
we sometimes have got up to 100 people in there
so I'll see how that works.
- It's very corporate.
I want to say two things of reaction to that.
I'm gonna push back slightly on the thing you said
about every software doing this.
I think Zoom is more egregious than most so far.
I think the point about Facebook is a reasonable one.
Facebook are obviously in some ways much more egregious
than almost anyone else.
But at this point, my neighborhood community group is on,
Facebook, my streets WhatsApp group is obviously hosted
on a Facebook owned service,
all of the local shops put their opening times
and announcements on Facebook.
So at this point, I must use Facebook to take part
in my community, which is something I resent hugely
but does appear to be distressingly true.
I will say Microsoft Teams is very good.
I think that the problem there is obviously you need
an Office 365 subscription, which not everyone has.
I don't think Microsoft have made any overtures
towards making Teams free to use.
I suspect because they see Skype as their consumer
chatting tool and they don't see Microsoft Teams
as something they need to open up.
Whereas Zoom, I believe, have relaxed a lot of their
restrictions in light of the coronavirus pandemic.
Ooh, Alison is shaking her head.
Teams doesn't have a free tier,
but only the host needs to have the paid account.
I think that's the important thing.
And Office 365 is not expensive,
if there's just one of you and you're using it
for this sort of thing.
People kept saying with the Zoom account,
because I got paid Zoom account to do the first Thursday,
"Oh, do you want some help with the cost?"
And I said, "Well, compared to getting a tube ticket
"to the pub and buying one pint of beer,"
it was there, that was the amount.
So these tools are not expensive compared to the life
we've just given up to get them.
- So yeah, that is my crumble.
- And also, nobody cares about your video chats
and the pub isn't exactly a secure environment either.
I don't think the cabinet should be using Zoom.
I did think that was a bit shocking
and no doubt they've done magic cabinet things,
but seeing as they don't for anything else,
it doesn't seem very likely that they really absolutely see.
- Well, that's one other thing,
which is because Zoom uses a predictable naming scheme
for archives of the chats,
the Washington Post was able to reverse engineer it,
see stuff like therapy sessions
and things that had been conducted over Zoom.
And so I do think that there are problems here
that do need addressing,
but I entirely take the point,
especially for the first Thursday,
it sounded like it was by far the best tool for the job.
But I do think you've just got to be careful
and just be aware and I will post links in the show notes
to help you do that.
Let's do a short staying sane in the apocalypse bit
to round out the show and then we can go back
to having nothing to do.
- I was going to call you out for your privilege
on six days over Easter and talk about having nothing to do
because a lot of people I know are actually losing
their jobs now, that their businesses kept them on
for a little while, but the workers now dried up,
the cash flow isn't there and they've had to let people go
rather than fall over.
So people are losing their jobs and that is very sad
and it's happening quite a lot.
And by quite a lot, if you look at there's a map
for the United States where the spike
in the unemployment rate is something like 10 times
the largest unemployment spike in the last 50 years.
So that's a big thing.
I have had to give up my business for the time being.
I mean, it will come back and all will be well.
But all of my income was dried up because the print
on the other side, I've basically stopped shipping T-shirts
now and I decided I couldn't run a next store at a point
where we were likely to get fit quite soon
and people kept asking me where their stuff was.
I did have a 24-hour period when I'd finally got my
much delayed shipment from China and sent all my old pins
and sent some new pins and then I decided
no, it's time to shut up with it.
But I'm fine.
People should not be worried about me,
but people should be worried about all of the people
who have no income and their savings,
of whom they're owed greatly.
- Yeah, and that's why I say I'm privileged.
I think I am still employed and my job does not require me
to go anywhere.
So I think I am incredibly lucky that that is the case
and I don't want anyone to think that I'm unaware of that
'cause I am, I am very aware of that.
- You also mentioned post and I have been getting things
posted to my house and a few of them have taken a long time
but I did order something at 12pm on Friday
and it was delivered at 12pm on Saturday last weekend
which I was a little bit confused by
'cause I thought the post was taking longer
and that one just seemed to sail through
and I'm not entirely sure why.
- I'm not really ordering a lot to the actual postal service
because I don't tend to post mediators or things like that
but also because Thailand has a thriving system
of motorbike delivery guys and messenger guys.
So for instance, I ordered some gin at about, I think,
4pm on Thursday and about 5pm a man on a motorbike
turned up with my gin, it's pretty good.
- We ordered some beer from Wildcard Brewery,
a link is in the show notes,
who are one of the breweries from the corner from us
and they delivered it just within a few hours
of us ordering it but that was not postal,
that was indeed a bloke from the brewery in a van.
- Yes, we get veg boxes, we've had veg boxes delivered,
ever since we've lived in this house,
they have had to stop taking new customers
because they are so in demand now
but we are getting all our vegetables delivered once week
and we ordered some coffee off the internet
and a man from the roaster came round
and dropped the coffee off, we ordered beer
and that was bulderingly actually posted from the warehouse
which is a 20 minute walk from our house
but that also arrived and we have been getting takeaway
more than usual in a sort of effort
to support our local restaurants
and that has been again very efficient.
So we are finding that it is easy
to get things brought to us which is nice.
- The thing I found most stressful,
not in the first week but as things went on
was not being able to get an almond croissant or a flat white
and we, after some considerable failure
to find anyone who would deliver,
we did in fact find someone to deliver these things
to us yesterday for vast amounts of money
but I was very happy.
- There is a bakery called Hochsten,
the bake house in Southampton that do sourdough bread
and lovely pastries and they are still delivery also
so we have been fine on the pastry front.
- I also have a local bakery that I frequent quite often
and since they are open and don't normally do deliveries
and so they're trying to very hard to pivot
to delivery right now, I have been there a couple of times
to do a sort of arms length by a croissant
on my daily exercise walk which is very nice.
And most of the coffee shops will basically send me
an ice coffee on a motorbike if I wanted it
but I have not yet reached that point.
- That is fair.
We are still allowed out here for exercise once a day
so I've been taking advantage of that
to thoroughly explore the streets near my house.
Alison have you still been going outside regularly?
Are you still driving to a nearby park or are you?
- No, no, no, we've not driven.
In fact, I have to, although it's not one of the approved
reasons to go out, I am going to send Stephen in the car
for a little drive because we have a car that really will,
the battery will pack in if we don't drive it
once in a couple of weeks.
So we're just going to go for a drive
and we'll say we're caring for somebody if our if stop.
I feel like I have elderly relatives
and having a functional car is quite important to us
and it keeps breaking down.
- Oh no, yeah, it sounds good.
- But otherwise, I haven't been out very much.
We have a garden, our garden is more,
it's not really, I think garden is too strong a word.
We have a patch of scrub land attached
to the back of our house and so that's quite nice.
I mean, just a little one, but it turned out that
if you'd elect a garden consistently for 20 years,
it looks quite neglected.
So we've been out there a bit.
Stephen has been teaching me Tai Chi in the sunshine
and he says, let's do a warmup
and then about five minutes later,
I'm like, I've done it off now.
- That's fair.
Liz, are you staying healthy?
- So I haven't been going out for too many walks,
partly because I live in a very built up area
with pretty narrow pavements.
So it's quite hard to do any kind of distancing
if you run into anyone.
It's also April, which is the hottest month of the year.
And so that's also an attempt to going for a nice walk
because it might be 36 degrees outside.
I have been carrying on though
with my doing aerobics in front of YouTube plan.
To a point where I have now found a channel
which will do me a six week exercise plan
and we'll see if I can do six weeks
of indoor YouTube aerobics without going around the bend.
- That sounds good.
- So we haven't discussed books or TV or video games
or anything like that, but we are at the point in time
where we have probably talked for enough this week.
So we will get to that next week.
So that was episode two of the OctaThought podcast.
As always, if you have any thoughts, comments, criticisms,
wafflings or other things you'd like to tell us,
please give us an email at octathoughtcast@gmail.com
or tweet with the hashtag octathoughtcast
and we will mention tweets and emails on future episodes.
But for now, it's goodbye from me.
- And goodbye from me.
- The music used in this episode was fanfare for space
by Kevin MacLeod@incompetech.com,
licensed under a Creative Commons BY 3.0 license.
(upbeat music)