Yeah, I think this whole thing is about not funny digression and we should just like move on.
I mean, I wasn't listening, so that's who speak.
That's a pre episode thing, isn't it?
Hello, everyone, and welcome to the 23rd episode of Octa Thorpe, a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And we have letters of comment this week from two old suspects, no familiar suspects, no old familiar people.
And we also have one from a new suspect.
I believe that also our letters of comments are going to be incorporated into also corrections corner.
Thank you to our commenters for pointing out several things we got wrong in the last podcast.
Yes, so we'll start with Chris Garcia, who points out that Alison was wrong about Monument Valley and it is in fact, fantastic.
So thank you for that.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, Chris. Okay, did he say why? Should I read this? He says, he says, he says my son John Paul is exceptionally good at it, much better at it than using the potty.
So, Alison, I think we can safely declare that it's a great game.
Well, I mean, I didn't realize that the better at using the potty was the criterion because that changes everything.
I think I'd be quite bad at using the potty because I imagine most of them are designed for asses that are smaller than mine.
This is a disturbing digression.
So he also says that I am exactly right about gloom haven. So this is my favorite letter of comment.
Actually, it's not. And I got in trouble on a discord for saying something else with my favorite of comment.
So obviously, my favorite letter of comment is always Claire's.
I would like to call out from Chris's letter that he says to him.
Haven is completely average in a fairly average way, which is just my favorite phrase this week.
He also pointed out that we forgot completely to mention the last of us part two as a candidate for best games.
Hugo, this is probably because I am currently stuck somewhere in the middle of the last of us part one with not enough ammo and I've given up.
So he also says that he doesn't think animal crossings new horizons will win.
He's wrong, but who knows whether we'll even have a hugus already at any rate.
Spoilers for layers, spoilers for later listener and posted on her Twitter because and we will link to this in the show notes.
She got a notification from her podcast app in which it said, Oh, 22.
I sometimes bum and and she had questions and we would like to apologize to and for the title of last episode and the unfortunate way it was cut off by her podcast app of choice.
Is that really something we need to apologize for?
Well, apologizing for it.
Let's just put it in in a way that isn't just her bum.
Yeah, bum.
Bums are funny.
We're bum.
OK, yeah, fair enough.
Name of the name of the podcast.
Possibly.
OK, and then we have our letters of comment from Mark and Claire from Croydon.
Mark says it's probably a little late in the season to express the sentiment in this way, but oh, no, we won't be checking the hugos this year.
That is.
So yes, we were incorrect.
Mark and Claire have done it in previous years, but are not doing it for 2021 and therefore presumably haven't been able to resign.
But again, spoilers for later.
And Mark also says that he has joined Eastcom as a virtual member, but that is a lot because he always goes to Eastcom.
And that Trump's his sense of, but what's the value proposition, which I think I think to a large extent is also why I joined like immediately because I always join immediately because he's gone.
He also says we were wondering whether or not they had edited the announcement and he says that he knows that it said on the 11th of October that it said what it says now because he had caused quote from it.
And so the text hasn't changed.
And I think that speaks to the ease with which it is possible to communicate something in plain English that then you do not communicate in a way that people actually hear properly.
And I think a lot of us in the community were hearing Eastcom saying they didn't have a lot of virtual plans.
And that does seem to run counter to the stuff they were like they wrote in this statement, but it definitely wasn't the impression we were getting in the community.
And I think that might be a topic we can touch upon later.
For reasons connected to other conventions.
A lot of foreshadowing this week.
Yes, we're good at it, Liz.
Yeah, Mark also gives us some clarification about about accounts.
It may be that we're the only people who are hung up about Eastcom accounts or convention accounts generally because.
Claire and Mark were the only people who mentioned it and we already know they're very interested in it and we are very interested in it.
That may mean that our audience generally isn't that interested in it, but I still think it's super important stuff.
All conventions should publish accounts into course.
I'm sure punctuation will any minute now.
We're actually still getting money in for punctuation, which I don't entirely understand.
It's because stripe keeps like some percentage of your money for two months or something in case.
Something bad happens.
And so basically we had, I think, about two thirds of the money we had made from memberships available to us at the time we ran the convention.
And now we are getting the rest of the money.
OK, that explains it.
So so we should probably be able to finalize the accounts in the next month, I think realistically.
But I think the other thing I want to say is this is also one of the reasons why it's not possible to run this sort of event at cost.
You have to run it above cost and then plan to donate.
Oh, we may have to take this offline because I hugely disagree with that statement.
So that's part of why we have passed along funds though, for long standing things.
We don't have any for punctuation, but we could perfectly well have run punctuation by running into debt and then having the money following later.
That is not the reason you can't budget at cost.
I think that but it is a reason you can't write like if you don't have a credit card.
But there are for example, the League of Fan Funds will give you money to cover that sort of thing.
As an example of the way that you could cover it, there are ways in which you can manage not having all of the funds you need come in fast enough,
including using a payment service that does give you the money and time to run the event which do exist.
They just take more of a cut.
So there are several ways in which you can handle it.
That aren't just plan to make a profit.
OK.
I think this does all tie into publication of the EasterCon accounts because we may say we're the only,
you know, none of our listeners apart from our shareholders letters indicating strong preferences for it.
But if I was coming into fandom and I wanted to try running an EasterCon,
then one, it would be very important for me to know the financial state of kind of the EasterCon pass along and how we've been doing over the past few years
and to know what people have been budgeting for different areas of the con,
otherwise it's very hard to know that.
And also you say there are organisations like the League of Fan Funds that will help you,
you know, if you need a float to be repaid later because of payment terms.
But you also need to know that you can go and contact the League of Fan Funds and they would be happy to do that,
which you might not necessarily know.
Well, they might or might not be happy to do that.
But I think at this point, if somebody asked the League of Fan Funds for a float,
we would be going, oh, yeah, that sounds like a plan.
Yeah, I'm not committing into anything, but just organisations,
which will do stuff like that, you have to know they exist and might be able to help you before you can go to them.
So the more public account information, the better.
As chair of the 2018 EasterCon, it feels like it's time.
I will get in touch with my treasurer and say, what is now stopping us from publishing our accounts
and see if we can't get that sorted by, say, Easter.
That's a public statement.
Oh, you heard it here first, folks.
Dolly, the treasurer did so.
Probably did also tell the treasurer.
I know that the treasurer knew that we had an intention to get it done in a year.
So, you know, I think while I agree with Alison's core point that you can charge your members less money
if other organisations give you money, I am not sure that raises my core point of this stuff's difficult.
That sigh was beautiful.
John's do you ringtone?
Yes.
I'm being I'm being facetious, obviously.
It is certainly I am not prepared to concede the general point that when starting up a convention for the first time,
you need to have a plan to soak your members.
There are, you know, that is one way in which you can you can cope with the fact that starting up a convention for the first time
is is a risky affair.
I would say that I think that punctuation made a larger profit as a proportion of membership than any project
I've ever been involved on in my life.
And I'm only very slightly embarrassed about that because it was only a fiver.
Yes.
Anyway, we have digressed and we have I mean, shockingly,
although to be fair, we digressed onto a non-topic topic.
I think it's also important to publish accounts because that way, if you're later going to make arguments
that some things you might want to do are too expensive, you've got the evidence right there in his in historical accounts
to support that argument.
Ah, true.
It's more foreshadowing, isn't it?
It's more foreshadowing. That's true.
So we're on to Claire's letter.
Claire writes to say, yes, that is true.
Any type of infutur messages from me are, of course, deliberate mistakes designed to catch you out.
Although I'd always intended that multiple grammatical and punctuation areas would be the way I'd indicate that I was being made
very under duress.
So maybe it's not such a good plan.
So just to reassure you, then, if there are any mistakes in this email, there are either tests or hilarious jokes and not a sign I'm changed to a radiator.
Claire, if you're being held under duress, please ask your captors to send us your customary video letter of comment.
Claire also reiterates what Mark said about not being in on the Hugo checking this year and also wrote to us about the value of publishing these two con accounts.
She also says that she needs to point out a misspelling of Karen Schafer's surname because we referred to Karen and her partner Mike in last episode as Karen Ward and Mike Schafer,
instead of referring to them as Karen Schafer and Mike Ward, which at least it is clear that we are not instruments of the patriarchy, but it is also clear.
We're daft.
So thank you very much for pointing that out, Claire.
We could we could we could avoid this problem by not making any mistakes next time.
We're very sorry and we will never make any mistakes ever again.
On the subject of never making any mistakes ever again.
All fandom was plunged into war.
What happened was as far as I can reconstruct this is a disc on three who are the 2021 Worldcon announcing new policy for Hugo finalists, which would be that they would announce all the names as part of the souvenir book and program and on the website.
And they would all get pins and ribbons, but when we actually list the final nominees on the ballot and you know on the PowerPoint at the Hugo ceremony and on the trophy blacks, they would only list up to four names.
And this made quite a lot of people quite annoyed.
This is because there are you know a large number of nominees for the Hugo's, especially in the fanzine and semi-prozine and bandcast categories, where increasingly more than four people have been listed as
creators of the works in question and why I think this gone through meant to say more prominently yes and we're going to list all these names in the souvenir book and in the program and on the website.
What they actually said was when the PowerPoint comes up with your name as a nominee, we're only going to list four of you.
And when you get invites to parties and so on, we'll only list four of you.
And so this made a lot of the larger teams quite annoyed and and we'll just we'll discuss why this got made these changes and whether we agree with them in a minute.
But it may quite have been quite annoyed, especially ones who pointed out that you know they were really very proud of having won the Hugo award and would not have been listed if this policy was in effect in their years.
Also pointing out there are a lot of minority creators who are involved with these these particular categories who would not have been listed on the in the finalist if this policy was in place.
This policy stayed in place for approximately 24 hours at which point this gone through apologized listed all the steps they were going to take to address the problems that they have caused and apologize that people for speaking out about it.
And I think it seemed like that was that at least for a few days.
It did.
But maybe before we continue, maybe we should discuss a little bit this policy that this can had and why we think we had this policy and whether we think this policy was a good idea or not.
Reading the tweets from this con, I think it calls to mind the thing we discussed a little while ago in the letters of comment, which is the things that they say and the focus of the ensuing discussion were it was very clear that people were discussing the feeling they got from what
this con has said rather than the sort of nuts and bolts.
And that is to say that like this gone are very clear in their announcement that all creators named to the convention as part of a here at finalists will be listed in the book, the serving program and on the websites and would receive a pin and a ribbon.
They specifically say that they will only list up to four names for each finalist on the paper ballot on the ceremony visuals and on the trophy plaque and they conspicuously do not mention whether every finalist will get a trophy.
And I think if they meant that not every finalist would get a trophy, then that is something where I can understand why the conversation that ensued really did focus on the kind of people who had won trophies in the years they were nominated to would be excluded by this policy.
And I think if they did not mean to indicate that only four people would be allowed to have trophies, then this was an enormous own goal of communication that they should have anticipated.
I will say that I have been nominated for Hugo's under the team journey planet banner.
I've edited three journey planets to on Star Wars and one on the matrix.
I really like editing journey planet and it gives me access to a community of writers and editors and a kind of a well to tap that I would not be able to access.
Otherwise, especially with James Bacon's sources in the Irish comic industry and Chris's contacts in kind of California and Hollywood.
And I think that in the years when I have been nominated, I have either been eligible to get a rocket or I have been eligible to pay a search charge for a rocket.
So I think it was Dublin, but it might have been San Jose who basically said we're going to make up to five rockets per listed finalist and anyone kind of in excess of that number.
Like, we're quite happy to, you know, let you pay us to make more rockets if you'd like more than that for your group.
And I'm not sure kind of where in that spectrum, Discon 3 was.
But yeah, I think, I think they really did need to, I think, make it clearer.
If this was literally just, we can't list 26 people on this very small bit of text.
They really need to make it clearer that that was the main drive.
And if that isn't the main drive, I think they needed perhaps to say that and to open a dialogue about that that wasn't, we have decided this thing.
But perhaps other people on the podcast disagree with me.
I think I do disagree somewhat.
So back in the midst of time, there was only one rocket.
And I think what's one of the things that's happening here is that we've got people are talking as if fans have just invented the idea of large team efforts and
collaborations. And it's just not true.
We give Hugo's for movies, which obviously have many thousands of people working on them because that's what it takes.
But even a novel, it's well understood, I think, that when you give an author a best novel Hugo, that's a huge collaboration that involves a lot of work from a lot of people, not least of which is their editor.
We've actually talked in the past about surfacing who's editing, who's editing the things that are winning awards.
But it could also involve a translator.
It certainly involves artists and publishers and copy editors and all manner of things.
And the notion that just because you have somebody's name on something, it doesn't mean it's a joint effort, or that somehow diminishes the joint effort.
I don't, I just feel like we're kind of going, oh, well, it's if you've got a team of, and if you have a team of 40 people, we should be celebrating all 40 of those equally.
That that's not the way it works.
I mean, so originally they gave out a rocket and that might have been an individual thing or it might have been a, it certainly involved in all the one person.
I don't think there's anything.
Maybe, maybe some fanzines are in fact the entire work of one person, but almost everything on there is going to be more than that.
And later they had some things that were jointly written and they started dishing out too.
I feel slightly guilty of this because I think Plochton may have been the first time they, they gave out three.
But at the point where Plochton won the Hugo, we were actually an editor, a collaboration of nine people.
And I do think, but it was clear that the people who drove the existence of the fanzine had generated all of, all of the work that we done there.
Although we had a lot of people working for it, it was primarily the three editors and that, and we are the ones who went up on stage and got to the rocket.
That doesn't in any way diminish the contribution that the other people involved made to the fanzine, which was very large.
And I feel like I don't really believe in this is a large team of a vast number of people, all of whom have equal weight.
I think that they're normally one or two or maybe three people who drive a project.
And we should be able to, we should be able to actually not have a thing where we go, oh, we're going to read out a list of 45 names for this nominee because they've decided that they're all of equal weight.
So I'm kind of, I feel that it should have done a much better job of because obviously announcing the policy by fiat and not giving the community a chance to talk about what, whether we actually have a collective understanding of what it should be.
Was not a very good way to go about it, but I think that you have a point.
I would like to see, I would like to see that point discuss some subtly, which it may never be now.
So I would say I can see that you might need to draw a line somewhere. I think if you have, I think if you had 50 names, then that is a lot to read out and a lot to have on the screen and a lot of people to potentially be rewarded.
But I think the kind of way of saying, well, you'll all be listed in the book, but then when it gets sexual ceremony and the ballot that I'll be for of you is setting it way too low.
And so one of my, one of my thoughts about this is I actually went back and looked at previous years to see how many people were listed. And I know this is imperfect because we know, we know informally that there's been a limit on this in the past and Chris Garcia has talked about this for journey planet.
There are more teams being listed who would cross that four person barrier, but it's actually not entirely, I thought it would almost entirely be in sort of semi-proseen and maybe fanzine.
But actually it catches some other categories as well because it catches the podcast that were in best related work when it was writing excuses, but it also catches some sort of things like comics which have five listed creators.
And if you have the writer of a comic, a penciling team, an incur and a colorist, and that adds up to five people, which ones you knock off to get you down to four.
And similarly with things like we say we don't list everyone for TV and movies, but actually we tend to list all the writers and the directors.
And so for instance, when they listed Captain America the Winter Soldier, that has officially three writers and two directors.
So you end up catching things that I'm not sure they're intending to catch by setting off at four.
I would be quite happy for them to say actually we're going to set your cut off at 12 or you're going to set the cut off at 20 and see how we go.
I don't really see the problem in listing people's names and we can see that even if you are in name a finalist and you're sat in the audience, but then the big sort of PowerPoint screen comes up and it only lifts up.
It's for people from your project and not you.
And then your project wins and you can't go up and take part in that and celebrate that.
Then it just seems sort of a change where I can kind of see the arguments behind making it, but I'm not sure it really gains them more than they are losing.
I think something that I would say, which is Alison mentioned, you know, movies have like large number of people and like books kind of have more than more than just the author.
Contributing and I think that's true.
And I think, but I think that the key here is to recognize the people who have the editorial on maybe not many editorials.
The wrong word, but people who have the creative control.
And I think the problem is that like in a movie, it's very clear that like the director and maybe like if a producer is very, very active, then they have the creative control over that project.
And like in a book, I think I would, I think I would argue that it is the editor and the author that have creative control and people who've listened to the podcast in the past will know that I have been kind of wondering for a while now why editors aren't recognized when fiction is awarded to you goes.
But I think for projects like, for instance, on Canney magazine or for projects like like Joni Planet, I think that one of the things that we are seeing is that these projects are not only in the world.
Are resulting in larger teams of people who have overall creative control.
So like in the case of Joni Planet, like Chris and James, kind of contact guest editors who they want to do the work, but it is project that is made by many different editors.
And I think without those editors exercising their creative control, the project would be very different.
And so I think even if you peg it as, you know, reward the people who did have that control and who helped shape the creative output of the nominated work, that number is getting bigger.
And that might, it might not be that that's because of kind of technological advances.
It might just be that like people are getting more inclusive in the community.
And this is a way to bring marginalized people in and to uplift them.
If you're a kind of white creator who has a platform, you can bring marginalized people and kind of give them creative control.
And in doing that, you're uplifting marginalized groups in a way that's really positive.
And so maybe that's why it's happening.
But I do think that you can see the disease happening.
And I think ultimately like, you know, I'm not saying that all of the people who do any work on a movie like that you see at the end of the credits should win a Hugo if the movie wins.
Like because that would clearly be silly, but I think that it is different to then say, well, I look at the list of six people on the uncanny magazine profile who usually win rockets.
And it's the editors in chief.
It's the managing editor, the nonfiction editor and the two people who produced the podcast.
And it's like, that seems fine.
And arbitrary, really saying, well, the podcast doesn't deserve recognition or or the nonfiction editing doesn't serve recognition.
I find it, I find it unconvincing that any of those six people do not have some level of meaningful,
creative control over that project that is part of the reason why it wins the award.
I think it would be interesting to have a discussion about the policy and the community and not merely about the flounce.
But I feel like we should go on to talk about the fallout, which is perhaps more interesting because even if this was a good policy, which I think we've said,
four, four seems like a rather arbitrary number announcing things by just kind of announcing them as a done deal seems slightly odd,
especially when it's anything to do with the hugos.
But also it seems to be clear from what we do know about the fallout that the policy was implemented by the board over the objections of the Wussfuss division.
And that does seem to be a very strange way to have gone about it.
So having essentially announced a policy which went down very badly and have basically
apologized and reverse course within 24 hours, everything was calm for a few days, then there was an announcement on the Disconsory Twitter that their co-chair collect for Zard would be resigning.
And she then posted a statement on file 770 about her resignation, which essentially says that the feedback they got about this policy was the last straw in a number of last straws of how she feels the volunteers and the people who work on Worldcon have been treated over the years.
So she decided this was a good time for her to resign, post on file 770 about how the internet had been mean over and over to Worldcon staff and then to do a sort of mic drop and leave.
And obviously Mike was very unhappy.
This is what is known traditionally in fandom as a flounce.
I like to collect a lot and I was very glad to get to know her as part of, because she was looking on Disconsory and she was supporting the bid when it was a bid and she seems like a really, really nice person who is fun tag out with.
She mentioned a number of examples in her letter of ways in which she'd been mistreated and quite a lot of people who were not necessarily of the belligerent kind.
But we know other thoughtful experienced con runners came back and said, we don't necessarily think these are good examples of mistreatment that the yes decisions were criticized in those cases, but they, and sometimes they were criticized robustly but that they weren't done in a way that was aggressive or personal.
This doesn't entirely add up and I think that seems right to me and I think it's possible because if you're sharing a convention or a big convention, people do criticize things about that convention for all sorts of reasons.
Some of them are valid criticisms and some of them are mixed and some of them are not that valid but as the chair, it's very easy to start thinking of the convention as if it was your baby or in an analogy that will make sense to more people who listen to the podcast, your cat.
And so you can become very defensive about criticism and start to feel that all robust criticism is abuse and that's not true.
Now I don't, I haven't got back through all of the details and people do, I think when people are criticizing, they probably need to be less in temperant than they often are.
There's all the stuff you learn in management training about delivering feedback with wrapped in, wrapped in good and secure thoughts about how wonderful the person or the organization you're giving feedback to is but there's this one little thing that they might like to change.
This probably applies to conventions as well and I think people don't necessarily do that when they're tweeting out so it does upset people.
But I feel like Koletta's overreacted, well she made a lot of overreacted by residing because I don't know what was personally going on but I think in making that statement, it seems to be to be a rather poorly thought through statement that has exposed, exposes rather more of her personal reaction to criticism than it maybe should have done.
So that too.
So I have, I have thoughts about this which is that I think it is silly.
I think emotions are silly.
No, that's not what I was like leap, leap, leap, leap.
We're science fiction, we're science fiction fans.
We don't do emotions, didn't you know?
Yes, that's right.
Okay.
And so yes, good.
Now, good.
See, I think there is a perception that I think, I think there is a real undercurrent in.
A lot of these conversations and I think this is not just science fiction fandom, but I think in a lot of discussions like this, it is, is kind of maybe not unacceptable, but like it is not considered the done thing to say stuff like I hear your counter argument.
And I see that you have a point, but the way you're expressing that point makes my feelings hurt and I would quite like you to go away for a little bit so that I am no longer hurt.
And I think something I have been trying in my personal life to do more recently is when I get into discussions that are hurting my feelings, even if I'm sure that everyone involved isn't intending to do that, I sort of say, well, no, I mean, I sort of say, like, well, this is the way we're having this conversation kind of means that I feel hurt or defensive or I'm in a bad kind of place emotionally.
And I'm sure you're not trying to do that, but maybe we should both take a step back and think, well, this discussion is a little bit hotter or a little bit more charged than it needs to be.
And maybe there's a way we can have this discussion without kind of without having it in a way that could result in hurt feelings.
And I think that is a very difficult thing to do because I think it opens you up.
It makes you vulnerable to the person you're talking with and it's something that is, I find it very difficult to do with people I've known for decades.
So doing with people I don't know who are on Twitter, I expect is impossible.
And the rest of Twitter is not going to help you with that.
Well, and so the thing with Twitter is Twitter is a fantastic tool and Twitter really rewards brevity.
I like that the nature of the website is that you are rewarded by being able to encapsulate your thoughts very tersely.
And I think that can be really valuable, but I do think it does mean that people tend to be very direct on Twitter.
And I'm not saying that's a bad thing, but I do think if you're very direct with criticism, it can be easy not to couch that criticism in a way that kind of recognizes the fact that criticism can be hurtful.
Even if that criticism is 100% valid and I agree with the criticism, I am, as you probably gathered,
listed as from the previous segment of this podcast, I in general oppose DC's decision here.
And I was generally on the side of the people who were complaining.
And I read Collette's statement and I do sort of think, you know, clearly, I think she is personally invested in a convention she was running, which I think I understand.
And I don't think that's unreasonable at all.
And I think clearly she has been hurt and I can see why.
And I think and are not saying that that's unreasonable.
I'm also not saying the people who criticized were being unreasonable.
What I do think at a fundamental level is this is why the chair should not be the person who is reading this.
The chair should not be the person who is responding to this.
The chair should be displaced from this criticism by people whose job it is to encapsulate the criticism,
report it to the chair in a way that is not quite as direct or to us as it is on Twitter.
And then maybe the chair says, well, here is what I think and the people on the social media kind of layer say,
aha, the chair respectfully disagrees and here is our response.
And I think a very good example of this is Elon Musk, who on no account should be allowed to have his own Twitter account because the fact that he goes on flame wars against people all the time is like, no, get to media manager.
I just want to say I completely disagree with that for in big and small ways.
So Liz.
So I would say one of the biggest things I have actually learned from working on World Cons is how to take criticism much less personally because I think that is the only way to work on a World Cons.
You have to take pride in your successes and pride in things that go right, but you cannot take everyone saying, hey, you've done this in a way that is bad or you know, you haven't thought about the effect this has on particular communities.
You have to not take that as a personal thing.
It's not personally against you.
It's saying, you know, this thing you have done in your role on this convention is not working for us.
So I think that was one of the biggest things I have learned from having fairly public facing roles to World Cons.
And I think the second thing that goes along with that is Alison's way of saying, well, you've got to do it in management speak and maybe you can couch your criticism, you know, with some positive things is I don't think World Cons is in a position where people want to give us the benefit of the doubt to do that.
And it's probably a longer discussion of how this announcement from DiscCon has to be put in the perspective and the context of all the other announcements from World Cons.
But last year's Hugo's, the Hugo ceremony went very badly in prominent ways.
So they're not people who we can say, look, this is our first misstep.
Please give us the benefit of the doubt on this one and we'll discuss it more.
These are people saying, look, last year you made a token cock up of it and we did not feel honored as finalists.
And this year you're proposing to do this other thing which makes us feel not honored as finalists.
So I can kind of understand why they got a bit angry.
And my third thing I will say in this round is that if you think that like the speed and immediacy of Trisha criticism is a problem for discussion and debate, then definitely I think the speed with which you can resign right along post by a resignation and posted on file 770 is another example of where the speed of the internet is really not helping.
I think this post should have someone else on Facebook gone in a draw for a week and then you think about it again.
And that's why I try to say with the layer between the chair and the criticism because I think that does cut both ways.
I think you're completely wrong about insulating power from criticism.
I think the fact that this happens is what leads to people being very bad at being chairs.
The job of the chair over beyond anything else is to keep an overview.
This is going to be awful management speak again, but you want him to keep an overview of everything that is going on at a high level, but also be sufficiently aware of what is going on at detail levels that you can make sure that policy decisions
do reflect the entire community, do reflect, build a consensus, do all of those things.
I mean, I think obviously Elon Musk should have a media manager.
That goes without saying, but your chair does need to be aware of the criticism.
However, as Liz said, I mean, I think if you've worked, I don't know, Liz worked with me on FollyCon and then we did have,
the punctuation was a flat collective, but in general, if I'm kind of doing things in difficult circumstances as a chair, I'll write what I want to say and then I'll fizz it to people that I trust to say, is this setting the right tone?
Is this taking us in a supportive direction?
Because I know that I am somebody who is inclined to shoot from the hip.
No.
One of the roles that chairs often take at conventions is being the final arbiter of the Code of Conduct.
And whenever I run a convention, I take myself out of the Code of Conduct management line because I know this is something that I'm not very good at because I am not measured enough to do that job well.
And also because I know that I have people who I could go to and say, will you do this for me and they will do it very well.
So, and I feel like that's kind of, if you're the chair, you have to be prepared to take all the criticism and deal with it in a way that is productive.
I don't think you could say, I have a media manager to manage all of that. I never look at Twitter.
So I think you're right and I think, yes, I didn't necessarily mean to imply that the chair should be insulated from the criticism.
I guess what I'm more meant was, I think I can see that there are modes of criticism that might be hurtful and like, I think I have two reactions to that, which is firstly, yes, I agree that the chair needs to be aware of all the criticism.
And I think ultimately the chair's job in some ways is to be the person who is criticized.
Ultimately, the conventions actions are at the final kind of in the final case, the responsibility of the chair.
And if something goes badly, it is on the chair.
I would say that the thing I was intending to say with that kind of insulating layer was not necessarily that the chair should be insulated from criticism in terms of like, you should never see any.
But I think like this kind of thing where you've got kind of collect writing a statement in file 70, 70, which is quite incendiary.
That's the sort of thing that I think having some sort of insulating layer would prevent.
And the thing that you mentioned, Alison, of kind of making sure that you, because it sounds like you're describing an insulating layer, but you're kind of bouncing messages off people to make sure that there is some level of kind of double glazing in between the thing you want to say in your head.
And the thing that people see you say publicly.
Resignation letters are a classic, a classic form of saying something in sensory.
That's OK.
What I'm not suggesting that collection not have said something in sensory.
That's her personal choice.
I'm saying that if she had been a bit more reflective, she could have said something much more potent and not necessarily.
It's basically people could look at what she said and go.
She should not have said that.
Whereas she could have definitely said that in a way that people went, oh, you know, she's got a point.
We need to address things in both ways.
I think I think I think in general, I am suggesting that the thing that got published in Fast Ever's ever, he was not necessarily constructive.
I want to say one tiny thing before giving Liz her turn, which is a very wise manager once said to me that you should never write an e a sentence in an email or in in or in any.
Published document where you could where you could append the words you idiot to the end of the sentence without changing its meaning.
And and collect finishes her statement with keep.
You'll have to keep this.
Keep around and we'll find out which I think is is is a giant example of that exact point.
So the other thing that we like to attention to is a long comment posted on for the post of file 7 17, which is from Jared Dashoff, who was the WISFIS division head for discount three and has now resigned.
And it's essentially a comment that says that the policies that were put forward for the Hugo Award were not his idea or of his Hugo admins, but they did roll through and help to plan how to implement them and how to roll them out.
And then they saw the response.
They hadn't realized how much displeasure there would be and he and his Hugo administrator.
I argue they should reverse course and which as we know they eventually did, but apparently there was a meeting where Jared Sugo admin was asked to resign.
And as a result of this, he says that he has resigned.
It's not clear who else is a giant, but there may be other resignations from his division.
But essentially it's kind of disagreeing with Colette's point and saying essentially this was a policy that was not imposing them, but was not their idea and they came up with how to implement it and roll it out, which is what sometimes is going to happen.
But then it seemed like the Hugo admin was the person who was going to have to take the fallout for this policy, which I would disagree with entirely.
And it sounds like he disagreed with it to the point where he felt he had to resign. So I feel that also puts a very different slant on Colette's post.
And I think the messages I would take from this is that like all conventions, there is some internal disagreement.
There is internal debate on things.
Sometimes you will have to implement a policy which may not be what you would do ideally in a vacuum, but it may be kind of imposed on you because of the constraints of other divisions or because of the other divisions.
Or because this is what the chair and the rest of the committee wants to happen or maybe just the chairs.
But I do think that what this show is a policy that was rolled out from the top downwards when like when it was received much more disfavorably than they thought.
And the book didn't roll back upwards to the top, but it rolled back upwards to kind of the Hugo admin, which really does not seem at the right level to say, okay, this is the person who needs to take the fallout for it.
And what it looks like this has led to is probably maybe the loss of the Hugo admin, but the loss of the Wisphist division head and quite possibly the maybe other members of the vision I suspect who are also not happy.
I think I have seen, we have seen resignation statements from other people within the Wisphist division of Discon.
So I mean, I don't know how much of the Wisphist division will remain when the dust settles.
I think, I think, and I know, and I think like whatever else I think about the policy and whatever else I think about the way Discon communicated the policy and whatever else I think about the way Discon climbed down off the policy and whatever else I think about
Let's post resigning. I think this message from Jared makes it abundantly clear that at some level, this was not a good set of decisions made by the Discon chair under duress from criticism from the community.
I'm assuming that the decision on the policy was taken by the board.
But the chair signs off, as I said, it is on the chair.
Yeah.
And especially if the chair is going to kick off this giant argument, it is definitely on the chair because she would have known that this was not the idea of anyone else in her organization.
It sounds very much like she attempted to shift the blame onto someone else to avoid taking the responsibility for this decision.
And ultimately, if she had come out and said, "I instituted this policy," the Wisphist division implemented it, but it was me and the board that kind of decided it needed to be implemented.
We sincerely apologize and we will kind of work on this going forward.
I would not want her to resign.
Collect through a very large amount of shade in multiple directions in her statement.
And I'd say that Jared's response is clear and measured and not excessive.
But they are doing that un-British thing of airing one's dirty laundry in public.
Jared's response is, I think, a very good response.
It clearly goes into like, "This is what actually happened."
And I'm reading it.
Obviously, I don't know for sure I wasn't there, but it doesn't seem like it would be an unlikely set of events.
And he doesn't know to like, part of the reason he resigns is because he wasn't having fun anymore.
He didn't feel supported by the organization.
I think for Zard saying like, "Oh, this is because people are overly critical and the way we like,
criticize our convention running is unacceptable, is all very well."
Then when you find out that her own division heads think that she has kind of sold them down the river for magic beams
and is a large part of why this has been so spectacularly mishandled,
it's then very difficult to say, "Well, okay, she has a good point about how we have this discourse."
I think it undermines her point that if she had handled it better as chair,
then resigned and then been upset with the criticism.
I'd be like, "Oh, you know, maybe we should have a discussion about this."
I'm not sure if we have time to do it today, but I did a job for a Worldcon.
I did a large job for the 2014 Worldcon and I concluded at the end of that that I did not want to do that again.
And one of the problems that we have with Worldcons is that for whatever reason,
we often find ourselves with the very large conventions, the very big jobs being done by people who may not either,
they're either not very well suited to doing those jobs or they don't have a sufficient support network around them
to keep them doing them properly.
Worldcon is very difficult and when they say, "Friends don't let friends run Worldcons, this is why."
But also that thing about back at the beginning, one of the things we did,
points we did not make at the beginning that we maybe should have done is,
the other question that comes to mind about this policy around the Hugos is,
"Shouldn't this be a matter for Wussfuss or the Wussfuss business meeting?"
It is relatively clear to me that the Hugo teams at previous Worldcons have been trying
to keep some sort of lid on the number of people who are on the ballot for each finalist.
It is relatively clear to me that there has been some pushback from the actual finalists.
But that has all been happening in private email chains and what we're currently seeing is a kind of like an explosion of stuff coming out.
Now that this argument is being had in a public sphere
and I think that maybe it would be better to sort of have some kind of panel items at Worldcons
and maybe some consultations and maybe some Wussfuss subcommittees
and all of these things that do a very good job of go away and think about things
and collect information and weigh up the pros and cons and then come back with a sort of coherent thing
which says, "Here's what people think."
You know, a policy document, for instance.
The week before last we discussed the video game, Hugo, and there is this beautiful document
"Beautiful is not necessarily the word I would use to describe this document."
"Elegant, magnificent, marvellous."
"Comprehensive is what I would say."
"Comprehensive, comprehensive, good word."
"Thorough, thorough is good."
Yeah, but what I think it does do a good job is taking the potential arguments against the case
and pretty forward the arguments against the arguments against.
So kind of saying, "Here's why we think this would work.
Here are some common arguments and here why we think they're not a problem."
And I think, although I'm not saying that document is like my favourite argument,
I do think that kind of approach to this kind of issue would probably be better
than just sort of arguing in the 5.7.70 comments and on Twitter.
And Alison did say, like, "Do you think we would have a measured and nuanced debate about this?"
And I concede that it is possible that people would still find things to be annoyed and angry and chowty about.
But I just, yeah, I think it might be better.
Also, for the avoidance of doubt, I would rather hear the complete list of every name of somebody
who worked on a large semi-prosean project than I would any more anecdotes by Robert Silverberg.
I think actually it was a valid point that is kind of a later point I had said before about context,
which is when people were pushing back against this policy on Twitter, it wasn't in a vacuum.
These probably are the people who work on semi-prosean
who have been having this back and forward with the committees trying to work out exactly who gets listed
and who gets left out every year.
And that's what you might not be able to see.
So you just see them making a tweet against it, but you don't know they have spent several years
pushing back against this and now they're just having this kind of imposed on them from higher up.
So I think that's a useful point to make.
And yes, I wholeheartedly with Alison, we don't need to mention that because that's obvious.
I do worry that WISFAS subcommittees are where things go to die,
but I do think that some guidelines on what is expected from this.
For instance, I don't know if the Hugo base design guidelines specify like the size of the plaque
that needs to be on the base, but if we are having problems fitting all the names on the base,
then either we need to have a larger plaque on the base or we need to say to nominees,
the base is this big.
If we can't fit all your names on it, how would you like us to label your Hugo's?
Yeah, I mean, I think somebody said you completely remove the emotional content of this by saying
the plaque has room for X characters.
It doesn't this doesn't necessarily work for Twitter mind.
I can fit a lot in a tweet.
If I could fit a tweet on a Hugo plaque, it would be pretty awesome.
So would you be able to have Hugo plaque threads where like?
You've got to win more than one year in a road, John, in order to properly thread.
Yeah.
Just keep reading every time.
You could actually see a world in which you could print the whole of answer
to its Hugo plaque.
Excellent. I am in favor.
Sorry.
But no, I think I think we have I think we have discussed this and and yes,
does anyone else have anything I'd like to add?
I do think adding some frivolous bits at the end is probably not a bad idea because this is quite a weighty.
It's quite weighty for us.
Before we go, we're going to tell you about some upcoming events.
So fanak, which stands for the Florida Association for Nucleation and Conventions,
are hosting a interview.
So John D.
Berry, who gave a fantastic talk on punctuation at punctuation is interviewing Ted White,
who is a fan who apparently needs interviewing.
Yeah, he's phantoms equivalent of Robert Silverberg.
They're hosting this at the 4 p.m.
Eastern Standard Time on the 23rd of January 2021.
It is a follow up to Rob Hansen's excellent tour of Spanish London,
which Alison and I attended a few weeks ago and was magnificent.
So if people are interested in that, go to fanak.org and poke around.
Roman Orzansky, who is a locker of the podcast and a noted adladian fan,
is involved with hosting a one day mini convention called Critical Mass.
It is running noon to 8 p.m.
Adelaide time and that is on the 31st of January 2021.
The last panel of the day is about podcasting.
I'm running at 7.30 p.m. Adelaide time, which is 9 a.m.
British time and I will be appearing on that panel about podcasting.
So yes, do if you don't get enough of listening to me on podcasts,
feel free to come along to that and listen to me on a panel about podcasts.
And then we're currently missing Arisha and I think
Capricon is coming up on the 4th to the 7th of February and Boscone is coming up
on the 12th to the 14th of February.
So Liz and Alison, are you going to any of these events?
I think I am going to Boscone.
There will be a fan funds auction at Boscone.
We haven't entirely worked out the format and plans for that, but it's going to happen.
I was also going to trade, but I think I might have missed the deadline
because it might have been Friday.
But I'm not.
I might get to Capricon as well.
Jeremy Coxen, who I like very much is running is the chair of Capricon and she was
encouraging me to go.
And these are not very expensive.
And I think Boscone is $25.
And I think Capricon's $10.
So they're not free events.
I'm sure critical maths will be free or very cheap though.
And Fanac is free.
Yes.
So yes, I'll definitely get to one or both of those conventions.
I just haven't got my act together to look at how and where yet.
But I do struggle slightly with American conventions because they
start partying just at the point where I am thinking of going to sleep and I am
quite a late stair-upper.
The advantage of critical maths is if they do have an afterparty, then it will
start at 10 o'clock in the morning, it sounds like, which is exactly the sort
of time when I think about partying.
So that's fine.
That was the 23rd episode of the Oct Thought
podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
There are a lot of people whose only interest in an engagement with the World
Con is the Hugo Awards.
And they are coming along and saying, we care about the Hugos.
We think the Hugos Awards are critically important.
And so therefore, everything else you do.
And this is evidenced by the fact that Hugos, that Wussfuss, is an entire division
in the World Con organization, which if you think about the way that organisations
are set up, it's quite strange.
It's a very, it's because it is an enormous amount of work.
But and that's not even the half of it because the actual Hugo Awards ceremony
are the two biggest parts of the events job, which is another division of the World
Con. And so that's why I have put in the show notes.
Maybe the Hugos just are a cankerous boil that should be excised from World
Cons' fourth with so we could just have a nice convention.
So my response to Alison would be, well, maybe the World Con is just a cankerous
boil on the bottom of the Hugos and we may need an entire other podcast,
I think, to do this justice.
To say maybe should we just split these things into two entirely different things?
So you could have the Hugo Awards along with the Hugo Awards weekend,
like the Nebula Awards weekend, and that could be a largely professional
industry body plus all the semi-prosy, sort of full of aspiring authors.
And we could call the Hugo Awards weekend because it would involve lots
of people convening from all about the world.
And we could call that weekend con of the world.
World Con. World Con. I got it.
Hang on, hang on.
I pause to say, Alison, I think this is a long topic that should have its own
podcast and then you proceeded to start that podcast.
I mean, I, in my defence, I just took the piss.
We're just fine. We are, we are that kind of podcast.
But no, I seriously think that we, if we are to do this justice and consider
the pros and cons of whether we should do this, that we probably do need more
than the time we have remaining unless our, you know, dear listeners,
which just spent two hours listening to us, which are on about a single top.
And no, that's fine.
Let's push that away for a future for a future thing.
Dear listeners, when Alison and Liz have their big discussion about
splitting up the world call of the Hugos, please just imagine that I'm there
shaking my head the whole time and that that will be enough input for me.
You don't think he was a Mark protector?
In practice, we cannot, we cannot split off the hugos.
Alison, he's doing the podcast unless we really don't think there's enough for us
to discuss this on a separate thing, but I think that there probably is.
And so, in a case, yeah, no, 100% we've recorded, we've recorded enough podcast.
Sorry, just in case that wasn't clear.
We've definitely recorded a podcast.
The theme music for this episode was
Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod at
andcompetech.com used under a Creative Commons
attribution 3.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
beep