We've waffled up for ages.
We have here I go have to please edit this down to something crisp and cogent John
Deep and crisp and even
Hahahaha, yes
Hello everyone and welcome to the
21st episode of octa thought the podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom. I'm Joel Coxon
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty and it's a special Christmas episode
Yay
Because you will be hearing this if you download it on Christmas Eve you will and
Christmas is you know the most marvelous time of the year the time when
families come together when people party every night for months when you
Hit up everybody you know no never mind
Where we sit alone in our houses
Saying it'll be we'll have Christmas in summer like the Australians as they actually said on the radio this morning
We won't and it won't be and I having talked to a lot of Australians this week about the classic Australia Christmas
I'm pretty sure it's a bit shit
They're kind of like oh we have roast turkey and all the trimmings and it doesn't really suit the fact that it's 93 degrees outside
But there you go. You step up. They have a barbecue, right?
I mean I actually went to a Christmas party
But there's nothing that puts it down on your Christmas party quite like a news alert saying there are
546 cases of covid just discovered
To make you think well, it's probably good job. I went to this Christmas party because I might be another one
Anyway, we had some we had two letters of comment
We had one from Peter Sullivan who sent us a
An editorial he'd written for his zine
and
Talked a little bit about online conventions and things and and kind of was
Inspired I think by punctuation what we ran with Steve Davis. Hi, Steve
And yeah, it's quite good. So there is a link to it in the show notes because it is available on the Internet in his
zine
So yes, everyone go and read that if you'd like and thank you for getting in touch Peter
And yeah, he does say some some nice things about punctuation. So thank you very much
We are glad you had a nice time
And then the other letter of comment we had was from Claire Breyerley of Croydon
and
So I should note before I read the letter of comment that Claire sent me a text message yesterday saying that the package
She sent me was finally on the move and I could expect it
hopefully before Christmas perhaps just after and
I said that I didn't know whether to be excited or terrified and she said possibly both for various reasons
So, you know, I don't know what's coming and she did all I know is that it's something that she hopes will be intact
And that did not make me less terrified
Because I don't know what my guess is a sculpture made of weeabicks. I
Mean I know you said please don't send you anymore
Please stop sending us a week because you've got too many me to fix but Claire has correctly pointed out
This was only a month after you told people to send you as much be too big as possible
So you could roll around in a massive bathtub full of we to bigs
So really if it is an elaborate we to big sculpture, I think it is no more than you deserve
Yep, that's me told
Claire also takes us to task for having carefully
After she had carefully said two versions of her previous lock
the second one amended
John read out the first one and Liz and I are blaming John. That's fair. I take full responsibility
class says I'm writing a lock
I'm checking it twice and then a dozen times because I'm now paranoid
I've made a mistake that won't get corrected by the podcast
well
Yes, I apologize
I I would say that I'll update the version in last episode show notes to be the correct version
But I will probably forget so I'm not gonna say that but I just have
Yeah, we're not really that kind of error checking fact-checking kind of operation, are we?
Perhaps not
We did cut we did go away into our homework
We did well. I did a fanzine
The fanzines motto was never ix to play never apologize. So there's that
Claire also notes that
Mark came up with a version of that Christmas song
Many years ago about Claire about Claire which goes she's making a list and then another list and yet another list
That's a list of all the lists and that does seem very organized. I have not got any Christmas lists yet
Except for mine with presents on it. Hopefully everyone buys me presents. Yeah presents
I haven't bought anybody any presents. It's a real problem. Everyone's getting a little note in their card saying
Whoops bit of a cock up on the present front. That's still a reference that you guys aren't going to get
But thank you for your letter of comment Claire
last episode we have some hot takes on the
Hugo award for best interactive experience, which is something that has been
promoted and proposed by our ira Alexandre
And we we have not read the 40,000 word report that accompanied the proposal and so we were coming from a place of
What we reckoned in the true Michelin web style and I will put a link to that sketch in the show notes
But now we've read it
Well, I think to be fair to us
We were actually bouncing off
Discons announcement of the best video game Hugo, which now I have read the full
Proposal for the best interactive video game. No best interactive experience of video game Hugo
They're not the same actually
So I thought it was interesting that
Discons had chosen to implement this and I presume that part of it was because there was quite a lot of
general debate and discussion over having a Hugo for best interactive experience of video game
But they've chosen to implement it in a different way
And I'm not sure we've actually seen what their definition of video game is going to be
Because it's a special Hugo so you don't have to have it in the Constitution yet
So I'll be interested to see where they differ
Yes, so this I think this I think is a very good point that we would discuss you before the show
And I think I think having read the
DC nomination, I think several of the criticisms we were applying that are not
Problems with the award as Ida Alexandre has proposed it
I think are more of a problem with the way that DC has proposed theirs and
I think that is an interesting choice
Because I think it's difficult if if someone has if someone has kind of proposed a category and has done an awful lot of work to
Demonstrate why it would be viable and why a lot of criticisms are not a valid then introducing a test category
Which is slightly different is very unhelpful
In some ways and because if it works great, but if it doesn't work
It'll be very difficult to disentangle the extent to which it didn't work because DC changed it
Versus the extent to which it didn't work because it was inherently unworkable
Yeah, I'm just gonna fact check myself because
Live fact checking on the podcast because having said I don't think I've seen discons full proposal
I have realized this could have got the full proposal and wording out there. I think it's interesting in the
Yeah, a gate so the defineer game is a work-wearing player choice interaction or participation significantly interacts the narrative play meaning or experience and the game is available on personal computers
Basically phones
PlayStation or Xbox so I mean it would definitely be possible to interpret that as saying that in their definition of
game they have included say
Black Mirror Bandersnatch which I watched through the Netflix app on my PlayStation for instance
So it might be that in trying to limit it they have inadvertently
Included a lot of stuff that would be in the best interactive experience or or game Hugo anyway
Hmm and also given how many of us have been playing
tabletop games but fire out outlets like tabletop simulator or
Tabletopia then in a way they they would also count
Yeah, they would like tabletop simulator
is available on personal computers and
Any more to written for that I would argue is a substantial modification of tabletop simulator
And so I don't really understand if what they want to do is limited to video games the way they've written this
spectacularly does not do that and I don't understand why they wanted to limit it to video games given that I think the original
Rose was a lot more elegant. So I think I agree with you on that I
Have been thinking about
interactive experiences because I suppose they do mean things like Bandersnatch
but I
Was thinking well, what are the interactive experiences that might be relevant and it struck me that things like?
Secret cinema which have nothing to do with things that you do on a computer
Are the sorts of things that feel like interactive experiences that that might come within a broad scope
I I don't like
The idea that you're going to have proposals that say you that talk about the way you engage
With the material. It's a bit like saying that novels only count if they're on paper
Which of course we did have with with certainly with the fan categories for for some time and and I
It all seems quite complicated and I'm interested in seeing how it comes out. I did I
Did feel that the 40,000 word document went some way to answering my
concerns, but also that
It's response too. Well, nobody can afford to play all the triple A games was oh
but
half the things that come through as best games of the year and not triple A games the other half still are and
and
You can you can go and watch let's plays, but let's plays are I think by their definition?
non-interactive experiences
So I am not completely I'm not completely convinced that my concerns here were answered
but obviously what we're gonna see is the
category shaking down when the Hugo voters get to have a go at it and
The I would have thought that the Hugo nominators and voters are quite clever at
Actually making sensible choices and all of these things and we've seen that in lots of other categories
Yes, so I was just gonna say that you mentioned
secret cinema whereas in fact
I think more maybe more even more relevant to that is the one they do mention in in the document
Which is they pull out sleep no more the interactive punch-drunk theater experience based on Macbeth
And I hadn't seen that but I have seen the drowned man, which is an interactive
Adaptation they did over the post office old sorting office in Paddington
Where you know you're all you're all masked up and you get to choose which bits of the story you follow and
Everyone who does it will have a slightly different experience and some people will have experiences that aren't possible for other people to have
That feels very much like the sort of interactive experience that would be in here
I'm not I've not been to any secret cinema things because they're really expensive. So I'm not sure how they
Compared to that the discom three definition of the category is a
game or modification of a game first released to the public in the last year and they define game as a
Work here with we're in player choice inter-sectional participation significantly impacts the narrative play meaning or experience
I am not convinced that secret Santa does have a secret Santa
I'm not convinced that secret cinema has that feature because at the end of the day you are watching the film and the film will be the same
Regardless of how people into engage with it in the cinema. So I don't think my understanding is not that secret cinema would qualify
Unless secret cinema does show films like clue where the endings are different and the audience has a meaningful chance of impacting them
But that is not the impression I've had
the the watching a film bit of secret cinema has been getting us
Becoming a smaller and smaller portion of the overall experience over time. It's the experience that's interactive
And the film is one part of that and I haven't been to secret cinema either
So obviously I'm slightly talking from talking rot here
But you know I've talked a lot to people who have so none of us have done our homework on this one
But I hope it would have been expensive. Well, we didn't in our defense. Alison has only just mentioned this
But the other thing I will say is that
But the other thing you said was about how you were uncomfortable with
Splitting this off in terms of how you engage with the work
Because obviously the category basically in in the in the games you go proposal
It defines what an interactive work is and then it explicitly disqualifies interactive works from being nominated from other categories
And introduces a new category for which they can be nominated
And I don't think I see your point about how it's a bit like mandating that a novel has to be on paper
But I think that the argument that the panel make is that
Interactivity does fundamentally
offer a different narrative experience to more linear
forms storytelling like best dramatic presentation or best novel and so it is necessary to
split that off
Sorry, that's not the distinction the distinction I was making was between board games and video games
I I think it is or you know, I feel like a fighting fantasy book is
The same is inherently the same the same sort of experience as the fighting fantasy video game
played on the iPad and
I think I'll defend to the death that they should be in the same Hugo category
And there is not a Hugo category for games that are not played on computers
Yes, no, I agree with that
So why why have they eliminated why have they said oh, it has to be on a computer to count
I'm gonna let Liz come in after I've said this. Sorry Liz. I
Think so my take is I agree. I think board games should absolutely be in this category
My suspicion is that it will be a bit like short films in best dramatic presentation short form where they're technically eligible
But they never get nominated because TV shows dominate
I suspect the same thing will happen here which one which I will be grumpy about when it does if it inevitably happen
But I do think you are right that they should be eligible even if the electorate does not end up nominating them
Yeah, I think I feel I mean
I'm basically willing to give them lots of leeway because this is a temporary Hugo category that can then be refined over time
I find a bit weird to have a category that sort of defines all the different ways it can be experienced
To the exclusion of some things that you think would fit. I'm also not sure if
Including board games would mean that board games don't get nominated because I actually think that
With some of the board games that do become very popular they might get played more widely than some of the video games
Like I think if you were doing this, I'm just thinking of
Wingspan which was board game came out in 2019 and I think
Basically a very large number of board game fans probably played quite soon after it came out and so you might see that
Popping up if that had been eligible
In a way that you might not for all the different AA games for instance because I do think people might play those a little bit
behind times
Um, so I also point is if you're gonna have like a game or a substantial modification of a game and that would be board games
Then john do you realize it means you could nominate? I'll come horror the card game basically for a Hugo in perpetuity
John is nodding. I know I am aware
I think we should get on to suggested nominations shortly
So, um one thing I will say before we before I think we should come back to this before I do
What to remember to say is this is how I nominate best pro artist
I go through the card games. I play looking at my favorite card art and then I nominate the artists on those cards
Because they're all eligible eligible
This is kind of like I like to burn fibers and throw them into the sea
Right that would be eco destructive and I will have no part of it
I said to buy favors to companies that manufacture things in China and that is much better for the environment
Oh god, no, that's kind of like me and my quest to nominate video games in best romantic presentation long form for a long time
Which yeah, it's like completely futile. I
Think one thing I will say is that listener, um if you are listening to this and thinking hang on
They mentioned that this report is 40,000 words. Did they read a 40,000 word report? I feel so special
Uh, we did not it sends out if you download the report, which is a horribly formatted, uh, google doc
um for some reason
the
Main meat of the report is basically you could be the abstract the introduction the conclusion and like tip bits of the bits in between
And I do think that in general it would have been better structured as a much turdsir report
With a larger number of appendices to make it clear that that is really how you can read it
See I think it would have been much better if it had been constructed as a choose your own adventure report
Where instead of having to reach the whole thing all the way through it would say
If you are interested in
Why we don't think why we think it doesn't matter that nobody could play all the triple a games click here
if you think
It when we're not giving enough credence to other sorts of interactive experience click here
If you wonder why board games aren't included
Um click here, but we haven't actually covered that
What they should have done is structured it as a choose your own adventure at the business meeting
If you would like to raise an objection along the lines of this turn to page 27
And when you turn to page 27
When you turn to page 27, you discover a giant ice ball and unless you can roll 11 on one die
You're not getting through his name's kevin
Oh my god
I want to win so this category oh shoot i've left it too late if
I we've left it so we have as it turns out 11 days to write this so it is eligible for the hugo
Which we currently discussing?
If we could do it in the next 11 days
So if you would like octa thought to be an interactive experience
Please go to episode 13
Uh, I suppose wait a couple of ways we could go in this
um
I will mention that one thing I was quite pleased with is part of the argument for why we need a video game hugo
Specifically is that worldcons have had increasing amounts of game related program
And I will note that this peaked in 2014
Um the fact that I was involved and we had estimate calum steward's involved and I guess we also had allysan involved since we put a big
Games tent in your space
Uh
May not be coincidental to why there are so many so many games items
Which I actively encouraged I should say yes, you were very pleased to put the big be a big tent in your space
And and steve jaxson was there and oh yeah, it was cool
So it yeah, it was good and I if that means people think actually there's more appetite for video game hugo than there would have been
Uh into 2006 because more people now see that are worldcons and people associated with games feel that will cons and more they think then i'm
pleased to have played a tiny part in that and I should say this is a good point to plug
the
The glass go in 2024 worldconbid which is of course chaired by the aforementioned estera calum steward
And which i'm now actually a member of the bid team. So yeah, go go gosh go
um for no doubt good content related to video games and interactive experiences
Is that so I must admit I skipped past some of the graphs
But does that mean that dublin 2019 with steve jaxson as a guest of hoda had less game related programming than loncon 3 that had no
Game related guest of hobbler and then so the caveat to that is that there is I think there are some game related program items that they probably
Couldn't track specifically in uh, I think
Some of the later ones because they were running there like uh
Interactive sessions and sign up through a different system and they may not have captured all the game sessions that were running
It may also be that we had things technically tagged as gaming sessions
You know, we may have had more things saying okay. This is a formal to our gaming session in the games tent
That didn't get into the program for other years. So i'm not sure we actually had more than 2019
Okay
I think it's also true though that there is more gaming at
London and dublin and health sinky than at the us worldcons where
You you us worldcon attendance is more homogenous
It's more geared towards older
Literary science fiction fans than european worldcons are
I think it's true, but they do say the same thing was probably true for 2018 in that they're not sure they've managed to track all the game sessions
so
28 being also made of an outlier. I don't know if there wasn't there
But this this you go. I mean it might end up being going to a game that's just good to play
But I think it's going to go to a game with strong narrative. I think there's a
Real push in what it's talking about and why it thinks it's appropriate for a hugo
that actually
the hugos are the awards for
You know our specular to fiction genre and and the argument for having a
award for video game or interactive experience is because of the
Because it is a way in which stories of specular to fiction are told
and I'm I'm not
You know, I although it's perfectly possible that that the hugo would be won by tetris or some 2020 equivalent of tetris
It feels to me remarkably unlikely that that will happen
And that there is going to be something there that's about the world building or the narrative or something
that is beyond just
Fun play and some of what is going on in gaming tensack conventions
I would argue is just having fun playing games without building a deep and consistent and coherent narrative
Yeah, we don't have a hugo for best bar is what i'm saying
We should do obviously and the campaign starts here
Yes, um, I I think there are two things I really liked about this
proposal
Which is firstly the way that it uses
The way that it points out that the hugo award is the way that was first recognizes
What's happening in specular to fiction that is worthy of recognition and that
They make the point that was first as a membership is interested in games and that games form at this point a significant and
Big part of what was first considered to be specular to fiction and the way they approach that is kind of demonstrating that that is being discussed at world cons and things like that
But also
Discussing in terms of these are people who we know are in wusfus and they are talking about some making games
So like nk jemisin and mirlafeteer two of the people that are specifically called out in the report
The other thing I like is that there is a mention in the report
of a collaborative role-playing game
which they kind of use to
call attention specifically to
um the idea of
collaborative and interactive world building and using that as a way of forming a narrative and the game that they
Highlight is a game called microscope, which I now really want to play
Um, but there's a really interesting section called interactive world building in the report
They also mentioned dwarf fortress, which I think is a
remarkable
Remarkable game of building building things out of stuff that doesn't doesn't exist before you stop playing the game
I read an article by the lead designer of arkham per other card game, which is long-time listeners may know i'm a huge stan of
And and the lead designer mj wrote a blog post in which they discuss
The interaction of narrative and ludonarrative and i've not heard the term ludonarrative before but ludonarrative is the
emergent narrative you get from playing the game versus the narrative which is dictated by
The narrative that has been written for the game and and they talked a little bit about the importance of the interplay between those two concepts in
Well
Explicitly in board games in in their example, but I think the same applies to video games
And I will post that link in the show notes because I think that is also a very interesting thing to think about when you're thinking about
Why this hugo would allow you to recognize forms of storytelling that the rest of the hugos don't currently
recognize
I think this is probably a point that is made in the
in the report, but the we use the hugos as a way of the
community not merely by the award, but also in what is nominated
surfacing what is good and what is worthy of our attention and
it feels like
Games as the largest entertainment genre are clearly worthy of our attention in terms of the money we spend on them
And it seems it seems likely that science fiction fans are spending at least as much money on
on games as everybody else does that they are a big part of our entertainment life
and
It seems it feels to me that there is an argument that the that the community should be starting to
Build this consensus of what is good
I would add that actually thinking of it in terms of narrative
Helps with one of my small problems with it, which is that because interactive experience or game covers such a wide range of things
And you could be asked to judge a shortlist, which is
you know an interactive
essentially an interactive TV show or
You know a video game
That's sort of an indie narrative game versus maybe a more traditional a game and rpg versus
You know a load of different board games
Just you can be asked to judge between lots of different things in a way that you maybe don't in most categories
Part of the best related work where we just throw everything in
Yeah, they're really more different than out were at answer ball and at world 71
You know what 72 a what sorry?
I don't know what at world 72 is Alison
Um, it's a massive massive labor of love
um compilation of fanzine that has just appeared
It would help if you could use references that people who were born after 1984 you've might know
It's a new fan scene
How is it it would help if you could use references that people who were born before 2000 might know
Basically Alison my experiences are the default of I resent any implication that they are not hashtag ybell privilege
I don't think it's unreasonable to okay, so so
All of our categories do actually have things that are very different in them
And when it starts to become too much of a problem the solution is to split the category
I I I I think we I mean we do and we do manage to give awards in best related work, which work more or less
Uh
Maybe we should save that for a different
Yeah, uh different podcast
one of the points the um report makes and and one of the things I think Alison highlighted a potential pit for last episode
Was that you might end up getting an enormous number of games nominated in such a way that you wouldn't end up with a kind of coherent
Shortlist that the that the nominators had settled on
Um, the report kind of highlights that in any given year
There are roughly 20 games that tend to get put forward to awards
And they tended to each get nominated for sort of two or three awards out of the big
Four or five awards the report highlights and it makes the argument that based on how that clustering works in other award
Categories it is likely that a similar thing would apply
Um for the hugos and I thought that was quite well argued
So I think I think they do highlight that
But you know, yes, there's the so take like
So take like 2017 where you could end up with a plausible shortlist that was horizon zero dawn, which is a fairly traditional aa
RPG
Versus super Mario Odyssey, which has a completely different kind of narrative while also being an aa game
Versus monument valley, which is a little indie game
Versus gloom haven the giant kind of
RPG board game versus
Well a whole other range of stuff basically, but you could you could end up with something that contains quite a
Wide range of different experiences and to me thinking of that as in well
I'm not really trying to assess them based on every different criteria
But if I'm trying to assess them based on what I think gives me the
best science fiction or fantasy like narrative experience and that makes that
I think comparison a bit easier
I mean, it's easy anyway because obviously in 2017 I would give it to horizon zero dawn
But I shouldn't it was a different year where there wasn't like something super amazing on the shortlist
Yeah, they do all seem like games though
Yes, they do all seem like games that is a very good point
But as you will know this I'm a huge horizon zero dawn stan
But what I don't have is a horizon zero dawn t-shirt and I do have a monument valley t-shirt
Monument valley was a phenomenal game and if if anyone listening hasn't played it
I strongly recommend giving it a look because it was fantastic
Yeah, I thought I thought monument valley was a bit really and I I kind of feel
Very well. It was a good run. We made it to the end of 2020
This is the last episode of the podcast everyone pack up
Okay, I will I will say what I thought was wrong with monument valley
Which is that I have probably played too many puzzles for it
Because I didn't I had not realized there was a puzzle element in this game
I just played it through and then it finished and it was like, oh, were there puzzles
Right, okay. I could see I could see I could see that
And and I I feel like a game like monument valley could have worked for me
But it it didn't because although yes, there was points where you had to think about for a minute about what you might do next
It didn't really
So you can actually you can actually fail to get the experience you're supposed to get out of something
For a reason that's got nothing to do
That's probably true of novels as well because there are lots of novels people like that I think are kind of
on rails
No, I think that's true. I think that's true of any medium, right? Like if you
like I'm trying to think of an example like if you're a
there will be
tropes
for instance in tv and film that if you're less familiar with you will find them into playing a certain way in a
In a film or tv show and you'll find that really interesting
But someone who's already seen that kind of interplay done better somewhere else might find it kind of all that and I thought that kind of
Maybe gets a little bit of what you're saying like and I will say like I would I if for eyes a zero dawn
I never want to hugo. I would be at 100% on board with that because I
Good can you get it from my pad?
Oh
PlayStation 4 exclusive. Oh am PC, but that seems less helpful to you
I'll be able to get a PlayStation 4 one day very cheaply won't I?
Okay, well, where do I get my ps5? I'll probably lend you by ps4
I like a lend you horizons are adorn because I've got it
Um, so yes, it's bany also loves it. She'll ban me up that is good. Um
And the next one set in san francisco, sorry I could talk about horizons are adorn for a long time. We should move on
But I think that sample
Shortlist does give you a really good idea and I'm like because I've not played much glume haven but I've played like probably
Enough to know where I would rank it on that list
I haven't finished glume haven because it is a game that would require hundreds of hours
Uh in order to finish
and like, you know
But I think they I think you're right that like the fact that you can focus on the narrative does mean that they can be directly compared
Which is really good and as i listen says they are all they all they all seem like games, which is good
Yeah, and I will concede that while I think this is uh, maybe a wider spread of things to compare than you might get in in best
Novel it's probably no wider selection of things than you do getting some of the other categories
You because you could get extremely different things same you could get in best dramatic presentation short form a five-minute
Short versus a 30-minute documentary versus a one-hour
episode of dramatic television as part of a series and we still happily ask people to compare those so
I guess it's not outside what we do anyway
It makes more sense than trying to nominate games in best related work or
Best dramatic presentation because I do think they are
Too much like I think nominating clipping in dramatic presentation made a lot of sense
And I think in some ways that shares things in common with things it was up against
I mean despite that i'm still not sure it's an ideal fit
I can see how it how you can compare it to other things with a game
It's like well, how do I decide where the glume haven is better than dr. Who like a what?
on what
Metric would I try and make that decision whereas glume haven versus maria wardesee seems like a much
Easier thing to do despite the fact they're still very different
I believe the rubric for hugo awards is something like
um, you're invited to vote for the things you most enjoyed during the year
Yes
And I will say i've played a lot of glume haven and I think it's only okay
But don't tell anyone because i'll be thrown out of the board gaming fandom
Yeah, we better not say that on the internet now do anything
but I will say um
My
Tastes in board games are weird and should not I do not pretend that they are in any way representative of wider board game fandom
Because glume haven is currently the top rated game or board game geek by a significant chunk and
Yeah, fine. So we should actually say so given 2020 being playing games
Um, what do we think we should nominate?
Because I think I think it's obvious what's going to win and I don't think you're gonna like it
It's going to be animal crossing new horizons, right? It is going to be animal crossing new horizons. What do you think? Yes
Okay, okay, okay
I think it is going to get the overwhelmingly largest number of nominations and then I think it's going to win
And it has and I don't think it has very much of the sort of deep narrative
We've been talking about
No, me neither. That's why I have a bit surprised by that pick
Which in fact is what stopped me playing it because I basically went oh, this is pathetic waste of time and honestly I should just grow plants in my garden
I didn't do that either
It is a lot of fun. It is lovely any any suggestion that
That it's a waste of time. It was very good, especially when I was using it as a form of
bonding experience with my family members
Um, but what I will say is that I played the original animal crossing on game cube
Uh, and what I
Found was that it felt an awful lot like
Every so often you come across especially on mobile you come across games where you play them so you can play them and there's no
um
There's no
kind of goal other than the more you play them the more you're allowed to play them and so there's like
A good example of this. They used to play Star Wars command where you play it and you unlock things that mean that you
Um have to spend more time doing things, but the things you unlock
Um means that you can do the things that take longer quicker
And then you can use that to get more points
And then the points you add a lot more things and the cycle just repeats infinitely until you decide to stop playing and
The experience I had on game cube and the experience I've kind of sussed out from watching the discussion about the switch version
Makes me feel awful lot like it's like that and I
Fundamentally don't really understand the appeal
Um, but a lot of people do love it and as I said, I am a ramen so there is that
I mean i haven't played it because i don't want to switch
What?
But I mean I did play a lot of stardew valley which seems like a pretty similar sort of concept
And I enjoyed growing a lot of vegetables and so on
I think stardew valley might have a little bit more narrative because you do have like
uh the narrative in the you know your
Relationships with the other villages that you can kind of unlock as you go through definitely not a 2020 game there
No, it's definitely not a 2020 game. I'm just saying that's the nearest
Comparison so so other 2020 games guys. Well, that's the thing is I was looking at all these, you know lists of best games 2020
They came out. I think I have played one game which came out in 2020. So that's really not very helpful
and and that game is um
Fall guys ultimate knockout which
Also doesn't have any narrative unless the narrative is that I put on a horse's head
On my little wobbly guy and ran around but that's not really narrative
So I think there's lots of things I could say might be candidates for game of the year
um
Like probably the last of us part two which I haven't played because I got stuck in the last first part one and it's too hard
As another assassin's creed game. There's a half-life game. There's cyberpunk 2077
If you have a computer that will actually play it, but I haven't actually played any of these games. So
I am told Hades is very good and I should play it
Oh, yes, that's the other one, but yeah again. I
I don't I'm a bit limited to gaming devices to
phone and ipad and
PlayStation so
John have you played any games 2020?
Basically, I'm trying to work out how you can get board game geek to show you games that came out in 2020
I can tell you for free that I have not played any video games that came out in 2020. Um, I just looked
Oh, I was thinking of things that would actually be eligible for this year's hugo, which means it has to be
A video game. Oh, no, I think and this and this draws me neatly onto why I think this is a terrible idea because I think the the
um
The hugo as suggested by our ira
Alexander day is a great thing. I would enthusiastically join in with the dc announcement of the hugo
They have decided to trial. I cannot nominate anything for and I think those are
different enough takes on the two suggestions that I am skeptical that the dc one will
Adequately stress test this from my perspective because I just think my interests are so much more in the tabletop direction than in the video game
Um direction, but the most recent two games I have played are pokemon sword
Which was 2019 and jennifer on order which was 2019. Um, so I have not as far as I know played any 2020 games
I think it is did did you not play star wars quadrants?
Uh, I played it for like two hours, but yes technically I did
Um, and I could probably nominate that but it wouldn't be because I
Had thought about all the games in 2020. I had played and decided that that one was good. It would be because
It's not because you like it. I have opinions on board games in 2020 though
So, you know if they ever announce a board game you go come back to me
Well, what what would be for your nominations for board game in 2020?
um, so um in 2020 there is a
board game that was released called the search for planet x which I really enjoy
Shut up and sit down reviewed it and my friend bought it for me for my birthday
And um, I have thoroughly enjoyed playing that. It's kind of a logical deduction game where you play astronomers
Um, and I was initially like oh god. This is good. A ui day job, but a board game
How am I gonna find this leisurely or relaxing?
But it turns out it's really good because um, the way you publish papers is really nice at like there are so many
Interesting little ways in which the mechanics really neatly fit how astronomy works in real life
Um, and yeah, I really really enjoy it. It's a bit like a more complex version of cluedo
almost
um in that
It's a logical deduction game, but it's not as luck based as cluedo and it is more space themed
So it is in two ways much more up my alley
Um, the other one I've really been enjoying it will not surprise anyone to learn is that I have bought the arkam horror expansion
the insmith conspiracy and
My wife and I have been playing through and it is I thought the last arkam horror expansion was okay like obviously
They're just staying for the fact I'm a huge fan of arkam horror and just comparing its other arkam horror products
I thought it was fine. Um, this one I am really enjoying and I think it might be my favorite campaign that I've made so far
So like I've also been hugely enjoyed that so those would be by two picks if I was going to nominate board game based things
Um, and then I was trying to look up what other expansions I might have bought
um, and I think
I can't remember when marvel champions released the um
Their big box expansion, but I might be tempted to nominate that as well
Um, but yes
Oh, oh and no, sorry. I forgot one. There's a game called artifact
Oh, was that in 2019 or 2020? I can't remember now
But there's a um a single player role playing came called artifact, which is a journaling game
And I got the the chap who makes it lives in south hampson and a friend of mine
Um, pointed me at his twitter feed because he was selling factory seconds of the game and I hadn't heard of it
So I didn't back the kickstarter but I got a copy of the physical version for cheap softness twitter and um, it's a game where you
Basically in most role playing games that are like fantasy driven or maybe not most but like, you know, oh g
Oh gd and d for instance you go on your adventure you find the dragon you slay it you marry the hot prince
And you get the loot and artifacts the game where you find a mysterious artifact in the loot and you single player
Are given a bunch of prompts and you play a game telling the backstory of the artifact you found in the loot
And I would also say that would I would highly recommend that from a kind of narrative
Perspective, um, and I think that would be a really good
I don't think you would ever make it onto the shortlist because it is a very very sporking
Um, but um, but yeah, I would also I would also enthusiastically not only that I think
It is a it is a trice trice game a solo rpg zine
a
Mm-hmm the advent of um cheap print a was around plus kickstarter
plus the renaissance in like um small experimental rpgs has meant there is a
A large proliferation in recent times of little zines that do interesting things with the rpg format and solo rpging or
um, there are several rpgs where you play by mail and you basically physically mail the rpg to like the next player and it's kind of
executive rather than concurrent and there's some really interesting stuff being done
this feels like the um
an interaction between um
interactive experiences and
game books and fanzines and I quite like that as a
Model I mean, I like things that match up different genres
Oh, I tell a lie. I have played two 2020 video games because I also played
uh
Just dance 2021
Yeah, no, it's just about to ask is um, his ring fit adventure a 2020 video game because I did play that
Oh, I think it's probably 2019. Let me check. I'm so I feel like it would be on
Fair enough. I wouldn't nominate it because I don't think it's sf no or all good, but um
Beyond that
It is clearly it is clearly sf no enough, but not very
Well, that's true. It does have a demon in it, doesn't it?
Yeah, I mean almost one of the things it does say in this um
In this report is that the vast majority of games have sf and fantasy content
They don't all but an enormous enormous number of them do. I mean that is probably fair, isn't it?
Yep, so no twer ringford to venture despite the fact that again it came to prominence in twer
So I think one of the issues here is that that unlike novels and um
Movies in particular games really do burn through slightly more slowly apart from apart from the triple-a games
Games do have a longer life expectancy. Yes, that's true
I mean among us is new for ipad in 2020 and I feel like it's it's a very convenient
It's very convincing as an ipad game
Um, but of course it's not a new game. It's been around a year or two and that's not uncommon
Well, and that that neatly segues into I think
One of the things I wanted to talk about which is the idea of substantial
modifications
And the argument made in the report is that you can basically say you're allowed to dominate substantial modifications
And the substantial modifications will get lots of nominations and the insubstantial ones will get hardly any nominations
And this will neatly fix itself
the issue I
see
is stuff like among us where among us is not a
2020 video game really it was released before that
But it's definitely hit prominence in 2020
And it has had a version released on a platform where it hitherto did not exist released in 2020
And I suspect there are people who would not realize it was pre-existing game who would nominate it
And then the administrators would have to decide are they nominated to get because they think the ipad version is a substantial
qualification or are they nominating it because it was very popular this year and
Is it therefore eligible or is it therefore not?
And I think this is actually a thornier issue than the report wants it to be and i'm not sure the report does a good job here
Yeah, but it is in fact not a thorny issue because the ipad version of a game is just like the paperback version of a novel
And we do have prior
Are it's not like mythic quest ravens banquet
Which is obviously a substantial modification of mythic quest therefore eligible in this category
That was a masterful reference
Is it not only is it eligible in this category, but i'm saying now
I'm going to nominate it and I hope that lots of other people do too
Oh
God
TV account are you nominating a
fictional video game
It's definitely it's definitely not eligible. It's definitely fictional. It's a it's a tv show
Um about a fictional video game. It is a substantial modification of a previous video game
Um, but hopefully sometime in 2021
Mythic quest ravens banquet will be released as a video game and then it will be fine
That would be brilliant
Um
It's difficult because it's sort of genre in the sense that it talks about science fiction because it does have a character who has one an epular
And is brilliant
um played by um, oh, what's his name the guy who played the senior good go out world in stargate sg one
go out
Go out world
Which one is the senior one? Hang on though the one that like t york
f mary abraham, that's the chap
Is spanish just texted me from the other room to tell me the answer is f re abraham. Thank you, early
Real time follow up from our live stream
It's difficult because it's a show about making a genre game that therefore has quite a lot of genre
Like adjacentness pleido whether it would be eligible for the best short form hugo or not really
But then upon 2013 like it is real gray area in things that discuss the genre
It's pretty it's nerdy enough. I think I think if it got nominations in
Um, best dramatic presentation short form, which i'm not entirely sure it should do
Um, I think at that point the hugo ministers would have a choice to make it. I think they probably would go
Oh, yeah, this is kind of genreish
I I would like to take us back just one second, which is
Do you say f re abraham was in star gate?
Yeah
Really?
Yeah, he plays the senior go out he plays like um, oh, what's his name?
Well, this is the thing then I could search him out
Uh craytack
Craytack is it something like that a star gate
Oh, that's braytack and that's not f mary abraham. That's why i'm confused
Oh, in that case, it's my
It's my fault then
Well, I was yet
Who plays him then they look very similar
I think it's a man who's very looks very similar. Um
Oh, well, this is just confusing people shouldn't look alike
Having just seen the prestige. I can confirm that that's true. Nothing good comes of people who look alike
I mean, it's very very confusing
He he has played a lot of different things there
He has just not the one I said he had
So that's which is an important point which I should be brought up on
But I think me and espania both thought it was him so
He has a guy called tony amendola. So that's why i'm confused. Well, it's not him and he's also not a ghoul
but anyway, this is
Revealing too much about my star trek watching habits. Yeah
There's a website on cheeseburger.f mary abraham totally looks like tony abadola
Excellent. Can you send me that website so I can put it at the show notes so I can prove that I am not mad
You are not mad. Um, but I mean you're not mad for this
Um, hang on. This is great. Yeah, but it's not really you heard a point
They do look very similar
Still on the subject of the games you go. Um, firstly, um, I think that um
2020 is is possibly quite a bad year to trial this category
Because I think the triple a gaming industry has taken a little bit of a
Dropping with covid the really the only big ticket game I can think of that's come out this year except for animal crossing is cyberpunk
I am wondering and a lot of board games have not
Done well either. So I am kind of wondering whether this is the wrong year to try this and I do
Wonder whether we'll see that when the nominations kind of come in
I think there'll be a I think there have been an awful lot of even more than usual
sequels and quotes substantial modifications and
things of that kind um
It is an issue with the gaming industry generally that it makes it's money by selling you the product once and then selling you more bits of it
Um, that also works for novels and
And tv shows and movies as we see
But the hugo voters have always been quite fond of
Original content and I think you'll see some of that in the in the nominations in this category
I see when I see we should trust the hugo voters to come up with a good category and it'll be good
Yeah, um, the other thing I will say is that I think we should probably touch on
The fact that the nebula awards also reward games, but they reward it specifically for the writing of the games
And I was wondering whether the two of you think that will mean that there is more or less
Overlap between the nebulas and the hugos than in most other categories where they have a kind of shared
theme so obviously the nebula novels and hugos usually have a couple in common
So the thing is it's only been like two
Two years of the nebula for best game writing
Yeah, it's a very new category for the nebula's. I thought it was interesting that they were doing it
Yeah, didn't banda snatch get a nomination
So banda snatch one the first one. Yeah
banda snatch one and and
I mean banda snatch is kind of
You know banda snatch is not interactive it it pretends to be interactive
But it has it has zero interactive content and I get very worst off about that sort of thing
Um, I like my games to involve gameplay and there is no gameplay and banda snatch you end up doing the same thing on all routes
It's just you can miss bits out
So, um
the winner in 2019 was the outer worlds and the winner in 2018 as we said was banda snatch
The nominees in 2019 were outer worlds the magicians workshop
Disco Elysium and the fate accessibility toolkit and then in 2018 were the road to Canterbury god of war rent a voice and the martian job
I will note that
Although there's a lot of clustering in the other big awards the report mentions the nebulas are quite quite different
I think to the games that were generally getting recognition
Um, so I my hunch is that the he goes would skew more towards
The bigger awards than the nebulas have done
But I don't know and it's interesting to see how different the nebula short lists were to the kind of prevailing wisdom in the rest of
Of gaming as it were and I wonder if that's obviously the nebula definition is to do with
Um, specifically the writing so it's it's an award for best game writing not for best game
So I wonder if that has a because I completely ignores ludonarrative
I am very interested to see what
How the community starts to write about this how other people start to what they take on this and is and whether
And whether we're going to see some campaigning around this is a chance to recognize video game writers who of course
you know often
are speculative fiction writers or that that that example of the
Writer who wants one a nebula is
They would not have put that into their tv show unless they got it from somewhere and they got it from game the games industry where
um
Science fiction writers are employed in droves
So I would say the nebula's look a little bit like an outlier to me because there's
many nominations from uh choice of games, which is uh a game studio. I haven't heard of who make interactive
Fiction um, but I recognize the names as being people who already
have been writing short fiction or novels already. So it may be that in some cases
Uh more s fw a members had played those game because they already knew the writers of those games
Then would be apparent in like the wider hugo field
It would be quite wrong of me to suggest that or alternatively they nominated things that were eligible by people
They like regardless of whether they'd had any involvement in the game whatsoever
and that is also a risk for the
Hugos, but I think less of one in this category than in some of the others
Yeah, I mean, I think it's also very new. It's clearly uh shaking itself down, but it will be interesting
To see where that goes if it does kind of converge with a hugo or split part completely and start rewarding different things
The poet laureate of the old thought podcast claire brianley of groiden has sent us a festive poem
Which we will end the podcast with today
I mean, I would I would like to say that I thought wouldn't this be a great idea and vaguely made a very sh*t attempt at it
Uh and don't mention it to claire and claire sent us a much much much better one
So we should really be thanking claire not only for the excellent poem, but also for saving you from my poetry
Yeah from saving you from the octa thoughts cruise version of this poem, which would not have been as good
I think it's fair to say
I sent claire a text message that said
We're thinking we're thinking about doing a christmas octa thought version of towards the night before christmas or
Um a visit from st. Nicholas, which is its proper name and I sent her that text message at
uh about quarter to
12 on the 16th of december and at about a quarter to five on the 16th of december we received this poem which claire had immediately
um
been seized with the need to write um so thank you very much claire it is fantastic
A visit from st. octa thought
towards the night before christmas when all through the house
Which is not very big but its best not to grouse
Not a creature was stirring not even a shrew
And there nestled shrug snug was the octa thought crew
Not too many time zones apart but instead together in one giant comedy bed
With visions of fested and fester of relaxing and rest or board games and card games and oculus quest
Allison liz in pyjamas with wine and john in his underpants star wars design
Was startled to hear in their silent night place the familiar music of fanfare for space
They all checked their phones text and discord and zoom and then thought of looking outside of the room
When what to their wondering eyes should appear but a bathtub with moose in the place of reindeer
No implausible mcu manifestation, but st. octa thought driving his own punctuation
Now dash now apostrophe hyphen ellipsis on comma on colon
Now who did i miss?
Of course you're essential both full stop and bracket land here on the roof and let's not make a racket
As if they were listening at double speed there was st octa thought what did he need
Can you help me he asked i'm in quite an odd fix i must fill this bathtub with fresh wheat a fix
The moose eat it constantly licking and slurping i tried them on turbinates but can't stand the burping
We know what you mean liz confided unplanned but john turned his mind to the matter at hand
For some reason we have a hundred to spare a plethora alice and surely that's fair
I like we to fix but some friends called my bluff. It seems i was wrong i could not have enough
And st octa thought said as he made his escape, you know, that's the title of your next sex tape
Of course he less presence in thanks for the food the patron of podcasters wouldn't be rude
There's no need to list them here nevertheless
You've all heard the podcast i bet you could guess
The bathtub threw off as they all waved goodbye towards the magnetosphere not quite that high
But they heard him exclaim as you all knew he might
Merry christmas to all and to all a good night and then as the moose took their ultimate leap
Remember this podcast will end at the beep beep