I know I had a joke on one of the letters, let me find it.
I can't remember, I cannot remember.
If you remember the joke, record a pickup and get John to drop it in and we'll fake some laughter.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 64th episode of Octa Thorpe, a podcast for Science Fiction
and Science Fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 18th of August 2022. I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Ms Batty and we're like eight squared Octa Thorpe.
Oh yeah we are.
Will you still need me? Will you still feed me? etc.
We're going to get banned from like Apple podcasts if you think that.
Not if I sing it, it's fine.
Liberty will notice.
First up we'd like to apologise to Andr and Caroline who's emails to us got caught in a spam trap
and as a result we have changed our email address to comment@octa Thorpecast.uk
and we are hoping that this will resolve any future issues.
So if you're emailing us, please note the change in email address.
We will carry on checking the old one for a little bit including the spam trap but do
send stuff to the new address.
Yes.
So Andr wrote in about episode 62 to say that she had read one of the Hugo nominees which is
a master of Jin which is unusual because she doesn't usually have a Worldcom membership and
when she does she doesn't usually download much of the voter packet.
I mean and agrees with me about Chard's worth being great so and thank you for writing in.
You're my favourite now.
She also says that she thinks she is an optimistic nihilist based on my explanation of my views
and that is entirely sensible I think.
Caroline also emailed us about OctaOpt62 because she is also reading all of the Hugo
shortlisted novels this year and she says that she is also stranded with the last one part read
which in her case was the master of Jin and she was stranded a third through because she wasn't
really enjoying it and she says that it and she who became the son were the two that she had to
finish for duty rather than for love which is pleasing because that feels like it's like a theme
in both those books you know duty versus personal life so that's good that is good to
exposition Caroline thank you very much.
Yeah thank you all to Caroline I think she picked up on a few things that we didn't mention
and in my case it was probably because I hadn't thought about them but there were a few things
I realised you know there were whole swathes of stuff about the novels that we didn't mention
so maybe next time it has to be not only like a bumper episode but maybe a bumper
bumper episode to fit all the Hugo novels in there really was a lot to discuss.
Yes.
OctaOpt.
Special extended edition.
Indeed indeed.
Mark Plummer writes I've just learnt that Galactic Journey is blocked on my office
IT network with the stated reason being marijuana and if you have ever been to 1967 you know why.
That's my joke sorry guys.
Excellent.
And Mark also says that he's very grateful to John for telling him about Knights of the Old Republic
and he's expecting it to in the weeks of time to come fill up as much of his time as playing Arkham
Horror Dust.
Excellent.
And he thought that it was great for the creator of the Great Potato War
is a YouTuber.
Oh.
That is great Mark.
Thank you very much and it also gives us our episode title so that's nice.
He also says that he was thinking of me earlier when he was looking through Kevin Smith's
TAF report which has just come out and is a report of the TAFTrip in 1982 and there's a passage
that says along with the badges there were ribbons.
My Yellow Ribbon said program on it and meant I was taking part in programed events.
It is entirely possible to have more than one ribbon and obviously I have never had more than
one ribbon at a convention.
I am very ribbon minimalist and anyone who is at WorldCom will be able to see the extent to which
that is a lie.
I think I drew you as a ribbon collector once.
For my TAFT report.
Yeah.
On your TAFT report also now available.
There'll be a link to the show notes.
And I think I did put all of my ribbons in my TAFT report by my Be Misremembering.
But I think you can see it if you buy it.
Well done to Kevin Smith for getting his TAFT report out after only 40 years.
Is this a record?
Bill Higgins wrote to us and said, well this is going to be much shorter than it usually is
when he heard me open the podcasts with the words hello everyone and welcome to the 62nd
episode of Octa Thorpe.
So thank you very much.
Bill, Mark, you don't get the prize for most tortured joke in this episode which is weird
but you're up against very stiff competition.
But thank you very much to Bill for airing.
I believe I'm on a panel with Bill at WorldCom which we will discuss later in the episode.
For shadowing and stuff.
Oh, we should talk about our schedules.
Yes.
We shall.
And we got a letter from Chris Garcia.
Yay.
We also had a letter from Chris Garcia.
Chris Garcia, please write in and tell us how you got the omelet jeff to do you a no egg omelet
or was it just kind of a plate of emptiness.
Or in fact, no, right.
And just tell me in a couple of weeks time.
Yep, indeed.
Yeah, if you're going to see a such icon you don't need to write, you can just tell us things.
But if you want them to appear on the podcast, right.
That's comment@octashopecast.uk.
We also got a tweet from Raj and Raj said thank you for pointing them to the Hugo Girl podcast.
You're very welcome, Raj. And on the subject of Hugo Girl, we had a big old discussion on Twitter
about hotel eggs. And, you know, go and read that if you like eggs.
We have submitted our Hugo Ballots and we're going to talk a little bit about what we put where.
Shall I talk about the Briarly voting competence threshold?
Which is the notion that you should only vote in a category if you have actually
absorbed all of the things in that category well enough to have appropriate opinions on
where they should be ranked.
And I'm not sure I normally do this in very many categories.
I think that's also true this year.
So I did vote in all the categories in which I was competent to vote under that standard,
which was novel and all the fan categories.
I think that was it.
And I also voted in a load of other categories just because.
So if you ever wonder whether people vote from positions of ignorance in the
Hugos, it's right they do. I'm sorry.
And I'm sure I'm not the only one, but I voted for short story for reasons that I will
explain later despite the fact that I hadn't read them all.
And I voted for novel for novella for because I had only read some of them,
but I've really enjoyed the ones I read and I thought they were very worthy of winning a Hugo.
So how do you guys stand on the broadly voting competence threshold?
Voted in best novel, best novella, best novel at best short story, best series,
best dramatic presentation, long for best direct presentation, short for best
edit, short form, best professional artist, best semi-prosean, best fanzine, best fan cast,
best fan writer, best fan artist, load start understanding.
I voted in exactly the same category as John, it turns out.
So my little rant here is because of the current 20% threshold,
I feel I need to vote in every category where I feel qualified to cast a vote at all.
That is more than I can possibly read.
The Hugo ballot at the moment contains more than I can possibly read between the date that
the finalists come out and the date when voting closes, because it's six novels,
it's six books in the load star awards, it's six novelettes,
it's six pieces of short fiction or more for this Downing Award,
in this case, at least three of them were nominated based on books,
and then we got into best series, which is, and it happens that I have read like part of a couple
of series, but that's by it, and then I haven't spent the 12 or 15 hours or whatever it is,
I would need to watch everything in best dramatic presentation, long form, too much stuff.
Yeah, so the three categories I voted in in which I did not have a view of everything were
dramatic presentation, short form, best editor, short form and best semi-prosean,
and that's because I can't possibly read, I voted in semi-prosean and best editor, short form,
and I think, although best series, I didn't, I also didn't read all the series, but I actually
find that editor, short form and best pro and best semi-prosean are the two that are most
difficult to get a wide view of, because it does involve a lot of reading, and because I read
series because they are one of the bits of science fiction I actually engage with,
I'm usually got quite the head start on that category, whereas like I read one semi-prosean
every year. Which one? Uncanny. I noticed when I was reading short fiction that the uncanny
selection of fiction had a load of fantastic things in, and also that uncanny had a lot of things
that when I was doing my short fiction reading, I really quite liked, so yeah, no, I might be
joining you and subscribing to Uncanny because it's full of things I liked. Yeah, I mean Uncanny,
there is a reason it keeps winning best semi-prosean, and that is generally because it is very good,
and I, I subscribe to it. I use Subscribe to Clark's World, and I eventually unsubscribed,
because I find Clark's World's editorial voice quite, if you read it for a couple of years,
you start seeing there's very much a formula to what goes into a Clark's World story that I
started to get quite irritated with, whereas I find Uncanny a little bit more varied, although I
think if you read any magazine for long enough, you start to see the, the kind of the recurring themes,
and sometimes it can get a little bit frustrating. I also, I used to listen to Escape Pod, and I,
I voted for Escape Pod because I very much want Escape Pod to win. I think it would be good to
recognise the work they do, and that is also why I voted for Laffeti and Divya for editor short form,
but shall we go through our ballots? I'm happy to pull some highlights out of my ballot.
We can do some highlights, I think. By a figure, we can say what we vote, we put top in like each of
the categories we voted in. Yeah, the short, or Lisa short, let's try the short fiction ones and
see how far we get without running out of time. All right, so what did we all put top in the
Vella? I put the Pastors Red by Catherine Valenti. Oh, I put that second, I put a sum for the wild
built as first. I put the Elder Race first and a sum for the wild built second, and I confess I
haven't read the Calc Valenti so I'm feeling very guilty now. I will read it though. I will say
that to my great surprise having not really enjoyed the eyes of the Becky Chambers novels I've read,
I put a sum for the wild built third as well with Elder Race in second. This sounds like our maybe
top three are quite settled there, but I did find a sum for the wild built maybe just because
it was a shorter length worked much, much better for me than the galaxy in the ground within did.
When I think having read Chambers' novella that was nominated last year, year before,
I thought it was very different to her novels. I mean, I enjoy both, but it doesn't surprise me that
there, that you might have quite a different opinion on them because I do think she is doing
quite different things in the two. I think the one from Tovea Year is actually more different from
her novels than some for the wild built is, but I did enjoy both quite a lot. And I did enjoy,
I put Elder Race third. I thought it was very good. I know we're not doing a long talk about the
things, but I thought the fact that a sum for the wild built and the Elder Race both have this
theme of the separation of different cultures and people getting together unexpectedly with
a culture that the cultures have been long separated was really interesting. And they had quite a lot
of points of commonality. I enjoyed them both very much indeed. I was really pleased to have read them.
You have inadvertently noticed a theme in the past is read as well, interestingly.
I think it's interesting because they're all about that, right? In a way, maybe not a spindle
splintered as such, but certainly they're all stories of culture clashes. Like Fireheart Tiger
is, and across the Greengrass Fields definitely is. I mean, I did, I will say again, I enjoyed
everything in this category quite a lot. I think there's a little bit of a gap between the top
three and the bottom three, but I did enjoy all of the bottom three. I would agree. I mean,
I would say the thing in the top three is it's kind of a culture clash, maybe between
civilizations at different levels of progression and industrialization, which is maybe not present
in the lower ones. That was quite interesting. Yeah. So maybe the Macquire had that. But I like
that Valenti kind of ties that one back. I thought it was a good novel tackling climate change in
a way the other two are not looking at. Yeah, definitely. And actually reminded me of one of
the themes from Horizon Forbidden West. Novelette, what did we put in novelette? I put the bots of
the Lost Ark by Suzanne Palmer. I guess I had a really hard time deciding between them, but I
ended up with that story isn't the story by John Wizwell at the top from Oncanny. So,
Alison, did you vote in novelette? I didn't vote, but I've since read several of these stories.
I really liked unsely brothers, but I thought it was a little, I thought it was a tiny bit slight,
but I really, really enjoyed it. So, you know, I liked so many things about it. That's interesting.
And I did like that story isn't the story. I thought that was very clever, but it was kind of,
I was sitting in a field in the glorious sunshine listening to fantastic music and
it wasn't the story I wanted to be reading right then. So, that's not the fault of the story, it's a
fault of me. I put that story isn't the story was a strong third. Very much enjoyed that. I,
when I read it in Oncanny gave on Silly Brothers three out of five and it languishes in fourth on
my ballad. Again, I thought it was, I thought there was quite a gap between my top three and my bottom
three. And I, I thought this is probably the weakest category on the ballad. I don't know if that's fair.
Short story? Short story. I think we might be unanimous here. Oh, do you reckon? What did you
put first Liz? Where Oak and Hearts together. Alison, what did you put first? I have to say,
I loved one of the stories in this category so inordinately that I've put it as my pick this week.
Which I know is why I was saying that. And that's not surprising because that story was cat lit for
Alison's. I mean, if somebody has sat down to write a story that Alison would love, they could not
have done better. It was fantastic. So, and that is where Oak and, where Oak and Hearts together.
I put it in second, thought it was a strong second. What did you put first? Mr. Death,
because I cried like a baby at the end, just a story had everything for me. Oh, I put that second,
I have not read that story yet. So, like it just hit me straight in the feels listeners,
just like this is my feels. That's the story. Boom, but both very good.
I put it in second on the grounds I cried but did not feel like emotionally manipulated into it.
And I think that is a very, very hard line to walk. It's such a beautiful ending and it feels,
it feels simultaneously so earned, but I didn't see it coming. And I think that's a really,
sorry Alison. Alison hasn't read it and is very enthusiastically.
We're not going to spoil it, we just say we cried. I'll read it between now and when I get the
transcript to do. I did also like, I liked very much all of these stories. I think Tangles was
my least favorite, but I feel like if it hadn't been a story written from Magic the Gathering,
it would have been better. It's told very straightforwardly, which I assume is at least
part because that tends to be what franchise short stories call for. I really, I started
really, really liking Tangles and then I felt it kind of wound up in a way that was a little
bit unsatisfying. But having now noticed that it's a Magic story which I had not noticed,
it's like, oh no, that makes perfect sense now. I do, yeah. But I mean, and very, very good.
Again, very strong category, I thought. Best series. Best series.
I'm like, I haven't read anything in this one. That was a problem. Rather read a tiny bit.
I have only read three in this category. The world of the white rat, I read one of them and it was
fantastic. And I will read the rest enthusiastically by did not have time in the deadline. I have
been reading the way with children series as we've been going through the hugos over the last few
years because they keep getting nominated. And then Terra Ignota by Ada Palmer. Now,
too like the Lightning was a finalist while back. And I confess, sorry, Neil, I did not really like it.
And so I put, so that affected my rating. But I did not get to any of the series. I had not,
I had not read any of already, if that makes sense, except for the Kingfisher,
slash Vernon title, which I put first. Well, again, I've read, John, I've read exactly the same as you
apart from the, I haven't read the Vernon, but I didn't get to it. I read too like the Lightning,
and I've read all the way with children because they're on the Hugo ballots in previous years.
I wonder if that will affect the voting in this category. It might, it might well. I wonder whether
Vernon will take it because, I mean, she's great. I mean, I've liked everything of hers I've read,
so I wouldn't be surprised. Yep. But I also wouldn't be surprised to see where
with children take it because I think it's an excellent series of novellas.
I did feel bad not, not reading the Stross because that was in the packet. And I did,
I did, I fully intended to read it and I just ran out of time. It was, it would have been my next
book, because I read series after astounding and load star. But Jade City by Fondalee
wasn't in the packet at all. And the CL Polk series, they'd put the third installment in,
and I kept thinking I should probably start at the beginning. And then I did not get around to it.
I put for dramatic presentation long form in Canto in first. I love that movie quite a bit.
Again, this is one of the categories I thought was weaker than most of the ballot. I didn't think
it was a strong showing for dramatic presentation this year. I think there are quite a few movies
that people told me about that did not make it on here that I think are probably better than
some of the ones. I put June first because I loved it despite the fact that it's only half a movie
and it doesn't really do anything. And there's a lot of things wrong with it. I still loved it.
That's good though, don't it? Really just for the,
or for copters, what's that called? Ornacopters, yeah, loved them.
Ornicopters. I just can't say why I liked it. In Canto got my second vote,
because I also thought that was very, very good. And if it hadn't, pulled its pudges in a shockingly
Disney way at the very end, I would probably have put it first.
Yeah, I vote the same as Alison with Wonder Vision in third, and I did not get around to watching
the others. Best dramatic presentation short form. There's an obvious first choice here. I think
Liz, what did you put in first choice? I mean, I thought there was a first choice, but I'm not
sure it's gonna be the same as your first choice. What did you pick? I went with For All Mankind,
because I really liked that episode. Oh, interesting. That was my second. And that is,
I think, a strong second. I did love that episode, but now I went for Wedge Dodge.
I have no idea if I'm pronouncing that correctly, because it's Klingon. I thought you would, yeah.
But Star Trek Lower Decks is still a highlight of my genre watching, and it is fantastic.
I had not watched any of Star Trek Lower Decks, and they put this episode into the packet.
I didn't have needed to do that, because I have Amazon Prime, but I noticed it was in the packet,
and I thought, "Oh, I'm supposed to be doing something else. I could definitely procrastinate
and watch this instead of doing the thing I'm supposed to be doing." And it had the Hugo Award
written over it, so I went and got it off Amazon Prime instead, and I went, "Oh, this is great,
but I don't understand it, so let me watch the very first episode of Star Trek Lower Decks,
and then this one." And I laughed, and laughed, and laughed, and laughed, and laughed, and it's not
that. It's not necessarily great science fiction, and some of the humor is a bit juvenile, but,
"Oh, I do like it a lot. I'm going to watch the whole of it now." Whenever I'm feeling miserable,
I'm going to watch an episode of Star Trek Lower Decks till I catch up.
That's how I gave it a vote, yes. But I am not competent to vote in this category, because,
as you know, guys, I don't watch enough television. I also gave a vote to Feral Magkide on the grounds
that it must... everyone who's actually watched it says it's very good, so, you know.
But lots of people don't have Apple TV, so it probably won't win.
I didn't watch, I didn't watch, I also watched Feral Magkide on the Expanse on Loki, but I didn't
watch the other two, because, again, if you haven't seen the episode of... I mean, I'm never going to
watch Wheel of Time. Sorry Wheel of Time fans, really not my cup of tea. And I am, arcane is on
the big list of things I might watch at one point, because I have heard really good things,
but the episode that got nominated was ninth. And so I would have had to watch four and a half
to five hours of television to understand it, I think. And I was like, I do not have five hours
spare, unfortunately. Especially because, very inconsiderately, all of the TV networks are
releasing TV, like it's not August. And therefore, I've gained further and further behind with all
of my watching. Cannot actually watch dramatic presentation to short form as if it were short form,
because it isn't really, it's all like... It's never a short film or anything self-contained,
it's always episode nine in a ten episode series. And so it's yet another thing that kind of demands
a lot of attention. Though I do think Star Wars, Lower Decks, you didn't need to do much homework
in order to enjoy that episode. And it was very funny, so well done. And it's quite nice having
humour. It's quite a something funny science fiction in the ballot. I like that. I'd like to
see some more of that, please. I mean, in a way, Lower Decks is building on the fact that you have,
you know, 50 years of accumulated Star Trek in the public consciousness that makes it very funny.
It's quite funny, even if you don't. It's got quite a lot of jokes that work. If you don't
know the reference and then work on a different level, if you do, that's what this sort of humour
should do, and I like that. I think I'm going to compare, and this might be hugely grandiose,
I'm going to compare Lower Decks to Pixar. Hold on, strap in. I think Lower Decks does a really good
job of having lots of jokes in it that work on a variety of different people. Like, you could have
just seen DS9, and there will be jokes for you, and you could have just seen Voyager, and there will
be jokes for you. You could have not seen anything, and there will be jokes for you. It's like a
Pixar movie doing jokes for the kids and jokes for the grown-ups. Like, I think they're very good
at it, because it's very easy to do jokes where you're like, I can tell that was a joke, and I don't
get it, and now I feel left out, and I don't think Lower Decks does that, and I think that's a very
difficult thing that it does very well. I mean, obviously, having seen lots of Star Trek, I do
get some of the jokes, and I mean, we laugh very much. There are also jokes about the fandom, and
ways in which they bring things about the fandom into Star Trek canon so they can make fun of them,
and that is also very good. And it's just very good. I like it a great, great, great deal.
Quite a lot of jokes about science fiction culture generally, and series is, and the whole structure
of not being the stars, and things like that, I love it. It's so good.
When you get to the episode with the plates in it, you're just texting.
Oh yeah. It's not the best episode. That should have, that should have been all the balance.
I actually will tell you which episode of The Dose to Put on the Ballot.
Best commemorative plate. You go category.
You heard it here first. Special, special award for Glasgow Esther. Come on, you've got to.
Right, shall we talk about the load star? My Top Pick was Redemptor by Jordan Ifueku,
which is a previous Octopic. I think Liz picked it maybe. I can't remember.
I did pick it, and I also put it in first, but then I only read two books in this category. Sorry.
I've really struggled in this category. I suspect I'm going to like a lot of the others,
because I've liked previous books by Darcy Little Badger, and I've liked stuff by
Chai Jin Anders, but I just did not get round to them, and I thought I should vote anyway.
Yep. Have you read any of these, Alison?
I've read about half of Victory's Greater Than Death.
I would say one honourable mention for Chaos on CatNet, and the prequel, or not the prequel.
It's a sequel. The original book in the series, which was Cat Fishing on CatNet, I think,
which are both, which are very good, and I'm not sure. They both talk about abuse in really
interesting ways, and I really liked that about them. I mean, and I very much liked a lot of the
books in this category, but the Naomi Critzes are particularly ones I enjoyed as well.
A astounding award. Me and Liz both put Miquaya Johnson in first. Have I guessed correctly, Liz?
Yeah, guess correctly. Hey! And then I put Shelley Park Chan, and then I put
Evarina Maxwell. Evarina Maxwell was my second. I really, really, really liked her book. I thought
it was really good, and I enthusiastically recommended it to Nick, because it has "pining".
And I was like, "You like pining? You all like this book?" And she was like, "Oh."
It is, I mean, it is a lot of your A03 tags made into a book, as you might expect.
I liked it a lot. But again, generally speaking, I think, loads of, sorry, astounding was a very
strong category this year. There was only one author where the books they have written, I was like,
"Eh, not sure. All the others wrote stuff I enjoyed."
Moving swiftly onwards, what we're going to cover in our last 12 minutes?
Worldcon schedules. All right, we've got some. Yeah, we do. I am on some panels. We're all on a
panel called Hugo Award finalist rehearsal, but you can't come to that listeners. Apparently,
there's no audience. Although that would be very funny. So yes, we're all doing that. And then,
what else are you two doing? Liz, do you want to go first?
I can do. I am doing a panel called DNA is Just a Code, which is about genetics,
so, hey, I like genetics. I'm doing con running in age of COVID-19, which would be interesting,
so I will talk about punctuation. I will probably talk about, you know,
Eastercons and Worldcons and all the stuff that we have been talking about for two and a half years,
whenever there's a lot of other topics of conversation. I'm running a in-person
convention tour, so if you are new to Ch icon, you can come along on Friday and I will show you
how conventions are organized in person. And I'm doing a panel called Everything I Know,
I Learned From Fandom, because everything I know I learned from fandom. Okay. Cool. That sounds like
a good mix of panels, a good mix of like, fanish stuff and your professional expertise as well,
which I think is always nice. Yeah, I mean, I did massively foggyed up by
warning to future people. I set my number of items too low and didn't really think about the fact
that I was thinking I don't want to prep too many panels, because that'd be like, I don't want to
have too much pre-prept to do without thinking that actually I'm doing like a crochet circle where
you just come along and like, knit for the day and that requires no prep whatsoever. So I pushed
you back up again and they put me on a science panel. This word prep. Yeah. I'm going to think
about things that I say on panels. Yeah, I know. Is this a foreign concept, Alison? I always prep
for panels. Yes, I know, guys. You probably also prep for the podcast, don't you? Alison, what are
you doing? I am on. On Thursday, I am doing fan funds from what we'll list to today along with
fear as a TAF delegate and Joseph Clary of Phallak, who's also one of the guests of honor of the
convention. I am on an air meet on a virtual panel on, so this is your first Worldcon,
where hopefully I will be able to sing the praises of virtual Worldcons and I'm definitely going to
have a ribbon for the people who turned up to that. So a virtual ribbon. So I need to do some
virtual ribbons for this convention, which haven't started yet because, oh God, right, I am on a
panel called Build Your Pug Cuff Community. I am on a panel and I believe I might be moderating a
panel called Organizing a Good Fan Lounge, where people I guess get to tell me how I haven't done
that due to not having actually done all the organization yesterday, it's only two weeks ago.
So do come along to that. I am one of many people helping out with the fan funds auction on the
Saturday. And on Monday, I've got a panel called Fan Clubs in the 21st century and beyond, which I
do have to do some prep for actually, because I'm not at all sure what I'm going to say on that one.
Well, you're moderating it, aren't you? I still need to do some prep. Even more prep if I'm...
Yeah, but moderating is easier than being on, right? Because you have to know the questions
more than you have to know the answers. But this is the panel that I can't really tell
what much about it because it scrolls off the bottom of my screen on my iPad, so I can't actually
find out about it, because there's a slight bugging planer over, which I need to tell them about at
some point. But at some point I'll turn my iPad round and find out more about that.
Bug, Alison could not be bothered to turn the iPad around. So I feel like that's a good bunch.
It didn't feel like too much. And apparently I'm having a lot of breakfast with people and going
on boat trips and eating dinners and finding some bars and running the fan lounge. My schedule,
I have living on space stations on Thursday where I'll be talking with my science hat on,
and basically being like, "Ready, yeah, sure." I will be on a panel called Building
Fandom Events, Myth's versus Reality, where I'll be talking about perceptions of how fan events
are built and run that don't match reality. So that'll be fun. I'm moderating a panel called
Starting Your Own Podcast, and I'm glad I'm moderating that, because hopefully I can make the questions
more interesting than what microphone do you buy, which is often the pitfall with that kind of
panel. And then I'm also on the Star Wars panel, Star Wars controller of the universe,
and that will be very good, and will probably be quite busy. It's in a ballroom, so that's fun.
And I am not on any virtual panels. I am entirely in person. So yeah, come see us listeners,
or don't. One thing about the fanzine lounge that we do need to squeeze in to our remaining
five minutes, which is that the WELCOME appa will be happening, the WOOF, which stands for
something like the WELCOME order of fan editors, but I don't quite understand how it works, but
what that means is you can be part of a physical and virtual collation of small fanzines, and all
the details are in file 770. Chris Gossia is going to put it together. No dead friend of this podcast,
I think we can say. And all the details are in a file so I have a link that we will put in the
show notes, but basically you bring your appa-zine to the WELCOME and it gets bound into a physical
or virtual product for the contributors to take away and for other people to read online. So,
very exciting. And I will definitely, definitely have a WOOF scene ready. I'm going to have a
WOOF scene ready. The WOOF scene is going to be my trip before from Orlando. You heard it here,
first listeners. Well done. Yeah, I mean, I'm kind of, you know, if nothing else, it's going to be
impressions of my first three days in America. I'm just going to print out in the fanzine lounge
or virtual that'll be fine. I haven't asked Alison. It'll be fine. We might be charging you,
but not very much. We might be working out what the actual cost of paper at Odera is
and charging you that. Can I pay in winning smiles? I mean, that's what we pay you for editing
the podcast. So, yes, but you won't like it because I'll give you a schedule. Oh, no.
We meant need to do we need to mention an electronic selection? No. Okay. Well, because there's not much
to say, right? It just works. It's good. More of this, please, WOOF us. If you were wondering why
the discussions on electronic site selection had gone quiet, it's because they just done it and
implemented it and it works and it's amazing and it's very quick and it works really well.
And it's still a secret ballot. And I feel like it's like they could have done this at any time,
but they had to wait until it was funny. Well, it turns out that whenever we are told that
something to do with WOOF us would be very difficult to do electronically and it's very hard.
When they dry it turns out it's actually super easy and there's no problem. Who knew?
Hara. Like, pics. Was that the shortest chapter in Octa-Thought history, right in listeners?
Just before we move on from Worldcon, we do know that Uganda is bidding Worldcon. It is very
exciting. We will be talking about it after we get back from Tricon and we have met them and
visited their fan table on all of those glorious things. But for now, hurrah. And more nuanced
thought next time or the time after. Yeah. All right.
[Music]
Pics. Well, that's not really told there are pics. You should tell you, tell us why you liked it.
Should I tell you why? So I've read the first line of Sarah Pinska's
Where Oaken Hearts Do Gather, which I had plunged on because I thought it might be the sort of
thing I would like. And the first line says something like, "Where Oaken Hearts Do Gather is
is an English traditional folk ballad child 315 round number 423." And I went, "The hell it is."
Which I think is not necessarily what Sarah Pinska intended. But after that, I was like,
"Oh, this is amazing." She tells the story in the form of argumentative commenters in a
discussion board that is a thinly veiled version of genius.com. And my goodness, she has worked hard.
She gets the form right. Although the ballad is obviously made up, she actually picks a lot of
themes that do occur in traditional ballads. And she wraps them together in a way that doesn't.
She talks extremely knowledgeably about the way that pop groups take English ballads and work with
them and border ballads and work with them. And the way in which ballads move across the Atlantic
and into different countries and the people she has, populating her message board,
are very realistic. And the actual story that is told indirectly through this is amazing. And I
was so glad that I had this story there to put top of my ballad. I was just absolutely thrilled by
every part of it. And there is one line in the middle of it, which actually caused me to fall
about on the floor laughing, which was quite difficult because I was listening to music at the time
to festival. And you're not supposed to suddenly roll around on the floor laughing in the middle
of a festival. People think you're on drugs, which I was, but only a very good story. It's fantastic.
And then I said that to a couple of people and they were like, "Yeah, I voted for it too,
Alison. You should read your, you go pick, pack it earlier next year." Loved it. It won the
Nebula Award for Best Short Story. It, I think, was quite well received by the Nebula readership.
And I think it might do very well in the Hugo readership as well. And I liked it very much.
I thought it was very good. And I liked kind of seeing how it unfolded. And yeah, it was good.
And there's an interview in the Hugo packet. There's an interview with her that starts by her going,
"I did a ton of research for this short story." And I'm like, "And that shows because one of my
pals said, 'I knew you might like this, but I wasn't sure if you would, because I thought you
might be going, 'Oh, it gets these things really wrong.' And it just worked really hard. It's a
great story. Because I do know a lot about ballads." Liz, do you want to do your pick?
I'm going next. So my pick is basically, I've spent all my time reading Hugo books
I'm looking about with the Hugo schedule and preparing for holiday. So my pick is the only
film I've watched, which is vaguely science fictional witches I watch. Dr Strange in the
multiverse of madness. And actually it's quite good. It's quite fun. I mean, it's not like the top
of the heap for Marvel movies, but it has a great soundtrack. It has great battle and fight scenes.
And I really like how the kind of different witchcraft versus spellcraft and different styles of Dr
Strange versus wong and so on are all in there. It introduces America Chavez, who is great and
punches holes between universes. And that means we also might get young Avengers at some point,
and that would be good. And I mean, lastly, it's got a really good Danny Elfman soundtrack as well.
Basically, if what you're always wanting in a Marvel movie is for there to be more zombies
possessed by their parallel universe doppelgangers who take the souls of the dead and turn the
mentor cloak, then you should watch Dr Strange in the multiverse of madness.
I liked it a lot. It is very much a Sam Raimi movie. Yeah, it's very Sam Raimi.
It's weird because it's very tied into the MTU in some ways, but in other ways, it feels very much
like a movie by the person what done it. And I did very much appreciate that. Up to and including
the inevitable Bruce Campbell cameo, which was very good. But yeah, no, I also enjoyed it. I
don't think, yeah, like you said, it's not the top of the pile for me, but I did think it was good.
There's a good episode of the incomparable that talks about it in some detail, which I really
found interesting, and I will put a link to that in the show notes listeners.
So I'm gonna pick two things because I am some sort of a wanker. John. Mainly because I want to
pick one which is like Addison's and one which is like Lizzie's. So the first one I'll pick,
I'll go for the one like Lizzie's first. Yesterday my wife and I went to go and see Nope.
And Nope is very good. It is a Jordan Peel film. Jordan Peel is very good.
Basically everything he's done is great. You should go and watch it all.
Nope is, I really, really, really enjoyed it. I thought it was just, it's very good, very,
very tight. Everything that happens has something to do with everything else that happens,
which is what movies should be about. And that is nice. Much in the same way that like there are
not many dangling elements in get out or in us, both of which are among the movies in the streaming
era that I've actually bought rather than just being like, "Oh they'll be on streaming."
Because I'm like, they're amazing. It's not as good as Get Out. Get Out is still, I think,
his best film. But where Get Out is a five out of five film, I think Nope is probably a four and a half.
So yes, very much enjoyed it. One of my other's pals said, "Watch it really soon,
like straight away because otherwise people are going to spoil it for you."
So I am wondering about going to the cinema in my copious free time this week.
Nice. Which I don't have. But actually it's very hot. So if we went like in the middle of the day
on a very hot day, that might be quite nice. Yeah, we went yesterday. That's why I've seen a lot
of random films. Yep. Well, we went yesterday for two reasons, which is firstly very hot,
and it was cooler in the middle of the day. And secondly, we're members of our local cinema
and our local cinema has a summer cinema deal on anyway. So between the deal and the discount,
we paid nine quid for two cinema tickets and that was good. The other pick I have is like
Alison's pick, except that it will be eligible for Hugo at Chengdu. And it is Family Cooking by
Anna Maria Curtis, which is a short story, clocking in at 4151 words. Brief digression.
Do wish they'd put the word counts in the ePubs of uncanny instead of just on the website,
because it does frustrate me that I have to cross reference with the website to find out
whether it's a short story or not. But it was so good. I loved it. I really just
I like the themes it plays with. I like the kind of world building and the magic in it.
I just really, really liked it. Listeners, it is 4,000 words, so it won't take long to read.
I highly recommend it to everyone, especially if you've ever disliked your grandparents.
That was the Old Thought Podcast, and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me. And goodbye from me. Hey.
[Music]
Chris also says he remembers when Koto came out and thinking it was really good, but also
realizing that he loved Dark Forces far more as a game. I'd say a controversial thing,
which is in general, I believe Star Wars games that do not involve Jedi are far superior to Star
Wars games that do. Right? And if you disagree. So you know the X-Wing game? Does that involve Jedi?
Oh, I see what you mean. Like does it still count if there is a Jedi piloting the X-Wing,
but otherwise their Jediness is not commented on? Yeah. I think probably not. I mean games without
like Jedi powers and light savers, because like Rogue Squadron, I would count as a game without
Jedi. I'm pretty sure you play as Luke Skywalker, but like you don't actually use the Force in any
meaningful sense. That, yeah, that's fair. I hear you talk about Star Wars games, and I keep thinking
about Wing Commander, which was technically not a Star Wars game, because it didn't have the IP,
but it was a Star Wars game totally, and also that arcade game where you had to, which was
vector graphics, and you had to fly around a load of laser towers. I feel very old now. I'll just
get my stick. I'll be over here with my Coco and my Zimmer frame. Yeah, I've just do good Wing
Commander and my God. Oh, it was amazing. That is an old game. Oh yeah. Oh God, and Star Wars arcade
game. Oh, it was so fantastic. So I was okay. Game was very good. Uh, I think, uh, Rogue Squadron,
Episode 1 Racer, Battlefront, are all good examples of, uh, Dark Force is actually,
and Jedi Knight 2 before you get the lightsaber is way better than Jedi Knight 2 after you get
the lightsaber much better as a shooter than it is as a lightsaber simulator. I feel like if you
want to play lightsaber games, you know, want a set of goggles, don't you? It's because they're
much better with goggles than they are with that goggles. No, actually, slightly discreet there,
because most of lightsaber fighting is to do with, uh, resistivity and until they come up with a VR
game that can like physically prevent you just passing your lightsaber through anything, uh, they're
all just not very good. Um, uh, I think the best- Yeah, no, they do that. Well, there's no, there's no
like mechanical thing in the gloves that stops you. Like, if I'm holding a lightsaber, someone else
has a lightsaber, I can't move my hands that way in VR. I can. Um, so it doesn't work. Oh, yeah. But
Fallen Order does a very, very good job of making you feel like a Jedi, mostly because it has a very
good, uh, um, manifestation of the powers, uh, very good combat system, in my opinion.
Are we using our precious 38 minutes to talk about, um, some of those video games?
Mark Plummer will write it. The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod
and Competec.com used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license. This podcast will end at
the beep. beep.