Also is this the first time we've managed to record from three different continents?
Yes!
No, John was in America doing some...
Did I record from the states though?
No, did you record from Germany or something? That doesn't count.
I definitely recorded from Vienna, but Vienna is in Europe.
Yeah. Yeah, but England isn't.
Yep, no true.
To Pumtish.
Let me draw you a map.
[laughs]
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 95th episode of Octa Thor, a podcast for
science fiction and science fiction fandom, which is coming to you on the 26th of October 2023.
I'm John Coxson.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And today I have written in my calendar that this
brand you will be doing Halloween decorating, so she may be listening to this while she's
doing that. And if she is, I love you. My co-hosts are utterly baffled by this
public display of affection in the way that befits British people.
I like this display of affection.
[laughs]
This is the bringing of pancakes to John while he is on the podcast by a
Spaniard.
Okay, so tomorrow, Stephen will be shipping something that I accidentally sold on eBay
in the middle of my gup trip.
Hi, honey. I love you.
Shall we do some letters of comment?
So the first letter of comment and arguably the most important one was a letter of comment
from Laurie of Hugo Girl, who said, "Thank you, next year is your year."
And that is because Hugo Girl won the Hugo for Best Fancast,
and we're very happy.
Yay! Hurrah!
Yeah, we're very pleased for them.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Well done. Well done, Pug Coss Buddies.
That was very good.
I would have had a champagne breakfast, but I'm tired, so I'm having a coffee breakfast,
like normal.
I was fast asleep for the Hugo's. I was very,
I was definitely going to stay up for the Hugo's, but it was all a bit much.
I went to bed.
I mean, we'll get into it.
Yeah, so by the time I'd wilt it up, I'd lost two Hugo's.
I've forgotten you lost two Hugo's.
Sorry, Alison.
It's okay.
It might be all for the best, because as I'm sure we'll get into later,
I'm not sure it would have been that easy to actually watch the Hugo's.
I did not watch the Hugo's either, because I was at the ballet.
But fortunately they announced our category literally like two minutes before I had to turn
my phone off and put it away, so when you were lost.
And it was like, okay, well, I'll watch some dancing instead.
If I had watched the Hugo's, I wouldn't have tried to log in.
I'd have just joined this Seattle Zoom and chatted to other people who were trying to
watch the Hugo's, but in practice, I didn't do that.
So I went to bed.
We had other letters of comment.
We had a layer of comment from Dave Mansfield.
Dave said that Liz's mic sucked the last two weeks.
Sorry to listeners who noticed that.
Basically, Liz has a new microphone.
This is very exciting, and there will be like a few dealing problems here and there until
we get that sorted out.
I want to discuss Dave's next point.
He stopped his Patreon for a skateboard, and he mentioned all of the discord that about
a quarter of their recent episodes were literally unlissenable due to audio quality.
So someone would reply and he'd respond, some more reply and he'd respond,
and say things like, they're trying to get more diverse voice readers,
and he'd reply that they make a point of saying these aren't amateurs,
and a skateboard pays all their contributors, and the other people on the discord said he was
being a dickhead, and then he is not voting for a skateboard in the Hugo's.
There is a difference between a semi-prosine and a professional media organization.
A semi-prosine will repay its contributors a professional wage, but they are semi-pros.
If the BBC ships one of its contributors a microphone and it doesn't work,
that will be discovered half an hour after it doesn't work,
and a new one will arrive half an hour after that, and that process will repeat until it is fine.
A skateboard doesn't have that level of ability, and if they're trying to bring in
more diverse voices, those more diverse verses will be in a position of financial privilege,
which is substantially less than any of the three of us recording this.
And I do think it is probably important to bear that in mind.
I'm going to give a simple version of the other thing, though, which is,
I don't listen to podcasts, I can't listen to, and I think that's a very common approach,
so it would be better to have fewer more diverse voices and give them equipment
than to have voices I can't listen to.
It should bring voices on one at a time as it can afford to equip them,
because I don't think there's any point recording narrators that people can't hear.
I would say here, the BBC has plenty of unlistenable podcasts that are terribly recorded,
especially with intrusive background noise and music that make them impossible to listen to,
and it's not just small producers that have troubles producing listenable content.
I mean, I was going to say, I think I'm somewhere in the middle, which is, I kind of
sympathize with both sides. I think there is a need to work out, you know, on
the part of podcasts with minimal budget, what is the kind of minimum viable setup?
And I will say I've been recording the podcast for three years on what is,
I think, a 20-quid headset microphone, and I don't think the sound is quite as great as it has been
from you two with actual more professional microphones, but I think it was okay and listenable.
So I think the need here is to say, okay, what is the minimum amount of tech we need?
Is that tech something that can be inquired in the places where your diverse readers are?
And to kind of, yeah, maybe either commit to providing that for your, not readers, for your
narrators, or is it a need for something where they say, okay, we're going to have to run a
fundraiser so we can get better equipment. That can be part of our Kickstarter or our goals for
next year to try and get that up, because I do think there is a real risk that if you're producing,
you know, content with more diverse voices, but then those voices in particular are the ones who
have kind of poor production values, and there's a risk that people will stop listening specifically
to those diverse voices. I completely agree with that. I think, I think, and I think the thing I
would want. I think the thing I think would help Dave's point a lot is if he had started with the
phrase, speaking as someone coming from a position of wealth privilege, I think that,
because I think the real problem with the way you're framing it, Dave, is that it doesn't seem to me
like you are taking that into account when you're complaining about this. And like, it might be
that you are, but nothing in your words actually says that. And I do think it's worth making people
aware that that's true when you have these arguments, because that was the first thing that
leapt out to me, and I feel like I'm probably a sympathetic reader of your complaints. So someone
who doesn't know you from Adam, it's an interesting thing to think about how you provide constructive
criticism to projects you like, because I think there is a way of doing it that will make it hard
for them to take that criticism on board. This is something I think a lot about, because I'm in
science communication, and most of my job on that side of things is working out how to tell people
things in ways that will be accessible to them and be something they want to hear.
Speaking true to power is great, but it's not useful if the person you're speaking to has no
obligation to listen, if that makes sense. I think we also talk a bit about the microphone
end of this, whereas the things that cause people with lower wealth privilege to have trouble
creating clear sound, or may extend to things like the room they're in, or the people they're
sharing their space with, which are much harder to solve than just getting yourself a headset mic.
Yeah, so I live in a, I mean, Alison and I both live in five bedroom houses, where we have rooms,
where we can podcast uninterrupted for two hours and be sure that that will not be interrupted,
unless we ask our spouses to bring us breakfast.
And coffee. And I think if you think about all of the forms of privilege that are inherent in the
sentence I have just said, and really dive into them, you'd be like, oh man, those peeps, they
got a little privilege right there. Like, hmm, I drink my Colombian coffee drink, which I kind of
want to buy from the market. And it's like, I think five bedrooms don't. Yep. Do you have like a
secret hidden wing? I didn't go in. I don't remember all those bedrooms. You know the
glorified cupboard next to the spare room, Liz? Yeah. Oh, that is officially a bedroom.
Oh, that's a cupboard. Welcome to the privilege zone.
I will finish this by saying what I've noticed while recording this is that I really need a pop
filter for this microphone. So I apologize to the listeners. Also, I don't have a pop filter this
week. So John, you must have some sort of software plosives thing, because I have got like a sock on
it, but I couldn't, I couldn't for the space to bring a pop filter. And you see, you see the other
problem, Dave, which is look at these two. I love you both very much. So Esther says that she will
arrange the cage fight between Chris and Abigail. And rest assured, she is a certified doctor and
professor of game studies, meaning that many years of drinking red potions and eating chickens I
found on shelves and in other people's rock sacks means that she is well equipped to be the medical
professional onsite. And then she talked about Glasgow presents. And she noted that it is,
it was set up by Megbitt Donald and Marita Averati. And it's being run by Pam Livingston and Robin
Duncan. They thought it was going to be a couple of pandemic panels. And it's basically spawned into
this collection of nearly 40 panels on various topics. And she notes this, she thinks that's
hyper innovation is something that they should be encouraging. And yes, no, there is a good point
well made. We got a new listener emailed in, or maybe not a new listener, maybe a long time
listener, but first time caller, S. J. Johnson said that they wanted to say they really enjoyed
the podcast. And they thanked Alison's recommendation of the actual star by Monica Burns, which is their
best read so far this year. They're in Melbourne. Did you meet S. J. Johnson, Alison?
Alison has gave me a look. I don't think so. No. What year is it? What day is it? What continent is
it? Ah, yeah, no, I've probably got a list somewhere. No, I don't think I met S. J. Johnson. Sorry.
S. J. Johnson, I was in Melbourne for the first time in my life about two and a half weeks ago.
It would be lovely to meet up. And she'll never be back. Join Nova Mob, which is a Melbourne Science
Fiction Society or the Melbourne SF Society, which is another Melbourne SF Society.
Chris Garcia emailed us about our best novel episode. Oh, hang on. And also emailed us on the
other episode. Lock number one, he says that Alison pronounces the word "giff wrong". No, no,
he said that before. We've said he's wrong before. We're done, right? Yeah. And we'll come back to
that when we discuss Jeff. And then he also said that the, he wrote in about our best novel episode
and said that the best episode, the best of the novels was The Spare Man. And I would characterize
every single other Lock we got on that episode as fundamentally disagreeing with him on that point.
Our comments on The Spare Man resonated with our listenership. Yeah, there are a lot of people
didn't like that book. I feel a bit bad because I think when I listened back to the episode,
that's the one where I really kind of, well, I think it was me and Alison. We both went off
and wanted exactly the same direction. And so we were maybe a little bit harsh. Might have been a bit
harsh. Yeah, I didn't think it was a great book, but I liked it a heck of a lot more than you did.
And we now know who won foreshadowing and I have rants. Well, that makes it worse, really,
because if it had won, then it'd be like, well, who cares if these two podcasters didn't like it?
But since it didn't win, I feel a bit worse. Well, we haven't got the stats yet, so we don't know
it. Could have come second. Ballsy. We got so many layers of comment. We thank you all for writing in.
You're all very lovely. Is there anything else we want to particularly pick up on before we
stop talking about that as a comment? Because there was so many comments and we can't read them all.
I don't think we could pull out all of the letters of comment, but thank you to everyone
who sent commiserations. Yes, thank you very much to everyone who did. Which is radge,
but I'm sure there'll be more. I want to pull out one thing from Abigail's comment, which I agree
with, which is her definition of cozy fantasy runs more towards something like Catherine
Allison's The Goblin Emperor, where the main character triumph spikes, then in trust and generosity,
but finding people who are decent and kind to promote and rely on puts to places meaningful
challenges in his path. And I would agree with all that and I like The Goblin Emperor and yeah,
I think that feels like a cozy, nice book to read because problems get overcome and it feels like
the world is becoming a better place through this one person, but not because they don't do anything
and things just kind of work out. Very realistic depiction of civil service and why you need one.
I, you know, it's a good book. I really like Allison. Yeah, it is a good book. I'm glad that Liz
Pook kicked it out because I also loved that book when I read it on the Hugo shortlist and I found
it very stressful. So I disagree fundamentally that it's cozy. Yeah, it had lots of interpersonal
conflict in it. There were several parts where I had to put it down and come back to it later.
So yes, it's not cozy in the way that legends and lattes is cozy. You know, I've had sweaters that
were less cozy than legends and lattes. It's goes in the way that makes me feel better about the
prospects of the world in a way, but not cozy in a yeah, in a this is like a comfy blanket way.
It is a great book though. I think we all agree with that. Highly recommend readers if you have
not read the Goblin Emperor, go seek that out because it is 10 out of 10. Well, maybe not 10 out of 10,
maybe five out of five. Good reach. But yeah, great book. So we're talking about the Hugo's.
We might as well carry on talking about the Hugo's right. What won a Hugo?
Let alone bone one the best novel Hugo, which is quite a good thing because it
involved prevented me from having to, you know, scream loudly and prolongedly.
Yes, that is fair. So yeah, so okay, should we do the good ones first and then the bad ones?
Or should we do it the other way round? We should do it in some kind of order.
How often am I allowed to say in the course of this episode, if only we had the long list at the
point we were recording this episode? That is the only time you're allowed to say it. I don't
disagree, but at the time of recording, we do not have the full stats. So this is wild speculation,
but it's good because it means we can ring, we can ring the speculation water out of the Hugo's
next episode where we do have the full stats. Or maybe the episode of that. I can't remember
what our recording schedule is. We should also say thank you to Nicholas White because without
Nicholas, we would not know anything about the Hugo so many. So thanks Nicholas. Also, we should
maybe thank him for being our designated acceptor. Yes, we would like to take credit for the fact
that Nicholas was in a position to be the correspondent. We needed him to be. But no, we asked Nicholas
to be our acceptor and he very graciously accepted. He was also my acceptor and I got an email
about, I don't know, well into yesterday going, you have not sent me a speech. If you want to
send me a speech, please send it to me by WeChat because it's the only thing that works here.
So I had to get back into my WeChat account whilst, you know, in Melbourne trying to do
guff things. I'm doing Melbourne. Where am I? Whilst in Wellington trying to do guff things.
And I did manage to get back into my WeChat account despite the fact that I was all
a different continent from the last time I've used it and friends. That's not always easy.
And I did send him a speech which obviously he didn't need to use which did not surprise me
in the slightest. The astounding award went to Travis Baldry who wrote "Legends L'Arteys".
I do not think, I do not think he was the best option in that category but I am not surprised
at who won. That is fair. I can't remember who else was in that. I don't think I read very widely in
"Astounding". Well I was, I voted for Isabel Kim in that category. Isabel Kim, yeah. It's got
short, their short fiction is great but I'm not particularly surprised that the person who is also
in best novel was maybe read by a lot of people as well. Yep, that is very fair. And like, you know,
it might be that as Baldry matures as a writer he writes slightly less cozy things that is more
to your taste but it also might not be. Well also I think he's already quite mature as a writer and
he was writing a particular sort of fan fiction. I'm sure he can write other things. It was very
competent book. But he's not. I don't mean like, I've written a lot of things but if I wrote a novel
you wouldn't use my like papers as evidence that I could write. You know what I mean? Like,
he has written a lot but not in this form I guess. I basically just be slightly optimistic about
things in my sort of general, vaguely positive way. Yeah, no, I'm sure he can write better things
because I don't think there's anything, there isn't anything wrong with the novel. It's just not
what I'm looking for in a science fiction novel. So you know, it's not really a matter of maturing,
it's a matter of kind of changing novelistic direction which you'll probably do if the money
in this particular novelistic direction runs out or if the ideas run out. And then in "Load
Start" it was "A Catwoman" by Nadiok Korafor which as previously discussed I think is the weakest of
those six but I guess it resonated with people. And I think I have not read most of these six books.
Listen, have you read these six? No, I've read one of them so I can't really judge. Was it the Rachel
Harmon? No, it was Naomi Novik. Oh yeah, have you read the Rachel Harmon? I've read the other ones in
the series but not this one. So I read it obviously in my way having not read any of the rest of the
series because you know I'm an absolute legend. I loved it, I thought it was so good, it makes me
want to go back and read the previous installment. I thought it was really really really good.
It's fannya didn't. In what regular listeners may come to be learning is a recurring theme.
But no, well done to Ocarofor for a Catwoman. A Catwoman is the third in a trilogy, the previous
two installments of which I had not read so I don't know whether it's sort of better if you read it
having read the others. Can I go off in a tiny tangent for you John? This is probably not for
podcast but I was watching the ballet of Anna Karenina yesterday and it had like little intertitles to
tell you what was happening in each mini act or dance. One of them was like in the Karenina household
there is a marital discord and I don't know, I just think you and España have a marital discord.
Oh not like the Karenins. No, not like the Karenins. I mean come on now. We don't have a marital
discord. We have an iMessage chat. A joke. That was a good story. Thank you Liz. Best fan artist
Richard Mann. So Richard did my wedding photography. He is a very talented man. He makes me laugh
whenever I hang out with him. I was glad to see him win this especially because he has been doing
adjacent stuff for a long time. He does a lot of very good work photographing a lot of people.
Yes. At photographing a lot of people at conventions. I mean obviously I'm sad for Alison and for España
that they did not win and for Ian that he did not win and Ryan and Leia are probably lovely people
but I've got no skin in the game. Sorry, Ryan and Leia if you're listening. But Richard is,
yeah. This was a category where I would have been happy. Like there's like four of the six people
that would have maybe absurdly happy to see them when a hugo. So like this would kind of a win-win
for me in many ways. Obviously not being one of the nominees helps. Sorry, one of the finalists.
One of the finalists. It's an honour just being nominated. Chris M. Barkley won best fan writer.
Again this is probably very eminently deserved. I think I am slightly sad that it wasn't
Bitter Corilla who remains one of my absolute favourite fan writers in the genre generally.
But I think Chris Barkley winning is a really good thing. Very difficult to be annoyed by that.
Congratulations Chris and congratulations Richard. North River actually said that out loud.
And then it was Hugo Girl. Transatlantic besties. Yay. Yeah and I wasn't surprised by this if I'm
honest. I sort of expected them to take it because last year they came third or second I think and
so I was like they got a good chance and indeed they have won. Hurrah! Hey and instantly recuse
themselves for future years. Did they? That's sweet. Best fan scene, Zero Gravity. I'm probably
the only one of us who's read this at all. I quite enjoyed the bits of it I read and I read it by
randomly throwing chunks of it into Google Translate. So I probably didn't get the perfect
thing but it was all fascinating stuff about the development of science fiction fandom in
Shire and I was like oh I never do that. I never knew that. I mean it turns out there's a lot of
stuff in the world I never knew. And this complete obsession I have with learning everything is not
too many favours but anyway I like learning those bits. So well done Zero Gravity. It does sound
fascinating. Is it? I'm thinking of it as kind of a sort of Chinese version of Rob Hansen. Is that fair?
I don't think it is. I think their episodes are different right? Different episodes are...
It's got a little bit of journey planet about it as well and I think they've got some crossover
work. So some of the stuff they have published is some of the stuff that appeared in the Chinese
issue of Journey Planet and there's some links there and some of the stuff they were doing was
kind of reaching out to science fiction fans in different places and writing greetings from them.
So you know it's just all that bringing fans together that gives me such a warm cozy feeling.
Yeah I'll just say that given that I think not as many of the finalists were at the ceremony as
maybe in other years because it was in China it does seem pretty nice that actually you know Chris
Barclay and Richard Mann won and you know Zero Gravity newspaper won all people who would be there
to collect in person which is really nice. So we proceed and you've already put in a rant about
that. I mean we know one can he's great I don't need to be told every year like there's more in the
genre than this. It's very frustrating. I'm going to stop I'm going to stop my Patreon to it because
I'm increasingly uncomfortable with the distorting effect it's having on the genre and yeah I think
I think if anyone from my county are listening the reason I am not subscribing to you anymore is
because you are dominating that category and it is not a healthy four science fiction in general.
It's very good. It's tricky I mean we've had this discussion about recusal before because they do
very good. They do. Stories is a problem but I think other other places do very good stories as
well and I do want some of them to start getting a bit more recognition. We had this with um
Ansible all those years ago and false alternative for that matter and locus and you know and Dave
Langford. I cannot think of a run of double digit winners where people look back and say it was
very good that that thing won all those times. Every single time someone looks back on the history
of the genre it is oh it was bad that that happened and so I do think I'm kind of need to think a
little bit about their long-term legacy because if they are mentioned in the same breath as all
these problem winners is that good for them I don't know. So you're going to be at the business
meeting at Glasgow right John? I mean so you'll put forward a proposal for automatic recusal after
three successive wins. No because Neil Clark already thinks I hate semi-prozine so I can't do that.
Well it's not just for semi-prozine. True for anything. You win three successive times you get
not you can't go and that goes for authors for books. If you as an author win with three successive
novels you're at for a year. I don't mind it but we should have this conversation another day
because there's a lot to talk about today. Angie Zhao I don't have opinions on professional
artists this year really. I have an opinion which is that they were all great but I really really
liked NJ's house stuff because it was a little bit of a different style. It reminded me of sort of
Stefan Martinier's stuff that he did for you know like him at Donald's books a while back.
I really love all that kind of gents. Spaceships and cityscapes and everything they just looked
amazing so I'm very glad with that winner. Oh yeah no I liked I liked their stuff a lot as well
especially the one of the redheaded women looking at the spacecraft engines was very very good.
I think I'm right in saying I did not put them top bar like I am not at all annoyed that they
won and in general as in many years I thought that the art on offer was like extremely beautiful
and lovely so no bad options. I did it a lot about the rankings for professional art so I think
I did it about that more than for maybe any other category because I just can't rank them on anything
other than this looks the prettiest to me and that's it's a really hard thing to judge.
So I want to be ranking artists on how well they're illustrating the thing that's supposed to be
illustrating and I often don't know. This is why Alison hates Chris Foss. What? Well he never
illustrated the thing he was supposed to be illustrated. He just drew cool spaceships but I have two
books of his art and one of his originals on my wall so I am very much not on the context train.
I am on the pretty art train. I think the one I voted for was Deet Jian Zhang. Their art reminded
me a lot of John Harris in a way and I'm a big fan of John Harris's work as well.
So yes but yes no good good stuff. We don't talk about editors so congratulations to Lindsay Hall
for winning. I'm sure that she edited real good. Neil Clark won best editor short form. He is undoubtedly
a very good editor so well done to him. Oh yeah I wanted to say it was particularly nice for Neil
Clark to win at a Chinese WorldCom. Yes. Because Clubsworld has done so many translations
from Chinese authors so I think it's particularly nice that he gets to win there and get the recognition
there where there's a lot of authors who might owe their first English language translations to
Clubsworld. So well done. So best dramatic presentation fundamentally abdicated is
for responsibility to do anything interesting or cool but you know I expected everything everywhere
to winks is very good even though I think it has won a lot of things already so I wish
severance of one but what on earth the expanse was doing being Andor. I have no clue. Come on Hugo
listenership. Having been around for longer. Go on Andor give us seven series. Star Wars have been
around for longer. This is the first of several times I'll probably say it's going to be really
interesting if we can work out how much influence the Chinese vote had because definitely it did
in other categories. It'd be really interesting to me to know where the expanse is super popular
there you know because it's this big space opera type show and it seems like that is a
quite a big thing in Chinese fandom or if it's just everyone really loves six months.
Because you would be like didn't you vote for everything everywhere all at once. No in fact I
didn't. I decided that you were quite right and severance deserved my vote. Oh I had an impact.
If I was writing an impact case study I'd be like I impacted Alison. Do you want to talk about this
in more detail or do you want to just put in what we already said? No no I think you were you
argued in the podcast that actually everything everywhere all at once has won every award
available all over the world all at once and they didn't necessarily need a Hugo. Whereas it might
make a real difference to severance it's just probably scrabbling for support in the way that
streaming shows often do. So I would say I think if we think the Hugo's really have everly any
influence over the renewal of streaming she owes I think we had too tiny a thing to really affect
that but also it is tricky when the best science fiction. Look they've just built a building for
the huge they've just built a building for the world called you know how much more impact could
they have. Yeah do we think Apple TV care or notice? I don't know I mean Hades which had sold
far more things than you know books ever sell was incredibly delighted by their Hugo.
I mean they can be delighted I just don't think it will you know particularly help a show that's
on the edge of renewal I just don't think it will tip the needle in much one way or another.
Like I don't think they're making a sequel to Hades because it won a Hugo I think they're making
a sequel to Hades because they sold a billion copies. A million to be fair but yes. I would
say it's also tricky when like a really great film which is recognised at the best of the year
also happens to be a science fiction film because you want to reward it for being a great science
fiction film but yeah it's also it's got a lot of other award it's not often that the Oscars are
like giving loads of awards the things that are in the running for the Hugos unless it's like with
the rings. I shouldn't make it sound like I'm very grumpy that everything everywhere all the ones
won because it is obviously a very worthy winner I mean like you know there have been previous
best dramatic presentation long form winners such as Wonder Woman which were much more inexplicable
but but yeah no there's just a small. In fact it may be one of the best films ever to win
best dramatic presentation long form that's a take. That is actually that is actually potentially
true also it had roughly infinitely more Asians in it than Severance did which I guess I think
Severance had none and I wonder if you're you're having the awards with lots of Asian voters you
might find that films that represent at least you know small segments of the Asian experience
might do better. I don't think any of us are surprised by the best related work winner.
No but it's another British winner so that's quite nice it's quite pleased yeah no I mean I should say
oh the way I said that was ambiguous I think I think a deserved win yes Cyberpunk 2077 won in
Best Graphics Story or Comic. I'm sure I saw someone say that it appeared on a couple of Chinese lists
of like things to nominate so I assume it's popular in China so maybe that was an effect
but I don't know I have not read it I have not played the video game either I have a vague resentment
towards a video game because I blame it for getting Android netrunner cancelled. See episode
wherever it was where John Monologues on Android netrunner as his pick. Yes anyone else read it?
No I didn't get to it but again I think this is something you can point to potentially the
influence of the Chinese vote being stronger than the maybe split non Chinese vote although no it's
transferable vote you don't really get both splits but you say I mean I was very pleased to see
that Children of Time won Best Series yeah pick surprise. The best series winning the best Hugo.
Oh you know there were other good series on the list but yeah well there I mean right and that's
the thing it was and I think actually so congratulations to Adrian I have no idea if you just need
Adrian but if you do a very hearty congratulations yeah we want you to win lots more Hugo's yes please
we want you to keep winning Hugo's to the point where we're going god it's Adrian Tchaikovsky again
when is he going to recuse himself? I would like to say officially here that my opinions on
recusation do not extend to Adrian Tchaikovsky and if Adrian won all five of the fiction Hugo's
every year forever more I would be down. I would also say this means that Children of Time can
have the Clark Award winner logo and the Hugo Award winner logo on its front cover and there are not
that many novels that meet that brief. Not off I mean are there any I wasn't going to make any
categorical statements because I don't know but I also want to say like the competition he is up
against in this category like it is fierce competition so it is a very good win. Sorry I just obviously
had to go and look if there's anything that could be both a Hugo winner and a Clark Award winner
and there is an Silly Justice because it won everything and in the Clark yeah it won the Hugo
the Nebula the Beers of Faey the Clark and the Locust Award. Good Lord and also the city in the
city. Okay so two thirds of those are Stone Cold classics that had to be fair and Silly Justice
and Silly Justice I really enjoyed at the time and I think it was the first it probably heralded a
wave of books that started talking about the gender binary in a way that I think we now think is
very passe but at the time really wasn't so I think that's probably slightly unfair of me.
Oh yes but yeah I did really enjoy that book when it came out. It was very it was very shocking it
shocked a lot of people. I think it gets huge credit for kind of almost spawning a sort of 21st
century different style of space opera which I think is really kind of hit a resurgence
you know we've got that we've got Yoon Ha Lee we've got RKD Martin. That is a very good point I don't
know because I remember some people at the time being very um I think there are some people in the
genre who think and Lecky is not perhaps like the pinnacle of the genre and are a bit bewildered
that she won a Hugo but I do think the impact it has had on the genre in the decade after it won
like it is very difficult not to say it has been hugely influential so it is probably a worthy winner
in retrospect for sure. But there were people you know respected critics people I know for a
long time who are like this book is literally unreadable because it has an unjend of character
and I was like you know you've been reading books in which the main character is called
Bleable Furb and uses words like "crogled" for the last 70 years and so why is this trip to up it's
not complicated and that was so that was really really interesting that people were just completely
failing to be able to read it at all despite the fact that it's much less hard to read than a lot
of SF it's quite a simple novel. Yeah imagine how much trouble that I had if it was complicated
and then Rowett tests which won Best Draw Story which I think we've talked about this before
I we all think it's a great story I thought the ending slightly whimpered rather than broad but
like still think it's a very deserving winner from Uncanny. The Space Time Painter by Hight Yarr
do we know what Hight Yarr's pronouns are? If they're pronouns as she/her this continues an unbroken
streak of all women winning the top four categories for I think since 2016 but if it is not it marks
the end of the streak so I would quite like to know what Hight Yarr's pronouns are but if it's
they/them this opens this opens a debate this is googling I could have googled but I've got Liz so
you can hear me typing with this new thing can you? No I just you have a look you get on your face
when you're googling Liz you get google face it's my it's my knowledge all knowledge is contained
in the internet and therefore I must be able to find this out face there is one news article
referring to Hight Yarr as he so we may have broken this streak I can't
remember when the streak began but it was it was shortly after the puppies so it's been a quite
long time Sean and Maguire won Best Novella for Where the Drowned Girls Go which was not my
favorite of these novellas but I did I did enjoy it I enjoyed all of them I think the Nivo was my
least favorite but I still like thought it was good I didn't get to all the novellas this year
sorry I thought they were in general much better than the novels like I think I enjoyed the Nivo
more than three of the novel finalists Novella can go either way sometimes it's amazing and
sometimes it's like not and this year I thought it was quite a strong category where the Drowned
Girl Go is kind of really sinister and creepy in a way that I really enjoyed so like it kind of I
I'm not unhappy to see it win and then Natlyn Bone by T. Kingfisher the objectively correct choice
won Best Novel No we all three thought it was the best novel of the six so there we go so
obviously that's everybody right yep okay here goes disgust
how is Juff going Alison oh it's amazing so yeah no I strongly recommend
going and having life-changingly amazing travel experiences every day for five weeks until your
brain leaks out of your ears and you forget what country you're in what day it is and the fact
that you left your precious kobo in the seat pocket of an airline but you have no idea which one
oh no yeah so if you're in the southern hemisphere consider running for north bangerf
because we'll be doing one almost immediately I really just mean Australia and New Zealand
they're probably if you're anywhere in kind of the Pacific you'll be good for this
June who's one of the people who's hosting me here in Wellington cannot tell the difference
between my voice and Liz's voice on the podcast which is I think at first apparently we sound
quite alike well you both do have northern accents oh I mean I have northern hemisphere accent
here's how to so if I say the word bath how do you say the word bath Liz bath there we get
that's how you tell yeah because there's no r in it what there's no r in it bath it's not bath
it's bath bath yeah so are in bath no exactly so why are you pronouncing it like there is one come on
okay right well all I think it's done here is started an accident conversation with two
firstly confirmed contrarians which is mistake one
anyway that's the number one identifier of the difference between the northern and southern
English accent so for people who are not familiar with that is that we that that people from the south
is say the a sound as an AR in many words not all because they're pirates are what's a pirates
favorite letter are yeah you'd think that but their true love is the sea
it's an oldie but it's a goodie sorry you talk about guff um so yes no it's been a lot of fun
I have met fans in many different cities I've got lots of stories they mostly make some sense
I've done I've done amazing things I went to womb or a job yes now I'm very excited about this and
you wanted to keep it quiet because you weren't sure if it's going to come off but it came off
I was yeah that was the that was the thing that I say it was going to be the peak of my holiday
but in fact the holiday I just had so many peak things like today I was at a concrete model of
Stonehenge in the New Zealand countryside love it but anyway I went I went to womb which is the
place that the British British rocket program launched its rockets from quite a long time ago
it's still a protected air force base but they have unprotected a little bit of it the rocket park
and the and the base canteen and when you go and get your sandwiches you go in and you think
you're just it just says it's a cafe but it's in fact the base canteen and some Australian air force
people walked in while we were there and they were wearing Australian air force camouflage and I'll
tell you F-Loss camouflage which is kind of blue sky blues is not much use in the Australian desert
which is not blue if they stuck out like a sore thumb but that you wouldn't be able to see them
in the sky you might not be able to see them in the sky I did discover that the I've discovered
all sorts of things but the the Australian air force logo is exactly the same as the RAF logo
except with a kangaroo in the middle it just that is bloody stupid and I love it and I said that
and Mink turned and said oh but didn't you know the New Zealand air force logo is exactly the same
as the RAF logo except with a kiwi in the middle which is at least a bird if not a flying bird
and it turns out that kangaroos could attain greater height than kiwis because basically the
only way to get a kiwi to fly is to kick it um I do not in any way condone the kicking of kiwis
who are with a kind of adorable and football shaped I have not seen a kiwi I have seen a kangaroo
seen several kangaroos but I saw one kangaroo hopped in front of the car as we were driving along the
road and luckily we were driving quite slowly at the time and the kangaroo was just far enough
away that it was quite exciting and not too scary for Damien who really did not want to have a close
encounter with kangaroo and it was an enormous kangaroo as well so that was quite nice
see some emus with emu chicks by the side of the road as well that's quite good yeah Australia's big
I've been on a lot of aeroplanes aeroplanes are still boring did you know that every airport in
Australia as far as I can tell has a brewery tap room in it so I've drank a lot of craft beer at
breakfast time on the on the excuse that I had to drink as much different beer as possible I've got
an aeroplane where I have to basically finish off as much postcards as a getting sent this trip
and also I hope you sleep and then I've got the aeroplane back to the UK where I'm expecting to
sleep as much as I possibly can and now I'm in New Zealand and I've just got a couple more
stops and then I'll be back in the UK which has been great have you seen any animals other than the
kangaroo that could kill you because I assume Australia is full of em I have been told by many
people about all of the things that will kill you Kerry Lanahan asked me what's the most dangerous
animal in Australia and I said I'm pretty sure that's man and he gave me that kind of look and he
told me about various things that would kill me but then when I went swimming I was swimming in a
kind of lovely rock pool in Sydney that's historic and it had a no photography rule which prevented
me from taking the the photograph of the thing of the posts that said beware of the following things
in this pool that might kill you do not let them kill you so that's what that's what Australia is
like Australia is full of things that will kill you and New Zealand doesn't have any things that
will kill you yeah apart from me don't cars and so on that's that's that's that's how you tell
the difference between and also Australia Australia has some quite tall mountains but they're all
just kind of lumpy they just look like lumps whereas New Zealand has lots and lots of pointy
mountains so even their little mountains are very pointy it's a pointy country rather the kind of
flat lumpy country people probably knew this but I didn't I kind of from the vantage point of
Wolfenstein Australia and New Zealand look much the same to me but now I'm here there obviously
very different I knew that I've read last chance to see so the only things I know about New Zealand
and Australia basically come from Douglas Adams explaining them because Douglas Adams is very
good at explaining things if you took the whole of Norway scrunched it up a bit shook out all the
moose and reindeer held it 10,000 miles around the world and filled it with birds then you'd be
wasting your time because it looks very much as if someone has already done it that was Douglas
Adams description of the south part of New Zealand so the first episode of last chance to see is
about the Kakapo and since then they've been doing a Kakapo recovery program and I believe
there are Kakapo at Zelandia where I'm going tomorrow I don't know whether I'll actually see
some wildlife refuge rather than like a zoo Zelandia's the most amazing thing they basically took a
square mile of the middle of Wellington not quite the middle but square mile of urban Wellington
and built a chain mail fence all the way around it with little with like cut links and killed
all the mammals in so or you know displaced them but basically got rid of everything in the space
that wasn't a New Zealand native and they've managed to keep it more or less mammal free
except that the house mouse managed to get in through these they didn't make the gaps quite
small enough and so they control the house mice but other than that there are no mammals in Zelandia
and they are trying to essentially make it a safe space for birds and it's had the effect that
there are birds that were rare in Wellington that are now nesting all over Wellington because they
basically recovered in Zelandia and are now nesting elsewhere in the city so it's very exciting so
that was all good and hopefully I'll see a Kakapo and much well they're not much recovered but
they are they are not so endangered as they were at the point where um covered in and Adams were
writing lost chance to see oh yeah you know it is I was just gonna say that the Adams when Adams
covered in went the people who were like working in the conservation effort for the Kakapo were
very against the visiting but it turns out that they're visiting a lot for the animal and for
the conservation effort so it was retrospectively a very good thing I think and they did in the book
they kind of describe how they turned they did kind of wink all their way into the affections of
the people but anyone who hasn't read last chance to see is a phenomenal book I downloaded the
radio show because it's a radio show right that then became a book um I don't know if we know of
any others like that and and I put on the first episode you know like a bedtime I kind of pushed on
and it's been more effective than I think anything else ever putting me to sleep so I've listened to
the first 10 minutes of the first episode with radio show about 45 times I have no idea what
happens in the rest of the series because you just just told there's like sounds of the jungle it
was commissioned as a book and radio series simultaneously I believe oh right yeah that's probably right
fair fair because they were like if you want Dr. Sam's to do a thing he's good at both I was just
gonna tell you some a cool cacopo fact which is there are so few cacopos that they actually genome
sequenced all of them and basically built a big family tree of every single cacopo that it was
alive in 2018 it's really cool that's awesome I'll put a giant cacopo family tree in the show notes
Zelandia sounds cool please take lots of photos I mean they're just professors of
green spaces with pixels in them that are birds one thing I will say when I did my TAF trip report
was that the one thing I never thought at any point was I regret taking that photo and in several
times I thought I regret not taking more photos so I would just photograph indiscriminately it'll be
like my photo of a snake we can't actually see the snake but I'm like there was a snake there okay
they maybe don't have cacopo I know cacopo were I think cacopo have been reintroduced to the
mainland though so I would have thought if it were anywhere it would be there but maybe not
see like they only have them in they have they probably have them in sanctuary because they're still
they're still enough that they know every bird right so I think they probably have the
accessories that are long way away from people hmm when if you look at the link I put in the
show notes it's got a map ha it does have a map I saw a load of birds coming up on the train and
I was when I got to when I got to well into that I said to smitty so okay so I saw these birds coming
up on the train they kind of look like that I was like a bit like moorhens but on stilts so she
was like oh yes no I know except they're papa case I think they are they're um they're like a bit
like moorhens but they're very they're very common birds but they're basically swamp so it's
useful if you're a bird that lives in a swamp to have to have long legs so far having fun
yeah no it's been amazing it's unbelievable thank you to everyone who voted for me and who
supports the fanfums and hopefully I will write trip reportage that will will amuse you
oh well I went to I went because I'm a nerd I went to a lord of the rings location today just
just one as a kind of token lord of the rings location and john I posed against the lord of the
the rings heich-chart marker, so I can confirm that I have taller than a dwarf, but I muched
taller than a hobbit.
Ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha!
Ah, friggin' love it - brilliant.
But not as tall as Gandalf.
No, no that's fair.
Oh but Gandalf's not as tall as he's got a big pointy hat!
It's true, we should buy you a big pointy hat, erm.
I'm gonna ask you one question, and then I suggest we move on from Guff, and my question
is, have you ever done anything like this before?
Have I ever done anything like your Guff Trip before?
How novel would you rate this experience?
Oh no, it's like, as experiences go.
No it's insane, it's like nothing else I have ever done in my entire life, because it's
the way that you do a thing, and then the next day you do another totally different thing
that is also kind of like, I'm like, well I spent a day in Crash Church, and I learned
all about how it's recovering from the earthquakes, I saw these amazing views from its gondola,
and every day is like this, even the days that don't have anything much in them, like
I guess, I guess Bruce ships might be like this, except if I think that the experiences
that people get are very sanitised, whereas a lot of the experiences that I've had on
this trip have been kind of very non, they've been like totally different, because they've
been like a particular fan, and said, oh we should do this, and then we've gone off and
done that.
And that's the thing that's so amazing about it, and I have spent a lot of time with a lot
of different fans, and I've just managed to cancel my hotel room for Auckland, because
I'm staying on Jo Van Ecker and's couch, so you know.
Say hello to Jo for me.
So it's an extra person that's an extra host, but also an extra guppy.
I was worried that some of the bits of this trip weren't quite guffish enough, because
I didn't have a host, but I've got one there for Auckland.
The other thing I was going to say though is the average person in the UK generates carbon
emissions of about 5.2 tonnes in a year, and the carbon emission calculation for this trip
is about 5.9 tonnes.
So I do have to make it worth it in lots of different ways.
There's a lot of giving back to fandom in terms of generating content about fans and
science fiction in different places, but also making this trip worth it in terms of things
like trip reportage and sending everyone their housecars and stuff like that.
That's a lot of carbon emissions.
That sort of travel, as well as being a sign of enormous privilege in general, is not actually
sustainable for everybody all the time.
So it's quite important that when you do it, you actually get the word out about it,
so you try and give some sense of what it's like, I think.
I mean I know that there are people out there who are generating that amount of carbon emissions
every week, so you know, but they're wrong.
I am flying economy.
I'm very fortunate because although a lot of people I talk to can't fly economy because
of various health conditions, but although I have some health conditions, I'm also very
short, which is a real bonus if you're trying to fly economy, let me tell you.
Yeah, no that is fair.
Alright, first pick.
Cox and straight in.
So I'm going to pick a game.
The game is called Don't Play This Game.
It is currently kickstarting, but they have a demo that you can play and they describe
it.
Oh god, how do they describe it?
They describe it as something like a cross between the ring and Pokémon Go.
So it's a journaling game and it encourages you.
So you're basically playing a character and something is following you and the idea is
that by playing the game you are opening yourself up to this thing which will then get in your
head like the ring.
It is a solo journaling game.
It uses dice and a journal, but it also encourages you to like in the third event I played,
it was like go out into your local community and take a picture of the place you wake up
from this dream and then describe it.
And so it is encouraging you to go and explore your surroundings for like specific things.
So like one of the prompts was like go somewhere abandoned, take photos, explain how you break
in.
So it's like a scavenger hunt.
Kind of, yeah.
It's really, it's really, it seems really cool.
I've been really enjoying playing it.
The reason I wanted to bring it up is that I thought it was kick, I thought it might be
good to point people at it because it is currently kickstarting and by the time you listen to
this it will have about a week left.
It is a British project and you can pledge for 15 quid to get the PDF.
And there is a demo.
So you can play the demo and if you hate it, go back.
But if you find it very intriguing like I have, then back.
So Liz.
All right.
I am going to pick a book and the book is called Love Theoretically by Ali Hazelwood.
And I pick this one to be honest most because I think John is going to get a kick out of
this.
It is a romance novel I read on a plane because I like reading no ads or I'm planes because
they don't generally take, you know, have super complicated timelines and plots and
so on.
But this is a romance novel.
Girl meets boy when the girl is basically fake dating for money, the aromantic asexual
brother of the boy.
And then she discovers that the boy is on her tenure interview committee at MIT.
So that is not a scenario I had come across before.
Basically, yeah, she goes to meet the hiring committee and turns out it's the annoying
brother who was almost seeing through her kind of fake dating of the brother, which
she's doing, you know, so he can get his family off his back.
And yeah, it's all about being a sort of, it's all about theoretical physics versus like
experimental physics and it has like a terrible mentor and the roles of women and STEM all
around quite satisfying romance plot.
So it's quite fun.
Yeah, no, that sounds awesome.
It sounds really stressful and sugaring.
I mean, yeah, okay, no, I could see that read.
I should say it's very American.
So it is all about getting that like tenure track position in America, which from my external
view seems like a massively stressful thing that everyone goes through in America that
doesn't have quite the equivalent in the UK doing that round of all the tenure track
stuff.
Over here, it's basically like, can you get a fellowship that they will promise you a
permanent job off?
It just works differently, right?
No, that sounds really cool.
I might have to look that up.
I still haven't read the book, the perfume book about the serial killer.
What's that one?
Oh, bass notes, yeah.
Yeah, I still haven't read that.
And that's still, that's like another one that you did that sounded delightful that I
haven't got to yet.
So I really do need to read more of the things Liz tells me to read.
Alison, you've had lots of time to do pics on your guff trip.
What's your pick today?
I've had lots of time to do reading and watch movies.
I have in fact watched some movies and I'm not going to pick any of them.
I have an anti-pick which is watching movies on planes, which is not good for you or the
movie.
I'm still going to do more of it on the plane back, but there we go.
Yup.
I'm going to pick Australia, Australia's a country.
It's full of nice people and fun stuff that you can do and it's got some extremely cute
wildlife and I understand quite a lot of wildlife that will try to kill you though.
I didn't personally notice any wildlife trying to kill me and I was there for about three
weeks and I'll go back because I liked it so much for another four days in a few days
time and yeah, Australia, it's great.
You should go.
Nice.
It's obviously very homogenous.
It's all exactly the same everywhere.
It's not everything in Australia is different.
Right?
So Australia, that's my pick.
And that was the Orchardaw podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me.
The
theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod in Computec.com, used
under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.
[ Silence ]