Hello everyone and welcome to the very 46th episode of OctaThorp, a podcast for Science
Fiction and Science Fiction fandom. This episode is coming to you on the 9th of December 2021.
I'm John Gogson. I'm Alison Scott. And I'm Liz Batty. And I think this might be our first three
country podcast. Possibly. Because I am in Portugal. I have never been to Portugal before. Portugal
is very nice. I've mostly seen the inside of a hotel because that's the way it works. But I've
seen Portugal a bit and I've had some very good meals. Somebody led us, somebody basically took us
into a restaurant where they had to, we all had to get into the restaurant, show our vaccination
status or recent lateral flow tests. And it was the most science fiction experience I've had for a
little while, not necessarily in a great way. But then they served us very large chunks of cow,
apologies to any vegans in the audience. Maybe we need a content warning. But it's been very good.
And it also, John's app tells me I'm an alcoholic. So for those who, for those who don't know,
which I think probably is most of Alice in a ship, except for Claire Brierley of Croydon,
I have written an app that helps you track your alcohol consumption. And I gave Alison the beta,
the day that she went to a convention, because I am what is technically referred to as a
bad friend. As a result of having an app that tracks your alcohol consumption,
I know that when I sit up late in the bar and say, I sat up very late in the bar, but I didn't
really drink all that much. I was mostly just chatting and drinking water. That is what is
technically known as a lie. And so far, I've had the app for two days, but I've now had three
consecutive days where I have drunk more than the UK government's recommended weekly intake of
alcohol on each of the three days. So I'm slightly worried about that, but not very,
because it will wear off next week and then there's Christmas Odea.
Yeah, I had a similar experience at Corflour and Overcon where I was like, oh, that's how much I
drink at a convention. Well, golly. It's a good app. It will be out of the
through at some point. And we'll, yeah, we'll definitely plug it. But it's good for you.
But it wasn't helped by the fact that James Bacon, who is one of the chairs of this convention,
has been playing me quite a lot. So he, there was a lot of port and I like port a lot. There
was port and cheese that I really, honestly, well, you are in port, you go. I am in Portugal. And
it is the local, I have to sample the local delicacies, which in this case is port. And when we ran out,
we we drank the hotel out of cheap, cheap Ruby port. So then we drank quite a bit of white port.
Oh, go. And then there's been some shenanigans with the surplus from W and 2019 as well. Irish
Bon amilla, they can call it infansines. So Swafcon is great. It's been ground at us. Yeah.
John, does your app have any social features so that you can wander around and
used to come bar and know what everyone else, how much everyone else has been drinking as well?
No, it does not. Because that is, I think, what would be called a privacy nightmare.
Oh, well, we've got some taps anyway, don't we?
So I went to Swafcon, by which I mean, I was on a panel. I did not actually attend any of the kind
of convention. I just appeared on a panel as a sort of informed person, which is a bit weird.
What were you informed about? I was informed about the role of publications. The people who
are listening to this may know I have opinions about, from my opinions about them in previous
episodes. But basically it was me and Case Van Tawne and Marcin Clack and Sarah Felix,
who moderated. And we had a jolly good discussion in which I think I was the person most in favor
of electronic things on the panel because Marcin is quite a big fan of physical artifacts.
And Case is also kind of a big fan of printing things out. But I think it was a good panel.
And Sarah, I think Sarah is less of a fan of printing things out, but she is a very great fan
of having all of the previous work lined up beyond her bookshelves so that she can get design
inspiration from things that people have done before. So I feel like you were the,
yeah, you were definitely the most pro-electronic of the people on the panel. And it was a good panel.
I've been on a panel about overworking at conventions, which was sparsely attended. And that's because
there are about 50 people in here in person. And then there's more people online obviously,
but there are often four streams running simultaneously. And I'm here to say publicly,
SMOFCON, that is too many streams, even if you are a "program heavy convention." You should be
having fewer better program items. I know that I say this to all the conventions except Corflum,
which only have five program items. But Corflum and SMOFCON are not dissimilar in size,
and SMOFCON has 10 times as much program as Corflum did. And the ideal amounts of program
is almost certainly somewhere between those two, even if you're quite a program heavy
convention, because we did a perfectly good panel to a room of about four people.
Just to say, it would be difficult to advise Corflum to have smaller, better program, because
Corflum had about three program items, and two of those were meals.
Also, how much has SMOFCON been affected by travel difficulties? I mean, how many people
had to drop out last minute, because I saw quite a few. Oh, lots. And they lost quite a few last
week. I mean, so one of the things that's been very interesting about SMOFCON is that
over the course of this weekend, everybody's return travel arrangements have been disrupted
by change testing requirements in the country that they are flying to when they fly home.
Almost everyone I know in the UK has texted me in the last 24 hours to say, "When are you returning?"
Because, "Did you know that?" And I'm like, "Yes, I did know that. I am returning four hours and
20 minutes before the requirement for a pretest comes into force." So hopefully, unless we're
very, very late, we will not have to have a lot of flow test at the airport. We will just have
PCR so we'll get there. So the other thing I wanted to say about SMOFCON is that it's a really
good example about a convention that's had to take very careful account of the need to keep
all of its members safe, because there are a lot of strains of worldcon at this convention.
And if you're not very careful, you're likely to catch one, including Margarit Smith, who was,
I guess, last time, who has spent quite a lot of the weekend going for 17 weeks. Mary Robin
Eckhole came on to the, came on and gave us a presentation about DISCON in which she said,
"This convention is cursed and we are giving it an exorcism, so you should all have protective
amulets to help DISCON. But there are many strains of worldcon circulating. There is a
particularly virulent Glasgow in 2024 strain, which many of the people here are infected with."
I recommend social distancing for avoiding infection with Worldcon. Just don't go anywhere
near anyone who's got it. I'm lucky in that I have some residual immunity from London in 2014.
This has not quite worn off completely yet. So that's why you're only working on one Worldcon?
I'm only working and I'm only very, very slightly working on Glasgow, that's right.
So that's why third convention is six weeks, which is very strange. I had a notion of what SMOFCON
would be like. I've never been to a SMOFCON in person. I'm that SMOFCON, as regular root listeners
were low because of the auspices of Dublin in 2019, which decided to use some of its surplus
to encourage con runners from around the world to come to SMOFCON. The average age of the
SMOFCON crowd is about half what I was expecting. And there are a lot of fans from around Europe
who are talking about their conventions in their area, are talking about what they're doing locally.
I have plans to maybe run a year ago on. It's just a much younger and more diverse crowd than I was
expecting it to be and it's been great.
Our sponsor for OctaThorp is once again Stowe shirts, reminding you that you can just about
get shirts for Christmas as long as you choose rush shipping. Our chapter art features listener
Gwen wearing the spaceman from the punctuation logo by Sue Mason. Gwen says this is her favourite
sweatshirt and people are always asking her where she got it. It turns out it's not a secret. You
can get it and many more lovely things from the OctaThorp shop at octaThorp.stoweshirts.com.
I'm actually wearing this sweatshirt right now and it is extremely comfortable and very nappy.
Use code OctaThorp for a 10% discount. Thank you to Gwen for letting us use her photo and thank you
to Stoweshirts for sponsoring the podcast.
We held off on discussing World Fantasy Con's single COVID case because we were at Nova Con and
we didn't know how Nova Con would interact with COVID and it turned out that Nova Con interacted
with COVID. Enthusiastically I would say. So Liz as our resident biology person and COVID expert.
Nova Con, so Nova Con wasn't a convention that happened and I was not there. The two of you were,
the reports seem to be quite good about you know everyone was vaccinated. Lots of people did tests
before they went. A lot of mask wearing. Okay no everyone was not vaccinated. Let's be clear here.
Everyone was asked to be vaccinated but nobody checked anything. Yeah this is a major problem I think
in the strategy is it was very much done on the honor system. So what we know is that
after Nova Con there were I think eight or nine people that we know of who had positive tests
and it's plausible based on the timeframe that they were infected at Nova Con and given that
sort of cluster around a single event it does seem quite plausible that the infection did happen
at Nova Con. Yeah which is obviously not a great outcome for your for your convention.
And there were also a couple of people at Nova Con who were definitely showing symptoms which
showed compatible with COVID. Those people were testing negative regularly. I think this is really
important to stress that the people, a lot of people were testing negative all the way through
the convention and yeah I mean I think that it's won't just stress but my general feelings on
lateral flow tests are they catch the people who are most infectious and we don't really know any
like chains of infection here. We can say it seems like these people were probably infected at Nova Con
but we don't know how, we don't know if it was another 10-day at Nova Con, we don't know if it was
you know anyone else they met while they were at Nova Con or while out in Nottingham.
Buxton. Okay it was in Buxton this time. I don't know I didn't go. They're all the same.
I was and I'm working on a fancy an article about this but I am of the opinion that the
they had said that people should have the NHS COVID pass before arriving which obviously means
that either you've had two doses of the vaccine or you've tested negative on APCR or you've tested
negative on an LFT within some time frame and we'll put a link in the show notes so that
eager listeners can go and read more about that. I do think it's become clear especially
in the last month like since Nova Con that two doses of the vaccine does not actually necessarily
give you as good an immunity as we would like and this is why we're currently having a large
discussion about boosters and things like that and I do wonder whether the next conventions
to run kind of post boosters and Omocron may need to consider whether or not they want to
mandate negative tests and vaccination rather than either or. For instance I've had both
Jabs of the vaccine but my last dose was in July and I don't know what that means from my immunity
at Novocron whereas Alison had had her third jab like two weeks before Novocron and so was probably
at a lot less at risk than I was. Now obviously I'm a lot younger so like I wasn't particularly
worried on a personal level but yeah I just I do wonder whether what we had been saying kind of
before the convention season started maybe that was a bit too simplistic and maybe we need to be
looking at mandating negative tests and vaccinations rather than rather than doing all
the same but I don't know. I think Eastercom's thinking about this. I am also slightly concerned
that there's a model that seems to be standard for events where we say oh well when we're actually
in the like the program rooms everyone will be masked and we will have social distancing and
ventilation and obviously people will take off the masks when they're eating and drinking
in an assumption that people eat and drink in kind of small contained groups of their personal friends
and then you get people like me and I don't think I'm alone here who go oh Novocron how many people do
I know who will be at Novocron? 171. How many of those can I realistically have an in-depth
conversation with over a drink over the course of a weekend? I think we have a word for people
like me and I think that's also true at things like smofkong. So if you have a lot of people who's
purpose in going to a convention is to talk to as many of their friends in
conversation in lengthy conversations as possible I think that does make it quite hard
even with vaccinations and negative tests and social distancing and aeration I think there is
only so much that you could do. I think the other thing I will say is there are a couple of things
I think Novocron did which I don't think helped and then there was one thing I think that we could
do as a community which I think would help which is starting with the community one. I think if you
are in the bar and not drinking I think we do need to normalise mask wearing kind of even in
kind of static social groups. I mean and I speak as someone who has trouble hearing people speaking
through masks I do appreciate it makes conversations harder and I don't like it but I do like covid
less so on balance I think I do think I was I was wearing my mask when I didn't have a point in
front of me and trying to try to make sure that I was doing that. The other thing Novocron did that
I think may have been unhelpful was they did have several program items which were everyone come to
this giant room and drinking in in it for a while and I'm not sure like whether or not that was good
practice necessarily it was very fun but I just I wonder whether they'd have been better off
instead of having a big party where there was free wine in the program room saying oh we've put
some money behind each of the bars and you can just kind of wander up and get a drink with like a
token that you found in your membership pack or something instead because it was fun but I did
think at the time is this actually a sensible program item to have at the moment and I do wonder
whether the answer was no but. Smofcon also has programs of this kind but I think the other thing
about Smofcon is it's a very small convention again and I think being physically a smaller
convention makes all of this much better still we are still probably rolling in a bucket of each
other's germs though portable much safer in lots of ways big airy bar rather than small comfortable
badly ventilated bar that sort of thing. I think the thing is you can never make anything you can't
make anything 100% safe and if we had this level of non-COVID-con crud after a Nova-con then we wouldn't
find it particularly remarkable although I appreciate that that generally a non-COVID-con crud doesn't
have people feeling quite as bad as some people did after catching COVID but I think I think you're
right I mean I think we have to say okay well we can't be 100% safe but how can we make this safer
and you know you have to base this on what the kind of environment is at the time but I think you're
right in that maybe we do need to try and drop the culture where everyone sort of sits around with
a pint in a closed room and you are continually kind of drinking your pint without your mask on
and say okay if we're going to have a really young conversation maybe we're better if we went
somewhere quiet where we can sit like a meter and a half apart and keep our masks on and have a really
long conversation like maybe there is our different models of socializing we should be doing I appreciate
that you know in many ways might make things less fun and it might mean that the convention is not
fun enough for people to want to go in some cases but I think there probably are ways we could make
it slightly slightly better it's also it's very difficult in November it's going to be it'd be a
lot better if you're in June you could actually say right well let's go and like you know sort of
bench outside and have a natter and that kind of thing but you you can't do that sometimes we
spent quite a lot of time at Bristol either outside or in extremely drafty pub environments
so nearly all of the weekend was spent in quite drafty spaces and then Buxton one week later I
think we got to the Cheshire cheese or Saturday lunchtime took one look at the outside tables and went
oh no we we there is no point avoiding Covid if we catch pneumonia through other routes I am very
different from Alison in this regard in that I went out for my birthday last year and it was
about -2 outside and I just wore three jumpers and so outside I have been very much of the
opposite opinion which is I would much rather need to warm up when I get home than catch Covid
yeah you're much less likely to catch pneumonia than me it's much less likely possibly but I
have bought I have now bought some long johns and some merino wool socks I think and I think
something I wanted to bring up is that well fantasy calm had one case despite being much
bigger than over conned despite having a lot of people from disparate places going which I think
is probably because they had a lot more negative tests kind of en route and so I'm wondering whether
having a stronger requirement for negative tests and not just relying on vaccine status would make
British convention safer and I'm not saying you can make them completely safe but I am saying that
I don't think we have achieved the best safety to compromise ratio we can I think there are small
compromises we can make to increase safety that are probably still worth making but yeah I am
actually not sure world fantasy was that much bigger than over conned this year oh interesting
I did go and I mean I I went and fished out I took on fish at the membership list at some point
take a look at this but no overcome was unusually big and I think world fantasy was unusually small
and possibly that is partly because it is quite difficult to get into Canada at the moment for
instance I would not have been able to attend world fantasy but I could have attended no we can't
I think also the US conventional spaces are much larger generally you know that the
Bucks of Palace Hotel was very nice but it was not hugely spacious so there were things like
corridors and and comfortable badly ventilated bars and things like that and we could probably
have done more I'm on a program item later about hybrid conventions and one of the things I've
been talking about is designing social spaces and the way that we need to we need to be thinking
more about how we're designing our social spaces and our social interactions for in-person
conventions at the moment than we have been for for this exact reason because I probably shouldn't
be allowed to spend any time on masks in that library bar that I spent the whole year before
we can't do I mean I should say I did tell any symptoms didn't catch Covid I was quite lucky
yeah I mean I think that's it ultimately we could have you know you could have tried to require like
proof of a negative pre-arrival PCR test but in the end it's kind of incremental
things that may not lead you to definitely prevent an outbreak so Nicholas who had the most severe of
the Levcocock cases is very much of the view that he was 100% going to catch this thing at some point
and he might as well have some fun while doing it and I definitely I'm clearly way over towards
the Nicholas end of the scale here you know but the thing is that like as a direct result of that
attitude as spaniel now doesn't want to go to Isakom and so it's all very well for the people
whose risk level is such that that's a fine statement for them but they're pushing people out of the
community and if we can make small compromises that keep those people in the community we should do
that and I don't think that saying yeah no I'm happy with that and Phil Dyson is looking really
closely at what they can do what they can legally do what they can practically do and what the
community will tolerate in terms of what they're going to say for for Eastergone I would be 100%
happy to have them say you cannot enter this convention unless you have your vax you have your
booster and all you have a thing saying medical a medical a medical or exceptional exemption and
you show a negative of 48 hour negative test like like is that's what's going on here I mean
I know that everyone at the convention I've had here is vaccinated and has has had a recent
negative test because that's what you need to show to get into Portugal yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah and I mean I would say like I just want to say that I mean I think when Nicholas saying you
know he's a bad take that risk what he means is he's prepared to go to conventions but I think
Nicholas saying like he's going to get at some point and so you know I don't think that means
anything made the convention less safe or the attitude makes it less safe it's just a
difference between am I willing to go to conventions knowing there is a risk or not go
not talking about Nicholas necessarily here it comes back to what you said earlier is about like
we can never make it completely safe and I agree that's true but I think that attitude used to
prevent trying is is spania doesn't listen to octa though anymore because she finds our
discussions about covert two stressful because she doesn't think we're taking it seriously
enough and I think part of this is because I and I think one of the things I'm coming around to is
it's not academic it's a real thing it's it's not like a hypothetical that we can discuss in a
scientific context which is devoid from considerations of personal safety and fear I very much get
frustrated with the I think we do if there are steps that we can be taking to make conventions
safer which are not like super owners like I don't know making everyone LFT on the door hello
why aren't we making everyone last you on the door John I think we should actually make hello
and LFT on the door I'd be up that is that I'd be up for that 100% well like I mean like I don't
think we could have like the LFTs in the lobby but I'd like I'll tell you what I said like I'd
like all the hotel staff to wear a mask all the time while they're working thank you very much
yes that would be good I need to get more water because it's a very very very dry hotel on the
back of just a sec I mean I think actually the yeah if you made people literally taken LFT at the
entry of the hotel when they came in on day one that actually might be a quite effective thing to
do because it removes any uncertainty about I know or maybe you know maybe you have to do that if
you don't have like a negative PCR test from the last 24 hours or something because that would
probably be more effective at catching infectious people it's impossible to evade and it probably
like gets people right as they appear I also I've got an anxiety thing apparently I didn't realize
but it took because I'm quite face blind anyway so so one of the things that happened this weekend
is the people I have known for many years and seen many times I failed to recognize because they're
wearing masks and it's been it's been quite difficult so there's that I mean and you can
get you're dazed to the social I would say it is definitely true that like as someone who does
sometimes struggle to kind of hear people sorry it is harder to keep up with conversations where
people are wearing masks in the bar I have I have been trying because you do that thing and I suspect
many people do this but like where you you say what like twice and then you feel awkward
continuing to say what but I've been trying to be like I've been trying to explain to people like
I can't hear you it's tricky these are all considerations I should say and I know I said I
wouldn't be at the Easter Car I will be at Easter Car and one of the reasons I'll be at Easter Car is
that I am bidding for the 2023 Easter Car and a core part of the 2023 bid is the contention that
some people no matter what we do for COVID management and making the convention safer for people some
people will prefer not to come to a physical Easter Car in 2023 and so we need to be designing
an Easter Car from the ground up that has both online and in-person elements and that is so
that we are not what I think the thing that John said was driving people away from the community
we are hoping to have people in the community in a variety of different routes and I think that's
really important because there may not be an Easter Car that both España and I are happy to attend
and this was something that came up on a panel at Nova Carne like one of the panelists at Nova Carne
made some disparaging remark about how like zoom is like very privileged and like by relying on
zoom we're like pushing people out and I was like yeah but all of the healthy people getting
together in a room is also very privileged it's just a different privilege like it's there's I think
I think using as many streams as you can also I'm here to say this on Opti-Thought I'm reasonably
certain I can get you on to zoom using crap I have lying around my house and if you're listening to
this and you cannot use zoom because of a lack of access to technology you need to get in touch
I will sort you out so that you can get on zoom if you haven't got the internet then that's
a problem but if you haven't got the internet I don't see the internet listening to Opti-Thought
No I think our listeners probably have a certain amount of technical privilege vested in them
I do like you know print out a copy of what you know will print out copies of Opti-Thought
and put them in the post for you if you'd like it will just be like a print out of the WAV file
so it might not be very easy to understand well Chris Garcia who will be listening to this
episode hi Chris did do a podcast that he recorded on cassette tapes so Chris if you want to bootleg
this podcast onto cassette tapes and send them to John Hertz we would be very happy for you to do
that um have we have we worked through kovit do we have lost thoughts on kovit at conventions
for the moment they'll be more unsure John can you trim that down so because I'm pretty sure we
said most of that like before and I'm not sure it's oh no I thought we took it I thought the stuff
about actually getting into the where some people's boundaries are I think is really good and new
but it might be quite hard to edit it will be difficult to edit just because it will be difficult
to listen back to I will keep that sentence in the podcast because it is hard to talk about this
stuff like it genuinely is scary it's scary to put it it's scary to have to define and defend your
boundaries you know this is a very new situation we find ourselves in where we suddenly all have
this this very big thing in our lives that we all have very different boundaries to and we have to
I think it is difficult to talk about these things because it's a thing we don't often have to talk
about we don't have to talk about like how we are comfortable and think about why and it's it's
hard it's hard to talk about it makes me very anxious to talk about it but I hope it's useful for
people listening to hear different people's takes so I hope it was good even if it's stressful
yeah just stressful then I think I find it less stressful because I can view it in a more academic
way and also because I'm aware there's like I don't know lots of diseases to my catch um that's
what we are all about you know I'm in a position where one of my close friends from uni is dealing
with chemotherapy failing and my mother has dementia and I feel like we did have 10 cases of covid
but there all everyone there is fine and we may at this point be getting to the stage where we are
over people are being overly worried about things that are actually not as likely to kill them or
severely limit their lives as the other terrible things that we all have to deal with every day
and and we need to live our lives and that that is and I'm not by any means advocating massive
risk taking here so listeners may not know I have anxiety and one of the things that I found
I had a very anxious reaction to having a bad concussion at work a couple of years ago because
I was very worried that like basically I was going to have a stroke and die and most of my anxieties
do revolve around kind of things that would be life ending uh mostly professionally but but
sometimes in a health context so it doesn't normally manifest as hypochondria but but the concussion
really did a number on me and it is terrifying it was very scary when I was like still having
concussion symptoms like three weeks later because I was like this is not I don't like this I don't
like the idea that my brain could be doing things it's not supposed to be doing and in some ways it
really did and I think this goes a little bit to what Alison was just experiencing it really did
help me with some other things I've been having anxiety about like realize like yes but being
afraid of literally dying is very different to being afraid to like having a paper come back
with bad comments and it really did recontextualize some stuff kind of that I had been worrying about
and so I do take the point that like we do need to be careful that we don't overcorrect in a way
that basically means that that we're not kind of carping the DM as it were I mean I had two things
one is I was I'm curious as to how job managed to get concussed at work because as far as I knew
your job most evolved sitting at computers all day and now I'm worrying about how I like get a
concussion maybe if I fall off my desk chair but I mean I think the other thing is also true in that
I think COVID is making everyone reevaluate the risks of various things and in fact I think we
will have a strong reevaluation of things like people used to get concred or the flu or various
other viruses and we just sort of like accepted that as a thing and maybe in the future we actually
won't accept that as a thing even if COVID is you know mostly you know not an ongoing issue we might
say well actually maybe we should wear masks when in large situations because it'll stop people
getting nasty coughs and colds you know I think there's going to be a big reevaluation because I
think certainly the UK has not been through this kind of multi-year evolving pandemic that most of us
can remember. So the point I actually wanted to make was a tiny one about anxiety which is I think
one of the things that you see throughout opto-thorpe which is that John is a very anxious person
who has treatment for anxiety and I am the person who spent six hours at hospital with
while I kept going is it okay if I go home now and they went no we really need to do some more
checking to make sure you haven't had a stroke so people have different risk appetite so I think
that's probably good. Some of what people's personal risk appetite is also comes off as not
being sufficiently considerate of other people's risk appetites. I think it mostly works one way
in that people people who are much more concerned about COVID tend to be much more concerned about
people who are not taking it seriously whereas the people who feel that people are taking it too
seriously tend to be less bothered because it doesn't make huge differences to them but it might
if you had things like masking in bars and stuff. I don't think people are I wouldn't say so and
so is taking it too seriously that's you know what I would say is because I'm worried about
testing not being very reliable and I might not do two conventions in two weeks again for a very
long time. Safe as Mofcom you know I've been sitting in the house for a week I could only have got
over by a macular conception I am not infectious at this convention and that makes me very much
more comfortable about sitting up till the bar and three o'clock in the morning talking bollocks
it's because the risk I'm taking is the risk I might catch it not the risk I might spread it
the risk I'm but spread it is much more worrying to me and that's why at Novocorn because it turns
out it would have been possible for me to catch COVID at Corflu have no symptoms test negative
cause continually and still have spread it over com I don't think it's very likely but it's clearly
possible I am actually more worried about that behavior now in retrospect. I will say something I
did think of and I don't know whether I said it on the podcast or whether I said it in a conversation
with people like at first Thursday or something was I was like I was a little bit concerned about
the week between Corflu and Novocorn because I was like if you get pinged in between it will be a bit
of a tricky thing and I think one of the things COVID is going to do is that kind of will hold
a convention a week before in the same country so that people can do both is going to get a lot
trickier because you do have that consideration of well what if there's an outbreak at convention one
and I do wonder whether that will have an impact on cons kind of for the next couple of years
so I think that is an interesting thing. Yeah that's interesting should you space them apart so you
don't end up turning one into a spreader event because the other yeah okay so so there are
several reasons why people are not at smothcon this weekend but one of the reasons that are
people are not here is that people who have large jobs on disc on are like oh we would normally fly
to smothcon two weeks before the world con and we are not doing that because the consequences of
catching COVID either on route or at the convention are just too great and that's perfectly I think
that does seem to be like a very sensible risk judgment but there are people who are not here
in need of expectancy because they have to be fit for disc on and there is one senior member
of the disc on team here and that's what and I'm done are we done with COVID guys yeah I just I
want to tell this how I did my concussion oh god I lent down to get my bag and I hit my head on a shelf
at speed and I I don't know if I blacked out but my knees certainly gave out and one minute I was
standing up in the next minute I was sitting down and my colleague looked at me and went what just
happened I was like hit my head and then I didn't really get symptoms of a concussion for another
few days and then they stuck around for an enormously long time and I was very worried
mostly because they keep saying if you blacked out when you had your concussion it's very
important you tell us and I was like I don't know if I did I don't remember it well enough and
many doctors seemed very displeased without answer I've bang my head on many things many
times I never got a concussion so also like now is my head extremely solid or Liz absolute unit batty
yes we're going to talk about site selection listeners in a ginger style
palate cleanser from our pretty serious discussion about COVID so I have paid my 50
dollars site selection fee and I have filled in my site selection PDF and I have emailed it to the
disc on site selection email address and your deadline to complete all of those steps if you so
desire is some point on the 14th of December I recommend doing it by the 13th to avoid any time
zone based shenanigans especially if you're Liz I'm going to suggest that you do it right now you
are listening to ops thought right now and you should stop what you're doing and sort your site
selection ballot out this will also give you a supporting membership in the new welcome whether
it is Chengdu Chengdu or Winnipeg and I think it's a good thing to do and it's a bit tedious the
kind of you know you print out a PDF and you fill it in and you scan it and you email it but
you have no idea how much better it is than it used to be we kind of go we have to reward
progress here one day one day Novocod is going to have an electronic hotel booking for it
note it is a lot better than it was kind of when I entered World Confundum it's still not quite
perfect but it is a lot better so well done to all involved Liz have you got any thoughts on site
selection I just haven't done it yet because I have to I mean I don't have a printer or a scanner
I've won in the office so I'd have to go and use the office one oh so I can't take your photograph
of it with your phone come on we live in the 21st century yeah but I can't sign it yeah no you
gonna have to print it off yeah I have to print it out to sign it and then take a photo which is
actually like at this point stricter than like when I tried to prove my identity for a bank account
at this point like I think I should be able to just stick it like an electronic signature on there
and take a photo of it well what I am actually going to do with this form is I'm going to put it
onto GoodNotes 5 on my iPad and then I'm going to sign it with my Apple pencil and then I'm going
to send it to them and if they don't I don't think they'll notice I think they'll be completely
fine with it I think I think I'm going to throw a file anyway it'll be fine I will try sticking
in there like my electronic signature on there which is just you know an image of my actual
signature and send it to them that's why I did tell you what Liz you feel it and add
send it to me by email and I will sign Liz Batty on it and send it back to you and then you can
send it in because they don't know what your signature is like this is not in any way an
actual security thing this is even less secure I'm just right just writing X Liz pretend you
don't know how to do handwriting just put an X on oh right are you going to vote for Winnipeg
or Chengdu Liz um probably going to vote for Winnipeg I sound very gluey about that I'm not
actually glue me I think the Winnipeg bid looks pretty good I just think that like the Chengdu
bid also looks good and the reason I'm not voting for Chengdu is not related to the individuals or
the like facilities they have accumulated all the Worldcon I think they would be able to run
it's based on whether we should award the Worldcon to China at this moment in time I am much in the
same boat but in fact Tony from the Chengdu bid has been at smothcon virtually this weekend
and I've had a number of conversations with swaps where they have been a Chengdu is kind of like the
Austin Texas of China and is very cool place and these are very cool fans and they want to do a
very cool convention but they are in have you nowhere ready to do the Worldcon quite yet in a way that
is totally different from the conversation about oh we also don't want to give it to China because
the Chinese government thinks I feel like there is also a bit of oh yes Chengdu but not yet going on
though this smothcon which is not not where I thought we would be I thought we would be much
more not Chengdu because China and it's it's not it's not been quite like that one of the things
that you get at smothcon which is very exciting if you're a total nerd is the detailed answers to the
Spanish Inquisition questions and they are published and they're on the smothcon website and you can
go read them all for a bit and it is really interesting and the Chengdu responses are very
quite interesting but I will be voting for Willabeg for those reasons and hopefully the Chinese
fans will not be too discouraged by this and hopefully the Chinese government will put it
sacked and what we're gonna have to resolve what we do about that one day. I would say that I think
that is interesting because from looking through kind of you know the bids um stuff they've submitted
to Worldcon and their social media and things like to me it looks like you know the Chengdu team
would be able to put on a pretty good Worldcon but it sounds like there is kind of more detail that
comes out if I would have more conversations with them and you know one reason I haven't done that
is because I haven't met the team at any conventions because they've been 20. Yes so I'm seeing a bit of
we think they could probably put on a good convention but they do not yet understand enough about what
Worldcon's need and are like and we are not sure that they could put on the sort of broad
generalist science fiction convention at Worldcon is. They could do a different style of convention
that would certainly be Worldcon. Yes this was not going to vote for that one right it's like if
somebody came along and said yeah we'd like to bid for EasterCon but we wanted to be a 10,000 person
gate show you know they could do it as much as they liked but they would look at that they wouldn't win.
While we're on topics that are more light-hearted topics I have been bleeding on for literally 30
years about the possibility of getting a digital membership of the British Science Fiction Association
so I was thrilled thrilled I tell you listeners to discover that is that possible to join the British
Science Fiction Association as a digital member what's the catch boys and girls? I can do it you can't do it
Well but Alison is currently international so if she just joins the BSFA before coming home I'm sure
it's all fine Liz. Yeah no I mean it does save residents in the UK it does not say on staying in
a hotel in Portugal. It is and I say this with love and a spirit of constructive criticism bollocks
I think BSFA if I want PDFs the fact that I live in the UK should not prevent me from getting PDFs
So I'm pretty sure why they're doing it is because the economics of running the British Science Fiction
Association rely on the costs of printing about your publications and so the thing about printing
as you know Bob is that if you do more of it it doesn't become any or if you do less of it it
doesn't become any cheaper that essentially printing about 10 other thing costs as much as printing 10,000
of a thing more or less and so they are worried that if they are worried that by giving UK members
a lower rate for the digital versions they won't be able to make the books out of I assume but I
would be very happy for somebody from the BSFA to come and tell us why they're doing this absolutely
appalling thing which is terrible for the planet and incidentally I'm one member who will not join
the BSFA because of paper publications and it's been 30 years you know I was in the BSFA for two
years I was concerned about the amount of paper I was getting I was like can I have a membership
with less paper and they said no and they have carried on saying no ever since oh that is what
I want so if you will gain some members who don't want your paper publications but would like to be
members of the British Science Fish Association because we know was that radtida for you? Yep yep yep
are we doing to do are we going to do picks? Picks, picks, picks do we have any picks? Yeah but I got
question in the show notes which is did us normally do Hades I kind of do Hades as a pick because I
haven't done anything this week you could do Hades as a pick I think it's quite funny I kind of like
the way that eventually John will get back into Hades and then John could do Hades as a pick and
they'll laugh at me three for three all right that'll be good okay nice um who wants to go first
Liz you can go first let us think of picks yeah so I have a pick which may be familiar to
listeners of this podcast but my pick is a video game Hades because I've been quite busy recently
and then my brain goes I want a video game which is chewy enough to give me kind of something to
think about something to do but you know I when I my brain is too dead for reading etc and so I've
been playing Hades which is great it is is it a roguelike I think that's what you call I don't
play many of this type of game it's a it's a road light with mess progression it's a roguelike
with mess progression apparently like roguelike with rest progression it's not a roguelike it's a
roguelike it's yeah oh I see yeah it takes it like about the internet says that takes certain elements
from roguelikes but it's typically but it's different yeah basically I think yeah I am old and we should
stop inventing new categories for games like four should be enough for anyone but I am enjoying Hades
you are Prince Zagres who is trying to escape from Hades and basically every time he's trying to
escape you get killed and then next time you get slightly further and then you kill the game and
you kind of you know as you do it you are leveling up and getting better better weapons better
strategies and uncovering the plot as well I am playing it on god mode because I'm bad at video
games and I would prefer to actually finish this game and see all the stuff that's in it more than
I would prefer the challenge of defeating it without an assistance so basically the game is
automatically getting slightly easier for me every time I die and I really like it because that
means it feels like I am getting better when really I'm getting a tiny bit better and the game is
getting a tiny bit easier and so that is a great function there are many good things about this
game but it has got the best god mode because that is a very very clever way to do it and it works
very well is an incredibly clever way there are other games you know where I will play them on
very easy modes if I'm more concerned with the story than the you know game mechanics but here I
actually you know I do enjoy playing it I just would not enjoy if I was dying every 10 minutes but I
do enjoy it when I'm dying every roughly half an hour yeah and I will I will get back with a full
verdict when I have escaped although I sense that may not be the end of the game I did everything
in Hades I did not turn god mode on I got to the point where I hadn't explored every single one of
the 700 000 voice lines but you know there were a lot I spent 300 hours on it so I would not
record so god mode would be a good idea in retrospect because 300 hours is a lot. Jon a pick!
My pick is going to a cottage with my friends for a week and playing board games.
Did you have fun? I did I played lots of board games it was good I would specifically like to
pick a few of the said board games so we played a game called escape from the aliens in out of space
which is a hidden movement game where some people are humans and some people are aliens but the
aliens and humans don't know who the others are at the start of the game and you sort of work out
as you go through and that's very good I like it a great deal and it's it's like a you write where
you're going on a little dry wipe kind of pad. I think it's our print I found a copy on eBay that
looks legit for not too much money so I'm hoping that it is legit and I don't end up just not getting
anything or just getting a moth in a box. I also played again called sushi go party which I friggin
love highly recommend if you played sushi go you should play sushi go party because it's better
and if you haven't played sushi go you should play sushi go party because it's good.
Is it is it better as it just sushi go with more people? Is sushi go with more more stuff?
More sushi? Yeah you shuffle a different deck every time so the it's not as static
so it's it's better. Oh and it's also like £19 and it comes in a lovely tin.
If I had a complaint about sushi go it would be that my family played sushi go enough that we'd
kind of done the sushi go and that was not that much playing. Yes sushi go party basically you have
like you still make a deck with the same like you know two specials an appetizer some rolls
etc but you you have like a vastly higher variety in each deck because each play through is different
so yeah I also have a problem with sushi go in that every time I play it I am sad because I am
not eating sushi and so that's a problem. There's an easy solution to this whereas that doesn't you
know if I if I play zombie dice I'm not sad that I'm not being killed by zombies you know
lots of I've played zombie dice but Meg Mcdonald was saying you got her into zombie dice.
Yep that's true zombie dice is great I have recently decluttered some board games I've recently
got rid of uh King of Tokyo, Luchador, Snake Oil and Geek Out basically because Luchador and
King of Tokyo and Zombie Dice are all kind of push your luck games and I kind of eventually
decided I would rather have the push your luck game that I could carry in my bag and crack out in
the pub and what and that's zombie dice. Zombie dice yeah it's a good it's a game it takes about 20
minutes the components are waterproof and um it's good in the pub. Yeah no um I think I might have
played it but anyway yeah I believe the time I should have been drunk while I played it and I
think Meg is getting attacked in the pub of the dead dog so hey good stuff and the last day was my
birthday and my friend bought me the exit the game advent calendar and the exit the game advent
calendar is very good we have been doing puzzles every morning I say that we did four puzzles yesterday
because that's when I got home and then we'll do a puzzle today after I broadcast I'm very excited
I like puzzles. I have a genre anti-pick this week oh hello we haven't done this before I think it's
okay I think it's legit right I've had a convention so I haven't been thinking very hard about podcast
apart from you know yeah go on you can have one someone's out there every week so genre anti-pick
which is that Stephen and I have finished the end of the Amazon Brian series we have finally finished
watching the band and the iCastle of what after what seems like a decade and it is like literally
the sunk cost fallacy of science fiction television and I feel like I may have been spoiled for science
fiction television forever by this series because I think SF television does this a lot where it starts
off very good and very interesting and very engaging and very evocative and by the end there's
really not a lot left and if you look at it you go well this doesn't make any sense
and one of the cool things about this is that I read a review of the last episode of the
man in the iCastle of like the thousand hours of god knows what and it said the end it doesn't
make any sense Philip K Dick would be rolling in his grave and thought if any listeners have not
read any Philip K Dick books the one thing which you can pretty much guarantee is that when you get
to the end of them you go oh wait that doesn't make any sense so I feel that making the ending
not make terribly much sense is the back when it's one of the most consistent things with Dick's
over over he showed it so I think I am now worried that all other science fiction that is longer than
say Russian doll has this problem that at some point it skates away from where it was going because
they ordered more episodes or they ordered less episodes or they got a series more than they were
expecting or they got two series less than they were expecting or or an actor left or an actor
demanded more money because he was very good or whatever and as a result the thing doesn't hang
together as a piece of science fiction it just kind of plods on for 40 episodes and is that really
what you want so I'm like go on listeners tell me what I should be watching on television next
and should I do I need to wait till it finishes so I can say oh yes that was a consistent share
because the man in the high castle is not a consistent share however it does have lots of good
things and lots of the stuff about the worlds that it draws are interesting and continue to be
interesting right up to the end but the actual plot and structure make nuisance whatsoever
what should I be watching? Well I watched two series about the high castle and then stopped
so it sounds like I chose wisely good choice good good choice I have not watched any I confess
on the subject of long-running TV shows that I think are going to stick the landing the expanse
is back next week I believe and I'm excited about that the last series and you'd say it's been
sticking things so far would you yeah I in general think the expanse has been in the unusual position
that every season has been superior to its previous season I think I would say that is broadly true
I think that is true of the books as well I think I think in general the story the expanse gets better
when the events of book one have happened and you can start exploring the ramifications in direct
contrast to Westworld where they were like oh we made season one because we thought you needed
the backstory but the story we really wanted to tell was in season two and three I watched
season one which was a masterpiece and then I watched season two and three and I was like and this is
this is the story you're excited about was it hmm so yeah you know I mean fun fact listeners
is that I also watched the first series of Westworld and then stopped so apparently I'm just very good
stopping before series get bad I think it's meant to be good yeah I mean I think in a way the expanse
has the same thing where if you watch the first series it feels like it has two fairly bland white
guy protagonists but actually the later seasons get much deeper and in fact I think those characters
themselves become more interesting and also other characters become more prominent and it is also
interesting that they definitely pulled some characters who kind of appear later in the books
into the earlier seasons to give it a bit more interest and a bit more depth I think yeah I
think it's mostly been sticking them I wasn't not taken with that series where um oh they're on a
planet with mean Owen from torchwood or whatever you think that season you think that season in
the tv was dodgy you should read the book I bloody love that book it I think it's fair to say
divided opinion but yeah in general I think the expanse I don't think the put it this way I think
you you even if you don't love season four I think in general the expanse is not um it is definitely
telling the story I wanted to tell I mean part of this is because if you are the favorite tv show
of jeff Bezos presumably you get the support you need to continue telling the story you won't
tell until you've finished telling it and so like I'm not advocating all art moves back to the
medieval patronage model but clearly it benefits some arts in some situations thanks jeff I mean
screw him forever for gels he does but this one thing hurrah I might cut that out yes that was the
ock of our podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
I think it's much more difficult but that's also sorry can you actually see me I've turned the
lamps on but I've bit up I love that I so one of the key things about this podcast is that
lisless god this is sitting outside and this has become dark while this has been sitting outside
today lisless and my fancy lights come on and she has tiny lights and they're very good they're
solar powered in my view it came it became dark quite suddenly yes no not doing it um they're
actually they're actually solar powered lights so they charge up all day and then they come on
in the evening for lara too we we have them in our garden which is significantly colder than lis
is yeah probably also significantly less than time to charge them up the theme music for this
episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in com protect dot com used under a creative commons
attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]