I'm going to use that as the transition between the segments this week Alison.
I'm going to put a little note at the beginning saying Alison Burpt and I decided to embrace
that as a motif and instead of having our theme song, I've perved into the microphone.
I don't know what I was thinking.
You really did.
I saw you move to the microphone to really get it on in the track.
You know how there's normally a beep at the end?
Not beep anymore.
Yes.
Excellent.
Okay.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 17th episode of the OctaThought podcast, a podcast
for science fiction and science fiction fandom.
This is the episode for the 29th of October 2020.
I am John Coxon.
I am Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
And today we are brought to you by two excellent letters of comment.
The first one comes from Dave Mansfield, who says that he found it really amusing hearing
the shift from reviewing online conventions to worrying the wrong format was getting to
be tradition to it being clear with hindsight that we were going to run one and then episode
15 running with that as an accidental gag of failing to announce it was perfect.
So thank you, Dave.
We would like to say that was all entirely on purpose and not just happenstance through
a number of episodes we recorded.
I'm glad that we're coming up with themes and stuff.
That's nice.
Join our before we forget to mention it.
Join our convention punctuation punctuationcon.uk.
If you are on that page and you are logged in, you will see the link to our Discord where
you can come and talk to people.
And a few days after you join, John will send you an email with the link to our Discord
as well, just in case you missed the one on the page.
But it will be a good time.
Come and join.
Yay.
Good blogging.
Since last time we completely forgot.
Plug early, plug often.
Yeah, it does feel like for those people who are listening to us, we have spent quite a
lot of time talking about online conventions and will spend yet more time talking about
online conventions this week.
So now we really have to do it and not make a complete hash of it.
Yeah.
I mean, that was already, I think that was already the plan.
Like we hadn't decided secretly to just like massively sack in.
But yeah, now it's getting a bit real now because it is.
Hang on, I'm going to check the widget on my phone.
It's 19 days and six hours until punctuation.
At the time of recording, by the time you hear this listeners, it will be less than that
because that's how time works.
I'm now worried because it's not very long.
Don't put that in the podcast.
That's absolutely going to get the podcast list.
No.
100%.
It'll be fine.
We just need to sort out the program.
If you want to do a program item for us, please let us know.
You can volunteer in the discord.
Yes.
If you remember.
So join first, then go to the discord, then send us your program ideas or you could email
us with your program ideas.
Yes.
Or use smoke signals as long as we can see them in Wolfenstoe, Bangkok and Southampton.
So it has to be pretty.
Yeah, please don't do that.
Don't do whatever it would take to generate that.
Yeah.
If you cause a global eruption in order to signal a program item, we will treat that
as a code of conduct violation and we will eject you from our online convention.
From the smoking pit where our online convention used to be.
I need to just edit the code of conduct to strongly discourage deliberate volcanic eruptions.
Dave also says if Zoom is methadone for consocial spaces and discord is paracetamol, is Octa
thought one of those double blind trials where it turns out the placebo is better than the
current version?
And I think that's a compliment.
Liz explain it to us because it's a biology joke.
I want to say that we should definitely not disallow accidental volcanic eruptions because
then where would Rob Hanson be?
That's an old, old, old, but nevertheless very finished joke.
Yes.
So, um, I don't understand.
Listen's joke and I don't understand Dave's joke.
That's the Liz verdict.
We've got two joke checker Liz.
She's come back.
I mean, are we the placebo?
I don't get it.
I think I don't know.
I don't know.
Claire Briley, we'd be able to sleep if we didn't actually run the convention but just
talked about all the lectures for a weekend.
Claire Briley of Croydon will understand the reference to Rob Hanson and volcanic eruption.
And we will also put a link to the explanation of that joke in the show notes.
So on this subject of Dave Mansfield's lock, I want to do some follow out Alison hat tip
to the upgrade podcast for the name.
But basically this never happens.
Discussed online convention mechanisms on their podcast and Dave has written to us about
Zoom and Discord and Octa though.
And I do just want to say they point out that Zoom and Discord are not as good as real
conventions.
And I just want to highlight I very much strongly agree with that sentiment.
But as someone who hasn't been to a proper convention 18 months and won't go to another
one for another 18 months, I am sort of trying to manage this three year stretch of loneliness
and isolation with some level of online interactivity.
And so we are trying our best in a difficult and trying time.
So yes, but I'm not in any way of the impression that any of this stuff is as good as a proper
convention.
And I very much look forward to the point of which they happen again because I miss them
very, very dearly.
So I take a point and also I do want to hear what is your plan for the convention you're
going to go to in 18 months.
But I can see that if everyone's be saying, oh, you can get on Discord and talk to fans
and do Zoom's and you get on Discord and it is basically I see, but I can use more emoji
than.
And gifts.
Don't forget those gifts.
Yeah, it's not exactly like, it's not exactly what we were promised at the turn of the 20th
century, I think.
Yes, I want the matrix.
And it hasn't come yet.
And second life isn't it.
So if anyone writes in, boo.
I want a virtual world in which my neck doesn't hurt, which is a little bit of fun.
Alison's neck hurts and we will get to that in staying injured in the apocalypse.
In the things not to do with your new toys.
Oh man, that's going to really set up.
Like people could be like, what on earth has she done?
Okay, so Claire Briarley of Croydon writes to us and says things which are very nice.
I picked out a highlight as I like to do with Claire's letters and my highlight is that she
says the Discord chat has already made me feel quite fanish, I interested and engaged
and amused and occasionally irritated.
And that seems like a good thing.
I am happy that it is engendered all of those emotions that I think means it might be working
in some way.
So hoorah.
And yes, it was a very lovely letter.
Thank you, Claire.
My highlight from Claire's letter is how in Stainche's prior attempts to baffle the
whole game of by sending him a corner of a completed jigsaw puzzle.
She's right.
That is the conclusion we came to and we should continue with that.
I think, I mean, I don't think he would be baffled.
I think he would be flat.
Neil, if you're listening, do write in.
No explanation.
I'm sending a corner of a random completed jigsaw puzzle.
Okay.
And yes, Alison, any highlights from Claire's letter?
Those two, but also she does mention the possibility of sending Neil Gaiman "Weterbix",
which reminds me that we have had the fourth installment of Claire's series of short fan
scenes about "Weterbix", which means that it is that manageable for Hugo.
So, you know, if you're thinking about your Hugo nominations for 2021, yeah.
If you can nominate things for 2021, I strongly, strongly advise that you nominate Claire's
"Weterbix-based" fan scene, which is called "Weekend Weeterbix".
It is eligible for a Hugo award.
I think it should win.
It's better that the fans that you know I'm usually nominated for.
And so, yeah, please go forth and nominate.
And also, it'd be really funny if Claire won for "Weekend Weeterbix" and not "Bonardo
Wigs".
Oh, come on, you can find that funny.
But there we go.
I'm a bad human being.
Yes.
One of my favourite moments in all of fandom was when I got to give Claire a Hugo award.
That was a 10-out-10 time in my life.
One of my favourite moments in fandom was when I got up one morning to discover that Claire
had sent me a "Weterbix" by a large letter post lovingly encased in a box made out of
Lego.
And I found out in the most recent edition of "Weekend Weerbix" that my wife and I
have won a prize and we don't know what the prize is.
So, that's very exciting.
Have you?
What have you won a prize for?
You don't know.
Sending sending the smallest "Weterbix" to Claire or sending a "Weterbix" in the smallest
amount of packaging, I suppose.
We didn't like sending mini "Weterbix".
I was going to say...
I was going to cover all the podcasts because I've just had an unrelated idea.
I think I'm going to cut that out of the podcast because I've just had an idea.
It's a good title for the podcast.
Yeah, though, I have to stay in, mightn't it?
Liz went to the "Fire Fringe".
So "Fire" is a magazine, the name of which is easy to pronounce unless you're an old
white guy.
And they ran a convention since the last time we recorded.
And Liz went.
So Liz, tell us about that.
I did.
I should probably explain what the "Firecon Fringe" was.
So "Firecon" ran over two days and mostly in, I think, the US Eastern time zone.
And they also had limited memberships.
I mean, they had quite a lot of members, but they didn't have unlimited memberships.
So I decided not to buy a membership because it would be a terrible time zone for me and
I would just be taking up a seat.
Someone else could otherwise be occupying in a more productive way.
So they also put on the "Firecon Fringe", which essentially on the day before the convention,
the organiser of the "Firecon Fringe", I believe, are Vida Cruz and Iori Kusano.
Basically put on " Fringe" programming so that people who were in time zones where it
would be quite awkward for them to watch a lot of the main convention programming would
get to feel involved.
And they very kindly made this all available for free.
You just had to register.
So I attended several items on the "Firecon Fringe" and it was all very nice.
It started for me at 7am.
So I did miss the first couple of hours.
But it ran from 7am to 7pm in my time zone, which was great.
What did I watch panels on?
I watched a panel on running a genre magazine.
I watched a tough panel on finding and getting involved in your local science fiction scene.
I watched a really good one called "Different But the Same", writing from the diaspora
versus writing locally where they had essentially a bunch of authors who were all either from
the diaspora or not, but had very different perspectives on how it worked for them personally
being diaspora authors or non-diaspora authors.
The benefits of being seen as one or the other and the way there's benefits of being seen
and one or the other was different depending which diaspora you were in.
And it was a really interesting panel that could only be done really by having a very
diverse and interesting set of authors who all came from a slightly different angle on
this.
So I was just wondering how I finished out by watching one called "Destroy All Emperors",
the post-colonial and anti-colonial insight fiction of fantasy.
And then I listened to part of "We Won't Phone It In" for an Anglophone audience, which was,
yeah, about how you write and thinking about your audience and thinking about where your
book is going to be sold and marketed and where the translation is going to go.
And also the difficulties of writing works where just because of commercial necessity,
you need to be often trying to sell them if you're writing an English to a US or UK publisher
and how what they see as what will be marketable and palatable to an Anglophone audience is
not necessarily the same as what the audience actually would like to see, they feel.
And it was also very interesting because they even discussed like what is the definition
of an Anglophone audience.
It's not everyone whose native language is English, it's not everyone who can read books
in English, it is kind of different depending on whether you're from a country which is
part of this dominant marketplace.
So basically they were all really interesting.
I say I listen to part of them because I did unfortunately have a few issues with my internet.
It didn't seem to particularly like streaming from their streaming service, but I think
that was my internet because no one else seemed to have problems.
And it was just inviting a bunch of really interesting people into your living room to
talk on an interesting subject for an hour.
And I very much enjoyed it.
And then I understand the rest of it was also really interesting if you're a full member,
you could join their Discord as well and talk to people that way.
Nice.
That sounds really, really cool.
I will say it was also an example of like for me because I wasn't on the Discord, it literally
was just a set of panels which were the panelists on Zoom and they were streamed by a streaming
service they used because you had to register.
And I was just sort of watching them or listening to them like a podcast at certain times.
And it did completely hold my attention.
So maybe you don't always need to have the social side of things in there.
Sometimes it is enough to just have great content and put it out there and there's an
audience for that.
Yeah, I think that obviously varies from like committed to question and from many to venue.
I missed a panel yesterday.
This is a bit of a digression, but it's on translation.
So I think it is relevant to what you were saying where the essence of Wonder people run
a weekend by weekend track of SF panels.
They are in the afternoon in Eastern time, US time, which is a little bit of a shame because
a lot of content is in that time zone.
But the one yesterday was on a conversation about SF and F in translation and they had
four different translators who presented interpretations of the same passage and discussed
like the differences between the choices they had made, which sounded really interesting.
And I was very sad to miss it.
But I will put a link in the show notes for anyone who's interested in signing up to that
kind of chain of panels.
I was in a panel at WELCOME with the nominees with the finalists for the LoadStar award.
#NotAHUGAR.
And they were talking about the that issue about the publishers expectations for the
audience being very different from what your audience actually wants with regard to young
adult novels, where I think it is also very relevant.
So did you find Liz that you felt that you were missing out from not being on the Discord
or did it kind of not really feel like there was anything that you hadn't been able to
interact with?
I did feel I was missing out because I saw a number of people on Twitter saying how good
and how kind of welcoming and also the Discord was.
But I think it's also worth pointing out that, you know, Firecom was very much aimed at BIPOC
participants.
And so it wasn't really aimed at me anyway, so it's possible that what I would have got
out of the Discord would be different from what other people got out of the Discord.
I'm sure I would have still had a really good time on it, but I wasn't looking to make
those connections with other writers from other communities.
But one other thing I want to say is that Firecom also, I think, had live captioning for
all their panels, including all the Fringe panels.
And that worked really well.
Cool.
But have gone to Firecom if they had had memberships and had not been full, because I felt that
it would have been an opportunity for me to essentially absorb a lot of other people's
experiences in quite a good way without having to be a participant or make any of that happen.
I could have just kind of listened to what people had to say.
But I couldn't do the Friday night for some other reason.
Although, although I never go anywhere and never do anything, my life appears to be incredibly
full all the time, which I find very strange.
I don't understand what's happened.
My final thought about Firecom is actually it worked.
Maybe it worked for me as something which I listened to rather than interacted with,
because really it was a convention designed for me personally to be listening to and learning
from, but maybe not interacting and putting out my voice in there, because that's not
really what it was for.
That was kind of what I wanted to say.
My brain is not working properly.
I think I basically nicked what I listened to and then faced it in a different way.
So, teamwork.
Yeah, teamwork.
No, and I think I think obviously the value of being an ally is good, because you can
lend your voice and weight to allyship.
But often it's more important to be a good listener and not to use your voice instead
of listening to black, indigenous people of colour voices.
And so, yes, I think that is probably a good point.
I did go to a convention, which was not Firecom, but I went to a convention last weekend, which
was IneffableCon, which was a virtual convention focused around Good Omen's fandom.
So Rachel Livermore and Bethany Windsor were the co-chairs, and I think they hit about
600 attendees virtually.
I didn't take part much in the social spaces because I was doing a few tabletop game related
events that weekend.
But I did see some of the programming.
They did Pointless, which was awesome, very well done.
And people seem to be having a really good time.
So, fandom, I have not been to conventions where the primary thrust of the fan stream
is centered around fan fiction and fan works in quite the same way that that convention
had a strong emphasis on that.
So it was really interesting to see that side of fandom.
So, yeah, that was really good.
I will say Rachel has posted a Twitter thread about the platform they used, in which she
kind of outlies some of the benefits and drawbacks.
And we will post a link to that in the show notes because it was very good and very thoughtful
thread.
I was particularly struck with one of her tweets in that thread, which was that they
designed their social spaces by doing exactly what I was planning to for punctuation, which
is to have a giant zoom with a load of breakout spaces for lots of different things.
You could go somewhere in it, you could go somewhere in chill, you could go somewhere
and discuss all sorts of things and you could have meat, spontaneous meat ups and that sort
of thing.
And she said, that's great.
And I was like, well, that is exactly what we were hoping to do.
So that was very exciting to me.
And then she went and said, of course, you have to get everyone on zoom 5.3.
And I was like, yeah, well, that is the story of my life for October has been telling every
single person I know individually how to upgrade to zoom 5.3.
So I think I'm going to do it again here and say, do upgrade to zoom 5.3 by going to www.zoom.us/dact.
Download, we will put the link in the show notes.
Actually, no, do upgrade to zoom 5.3.
We will put the link in the show notes before coming to punctuation or other cons that are
using zoom because your experience will be much improved.
So as I say, I went to an F double.
I had a good time.
I'm kind of on the periphery of both the technical solutions used to implement the convention
and also the fandom.
So I kind of feel like I don't have much more to say this inside falls.
[MUSIC]
Liz put a link in our show notes to an article on using game design to make virtual events
more social.
So Liz, do you want to give us a quick pre-see of this article and kind of why it's interesting?
Yeah, so it was just a conference called Roguelike Celebration, which is a game design conference.
And rather than just using discord or Slack or zoom or whatever, they actually built themselves
a mod to run the convention.
So when you log in, you're placed into, do I need to explain mod?
I had to look it up.
Oh my god, oh my god.
I remember using what when I was a kid, but I think I only used the flight for five minutes
and they were not really a thing when I was at school or at uni.
Oh god.
They weren't really a thing when I was at school either, John.
Well, yeah, but you guys had I because it's right.
You made your own fun.
Okay.
So there was a period between when I went to school and when John went to school, when
the mod or multi-user dungeon was the state of the art.
And it is in fact a text based, a multi-room text based adventure game that you manage
for yourself.
So wander around.
Yeah, I will then I return you to Liz.
Yes, so they basically decided that since this was something that their attendees would
probably be quite into, they would run it.
Essentially, they have something sort of a bit like a discord or an ILC, except you're
actually navigating around this little ASCII art map.
And when you go to different rooms, you're in a slightly different channel.
And if you want to watch the talk, then you go into the theatre and you can see their
talk being streamed there and chat underneath it.
But they kind of added into it kind of lots of little Easter eggs.
So you know, there was a swag table and you could take swag and then you could see everyone
else who was there and they'd be holding a piece of the, you know, virtual swag.
And like that, you think you could you could randomly drink potions that would put an emoji
in front of your name and things like that.
I'm at the bar at the bar and it just made everything it kind of gave people things to
play with things to chat about playing with because you could see all these other people
have little emoji in front of your name and ask them, well, how do you get the emoji?
And they could point you to the potion and things like that.
Just to add a bit of fun to it.
And also having the different rooms allowed them to divide things between, okay, you can
go into the theatre or whatever and talk to lots and lots of people.
Or you go into one of the smaller side rooms and talk to a few people.
So the kind of thing you try and do with a big Zoom channel versus breakout rooms, except
you do it by, you know, clicking around on a map and ending up in the different rooms
they have, you know, and if you look at their map, they have like, you know, they have a
theatre and they have a bar and things like that.
But they also had a haunted foyer and the astral plane.
Okay.
At this point, I'd like to say there used to be a Spanish mod called Elle de Mu, which
I suspect quite a few of Alice in us will remember.
And this is a thing that I can, it was run by Lucy Hunt Singer.
This is a thing that I can date almost precisely because I know that I was in Elle de Mu in
August 1997 because when Diana died, Alan Harris and I were in a room in Elle de Mu
swapping, you know, all those die dies, dody deaders, dodo type jokes.
And Lucy became very quiet and it turned out that she was genuinely upset at the death
of Diana Princess of Wales and none of the British fans could understand how this was
such a thing was possible.
So, and that demonstrated again that text based chat is not perfect for catching the
mood of the people you're interacting with.
But anyway, Elle de Mu was amazing.
And if any, we want, we quite like the idea of putting a mud onto punctuation, but concluded
that we didn't have time or energy to do it.
So if you're listening to this and are like, oh God, I could whip up a mud for punctuation
in 10 minutes flat and I'd be happy to, please get in touch.
This that you can go and use the one from Rogreic celebration if you like, but I think,
you know, they literally wrote it for that conference.
And so while it's open source, it is not open source, but ready and easy and friendly
to deploy right now.
So it, one of the things about these conventions which have successful social environments is
that it seems to be very obvious that a mud is a great environment for people who are
going to a Rogreic conference because they're probably pretty used to interacting through
mud.
Zasky Rogreics are very much the sort of thing which anyone going to a Rogreic convention
is going to be up for or at least have familiarity with.
And in the same way, when I went to the 3D convention, their social spaces were very
successful and one of the ones that was successful was the actual virtual reality space because
a significant proportion of the members of that convention already own VR headsets and
VR space is a great for socialization.
Like second life because you can actually wander around in a much more natural way than any
of the flat, flat social environments that we've found so far.
No, and I think that's a good point.
Like, I think there is a certain level of buy-in that a gaming convention will have for
gaming inspired social tools.
And that was something that the UK Games Expo also leveraged although apparently the big
gaming convention in Germany, Spiel, often referred to as Essen, apparently their online
spaces are a bit awful.
I've not actually looked really myself but I've heard from a couple of friends that their
online solution is not very good, which is a shame.
Obviously, we're not planning to do a mud punctuation because they're a phenomenon of
our work and we don't know how to do it as our lesson says, if you could do it, please
volunteer because that would be awesome.
But it is interesting to see people kind of trying to take a more lateral view of how
we could solve some of these problems because I do think that like the Zoom Discord model
has some pretty significant flaws and I am interested in kind of how we can come up with
alternatives which maybe do better at some of these things and I think this looked like
quite an imaginative way of doing it.
And I may not be familiar with muds but I did write the most popular walkthrough for
the Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy text based adventure on gamefakus.com to go and
check that out.
Speaking of games which must have come out before you were born, John.
Yeah.
I played that when it was new.
I have a puppy.
I mean, at the time it was one of my favourite, it was just extraordinary.
I mean, it is quite a hard game and we didn't have any walkthroughs then.
We just had to kind of cry and then we meet people in the pub.
Do you remember that?
And we go, oh my God, I'm so stuck on this terrible game.
And amongst other things, it has a point where if you didn't do something at the beginning
of the game like approximately 8,000 turns ago, you are now f***ed.
Which is what we call in modern terms, bad game design.
A negative play experience.
Yeah, I was going to say I obviously fall between these tools because while I did not
ever write a walkthrough for gamefaks, I do remember buying the walkthrough to a LucasArts
adventure game from an advert in the back of a game magazine for like £2.50 and they
sent you like a photocopied sheet listing everything you should do.
So I could unlock Atlantis, I think?
Yeah, it was high quality.
And then of course the internet came along and destroyed that.
Oh God, remember the small ads in the back of games magazines?
They were the best.
Yeah.
I remember rigging.
You could ring a number.
You could ring an '08, '08, '70.
Maybe it was even an '09 number to get the answers to questions.
And a woman will give you hints in a very breathy voice.
Ha ha ha.
No, it was a man, it was a Scottish man, I'm pretty sure.
But I was stuck on Final Fantasy Adventure on the Game Boy, which was a game that came
out the year I was born, and it did not have a good walkthrough on the internet.
And there's a bit where you have to like take a riddle and use it in order to open a door.
And it was like, I can't remember what the riddle was.
But the answer to the riddle was you had to walk around two palm trees in the desert in
a anti-clockwise figure of eight or something like that.
And I had to call a helpline to get that piece of information so I could continue on.
Great game.
Just got very stuck on that one bit.
Happy memories.
If you have never played the Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy, you should-
We will put a link in the show notes.
You should do it because it's fantastic, but I'm going to tell you now and for free,
read the sandwich to the dog. You will thank me later.
I just have a sandwich right. I'm pretty sure it's a sandwich.
Yeah, you've got to feed that dog.
And you've got to- You need to take your junk mail with you.
Don't leave the junk mail behind.
Yeah, I mean in general though, for difficult measures, adventures do not leave anything
behind. I mean, take everything.
Yeah, it'll all be useful.
Yeah, no. If you get to the end of the game and you're going to need everything, yeah.
And it's not the junk mail, it's the feeding the sandwich to the dog, which is very much
non-obvious thing to do.
And yeah.
And you do have to have done it.
I'll link to my walkthrough in the show notes.
If you are someone who would find it more fun not to be enormously frustrated.
Yeah, especially, you know, you're going to get stuck for weeks otherwise.
I kind of have a no walkthrough policy for games, which I'm kind of relenting on.
And I'm kind of going to, oh, now I do walkthroughs and you go, oh, God, was that even
a thing?
So yeah.
Okay.
We digressed slightly.
Let's talk about our convention.
That was a elegant segue.
Nailed it.
So punctuation coming up 13th to the 15th of November, 2020.
We have some members.
I believe we now have 88 members.
So it's going to be a swinging time.
Lots of people talking on the discord already.
And yeah, hopefully it'll be good.
Sorry, 90 members, 90 members.
Two thirds of the This Never Happens podcast have joined up.
I leave it to the audience to guess what the third person is.
And yes, Alison is wetting herself in the background.
Okay, so that's a thing about middle age and he's, ow.
That was a very deep encapsulation of the effects of middle age in audio for.
Oh, yeah, no, that was so sorry, Alison.
Crick, cricks of the deck are horrible.
They really are.
But yes, I think our convention will be very good.
One of the things we have been trying to do in order to make our convention better is
to find out from the people we know and the people who might be coming.
While things they miss about interacting with people in the real world and trying to think
about how we might be able to emulate or get out the same kind of feelings in a virtual
space.
And this is something that Alison posted a Facebook comment about, sorry, Facebook post
about in order to try and get people's opinions.
So Alison, do you want to talk a little bit about that?
I think you basically said roughly what I was going to say, which is that I asked people
what things they used to enjoy and if they can't do them now, how have they replicated
it online?
And I did get some answers that were kind of the thing I enjoyed doing is impossible
to replicate online.
But I got quite a lot of answers that weren't like that and came up with quite a lot of
quite good ideas for things that you can do socially, including obviously the things we
already know like, like Zooms and Borg gaming and and knitted natter type event, you know,
the sorts of you could do your crafting workshops online and you could do lots of things where
you're socializing and but also doing something like playing a game or crafting.
Some whole slew of things which are kind of not quite as satisfactory.
I think one of the things that we've lost and we may never get back is voices joining together
in song or people playing together as a band in a way that the internet is not delivering
at all at the moment.
And so music is one of the things that the ways that we're doing things online kind of
involve turn taking and solo performance.
But lots of interesting ideas.
Lots of people saying, well, the thing I used to really like was getting drunk with a load
of my mates and behaving hugely and appropriately.
And I think that's an issue, isn't it?
You know, I feel that sort of sense that I'm never going to get pissed in a space that's
not surrounded by my actual own home is a problem for me.
#NotAnAlcoholic I promise, maybe if I had a beer it would suse my neck.
It do write to us about the things that you are doing that are translatable online and
are not translatable online.
And it was quite, you know, it was kind of people kind of talking about what they're
doing to make up for not having air shows and all the different sorts of activities that
people would normally have done in their spare time.
And that's, so we've got to replicate some of those at punctuation if we can.
And we are very keen to listen to how other people, if you are someone who feels poorly
served by the way in which socialising and conventions have been in the pandemic, please
write to us and tell us what the things you have trouble with are because we may not be
able to fix them, but we would like to think about them.
But particularly if you have a different hobby space where people are doing things better
that science fiction conventions have not yet worked out how to do, then do tell us because
we do want to steal good practice from other sorts of events.
Yep, good artists, good artists borrow great artists steal.
I do miss going out and singing in groups, but that's just one of the few things that
hasn't restarted them.
We tried to have a sing-along on Zoom and it was very funny, but if what you're missing
from Sing-alongs isn't the hilariousness of time lags on the internet causing it to
sound awful, I'm not sure whether the way we tried to solve it will help.
Apparently that's what we're going to get from 5G.
Whenever people go, "Oh, 5G is a solution waiting for a problem," which it certainly
is, it should be possible to use 5G networks to eliminate lag and allow for essentially
spontaneous activity like singing and music making.
I do think now we've got gigabyte fibre, then I think the next obvious frontier is reducing
latency.
I mean, obviously you can get really easily bitten in the butt by saying this, but no
one could possibly need more into that than gigabit fibre.
Right?
But certainly at the point where it's fine for streaming 4K video, I kind of feel like
maybe the next job is to reduce the latency.
But the put-back cables is that cables have limits based on repeaters and contention that
mean that they are not achieving.
The speed of light is not a hard, you know, the amount of time it takes to light to go
all the way around the world is not very great.
So that's probably not going to stop you singing with your friends.
That was the 17th episode of the Octa Thorp podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
The theme music of this episode is "Spanfair for Space" by Kevin Macleod at Incompetech.com
used under a creative commons attribution treatment point of license.
We haven't done a staying sail in the apocalypse for a while.
I mean, we've hugely digressed many times.
We haven't done a formal staying sail in the apocalypse segment for a while.
So Alison, why does your neck hurt?
So about six years ago, I was a science fiction convention or some similar event and Alex
Holden, who is a science fiction fan, sidled up to me and said, "I am thinking of going
into business as a high-end concertina maker.
Does that sound like a stupid idea?"
And I said, "No, Alex.
That sounds like an extremely good idea because there is a massive shortage of high-end
concertina makers and once you get the hang of it, you will sell everyone that you make
because you know."
So there is a question about whether you can actually make them in a commercial way that
makes you money, but subject to that, yeah, it appears to be a great business to go into.
And let me know when you've got the hang of making concertinas and I will have a concertina
off you.
All right.
So with me so far, so about two years ago, he came back to me.
He learned how to build a concertina and he made a couple of concertinas and they came
back to me and said, "My order book is starting to fill up and I am starting to raise my
prices and would you like to put down a deposit on a concertina before I raise the prices?"
Seeing as you said you would.
And I was like, "Absolutely.
That sounds amazing."
He said, "It'll be about eight months."
And that was about two years ago.
So I have a concertina which I got this week and I should say in Alex's defense that about
four months of that was my fault because I decided I wanted amazingly fancy bellows,
papers designed by Sumaces.
We will put a picture of my incredibly beautiful Holden Dumberate concertina in the show notes
or you can even use it as the chapter title, John.
I will.
Yeah.
When I'll get your photo.
I mean, it's only going to be the same photo that I had as my zoom background or something.
Anyway, so I got it on Tuesday and I cannot play concertina at all.
I play Melodian.
How I've been explaining this to people is that if you, it's like going to a Jvorak
keyboard.
So you were, you need to kind of relearn the way you type.
And also there are some other things that are different.
So I can now after five days of extremely concentrated concertina practice, I can now
play concertina very badly and I am going to a all day concertina workshop just as soon
as we finish recording.
So anyway, I've played concertina.
You're supposed to build up very, very slowly about kind of 30 minutes a day when you get
a new instrument into 15 minute chunks so that you don't do something like massively
put your neck out due to playing concertina for six hours.
Anyway, there's the end of the story.
So I woke up this morning with a spectacularly stiff neck as a result of playing too much
concertina which would not really be a big problem.
We're not the fact that we're recording the podcast and then I'm going to an all day
concertina workshop, which I'm not sure how much concertina play I'm going to be able
to do with that pain.
Concertina is they're great.
If you'd like, we'll also put a link to Alex's Instagram where he has a lot of exceptionally
beautiful photographs.
If you like photographs of squeeze boxes and also his website where you too could purchase
a had built concertina.
So my concertina was a very prodigious bargain.
I assume as a result of that conversation I had with Alex six years ago.
I think he charges a lot more for them now than he charged me, but it's still, it's still
you know, if you need a concertina definitely the place to go.
Obviously they're hand built traditionally made concertinas and they are not cheap, but
they give.
It is spectacularly beautiful.
It made me want to buy one even though my own experience is attempting to play the
melodian and being really bad at it and giving up.
Yeah, I would say that I should probably have started from the beginning, which is in 1829.
I was Wheatstone who invented a great many things put down having seen German small
accordions which were instruments for playing chords on made a patent to make a hexagonal
instrument which he called the concertina and that is essentially the start of the instrument.
And instruments much like mine have been made since about 1840 or 1850 and they haven't
really changed a design very much since the in the last 140 years.
So would you say that it's an area which is rape for Silicon Valley disruption?
No, but it's clear some of the things that Alex is doing are about applying being a modern
person with a modern sort of brain because Alex isn't actually a folky, but he's clearly,
he's coming at it from the point of view of being a person who can make things.
So he is actually being his concertinas are quite disruptive, for example, by the way,
has aluminium reeds which is quite a disruptive thing to do.
Yeah.
And as a result, it's very light.
Nice.
Or aluminium reed frames rather.
Yeah.
Your story about being very achy reminds me of the time.
So I went on holiday with my three brothers and my mother and my father to Newqui and
my mum and dad said they do surfing lessons.
You want to learn to surf?
And I was like, what?
Your dyspraxic son with no sense of balance.
Now you can pull the other one.
It's got bells on.
But two of my brothers did want to learn surf because they don't have to sprax your
and can balance.
And so they did.
And they decided to surf and then they decided to spend the morning with surfing lesson and
they decided they would keep surfing all after doodie evening.
And the next day they had like wounds on their feet.
We had to go and get antiseptic dressings like they ached all over because if you just
if you don't have a break, yeah, you don't notice until the next day how much stress is
putting on your body.
And the answer was many.
So I was cheerfully just sort of stretching and generally walking to places and they were
really having trouble with those kinds of activities.
So so yeah, it's like the day after I did ring fit adventure and re-January knows the
ache is real.
I have two more things to say on that.
One is a response to you.
One is one of the things I actually put in the show notes, which is thank you so much
for your recommendation to download a program called Buddy move, which stops you sitting
in one place for a long time and make sure you do stretching exercises.
I had downloaded it, but I had not installed it.
Apparently you also need to install it and act on the things it tells you do before it
works.
Yeah, that's the.
And the second thing is that my I used to ride horses periodically as a small child in
the way that small girls tend to.
And I never, you know, obviously horse riding is one of the things where you can overdo
it.
But in fact, I never really did have a problem with a child, including go for an entire week
horse riding.
But then about 10 years after I'd never after I'd written, we were in Brecken for Brecken,
which was the Hey on why convention, one of the Hey on why conventions that got organized
in the in the Swan Hotel in Hay that had no program.
But Caroline Mullen organized a pony trek for people who liked that sort of thing.
And I went pony trekking for three hours.
And the following day I was in very significant amounts of really spectacularly saw after
that.
So yeah, amazing.
I blowed Caroline.
So Liz, you've been staying sane in the apocalypse by eating cakes that have been sprayed with
rum.
So I saw this post on your Instagram and I knew we had to cover it on the podcast.
So could you please tell us where to go in order to get a cake spray painted with rum?
Oh, I went out for afternoon tea.
What can I have questions?
What is out?
Yeah, I'm saying you met friends for an indoor meal.
Yes.
OK, so we're already fizzing with excitement and jealousy.
Yeah, I try not to mention it too much when it's on staying sane in the apocalypse because
Alison, you know, is saying how sad it is that she can't basically go out and get smashed
and do inadvisable things.
And I could if I wanted to go out and get smashed and do inadvisable things and I wouldn't
have to do it.
Because every Tuesday, you listener, if you ring Liz on a Tuesday after about seven in
the afternoon, for all, she's so getty said, Zavar.
So I went out for afternoon tea, which is a thing you can do when the cases of COVID
are minimal, I understand.
And yeah, we went for fancy afternoon tea for my friend's birthday treat.
And you know, it's a sort of place where they bring you a tea menu and then they bring
you lots of little tiny cakes and scones.
But the start thing is they bring you a rum Baba cake, which had matcha cream on top.
And then they ask you, would, would you like it sprits with rum and either pineapple or
mango flavoring?
And I said, yes, please, I don't know if you did anything at all to taste, but it's
quite fun to have someone come and sort of spray rum on your cake.
Like it's from a tiny perfume dispenser.
That is excellent.
And when international travel is possible again, I'm coming to visit you in Bangkok,
a photo show.
And we're going out for fancy afternoon tea.
Yeah.
Oh, can we, can we like have like an octa-sore holiday in Bangkok, Adam?
And do the podcast for real there?
One day, one day, that would be great.
So I, so, so yes, so on the topic of seeing friends, I have been staying sane in the
apocalypse by purchasing an outdoor infrared heater and putting it in my garden.
And there is access to my garden from outside.
So you'd have to come through my house.
And my table is about to be too wide.
So I could have a friend at the other end of the table and we can have tea and there
is a heater and I've got a little sheltered bit of the garden.
So the rain doesn't get us unless it's a yellow rainwater, which I postpone.
And so I've had a couple of friends from work over in the last couple of weeks for sort
of morning tea breaks.
And that has been brilliant, would highly recommend living in a semi-detached house with a garden
and then buying a heater for the garden and having friends come over to enjoy tea.
I appreciate not everyone listening will have that list of things.
But I will put a link in the show notes to the outdoor heater I procured.
And, and yeah, it's very exciting.
And I have been thoroughly enjoying it.
It was Spanish idea.
I can claim no credit at all for the planning phase of this.
But it's bad.
He said very tentatively, can we do this?
And I was like, yes, go and find which one we're buying now.
And she was like, oh, I was not expecting that level of buy in that quickly.
But yeah, it's as I miss people being able to see people is nice.
And that has been because I think I'd be lisual no more about this.
But the impression I get from reading the news and the learned people about COVID is that
outdoor transmission is a good deal less of a problem than the risk from indoor transmission.
And so I think seeing one friend at a time for outdoor pursuits seems pretty safe generally.
I'm going to say slightly edgyly.
At least some of that, though, is going to be that we cannot, we are less likely to know
when the transmission happened when it's at an outdoor thing.
So but yeah, no, it's clear that outdoor events are much, much safer.
Though not that the Amy Barrett thing in the Rose Garden clearly spread it to lots of people
despite being outdoors.
So it's not 100%.
That was not entirely outdoors.
It had indoor sections.
Ah, that's good to know.
Well, but also what I haven't done is I haven't lined my garden with seats, which are next
to each other and put 300 people in it.
So that is also.
Yeah.
You can't actually get to my garden without going through my house.
So I'm always slightly edgy about the whole outdoor thing.
I've just realized what your statement means, Alison.
It means that this was the secret emergency podcast about Trump's coronavirus.
Because we mentioned the Rose Garden meeting and outdoor and indoor transmission.
So listeners that have been waiting on 10 to hook.
It was this episode.
I've done two other things to say saying in the apocalypse, which is firstly, I've deleted
my weekly reminder to nag Alison for TAF Art because Alison has given me TAF Art and
that means my TAF report is finished.
So it is about to be on sale.
Okay.
For the benefit of people listening who are not on Facebook, John posted to Facebook saying,
I have finished my TAF report and I followed up with, that's a very kind way to say, Alison
finally delivered the bloody cover, only seven months late, isn't it?
I mean, but I will say that of the nine years that it took me to deliver my TAF report,
less than 10% of that was your doing.
So I think in general, it could be safely said that I took most of the time on my own.
Yeah.
I mean, I think it was only a bit late.
It would have been done for Easter if we'd had Easter and sometimes, sometimes, you know,
this happened when they happened and I'm quite pleased with the cover now that it's done.
Oh, yeah.
Me too.
It's not your fault.
It took a long time.
It took a long time because I decided you ought to wear Arthur Dent's dressing gown and
instead of just saying, "I'm going to take the photo, I found a suitable dressing gown
on the internet and used Photoshop's puppet warp to add it to your body digitally."
And then I thought, "Oh, that ribbon crawl."
It is fantastic, listener, like I cannot.
Ribbon crawl should automatically have the sort of ribbons that John would actually wear
attached to his combat.
So I photoshopped all the ribbons individually, which was probably a bit stupid, but will
be useful for punctuation where a lot of these ribbons are going to get you reused.
And if you have any ideas for great con ribbons that you'd like to take to a con, let us
know and I'll photoshopped them up before punctuation.
But that was one of the things I did that did not help.
It's also what I'm talking about, muscle pain.
It's not impossible that the very large number of hours I spent on photoshopped this week,
where again, I could have done with somebody to tell me to get up and stretch a bit more
often, might actually also have had something to do with my neck.
This is not in any way meant to be a guilt trip.
It's definitely mostly the concertina.
Apparently I have terrible, terrible health habits.
Steve was like, that's why I do a set of Chigong exercises every day that I decided to prevent
this sort of thing.
And he was very lucky not to have a microwavable dragon throw at him, I can tell you.
And I also yesterday spent 13 and a quarter hours playing Arkham Horror the Card Game or
my computer with three people from across the world in an Ironman run of the circle
and done.
And we won.
I sat down at my computer at about 8.20 and I stood up again at about 10 o'clock and
it's been brought the water, coffee, pancakes, a little eggbook muffin, a re-imagination
of a Taco Bell Crunchwrap Supreme, some toast and biscuits.
And she is a 10 out of 10 spouse.
Thank you very much, darling.
And if you do that in 20 years time, you'll wake up the following day with a majestic stiff
deck.
What I did was, firstly, I stood up every time my watch bleated at me, so that helped.
But I also went for a run immediately after finishing, which I think might have also helped
blow some of the cobwebs out.
Although it was a pretty slow run, I will admit.
That is all that I've done, stay sane in the apocalypse.
But I feel like it's been a pretty full fortnight.
I should say that I saw my daughter in the outdoors yesterday.
I love the family that she with her girlfriend.
Oh, because she's not living with her family.
Yeah.
So along with Marianne and Marianne's girlfriend and Marianne's girlfriend's family, which
made seven in total.
So we actually went on our walk in two non-mingling groups.
And then we got back before the other group because obviously it had me in it and Marianne.
And we found ourselves, we went, it was a much shorter walk, I should stress.
And we found ourselves at a pub that would be converted to a steakhouse.
And so we sat outside this pub that would be converted into a steakhouse and sent Stephen
in to see if he could get us three copies.
And they said, we only serve drinks with meals, I'm afraid.
And so we said, can we have the menu?
And they said, certainly, but you would have to sit out inside because we cannot serve food
outside.
And I'm just waiting for this company to announce that they've got a bust as a result of COVID.
And I'm going, you know what?
You need to work out how you can serve meals outside.
And I know you're not supposed to ever say anything that could be finished with the words
you idiot, but there we go.
You should learn how to serve meals outside you idiots.
If your pub is empty, you should also serve people coffees, even if they're not eating
a meal because money is money.
You idiots, yeah, like that.
So I would have liked to have had a coffee with my daughter afterward gov for a walk.
The obvious proviso is unless you're in a tier three lockdown city in which you're not
allowed to serve drinks with our meal.
We are in a tier two space as was the thing and they are allowed to serve drinks.
No, no, seriously, there are alcohol.
Those are alcoholic drinks.
You're allowed to serve coffee without a meal.
Okay.
So, so that's the other thing is that somebody was like, Oh, that can't be able to serve
drinks without food, might be a licensing requirement.
There is no license on coffee yet, which is honestly a good thing for me because obviously
addict and everything.
I remember I went to a long gone three committee meeting with Claire Briley of Croydon and I
saw her order a point of coffee and a triple espresso and poured the triple espresso into
the coffee.
Civil service life.
I believe that leaving the civil service has helped with Claire's caffeine addiction,
but I'm sure she's going to be along in a minute to tell us.
I don't think she drinks as much coffee as she used to.
She used to drink enough coffee that made my hair stand on end.
This podcast will end at the beat.
*burps*