There's still one manoeuvre. It won't work if you guys caught.
Sorry, sorry, sorry.
*laughs*
You guys, it was in the show notes, it was funny then.
It's still funny, the idea of putting these jokes in the show notes is the same as you don't start.
At the point where I read them out, I just-
I just- I just- I just f*cking love- I had not-
Right. Mmm.
Hello everyone, this is just to let you know that we will be recording a live episode at confusion,
which will be on Monday at 11am, we think.
So, look out for us on the programme and we will see you at Eastacom.
Now onto the episode.
Hello everyone and welcome to the 28th episode of Octa Thought.
The vodcast for Science Fiction and Science Fiction fandom.
This episode is coming out on the 1st of April, which is both April,
Thursday and Monday, Thursday.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
I'm Emily's Batty.
And as you are listening to this, you are either excited for Eastacom
or listening to this instead of Eastacom
or you have already been to Eastacom.
One of those.
Or you don't care at all about Eastacom, that's also an option.
But if you don't care about Eastacom,
this may not be the perfect podcast.
Why are you listening to this podcast?
If we have listeners who don't care about Eastacom, then I respect that.
Right in.
Anyway, we have some letters of comment on the subject of writing in.
And the first letter of comment is from Claire Briarley of Croydon,
the lovely and wise locker from the South-West of London.
Or Surrey, as it's also known.
The lovely and tolerant Claire Briarley since I believe she has not written to us
to complain too much about the joke in the last episode.
She says, "Seens we seldom see.
I don't like having to do these things at the last minute," says Alison.
Right.
Claire has written us some poetry.
Yes, she has.
You don't read out letters prolifically long
unless they are from Chris Gothia.
And that's fair enough since it's patently wrong to pass up a rhyme for Mozilla.
There's still one manoeuvre that offers the succeeds,
but really I know when I'm beat.
With Chris there for filling your poetry needs,
I'm totally obsolete.
Thank you very much, Claire.
I'd like to report to you to Claire on behalf of the Top of the Podcast for Alison.
Ah, that was very funny.
That was very good.
Now, Claire does also say,
"Seven letters of comment is not a record.
A record is a round black thing with a hole in the middle."
And I thought around black thing with a hole in the middle was a bowling ball.
So, clearly I need to adjust my mental model.
Yeah, I think around black thing with a hole in the middle may no longer be a record, Claire.
I think that some old jokes reach the end of their life expectancy,
and that might be one of them.
I believe around black thing with a hole in the middle is a vinyl.
Mmm.
I have vinyl in my kitchen.
Thank you, that job.
I wonder whether Octa thought made any sense to Jerry Sullivan in reverse order.
It certainly provides for some significant foreshadowing.
Perhaps you could set Chris Garthia on to listening to episodes actually in reverse,
and thus decoding your dark hidden messages,
"Weter bit more, John, send."
Ha ha ha ha ha.
I am safe from Jerry sending you more, e to bits,
because Jerry would have to get Claire to send her the "Weter Bicks" in order to then send it to me.
That would be silly.
Claire also writes, "Crossing the streams with Lulzine."
She began to think about what other comedy trios we could work in,
and she mentions there's one obvious possibility with a very enthusiastic younger character
and older character swearing and shacking out "drink."
But I don't understand that reference, so what are you going to have to explain it to me?
You don't understand the reference to Liz having Octa thought one who just resting in her account.
I don't think so.
Okay, John, we'll sit you down and tell you later.
Oh, it's a father-thed joke, right?
It's a very good joke.
Oh, I've never watched Father Ted.
And I still haven't seen Father Ted, and it's a problem because I feel like it's now problematic,
so I'm not sure I'm going to catch up.
Yeah, maybe too late to catch up, but it is a good joke, although it does make me Father Ted.
Listeners who are interested in our thoughts about Father Ted can listen to the episode
in which we talked about it, which we haven't released yet.
So if you could just hack into my iCloud account and get the MP3,
you can find out all about it there.
[laughs]
But she does also say, if Liz is the EOR of EasterCon, then does that make Alison and John Pugham-Pigglet
or Rabbit and Tigger, or no, of course, Canga and Roo?
And I'm not sure that I am the Roo to Alison's Canga.
I think I am much more a Tigger character.
Well, I think I'm much more a Tigger character, so we could have some kind of Tigger off, really.
[laughs]
And you've heard it here.
That will be the other opening ceremony at punctuation, too, with me and Alison's Tigger off.
[laughs]
I would also like to full-clare that I do remember Rent-A-Ghost, but only vaguely.
I do not. But I do own some vinyl.
I do not. I do not.
Is it true that the youngest member of the podcast is the only one that owns any vinyl?
Actually, I do own it. I do own it as a vinyl.
I have a 12-inch of the Circle in the Square by Redbox.
I kind of picture this, and I have it framed on my wall.
And for younger listeners, that's 30 centimeters.
[laughs]
They have a 30-selled, 30-centimeter, or 22-and-a-half, or whatever, it is 17-and-a-half centimeter records.
That's not how it works!
[laughs]
So, Chris Garcia also wrote to us, saying "anywho, my audio multitasking is all out loud,
as long as they're all from different sources.
If I've got a single source of sound like everything off of a single laptop, it gets muddled shockingly."
[laughs]
I usually have a phone, two laptops, a Bluetooth speaker, and a pair of children.
This, in fact, drives my wife crazy.
Your wife is a saint, Chris.
I think we knew that, actually.
[laughs]
Uh, hmm.
And, uh, he's also--so he's listening to OctaThop composing a theme song for his new podcast on one laptop,
writing an article on the other and filtering spreadsheets, and drinking coffee.
I mean, if drinking coffee counts as multitasking, I am great at multitasking.
So, yes, top multitasker.
He said, "multitasking."
[grunts]
He also mentions that if we do an OctaThop live, which we are, in fact, doing, foreshadowing for later in the podcast,
we must include a live dancing section.
And I have to say--
Yes, and we categorically disagree.
You're very welcome to come to live podcasts, but you will be disappointed if that's your expectation.
Unless he's offering to do live dancing at the recording for us, in which case, you're on, we'll see you there.
[laughs]
Yeah.
And also wrote to us saying, "Oh, God, if you published this letter, take the serial killer comment out."
We will do, and don't worry.
And Mark Plummer wrote to us to say that he wasn't sure yesterday why he's only just got around to OctaThop 27,
probably because he's just too damn busy playing Arkham Horror, he imagines.
And he agrees with us.
So, thanks, Mark.
Glad you agreed with the things we said.
[music]
As you are listening to this listener, it is no more than one day from the start of Confusion, the 2021 EasterCon.
And we are excited, and we hope to see lots of you there.
So, Alison is running a fan-fund auction.
So, do you want to plug the fan-fund auction, Alison?
I do. The fan-fund auction will sell things for the fan-funds.
They are things that have been donated by people who support the fan-funds,
which hopefully includes lots of you.
And there's probably still time to donate things if you haven't quite.
So, if you want to donate anything, get in touch at guffeEurope@gmail.com
and we will put a slightly disguised version of that in the show notes,
but that's the guffe email address, and that is me.
We are going to be at 7 to 9 p.m. on Sunday, which is...
That's going to be like in the stupid hours of the morning, if you're in Australia or New Zealand.
Or Thailand.
If you're in New Zealand, it's getting on to be okay, actually, I think.
It's mid-afternoon if you're on the east coast of the United States
and late morning if you're on the west coast, and you would all be very welcome.
So, we have a kind of circular arrangement where you donate things,
and then you bid on other things, and in this way the fan-funds acquire money
and we would love for you all to come along and support it.
We're just working out the details of how we're going to do it with the convention
because we know how we do it in Zoom, but we don't quite know how we're going to do it on the East Coast platform.
But we will. It will be fine. We're going to have some unique things,
like some unique dice from James Shields, and we're definitely going to have one of Esther Schul's
and Dave Langford has donated some stuff, and we have many other interesting things
and do come along and bid.
And I will be bidding on the unique dice, so just get ready for a competition.
Anyone listening who thinks they sound cool?
Oh, I might go to James Shields and do it say, "Oh, we have something from Arkham Horror on one of these things
and they will be up for 200 quid from John Coxer."
I've already got enough Arkham Horror dice, Alison, because they sound official anyway, that's off topic.
But do you have an Arkham Horror dice that has Arkham Horror logos and also a coronavirus?
No, but I do have too many dice. I have over 50 six-sided dice, which are from various promotional sources.
So it could be argued I have enough.
No, okay, you're not being clear enough on the podcast, because I could have sworn I heard you say you had too many dice.
Yeah, I mean, I think, inarguably, I did downsize my dice recently. I got rid of all of the boring dice.
But there were some aspects in which I don't have enough dice.
I've only got two D7s, and it's like if you play a D7 based role playing game two is not going to be enough.
You need at least five. If you play a D7 based role-player game, then you have bigger problems than anything I can help with.
You're deep in the rabbit hole.
Couldn't you just use D8s and ignore the eight?
Steady on Liz.
If it comes up.
That is what we call in the tabletop gaming world, Quitter Talk.
Okay, one of the nice things about dice is that they don't take up very much space.
I mean, you have to have really a remarkable number of dice before your dice collection is anything like as much trouble as say your beable bear collection or your collection of antique helmets or your Weetabix collection.
What I like about this is that I'm going to need to write a jingle at some point for Octa-Thork gaming corner. Sorry, Mark.
The other thing that's going to be put up for auction at the Fanfond Auction is make the Octa-Thork cast say whatever you want as long as it's under a minute long and we get a veto on grounds of taste, eventiveness and legality.
So, yes, you better not play, say, piss motherfucker, cocksucker or tits.
I think tits is fine.
Well, those are the, yeah, okay, so if you aren't already familiar with George Carlin's seminal comedy routine, the seven words you can't tell on television, you should go and look at it.
But I mean, I think fundamentally those are the words you can't say on apple podcast except possibly tits.
It's just, it's, it's, it's, just, it's, just, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's, it's just going to be a big string of beeps basically.
But if you've ever wanted to make Alice and say that Windows is better than Mac OS or wanted to make me say, actually, I don't really like Arkham Horror all that much or make Liz say that Beaches are rubbish, then now you have the opportunity to do that.
And we will sound like we mean it.
We can be very committed.
And if you give us, if you give the fans an extra 50 quid on top of what you've bid, we will actually mean it.
I would change my mind for that, that minute long segment.
Only for the minute.
I'll change it right back again.
But for that minute, you'll know that I really believed it.
Method lying.
Um, this reminds me very much of Ian's Patreon.
I signed up to Ian's Patreon along with Andrew January and in return, Ian respected us for a month.
Um, right.
We will be doing a live podcast at confusion, which is at 10 o'clock in the morning on Easter Monday.
And which will include the winning one minute read.
Ah.
You don't just know that we will do it.
You will actually be able to hear us do it.
If we have to record it three or four times to avoid laughing, then you'll get to hear that.
Yes, yes you will.
Um, it's four p- four p.m. for our Thai co-hosts and listeners.
Um, it will be, uh, I would guess late afternoon, early evening for Australian New Zealand people.
And if you're in the States, uh, you're probably not going to come.
So apologies.
Chris Cosier, it's midnight.
You'll be fine.
You'll be absolutely fine.
No, it's not.
Two a.m.
You'll be absolutely fine.
Jerry, it'll be five a.m.
Just stay up a bit too late.
Yes.
Do that.
Okay.
And, uh, we, I think, are on for an hour.
Um, and that, if you can't attend, will be the episode that comes out after this one.
So don't worry.
You will hear it at some point.
All three of us have volunteered for EasterCon, Alison and I are volunteering on newsletter,
um, which will be called Happy Days and, um, has some fantastic artwork.
That's D-A-Z-D.
Yes, it's a sort of pun, you see.
And Liz is working on program ops because she knows about programs and ops.
Is that how program ops works, Liz?
Yeah, I don't really know how it's going to work yet because most of the things program ops does is generally hanging about in the green room, fixing problems as they rise and occasionally wandering around the corner looking for people or, you know, making last minute changes by wandering around looking for people or by carrying a radio in case there's any emergencies.
Um, and I guess most of this is going to be replaced by a Katie checking into a Gather Town channel somewhere.
Do they even have channels?
Anyway, so I don't know how it's going to work.
No, no, Gather Towns are space.
Yeah, if you do, we'll have like a space or something, but I haven't actually got into the details and this is partly because they're going to have to run a special session to teach me how to do it because I can't make any of the regular ones because they're in the evening UK time and I'm in bed.
So I am a pain. Yeah, I think that will be fun.
You need to keep an eye out for the newsletter, which we will distribute all over the Gather and all over the smeds for the convention.
This is the point where Liz says, "What a smed."
"What a smed, Alison."
"Smeds is short for social media feeds and I thought it was a terribly useful and funny word ever since I first heard it which was about five years ago, but it really hasn't caught on."
So, you know.
Yes. I heard it for the first time today, so there is that.
And, yeah, the newsletter will be great.
I wouldn't go that far.
It will be great.
The newsletter has a great team.
You know, I've recruited a great team by my standard method of rounding up all the people who normally help on the newsletter.
And it will have great art from Sue Mason, who is not coming to the convention, but is very good at art and has done us loads.
And it will have great layout from Flick, who is not coming to the convention, but is very good at doing newsletter layouts.
So, confusion have started to drip feed things about the program to their smeds.
So, they have announced a beer tasting and a cider tasting, and there's a panel about Chinese literature, and there's a show by Synthony, which sounds cool.
Sounds like a character from Steven Universe, but still sounds cool.
They've announced the Great Fanish Bake Off.
They've announced the Fan Fund auction, and they've announced the Dark Room is going to be coming to EastCon virtually.
So, it's all very exciting. We're starting to hear things about the stuff that's going to happen.
I've ordered my beer, which is from a brewery in the English town, Karen.
And which includes a beer called Crazy Days.
Yes.
Oh, and we should mention that Crazy Day is the one who told us we should do the one minute long read in the Fan Fund auction.
So, thank you very much for the suggestion.
Crazy Dave.
Crazy Days beer was also the inspiration for the Happy Days title of the newsletter.
Yeah, I'm a little bit sad.
There's so many cool things that as yet I'm going to have difficulty getting to, because someone's having really good, but then it's like I kind of calculate the time and it's like, "Oh, that'd be 1 a.m.
Am I really going to be awake enough to watch a program item at 1 a.m.?
Because the answer is no.
I know at least one person who is more out of type than you are who has switched their time zone this week so that they will be perky for all of EastCon."
That's all well and good, but I have a job. So, that is quite difficult.
You poor sod.
I have a job which involves going in and being physically present in places this week as well.
I know it's a novelty to many people at the moment, but yeah, so it's very difficult. I mean, I'm not really intending to shift at all just because trying to shift myself any significant distance just for a weekend and then back is a lot of work for me.
And I'm not very good at shifting my sleeping cycle.
You can take Tuesday off work though.
I could because actually Tuesday is a public holiday here.
So, I as well as the Oct though live and the fanfans auction, I'm on two panels, one on bad technology where I'm going to go along and tell the rest of the panel that their problem with bad technology is that they're not buying enough Apple products.
I'm going to go to that panel and I'm just going to hide, but it's going to be very funny. Oh dear.
I do have a, I do actually have one spectacular story about terrible Apple products which is going in my blog on the 31st of March. So, so I might manage to find some time for that.
And then the other panel I'm on is on ways to stay sane and focused in the apocalypse.
It's actually about lockdown past times, which I think I have done a great many of and due to not having a job that I need to go places for.
And so I think that should be a pretty good panel and I'm looking forward to it. And I think John is on 106 items.
So yes, I am on many program items.
I did initially turn one down and then they were like, but you'll be good at it. And I was like, okay.
So, I am on a panel called an even newer hope, the next generation of Star Wars, which I found confusing because I thought next generation was a Star Trek show, but clearly I'm wrong.
I'm on artificial intelligence, poor trails in SF compared to the real world, which I'm moderating, and which features Liz Williams, Charlie Stross and Trisha Sullivan.
I'm on Good Luck.
I'm on D&D through the ages and what lies ahead.
I'm on itch.io crowdfunding and the growth of indie games.
I'm on Beyond the Big Names, favorite little RPGs, and I'm on accessibility in gaming, Braille Dice to controller remapping.
So, yeah, should be good. Mostly games. The astute listener will have discerned.
It's open at your everything, John. That's a lot.
I'm good at talking about games, which I think is why I'm on so many games ones.
How many panels are you on in the end, John? Well, panel/items.
Seven.
Yep.
No.
People who are not professionally engaged in science fiction should probably not be on that much stuff.
Yeah, I'm on zero because I didn't volunteer to do any.
What I've put in here is that you could say at this point, "I'll be at the bar."
I don't even know if there'll be a bar. It's in gather.
I presume there'll be a bar somewhere in gather, but who knows?
I will be somewhere probably trying to see if I can stretch the boundaries of gather as far as they go.
I think on the subject of being on or not being on too many program items,
I think the problem is with Eastcons at the moment is that there are not enough people who can talk intelligently about games.
Oh, yeah. No, that might be true. But seriously, you keep talking about this, about all the privilege.
I should not be ending up in a position where white men who can talk about games end up being put on seven games panels.
All they should say, "We need John for the games panels. We will not put him on the Star Wars panel.
We will put somebody else, maybe a black woman or maybe just anyone else, onto a games panel because we have too many white men on panels."
Anyway.
But certainly, like, I'm on the AI panel because I'm moderating, and I did turn that down originally.
But I think part of the reason they've put me on that is basically because I can moderate, and I am technical enough to be able to do a good job,
but not knowledgeable enough to actually kind of have a big impact on the panel, which is kind of what you want from the moderator, I think.
I am quite looking forward to the Spanish Bake Off, and I do have an idea which I will attempt to bring to fruition,
but I've only got four days to do it, and I'm not sure I can actually buy all the things I need.
But if I can do it, it'll be cool. And if I don't, we'll just pretend I never said it, and I'll sit here eating, like, failed cupcakes in the privacy of my own house.
I think the Bake Off is a very good thing where they've given us a good example of something where they've given us a prior warning,
but I kind of looked at it and went, "Oh, they have not given me enough prior warning that I would have liked a month for that, please.
I'd have liked to have had a couple of weeks to really work up a good idea, a week to source the ingredients,
and then a week to have two or three goes at it." And that's not a thing that's happening.
Their person constructing the Gathertown environment for confusion is Alex Stora.
People who have been to convention art shows will probably have seen Alex's art.
I know I've seen his work at Novicon art shows in particular, but I assume he's also exhibited at previous WorldCon,
Easticons, and they are producing the Gathertown environment.
The announcement on the confusion Facebook seems to imply that there will be a musical component to the Gathertown environment.
And I have a little rant.
So this dropped me into a flat spit, because if you know anything about science fiction conventions and science fiction fans,
you'll know that part of the negotiation with the hotel is getting the hotel to turn off incidental music everywhere in the hotel space
that you can possibly get them to do that, and that part of your negotiation with the tech team is to say to the tech team,
"You must not play any incidental music, or if you do, you must play it very, very quietly and they will ignore that."
And in general, there is a major problem with accessibility for incidental music, because most fans hate it.
So I kind of went, I saw this announcement, I'm not sure they're not planning to put background music,
or indeed any sort of music, into Gather, because you might not want to add extra bells and whistles when people are already struggling with the computer load
that Gather is putting on their computers, and you might not want to add extra bells and whistles when people are clearly struggling with the cognitive load that Gather is putting on their brains.
So I'm a bit worried about it. I'm probably just being paranoid.
Yeah, I think it's hard to know until we get there, but from the little bit of fling about I did with Gathertown,
which I will say has made me more positive about it, because once I had a little bit of messing around with it,
I would say that drove my little avatar around and sat them chairs and had discussions, I feel it's a bit more promising.
But I think it could be that they have certain aspects of the Gather, which are certain areas where you go and there is art and music,
and it's more like a sort of interesting insulation to look at.
And then you come to the bar, which has no incidental music, and you chat to people.
And that would be totally fine, I think. Look at me being optimistic.
It's an accessibility issue. 25% of people aged over 50 have hearing loss.
If you have hearing loss, then having extraneous unnecessary sounds in your environment makes everything worse.
I do not have hearing loss, but I am basically the anti-criscasia in that if I am listening to a particular audio source,
I want to listen only to that audio source, and if you introduce another one, then it confuses my brain.
So basically I just want to chat to people, not have other music, but I am sure that the music will turn off if you enter an actual conversation with people,
or it will be in certain areas. I can't say it would be there all the time, because that's obviously just not going to work if you are trying to chat to people.
So, yeah, it's an access issue. They shouldn't do it. If they do do it, they should make it easy to turn off.
I may be being totally paranoid and they have no plans for us at all, and then I will look silly, which is fine, and I will be very happy.
They will not be in the musical in the newsletter room. Come hang out there.
I say this. You are going to have a newsletter room full of people now, Alice, and you realise that?
It's tragic.
Yeah, this is one of those things where I don't mind incidental music, but I do really mind people distracting me when I am working on the newsletter.
Okay, so the newsletter room is going to have a private space for just the person who has actually tried to do the hard work.
Yeah, that actually is quite a good feature of Gather, is you can set up the little isolation booth in Gather.
So the person can literally be sitting in the newsletter, doing the newsletter, and people can pop in and talk to them, but they can also have background conversations, and it won't disturb the actual newsletter editor.
That seems quite good.
I've been running some Gather practices and plays for my mates, and they've been pretty good.
What we're finding, I think, is probably that about 80% of people play around for about five minutes, and though this is cool, and then get into a conversation with somebody and chat for a bit, and go, "Oh, that works."
And then the other 10 or 20% find it a bit harder to get to grips with, and some of those people just hate it in the way that some people hate Zoom.
Some people hate this, discord. Some people hate everything. So there is no internet.
Some people probably hate hotels while we're thinking about it.
There is nothing that is going to work for everyone. Gather's pretty solid.
Yeah, there are hotels that I think are good at Eastacorn hotels that many people think are not great Eastacorn hotels, and quite often for the same reasons, I think.
I like hotels where there's lots of little nooks and crannies and corners where you can go and have chats and hang out, but for some people those are the worst, because then they don't feel as comfortable in places where they can't get a feel for how the hotel is laid out, and they don't know what talk was around corners and things like that.
So yeah, you really can't have something that pleases everyone, and I think that's as true for internet things as it is for real world hotels.
I think the difference here is that obviously the actual hotel is a thing you bid on, usually two years in advance.
But that's pandemics for you.
Future Easter Kams. So, Eastacorn in 2022 is being led by Phil Dyson, and we don't have much information about it at the moment, but presumably they will be bidding at the bid session on, I'm assuming, Easter Sunday.
I'm assuming that's because they've got a big launch planned, and it's going to be amazing.
Yes, so I don't know, as I said, not much has kind of leaked out of that bid, so we will be excitedly looking forward to what they say.
One of the things I am interested to see what they say is what they say about their plans for virtualisation in the event that this time next year, there has been a new variant that does not easily react to the vaccine.
And we are all still in lockdown. I am wondering what their plans will be around that, and if they don't have any, I'll be voting against.
So, Phil, if you're listening.
Your array of sunshine, John.
They may or may not have some, but they'll have an answer to that question, because this is something I've talked to Phil about on numerous occasions over the years.
If I was answering that question now, I would say, that's a really good question. Obviously we're planning for the possibility.
What we're going to do is reflect on the experience of people this weekend and other conventions, and then put together a plan for a virtual convention based on those experiences.
Because they can't have a plan to say, "Yeah, we're going to use gather, it's awesome."
Or a plan to say, "We're not going to use gather, it's pants."
You know, so...
I mean, no, for enough.
I just want to know that they've thought about it. I don't necessarily need to know what their thoughts were.
And then there is no bid for 2023 as far as we are aware, and if you are aware of a bid for 2023, please do let us know we would be very interested to hear.
Yeah, we'll ask this again on Sunday morning.
We will ask this again on Sunday morning.
I'm much more relaxed than I'd normally be about there not being a bid for 2023 because I think this might be a very good year to plan for one year bidding.
I know that Phil has had some issues getting a hotel for 2022 because hotels are not in a good place to have these sorts of conversations at the moment.
And it may be easier to just kind of wait and see and then design a plan for 2023 based on what the world looks like in about six or eight months time.
Yeah. I mean, in one year, there have been many good one year East cons, so I'm not too worried if that is what ends up happening.
However, is anything happening in 2024, John?
Yes, so Farah Mendelssohn and Pat McMurry are co-chairing a bid for East con 2024. So far.
I think you meant we can exclusively announce.
Sorry.
Dun dun dun dun dun.
Yes, we can exclusively reveal that Farah Mendelssohn and Pat McMurry are bidding for 2024 to hold an Easter con.
This is partly because the Easter in 2024 doesn't overlap with Passover.
So Farah is very excited about that.
And obviously that will also be a UK World con year.
So they're kind of putting their stake in the ground now to kind of say, if you're not working on World con, why not come and work on the Easter con?
The Convention Committee will be announced in more detail at confusion, but suffice it to say that I am the head of communications for that bid
because I got all excited and then I said yes a lot of times and Alison and Liz promised to show me how to say no to things in the future.
We have a series of remedial training exercises planned.
But yeah, no, I'm excited.
As listeners know, I have thoughts about Easter con communications. And so this is kind of an opportunity for me to put those thoughts and opinions into action.
So I will be overseeing social media and publications under my communications banner and trying to make sure there's a little bit more joined up thinking between those two aspects of the Convention than might have been traditional in the past.
I think you should actually be the Deputy Head of Communications because I've always seen you as more of a Sam Seaborn type than a Toby Ziegler.
I think that was a reference.
It was a reference and some of our audience will get it.
It's a Westring reference, right?
Yes.
I was very flattering. I said I called you Rob Lowe. I mean, that's quite a flattering one John. You can leave that one in.
Yeah, thank you. Thank you. Thank you. That is literally the best thing you've ever said about me.
I got that reference too.
What reference?
But yeah, no, so I'm excited. I mean, basically to very quickly,
we see my opinions about communications. It is that very often publications are seen as the act of making PDF or printed artifacts to communicate information.
And then your website and social media team are communicating exactly the same information, but with no proper crossover with the publications that you're putting out.
And this is something that we were kind of beginning to struggle with a little bit of long gone three even because the role of disseminating information was kind of split between publications and promotions.
And that was kind of not good for being able to take a unified approach to getting messages out.
And so one of the things I wanted to do for a while is try and make those a little bit more joined up.
And that is what I'm going to be doing for EasterCon in 2024.
So if anyone's interested in being the head of social media, do let me know.
I like doing social media for conventions.
There's basically 95% of the work happens in the last week before the convention.
Social media for an EasterCon is two different jobs because there is a job that you do all the way along.
And then there's a kind of job you do in the last week before the convention and during the convention where you are reacting to things that people are doing.
Things that people are saying to you and about you.
But before that, although people do say things on social media to you and about you, mostly your job is just to channel those to other people at the convention who need to know about them.
And it's very easy for an EasterCon sized convention.
It's a very easy relaxed job that takes about five minutes a day when you're on social media anyway.
But then the last month is kind of like a velociraptor.
So you need a big team and all of that stuff.
But that means that in terms of a head of social media, you probably just need a social media person and they might not be the same person that you have running that reactive team on the day because that's a management.
That's possibly true.
And I think the role of social media is twofold and I think you've kind of outlined that well in that it is communicating in both directions, communicating things from the EasterCon to the membership.
And communicating things in the reverse direction.
But also communicating and trying to reach out beyond the current membership to the rest of social media who might be interested.
So you've kind of got that almost like a third component.
And I think the reason I want to point someone sooner rather than later is because I'm also actually not great at social media.
I understand in sort of academic sense how it works, but I'm not good at that kind of retweeting people on Twitter sort of engagement.
So I am keen to have someone on board who can address that sort of lack of expertise on the team.
Other thing about social media is that you find that a lot of your job is answering queries of the form.
I have written in the approved manner to the approved part of the convention and I have heard nothing back what is going on.
And if your convention is well formed and is running happily, most of the time that won't happen at all.
And when it does happen, all you need to do is kind of send little messages saying, "Have you had something got into spam?
Have you just forgotten to go back to this person? Can you sort it out so that we aren't getting them whining on Twitter?"
And when conventions are not being very well run, you get a lot more of that sort of thing.
So it's kind of a very good early warning.
This is why the actual head of social media is probably ought to be on the committee because it's kind of a feelers for the chair about what bits of their convention structure are working properly because people are writing to them and not getting any replies.
Yeah, so there's that too.
It's quite useful as a spy for the chair. Not that the chair needs spies, but the chair totally needs spies.
It's almost like for those people listening who have played a lot of Warhammer 40,000, the social media team is almost like the commissar of the convention.
Doctor thought, gaming corner.
Hog will get that joke and he will think it's funny. And that is why it's in the podcast.
The podcast is basically a series of increasingly misjokes aimed at a very small number of listeners.
It's almost like a fan scene.
It is almost like a fan scene.
I do want to talk about the Seder.
I'm probably going to write about this for a fan scene, but Julian Polak said about a month ago, "Oh, I'm a bit sad because my Seder plans have fallen through."
And those of us who remember Rec Arts SF fandom, which was a Usenet group,
Usenet was a thing that we used to have on the internet when the internet was a series of tubes, John.
I was on NewsNet.
Yeah, I was on Altfhand Doctor's Adams and Altfhand Star Wars Jar Jar Binks Die Die Die.
Yeah, okay. I guess she's fine.
So Rec Arts SF fandom was kind of like an alt group that accidentally fell into the Rec groups for reasons that are complicated.
And they used to talk about Jewish minutiae a lot, and I always vaguely wanted to go to a Passover Seder,
but I never really had the opportunity.
And Julian said, "Oh, I don't know my plans for the Seder have fallen through."
So we said, "Well, can we do it online?"
And I just wanted to mention it because one of the things that has been helping me stay sane this year is spotting opportunities for things that you could never possibly do in other years,
like have a Zoom Seder on multiple different continents with people coming together from all sorts of different Jewish traditions,
and also no Jewish traditions whatsoever.
And while breaking bread together, and it was very interesting and good fun,
and it also gave me the rare opportunity to drink four glasses of wine before noon,
which is not something that I normally do, because we were on Canberra time experiencing an Australian Seder,
which involved singing one extremely important Jewish religious blessing to the tune of "Waltzing Matilda",
which was amusing, and another much less serious Jewish song to the tune of Clementine,
which was much more the normal sort of thing.
And it was fun and we had lots of good people, and it was mostly Spanish, but not entirely Spanish.
And it seemed like exactly what fandom ought to do.
And I was not the only person who was primarily there because we remember all the talks about Judaism in records as a fandom 25 years ago or more.
That's all I really want to say about it. I thought I was short enough, really.
And also weird food things, very weird food things, like a lamb bone.
Yes, yeah, and chopped liver.
And chopped liver, which is delicious.
I kind of like chopped liver has a terrible reputation, but as in fact, it's like very nice pate that you've made yourself from fresh liver and it's delicious.
Do you like pate?
Pate is great. So is it better or worse than Tereen?
Do you mean tarene?
It's kind of a trip to read because it's quite a course, pate.
Okay, cool. I think you mean pate.
Pate.
Yeah, I got in trouble for considering tarene to be a solid and trying to take it on an aeroplane,
and then we had to have a debate about whether my tarene was in fact solid or a liquid.
Oh, God.
Over the liquid limit. And it hadn't occurred to me that actually it might be, you know, fine enough
to be non-liquid. And I didn't really want to open it and have to like pull it out to demonstrate it was quite solid, but I, we ended up agreeing that it was in fact quite a, you know, course, Tereen, and I could be allowed to take it back on the plane with me.
I have never concealed explosives in pate, but one of the other things that you do for the cedar is a roasted egg and shaders egg exploded. So, so there's that.
The roasted egg sounded absolutely gross.
It is absolutely horrible. And although in some traditions, it's eaten as part of the service in Gillian's tradition. It just sits on the table like the bone and is just ritual.
And, and then she does eat at the very start of the, of the feast part of the cedar.
She eats hard boiled eggs dipped in saltwater, but they're not the hard boiled eggs that was roasted. It's a different hard boiled egg, which, and a hard boiled egg dipped in saltwater is delicious.
As is cold boiled potato dipped in saltwater, I had no idea. Both of those things are very tasty.
I'm a bit jealous, but you did do it at six in the morning UK time and I did not get up. I was in bed.
So, so Lillian Edwards is, is Jewish by heritage, I think not my practice generally. And I did think, oh, I should tell Lillian about the cedar because she might not know about it.
And then I thought, oh Lillian, six thirty in the morning. That's not ever going to happen is it. So, and indeed it didn't.
On the subject of getting up early, what are your plans for East Con Breakfast? This is an important issue.
I mean, are you asking me? Both of you. Like, like East Con Breakfast.
I would love to have breakfast with you. I don't know whether there'll be breakfast programme items, because a lot of conventions have had sort of general communal breakfasty things and it's been very good.
It's kind of set you up for the day and I think, oh yes, I'm having breakfast.
Yeah.
Yeah, I'm for breakfast. I mean, it will be mid afternoon for me. So, I probably won't actually eat breakfast, but I can have an extra coffee.
Hey, coffee's good. Yes, we have Tim's Beast Row has reopened. That's good. But our favourite cafe will still be shut at Easter.
So, there's no, there's nowhere we know that we like that's open on the Sunday. So on the Sunday we might have to forage for ourselves, which is, you know, clearly a travesty.
I've been going through the, my diary for the weekend and thinking about what I normally do at the Easter Con and how I'm going to replicate that because I would not normally do any cooking over Easter weekend and I'm not intending to do any cooking next weekend.
But I realised that one of the things that happens at Easter Con is about one in the morning I am often found in the bar and along with beer, which we have saw.
I, there are often people there and I'm thinking of Michael Abbott and Malcolm Hutchison who sidle up to you at one o'clock in the morning and bar and say, would you like some chocolate?
So I am going to order the sort of chocolate that Michael might have, which is kind of the kind of dairy milk with bits in it type and the sort of chocolate that Malcolm might have, which is single varietal dark chocolate with Peruvian raspberries, that sort of thing.
And, and have both of those sorts of chocolate available. So if I meet those people in the bar or, or if you think, oh, I would really like a bit of chocolate now, I can go and get it.
And, and also I realised that about an hour later, like about two or two thirty is about the rat time that Tobe's comes around snogging people and I don't know what I'm supposed to do about that.
Tobe's is lovely and he's a good kisser, but like, but yeah, I'm trying to work out ways in which you could replicate that experience in the comfort of your own home.
Don't have any good ones.
Yeah, buy some Calvados, that'll work.
So maybe I need some Calvados actually, because he does also.
And pistachio nuts.
Pistachio nuts. The most romantic breakfast I've ever had was the morning at East Taconne in 2008, where I woke up and Tobe looked at me and said, "With his breakfast" and then gave me a coffee spiked with Calvados and four pistachio nuts.
And there were only seven pistachio nuts, so that was more than half of his pistachio nuts. And also I had been to breakfast and then gone back to sleep.
With Tobe's, apparently.
Yeah, well I used to share a room with Tobe's, because we could mate.
Um, now I share a room with my wife, because we're also good mates.
Yeah, but has she ever brought you coffee spiked with tap Calvados and four pistachio nuts? That's all I want to know.
No, no she hasn't.
But she did make me pancakes with chocolate chips in this morning.
Banya if you're listening to this.
Are we sure we want to blur the lines between Tobe's and this Banya in Chod's head?
I mean, what do you mean, I don't understand?
*laughs*
Um, made out with both of them, had breakfast with both of them. Basically the same person is.
Not going there, not going there.
Was there anything else we were going to say in the podcast? I'm really looking forward to East Taconne.
I am so excited for East Taconne. I am going to have such a good time at East Taconne. I am going to get so pissed at East Taconne.
I'm going to be wankered.
That's pissed in the UK sense of drinking too much beer, not pissed in the US sense of...
Angry.
Of angry because I've given up anger as you know readers.
I am really excited. I'm hoping there will be loads and loads of cool people there and lots of fun interactions will happen.
And we've also, we should mention as well, that there is a first Thursday pub meeting the night before East Taconne.
So we don't know whether East Taconne is going to have anything on the Thursday night kind of officially.
Because obviously...
That's tonight, Pop Pickers.
Yes. So if you are listening to this before 10pm British time, which is UTC+1 at the moment, then do come to the first Thursday.
And you can get to the Facebook group through a link in the show notes.
Yeah, you can. It's still for British fans and London, London and... Yeah.
There's a lot of people who might be at the first Thursday the week before an Easter con, maybe.
Yes. It's very much a meeting for the sort of people who might come to the London meeting on the first Thursday.
Which is probably most of you if you were in London the night before the Easter conne and the Easter conne was also in London, for example.
Yes. If you're coming to East Taconne, then definitely feel free to drop in to the first Thursday.
And if you're not coming to East Taconne, but that's because you're grumpy rather than because you don't go to East Taconne's then also come and join the first Thursday.
Or if you'd quite like a drink or if you like Thursdays, you know.
I'm very bad at being exclusive.
Yeah. So this is another thing about age has withered me.
There is an issue that Mini-Con had where they woke up one morning and they had 3,500 people coming to their convention.
And they were like, but we're all volunteers who are we organizing this for?
And of course we are, in fact.
And it's all very well for me to go.
I am very happy for all my mates and all the listeners of my podcast to come to the first Thursday, which as it happens I organize.
But in fact, I think because we drew that demarcation line around it that said it's for fans who might come to the first London fans.
If you're in or near London, it's definitely for you.
And fans who come to the first Thursday, who include some fans from a further field like Cambridge and Reading in Brighton.
And fans who would definitely come to the first Thursday if they were around.
But it's not in fact a meeting for every fan in the world because of the long term accretion overheads of that.
I know that's really tedious, but that's kind of, and I wanted to draw a box around it that wasn't just,
it's for me and my mates. I wanted to draw a box around it that included a lot of my mates,
but was also actually saying, no, this is a geographically constructed thing.
You know, if you don't have any friends who are London fans, but you obviously do have friends who are London fans who are listening to this podcast, but you know.
Because we're your friends.
But if it got huge, it would be less fun than it is just not being huge.
That's all.
That was the OctaThought Podcast, and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me, and it's goodbye from me.
So I came up with a poem.
You came up with a poem?
Yeah.
Alright, you can do the poem for us.
Hang on.
I'm going to read the poem.
I might need to write it down before I read it out in case it doesn't scan.
Oh, John has written a poem live on OctaThought.
I have my poem.
[clears throat]
Liz has a job. She can't come to the con.
It makes her sob. The time zones are wrong.
[clears throat]
I don't know. We need like, sad violin music there.
A poem.
No, I think we need that.
Wob wob wob. No, he's out there.
That was the one.
But in fact, we need just...
Now we know that Alison can just hum the theme music instead of having to put an actual song in.
Expect all future episodes of OctaThought to have entirely Alison-produced sounds.
Do not do this.
[laughs]
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod at Ncompetech.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 3.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.