Anyway, this bit is all not for podcast. You should have pushed it not for podcast button.
Oh yeah, I should have done. I forgot.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 73rd episode of Oxford or podcast for science fiction
and science fiction fandom. This episode is coming to you on the 22nd of December 2022.
I'm John Coxon. I'm Alice Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
And I hadn't quite put it together until I said those words out loud, but this is the Christmas
episode. Ho ho ho. Merry Christmas. Hey. Keep up some like dingle bells and shit.
I hope said Doctor Thought brings you everything you desire for a podcast. One of those.
Right then we had letters of comment. So let's start with Raj writing in about episode 71.
Part of the problem we have been recording listeners, a peek behind the curtain.
We have been recording about a week early for a few weeks now because of various scheduling
trivialities, which two boys go into. But this does mean our locks. There's more overlap than
normal. So Raj, thank you for reading it. Writing in about episode 71. Raj says that
they were from his graphs. I have made the graphs. I put them in discord. I forgot to put them on
the alt to the twitter, but they do exist. So that is progress in 72. I again mentioned graphs and
again haven't done them, but this time they will be in the show notes because now they do exist.
So that is concrete progress. He says he liked the idea of best publisher Hugo until Liz pointed
out how limited the winners have been in the Lucas Awards. I still think it might be worth a go
and says he loved Alison's episode art, which was great episode art. Thank you. Nobody else has
mentioned it this time. Chris did love your episode art and he used it to prove that you were wrong.
I say prove very lightly. We'll go into that later. Oh, I have like a whole rant about how it turns
out that if you're going to set a piece of a word with some negative space in the o's,
then octothorpe is a much better word for it than Andor because it makes the whole thing look
more balanced because there are three o's and although it's still got the really weird
kerning thing going on, it's kind of because there's a tracking issue with the Andor logo.
It's at the end of the word rather than at the beginning of the word. So it doesn't look so naff.
Is the tracking issue that the Andor logo has gone into hyperspace and therefore you have to
employ active tracking? But I have finished Andor now, but I was told I couldn't talk about it
all this week. So I'm just going to slip bits of it in everywhere.
I just Oh, Andor so good everyone. Go and watch it. It's really good.
Except that one of the things that's really good about it is got this fantastic 70s aesthetic
except the logo, which has absolutely is clearly not a 70s piece of graphic design.
It's I mean, it's very annoying. Anyway, where were we? Raj also said that he would vote for
cleverly for best letter hack, but only if she starts writing poems again. We have had a lack
of poems this year. We should we should get on that next year. Listeners, please write more poems.
Seriously, if you get a Christmas poem to us, and that's a couple of days, we might record it
and stick it out in the episode where otherwise going to miss. Yes. So we won't be recording a full
episode over the Christmas period. So at the moment, our first episode in January stands
empty of content. If you'd like to help rectify that, please send in your readings of a visit by
St Octothorp and I will combine them together and you can you can hear your voice on the pod.
Not reading of it. Your interpretation of it. Write us a verse for a visit from St Octothorp.
Don't all make it the first verse or the last one or or it won't work. I don't know. It sounds
like kind of intriguing Lovecraftian hellscape. Just repeated. Intriguing Lovecraftian hellscape,
the podcast. I mean, your problem is that the listeners have stopped writing as poetry.
And so I think no one's going to write us any poetry here. And so it will be a dud.
Liz, I hereby on the podcast bet you the princely sum of one point of beer that people will write in.
Perian Lurie wrote to us to say that the Washington Science Fiction Association,
which she says do not confuse with Wussfuss, which is of course the World Science Fiction Society,
or presumably Boa-wa, which is the Boston and Washington area. Baltimore. Boa-wa-wa.
Baltimore and Washington area. Will, what do the world was, stand for?
People's. Look, if you're going to make this joke, you should have done the research for your
joke out of time. It is the Baltimore Washington Area World Con Association Incorporated.
And as we all know, you pronounce it boa-wa-wa-wa. It's not that either. The Washington
Science Fiction Association gives an award for Best Story published by a Small Press every year.
So that's quite good. I approve. And crucially, she says that they give an award to the editor of
the, sorry as well, which is why it was relevant to our discussion of editors and so on.
Yes. And that is, that is a good idea. It's good to hear that that happens at other Science Fiction
Awards. And I think there is no reason that that could not happen in the Hugo's. And actually,
I'm going to go, I'm going to discuss my graphs because they've unexpectedly become relevant.
So I drew some bar charts of the, of the distribution of the number of nominations in each category.
And I would say they're broadly speaking three ways you can, you can kind of group these
categories. So there's, there's one category which has best novel, best short story, better,
best dramatic presentation in both forms. And those are ones where you get significantly more
people nominating five than you do nominating one. And I think that basically says there's an
awful lot of novels and short stories and best dramatic presentations of which people are aware.
And so lots of people nominate lots of them. And that is good. And then there's ones where the number
of people that nominate five is very close to the number of people nominating one. So that's like
novella, novelette, professional artist, and semi-prozine. And those are ones where like clearly there's
slightly fewer options. But if you're tuned in, then there are as many people who know one as no
five. And I think that basically says that those are quite vibrant categories of quite a lot going on.
I think in the case of semi-prozine, it probably means that the semi-prozine category is not adequately
reflecting the breadth of the semi-prozines in the field, perhaps. And then you get categories where
the number of people who know one is way higher than the number of people who know more than one.
And these are all the fan categories and both of the editor categories. And also best graphics
story, best series and best related work. And I'm not sure I would have grouped series graphic
story and related work in this category, although having now seen the data, it makes a lot of sense.
But yeah, basically, I think this is saying that people really don't know the field in terms of
editor or in terms of the fan works. In the fan works, it's a bit to be expected because the
fan works were obviously less high profile than the pro works and for longtime listeners. You will
know that fanzine editors have not always enthusiastically embraced the Hugo's fan awards. But in terms of
editor, I think this is really pointing out that these categories are not particularly healthy ones,
even at the nomination stage. And I do think that is further evidence that an alternative
tag would be good because editing is a hugely important part of the genre. And we should properly
recognise it. And it doesn't look to me like the Hugo's do a good job of that. And this and this
banks that up, I think, I think is also probably an argument against best series. But that makes me
sad because I like best series. So I'm conflicted. It'll be interesting to see best game. Thank you
for doing the graphs. That was cool. Yeah, no, they're good. It's it's amazing how visualising
data can let you draw conclusions that just tables a day don't. He said with his I do graphs for a
living how? Hooray for whoever invented the graph. Listeners, write in and tell us who invented the
graph. I don't know but I do know who invented the pie chart because it's it's one of these cool
things. It's Mr. Pie. I think everyone knows who invented the pie chart right or who popularised
the pie chart. Mr. Pie. Florence Nightingale who used it to get money out of the government because
the notion that Florence Nightingale was a nurse and not a bad ass statistical expert
and and cast that administrator who's data a lot to affect medical improvements is is well,
you know, that's one of the things nurses do. But it's not the thing that nurses are traditionally
able to do. So she's a nurse of the bad ass administrator and she is a honorary fellow of the
Royal Statistics Society or something like that for that purpose or past precedent or whatever
it is they do. I should invent the pie chart. No, it's I'm sorry I misgendered her as Mr. Pie.
My ex wrote in with some pedantry and I can't find his lock now but it was basically,
oh no, you're going to have a canner's gonna have a high consulate because it's a Commonwealth
country rather than a rather than a embassy and that is of course correct but dull so you know.
And for those who don't know, Alison's ex is Mike Scott. Thank you very much for it again Mike.
Christopher J Garcia wrote in basically saying locus is a hugely important part of SF and he says
he hopes they meet their goal. And in the discussion we had last episode was that we all hope locus
will be here in 10 years in a sustainable form. I think the discussion we had last episode was
around whether or not we think they're going about that in a way we think we'll reach that goal.
And I think we're all a little bit skeptical but if they pull it off great and we are all
rooting for them to still be here in a decade please because they are an important part of the
genre and it is nice to have some of these old institutions knocking about. But yes thank you
very much for hanging Chris. Chris did also mention the Andor logo but we mentioned that earlier.
But basically he says that it's very clever and so Alison is wrong.
Chris also wrote at length about his low relationship with locus on locus's website which we will put
in the show notes for you. Complete with a picture of Chris which I don't know how that picture of
Chris's but you look very young Chris so let us know when that picture was taken. I have a picture
taken of Chris roughly a decade ago where we met up for high jinks in San Francisco and he was
wearing a t-shirt that said earth first will strip mine the other planets later and he looked very
young in that photo. The last 10 years have distinguished him. I think maybe having children
makes you age. Alison sort of grinned so I think I might be on something there but we'll see.
Yeah no no I had children and I turned around and it was 20 years later and I was 51. How did that
happen? He also asked a question which is query would John Paul be eligible for best John?
And I've got a potentially controversial opinion here which is if John Paul had a space in it yes
but it doesn't so no. Yeah because you asked last week about Jonathan's and I was like definitely
not. I would I would be anti-Johnathan inclusion mostly because people insist on call it be Jonathan
which is not my name. I did it once I did it once. Oh no I don't mind people doing it once it's when
people do it repeatedly. I did it once and yes I'd kind of because I'd go through people like oh
hello Liz John Marianne Steven Oh Caroline because as previously measured I've been in my 50s now
it's what we do. I go upstairs and forget what I came up for. See I've been doing that since I
was 18 so I'm a bit worried that when I get to my 50s I'm going to be a hot mess. Emphod is on the
hot John. Hey we have a late entry from Phil. He says the space shuttle enterprise was a need
named after Star Trek ship but it wasn't NASA's first choice it was going to be called constitution
but a high profile campaign by Star Trek fans persuaded them to go with enterprise instead.
Rodhamry named the Star Trek enterprise after the USS Enterprise which was the first nuclear
powered aircraft carrier and Gene Rodhamry was apparently fascinated with it so thank you very
much to Phil for writing in that was good context. And when you say Phil that's Phil Dyson. Phil Dyson
who was named after the vacuum cleaner or the Dyson sphere one of those.
Yep.
So we're going to segue seamlessly into talking about fan funds and we're going to do that because
Raj mentions at the end of his lovely lock that the European fan fund has launched and we have
not yet talked about it on the pod and also there is a TAF race so we're going to talk about those
things listeners. Great congratulations to machine crack for getting together the European fan fund
which he's been talking about for a little while but it's happening now and you if you're a European
fan you can apply to the fund for a trip to next year's Eurocon which is we con.
Yep it's in Sweden unlike the smothcon and we'll get to that later it's called conflict.
For shadowing.
Called conflict being held in up south of Sweden 8th to the 11th of June 2023.
I think this is a great idea I think it will raise the profile of Eurocons I think it will
improve harmony across European fans we love our European friends and our European listeners
do we have the European listeners anyway.
No yeah no I think it is good.
My only thought is with it being a European fan fund I wonder if there could be some kind of
potential for trying to get the fan fund winners to travel by train rather than flying
because one of my sort of worries about you know one of the things about fan funds is we do
essentially pay for someone to fly quite a long distance and I wonder if we could say well if
you're taking you know a longest European fanist trip maybe you could be encouraged to do it overland
might be nice.
Beginning this is being put together on a bit of a shoestring so it's not paying for an extended
trip in the way that the other fan funds do and it may be that going by train is outside
the funds budget but I think that's something definitely something they should think about
working towards because if they were doing a more extended trip doing that more extended trip by
train would be awesome.
Yeah I mean definitely like once the fund is more well established I think this is something
that could be really good because you could buy like an inter-rail pass or something and like
there are options there which are quite cool.
I will say that if you are a Brit and you run for this and you win I believe it will take you
roughly one day to get from London to upsella by train so I won't judge you harshly if you choose
to avoid that.
I think it probably works a lot better when the eurocon is like in Brussels than it does when
it's in upsella which is I mean you go to Copenhagen and then you go to Stockholm and then you keep
going it's a long way.
I know it's a long way because I have friends who work there because it's good to study the
Aurora there and now I'm wondering whether I can go to the eurocon and stay with my friend Dave so
intriguing.
This is a great idea this is something that the Canadians and the Antipardians already have.
There is for fans which is the Australian New Zealand Fund Fund which sends people
from Australia and New Zealand to Australia and New Zealand and then there is the Canadian
Unity Fund Fund which sends people to Canadian conventions.
These are very good things.
I don't think there's a US one please write in if I am wrong listeners and it is high time there
was a European one.
I'm very glad to see this has happened.
An important thing is that there is a long held wisdom that you don't run for one of the big three
if you've already won one of the big three so you don't run for Duff or Taff if you've already won
them but the smaller ones don't follow that rule so there's no reason that like old Taff winners
and Duff winners can get involved.
So like Christina Lake for instance might be a really good EFF candidate or other people of that
ilk.
Probably not if you're the current guff.
A trip by train can start with seven hours from Cornwall to London.
Well I was thinking when John said it would take you a day to get a top sauna I'm like well how long
about it is just getting to the edge of the UK probably like 80%.
Oh no I was doing it from London from Newcastle it's a day in seven hours
and it's the seven hours which is going down to London.
Or you could just take an overnight ferry somewhere which is awesome.
Yes no that is true.
I mean yeah because I could take the ferry from Shields to Amsterdam and then presumably I could
take the train from Amsterdam but you've still got to go you've still got to go kind of up
Denmark and then across the Peninsula and then up Sweden.
I think you can take an overnight ferry to Norway and then another ferry from Norway to Sweden.
Oh maybe. I mean you may not be able to now because overnight ferries were better in the past.
As with so many things.
Pretty sure you can I mean you can go to Amsterdam but I'm not sure you can go anywhere other than
Amsterdam from Newcastle.
I had another thing to ask about the European Fan Fund.
I had two things.
One is that presumably this is not directional any European fan can apply to go to any
you know Eurocon.
Yeah I don't think there's any eligibility around you need to be a certain distance away
from the Eurocon but I think you know if you're a Swedish fan applying to go to
conflict then you probably feel that that might be a little bit rum.
Yeah but we probably do have to it'll be interesting to see how it goes like in the first few years
because depending on how well it gets promoted in different regions you could end up like is there
a regionality voting thing like there is for Tath like you know how on Tath you have to win
kind of you know both sides or you know get a certain number of votes on both sides just because
there is a potential of this be dominated by countries with more fans right so you always end
up with say UK fan traveling to a convention so it'll be interesting to see like how it works
with that voting and whether we do get kind of fans more of a Europe going to other places all
over Europe whether it sort of ends up being a I don't know that's kind of definitely how it will
be but I will be interested to see how it gets promoted.
So the rules are on Marching's website and they were posted in 2019 so we have had time there has
been a consultation phase the plans have been on display in our local Marching's website for
three years and it's far too late so I'm making a fuss about it now but I have the rules so you
have to live in a European country you have to be going to Europe on which is in a country other
than your country you have to be active in fandom for at least two years which I think is more
stringent than Tath I don't think Tath has any rule about that. The previous two races have to
have been won by candidates from different countries from the one that you are in if there will be
no other candidates this rule may be omitted they will find three nominators and at least one
has to be from their country and at least one has to be from a different country that answers
some of our questions. Boccin you're great you're a brick well done. Yes turns out if I had just
read the rules all this would have been explained but instead I just pontificate about it isn't that
always the way. Quite a lot of time yeah. So the nominations are open until the end of January and
voting stops just after Eastercon as is right and proper so yes if you are interested in running
then go for it I think I will be brilliant. Liz you're gonna go move back to Europe and then go to
a European? It would be quite a lot of effort to go in order to get a trip to a European I feel.
Fair enough. Might not be able to live in a European country again. That is fair. Well it was actually
I had one extra thing which is is this gonna like when we have fanfon options is now the European
fanfon going to be one of the things which gets money from the fanfon options? I would hope so.
100% I think it is a fantastic idea and maybe this is pro-kill building the community of European
fans is probably I think there is a much stronger community of English speaking fans across the
Atlantic and across the Pacific than there is links between different European frontoms and so
this is actually the one of the fanfons I think is going to be doing the best work for the next
few years because I love Taff and I love Guff and I love Duff. I think in terms of cultural exchange
the culture is relatively accessible in those races whereas in this one I think going to like a
Swedish convention would feel much scarier to me. I mean I guess it's not surprising that you're
less likely to go to conventions in countries that don't speak English if you speak English. I think
that's probably entirely understandable impulse but I do think more things to encourage that kind
of cross-linking might be good. Many European conventions have an English track. We should we
should do more to publicize it conventions in Europe which we can do as a as a leading community
podcast European Community podcast. Yes Europeans right in. Taff can we say such a bit Taff? Yes Taff
Alison has been machinating behind the scenes again and her machinations have borne fruit!
I haven't really at Novicon Sandra Bond said she was thinking of running and I said yes do it.
That's it really and then and then Sandra Bond is running for Taff and I am one of the
nominators and we have two candidates and the other is Miklai Koveleski who ran last time but
was beaten by fear along with lots of other people and so it's a great race both these are good
candidates and I am one of Sandra's nominators so I'm going to tell you that she's a fantastic
Taff candidate and you should vote for her. She's incredibly interesting and funny and she has done
a whole lot for Fandam and she's also a very good author and poet and if you're listening to this
Sandra please feel free to write it with a Christmas poem for Octa Thorpe. No two good candidates
one good race coming right up I'll put a link in the show notes. I have something to say about
Guff very quickly oh good which is that I'm going to Australia next year if you're in Australia and
have a spare bed please get in touch on New Zealand I am going to fly out almost immediately
after the coronation which is I think the coronation is six of me I'm probably going to fly on the
night and I'm going to return on about the 15th or 73th or 18th of June something like that depending
on exact timings and what flights are and something like that so a bit over a month and I'm intended
to go to at least Perth Adelaide Melbourne Sydney and Wellington and I may go to extra places well
if you're in one of those extra places and you have a spare bed so get in touch really I just
want to meet Australian New Zealand fans that's all I'm doing so yeah really looking forward to it
and in order to support that I'm going to have a pre-trip report which will be available at Easter
you heard it here first which conventions are you going to go to don't know if there's going to be
a convention going to do the trip anyway because it's time we need to run a northbound race
for 2024 so I need to travel next year so Australian fans get planning your conventions
come on I have been poking but it's really I mean the the New Zealand that cons going to be virtual
and I will be at it but it's going to be virtual
okay so smoth gone there was a contested smoth con this time I tried looking this up on the internet
but I couldn't find much detail but Liz knows about it so take it away Liz
I'll only know about it because of what I read about it on the internet which is mostly on
Facebook yeah I think I did check on Fars 717 I couldn't find any uh rating about this
so uh what what I saw was a bid was proposed for smoth con in Sweden
so there was a bid proposed for Stockholm but there was also a second bid that was set up
that had been set up a bit earlier I think for Providence Road Island and it appears that
the Providence bid won I think they were both set up at fairly short notice so hopefully Sweden
will bid again because it would be nice to have uh smoth cons in Europe every often I'm I know
there's one in there's one in 2020 Alice in went Alice in was there's an off con 2020 in Lisbon?
uh no it's 2021 nothing was in 2020 oh okay yes very enough and so yeah it's nice to have
another sort of thing I thought I think it would have been nice to have one kind of not long before
a UK world con but maybe actually you're better having them slightly after UK world cons then
anyone who's got excited by Glasgow can then continue to come to Swaffa so it's not come when
it will be in Providence but apparently they have committed to a substantial like having a substantial
hybrid con as well yeah now I'd have really liked to have been in Sweden because I had infinite fun
at the Lisbon's soft con I'd like to go to another European soft con true but one maybe it will be
there after the 2024 world con which be nice and two it may not be quite as nice weather
in dot com in December as it was in Lisbon I do have a problem with the soft con weekend
which I'm going to get to foreshadowing all right then that was all I had to say on
the soft cons have fun Providence road island Providence does sound like quite a nice place to
go to for a convention actually I probably could be pretty good I want to go there at some point
at some point I want to go to all the places Lovecraft light wrote about uh and obviously
Providence would be on that list.
Wandering shop so uh Mastodon we've all been
masturbating over on Mastodon except for Liz who hasn't I've got an account I just haven't
actually done anything with it yet lizz is to be fair the podcast musk fan so you know it makes
sense oh oh you take that back that is a joke too far
are you lizz bat a at mast dot two yes she's got on the wandering shop Liz is where all the
cool kids are by which I mean Alison and I because wandering shop was closed still is it took ages
to go there wandering shop is still quite closed in that every week existing wandering shop members
get a link that they can invite people and and I think it's like 50 a week or 100 a week so it's
growing slowly but the last couple of times they've released code I have got a friend or two in on
it so if if you know me and you want to get on wandering shop then get in touch and when I have
a an invite I will get it to you but wandering shop is very nice because it is an instance I think
Chris Rose is the primary person behind it and well done Chris this is good thing it's a server
primarily for science fiction and fantasy community generally so including authors editors and fans
and readers and obviously that makes it kind of it's got a great feeling it reminds me a bit of
records as a fandom and records as they've written if you're very old so the local the local feed is
full of people saying stuff that's interesting and I just really really like it there and
masted on itself imagine twitter without all the corporate shilling and politics I mean it can't
last obviously but it's very very nice at the moment no but it is it is basically quite good
I was on another instance originally which I also quite liked but they defederated the big
server and that meant that there were several people I wanted to follow and couldn't I was
extremely annoying if you don't know what that means listeners it's not important and if you do
you understand why it's annoying it means go and ask Allison she'll tell you in detail but yes
no wandering shop is good and if you are in the science fiction fandom space is an instance which
is designed for you to enjoy so yeah is good instance to go for if there are sign-ups and like I say
Allison and I both have both have access to the codes so yeah if you want to be on there let's
know and then when the codes come out you have a very short window to get on it but it's been
lengthening recently it's not me so bad so I know Raj is on masted on on the masted on dot scott
service there's like scottish one there's a bunch of different ones it's cool if you are on a masted
on server one of the things about masted on being run from the ground up by people rather than run
by big industry is that that means that people who are probably people you know if you're on a
fairly small server need money to keep it going so do throw small amounts of money at the admins to
keep your servers running because otherwise this entire business bottle is going to fail and we
will go back to something where you don't pay anything except your soul to be on there you're
very so yeah I mean you it is much better to just pay a small amount of money to get the thing that
you want rather than not paying anything and in return getting a torrent of garbage advertising
posts in your feed all of the time all right shall we do picks yeah Liz what's your pick do you
want to start with it yeah so my pick is I mean I pick it not without reservations but basically
the only book I've read over the past few weeks is Stephen King's It because it was on my Kindle
and so I thought oh that might be good I'll start reading it and when it's on your Kindle you can't
tell that it is actually 1500 pages it's a very long book so basically we're ahead an entire trilogy
yeah it is an early Stephen King book I hadn't read if you've read lots of Stephen King books you
kind of know what you are getting which is small town American horror but it's just a kind of really
well-done example of the form I think so it's got two intertwining plot strands one in the late 1950s
and one in the 1980s and it kind of into times and really well so you get this kind of impending
sense of you know from the 1980s plot strand that in the 1950s they essentially went to kill the
demon creature that lives beneath their town and basically ends up on a murder spree every 20
something years and from the fact they're back in 1980 you know that they did not actually do the
job first time round and basically it enshrines all the plots and they build to the fact they were
getting the kind of first battle with this creature and the second battle kind of happening both at
the end of the novel but in totally different time strands so you know where it's going to end up
and you know it's quite digressive it spends a lot of time on the inhabitants of this small
town and building up the small town feel but I think it does pay off in the end maybe not quite
to the extent of needing 1500 pages but I felt quite satisfied with it at the end of it and it's
just really good at this sort of individual scenes of there's a part where Mike one of the
children they've been there kind of pre-preetines goes off to the site of an explosion and basically
is menaced by an enormous bird and when I just say that it sounds like it might be quite funny but
it's a really menacingly written section where he is in Otterra of this colossal bird which is
chasing after him and trying to kill him and it's just full of kind of like little chapters like
that which do really well at building up this creeping sense of horror if you read any Stephen
King books you probably know that's why you're reading Stephen King books right so yeah still
recommended but very long so I have a confession which is I've never read any Stephen King oh you
probably should yeah I knew this was coming it's just like yeah yeah I've never read me and I should
what I want to do so I know that there is a novella called The Mist yes which is very famous I think
and I want to read that because I'm a parody of myself and it was the inspiration for one of the
later Arkham Horror of the card game scenarios as far as I watch read that and then I'm like
probably more of his stuff given I quite like horror so yes at some point I will get to it in my
copious spare time I have read a very small amount of Stephen King and it's one of things that help
form my view that I do not really like horror very much and in fact I tend to go off things if
they have too much horror in them so I'm not going to be reading a 1500 page horror novel anytime soon
but John should definitely read Stephen King oh I've read Carrie Carrie's amazing I loved Carrie
I'd forgotten that so you have read some Stephen King there yeah yeah we read it in book club
when I was on grad and it was amazing very very creepy I've very much enjoyed it yeah I mean the
thing about that so I have read the myth the thing about the myth is that famously there is a film
adaptation of The Mist which changes the ending in a way I will not spoil but is really very grim
hey yeah I think that's as good a good as good a place as any to start yeah basically don't start
with one of his you know 1500 page works although they are you know the stand is also pretty good
but yeah Carrie I think would be would have been a place I would say you could start if I hadn't
only read it or you know something like Misery is also good Salem's lot quite a lot the early ones
are pretty good mm-mm Alison do you want to do yours so I had never been to Dragon Meat which is a
one-day tabletop gaming convention in London um for a couple of reasons it's the smothcon weekend so
yeah that's the thing but also um I'd always gone to a big house party on that day so it clashes
with that and at the moment the big house party isn't happening so that sounds like a good reason
to go across London and go to a games convention what what happened was that it's run by John Dodd
who is doing a site for a lot of conventions at the moment including um Eastercon so and he said
to the rest of us and also to try to pledge for committee why don't you all come to Dragon Meat
and I'll put your names on the door and give you a table and you can promote the Eastcon so we did
that and we had a lot of fun and we were in a lovely kind of science fictiony area of the Dragon Meat
Trading Halls with third vault your yarns and um the BSFA and the BFS and Ian Waits like New
Compress and and a few other things like that and it was awesome um and we talked to lots of people
some of whom were already coming to the Eastcon some of whom said they would definitely join but
hadn't got around to it yet some of whom had um heard about Eastercons but weren't sure they were
for them and some of whom had never heard of Eastercons and some of those were like oh that sounds
amazing that sounds wonderful so hopefully some of those will come and it was all pretty good um
I had an accident at Dragon Meat oh no are you okay I am not okay I was decluttering and I decided
I would take a bag of games I did not want anymore for the Dragon Meat bring and buy sale and sell
them and I would definitely not buy any games and bring them home and how did that go Alison?
I bought how many games net did you acquire? I came home with seven more games that I took
some of them were small for content listeners this was my birthday weekend and I had an enormous
amount of birthday money and I bought fewer games than that yeah but I think you bought more
expensive ones because one of the things about these games is that they were incredibly cheap
hopefully I will play them and they will even go back to next year's Dragon Meat or I will
pass them on to other people who would like them and they will not stay in my house forever but they
might do but I feel like I have a lot of games in the house and they're mostly games from the 70s
that are not very good and mixing them up for some more modern games some of which might be very
good uh it's probably a good bet but it was so good it has so much fun and um it's full of it's
full of nerds full of full of our sorts of people sensitive faddish faces and and the trading halls
are like a magic cave full of games it was very good there were an enormous number of people
wanting to sell me very expensive dice that I was like how much is it reasonable to pay for
dice the answer is not that much I mean you got octa-thunk dice what more do you need I like the dice
that had liquid centers I thought liquid center dice were pretty good have you seen the dice that
look like baked beans oh I see the baked bean dice yeah they're horrible they're great did I did
dice I have not seen dice that looked like baked beans but somebody was selling uh I will put a link
in the show notes listeners they have they're doing a kickstarter for solid foam dice about that
sort of size that you you throw at people as a game and there's gonna be a kickstarter next year
and I'm like oh oh this this great this looks awesome for the listeners Alison is holding her
hand up about you know two or three inches long yeah maybe about six or six centimeters across
maybe seven because for all the readers now you could have been holding your hands up like this
like three feet apart which would also be fun but different the reason I think why the trading
halls are so amazing is that the first Saturday in December is if you were going to
run an event focused around selling games crap the first Saturday in December would be quite a good
time to do that yep um and the bring a buy oh the bring a buy and all credit to the people who'd
sorted out the website for the bring a buy because you actually you registered your games in advance
with how much you wanted to sell them for and it was way easier than listing things on ebay i'll
tell you and then when you got to the convention they basically bridged out bocos stick on your
games in approximately one nanosecond and then you could sit at your sales table for the eastercon
every so often you'd search through the list of available games by price from low to high and
go god that looks like a bargain and nip round and buy it so yeah i was in my happy place which is
buying crap to fill up my house there's already full of crap wait no i like games conventions i
haven't been to uh dragon meat but i have been to other games conventions and they are a lot of fun
and there was an Arkham horror event a dragon meat uh which apparently went very well i didn't
actually play any games because it didn't really have any time because we were on our table all day
and um had the truest expression of the games convention buying stuff while not playing anything
also i don't i think if it was a two-day convention i'd probably get some games in
and i used to love a games convention called stabcon which when i went to it didn't really have any
traders at all it just had a load of people in the room i didn't have any organized games it didn't
have any traders it just had a load of people in the room playing games and i really really like that
stabcon is still stabcon is still quite like that so so i mean like and you just sit around
waiting for somebody to pull out a game that looked interesting and then you go
oooh do you need players and they go yes and you sit down and play and then a couple of hours later
you do it again until the end of the day it's good and then i think we all stayed at a student
accommodation that was some of the worst accommodation i've ever slept in but you know that sort of thing
stabcon south is held at the hilton double tree in salampton i went once twice i think i went
once and then the pandemic happened it was very sad but it was a good convention it had two traders
and a lot of games and i played a lot of wealth and it was pretty great games conventions are
weird for me because i got into science fiction conventions and games conventions at roughly the
same time and i was like oh science fiction is a convention it's a good but like what i really
like is games conventions and then i changed my mind because i kind of basically went oh i can
play games anytime but i can only get the science fiction convention experience at science fiction
convention the thing i like about games conventions is playing games that haven't come out yet so like
i have ruled that i don't back things on kickstarter unless i've played them but games conventions are
a good way of playing games that are shortly coming to kickstarter to see if you like them before
the wrong kickstarter for instance okay so the great thing about having ignored the tabletop gaming
hobby for the last 40 years is there's an awful lot of games i haven't played yet it's certainly good
oh no that's fair that is fair when there are failure modes like i played a game at the convention
in 2019 which was amazing and it still has not made it to kickstarter so i'm like champing at the bit
yeah i met Francis Tresham at a games convention in about 1985 and he was like oh here's my follow-up
game to Spanish main which was his game at the time and um and we played that and it was really
weird and that level what should i do anyway i am gonna pick a thing a series of 15 comics and a
series of 13 comics and a series of three novels and a series of three ya novels and two mangers
and some other bits and bobs and an audiobook because i'm picking phase one of the star wars
high republic project which i have finished reading the people who write star wars books got together
and they were like it's really annoying that when we write star wars books about bits of star wars
that are being done on telly and in the movies the telly and movies keep contradicting the things
we want to do and wouldn't it be nice if we had a little bit of the universe we could play in
where no one else is telling us what's going to happen and so they did that it's called the
high republic it's about 200 years before um the rest of star wars and i finished it and it is
really good i liked it a great deal basically focused around the jedi at the height of their
success and the republic are kind of forging out into the wider galaxy from the core worlds and
they hit upon a group of pirates called the nai hill and it's basically about what ends up happening
then and then the last book is very sad and uh i spent ages reading it because it really stressed
me out it was very good i'm just a coward and then they're starting phase two and phase two is weirdly
a prequel which i guess makes sense because if you're going to do a three act star war you start
in the middle and then do the before bit and then do the after bit and that is well established
in star wars lore it's kind of what uh roguan and andor have done and also i will say the audio
production was amazing it was forecast and it reminded me of like listening to like radio for
um stuff and hearing that kind of thing done in audiobooks is really neat and i hope there's more
of that in the future um although it will reignite the discussions about best dramatic presentation
audio best audio presentation hugo for the win i mean to be fair i could submit it in the best
long form category but i don't think it would win compared to severance and or everything ever
at once so you know do we have two more nominations for that category i have to talk about this in
our hugo nomination episode in january our listeners can write in writing listeners anyway that was
the old thought podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
and for those who don't know alison's ex is mike scott thank you very much for it again mike
and and thank you for remaining on form true to brand i divorced him for a reason guys
and it wasn't that i have a question is that staying in the podcast i mean i think i divorced
him for a reason guys but it wasn't that it's fine right i don't know that's what i am asking
i'm happy if i had if i hadn't wanted to do the podcast i wouldn't have said it love you mike
i feel it is unfair that you would never get a name we do have to give him you know no one else
is on the podcast no one else's letters are oh referred to in in terms of their relationship to
the podcasters else is spaniel would would just be wife my soulmate christopher j gossita
wrote in the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in
compactec.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
Thank you.