Ah yeah, we've got an awards bit, yeah, because of course we do, yes.
There's always an awards bit.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 106th episode of Octa Thorpe, the podcast for
Science Fiction and Science Fiction fandom, which is coming to you on the 28th of March 2024,
or Maunday Thursday. I'm John Coxon, I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
And hello to everyone who's listening to this on the way to EasterCon. We hope your car/plane/rail
replacement bus is pleasant. I think there might actually be some trains. If you're listening from
a train, do let us know. There might be some trains in the kind of phase where you can still get a
train before you get to the rail replacement bus. Let us know listeners. If you are delayed by 30 or
more minutes, you can claim delay repay and then you can spend it on board games. Board games,
better than delays. You know what else is better than delays? Letters of comment.
And we have some letters of comment. So we heard from Bob Morrell on Blue Sky,
who very much enjoyed the artwork on episodes 103 and 102, which is the ones about wearing your
different Hugo hats and David McArty in a pander suit. So I think they are some of our finest art.
Thank you very much Bob Adlers. Tom Roch. We heard from Colin Murtar who wrote into comments,
"If part of your aim is to explain what's going on in the bubble, I would say you manage that with
a plomb. I'm not in the fandom, but between you and Fals
7.8, I get clear and concise explanations of what's been going on. So for that, thanks."
Hoorah! We're being helpful guys. Yes. I will say Colin, if you stop knowing what we're going on
about, please let us know because I do sometimes worry that we'll stop being good at it. We heard,
and this is going to come as a surprise from Chris Garcia who said, "There's a photo of a friend of
Mylo on your cover art." Well, it obviously was because it was this, right? Maybe not a friend,
but I got to interview Margaret Hout and advocated her for the Computer History Museum Fellowship.
So I feel like this is more evidence that Chris Garcia is better at name-dropping than most of the
rest of us. And it's always really cool name-dropping. It's not like, you know, I ran into such a body
on a train station platform and said hello. It's like, "Oh no, they were in my car along with the
lunar lander." And he also says, "I have listened to OctaThorp on a 20th anniversary Mac, the best
Mac ever made." And I know that nobody else cares about this, but that gave me a warm feeling.
Thank you. I'm very glad to know that OctaThorp has been heard on that device.
He does end the lair by saying, "Friendship is the greatest pick of all." So that's good.
Alison, I have an art prompt for you. Can you draw us as my little OctaThorp friendship is magic?
Oh yeah, no, I think that's that's doable. Chris also says, "The NPC's censure is the
closest we've got to any group officially condemning the actions of Chengdu. Pretty much
James and Mary Robinette are the only two former chairs who haven't read the type seen."
And that's a good point I think. And also, I feel like, can we formally condemn the actions of Chengdu
guys? I mean, I think we were formally condemning the actions of Chengdu before it was cool.
We haven't been using the Chengdu as a shower artwork enough in the wake of all of this, and maybe we
should maybe we should dig that out and we should probably get it on t-shirts. Well, it seems to
have come down a bit, but I think there will be a point where, for instance, the 2024 Hugo winners
have a Hugo in the 2022-2023 winners do not have a physical Hugo that maybe we can drag out again?
I believe they're still a Dave McCarty's lock-up, aren't they?
Laurie Anderson of the Hugo Girl Podcasts has taken matters into her own hands and made adorable
little tiny awards for people. They are extremely cute and we apparently are going to get some
at Glasgow. We're very excited. Yeah, we're very excited about this.
So yes. And then we also heard from Mike Glier of 5.7.17, among other pursuits. Every episode,
I send an email to Mike and Bill Burns to get our episode on 5.7.70 and efranzines.com. And this
time I noted more explicitly that there's a transcript of the episode, and Mike, he might
have actually a transcript, "Blessings upon you all. I've stopped everything and read it." Which is
high praise. And he wanted to discuss the thing that, um, Alison said, "People reside above you
as things go terribly wrong, and then suddenly you'll be working on the world colour, a high level."
And Mike says, "That's a fact, and it's less fun now than it used to be, because I remember
Anita Raj at the 1989 Worldcon Family Gathering, or whatever it was actually called."
Speaking about how she'd come to volunteer at Norie's Con 3. The sport life found the last
speaker in the centre, IEL, diminutive Anita Raj who told her story. "This is my first
Worldcon. A month ago I was a simple mundane and wandered into a work session for the convention.
She collated, stapled, mailed, and round up with a radio and a beeper in charge of a gang of
teamsters during setup. Don't even try, because you can't get rid of me now." Yeah.
Um, which is brilliant. Thank you for your much, Mike. That was good.
So Mike mentions transcripts, and we've, we've, we wanted to transcript for a while, but we had a
problem, which is that we felt that AI transcripts are, are, were not good enough. And hand transcribing
is more work than you think it is. If you, if you've not tried it and you don't think it's a lot of
work, you should try it and then you can think it's a lot of work. So we've done a few, but we
haven't done very many. And so we now, we have a better AI transcript, which we will release with
the episode on the day of the, we drop it. But we're going to then, over the next week, improve
it quite a lot. We'll correct all the obvious errors, but it won't be kind of what I think
offers a Clare Broily standard of correction. It will be a kind of us standard of correction,
which is definitely not as good as that. More about that later. And, um, and you should get that,
the following week is the plan. So we'll have a links on our show notes to where you can get the
transcript files. And, and what we'd like you to do is you probably have friends who
have hearing loss, who aren't listening to the podcast, because they can't hear it properly.
And what we want you to do is let them know that we have transcripts available. Yes.
The other thing we would like you to do is if you notice a problem with a transcript,
let us know. There is a link in the show notes to the GitHub repository with the transcripts,
and you can browse them there. So if you notice any errors, let us know either by email or by
launching an issue on GitHub if you are conversant with the forms.
If you are a proper nerd, so one of the things I have done in the last two weeks is start to
understand how GitHub works. Not very well. If you're proper nerd, you can correct it and just
send in a pull request and Donald merge it back in. So yeah, if you do that, you will get a ribbon.
Although if you're, if it in my experience, you can send John a pull request and then he'll
send you a load of queries about why your pull request isn't good enough. Just say it.
It is possible that that's more applicable to co-hosts than it is listeners.
And we also heard from some people on Facebook, we heard from Farah Mendelssohn and Alex Holden and
Johnny Badley and and Rosin. Thank you very much all for writing in.
Deb Geisler, who was the chair of Noris Khan for, which was the Worldcon in 2004
and was generally a very good egg. It was announced she had died yesterday as we record.
None of us knew Deb super well, but she helped out on Lunkon a lot. So we all got to know her
through that and she was an absolutely wonderful person and she will be sorely missed.
Yeah, she was very supportive of many of my kind of fan,
vanish and corollary endeavors and I, this is a great shape.
Who wants to introduce Eastercom? I joined the Eastercom. What? Let's join the Eastercom.
But last year this was like a nice and exciting surprise that it also put to plane ticket,
but this time I just bought a virtual membership. So that's fair and you're not going to be as
stuntless. So philosophical question, can I be a stuntless? You can be anything you want to be
Liz. Don't let imposter syndrome stop you. It would be quite funny. Will I be able to see your face at
any point during the weekend? I would virtually, I would virtually present at the Eastercom and
you might possibly be able to see my face if I join like a Zoom party or something, but I'm not
time shifting. So I've got to get up early to your face. Only if we could zoom you into breakfast.
You could zoom me into breakfast. Yes. Oh, whatever. Do you know if there are any greasy
spoons with good breakfast in Telfer? So the thing about this Eastercom is that it's being held
in a conference center with a number of on site hotels and then a number of other hotels and I
am in one of the other hotels and I think John and a Spaniard are also in one of the other hotels.
Yep, it's got pool. That's quite nice. And what that means is that I won't just be kind of wandering
down to breakfast in the Con Hotel and then at quarter to ten for my ten o'clock thing. I'll have to
actually get up and plan. So I was hoping that there are some good cafes in Telfer. So if you
know of any, do let me know. I know it's like Vlogy Thursday when you're listening to this.
And it also means that the conference said to shut the type of leave 10 30 in the evenings.
And after that, there will be a late bar in the holiday inn. But you will only be able to buy drinks
at the late bar if you are staying in the holiday inn or the other, the international. Is it the
international? The international is the other official Con Hotel and I am not an either of those
two hotels on account of how I'm a cheapskate. I'm either going to spend Eastcon super sober
or have a sack full of tins with me. One of those. Or if you are staying in the holiday inn
right in because we will trade ribbons for beer. Oh yeah, no, also you can buy me
you can buy me a beer in exchange for an octa thought ribbon or indeed a cafe moose ribbon because
I'll have cafe moose if you're only if you're a mooseter for the cafe moose ribbons. But there'll
be a cafe moose meetup at Eastcon as well. We just don't know where and when yet. This is a
spectacular deal because I bet the the beers in the holiday and are not cheap. I think you can feel
free to demand some actual cash off my co-hosts. Not that anyone has cash anymore.
Let's stop ruining our elaborate plan to get cheap beer. Okay, so so one of the things about
this is that during lockdown about 600 of you said to me, oh, I'll buy you a drink when all this is
over. And what you don't realize is I was taking names. There is a statue of limitations on offers
of drink. I think it may have expired. I think it might have done. No, that's fine. Yes, we would
like you to go to the bar for us with our credit cards. Yes. And and and and make sure that we
could drink. But also the only the only thing that I recognize as beer in the in the late bar is
Camden IPA. So I might have a bag of tins anyway, just saying. So yes, I mean, so having
having been someone who has stayed off site at previous Eastcon's, this is
this is not the first time that there have been late night things where you have to find someone
who was in the right hotel to get them to buy you a drink. And also there have been times when I've
been staying in the right hotel and I've still wanted to find someone who was staying in the right
hotels by me a drink on account of how I used to be an undergraduate. So thank you very much for
tobs buying me drinks when I was on the graduate. This is very good. And any rumors that I learned
how to forge his signature so I could charge things to the room are entirely unfounded. Oh, that sounds
so plausible. Maybe I've found it but it's very plausible. We are not staying in the holiday
and but I will be in the bar probably. I'll also be in the games room. We'll talk about the games
room in a minute. And Liz will be in her house. I will be in my house with tins. Maybe with tins.
It's just I'll be no wait. I'm going to be very confused as well. I'm going to be because I will
be a varying number of hours ahead depending what day and time of day it is because the clock's
go forward, right? Yes. The clock's go forward on the Saturday night of Eastcon.
Yeah, that's going to be confusing. So I mean I think this is just a ploy for a
fitter happier healthier Eastcon because I also noticed there's a great big park next to the
conference center which looks very nice actually. There's a great big park. Everyone's going to go
to bed at 10.30 and you're not all going to be having breakfast together in one giant room full
of plague. So yeah, I think everyone's going to come out healthier from this one than from previous
Easticons. Okay, so based on the last two Easticons, I hardly see how I could come out less healthy.
Oh no, that's tempting fate, isn't it? They'll be a sweepstake listeners. Look at the show notes
for a link to that. I will not be joining you for breakfast in a cafe, Alison, because I will
have a breakfast in my hotel which has breakfast included. And I'm hoping it will have mushrooms
and hash browns. Those are both healthy right liz. Those are vegetables. Absolutely. Good. Good.
Good. Good. Good. Good. I have also been looking to see if there are any interesting breweries
around Telford and I am not seeing many and I have had this similar look around
Shrewsbury when I've been visiting with friends and also been similarly rather disappointed.
So if you know of any local beers that I should be trying to obtain while I'm there, please let me
know. So here's what I'm doing at Easticon because although the program has not been released yet,
apparently we believe by the time this drops, the program will have been published. But we are
using a little known secret method which is called guessing the URL that the Easticon program will
probably have to see if we can find it before it's out. And we have listeners, so we're going to
discuss it now with a proviso that it might change. But the program will obviously be out by
the time you get this, which is early on Maundi Thursday because no, it will be. I'm
paying up fairly. It normally is, isn't it? So here's what I'm doing. I'm on a panel about
starting a skill from scratch. The moderator wrote to me and said, "Tell us which skill you
started from scratch." And I'm like, "Oh, there's so many because for people who don't know,
I randomly pick a hobby and then do it obsessively for a while and then stop and do a different one."
So I have quite a lot of things to say about that. And then I'm on an item at eight o'clock
of Friday called Talking About Tabletop Games, I think possibly with John. Me, yes, with me.
So this is a panel I suggested and you can come along to hear why I suggested it and what I think
about it because there is a real danger that if I talk about it here, there will be no point in
having the panel. Fair. There's a fan fund item at 11 o'clock on Saturday called Around the World
in 80 Trip Reports, to where I'm talking about the fan funds and about trip reports probably.
And then there is a fan funds auction, which you should all come. It brings us stuff, but actually
let us know as soon as possible if you have fabulous things for us to auction because we're
going to have a catalogue as we have done for the last couple of times. So if you bring us things
at later in the weekend and say, "Can you auction this?" we'll be like, "Oh, we definitely can,
but possibly at Glasgow." So. And then on Monday at one o'clock we have OctaThorp live in what is
becoming our standard slot. Yes, because it means that, you know, we can talk about the Eastercon
at the Eastercon. And Liz will be, I believe, in the audience for this. That is my plan.
Yeah, and we will have a special stunt Liz. So yes, I have a schedule. And my schedule is, as
Alison mentioned, I am on talking about tabletop games at 8pm on Friday. I am on fan funds auction
at 8pm on Sunday and I am on OctaThorp live at 1pm on Monday. So I'll see some of you there,
I'm sure. But I am also on on the Friday at four o'clock, a panel on Andor, the Star Wars
television program called Spies Savaters, Assassins. And I think that is going to be a good panel.
I think it's being moderated by Tommy Ferguson, who is the chair of the next Eastercon and has
some good people on it and should be a good hoot. I am also on a panel at 10am on Saturday called
The Threat and Promise of Mega Constellations. I will be on the promise side of the panel argument
and I suspect I will be very lonely. I don't know what a mega constellation is. That's why you
should go to the panel. Constellations with lots of satellites in is what a mega constellation is.
But I promised to go into that in more detail on the panel. Oh, so it's not like a lot of stars.
I was like, oh, it's going to be a lot of stars. So this is like space. This is like endlessly
or anything space junk. Well, that if you take the threat side, yes. Of when have I ever done that,
John? My career has largely been based on analyzing data from mega constellation. So,
and I believe that is being moderated by Jackie Burns, who is the guest of honour,
who's also very kindly supplied an art for the newsletter, which I'm running. If you would like
to help with the newsletter, please come and help. Alison, I believe is helping with newsletter.
Yeah, 100%. And are you volunteering with anything else at Eastcon, Alison? Or is it?
It's you and fanfons, I think. Ah, fair enough. The other thing that is happening at Eastcon
is there will be, well, lots of things happening Eastcon. Yes, many other things are happening
at Eastcon. One of the things in which I am interested is games. Games. So I'll be bringing
some games. Games. I'll be bringing Atma, a role-playing card game by the people who made
Shipwreck Arcana, which Liz introduced me to, a boil back. Well, that's my good of a bringing.
I will be bringing back to the future of the card game. I will be bringing Cthulhu and
Pirate Flux. I will be bringing Hanabi, and I will be bringing the noisy person's card game.
So yes, if you'd like to play some games, do let me know. And I see Tim Kirk is bringing
Blood on the Clock Tower, and I'm hoping that I'll be able to play a couple of games off that,
because I love Blood on the Clock Tower. So yeah, I'll be good. There is a spreadsheet,
which I will link in the show notes, which you can peruse that has some games on it.
Yeah, I mean, you can look at the list of games I have on board game geek, and if there's any
you want to play, tell me, oh, before this podcast comes out. So that won't work. And then I can
pack them. Yes, that's your problem. Please go back in time and tell Alison so that she can pack
them last Tuesday. I will probably be bringing Mindbug First Contact, a game that I only bought,
because it fills a challenge on board game geek. I don't know what I'll be bringing. I might not
bring too many games, but I am playing a card game every day in March, and that includes some of
the days in the Eastcon. So we'll have to have some sorts of games, but there's been a couple of,
there was one game where it got to 11 30, and I was like, oh, I have not played a card game today.
Oh, look, I could play clock, I could play clock patients on the internet. That'll do.
I am mostly bringing small card games, because they take up less room in my luggage.
The Guff Racer started there. We have two candidates who are Ian Nichols, who is a
Perth fan of very long standing, and Cat Clay, who has won the Ditmar for Best Fan Writer for
the last two years. So we are delighted to have two excellent candidates, and do please vote.
You can vote online, or we might put a link in the show notes. That's probably what we'll do. We'll
put the link to voting for Guff in the show notes. You could also vote at Eastcon at the Fan Funds
table, and yes, one of those people will be coming to Glasgow, along with the winners of TAF,
and not the winner of EFF, who will be going to ErasmusCon the following weekend instead, and I have made
that mistake every single week on the podcast. It's kind of something I do now. I'm just kind of
overly will-con focused, but I make that mistake every week, so hopefully I will stop making that
mistake by the time we get to WELCOME, or indeed ErasmusCon in Rotterdam, which I will not be going to.
Voting for the Doc Weir Award will also be happening at the Eastcon, so Doc Weir is given to the
unsung hero of the Eastcon, or of British, Random, or generally I suppose, and last year it was the
excellent Claire Breiley of Croydon. This year, Claire will be administering the award because
the thanks you get for being an unsung hero is being made to do more work behind the scenes,
as is the great tradition of con running. And so if you would like to vote, I believe there will be
an online option. There will also be a paper option, so do exercise your right to vote,
and if you're not sure who to vote for, ask around, because there's usually some ideas
being passed around at the convention. And you can also pass ideas around. Yes, I put the fix in once,
and it was very good. I felt like a proper smoth. This is a chance to mention one of the things
that Eastcon has done spectacularly well, which is that they have an Eastcon members portal,
which you should have had a link to in your email, but you can also just Google it and find it,
and that has links to the read me, the discord chat, the souvenir book, and voting in the
dotware award and bs-fay award, and other information about the convention. And I'm hoping it will also
have, by Thursday, links to vote in all the fanfums races as well. Yes, so as noted, you can go to the
member portal and vote in the bs-fay awards. This is the only place you can vote. You cannot vote
on paper, and I will note that you have to vote by noon on Saturday, because the winner will be
announced at 1pm on Saturday, which I've got to say is a tighter turnaround than I would have been
happy with, but I guess you can be checking there's no wackiness going on in the votes as you go along.
If you are on the train to Eastcon, you can still go and log in and vote in the bs-fay awards.
I mean, it's also ranked choice voting. I hope the spreadsheet is, you know, doing all the elimination
for them. In best non-fiction long, especially, there are some very good things that you should
go and vote for, but there are some very good things in all of the categories, and you should cast your
vote accordingly. In further awards news, so far, announce the finalists for the Nebula Awards,
which will be presented in June, and we also know that the Hugo Awards shortlist will come out at
Eastcon. And so, we are currently in that 24 hours where we can speculate wildly about the
Hugo is based on the information for the Nebula Awards, and if you are listening to this
any point after Friday evening, it's out of date. Indeed, so yeah, there's a sweet spot of about
36 hours where this podcast will be scorchingly relevant, and after that, it will be, we will
know the Hugo finalists and it will be less relevant, but still very interesting. After Friday evening,
you can listen to this and laugh at how completely out of touch we were with the Hugo electorate.
So I would note that the novel list has two books that we mentioned when we were talking about
possible novel nominees, which are the Saint of Bright Doors and Translation State.
I think we also mentioned the Terra Formers by Annalyn Neuets.
Oh, we might have done, actually.
I mentioned it on a cat if I didn't like it very much, but yeah, sorry.
I mean, I was going to put it like that, but yes, but it has been in the buzz.
Yeah, I think this looks like a solid list, and I would not be surprised if there is significant
crossover with the Hugos.
We didn't mention Witch King, which now that I look at it will surely be on the ballot,
but I don't think any of us had read it.
No.
I'm going to wait for it to be on the ballot and then read it.
There is that, like...
Some tour.com, so that's probably probably a shout.
Yeah, some stuff is such a dead lot for the ballot that I'm like, well, I can just wait until it comes out.
Like, I expect that to be on there, and to be honest, expect John Scales's latest to be on the Hugo
lists, and so I'll wait for them to be in the vote back.
A lot of the people I hang out with listeners are unrepentant hipsters when it comes to what they
read, and none of the people that I talk to about science fiction have been talking about,
Witch King.
And so, yes, if I'm very honest, hadn't occurred to me, it might be nominated,
hadn't thought about it at all.
But now it's on the Nebula list.
Yes, very obviously, it's probably going to be on the Hugo list.
I did want to say one thing about the Nebula list and its potential crossover with the Hugo list,
which is particularly in game writing.
So, the Nebula's award game slightly differently to the Hugo,
and the Nebula award is specifically for the writing.
But it is curious that Tia's For The Kingdom is not on the list.
Chancesinar and Baldur's Gate 3 are both on the list.
As is Dredge, which I think we have previously mentioned.
I did, yeah.
There's also the Breadmasterise, which I think is a text adventure,
because I think choice of games is a one of the things that was covered in the 50 Years of Text
Games project.
Alan Week 2 and the Nine Fox Gambit Roleplaying Game by Yun Harley and Marie Brennan.
But I'm a bit confused by that because I read Roleplaying Game and assumed that it was
a paper RPG, but then it says "Android" and I'm like, "Is it a phone game?"
And I don't know.
Let's find out.
Live research.
Yeah, it's Android Press, not Android Phone.
I thought we talked about the Breadmasterise, and now I feel terrible that we didn't,
because we probably should have done.
I think the thing about the Nebula's and its award for game writing is that people look at a game
like "Tears of the Kingdom" and don't spot the fact that it's got writing in it,
because that writing doesn't end up being words on the page while you're playing.
It's the writing is in the design of the scenarios and the puzzles and all of that.
And I think that this is a reason why you're not going to see games like that on the Nebula's.
Yeah, I mean, I would word it slightly differently, which is,
I think Zelda games have "wank writing", and therefore it is not surprising to me that Zelda
is not on this list.
It might be that they've leveled up significantly since all of the other Zelda games,
but I've never played a Zelda game and thought, "Hoh-oh, this is a good writing".
Okay, fair. I went and looked at the Breadmuss Rise, and it is a 450,000 word interactive
commissive fantasy baking eldritch horror novel.
Yes, which sounds like I might have to go and encounter it.
"Choice of Games" is an app I have on my phone ever since the 50 years of Text Games project
concluded, but I have not yet actually played any of the games on it,
because I don't really know where to begin, so this is a good thing,
because it gives me a place to begin.
And I gotta say, 9fox-guy-mit world sounds like a great place to have like an RPG,
you know, pick your faction, you know, decide what your customs are,
you know, and there's a lot of space for making a lot of really interesting stuff up there in that
world, I think.
Yeah, on that topic, I'm extremely curious about an RPG set in that world, because I think one of my
core criticisms is harsh, but I think one of the things I thought about that world was that I
wasn't really sure how the internal logic worked in anything approaching a coherent way,
and I am fascinated by the idea that it's got an internal logic that can be codified into a role
playing game, and I think I might buy the role playing game just so I can see how that works.
But also, I had not heard of Android Press, and that is partly because they are, I think,
mostly known for science fiction and not gaming content. I've visited their itch.io page and
they have published this RPG and they have also published a GMless RPG based on the Sam for the
Wild Built by Becky Chambers, which you can purchase for a price of your own naming.
So yeah, those are their two games. The game they've done based on the Becky Chambers Nabella
is a hack of Wanda Home, which has been receiving various rave reviews for a while now. It was also
a Nebula Award finalist, and it won a few NEs as well. NEs are like the Hugo's role playing games.
I might have to keep an eye on them because they're clearly at the intersection of tabletop gaming
and science fiction. I have just downloaded the Red Must Rise, and I love it already because
the very first screen is, "Would you like to play an omnivore mode or vegetarian mode or vegan mode
if you don't want animal products in your baking?" Brilliant. So I like LOD in my baking.
Yeah, well, my pick for next time's sorted, guys. Liz has put in a link in the show notes.
Since we've started talking, entitled Hugo Award betting markets. Liz. Yeah.
Is this a contender for best interactive work? It's not super interactive. So what it is,
there's a website called Manifold Markets where I think basically you get some fake currency,
and you can use it to set up your own betting market on anything you want to bet on.
Yeah, so I'm coming by how I found it, but I became aware that someone is running betting markets
for four of the Hugo Fiction categories, novel at novella and short story. And so you can look at
this and look at how many votes there are for the different items. And if you use your fake money,
you can move stuff up and down. You can say, "Yes, I think this will be on the ballot." And then
probably it'll get high percentage. Or you can say, "No, I don't think it will." And then like the
markets adjust. So it's going to be interesting to see how well it has actually predicted the
Hugo Award. The top six at time of recording are two that are on the Nebula list, translation state
and Witchking, also some desperate glory by Emily Tesh, Zalinghouse by Alex Harrow,
the Adventures of Amina Al-Sarafi by Shannon Chakraborty, and starter villain by John Scaldy.
So they're the top six. And then the next ones are the Terraformers and Water Outlaws. Now, of course,
I'm discussing this after the Nebula Award ballot came out, but that doesn't actually seem to have
boosted the Terraformers and the Water Outlaws. So maybe there is not that much information going
in there. But it is quite interesting. I mean... There's an interesting thing which is that this
is from 11 traders. Ah, yes. Fair enough. So does that mean that 11 people have bet? Yes.
Yeah, that's fair. I think I think that this is a plausible look at a slice of the voters, but I
suspect that basically... Because it's got bookshops and bone dust by Travis Baldry down at like 10th.
And I think what that says to me is that the people who have voted on this are not Baldry fans,
but I wonder whether Baldry fans and the wider electorate, they might not have a perfect microcosm
is what I'm saying. This might not be a representative sample, but it is interesting. And also, we should
all bet on it. How do I bet on it? I send you my affiliate link and you set up an account and then
I get some bonus fake books. Oh, you should also do that to me.
And also, you should put that link in the show notes, Liz. Yeah, absolutely.
And rake in those fake bugs. We are not sponsored by Manifold and Liz received no monetary
value for plugging Manifold on the pot. Yeah, but she is putting her affiliate link in the show
notes. We now have to have a thing saying, "Our show notes may contain affiliate links."
That can be the episode title just to make it very clear.
Yeah, so we should make our prediction for the ballot, shouldn't we?
I don't have any predictions. Is that helpful?
In size of commentary. Okay, we probably shouldn't make predictions, but I think
I think the top five, the ones on the ballot, are definitely going to include
the mothwells and the Travis Baldry and maybe the scales again. Oh, it's depressing.
Doing it based on previous finalists, I would guess it will be the parka chan, the Baldry,
the Wells, the Harrow, the Lecky and the Scales. That would be my guest based purely on these
are names that we know Hugo people will nominate. But there's a slight wrinkle in that the nominating
community is it's Chengdu and Glasgow. So it's like a little bit atypical.
They won't be throwing out the Chinese ballots this time, so that could put a wrinkle on the ballot.
That is true. There's no Chinese names on here. No, but I think also novel is particularly tricky
for anyone who is outside China to work out. Because when I was trying to work out what even
were the things that got thrown off the ballot in Chengdu, it's really difficult to work out
where they were published or who they were published by, whether actually eligible.
So yeah, I mean, and the things on this list are just the ones that have been input by,
you know, the 11 people are bang on them. Yes. But yeah, it will be interesting to see if we do
get another mixed ballot because everyone who voted in site selection in DC for Chengdu got us
supporting membership, which got automatically turned into a full WUSFUS attending membership
of Chengdu. And so they will also all have nominating rights, right?
Yes, that is true. And they obviously, well, not obviously, but they won't have voting
rights unless they join Glasgow. Because one thing we know is that there are a lot of people
at the Chengdu Worldcon who did not have a WUSFUS membership, but all those people who voted in
site selection do you still have a full WUSFUS membership that lets them nominate?
On the subject, the Hugo Awards, Hugo Girl after the nomination deadline passed,
unrecused themselves. So we think this is generally good because we think recusing is good, but we
also think winning Hugo Awards in unesterisked years is good. And I'm just happy that I'll be
able to vote for them again in Seattle. Yes, I think also that the timing of their announcement
was very classy. They obviously waited until Glasgow nominations were closed to say, actually,
we're going to put ourselves back in the game for Seattle, which I think would have been fair anyway,
like there was an argument that maybe you should recuse yourself for a year or a couple of years,
but you don't necessarily have to do it forever anyway. But I think it's totally reasonable that
if you have won in a year, which now has a big question mark next to it, and you're not really
enjoying the glory of being a Hugo winner because you're forever wondering about it, that you get
a chance to have an unambiguous win. Good show.
I will do two quick picks that they will be quick. So I have a non-genre pick, which is a video
game, which is a little bit like a card game called Bilateral, which has been kind of, kind of
viral if you're in the right place. I first heard about it from reading about the Guardian,
which readers is not how you normally learn about how and I normally learn about video games,
and I learned it the second time from my kids who were like, "Oh, mum, you should definitely play
Bilateral, but you better not plan to do anything else for about 72 hours." So that was right.
And it is basically a chap who working alone has discovered a way to make video poker a bit
more addictive, which is not a thing that it needed, and has written a deck-building road
like on a poker theme. It's fantastic. It's very, very funny, and it's got lots of things,
and it is just a poker game. So it's exactly the sort of game I like in that it doesn't have any,
it doesn't have deep writing, it just has that loop that makes you go, "Oh no, I want to
have another run and see if I do better than I did in the last run. There are lots of different ways
to build your deck in order to win. There are also lots of ways in which your deck will not win."
And despite having a poker theme, there's no gambling involved. You pay once and you get the whole game.
Nevertheless, it's been given an 18 rating by game raters, because apparently,
pretending to be about video poker and then gambling is bad, but actually having lots of paid-for
loop boxes is not so bad. I don't quite understand that, but there we go. So Bellatro, it's very good.
It's only starts fictional content is that it has got planets in it and also tarot cards,
but that's not really very starts fictional, I think. So, but it is good. And it's exactly the
sort of game I like, which is it has that kind of, "Oh, I just need to keep playing this until I
forget to eat sleep." But then I stop playing it because of my other pick, which will be out by
the time you get this, which is because it's going to the printers tomorrow, which is the conversation
2023 souvenir book, which has excellent writing by all of our guests, well, not writing by all of
our guests, about all of our guests, and by some of our guests, and then a fascinating and lengthy
con report about our convention and a, and then all the stuff you'd expect to have like a copy of
the program and accounts for many previous Easter cons. So it has wonderful things in it, and you
can either get it as a PDF or if you asked in time a paper copy, but you had to ask by last week.
One other thing that I believe the Easter con souvenir book will have is a review by Neil Harrison,
who is, who was the guest of honor at this Easter con, and this is a review of iJedi by Michael A.
Stackpole, a Star Wars book about the galaxy's best detective jedi starfighter pilot and lover,
and distressingly it's an incredibly insightful and good review, which is very annoying because
you can't win with Neil, he turns out gold no matter what you do, but yes.
It is a startlingly good review in a number of respects, it's very insightful and it is also
extremely funny. Yes, so Andrew Hogg and I bought the review, it came with a free book,
but the review was really what we wanted, and we're very happy with it, so we're looking forward
to other people reading it. Charlie my bike, is that what you're waiting for? I don't know,
you can if you like. John, you're going to be pleased because... Oh, I like being pleased.
You're not going to be pleased for the reason you're thinking you're going to be pleased.
You're going to be pleased because you said at some point that you might try and read all my
picks this year, and I almost picked an entire trilogy of books. Right. And then I thought better
of it and just picked a YouTube video series. Hey! So I've picked a YouTube video series which
is called No CGI is really just invisible CGI, and there's three parts out of a planned four parts,
but I think the three parts are good enough to watch without the fourth. And it's by a VFX artist
who wanted to kind of take something on about a lot of claims you see in the marketing and
promotion of films that this film was done entirely with practical effects and there was no CGI
and that that makes it superior. And so he unpicks quite a lot that films going way, way back have
not always literally been filming everything that's on screen and goes back through a lot of
stuff about like map paintings and so on. And that this manipulation has always been there.
And then goes through some films which have kind of marketed themselves as No CGI. We really filmed
all this and then shows all the CGI in them. And the really interesting bit in one of them is that
he looks at Barbie, a film which he's obviously very positive about and thinks you know VFX in a
really interesting way. But also in the making of section they basically crudely removed all the
blue screen to make it look like things weren't filmed on a blue screen background, which is hilarious.
And you can see how badly they did it in some places because he's like look you can see the
blue screen through this person's hair. So they're so desperate for people to think that they didn't
film it on a blue screen that they actually now try to remove it from all the kind of extraneous
material. So I think it's really interesting and it's making a very convincing kind of case for why
you know No CGI should not be a marketing claim. But also he's got access. He's obviously read a
lot of interviews, listened to a lot of interviews in like cinematography magazines and so on and
also has loads and loads of examples from these like VFX reels that the different studios do to
show you exactly where the VFX is. And a lot of the time one either it looks like magic to me or
it's like they VFX something that I would never have considered you would do by kind of CGI.
So yeah it's interesting it'll take you about an hour to watch.
So it does sound very interesting it sounds very much up my street but if you are interested in this
the VFX artist Todd Vaziri is on Mastodon I believe Bruce Kai and on X and he is a VFX artist who's
been working in the field for a very long time. His first his first movie was I believe the first
Michael Bay Transformers but he worked on like I'm Antu, Rho Gua, Navatar. He's what he works at ILM
and he does this as well is he he basically he specializes in retweeting tweets from studios
where they've said we shot everything practically and being like nope I worked on the VFX effect
that's in this screenshot and it is great like so if you like this sort of thing it is very very
good but yes no so I'm fascinated to watch this because this is really in my wheelhouse because I
think I think it's just absolutely fascinating this is a great pick.
The history of the history of cinema and the history of theatre the history of theatre is all about
doing things on stage that people don't believe you know we've been doing this for hundreds and
hundreds of years thousands of years maybe in fact no 10,000 years I'm going to say 10,000
years because I went to the Ice Age exhibition at the British Museum I've probably mentioned this
before and they had tools that I say that we that we think that Ice Age people's used in order to
create to put in front of fires so that it would cast shadows on walls so that they could tell
theatrical stories using VFX effects in 8000 BCE they can do that.
I'm gonna talk about something that isn't genre which is I played a card game at a convention
and it was called Overs and it's a card game about cricket. It's basically complicated rock
paper scissors but in the gloriousest possible way I'm just really enthusiastic about it I won't
have a copy of it before this easter con but I will be bringing it to a future easter con probably
it was really good it really captured the kind of the trying to outthink your opponent of like
you know trying to ball the right ball based on what shot you think the bat is going to play
and voice versa it was really really neat but I did that at the convention air con which is a
Harrogate board gaming convention which occurs in march every year and I went down to Yorkshire
with a couple of pals for the day and we went to air con it was in the Harrogate Convention Center
which is opposite the majestic where the 2018 easter con was and it was really good convention but
it was a bit new for me because it's the first time in a long time that I've been to a convention
kind of almost on my own where I didn't really know anyone and it was kind of an interesting
because that isn't a common experience for me and so I think on a future episode we might talk a
little bit about that listeners foreshadowing but it was good I enjoyed it I also played a
great game of a lot of the clock tower where I managed to convince everyone I was the mayor
but I was actually the imp and then we won and I made a lot of enemies that day it's good yeah we
we now have a balaclava of evil for situations like this that happened in our house which we
have liberated from the game it was what's attached to when I decluttered my copy of war on terror
the evil balaclava was the one thing I was like oh but I could keep it because then I'd have the
evil balaclava but does one really need an evil balaclava yes I regret getting rid of that game
every day yeah I kept the cones too because I make front and play games and cones are very useful
for a printer play game and also to quote pop culture phenomenon it's about the cones
cones of duncher cones of duncher every so often I will be playing a game and I will
realize that I have gotten off base on what it is I'm supposed to be doing and I've got distracted
by some neat mechanic that won't help me win and then I just mutter to myself it's about the cones
this is john's poker towel if you're ever playing poker against john
that was the old thought podcast and it's goodbye for me um it's goodbye for me and it's goodbye for me
[Music]
coming on the train aren't you no no no you're not coming on the train no I'm going to come
with Neil and Nick and there's a very real worry that they'll want to listen to octop
so if we're listening to this in the car hi Neil and Nick I hope it's not all quick oh that's quite
funny though isn't it I have previously put my headphones in and listened to another podcast
because I'm in a car where people are listening to octop was that also Neil and Nick uh no I think
it was Ian actually I don't want to listen to my own voice for any more time than that's the answer
when when I'm doing the listen the listen for editing I do I often if there's people around I'm
still kind of like oh no I'm going to do this with headphones on so you can't hear
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in competec.com
used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will self-destruct at the beep