Oh, and the other thing I've learned is I can't sit back in my chair because it does this.
And it turns out that you can hear that on the recording.
So if I leave that when I'm speaking, very difficult to add out.
Hello, everyone.
And welcome to episode five of the Oxford podcast, a podcast about science fiction and SF fandom.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And we have a letter of comment this week from Claire Breiley of Croydon.
And one of the things she asks is, why do we always go John Allison Liz?
Alison and Liz, do you want to reveal the secrets behind the curtain?
It's because if we don't go John Allison Liz then.
Then Alison and I talk exactly the same time.
And every time we try and do it again, we again talk exactly the same time and dissolve in
Fitzgiggles and John Francis.
And says we have to do it again.
The beauty of having you record on separate tracks is actually that I can make it sound
like you didn't talk at the same time.
But yes, it does sound weird when you're listening to it lie.
Yeah, but Claire is very observant and noticed that we do this.
But yes, that is indeed the reason.
Claire also gave us some corrections.
So she noted that we got the fan fund bounty stuff.
Slightly wrong last week.
I did put that in the show notes because I realised I had done it wrong while I was talking about it.
But she noted that Fanac doesn't cover the Guff trip reports and sci-fi still does.
And their five years run from the date of the trip rather than from the date of winning the fund.
So that's good news for Alison.
Because the date of the trip may be five years after winning the fund.
Indeed.
The other thing that Claire mentioned is that she very carefully stores all of her Hugo
Fidalis pins together and knows precisely where they are, which is extremely organised.
Alison, do you have any relevant anecdotes about Hugo pins and the care they're off?
Well, I was thinking about the care of Hugo pins because I have a neighbour who makes giant
public artworks out of little mosaic tiles and she normally generates these tiles in big
community workshops and I've never quite managed to get to one of them.
These are beautiful and I will put a link to them on the show notes and you can be amazed.
They are exactly what public art should be like.
And in lockdown she worked, she started off being a bit depressed that she couldn't have
these big community workshops.
And then she realised that she could roll out a lot of tiny little mosaic tiles and put
them in boxes wet for local families to pick up and then stamp out the tiles using tools
they find around the house and then return them.
And I so I have stamped out a load of tiles and a load of things around the house that
are important to me and to my family, including one of my Hugo pins.
Claire is inert, it won't have done it any permanent damage.
It does have quite a bit of clay on it now, but you know, I think that'll be OK.
Not only do I not keep my Hugo pins carefully, but I did manage to find one so I thought
that was quite good and I will brush the clay off it.
But I also don't tend to look after them very well for which I'm sorry I know it's very
important and I should be very grateful of the pin.
My other Hugo-abusive note is that of course the very first thing I did after winning Hugo,
apart from brandishing it on a upper deck of a bus, was play ring toss with it.
Would you get a bus tour of London when you won a Hugo?
Like the cricket team?
We got a bus tour of Glasgow which is just as good.
It's amazing, I didn't know that.
We won the Hugo's at the SECC.
The party was somewhere else in Glasgow.
Was it in the party hotel in Glasgow?
It was in the party hotel and so we got driven by double deck of us.
So the plot to Cabal were on the top of the double deck of us waving air, Hugo's around
and and and George RR Martin was there waving his Hugo around.
And I asked him whether the next book was coming out which was probably very bad.
And the next book did come out but not the one after.
So you know, there we go.
And then we went to the Hugo party and it was full of authors and kind of a bit dreary
and so we came back to the fan lounge in the Motast Ex to the SECC which is really where
we should have been all along.
But we wouldn't have wanted to miss out on riding around on the top of the bus.
Obviously the population of Glasgow came out through Ticotay Patos.
No they did not.
But we had mentioned it.
Fair enough.
It was one of the best nights of my life I have to say.
I strongly recommend witty Hugo's.
I think I also played Ring Toss at the 2005 Worldcon.
I think I was standing kind of on the balcony around the lobby of the party hotel in Glasgow
who's now my have forgotten with a bunch of I think they were like glow sticks and trying
to throw them at people down in the lobby.
Didn't do that very long though.
I mean I think the glow sticks rings a bell because I was like well what will be using for
the rings and I think it was in fact glow stick.
So I think we must have had those little glow sticks that you clip together and push out.
Somebody who's a proper fan of history and is going to remember this is some detail and
write to us.
I suspect it will be what Claire Bradley have coidded.
Before we end the anecdote I should say I was throwing the glowing at someone who was
expecting me to throw the glowing at them not like completely random people standing
in the hotel lobby which would not be correct.
That's fair.
The other thing I remember from that night is that Corey Doctorow was like oh my god
can I hold your Hugo?
So that tells you approximately how old this anecdote is.
The Hugo is just a physical representation of things that actually matters which is the
acclimation of your friends and peers.
What we're interested in is validation emotionally.
We're not interested in physical artifacts a lot to the thought.
We are interested in emotional wellbeing.
So do tell us how marvellously podcast is because we really care about that.
Please, please tell us how great we are.
I will know also that I have highly materialistic so I do achieve my emotional wellbeing by
acquiring more things so that is a whole conflict of interest.
We should talk about Conzeland because since we last discussed Conzeland in any great detail
they have announced what it is they're doing for worldcon during the pandemic.
So they have a streaming partner which is the and this is a URL.
This is a band name which is watch.thefantasy.network, end of URL and they have a new pricing structure
which is £150 or they're about for an attending membership so approximately $200.
How do we feel about the fact that the Conzeland attending membership is roughly the same as
the discount 3 attending membership given the fact that one of those is not happening
in the real world but inside the space?
I don't think that's a fair comparison because the Conzeland attending membership is the actual
front up right up to the convention attending membership whereas the discount 3 one is going
to be a lot lower than the discount 3 membership will be this time next year.
So you're not quite comparing like to like but it is certainly not cheap and when I talked
last time about my experience of EasterCon being that I didn't go to any programming
and then partnered with my friends every night so it was almost exactly the same as a real
EasterCon and I drank too much ale.
So it was exactly the same as a real EasterCon apart from the fact that I ended up in my
own bed at home and didn't have to manage hotels and things but also nobody cooked me
enormous breakfast which was a bit of a shame.
I do wonder that for people like me who habitually don't attend a lot of the programme, I am
Conzeland accompanying my membership as the Guff delegate and I am extremely grateful
to them.
Thank you very much.
That is very kind of them and I will come along and of course I'll be on programme
and I will do programme-y things during the programme time.
We're going to talk a bit about Guff later but for people who aren't me but who are kind
of party type fans I do slightly wonder if the primary benefit of a WorldCon for you
is the socialisation structure, what it is that you get for your attending membership.
So they do say that as part of their collaboration with the Fancy Network that they're going
to try and have some as well as the panels and video they will also have networking and
late night hanging out and informal hangouts as well which I think they're right that is
like a key part of the WorldCon. You can't just put on some streams of panels and replicate
the WorldCon experience. You have to include some ways for people to hang out and network.
I think I'm quite pleased to see that they've got this partnership going because it sounds
like they've got some people who have really experienced doing sort of video on demand
and so it will be, I presume, all quite nicely done.
There won't be a lot of this.
Hello are we all on Zoom? Can you hear me?
Oh you're on mute, please unmute yourself. It will presumably work nicely which I think
is something worth paying for and maybe they have a really good way that they do sort of
informal hanging out and social spaces with their current membership.
But I do think that £150 is probably more than I want to pay for that experience.
That's fair. I think it must be very tricky if you're the Consi-land Committee because
I imagine that £150 is how much they need to charge to make this work and that is a
tricky thing to get past if you can't sell people on the value.
Obviously they haven't announced what they're doing in terms of the programming or any details
about the social spaces.
Last episode or perhaps episode before we were talking about how much you could attend
in terms of programming a day. I think Liz had been on a training course and found it
quite exhausting to do 8 hours of content in a single day virtually.
So lastly's first, how do you think you can do programming a world con over 5 days in
a way that won't be exhausting in a similar way?
Well I guess the question is what do people normally do at WorldCon because I think most
people do not go and do 8 hours of program on a regular WorldCon day and I think it'll
be much the same as I would do at WorldCon which is you might pop into one panel or two
panels that you really want to see and then you'll go and have learnt and then maybe
you'll intend to go to a panel but you'll end up hanging out in the bar instead and so
actually you'll go to maybe three or four panels or items and spend the rest of time
chatting to people.
I think there are a lot of people who do go to conventions and spend a lot of time in
the program literally 8 hours especially when they first get into fandom and do that
Gosh wow oh boy oh boy oh boy oh thing I think your first few conventions you do in fact
hit panels continuously I mean I still talk to people who have been around a few years
who sit there checking off things on a program book and going well I want to see all these
things I think even more than usual when the WorldCon program book comes out and people
see what's there I think you're going to get a lot of people wanting to go to a very
large number of sessions and I think at that point they'll get a flush of people joining
as they realise that they can actually see some very exciting people in environments where
they wouldn't necessarily otherwise see them.
There are other organisations that already have virtual events of this kind that are
very successful a lot of gaming and esports things do do virtual conventions and have
virtual access and they charge quite a lot of money for it and people are very happy
because they're not incurring the costs of a hotel and all your meals and your travel
so you get all of that experience of hearing your favourite authors talking to each other
but without any of the on costs and I think for a lot of people that is quite a good value
proposition and it will be fine and they will have a marvellous programme and people will
be amazed by that.
That's my gut feeling of that I don't know what they're actually planning to do.
I mean the other part is that I would usually spend some of that time hanging out in the
dealers room looking at things I can't afford to buy but I can replicate that online.
One thing they are actually planning to do is have a virtual dealers room and I know this
because I'm doing a little bit of the playtesting on being a virtual dealer which is coming up.
The other thing that Liz mentioned is the idea that you would go to a panel and then
end up talking to friends in the bar.
How do you replicate the experience of doing that in a virtual convention?
Do I either of you have any ideas?
I assume they have to try and replicate it but...
I have an idea based on Anna Raftery's trip report sessions which you can come and see
where we have been running the trip report sessions in Zoom and then having a bar session
afterwards.
What you could do for the worldcon, and I don't know whether they've got this planned
but I am offering it to them as a suggestion, is after each event you could then have a
break into the bar that then breaks into smaller groups so that people can have sensible conversations
and you could just make that part of what you do for every single item because that's
how real conventions work.
People have an item and then they go off and chat about it in the bar with their mates
or people that haven't met yet.
So I was looking a bit more at the fancy network team who will be assisting, I think,
or running or whatever with Consilend and they have things like they have a Discord channel,
they do stuff over Twitch where there will be, you know, you can watch the chat and watch
the item at the same time.
So I think it won't just be, we all sit and watch Zoom.
It might be sort of interactive and we are chatting at the same time and then we can go
on Discord and form a channel to chat about whatever subject we want to later on.
You know, you could even have Discord channels which are going to be okay, so this is Alison's
party room and everyone who wants a party with Alison and her friends this evening can
go in Alison's party room.
I mean, there will be some issues because normally this is not kind of completely open
to everyone.
You know, sometimes you go and sit in the bar and have a conversation with friends and
that doesn't necessarily mean that everyone in the convention is going to walk up and
join that conversation with you and your friends.
And so I don't know quite how you manage those sort of social spaces which are not kind of
public to everyone but people can kind of wander in and out.
But it does seem like they've got a good handle on the sort of tools that might help
them do that.
I think Alison's right that the Anna model will work very well, kind of laying people
break into social groups after panels.
My concern I think is firstly that means you have to go to panels in order to enjoy
the social space which is a slight change from how conventions are normally structured.
And secondly, I think that it does mean that there's no equivalent to wandering through
the bar and spotting someone you want to talk to if that makes sense.
If you don't see someone in the same panels as you, you're not going to bump into them.
For the virtual first Thursday meetings I've done, I've experimented or I am experimenting
with streaming the list of who is in the bar to Twitch so that when people come into the
room they can go, who's in the bar already?
Oh, there's these tables and they've got these people at them.
Now, if you can't do that for a Worldcon, I mean you can do it to some extent but you
can't really do it for a Worldcon because we have a load of people at Worldcon so if
you did that they would kind of do the virtual equivalent of turning their badge around.
You know, they don't want random fans to be able to come up and talk to them quite all
the time or much of the time because they would be mopped.
And at that point you could have people say, "Oh, and if you don't want to be on the list
of who's in the bar so people can't see that you're there, let me know and I'll make sure
your name's not on that list."
So we've got some scope for, but it's still a very blunt hammer compared with the joy
of being able to go through a bar and see people you want to talk to but it's quite a
refined hammer compared with the not joy of being able to go through a bar and discovering
those 200 people in it and not being able to see the people you want to talk to because
it's too crowded.
Ooh, and I don't know if this is secret but one of the people I've been talking about
because I went to a very big meeting on this exact subject yesterday with Smoughs.
So just to know that the British term for Smoughs is con runners which is an unimaginative
but descriptive word.
One of the things I did discuss is I spent some time talking to Stephen Silver about the
plazities got for running social spaces at the Nebula weekend and I think we should very
much watch that and see how that works because I think that'll be a very interesting lesson
for the community about what works.
I will say that the Nebula conference apparently is $150 so maybe £150 is the right price
point for these things.
Maybe that's just how much it costs.
I didn't realise that.
I'm still excited about Cozziella and I think we're at that difficult point where we know
that it's going to be strange but we don't know all the ways it's going to be good yet.
If you were already planning to go to Conzeland, this will, instead of looking like a very expensive
thing to those obviously weren't planning to go, will look like a bargain way of being
able to maintain your plans in light of everything that's happening.
I think there are also a lot of Americans who always go to the Worldcon but could not
manage the costs for Conzeland particularly having been to Ireland last year and those
people will now for $200 be able to get as much of their Worldcon experience as is available
this year.
Yes.
My last thoughts on pricing are one that we don't know how much money Conzeland basically
has already spent and cannot recoup so we don't know how much of the money they've
already taken in is basically lost on preparation and payments for the physical spaces that
they then can't use.
I will say the other point though is that a virtual Worldcon could be a really good
opportunity to bring in new members who actually never get to go to a Worldcon in person because
they live in places where there are never Worldcons and maybe giving them the virtual
experience.
They might then consider coming to a Worldcon because they've managed to get a taste of
the experience and enjoyed it but I think 150 pounds is going to be too much for the
people who might join on a whim.
So I wonder if they might consider having a sort of first Worldcon membership for this
streaming membership.
That touches on something that you mentioned in a previous episode which was you pointed
out when I was talking about professional conferences that virtually attending a professional
conference is a very good way of lowering barriers to entry to less wealthy people generally.
I think that is actually a really good thing to bear in mind is that this could be a huge
leveler and that as three relatively wealthy middle class white British people we perhaps
are not the people who can't go to Worldcon because of various circumstances.
I don't want to go into passive details about my finances but if I decide to go to a Worldcon
I can save up and I can go to a Worldcon that's fine.
But there are so many people for whom that is a statement that sounds insane but I sometimes
forget parts of my privilege and I am always very grateful when other people remind me
of those parts before I make a giant fool of myself.
I think I'm something like in the 95th percentile on world income scales or maybe a bit higher
and I could not possibly have imagined ever going to the New Zealand Worldcon on my own
time.
So yes we could theoretically save up and do it but you know not not ad eat.
I considered it but I am basically halfway there already and that's the way it would
be feasible.
So for me it's like considering a trip to Europe except a bit more expensive because
New Zealand is harder to get to but that kind of thing.
I am in a similar situation where the reason I did not want to go to New Zealand was because
I couldn't afford it but part of that was because I was planning to go to Disney World
so it's not really a sob story in any meaningful sense.
Except you didn't get to go to Disney World either.
No this is this is now that is a sob story.
I'm not going to get my lightsaber Alison my lightsaber.
I knew it was a life saver I was getting because if you play sorry huge digression if
you play Jedi Fallen Order they used the same lightsaber parts as you get in Galaxy Edge
so I had built the lightsaber I was going to buy in Galaxy's Edge in Fallen Order and
I knew which crystals I was going to have and I was so excited and now yeah.
Done there is a potential silver lining to this which is that I am also not going to
Disney World this year so maybe we could go to Disney World at some point in the future
at the same time.
The listeners cannot see the excited head motions I am making but you can see you know
how excited I am.
So the last thing I want to ask you about New Zealand is as far as I know Conzeland haven't
yet announced what time zone they're planning to run their program in.
We've speculated previously that they would probably pick a time zone that would favour
New Zealanders and US fans but do either of you have any thoughts about what makes sense
in that regard and have any of you heard anything about what they might be planning
to do?
I have not heard anything about what they might be planning to do.
I think it makes sense to prioritise New Zealanders first and then what time zone will
allow the maximum number of your members to attend.
I resigned to this as it means I would probably be able to attend really weirdly timed things
like possibly parties at 7am my time and the hugos at lunch time or something like that
but that's just going to happen.
My understanding is that we should be getting an announcement on this quite soon.
There's been obviously as you can imagine quite a lot of thinking and working around
the issue but I understand that that's coming to a conclusion and you should expect to be
resolved and they're going to try and make a decision that works the best for Conzeland
and for their members.
So I think we're still expecting a lot of announcements for New Zealand and there's
a lot of work going on to work out exactly what these will be but I think things are
happening and I think fairly soon the white smoke will go up.
You expect the water to go up?
We're electing a new Pope of all World Conz.
Yeah hey.
Space Pope.
I've had for Vince Dockety.
Vince would pull off the robes.
But I mean we're obviously not world conch-airs because you know there are some things that
you don't do if you've got any sense at all.
Because you and Liz haven't had time to do that yet and I'm not stupid enough.
No no no seriously I wasn't about to say you and Liz probably still have that as a plan
but I'm not stupid enough.
Imagine a world conch-aired by me and John.
I'm imagining it's so hard Liz.
I will not even imagine it.
I will give you £10 to pre-support it right now.
Oh man.
All you need to do is pick a year.
I'm going to go for a 2150 on the basis that if I am still alive I'll presumably be wise
enough to do it by then.
You'll be in a vat.
Liz ever going to chair a world con?
No.
She did not deny as fast as either of us did.
I thought that there might be like I can see coming back to this in like 25 years or
something when I do chair a world con and someone digs this sound by and goes ha ha
so I thought should I hedge a bit but then I'm like no I'm not going to chair a world
con I'm going to say no.
I would strongly recommend not bothering about that because if you did chair a world con
you go yeah well people change and if you don't deny it very firmly all the time then
you will find yourself chairing a world con that is how it works.
I think we are following and actually we have sufficient people who want to chair world
cons right now and I also think chairing a world con is maybe a full time job at this
point and I already have a full time job and of course my part time podcasting hobby.
That's exactly it.
We do have a circuit of people who want to chair a world con and rather to few who want
to do all the work.
Yes.
I'd love to chair a world con if someone else would do all the work.
You heard it here first.
On the subject of time zones Alison you have an itinerary for your guff trip.
Do you want to talk to us about that?
I do.
I was originally planning to not fly directly.
I'm going to do the entire experience virtually and I think I might have trailed this last
time but I hadn't really set any of it up when we were talking before.
So now I have a Facebook group it's called something like Alice in the Scots virtual guff
trip that will probably find it for you.
If you are interested you can join and help me plan it.
If you're not on Facebook then get in touch and I will send you the stuff and you could
also give me your thoughts.
I'm particularly interested in people in Australia and New Zealand.
I am planning to do stopovers.
I was originally only going to do one on the way back because my logic was that I would
be flying non- I would be not flying non-stop from Heathrow to Perth as that is now not
possible but if it were possible that would be how I would be flying.
Now the west coast of the US people have said well why can't you do a stopover on the west
coast of the US and I'm hoping to organise a stopover in the other direction in either
Shanghai or Japan.
So it's practically around the world tour at this point.
Thailand!
Stop in Thailand you very rarely get to speak to Liz.
It's not occurred to me to stop in Thailand and I'd like to say well Pete Young is also
in Thailand but of course Pete Young is actually holed up in Stoke so not in Thailand at all.
How hot is it where you are Liz?
It's been in the high 30s.
Yes, okay so that's one of the nice things about going on a virtual guff trip is that
it will not be that hot.
The other nice thing is that because it's going to be summer in the UK and winter in
New Zealand.
New Zealand's 11 hours ahead of us rather than 13 hours ahead of us which I think would
be quite a bit worse in terms of managing it.
But I am going to go on to Australian, first Australian time and then New Zealand time
for three weeks.
I'm going to get one of the other sort of face masks, the one you wear on a plane that
covers your eyes so that you can sleep in your very light bedroom in the middle of the
day and go on to the night shift for three weeks and hopefully meet lots of Australian
fans.
I'm planning, I've definitely got plans for Perth, Melbourne, Canberra, Sydney, Adelaide,
Hobart, Wellington in all ready.
So I'm definitely going to go to lots of bits of Australia virtually and see their local
attractions virtually and hopefully I asked for ideas for cooking the local food and everyone
comes back with junk food.
I think the only actual plausible recipe that's not either this is an interesting sort of biscuit
that you can probably get hold of or roast kangaroo is chicken parme giana which apparently
is an Australian specialty.
So I will have some of that but in the near future I'm going to have the Middlesbrough equivalent
of chicken parme giana which is called a parmo and it's where you get some chicken, you
flatten it, you breadcrumb it, you whack some Besshamel sauce and some cheddar on it and
then you put toppings on it like it's a pizza and it comes in a giant box.
And that is the Middlesbrough equivalent of the Australian delicacy you have just outlined
and there is a place that delivers them now in Southampton.
Oh yes, but if you go anywhere in London that does parmose you might be able to get a sort
of British take on it delivered.
Authentic one, yeah that sounds really good.
I mean because delivery food is definitely an option here and in general I'm getting
Australian wine and beer delivered seems like part of the plan as well.
So it's coming all nicely and I have quite a lot of people are coming up with some quite
nice things.
There's some questions about how we're going to get some famously reclusive Australian
fans to try zoom or discord or some other video conferencing solution of their choice.
But it's quite interesting because it turns out that my trip, I'm doing three weeks plus
travel, it's quite full even despite the fact that I'm not going anywhere and it really
brings home how difficult it must be to plan a fan fun trip and not die in the attempt.
No it is, I remember planning my fan fun trip, I did it when I was in my final year
of my undergrad degree and I did it very much as an undergraduate as I mentioned on
Anna's trip report but I think my entire month long trip clocked in at something like 1200
pounds.
I'm going to spend more than that.
Yeah I should have spent more than that.
I was going to spend more than that.
Even virtually.
Ha ha!
No I did it really.
I took the absolute cheapest flights I possibly could at every juncture and I was bewilderingly
frugal.
We should bully Liz into running for guff.
Liz, rather guff, comes to England from Thailand.
Is that a good guff trip?
Ha ha ha!
I do not think Thailand falls under the remit of guff, John.
I'm not sure if I need to send you a map with some scribbles on it to explain where
countries are but it is not in fact in Australia or New Zealand.
So I'm torn here because obviously I could just look at a map but equally the notion
of receiving mail from Thailand that is just Liz annotating maps of the world being like
Australia, Arrow, not Australia, Arrow.
That would be, I would not say no Liz.
That would be a great way for a good year.
Liz, are you near or further from here than you are from Australia?
I am closer to Australia I believe, I'm about the same distance between the UK and New Zealand.
I'm not entirely sure on that.
Yeah, so only really half way.
Yeah, I am really sort of half way.
I did look up how long it would take me to go to New Zealand for the Worldcon thinking
oh, I must be like most of the way there.
No, it's still a very long trip.
So I don't want to be too dramatic with fan funds.
People can run for fan funds if they think they should run for a fan fund.
But I do think there's something nice about having fan fund delegates who have not otherwise
visited the place or maybe visited the place once a very long time ago for a short while
and are now getting to do something without the fan funds would not be a practical journey
for them.
I don't want to say it's a requirement or anything like that because it clearly isn't
and shouldn't be.
One of the things I think about when voting is how much would I not expect to be able
to see this person otherwise?
Yes, I don't think John was entirely serious that I should run for a fan fund.
But I would not consider running for a fan fund unless I was living in one of the places
in the fan fund.
Anyone would like to start a fan fund to just send people to come and visit me?
That's fine and I will take them out and show them around.
But I think that's called a holiday fund.
When I was still enthusiastic and young, me and Claire talked about doing a fan fund
called OOF which would be the out of the ordinary fan fund for conventions which were
not in traditionally served countries.
I don't know if you remember when Chris O'Shea went to Japan, he won jets which was a one
off fan fund.
But I thought it'd be funny to have a fan fund called OOF.
What was he going to do a trip report?
No, of course not.
So we've talked about Alison's guff trip.
Is there anything else you want to say about it apart from come to Thailand and I'll show
you around?
Well I think we should when you're visiting Liz on your stopover in Asia on your way back.
I could stop over everywhere in Asia on my way back from Australia all in the same day
couldn't I?
Yeah but we should do a live recording of your stopover in this house and we should let
people ask questions about your trip and that would be fantastic.
And I'll be in Thai time so when would suit you Liz?
Well now it's fine it's a thing.
Oh okay what time is it there?
Like tea time.
730.
Yeah okay so that's what we'll do.
Well yeah we can.
Alright we'll do a virtual guff.
I'm not sure what it won't be Sunday though that's my problem it's going to be mid week
so.
That's fine we will we will cope.
I'll get it to the diary because I think a live octa thought from Thailand.
Now we discuss staying sane in the apocalypse for a few minutes before we clock off.
We're expecting some slight lockdown reductions today but I don't think they're going to be
very specific I think most things are going to be you'll be allowed to go out to exercise
more than once a day if you're a very enthusiastic jimbani.
But otherwise it is much of the same we hoped we would have a podcasting studio in our back
room and that's not work quite as well.
In fact we found that we're struggling to get internet across our whole house and it
seems to be because our internet provider is struggling to put as much internet as it
is contractually obligated to into the street as everybody in the world uses all of their
internet all the time and this has been getting steadily worse over the period as people have
managed to train their elderly relatives in using video conferencing and all those years
that they said people don't need as much upload as they have download that turned out to be
wrong didn't it boys and girls so but otherwise I'm much less in set because I was quite insane
last time and I've cheered up quite a bit since then.
That's good.
England is currently having kind of the world's worst outbreak which is strange and not necessarily
what we expected so that's quite bad that might improve.
I am playing a play by post game of the Arkham horror board game where a man who lives not
far from me has set up a board in the room with his piano in it and he records YouTube
videos every night of what happened and then the next day we tell him what we want our
characters to do and he does it and then he we sent him photographs of the dice that we
have rolled and then he does another YouTube video explaining what happened and we continue
on like that which is an incredibly surreal thing that I never would have thought to do
before I wasn't allowed out of my house but it is strangely soothing it is very nice and
relaxing and a wonderful way to play board games so I recommend making friends with someone
who has a board game permanently set up in their house and sends you YouTube videos of
how it's going this may not be as broadly applicable as previous episodes have been.
Alternatively I can highly recommend playing board games with people on tabletop simulator
as John and I have been playing board games on tabletop simulator and it is extremely
funny because John has played all the scenarios before and so when we have to make a very
important decision like should we read the neponomicon and keep it submittent knowledge
or should we destroy it I can see John on the video sitting there trying very hard not
to influence us to do the sensible thing you should destroy it and never I mean I think
I haven't played this game but I'm 99% certain that's the correct answer.
The correct answer was destroy the nekonomicon and we did destroy the nekonomicon.
The problem is that there are arguments for and against Liz and I know what those arguments
are I know I know what happens if you pick either one I cannot confirm nor deny that you
picked the right option.
Which is good for if you want to play it again.
Alright we are pretty sure that destroying an ekonomicon was the correct thing to do.
But I am also like allowed to leave the house and things because we're in phase one of
lifting restrictions so I mean we never had I think quite such a strict lockdown as the
UK did but we are sort of back to you can work 50/50 in the office so try and keep the
office 50% empty restaurants are reopening with quite a lot of restrictions on seating
distances and things like that handful of other things have opened like parks and golf courses
and if all goes well at the end of next week we might go on to the next phase so I may not
need these coping measures for all that long although I'm still working from home pretty
much full time.
I've observed that we start off buying a little bit of cheese the amount of cheese we
would normally buy.
Gradually as the lockdown has extended we've started to buy more and more cheese so each
week a greater proportion of the food we eat is cheese and a greater proportion of the
meals that we eat are formed of going oh nobody really fancies cooking I'll just eat
some cheese.
I have been doing some jigsaw's we still have we have kind of a jigsaw transfer network
round the covid mutual aid group now so all the jigsaw's are getting passed around which
is good because the street value of jigsaw's is treble in the last two months.
If you have any mecholism for selling jigsaw's I would recommend that.
I've also noticed as well as my cheese intake going up my beer intake is going up gradually
that as I've worked out more and better ways to socialise online I find I'm doing it more
and therefore I'm it's more effective and therefore I drink more beer.
My daughter said sadly yesterday but there's so much theatre we'd never normally go to
the theatre every week and and yet there are all these theatre things they come on every
week they only last for a few days and so yes lots of theatre lots of highbrow entertainment
is being provided for our enjoyment.
My part of my staying stay in the apocalypse is that I have bought a new microphone and
the microphone has not appeared I have not been charged for the microphone I don't know
what I will be charged for the microphone I don't know how to cancel the microphone it's
all very stressful because I found out that Argos sells this microphone and buying directly
from the manufacturer might have been worse than buying from Argos which seems backwards
to me.
One of the things that people don't always know is that if Argos has the thing in stock
and will get it to you they are often the very best option for getting your thing especially
if it's kind of a small electrical thing because they they just kind of bring it right
round and you can also they also do click and collect from Sainsbury's so I would click
and collect from Sainsbury's I think I assume that still works at the moment.
Yeah it does there has been some discussion about whether it should work.
There is massive tension at the moment between the people who don't want the economy to
collapse and the people who don't want everyone to die of the plague.
You know fair but the people who don't want the economy to collapse are like Argos has
all these sites in supermarkets which means it got a huge benefit over every other retail
stop because it had to shut its main retail sites but it could continue to operate its
entire business through these click and collect sites and says and then the people who wanted
the economy to survive went well actually that's okay we do not want the economy to
collapse so letting people making it possible for people to buy manufacturing goods is no
bad.
Yeah I think I'm not going mad but I am ordering a lot online.
When you do get your microphone from Sainsbury's you will also have to buy your groceries.
Oh yes sorry I should clarify we have the largest Sainsbury's in my city is a five minute
walk up the road and so I do my grocery shopping there used to do it all the way back from
work whenever we needed bits now we'll do it every two weeks in Giganto shops which I
am still not really used to and the sticker shock of spending two weeks where the groceries
in one go is still a little bit like what is that really how much spending yes it is
especially if you call cats.
You should try having four adults in the house.
I don't think I should try that Alison.
I think I think two adults and two cats.
And a very big hang of cheese.
On the subject of that we've been drinking much more beer.
We are ordering six pints a week from the pub across the road.
Before lockdown we never used to drink that much beer in the pub across the road but now
we do.
One of the ways I'm staying sane and the apocalypse is to play board games with members of my
own household.
I have been doing that as well.
Because I grew some so that is the upside of having children and then waiting 20 years
is that you can then play board games with them in lockdown.
I actually logged my 800th board game yesterday or my 800th play yesterday which was a game
of Arkham Horror of the card game with my lovely wife.
We got our asses handed to us in the carnival in Venice.
That was very embarrassing.
It turns out that I did not have the ability to kill enough cultists and that was a problem.
But yes I've also been playing a lot of games with this band yet and also watching a lot
of movies with this band yet.
And also Animal Crossing and I posted a very adorable picture to Facebook of a kitchen.
We basically designed an entire Animal Crossing kitchen and then we filled it up with turnips
because one of the features of Animal Crossing is that you end up with a lot of turnips in
your home.
And said oh I'm having trouble with my veg box does anyone have any ideas on what you can
do with turnips.
And one person accurately identified that the answer was sell them for a fat profit on
Wednesday afternoons.
And everybody else gave me ideas for using turnips.
In fact they were obviously cartoon turnips on the floor of a cartoon kitchen.
Marianne, my daughter is in her final term at Oxford and had a large not quite thesis
to hand in.
And this is obviously been a source of stress in her household and it was due at noon on
Thursday.
And at 11.52 on Thursday she uploaded it and got the confirmation thing to say.
It was great and we were like oh that's lovely darling, well done you can relax now.
And she was like no we only have eight minutes to sell our turnips because there is a stock
marketed Animal Crossing where you sell turnips at a high price if you don't sell them with
a week they rot and you have a pile of rotten turnips.
So you use turnip price predictor apps on the internet to tell you how much your turnips
will sell for.
And so the eight minutes after her getting her essay in for the deadline while we were
trying to get roomfuls of turnips sold before the bell rang at noon was much more stressful
than any part of the preceding two hours of exactly what format does this need to be
and how do the citations need to be.
But the essay has gone in and I made half a million bells selling turnips.
Yay, excellent.
So that's probably more than you want to know about Animal Crossing.
The world's an odd place.
It's not just me the Financial Times had a long article about Animal Crossing and the
Bank of Animal Crossing and the steps that have been taken to avoid cheats in Animal Crossing
and the virtual turnip market that I've just described to you.
And it was played not for laughs at all really it basically said it was obviously a funny
article but it wasn't April Fools because I checked repeatedly they just thought that
it would be funny to have an article about turnip trading at Animal Crossing in the middle
of the F.T. because people need that sort of thing these days.
Thanks everyone for listening to the fifth episode of the OctaThought podcast.
We will see you in a fortnight's time but for now it's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
The music used in this episode was Pamfer for Space by Kevin MacLeod at Incompetech.com
licensed under a Creative Commons BY 3.0 license.
Yeah that's a wrap.
Now of course there is the after show thing so...
I have spent lots on Arkham Horror.
I'd be surprised.
It must be about 700 or 800 pounds.
Isn't that quite a lot of money?
That's alright.
That's why I can't go to New Zealand Alison because I've spent it all on board games.
No no no no no it's not quite a lot of money for a board game because I was thinking about
whether we wanted to buy Gloomhaven and it seemed like quite a lot of money for a board
game.
Gloomhaven is quite a lot of money.
So my answer is it depends what you think a lot of money is and I don't know whether
that makes sense.
How do you manage to spend so Gloomhaven may or may not be value for money.
So Gloomhaven is almost certainly value...
The differentiation is between expense and value.
So Gloomhaven is 120 quid which is quite a lot of money.
If you buy Gloomhaven you will almost certainly play it for at least 120 hours which means
it's probably cheaper per hour of entertainment than a book or a movie or a video game.
Okay so will we is the question?
Will my family actually get a together to play it?
That is very much a question for you and your play group.
So we have some other cooperative games and we were going to go well we're going to play
some of those and see if we play them enough to make Gloomhaven worthwhile.
But if Gloomhaven is just majestically better than those.
I have controversial opinions about Gloomhaven I think it is okay.
I don't understand why it's the top of the board game geek rankings.
It just makes no sense at all to me.
It is a competently done dungeon crawler with a relatively minimal layer of narrative on
top.
So that is your bag.
You'll probably really like it.
If that is not your bag you might not want.
It is available on Tabletop Simulator in a version which is sanctioned by the designer.
So if you want to know whether it is your cup of tea you could play through the TTS mod.
The only thing I will say is that I personally feel like when you're playing a TTS mod you
have to bear in mind that it is probably more clunky than playing the actual game because
well just playing board games on virtualids phases tends to be a little bit less tactile
and less good.
But as long as you bear that in mind it is a good way of trying it out.
In terms of Arkham Horror so buying the base set is the equivalent of the way that it works
is that you can buy expansions which are big ish boxes which cost about 25 quid and then
you can buy smaller packs of cards which are called mythos packs which run you about
12 quid.
And if you buy one of these big boxes and the six associated small boxes that is a single
story told over 8 scenarios of a campaign.
So to do that runs you somewhere in the region of 100 pounds to buy like one 8 scenario campaign.
What I will say is that is 100 pounds but so far I have with the one that I spent 100
pounds on which is the first one they did was the Dunich legacy.
I played that once through with my wife and my friend Michael and playing it once through
with Liz and Hog and Ian and I play it once through my friend Ian.
So by the time I have gotten my play out of that for the foreseeable future I would
play through it three times and if you say each game is somewhere in the region of 90
minutes to 2.5 hours that means that I have spent about 60 hours 50 to 60 hours playing
it which works out about 2000 hours and that doesn't include the fun my friends have had
with it.
So that is back to this general question about with any investment purchase will you actually
play it.
That is the problem we have with the family because although I say we play board games
with the family we don't actually do that that much we do play a lot of video games
together but we don't play an enormous number of board games although we all like board games
in degree we should do it more.
I think if you are trying to get into playing board games I would set yourself like a there
is a thing called a 10 by 10 challenge which is when you play 10 board games 10 times over
the course of a year and if you have got 10 board games in your collection already that
you like I would I would set yourself one of those and try to get the habit before splashing
a huge amount of cash on something that's heavily scenario based.
The other thing I would say is if you're looking for a game to play cooperatively over
a series of sessions it's my impression the pandemic legacy is a bit more accessible than
Gloomhaven it's certainly half the price the only problem is you only get to play it 12
to 24 times.
Yeah I'm not playing any game on a pandemic theme this year.
That's fair.
Is that not reasonable?
I mean I know I think that's absolutely reasonable.
The thing I would say about Arkham is you can buy the base set for the acquit and if
you hate it you can sell it for 20 quid and then you're 10 quid in the whole and that's
not that bad.
If you buy Gloomhaven you don't like it it's potentially a lot more money that you've
thrown down a drain.
Yeah though you can buy a reusable sticker pack so one of the options for Gloomhaven
is to buy it and it's reusable sticker pack so you do not in fact mark up your game permanently.
So I'm not sure how practical that is anyway.
I'm on hold with the Help Center it's very annoying and I have no Mexican food.
Who?
Who named three condos in the same area with very similar names?
Thailand.
Is that helpful?
Is that what you needed John?
Yeah I could have added that.
Something hopefully anyway.