John there appears to be a cow in your room somewhere.
He said "Boo not Moo".
It's all sort of sheep really b-b-b-b-b.
So in this episode John makes animal noises.
Meh.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 102nd episode of Octa Thorpe,
a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom,
which is coming to you on the 1st of February 2024.
I'm John Coxin.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
Glasgow have opened their hotel bookings and Hugo nominations processes.
That is just a public service announcement.
You also might not have got an email because they've had
continuing problems with actually getting emails out to people.
So lots of people say that their Glasgow emails are going into
into holes.
If this has happened to you obviously check your spam,
but also all of the information is on their website and their Facebook page.
So they have got it out in other routes.
Yeah, I never got an email about hotel booking opening,
but I did get the Hugo email twice.
Yeah, I am getting most of the emails two or three times.
So that's, I guess that's good.
It's better to receive an email twice than none.
Yeah, I mean, it's a good job that I am paying attention to their other social media,
because otherwise I would not have known like hotel bookings are open.
I mean, I'm staff, so I was all right, fine.
And also on hotel bookings, and indeed this happened to me and I forgot to mention it.
When I tried to book, there were only bookings available for double rooms.
So if you needed a single or a twin in many of the hotels,
you had to book a double and then go talk to the convention booking people.
And I think that is still the case in some circumstances.
So if you go and look at your hotel and they have doubles,
but they don't have other sorts of rooms, do try that.
I assume there were no single rooms, to be honest.
I assume everything is just like a double book for single occupancy,
for which you do get like a fiver off.
I think that's right.
But there are twins.
And they may not be twins now, because twin is, we are,
we use a lot more twin rooms than the general public.
So there's often a shortage of twins.
[Music]
And we have some letters of comment.
Christopher J Garcia wrote in to say, "I win victory!"
So yes, yes he does.
And he says he is hoping to be at Worldcom.
But who knows with this crazy world?
I don't, I don't know, with this crazy world, Chris.
That's the short answer.
So yes.
But yeah, thank you very much for writing in Chris.
Chris also spends an unreasonable amount of time
staring at the OctoThought logo,
which I very much appreciate.
Anyone who is a fan artist appreciates it whenever anyone spends
lots and lots of time staring at a piece of art, what they did.
It makes you feel like Michelangelo or something.
And the campaign to get the OctoThought logo painted on the Vatican starts here.
Sistid chapels due for an overhaul, right?
Anything else or Chris or shall we move along?
I think I am still technically a member of the Catholic Church,
but maybe that's the sort of thing for which they would excommunicate you.
So we had a fantastic letter of comment from Bill Higgins,
who listened to our episode where we played if we ran the Zucom.
And we said, "If you have been in any of these scenarios,
please write to us."
And Bill said, "I know what this scenario is."
So Bill knows who the 12 year old in the games room was.
And we'll link to his Wikipedia page in the show notes.
But you know, Bill says he went to a convention,
WindyCon in 1978 and shared a room with friends who'd brought along a new student
called Dallas Eggbutt.
And he doesn't remember a lot about his conversations with him, but he seemed nice.
And then it turned out in 1979 that Dallas Eggbutt had disappeared from campus,
that he was possibly a troubled genius, 16 year old studying computer science.
He was a big fan of D and D,
and maybe he was hiding in the labyrinth of steam tunnels below the campus.
Apparently he was missing from months.
This parents did indeed hire a private detective who wrote a book about the disappearance,
and this turned into lots of newspapers and TVs,
trying to explain D and D and why it might be the sinister mystery
and why this teenager had gone missing.
Yeah, and the detective did in fact send people to look for him at the Nastvik in Louisville.
I remember this story in real time because when it happened,
it was the thing that took D and D for being a weird cult game that only a very few people played,
something that enormous numbers of people played.
It was fantastic publicity for the hobby, even as people were going,
"Oh, it's all a tool of Satanism."
Yes, and I knew that there were rumors about D and D as a tool of Satanism,
and I mean, it's plot point in "Strainty Things," but I didn't know the exact reason why,
or that it overlapped with this particular scenario.
So, yeah, it was really interesting, and you can in fact get this private detective's book
still on Kindle for about three quid, so I might have to pick it up and read it and find out more.
It was brilliant to just get a letter saying,
"We were kind of like, 'If you have been in these scenarios, let us know.'"
And I thought we were going to hear about like the snake that was in ops,
but no, we heard about one of the other scenarios,
so thank you very much Bill for writing in.
More letters like that, please.
We also heard from Raj on Mastodon, who said that he was sorry that putting.cool
doesn't contain delicious desserts, but he was losing a chunk of time browsing the articles,
and he also wrote in with the things he enjoyed from 2023.
If you read, consumed, listened to other things in 2023, please continue to send them in,
because we will discuss them on a future episode.
But thank you very much for sending them in, Raj.
We had a letter from Colin Murtar, a long-time listener, first-time writer,
who wrote to say that as we knew, but probably didn't mention last time,
poor things has been made with the absolute love and support of the Alistair Gray Archive,
so although it isn't set in Glasgow, it is absolutely a wash with Alistair Gray features,
and is a very faithful rendition of the book, I understand, and also says that they loved,
"Why don't you love me?" but when it came out in her back, went all over Manchester trying to buy
a copy and couldn't find one. Oh, and every comic shop in Liverpool, and every comic shop in Manchester,
even after the book had been spotlighted in the Observer, that's possibly why the,
as a result of the book being spotlighted in the Observer Colin, and indeed also mentions ducks by
Kate Biesen, and says these important works aren't necessarily picked up and supported by comic
shops, which I think comic shops can't do everything. It's quite a hard business running a comic shop,
possibly a lot of people who go to comic shops aren't really interested in actual novels in graphic
novel form. I don't know. I have been lent a copy. I think I read the copy of Friend of the Show,
Alex Ingram, who also sent us a letter about "Why don't you love me?" saying it was originally
published in Aces Weekly. Yes, Colin also read it on the website as it was coming out,
so I was wrong when I said I didn't think it would be published that way. It obviously had.
Yeah, so Aces Weekly is the online magazine from David Lloyd, so it was originally designed for
screen, not for printing. And I don't know if that means it's not eligible for a Hugo, because it
was previously published. No, the way it works is that if it was never previously nominated,
it's nominated and the year it's collected. That's why Wheel of Time was nominated as a
compilation when it was, because none of the previous installments had been nominated separately.
I think so, but comics can be weird about when an arc is deemed to have ended, can't I?
Until there was for Scholstitution, Liz. It's not like we're going to be doing that at all this week.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no,
bad, Liz. I can't believe I don't have it open already, to be honest.
Shall I quote the bit of the Constitution? Oh yeah. Best graphic story or comic, any non-interactive
science fiction or fantasy story told in graphic form appearing for the first time in the previous
calendar year? That's the same wording as novel, right? Now, best novel just says a science fiction
or fantasy story of 40,000 words and more. It doesn't have that appearing for the previous time in the
first calendar year, but weirdly. Well, all right, let me let me let me reconstitute my argument.
DIGA was eligible as a single work. Oh yeah, fairies. I mean, I think we always nominate graphic
novels in the year the graphic novel comes out, yeah, rather than all the time it appeared on the web
individually, I think. It would be interesting to have a look at this in future, though, that is,
I didn't realize I just assumed comic was the same wording as novel, but with comic instead of novel,
and it is interesting that it's not. I can't remember if you've kind of, this has been treated
as weirdness of if like, you know, the comic with six issues and the last one comes out in November
of one year and the collection comes out in February or whatever. Ah. Karen said this,
congratulations on our 100th episode. Thank you very much, Karen. Thanks, Karen. And says,
have I mentioned that I host a little free puzzle exchange on my front porch? It's a great way to
play catch and release. And that is, I assume, jigsaw puzzles, because we know from past that
Karen likes jigsaw puzzles. He said it's a photo which we might stick in the chapter or maybe.
I think it is jigsaw puzzles because if you zoom in on the picture, it's a picture of lots of jigsaw
puzzles. It is indeed. And, and the thing about this is that jigsaw puzzles is a great way to do
this because in fact, my WhatsApp group passes jigsaw puzzles around at great rates because
lots and lots and lots and lots of people like jigsaw puzzles. My jigsaw brings all the boys to
the yard and they're like, it's better than yours. We've told you about wrapping and singing on the
podcast before, Sean. I am a little bit sad for reasons that will become clear. I can't prolong
this. I told you so as much as I would like. But we had from various people on the subject to Pico
Con. Basically, it turns out that at the time we recorded Pico Con was not set in stone. It is
now set in stone. I did put a pick up in the show notes with the date. But yeah, so we heard
from a couple of people who basically said when they were at university, the bookings for the
Student Union space didn't open until after Christmas. And so it may be that that is true for Pico Con.
The only, the only actual primary source we have is Exeter University. Thank you very much to
Jersey Griffin and Freudian. And then also Edward Moreland wrote in to disagree with me.
So Edward says he feels like tears of the kingdom is going to lose out to Baldur's Gate 3.
And I had not considered that possibility. But a lot of other people have also said that to me
Edward. So I think you're in good company with that opinion. It will be interesting to see which
one wins. Also, I hope it means I get a free copy of Baldur's Gate 3. Come on Hugo Verpaket.
Probably not. It depends who's doing the Hugo Verpaket and whether they're prepared to spend
a vast amount of time currying favor with games companies like I did for the sample one.
I was hoping to set a precedent though. But we did get a lot of games.
You did? No, it was good. Do you think they will also send me a PlayStation 5 so I can play
Baldur's Gate 3? I think it's unlikely that they will send you a PlayStation 5 list. I regret to
report. So we also heard from Tobe's Valois, a long-time listener first time writer who said
I am looking forward to the next episode of OctaThorp as I assume you'll be covering the Hugo
Controversy. And thank you for pointing us at that coat Tobe's because we were like, well, we
were just like having a relaxing week. We were like, what is this Hugo? And then we looked at the
internet. We were like, oh no. Since Tobe's let us know about the Hugo Controversy, Liz has been
doing a lot of work to understand exactly what's been going on and why. And she now fully understands
everything that's happened and will summarize it now. I just want you to know how serious I am
about this. I've actually put down my crochet for this bit. Can I just check Liz? On a scale of
one to ten, what would you say is your full understanding of what has happened? What do you
mean on a scale of one to ten? I'm missing something. I don't think it's actually possible to fully
understand. I don't think there's a person on the planet who fully understands what's happened.
Oh, I see. This is fun for Rob Hanson, 2062, to unravel. I fully comprehend the mysteries.
I am going to try and summarize the current thing that's going on with the Chengdu Hugos. It might
take me a little while. If you have already been reading like the internet for the past week and a
half, then you may skip to the next chapter, which is a good bit and has Marvin in it.
Prof. Institute Knowledge. We have known for some time that Chengdu have to release the full Hugo
nomination stats within 90 days. And 90 days was last Saturday, and they did in fact release the
full nomination stats. Hooray. Oh no, we have questions though. There was a brief period where we
thought the most controversial thing was that it has taken 91 days, and that was a glorious 12 hours
that I miss. I actually said in a place I won't reveal online, what if the stats are a big letdown
now? And they're just not interesting. Wow, I wish I was in that universe. In the first two
minutes after the stats were announced, I got various people congratulating me and I set various
people congratulations for where they had appeared all the nomination stats. This was before we'd
actually read them. They released the full nomination stats, which for anyone who hasn't looked at them
are generally the rounds of EPH which cover the top 15 nominees. They also do generally release
the total number of ballots that voted in each, sorry, nominated in each category. We should say
again what EPH is for the benefit of people who are new listeners. EPH is E-Pervous Hugo. It is the
way of nominating for the Hugus, which is basically a system that kind of apportions your
nomination points according to how many items you nominate. And essentially it is an anti-slate
mechanism that was instituted after the sad puppies. And it works pretty well basically to dilute
voting slates because it will reduce the total number of points for items that kind of come
and sit together on people's ballots. If you want a full explanation of EPH, there's actually quite
a good one in the 2022 Hugo nomination stats, last year's ones, which have a lot of extra
information, helpful numbers, interesting stats, explanations of the voting process. In contrast
to 2023s, which do not have any of that. Thank you, Nicholas and Kat. Yes. Immediately upon opening
the 2023 nomination stats, there are a few things that jumped out. The first is that there are a
number of nominees who have enough points that you would expect them to be on the final ballot
who are declared not eligible and no explanation is given. Those include "Bable" by R.F. Quang in
Best Novel, Zira and Jay Zhao in the Astounding Award, Paul Weimar in Fan Writer, and the
"Novelet Fog on Temple" pagoda by Haya. And Tan Man. No, but Tan Man is slightly different.
Okay. So those are just declared ineligible and there's no reason given. There are items that
are declared ineligible and there's a footnote that explains why, which include items that were
not published first in 2022 and one that was removed because one of the authors on the Hugo
Subcommittee and there declared ineligible. There's also a very weird thing with Sandman where it
got enough votes to be on the ballot in both best short form and best long form dramatic
presentation. But then one entry says not eligible because it is eligible in the other category
and then the other category it just says not eligible. So those things were missing entirely.
I mean, there's a few people who declined nominations, which is, you know, normally there's a few,
so that was not unexpected. But yeah, there was no there was no explanation given for these.
It is now evident from statements made by R.F. Quang, Zira and Jay Zhao and Paul Weimar and Neil
Gaiman that they did not know that they had been declared ineligible and cannot think of any reason
why they are ineligible. So they ruled ineligible. No one knows why the, I think, predominant explanation
from the internet is that they were ruled ineligible because someone on the committee, either because
of overt messaging or just to cover themselves felt that they would be not approved of in China
and so decided to knock them off the the finalist ballot. And then it got better way of putting that.
No, I think that's fair. I think that's our working assumption.
And to say that is our working assumption because we have no information.
We have a tiny bit of information from a piece in PR2 where China did say that it would administer
the hugh goes in accordance with wusses constitution and local laws, which people are reading the
tea leaves of and saying that means we will censor anything we don't like. Which I think is not
an unreasonable assumption. I think that is the point where they told us they would make these
sorts of judgments. This is made a lot of people very angry and been widely regarded as a bad move.
Yes, I mean, I was going to say if I want it doesn't, it doesn't quite make sense to me
because I'm not quite sure why you would single out exactly that set of finalists. I mean,
some I can kind of understand. I mean, Babel certainly is written by an author born in China,
but now living outside China. People have noted other if that was the if that was a hard of
ass rule, there are other finalists that would have been mysteriously ruled that weren't so so yeah.
Yeah, there's a very good blog post by Ada Palmer, which I think we should link to in the show notes
where she talks about self censorship and censorship and how her regime censorship works.
And one of the impacts of that is that it's extremely inconsistent. So people have pointed
out that Babel has a mainstream Chinese publisher, but it may just depend on what the particular
person who decided that some some finalists had to be taken out was thinking on the day.
It doesn't need to be consistent because actually consistency is one of the things that comes with
transparency, which we do not have here. I don't think we can speculate any better than other
people have on the internet. We have no extra information. We don't really know anything extra.
Just there are a set of nominees who were ruled ineligible and they should not have been by any
ruling we can find if you're confined solely to the WISFIS Constitution. I think that is fair.
There is definitely something happening here, which goes above and beyond anything that has
previously happened with the administration of this award. And we'll get onto this in more
detail in a minute. Anytime anyone asks the man who released the stats, he just cites vague rules
and does not elaborate. Because that was one of the things that someone asked on the anonymous
Claire Discord was like, you know, how similar is this to previous things that have happened?
And I think the answer is very dissimilar. So if you're relatively new to the Hugo's, this isn't,
this is new. Yeah, I mean, I think there's been the occasional issue where eligibility has been
got wrong or where votes have not been canonised properly. And so stuff has left left off the ballot
that should have been on or potentially been on the ballot that should not have been, especially
for things where the eligibility is quite difficult to determine. But I don't think anything has just
been not eligible when it clearly should be. There's also some issues with the ballot based on
digging around in the EPH point transfers. I'll point your transfer. That doesn't even make sense,
John. It wasn't intended to Liz. So one, one thing is that because of the way EPH works,
every individual essentially gets one point that is split across everything nominated on their ballot.
The practical effect is that the number of points of EPH that never exceed the number of people who
nominated in a particular category. I checked the stats for the past four years and yes, the number
of points never exceeds the number of people who nominated in a category. In 2023, in four categories,
it does. I think it's just that the people nominating in 2023 were more engaged than previous Liz.
Liz, does that answer the question? No, you can't have something that's some some more than 100%.
You can. You can give 110% Liz. I've seen sports movies. Have you covered the ludicrous
absolute nomination figures here? She's working on it. She's working on it.
No, I'm getting to them. I'm getting to them. The other issue, I mean, there's also some
strangeness in EPH in best related work in which the number of total points which
should always ever go down as stuff is removed goes up again and then back down. It's weird.
I mean, the other thing is those things are definitely, there is no way under EPH these numbers can be
correct. There are also things which are like, well, these numbers could be correct, but they're
really weird. In quite a few categories, there are very, very high numbers of nominations. I mean,
we knew the nomination numbers were high because they announced like the total number of nominating
ballots, but that is explainable, right? Because you've just got a lot of members who are nominating.
However, it's really weird when you have, for instance, in best series, like the top set of
nominees all have over 800 nominations, and then the next one has 50. Like it is this very weird
pattern where the top ones have a huge number of nominations and then the number falls off.
And this is most pronounced in like best novel and best series, but it's also there in quite a lot
of categories. Like there's a lot of categories where the numbers just look a bit higher than you
would normally expect. I mean, including fan cast. Like, you know, in theory, according to these
nomination stats, Octa thought got 150 nominations, which is almost as many as our number of regular
listeners. I think it's 125. So no, but let me look it up. So yes, I will say that in 2021, when we
were not in the ballot, we got 20 nominations in 2022. When we were, we got 46. And in 2023,
we got 125. So that is a pretty like, it is big jump, probably a bigger jump than is possible.
Yeah, it's true. Oh, that's hard because we doubled from one year to the next year. And if
we doubled again, we would have had 80. So 120 is like probably too many. But it's not as too many
as it might sound. I'm probably doubling every year. It might be better to assume 20 extra every
year, in which case, like it would be 60 out. I think the thing is, in a lot of categories,
the top end was a bit higher than you would expect. But like the bottom end is still low.
Like if everything shifts up, that's one thing, but like the bottom end of fan cast,
like by the time he gets a 15th nominee, it's still like five nominations or whatever. It's not
like it pulled the whole thing up. It's just the top. And I would say the last thing is,
there's some of the redistribution of votes, which is a bit strange. Basically, in EPH, you can see
when someone is eliminated, where their their who else's points totals go up, which means that
they were on the ballot of some nominees together. Now let me explain that in a better way. So in
EPH, when an item gets eliminated, it means that all the ballots with that item on will give slightly
more points to the other items on that ballot. Basically, you get more power as stuff that was
on your ballot was eliminated. And so you can see where the points go when any one, you know,
potential finalist is eliminated. And you can see in a lot of cases on this ballot where there is a
mix of nominees from Chinese fandom and from Western fandom, you can see them kind of redistribute
how you might expect when one of the Chinese nominees for best artists is eliminated. Their
votes go to other Chinese nominees. And mostly when one of the Western nominees is eliminated,
their votes go to other Western nominees. But there's a few kind of strange examples where
this doesn't happen. There's one in in best novel, the redistribution of the nominations for a
novel called the Red Stone, which all seem to go to the mountain in the sea, which was spotted by
Commestras for Lapton. I should say also lots of people spotted the errors in the kind of EPA
and the weird distributions, including Marshall Mreska, Heather Rose Jones and Commestras
Flapton, and James Quinn, who came up with the EPH system, is also looking at it on blue sky.
But yeah, there's stuff like when David Pomerico is eliminated in best edit, it's a long form.
None of his votes redistribute to any of the other American editors on the ballot. They all
redistribute to only one Chinese nominee, which is just a really weird pattern that you wouldn't
expect, especially when, you know, the person who gets eliminated after him, their points
transfer to nearly all of the like top, they're transferred like six of the top seven left on the
ballot. And then when this other editor gets eliminated, they all go in one direction, which
basically, which to the point where you can work out that like there must have been like 72 ballots
that only had like these two editors on of the top 15, it's just a weird, it's just weird patterns.
I spent a lot of time staring at figures and graphs in order to bring you this segment,
and I hope you now understand basically. I mean, this is good a show. I don't understand it other
than understanding the vibe, but it's basically very similar to single transferable vote, but for
nominations instead of voting. Oh, no. Oh, no, I think it is. You have like, you have your preferences
and as they get eliminated, your other preferences get redistributed.
But there's never a penalty in SDV for having multiple things on your ballot. There is interior
penalty in EPH if you nominate five things and they all have sufficiently low totals, they all
get eliminated before you get to the later rounds. You'll never get anything on the ballot.
Yeah, I guess that's true. I get the values, which it's designed to be kind of fair and proportional
and to never reward kind of runaway success. Yeah. From a value standpoint, yes, it has the same vibe.
Quite like it from a vibe standpoint, but I might be alone. No, I like it.
I think if that's a, is that the summary of what we think has happened? Because I think it would
be good to have a little bit of reaction here, because I have a reaction I want to get in
before we start talking about all of the implications. I think that is the summary in a very technical
way. You know, and I kind of stopped way earlier and just said, look, the stats look weird.
My reaction is as follows, boo, boo, boo, boo, boo. After I kind of started to look at the stats
a little closer and realize they were all screwed up, it made me very unhappy because this was my
first ever individual Hugo nomination after 40 years of phalak. And it was so it's really,
it really sucks. It sucks to be a Hugo finalist this year, especially if you, you're in that sort
of position. People have been calling for, well, why don't we rerun the awards or something? I don't
think that's very practical. I don't think it's going to happen. I think it just sucks. And we now
have a slightly, a slightly tainted set of awards, which is a bit sad. And I think there's no way that
can't take some of the joy away from from the people who won and the people who were finalists.
I want to say something here, which is so my, Espa単o, my wife was also a finalist and she
is also very conflicted about that. I don't understand why the nominations were fiddled,
because they declared anything they didn't want to be on the ballot ineligible by magic anyway.
So I don't really see why they went into the numbers. Like, if they were going to just do it
by fiat, I don't understand why not just do it by fiat. And I will say like, obviously,
I think any finalist who was on the ballot prior to this year, or prior to 2023, I should say,
like there is a very good chance that they would have been on the ballot, like in 2023,
if they'd been on before. So I think those people are probably less conflicted. But if you're a
first time finalist or the first time finalist for a long time, it must be very, very, very sad.
My gut feeling is that I don't understand what the motivation for the fiddling is,
but my gut feeling is that like no one in the team had like a special interest in getting like
Alice and Espa単o, for instance, onto the best fan artist ballot. And so I think that if and if
the awards have been run the way they usually run, Alice and Espa単o would still have been on that
ballot. It's, but the thing is that the voice in my head telling me that's not true is way quieter
for me than it is for someone who's in that position, because I've had anxiety and I know
how those little voices in your head work. And so it must really be horrible. And it's really
annoying that it's tainted that whole thing. And you can't, you can't take that taint away,
because it wouldn't be rerunning the awards, or it wouldn't be rerunning the voting, it'd be
running rerunning nominations. And there's no way that people wouldn't nominate the things,
like, you know, Espa単o said that she didn't make it on legitimately. So I'm sure lots of people
would nominate her, because they're like, fuck those people who made her feel sad,
she deserves to be on the ballot. And so I don't, there's no way you can go. The only way to go
back and have a fair Hugo is to invent the time machine. And we can't obviously do that. I mean,
despite the fact that we've got one as referenced in episode 98, I can't remember exactly which
one it was, but I don't see a way of going back and having a fair process.
Just go back to episode 98 and record a pickup, John, you have a time machine.
Hahaha. But I will say, I think it's also notable that they released the voting stats a
long time before the nomination stats. And that to me says that there wasn't a problem, or there
wasn't fiddling in the actual voting. And so I think if you were on the ballot and then you won,
you got that win on that ballot. And I think if you are a winner, you should hold your head high
and celebrate the fact you're a winner. Christopher Jay Garcia said it very well when he said the
second Hugo he won, he won specifically because he was not a sad puppy and everything else in
that category was a sad puppy. And therefore, Journey Planet got the Hugo and he loves it just
as much as the other Hugo he has. And I think that is a good attitude to take. If you are a winner,
I think you are a Hugo winner and you are just as much of a Hugo winner as any of the other Hugo
winners. And if Hugo others is thing, definitely Hugo Girl, because you know, you deserve those
rockets and display them on your mantelpiece proudly, please. Like the one thing I would hate for this
to do is to make those people feel like those rockets weren't worth what they're worth.
They don't actually have the rockets, you know. We will be getting on to Dave McCarty's
various talents as Hugo Awards Administrator later, but that is foreshadowing. But it turns out
shipping rockets to winners is not one of them. Yeah, I mean, I think the voting actually,
the voting feels pretty consistent with the nomination stats being in some way inflated just to maybe
up the total numbers. Yeah, there were some, there were some hinky things about the voting stats,
weren't there? Well, there's just a lot of things that win in the first round, which is not necessarily
hinky unless like there actually wasn't a huge amount of support for some of the nominees.
But I mean, it is a different voting population and specifically, like everyone from Chicago
couldn't nominate, but not necessarily vote. But I mean, it's kind of weird when, you know, in theory,
the founder's strategy had like 900 plus nominations. And yet when it came to the actual ballot,
it came in sixth. And in fact, only had 313 people who put it above no award. It's kind of weird
that something that was so high on the ballot did not have any actual, it didn't turn out to have
any support at the voting phase. I would let's say two things, which is firstly, we know
that where you place nominations, the way you place the category aren't always one to one. And
the best example I can think of this is we discussed on a previous episode and God knows which
year it was, but the person who won best fan writer got on in sixth place and was quite far down in
the raw number of nominations, but EPH bumped them up quite a bit. But then they ended up winning
the whole category. And so if it's possible for someone who got by far the fewest raw nominations
to end up winning, presumably it's possible for the reverse to happen. And we've seen that
in fairly administered awards, or awards, I assume were fairly administered.
Yes, that's true. The reason I argued, I think the votes are solid is because I think if they
weren't, they would have come out at the same time as the nonce. The behaviour of the Hugo
subcommittee makes me think the votes are unlikely to be rigged. Does that make sense?
It does make sense, yeah. Okay, so I think it is possible that there is inaccurate data in the
voting, but it's clearly not as much. The inaccurate data, the reason the nomination statistics were
further delayed was because of the, I think, is because of the unexplained ineligible,
because I think if it was just that the voting data was, the nomination data was corrupt and
hinky, we'd probably have stopped. The row would have been much less. So that's the first thing.
And the second thing is I do think it was just they were so desperate to say the most
nominees ever, that they just dumped a load of erroneous nomination data in there,
forgetting that somebody was going to look at it later. I think a lot of people didn't think
that the nominating statistics got much attention, which, you know, if they'd been paying attention,
they would know that the nominating statistics always get a lot of attention.
I think I agree with John in that I can't understand why you would, like, if you're going to tweak
the nomination stats, why don't you do it by just inventing a bunch of extra ballots and putting
them into the system? But that would not explain why the numbers don't add up.
So it's kind of weird that you're like, I don't know. I think what I'm saying here is,
if I was, like, faking some Hugo nominees, I would do a better job.
Liz in wants to fake Hugo's better controversy.
So one of the explanations is that a standard form of protest in China is that you release
something that is clearly nonsense as a way of protesting because that's a form of protest
that is often acceptable. I understand. And then nobody says anything because everybody knows
that you don't say anything because it's China. And so we've had a combination of that form of,
I have released nonsense data because I know it is a form of protest against the repression and
censorship combined with, but in Western fandom in particular, everybody says everything because,
you know, people do thereby creating a storm.
Do we want to segue from that to the reaction of Chinese fans?
To go back to the thing of, like, did the people who did this not realize that the nominations
would get quite a lot of scrutiny? Have they not been paying attention? There have been a lot of
rumblings over the last few months that the Chinese people on the committee were not the fans
that originally wanted to hold the Worldcon. And there is a letter in file 770, which was posted
yesterday by a Chinese fan. And it's really interesting because that fan basically goes into
some detail. But it is not our intention to defend the arrogant, haughty and insolent Dave
McCarthy, more on whom later yet, while he was the target for the most firepower, some bugbears
masquerading as Chinese were stealthily making their way through the organizing committee.
They were never science fiction fans in the first place. They were not a part of fandom.
A couple of media companies executives have somehow gotten involved in the convention,
taken over everything including the Hero Wars, and used their few contacts in the media world to make
a bid splash in the press and in government hospitality receptions. They then passed the job of external
surrender to McCarthy, who would bend over backward with small favors and the job of internal repression
to the Chinese workers who had to be forced into surrender through the use of intimidation.
That's from a Chinese fan. And so I will say, there's been quite a lot of debate and we will get on to
this. As to whether or not the reason Dave McCarthy has acted how he has was to try and protect.
The Chinese people who were involved in this decision. But I think that might have been quite
a pro-kill perspective, because certainly the Chinese fans seem to be utterly fucking furious.
This is not just Western fans applying different views of how it should work to a world con held
in a different country. The Chinese fans who we have reports from seem to be hopping mad about this.
So the question is, who was Dave McCarthy protecting and the answer appears to be local
functioners. The reason I read that out and the reason I wanted to do that before we get to Dave
is because I think that ties into if it was people from media companies who were involved with this
and it wasn't the local fandom who might have been much more aware of the world
cometer why they wanted to run one. They wouldn't know, right? They wouldn't necessarily know
the Spanish traditions, especially Spanish traditions the other side of the Pacific.
I had not put that together until you guys had that discussion, but I think that might be right.
And certainly that seems to accord with stuff that's coming out of China itself.
Yeah, I think you might be right. And also I think, yeah, if you end up with a group of people
running the world con who, you know, are doing it because they see particular opportunities in it
and not because they have spent 10 plus years really, really wanting to run a world con and
bring the Hugo Awards there, then you might not realize. And also I think it is, in no previous
year, have I scrutinized the stats in quite this much detail. I have never summoned every column and
row and tried to reconstruct individual ballots. Yes, but Nicholas White has.
I mean, I think, no, but I think Nicholas White has produced stats, which I am sure he has checked
because he is a conscientious man. But I don't think external fans have ever dug into the extent
that we are digging in. I managed to reconstruct basically what the ballots must be for certain
nominees. I mean, I've looked at transfers, but I've never tried to go, is this number actually
explainable because we've kind of always trusted them to be so and having checked, like, some
retrospectively, they have been like that. So I guess you might have thought if you had like
numbers that looked superficially pretty good and you wouldn't spot any errors unless you dig deep,
deep, deep, deep in, you might think it was okay. Can we move on to Dave McCarty? As soon as the
world con ended, Dave was asked where the nominating stats were in the voting stats and said they
would be the Addentew course. And then he kind of got into a big row with people. And the upshot of
that row was he was like, we'll not, we'll release them on the last possible date. And of course,
the voting stats came earlier, but the nominating stats did come out slightly after the last possible
date. And at that point, Dave, I think must have known that this was going to kick off quite a big
row. And when people started asking him questions about it, he got stroppy. And I mean, not just a
little bit stroppy. He was phenomenally rude to people. He was rude enough that it's been picked up
all over the wider internet, not merely in a little corner of fandom. It was as if all of these years
of understanding how you do social media had vanished in a trace. And it was all right for Dave just
kind of tell people that they're stupid and not reading things properly and didn't understand what
they were reading. And could they now go away please? And and all of that. And I feel like this was a
very, very difficult and sensitive situation. And Dave decided to make it a lot worse. He has
since apologized, and we will put a link in the show notes to the apology. He's apologized for his
profoundly offensive behavior when he released the stats, but he hasn't apologized for his profoundly
offensive behavior in China, where he posted multiple photographs of him whining and dining with
Chinese with the Chinese local organizers, talking about how marvelous China was at every possibility,
launching a new Chinese symposium or award or foundation or something where Dave McCarty was the
only non Chinese person involved. And all of that stuff, which I feel is actually a much bigger deal.
And he did all this at a time when he must have known that the data was profoundly corrupt.
And he did not at that point resign or consider resigning or do anything to indicate he was not
happy with that process. But I think a lot of this makes a lot more sense if you think
that Dave genuinely didn't think it would cause a big row, or if it did, he could win the ensuing
argument. He has said he genuinely didn't think it would cause a big row. He has said he thought he
was only on his public Facebook post, talking to the few people who had asked the questions,
not realizing that those few people were asking questions on behalf of say, all the hugot finalists.
But I think that if I had been in his situation, which you wouldn't have been because China would
have come along and said we're going to mess with these figures and you'd have gone, Oh, I resign.
Depending on when you find out, right? Like if they had said we're going to do this,
I might have resigned before that happened. If I had ended up in a situation where 90 days after
the deadline, I have been merrily assuming the stats are all completely kosher. And I do not know
there has been any interference, which seems highly unlikely, but let's give him maximal benefit of
the doubt here. If I got today, say I look at the stats at day 85 and I think I'll bugger. There's
a real problem. The first thing I do is I start talking to people off the record saying I'll
bugger there is a huge problem. I start trying to diffuse the situation. I what I don't do is 75
minutes before midnight in my time zone on the day where I have promised to reduce the stats. I don't
post an RC comment about Oh, I think there's still over an hour left in this day. And then
miss the deadline I've set for myself due to my own incompetence. I don't do that. I don't do any
of these things. And so there's there's obviously and I don't think I'm the most competent man.
I think I'm relatively confident competent by my mistakes all the time. I handle situations badly
all the time. I don't think I've ever handled one this badly, but like, there's still time, John.
There's still time. But both Alice and Elizabeth can testify that I have had
rails with them where I've not covered myself in glory. The fact that I can see how you would
get out of this or no, not how you would get out of it. But if I was in this situation,
there is a way I would deal with it. Dave did not do that. For me to try to interpret his
motivations is extremely difficult because he very clearly has extremely different motivations
to me. And that makes it really hard for me to put myself in his head. And so this whole
thing's really difficult. I'm like, well, you wouldn't do it like this. Like, there's no decision I
would have made at any point that would let us hear. And I don't fundamentally don't understand
why he made these decisions. And then we get on. Well, no, then we get on to Liz. Liz, you said
not five minutes ago that if you fiddled with the Hugo's, you'd do a way better job.
I'm never going to be Hugo and administrative. I can't really I can't really fathom
Dave either, except that I know like personality wise, Dave is much more argumentative than me. And
I can see so but I think hypothetically, where I in Dave's position, where I had these stats.
And I had to release them because I promised to release them and they were going to look weird.
I would just have released them, made the statement he made a few times that we followed all the rules
and I can give you for further explanation. And then just stop there. There, people are going to
still debate it. People are going to still argue about it. But there's nothing you can add to this
conversation here. You just have to stop and say these are the nominations. Yes, I think if I had
been in Dave's position, which as I said, I would not have been because I think that he has behaved
in a I he cannot have behaved in an honorable fashion throughout this process. I think is what
I'd have to say. But if I were in that situation, I would channel Francis Erkwart. If people said
there's something dodgy about this, I'd go, you know, this is a statement. There isn't another
statement. I understand that you might assume that something strange has happened, but I couldn't
possibly comment. I mean, I would add, I think we've seen throughout the Chengdu process that
they do not respond to random inquiries on social media. They do not put out a lot of
press releases. They put out what information they want at the time they want and they don't
really engage with fans all over the internet asking them questions. And so, yeah, okay, if
you're going to do that, why not stick with that? That at least would not result in everything going
through for some reason, the Facebook page of the Hugo administrator where he has a big
argument and insults a bunch of people. I want to pick up something that John said,
which I think is very relevant here, which is he said, well, if I was in this position, I'd go and
I'd make soundings off the record with people I trust and who could provide me with useful advice
on how to manage the situation. I feel that Dave has been very isolated throughout this process,
that he's not got a lot of help from people around him, even people around him who were
engaged with China, but certainly not people around him who were not engaged with China. Now,
that might be because he didn't ask for that help because he thought he knew what he was doing.
The one other thing I'd like to say before we get off Dave McCarty is to talk about Lenin's notion
of the useful idiot, which is the westerner that a communist regime uses in order to promulgate
their ideas in the west and that you could do this by making life easy for them and they therefore
think that maybe have a more favorable view of your regime than an unbiased observer would.
I'm also going to say I'm also going to repeat something I said earlier and I'm going to link
to a Facebook post, which is a public Facebook post, in our show notes with no further comment.
The Chinese fan that I quoted earlier on in the episode, I'm going to restate this, which is
they pass the job of external surrender to McCarthy who would bend over backward with small favors.
And then I'm going to post to a Facebook post made on the 23rd of October, 2023 by Dave McCarty,
which is a picture of lots of empty carrier bags with the text "I fit all the gifts in my luggage".
I mean, I think there is also something we might be missing, which there can be like more of a
gift-giving tradition to guests that you are missing out on. Yeah, there's all sorts of things
where you know I do a talk or a presentation somewhere and I am given like a mug, a branded
mug or a notebook and a pen and that kind of thing. So I mean, I'm sure there was definitely a lot
of like here are some Chengdu pics and pieces that we give to all our forum visitors kind of thing.
Okay, shall we move on to the rest of the Hugo Sub-Committee?
I think pretty briefly, yeah, because there were a bunch of people on the Hugo Sub-Committee,
including North Americans and Chinese people. But Dave is the only one who ever made any public
statements about the Hugos. I think Ben was off being co-chair and the other two people were essentially
doing the administrative work of the Hugo team in North America. And I don't think we got any data
from Chinese fans involved in the team at all. So yeah, so the list of people is Dave McCarty,
Ben Yalo, Amari Rudolf, Diane Lacey, Xi Chen, Zenyu Jiang, Zhou Yao, Tina Wang, Dong Sheng Gu and Bo Pang.
I will just comment that the actual final stats are titled, 2023 final Hugo stats final Joe
Doc Doc. So he can shoot more at least one other person read them along with Dave.
Is this sort of forensic analysis, which is why we keep Liz around? At least it's not called
final, final, to final, final. Hello everyone, it's John here with a quick pick up before we
release the episode on the 30th January, which was Tuesday. Worldcon Intellectual Property
released a statement announcing that Dave McCarty has resigned from the organisation.
Kevin Stanley has resigned as chair of the organisation and Dave McCarty, Chen Xi and Ben Yalo
have been censured for actions of the Hugo Administration Committee of the Chengdu
Worldcon and Kevin Stanley has been reprimanded for public comments regarding trademarks.
We plan to get to the trademark debacle next episode. That was a conscious choice because there
was a lot in this episode and we will discuss the ramifications of the other actions in the
next episode as well. So a lot of people have wondered what is Glasgow doing about all of this
as Glasgow 2024 is this year's Worldcon. The first thing is that none of the people who were on the
Hugo Subcommittee in 2023 are working for Glasgow in any capacity. Ben Yalo was but is no longer
and none of the others were on the stuff as well as far as I know. They have also announced that
they will release the long list of nomination statistics immediately after the Hugo Awards,
which is the traditional time it's always been released until this year. It sometimes delayed by
a little bit but not much and that they will announce eligibility decisions and withdrawals
from the award when the ballot is released. I think this is not a bad thing but maybe some of you
have differing views. Liz this is your cue. Yeah for once I am the person who really hates it
and have strong feelings. I think basically when you are coming up with proposals to try and make
the Hugo's more transparent which I do approve of I think you should be very careful to do it in
a way that doesn't make the whole experience less fun for the Hugo finalists and I think this will
make it significantly less fun. Imagine that in you know they announce all the finalists and at
the end of this they announced that like Anne Lecky withdrew her name from the ballot for translation
state and that you know Anne Leenuets and Charlie Jane Anders withdrew for our opinions are correct.
This is all hypothetical but if I am a finalist at that point well I really don't want is people
going oh I wonder which podcast was seventh on the ballot and only got on there because
someone who was higher up withdrew or oh I wonder why you know this thing was disqualified from
best novel let's have a debate about his eligibility. I don't mind having that debate but I don't
want to do it on exactly the day they say oh and by the way here are the actual Hugo finalists who
should be having like their moment in the sum. So I was much more reasonable than I hoped it would
be. I was hoping for much more vitriol Liz. I mean I'm already quite annoyed by it.
Is that a vitriolic enough? I find it quite annoying. That's your version of quite annoyed.
If you don't know Liz well you don't know but I could tell that was Liz being pretty pretty wound
up about the whole thing. "I am not as quick to anger as Dave McCarty you said and I was kind of
thinking well John and I are not as quick to anger as Dave McCarty it were a lot more quick to
act of the licks." True. True. I agree that. I agree. I think Glasgow has done a good thing here
in that I do think it would be nice to be able to know the eligibility especially before the voting.
Like it has never quite made sense to me that we don't get the nomination stats before the voting
but I guess you don't want them to affect the voting. Sorry I still think it would impact on
the eventual voting very significantly if people knew which ones and got lots of nomination.
A) Because humans are like that they vote for things that they think are popular,
very well-known, very well-established effect over many years in social sciences but also
people will start their reading from highest nominations first in many cases so that will also
skew the voting. So that is a good argument. There is an argument for releasing the whole
shebang after the ballot is out but before the final result, after the ballot is closed but before
the final results but then you just have the fact that people will sort of go no such as such one
but such as such have more nominations. Well you have that you have that anyway. If I'm honest I
wouldn't release the Hugo stats because I find it really exhausting that the first thing we do as
soon as we know who won is debate all of the framework of that rather than just celebrating
their win which I think is exactly the same problem Liz is having with the joy of the nomination.
I think part of the reason I'm not angry at this is because the Hugo's already does this so it
doesn't seem like a massive change. Like and actually if we're going to have this argument,
I think having it after the nominations come out is way better than having it after the winners,
way better. But I am not a Hugo stats wonk. I am also going to channel the younger people who
are not us apparently but because I'd have said well 20 years ago you might be right about the
withdrawals and and in not so much an eligibility for the withdrawals but nowadays all sorts of
people recuse themselves all of the time in public at various different times before during and after
the nominations are released and it's just not such a big thing as it was 20 or 30 years ago when
it was pretty rare. I just don't think it I don't think people are really going oh it's the best
fancy that's not answer. From my perspective next year I will know that Hugo Girl is recused and so
if they get enough nominations they will have declined and I'm not sure I mind but I can see
like I wouldn't have a problem with them releasing the stats like two weeks after nominations. I can
see the point that doing it straight after is a bit mean but then I was not one of I was annoyed
when Dave said he'd take 90 days but when it looked like it might be a week I was not at all
concerned so I wouldn't mind there being a week gap between these things a week to let the nominees
or the winners settle in and then you crack on with the analysis that that that in general that
would seem good from both perspectives to me and I think it would address your concern list but I
don't know you might hate it. I'm surprising myself by saying this here but I would actually get behind
the full voting and nominations that's being released like a week after the ceremony because
you're right there are people who don't like having them there right at the time and in a normal year
I don't think the week would make much difference except I'd probably be at home and could dig into
the stats more rather than doing it you know during the Hugo Loser's party but what I can see is that
if you wait a week or two to release the names of those who declined or deemed ineligible then you
have to wait open voting because part of the point of this is so that if there has been an error you
can see it and correct it. I think in general I understand why Glasgow has taken the line they have
with all of their reaction to this I think one of the lessons that a lot of the people involved
with Chengdu should have learned is that maybe less is more when it comes to commentary and I think
Glasgow waiting to see how certain things pan out before having a response was wise they still
haven't issued like an explicit statement as far as I know they have they have said how they're
going to administer the Hugo Awards but they haven't like made an official statement on the
Bruha Ha which might or might not be wise I can see there's a logic to waiting until certain things
have died down I'm not sure everything has died down yet so I could kind of see that but I think
in general Glasgow seem to be trying very hard to do the right thing and not add fuel to the fire
and I think in general I applaud that. I feel that as people who do a fortnightly podcast
this is quite good for us because we I feel this podcast has been very different from the one
that we have recorded today after the Hugo
Awards.
I yes I think one of the things we'll be picking up in the future episode is some ways forward
for waspus and what it might want to do about it and but we are not the only people who have thoughts
on this so things are probably still happening in this space all over the place.
Liz you've probably read a book or something I mean I have um so I'm actually going to nominate
for my pick this week a book that I read in December so it's not super fresh in my memory but
actually it has stuck with me since December and therefore I think it is worth mentioning
so I'm going to pick a book called The Reformetry by Tana Reeve Dew which is a horror novel it's
set in kind of Jim Crow Florida and it's about a young black boy called Robbie you know has like
a minor altercation with the white youth and ends up being sent to reform school it's it's heavily
based on a real reform school that existed during the 1950s if you've read The Nickel Boys by Colson
Whitehead it's kind of very similar backstory to that and so obviously this was you know a deeply
deeply unpleasant place to be sent but the the twist it do puts on it is that Robbie essentially
can see supernatural figures can see these ghosts or hints as they call it and of course there are
a lot of ghosts in in this school which has been a site of of murders and like other horrific
goings on for many many years and so the book is all about Robbie and his like interactions with
these ghosts and how he sort of survives at reform school but also about his older sister who is
like working to get him out it has a lot of quite dark passages it isn't entirely you know it is
quite a difficult read in places but it's also very uplifting because I think a lot of Robbie's
seeing ghosts is not a terrible terrible thing seeing ghosts in some ways is something that
allows him to feel the presence of his dead mother these ghosts are just boys some of them who are
at the reform school who he forms relationships with and I think the plot strand of the sister
is also really interesting because she is trying to work to get him out in this system and so she
ends up kind of working again with a lot of kind of white or not black people in the in the south
who all are trying to be allies but often doing it in a very imperfect way she talks to black
lawyers who are helping her but often they have their own agendas and their own ways they want to
do things that are not necessarily immediately getting her brother out of reform school I think
it kind of has a really a really nice spin on this story which is a little bit similar to the white
head but balance is really nicely what was it's a very grim story with also the relationship between
families and found families and people in the community and how they pull together or don't
in these situations and I really I really enjoyed it it's also 2023 but and therefore eligible for
the 2024 pukos I have discovered and actually this will come up in my pick but I really enjoy
basically earlier that puts me in the shoes of places that I could only kind of academically
understand but I can't emotionally understand like I understand that Jim Crow Florida was a bad
place but reading a book with characters set in that place will be really interesting because
because it will actually force me to like emotionally relate to it in a way that I might not otherwise
so I am this is a very interesting pick this is one of the reasons that I like reading books and
consuming other media that was produced in the past because if you go far enough back people
people cannot help but fill everything fill the right of what topic they're writing about
their worldview comes over all of the time in everything in a way that does I find for me I find
that very immersive often or even when it's not immersive it's like oh wow people really
didn't think differently yeah and I would say this one it kind of really does get you emotionally
into that mindset of people who are continually aware of kind of how much a lot of their neighbors
either overtly dislike them or like them up to the point where they are the helpful
helpful black neighbors but they will only go so far yeah it's so it is quite emotional it does get
very tense at times when Robbie is trying to balance his responsibilities to certain
to try and get through things in the reform school but also get justice for the the ghosts of the
boys have been killed there is really quite tense all right Liz I'm buying it all right
I'm already too behind on my pleasure to read all of your picks this year but you know I will
continue trying Liz this book's 182,000 words long is it yeah sorry this likes long books no I don't
like long books I hate long books I often call books way too long Liz loves long books and she
cannot lie you other others can't deny so I remember feeling this book is quite long but I don't
remember it feeling like super duper over long but I also like read it well I was on holiday and so
you would be times when I would otherwise be just sitting around doing nothing for four hours in an
airport so I'll pick some short fiction next time how about that John thanks Liz appreciate it let me
let me help you catch up John because my pick I said I can't really do pick this week because
we've got no time and literally the only things I've consumed in the last week are printed play games
and back chat about the Hugo Awards and my pick is in the former category here which is a game
called dangerous space and it is a printed play Roland Wright where you have a single sheet of
paper and you play on that but they sell you lots of different sheets of paper for a very
small amount of money you could get I think the first four and their kind of mix and match this
is a science fiction adventure where you have a a character who is trying to infiltrate a spaceship
and do some things like rescue some people or whatever and things are trying to stop them
and your your goal is to get out so you can mix and match people and ships I may have mentioned
dungeon pages last year which is a was a kind of fantasy version of this but this is the science
fiction version I think we're getting 52 sheets one a one a week for the whole year if we have the
more expensive version of this which I do I played one really early on when they had not quite
worked out what rules they wanted and in fact due to interventions from various people including
one John Coxon of this parish they massively improved the rule sets so does it's much easier
to play I think than it was when it first came out and it is it is great it takes about 15 or 20
minutes to play a sheet and you can play it perfectly well on the iPad and the whole thing's
fabulous and really very charming in its way and it worked very much money and unfortunately
this is 2024 art so it will be eligible for the you goes in 2025 but dungeon pages is eligible vote
for that which is their fantasy one I have indeed so I also I backed this whole kick star because
I also played dungeon pages it's worth noting that the core set and the year long adventure are
different products so if you buy the year long adventure you don't get the core set but but
they're like not expensive get both but no it is I do enjoy it and I have already played it so that
is great from both perspectives I realized I should probably explain what a role on writers
which is it's a game where you roll dice and move around and fill in squares on a map I'm going to
pick uh the kitchen which is I don't know what its eligibility is it was it was premiered at the
BFI London Film Festival in October 2023 but it wasn't released in cinemas uh in the UK until
January 24 it is the directorial debut of Daniel Kluer so you may know him from get out he was the
lead in get out which is a very good movie which you've heard me talk about before and he has made
a movie about dystopian London in the sort of near future it's kind of about the disconnect
between private landholders and social housing and communities and the money in the land they
occupy I think you could probably pick calls in some of the world building but the central
emotional journey of the movie is so fantastic and what the movie has to say what the movie has to
say about the way London and other cities are evolving is is so relevant that I am inclined to
uh not dwell on it too much so yeah I really really enjoyed it and then we went to there was an
exhibition of the costumes from poor things at the Barbican to enter the Barbican which is also
where a lot of the kitchen was filmed especially the bits in the funeral home is probably the best
way to describe it which were filmed in the conservatory at the Barbican so we went and had a look at that
while we were there for the costumes from poor things and the Barbicans fabulous like it just
looks like the future that was the old thought podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye for me
and it's goodbye from me
[Music]
all these all these names have been majestically mangled so I wouldn't worry about it
Chinese listeners write in yet Chinese written as please write into John and explain it great length
uh tone on languages with examples and IPC not IPC IPA IPA is a type of beer I know about that
Liz come on the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in
competec.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]