John, edit this down.
I'm going to, don't worry.
Edit it down to only the funny bits.
I have faith.
Yeah, you've got to edit our lesson.
Oh, is it going to be very careful edit?
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 39th episode of Octa Thorpe,
which is coming to you on the 2nd of September 2021.
The podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
I know I'm Liz Batty.
Summer is over.
There is no more fun.
Cease having fun immediately.
Now I'm really gloomy.
Yes, it has been summer.
But we have all sat down at our usual recording rigs on the usual day at the usual time
and we are recording a usual Octa Thorpe.
It's been a while.
It's been like six weeks since we sat together on our Sunday morning recording
Octa Thorpe in our separate places.
Too fair.
I'm not in the usual place.
Are you on Plague Island?
Well, I think that I am on Plague Island,
but specifically the reason I could be here is it is least Plague Island, I think.
I am in Sandbox Quarantine.
Worst Sandbox game ever.
If Liz actually says the name of the place she is, I have to bleep it,
so please don't say the name Liz.
It's not pronounced like that.
Is it not?
How is it pronounced Liz?
Who can't?
Oh, f*ck it.
Definitely not pronounced about that.
You're all very rude.
Yeah, Alison.
It's like are you five?
Yes, you are.
Hey, I resemble that remark.
I am 12.
We have a myriad of letters of comment,
but on the subject of the word myriad,
I was reading this here,
and Mark Plummer used the word plethora in a letter of comment,
wondering if I would spot that it was a reference to Octa Thorpe,
and I sent him an email saying Alison would not approve,
and he sent me an email back saying, "Aha, you read it."
So that was very good and made me google quite a lot.
Hoorah.
So yeah, me and Mark are now like, I guess, doing references for each other in our locks.
This is a great sport, I highly recommend.
And we have letters of comment, although not from Mark,
but we have letters of comment from Ali Baker,
Fran Dowd, Chris Garcia, twice,
Caroline Mersey, Karen Schafer and Peter Sullivan.
Yeah, this is what happens when we don't do a regular episode of six weeks, isn't it?
We have a backlog of a myriad of plethoras or something.
We have a blog, which is a backlog of logs.
Ali Baker writes to tell us about her hobby of watching
how inappropriate children's books that are recommended to children
by adults who haven't read the book for 50 years can be.
Yes.
She includes the next time I see Pierre Santini recommended for a nine-year-old girl,
I'm burning the internet down.
I have never read any Pierre Santini and I have never been a nine-year-old girl,
so I am badly placed to comment on this.
But Ali does say don't recommend Enid Blightened kids,
and yeah, I think even someone who read Enid Blightened when I was a kid,
I would not do that now.
No.
She also says she's seen Conan the Barbarian recommended for an eight-year-old boy,
and if you have an eight-year-old boy who you think might like that sort of thing,
they might like Beast Quest books if they haven't read them already,
which are basically Conan the Barbarian without so much sex and violence.
In fact, without the barbarous bits, I think I realise.
On the subject of Ali, our very own Alison Scott was on episode three of Fantasy BookSwap,
which at the time recording is the latest episode.
I was discussing Tamarind and the Star of Ishtar by Jasbin de Billan,
and Marianne Dreams by Catherine Store, which was my fondly-remembered children's book,
which I think held up quite well.
It's a bit old-fashioned, but it doesn't have anything that causes you to choke on your tea,
unlike many of these books from Aft childhood.
Yep, that's rare.
And it was a lot of fun, and I enjoyed doing it,
but it was me kind of talking with Ali about books for a whole hour,
which is not like me, because I don't normally talk about books very much at all.
Is that why Fault in the Spillennial Daughter has the name she has?
Yeah, no, she's named after Marianne of...
Well, she's not named after Marianne of Marianne Dreams,
who's a grumpy, spoiled child, but I liked the name,
and that's why I liked it.
I had liked it for quite a long time, and when I said,
"Should we call our daughter Marianne?"
Stephen was kind of like, "Hm, yeah, I suppose."
That's kind of half of a nice story.
Ali said that starting the podcast had got her unblocked on reading.
That's really good.
I thought it was...
It seems to have got other people unblocked on reading as well,
and I think it's really good as a way to start to think critically about books
without having to think too critically about them, if you see what I mean.
So I really enjoyed doing it, and I think it's a great podcast, and people should listen.
He agreed, and Ali am going to be on a forthcoming episode of Fantasy Book Swap as well.
So I very, very nervously emailed Ali to be like,
"I'm sure that you've got loads of people, but if you need someone, I would love to be on."
And Ali very kindly invited me.
"Did it invite if you ask?"
I don't know, probably not.
I invaded an invitation, I suppose.
And yeah, so I'm going to be on.
I'm super excited.
She sent me the suggestions for the books that she might link with my book,
and one of them I was like, "Ooh, I want to read that anyway."
So I'm going to read that one.
I'm very excited, and it's also, and this is a hint to the listener.
It has recently been made into a movie, which you can stream on Disney+,
so I'm also excited to watch the movie after I've read the book.
So it's like going to be a whole thing, and I'm super, super, super jazzed about it.
So, hurrah!
Thank you very much to Ali for her lock.
And then we have a lock from Fran Dowd, who writes about a piece she wrote for the program book for Intuition in 1998,
which started as an all-women committee, and she wrote a piece called From the Depths of the Sopher.
And it's a kind of a long paragraph, and I'm not going to read it out here.
But it was kind of talking about how they did their internal structure for running their convention,
and kind of, instead of having a line management system, they had a webbed subgrouping pattern.
So instead, you kind of had a working group of people, and then you had different kind of groups of people
doing different things within that kind of large group.
And it sounded really interesting.
I might ask her if I could just put the piece in the show notes, or link to it somewhere if it's online.
But yeah, so it's really interesting to take on kind of how you can do kind of convention running
in a way that is a bit less strictured, and ties into some of the stuff we were saying about divisions
and that kind of thing in previous episodes with regards to Eastercons and Worldcon.
Not sure it would work for a Worldcon, probably too big to be running in a kind of anarchic way,
but definitely possible for smaller conventions.
Yeah, I found interesting how I had no idea this happened in 1998,
and I suspect a lot of people who weren't working on the con in 1998, or really paying attention kind of know about it.
And it's interesting, because I don't think anyone's ever tried it this way again.
I suppose I know most conventions have gone back to having kind of a fairly traditional committee structure.
So yeah, it was interesting for two reasons.
One that, you know, Fran saying this is only a historical interest,
but yeah, it is like history that I had no idea about.
I may have been completely forgotten if we don't have Fran or other people around the time letting us know.
But also, yeah, it doesn't seem like anyone's ever tried it again.
So if you have tried running a convention in a similarly non sort of committee based hierarchical way,
please let us know.
What like punctuation, you mean?
Well, we already covered punctuation in our kind of like weird anarchic collective type approach,
but I mean, we do sort of have roles.
So the 1988 East Con didn't have a chair, and that was quite stressful.
What were you doing for the 1998 East Con?
Causing trouble.
All right.
[laughter]
It's good to know that some things haven't changed much over the last 32 years.
I feel like I was kind of like the Jamie Tarte of Con running.
[laughter]
Alison Scott do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do.
Alison Scott.
Yeah, if you put that on the podcast, the baby shot, the lawyers will be in contact with you.
[laughter]
I don't know what you mean, entirely original track.
I was so yes, there were too many egos and it was we were all young.
Very young.
We all felt much older than I mean there were people who was old as 29 on that committee.
And Roger Robinson.
Oh no, Roger Robinson wasn't on the committee.
He stepped aside sharply.
[laughter]
I have an important question, Trace, which is if Alison Scott is Jamie Tarte and I presume John is Ted Lasso, then who am I?
Roy Ken.
[laughter]
[beep]
Chris Garcia sent us two letters of comment.
He didn't just get super enthusiastic.
It's just that we didn't do anything with the first one until he sent a second one.
So he says that with regard to convention of publications, things have changed and ACOM materials are actually more important.
What the ACOM newsletter does is present you with the essential info in one curated spot.
And yeah, I think I'd agree with him on that point and kind of talks about he then goes on to agree with us on.
I'm trying to bring publications and promotions under the same umbrella and et cetera and et cetera.
But that's all kind of from the world con perspective.
In his follow-up letter of comment, he says that Celsius is just wrong and we should do another punctuation.
One of those two statements is correct.
[laughter]
Agreed.
I would also like to pull out Chris's point.
He does mention that part of his job is to be a social media professional and he mentions how good promoted tweets can be,
which is something I hadn't thought of about what is the return for doing kind of promoted tweets and promoted Instagram posts.
I think I've seen some sort of like promotional Facebook post boosting being used.
And I think you did that for FollyCon or we did that for FollyCon, but I'll let you do it because you know we're at Facebook.
Only to the extent that Facebook said, "Oh, you don't appear to have boosted this with ads, but you've used ads on other pages in the past,
have £33 to run ads."
And I said, "I will run exactly £30 worth of ads for nothing and then I will stop."
I do not think that Facebook boosting is good for community groups and I am very happy to talk about why not at length in a bar sometime
because it's unlikely that Facebook will show your post to the people who need to see it.
What does work very well though is getting all your mates to share out posts on their personal pages.
If you can get them to do that, then you will get traction.
The other thing that Chris says in his second layer of comment is that one thing that he's interested in at the moment
is when we're going to take up the question of what roles podcasts should be playing in fandom today.
Maybe it's me, Chris writes, but we've got a bunch of great podcasts about science fiction but a last few about fandom.
And while the origins of OctaThorp are as clear as rainwater, which I think is a compliment,
what should the role of podcasts be? Are they simply fanzine replacements? Are they more appropriately tools to allow for debate
on topics of fanishness-esque subjects? What? And I would just like to say, I agree.
I think the complementary to fanzines, aren't they? Because a good fanzine probably has some tooth some articles in it
and although podcasts could be doing that sort of thing, they mostly, well, we don't.
I mean, other people do. We could get, we could have interviews with the important mover and shaker fans of the day
and things like that.
So it occurs to me, we could do a serial-esque, true crime-esque episode of OctaThorp where we do like a deep dive into some
convention thing, but we present it all as like highly dramatised interviews with people who were there.
That sounds like an absolutely fast amount of work.
Be quite funny though.
Oh, I said no to something yesterday.
Oh well done.
Yeah, no, that's what you'd be pleased.
Yeah, I'm not good at that.
I also, I also said, I think we should probably help with that about something much bigger.
So, you know, it's okay.
Right, fair enough.
Swings, roundabouts.
John, have you watched American Vandal on Netflix?
I have not.
Should I?
So it is basically a sort of, it's a comedy show about like, you know, a teenager at a high school who investigates in a kind of serious,
you know, true crime drama, serial podcast style, the question of who drew a load of ticks on some cards in the car park.
It's very funny.
It really kind of captures that sort of true crime documentary style thing in a way you were suggesting.
So I think basically you should watch that because I think what you're proposing is that we do American Vandal with a load of
Spanish in-jokes.
That actually could be incredibly funny.
Though I feel like Andy Hooper's radio plays were trying to get into that sort of space.
No, I mean, and it sounds a bit like, I don't know if either of you have seen the Ryan Johnson film Brick,
which is a noir set in a high school, which is also amazing, and would highly recommend to any listeners who have not interacted with it.
But I really like things that take the, especially, especially stuff that has like a really specific and defined language
that applies it to something that it really wasn't intended to.
I love it.
So I will have to look up American Vandal.
Thank you for the recommendation, Aliz.
But I, I, I, I learned to go back to Wiles from saying, but I basically think that, yeah, podcasts are, I think, complementary to fanzines.
It slightly frustrates me that there's not more people from the fanzine, fandom tradition, exploring different media.
Because I like old style fanzines, but I wouldn't have mind if like some of the people that were writing them were also doing other stuff that was a bit less old school.
But that's a conversation for, well, it's a conversation we've already had on previous episodes, and we will probably have again on subsequent episodes.
Hara, Pat McMurray wrote to say that he really enjoyed our piece on communications, and he talks about kind of his thoughts on what convention communications are for,
which I think we, we covered, but he's kind of vociferously agreeing with us.
But he also says that if he was going to go on the Fantasy Books podcast, he would pick either Swallows and Amazons or Citizen of the Galaxy.
I mean, I think Swallows and Amazons, I'm not sure whether, I think eventually, Ali will probably have someone on who just has a thoroughly on un-genre.
Um, but.
Yeah, Marianne Dreams was quite close.
But I mean, I think it's genre, I would argue it was genre.
It's got magic in, so.
I think it's hard to argue that for Swallows and Amazons, unless it's all a dream.
If you actually had, we didn't mean to go to see or the other, what's the other, um, Fantasy one.
Two of them are not, a Fantasy novels, not, not, um, they're Fantasy novels about sailing.
Yeah.
But they're, they're, they're the stories the children make up.
So, so you could have one of those, and it would be on topic.
That's true, and for that.
Caroline Mersey points out that we've omitted Trebake from our baked goods taxonomy.
And says that Brownie's millionaire short-read Rocky Road Tiffin and Fifteens are Trebakes and not cakes nor biscuits.
Now, I don't know what Fifteens are.
No, they're Fifteens aren't.
What is a Fifteen? I've never heard of this.
Okay, so Fifteens aren't, I mean, I'd defer because Caroline Mersey is actually from Northern Ireland, and these are an all-in-arish thing.
Um, Fifteens are made from Fifteens and various different things, like Fifteens, Glasset cherries and Fifteens chocolate buttons.
I can't quite remember.
Fifteen marshmallows, Fifteens ounces of flour.
I don't, don't quote me.
I'll find a recipe and they are delicious.
But when I have made them, you have rolled it all up in the log and put the log in the fridge and I cut it into Fifteens slices.
So, that might be a different, I might have been using a slightly different recipe to her.
Fair enough.
I have a ingredients for Fifteens, Fifteen digestive biscuits, Fifteens marshmallows, Fifteens glassy cherries.
This sounds amazing.
A small tin of condensed milk and a loaded desiccated coconut and they are very delicious.
Okay.
And I will put the link in the show note.
They do sound very nice.
And then people can argue possibly a lot.
But it's not a tray bake because it's not baked.
You just basically roll it up and stick it in the fridge and then cut it up and eat it because it's made from cooked things.
But I know what, because I know what Caroline means, because I would have called Rocky Road a tray bake too.
But you don't really bake Rocky Road.
You melt the chocolate pour it into a tray with the ingredients and then leave that in the fridge to set as well.
So, so it's...
Yeah, but that's still in a tray.
Yeah, that is true.
But no, my view is that things like flapjacks and brownies are traybakes because you bake them in a tray.
Very, very simple soul.
Look, all right, stop it with your unceasing logic.
And then Liz, Peter Sullivan agrees with you.
So Liz, do you want to tell us what Peter Sullivan agrees with you about?
Peter, agrees with me or conventions not like just randomly posting stuff about fandom generally in order to boost their social media activity,
which is something I call that was being a basically a not great way of engaging with people because it just feels super generic.
And back in the days before social media, he says he ran the RSS feed for the Christopher Taff campaign,
which is basically posting whenever Chris Garcia did something on the internet, which is basically all the time.
So really, it seems like the key thing here is that conventions need Chris Garcia as part of their convention in order to have a continual stream of things to post about on the internet.
Or if not Chris Garcia, some Chris Garcia equivalent.
I think we need a standard unit of Garcia's for this.
I feel like I'm looking for something like a milligarsia as a unit of exuberance.
What could Chris launch?
Maybe it's like, you know, some people lock Octa Thorpe at a rate of five milligarsia's, which means they send us a letter every so often rather than a letter every time we release an episode.
I think we should probably define the unit of locking Octa Thorpe as the Briarly and not the Garcia.
That is true.
Karen Schafer says that I am right, yes, and that brownies are bar cookies, which I think might be the American word for trabakes.
Oh no, they're trabakes. Don't they have trabakes? They have trabakes in America.
Do they or do they have bar cookies? Because I'd never heard of a bar cookie before.
Yes, a shortbread's a bar cookie, right?
She doesn't mention that.
No, because they don't really have shortbread in America. I mean, they do, but it's terrible.
Do we need a Twitter poll on this one?
Oh, maybe.
Engagement, hashtag engagement, hashtag content.
She did also send us a picture which I will put in the show notes of a page from a cookbook she has in which she says how to make bar cookies.
So I will put that in the show notes, but it includes brownies, dainty tea brownies, brownie confections and butter scotch brownies.
So I might have to try making some of these. Thank you very much, Karen.
Peter Sullivan tweets in about degrees Kelvin.
There was a postal games fanzine called absolute zero that started at issue minus 273 and got to issue about minus 250 before it folded.
He has no idea why he thinks he might we might want to know this, but I enjoyed knowing it very much.
So thank you, Peter.
Is it very good scheme for a fanzine to call absolute zero and start at minus 273? That's just 10 out of 10.
10 out of 10 temperature fanzining.
But that concludes the letters of comment.
Whoo!
So this week we heard the sad news of the death of Earl Courshack.
So Earl Courshack was one of the last two surviving attendees of the first Worldcon and also part of the leadership of the Worldcon in 1940 in Chicago.
He was scheduled to be a guest of honor at Chicon 8 in 2022, which would have been 82 years since he had chaired the Chicago Worldcon.
So I think he was member of the leadership of the Chicago Worldcon at age 17 or 18 and then it had been invited back basically for the most recent Chicago Worldcon.
I met him very briefly in 2019 at the Dublin Worldcon.
I think he came into program ops and we chatted a little bit and it was really astounding to me that I could still meet someone who was coming to convention, so he'd been there kind of right at the start of everything.
So it's sort of right at the start of organized fandom.
And I think that is something that we are gradually losing.
We now have one attendee left of the first Worldcon.
And it's just another sad event that kind of all this Spanish history is that was there for us to talk to and spend time with is now passing on.
I also kind of really loved that he had a long enough life and a long enough career and a long and Spanish career that he could actually lead Worldcons very early in his life, then drop out to fandom for many years and then come back to find that Worldcons were still going on.
And I would love to know what he thought when he sort of came back to Worldcons in the 1980s to see what they'd become.
To some extent it's sad that we're losing these threads to our early history, but I think it's kind of fantastic that fandom has survived and remembers its traditions and has that continuous thread of experience that goes on for long enough that people who got into it as young teenagers are now dying at the age of, I don't know,
World was quite old, but Bob Madal who is the lost survivor is 101 because I sent him a little badge with a propelebenie on it for his 100th birthday last year.
I don't think it's that sad, I think it's kind of nice that we have all of that tradition and that we wrote it down because of fanzines and as guests podcasts are also a record, though I don't know if anyone's going to go back in 100 years and listen to old podcasts and go, "Well, what was Weetabix anyway?"
I didn't get to meet Earl, I did on my TAFT trip, get to meet Russ Hodgkins who chaired Chikon One, which was amazing and he was at the first Worldcon and I got to meet Dave Koyer and Art Widner as well.
And it's fantastic to kind of get to interact with people who do connect right back to the start and I don't know whether any of those people have kind of written about their perception of the differences between fandom then and fandom now, but I agree with Liz so that would be interesting.
But it is really nice that there's this consistent throughline right back to the beginning of our community and I'm not always interested in using that as an excuse not to move forward as a community, but it is really nice to have that sense of tradition and of history and to understand our origins is a lovely thing to be able to do.
So yeah, it's a very great shame and as Alison says, only one remaining person who does kind of take us right back to the beginning.
I think Chikon H has said that they are going to honor Earl anyway as you would expect them to do.
I think that is the normal practice when guests of honor die between the announcement and the convention and hopefully they'll find some good ways to do that.
You can of course, you can't interact with people from the earliest days of fandom, but you know what they thought quite a lot because they live left of the fanzines and you can read those.
I mean, it's not true that everybody was a fanzine fan even back at the very beginning, but there were lots of fans fans around.
And yeah, no, Dave Kyle was always very fond of newsletters and he would always go into the newsletter room at every Worldcon and congratulate the team on doing what the best Worldcon newsletter ever.
And it wasn't until about the third time round that we worked out that we were sick or we should just kind of go, "Oh, that's nice."
Excellent.
[Music]
Okay, on the topic of Worldcons, Discom 3 have released their new COVID-19 policy and we've linked to the file 770 post about that in the show notes, which has not only the policy in question, but a plethora of comments you can read discussing people's thoughts on this announcement.
Basically, you can't go unless you're double vaccinated, you've got to wear a mask at all times and if there are reasons why you can't have had the vaccine and you can't wear a mask, you should look at getting a refund or attending virtually.
And you can read more about this, as I say, in this article in the show notes.
I think this in some ways makes a lot of sense and in some ways has made Alison very grumpy. So Alison, do you want to, maybe I should introduce your thoughts a bit more diplomatically? What do you reckon?
No, I mean, I don't think I was very grumpy, but you were saying reaction have been mostly positive.
I've not seen many negative takes.
And I have seen some negative stuff, but not a vast amounts. Most people are happy. This policy disenfranchises people who can't get vaccinated or cannot wear masks, both of which do actually exist in countries that are less benighted than the United States.
If you can't get vaccinated, you can get a your COVID, you will still get a COVID certificate. If your doctor said you cannot have a vaccine, you will still get a COVID certificate.
But that's not the case of the US, so it is disenfranchising people. It is disenfranchising everyone with a child under 12.
And the notion that the way that you're going to deal with marginal groups is to say, just don't come.
It's like taking the whole story on inclusivity and making it possible for people to do things back 50 years.
And, you know, they could do that and they think it's legal. I don't think it would be legal here, but I think it might be legal there.
So it would be interesting to see whether that's the case, but I think they could have gone quite a lot further to say, oh, right, no, we will make accommodations for people, but we will require a letter from your doctor or we will require you.
If you've got children, we'll require you to quarantine for two weeks before coming to the convention, something like that. They could have done these things if they wanted to.
And they decided, oh, no, we'll just, it's easier to just exclude chunks of the community.
The other thing that concerns me about this is that I don't think the clear masks that they're going, they may find that they're marvelous and it's all fine.
I'm interested to see how that goes. I don't know how doing program items through masks is going to work. I don't know whether it's actually going to be significantly better than being on Zoom.
I do know that what you do, if you sort of say, oh, well, we'll implement extremely stringent conditions in public area of the hotels is that you'll encourage people to go and socialize in room parties and other places where those conditions work.
Conditions won't pertain. You might go, oh, well, those are the people who don't care. But in fact, I'd rather see well ventilated public spaces and I'd like to see some testing, which they're not doing at all as far as I can see.
I think it's an interesting choice. And I hope everyone who goes has a phatactic time. They've also disenfranchised everyone in the UK, but in fact, that's just because we can't travel to America.
I don't know if we'll ever be able to travel to America again.
I feel less strongly about than Alison, all this probably because I do not have never had kids under 12. So, you know, this would not be something that would stop me going.
I think they're just in a very, very tricky situation.
And I suspect they thought this was the best way to get the majority of their attendees there because I think they not had a vaccine mandate and a mask mandate.
They would have also had a large number of people who said they didn't want to come because they didn't feel it was safe.
So I think they've chosen this route on some very difficult public health grounds.
I think there are problems. If they had tried to mandate quarantine for two weeks, well, you can't mandate quarantine for two weeks because you can't actually check on that one.
So you could ask people to do it. But obviously, if they felt they could run a convention on, please wear masks and please get vaccinated before you come if you're able.
Then they do that, but in fact, they feel they have to mandate it in order to get that to happen.
Yeah, I think it's really tricky. I think a large part of this is going to depend on how well they manage this kind of hybrid in-person virtual thing they're trying to pull off because obviously there are lots of people who can't go.
No one with children or 12 can go. People who cannot get vaccinated cannot go because there's no medical exemptions, even for that very small proportion of people who can't get vaccinated.
Obviously, it is going to be difficult to get people from non-U.S. or maybe Canada to the convention, partly because some of them are completely blocked from entering the country and partly because some of them are not vaccinated and will not be vaccinated by December and therefore can't come to the convention.
So I think it's really tricky and I would obviously like to see this not have to be the case, but I think when they have to decide now what they think they will be like in December and what they think they have to do to put on a safe convention, this is the route they've chosen.
And like we say, it's not new. It's the same approach that convergence com took earlier this month. I'm not sure if there are other U.S. conventions that have had the same plans.
I've not actually looked at what Dragoncom's policy is. I should look that one up.
And yeah, I can't comment on it from a legal standpoint. Obviously, just going to think this is something that they can do in the United States and given that other conventions, I wouldn't be surprised.
I'm not sure if the same is true in the UK or if there's a way you could say do this in the UK, but with sufficient opt outs.
And I think they should also be encouraging testing even with maximum vaccination with potentially thousands of people in one place.
And it is December in Washington, D.C. People are going to be socializing indoors. They are probably not going to be socializing outdoors.
I think you would try and encourage people to at least be doing lateral flow tests on a daily or every 48-hour basis, just in case.
I mean, lateral flow tests not perfect, but they catch a lot of positive cases if you could cut down the number of...
It's just another string to your bow, really.
Yeah, it's another string to your bow. You have your strings of vaccines and masks and social distancing and ventilation and testing.
And you put all those things together and you know, it's like the Swiss cheese model. You're less likely to get a big hole.
I think in general I am a little bit surprised they're not doing testing.
Liz informs me that the US does not have free lateral flow testing, which may have meant that D.C. felt unable to mandate every on take a lateral flow every day.
But I think if this was being done in the UK, we would probably be doing that.
Although I say that, but I don't know whether an overcon or a core flu or fantasy con are. I haven't really seen much from any of them.
So whenever I go to anything, I do lateral flow tests before I go to it and then after I come back.
And when you go onto the NHS website to report your result, it's always like, "Why would you be doing that? We can't see any reason.
This isn't one of the reasons why anyone would use a lateral flow test."
I'm kind of like, "You know what? Your messaging is way off."
So yeah, so I lateral flow before I go out pretty well.
Certainly before I go to a fake festival or a science fiction convention or anything like, "Well, meet my mates for drinking."
But that doesn't have any bearing on policies from UK conventions, right? Like, I agree with you. I also do that.
But like, the Discon has a more coherent COVID strategy than any of the British conventions happening for the rest of this year, I would say.
Even if we don't agree with necessarily how they're implementing it.
I think part of the difference is that I think for something like NovaCon, which is Friday through Sunday, taking a lateral flow say on the Friday morning and then not testing again, might be OK.
Whereas for a five-day event like WorldCon, you could potentially have people becoming kind of infected and symptomatic, sorry, not symptomatic, kind of becoming infected and becoming infectious kind of within the five days.
So maybe it's more important to try and get people to test midway through the con because then you might at least get alerted to the fact that you're going to have a super spreading event at your con.
Oh no, I mean, I completely agree with that. But like, I've just looked at the FantasyCon website and it doesn't even ask you to do a lateral flow before you sit off.
There's literally no COVID policy on their website at all.
NovaCon have said that they are going to have a COVID policy which reflects the state of affairs at the time they hold their convention and they have Dave Hicks doing this.
So they seem to have this in hand.
Their website notes that he is a dipney Bosch, a gradios, an ISO 18001 lead auditor, and he's won three nose rewards.
But it's not clear to me which of those qualifications puts him in better stead for the COVID policy.
Yeah, he's a health and safety professional, so he does know about this stuff.
Yeah, but like, it's not they don't have a policy.
Well, I mean, they shouldn't have a policy yet because they don't need to set their policy until a few weeks before the convention.
That might be fair.
That's not so true for the WorldCon where people make travel plans, but I think for NovaCon.
But they're expecting a lot of international visitors to NovaCon because it's been scheduled right after Corfley.
And I don't think Corfley has anything about COVID on their website.
So like, I think it's fair to criticize the weaknesses in the DC plan, but at least they've got one that they're talking about.
I'm a little bit concerned.
I mean, NovaCon say they will have one, which is something.
FantasyCon is in four weeks and has no mention and Corfley is in two months and has no mention.
And it's like, what are you doing? Like, I want to know because I've bought my Corfley membership, but if it turns out that anyone can go and have licked anything they want, I'm going to be pissed.
Well, I think you should be less pissed because I think people are overestimating the risks of this disease to the fully vaccinated.
So you might want, if you would say caring for somebody who is immunocompromised or couldn't have a vaccine for whatever reason, you might want to make different personal decisions.
If you're fully vaccinated, you're saying, "Oh, well, I might go pony trekking, but I wouldn't go to this convention because of the risk of getting a breakthrough case of COVID."
You're making very poor risk decisions because, or you know, you might travel on a motorway or cross or cross busy roads.
You know, it's not that dangerous, is it?
But I minimise my risk. If I'm going to cross the busy road, I will cross at the crossing. If I want to minimise my risk, then if I know everyone else at the convention is vaccinated, I know the chances of them having an infection are lower, and it seems to be the chances of them transmitting to other people are lower.
Whereas if I don't know if one of the convention is vaccinated, then there is a higher risk. So, you know, I don't think it's, you know, that, I mean, I don't think it's entirely overestimating risk, just that there is a risk and we know ways we can minimise that risk.
And we don't know at the moment, in what ways, cold flu and overcon are going to do that.
Yeah, and like, I think, I think in general, like, I am happy that overcon have thought about this and I'm not entirely sure what their policy will be, but I think they will at least be trying to minimise that risk.
But in the case of a convention that hasn't mentioned it at all, you're sort of like, well, how are you managing this risk?
Because I do think, although, like, I don't know, I'm not well versed enough in the biology of it to know what the actual risk is.
And I don't, I get the impression that this is actually not a well known thing and it's a sort of much controversy in many different circles.
Like, I want, if there is a significant risk, I want it to be mitigated.
And like, I'm not sure that requiring natural flow tests before setting off and requiring that if people can be vaccinated, they are vaccinated, is unreasonable.
And if the convention is not even willing to do that level of leadership, then I am not impressed by that.
Because even if it's milder than it might be, I still don't want to get it if I can help it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So, Corflu, if you're the Corflu Committee and you're listening to this, which I'm sure you are, then it's time to sort out your COVID policy and, um, incidentally, please don't copy me into the emails.
Thanks.
Corflu's been copying me into emails while running a virtual convention.
Brilliant. That must be amazing.
And then they, having done that, which was fine, they carried on copying me into emails about traveling techniques and PR4 and all sorts.
And I am not on the Corflu Committee.
I'm just deleting these emails unread at this point.
You know, people end up with a cat because, you know, a cat walks in.
I think this is how you got the Corflu Committee.
No.
Oh, no.
Anyway, I had a more serious point, which is, I think you can tell just from our discussion here that, you know, the three of us probably have slightly different ways.
And we have, like, slightly different attitudes to COVID risk.
And I think one reason as well for having your convention policy out way ahead of time is to find out what your membership thinks.
Um, because I think it's going to be really useful to you to know whether your COVID policy has just made 50% of your attendees say, you know, actually, I don't feel I'm going to attend this year.
And that's probably something you want to know sooner rather than later.
We emailed FantasyCon to ask whether they had a COVID policy and they say that they do is just that they've only put it on their emailing list and they haven't updated their website.
And that's why I couldn't find it.
Leaving that aside.
The policy is basically the situation is changeable.
They don't have control of the whole venue and it is difficult to mandate requirements and the political climate and some spaces will make it difficult to achieve distancing.
They are asking attendees to wear face masks indoors. They are providing sanitizer in all the rooms.
They are encouraging distancing where possible.
And they are going to encourage people to take a lateral flow test before attending.
And if they have symptoms to get a full COVID test and if they are not well, please do not attend.
So don't go if you've got COVID.
That's important.
And they do also note if a group of people wish to sit or stand close together they can, but they would ask attendees to respect that other attendees may need space.
I mean, okay, I guess.
I'm quite comfortable with that sort of policy because I kind of think if you're going to a convention it's because you want to see your friends.
But I'll grant you it's a lot wishy washer than the, than the, um, discount one.
I would be requiring masks in, um, flow spaces between program items and I would be requiring natural flow tests.
I don't think I would be asking nicely on those.
And I hope that because I think what happens is you get what happens on the trains, which is they ask people to wear a face mask and then about 5% of people do.
And that I don't like.
The thing about lateral flow tests is that you can't actually mandate them.
So what you can do is say, please can everyone take a lateral flow test, but I mean, any checking process you have is going to be a bit rubbish.
This is the same thing that happened with the mask because people argued when the government made wearing masks, not wearing masks in shops illegal.
That it would be very difficult to enforce.
But what happened is a large number of people started wearing masks because it had been mandated and then stopped again when it was no longer mandated.
And it didn't really matter that there wasn't a coherent enforcement policy. It was the fact that it was mandatory that did it for a lot of people.
And I think there is a difference in even if your process for checking whether people are obeying is a bit rubbish, you still see it uptick in, in doing it.
If you say you have to rather than we encourage you to.
Yes, so I have a little policy hat on here, which is that you cannot mandate things without sanctions.
So if you say something, you must do something, then you have to have something that says, and if you don't, this will happen.
You don't have to have enforcement, but you do have to have sanctions.
But we probably don't have sanctions in practice.
So I think it's still fine to say we want everyone to do this.
But I think if you say you must do this, then you are mandating it. So you say otherwise we will kick you out of the convention.
I think you just have to say you should take a lateral flow test before attending.
You can't say you must because we can't make you.
But I think if you say something like you should take a lateral flow test before attending, maybe it's a bit more forceful than it would be.
It would be a good idea if you took a lateral flow test.
And the only other way to do it is to have a bunch of like desks where you have to watch people swap their own noses.
But I feel that's going to have a risk.
I also like that they'll have sanitizer because having been to two festivals, one of which said, "Oh, we will have sanitizing stations everywhere and did."
And one of which said, "We will have sanitizing stations everywhere and didn't."
I know which one I prefer.
The UK Games Expo did was they said that lateral flow tests were mandatory before attending, and you had to bring the text message you got from the NHS.
Obviously that would be trivially easy to forge.
But the thing is it's not so much about, obviously there are loopholes in that way of doing it that you could drive a bus through.
But the thing is, I think it would still mean you got more obeying than just sort of asking nicely.
That was actually something that got implemented after they said, "Oh, we're going to ask nicely."
And social media just went, "What?" and said, "What?" for long enough that they changed their minds eventually.
So I do think the other thing is if our community does not make a loud enough noise about, actually, we'd quite like you to say this a bit more seriously,
our conventions won't, and that will make our conventions more risky, which I don't like for.
How much COVID did UK Games Expo have?
I don't know.
They had 10,000 people.
Yes.
That's quite a lot of people.
And it totally, listener to the show, Andrew January says that a lot of the people he knows who work on stands at the UK Games Expo got pinged.
If listeners have read about anyone who contracted COVID and thinks they contracted at the Games Expo, so please let us know.
Yeah, I was going to say, I think it's interesting.
There's probably a psychological effect of, "Please bring us your text message because, yes, you could forge it,
but then you have to make the deliberate act to basically say it's negative when it's not done, put it in the website and get text message."
I think that's a much higher barrier than just not doing your lateral flow because you think you feel a bit snotty.
I think your vaccinations, if you can, and test and bring us a thing is good.
Yeah, the Octa Thought podcast endorses COVID vaccination.
It does.
I also wonder, what is it that you get out of being at a convention that you can do if you are masked at all times and keeping a social distance of a meter?
So, what way is that better than Zoom?
So, I think there are many people who prefer in-person things to Zoom.
Think about all the people who haven't been at the first Thursday's on Zoom, for instance, and imagine how much they'd rather have a first Thursday where everyone was masked and unvaccinated people were banned than they would a Zoom one.
Given that for them, the Zoom one means there isn't one versus there being one.
I think you and me are biased here in that we have spent an inorn out of time on Zoom.
I understand where you're coming from on that, but I also understand that there are people for whom that maths is very different.
Yeah, no, I'm not.
I don't think I'm, oh, we should have, what was it?
Lots of young people cram into tents and share vapes.
Yeah, I don't think I want the Ted White room party of COVID policies.
I don't think it would be fine to say that if you can be vaccinated, you must be vaccinated, and if you cannot be vaccinated, it's not just because you have some personal conviction.
It's because you have a letter from a medical professional saying that in their medical decision, the risks of vaccination to you are too grateful to let it be happen.
I think it's fine to say masks in public places, but not for speakers, and I understand that there's a risk there.
I would recommend lateral flow twice before you go, and then once every 48 hours, if it's going on, so that would be my COVID policy in a nutshell, and open windows.
Can we all have lots of ventilation? Put a sweater on. It'll be November.
Yeah, probably about 12 sweaters on, I think.
As you know, I went to Washington, DC in November and it was perfectly fine, and I'm talking about core flu and Novocon, which I am going to rather than discount, which I was never ever going to.
So, because, I mean, I wouldn't fly. The notion that I get on an airplane. I'm sure airplanes are very safe.
Are you? Liz, tell us how safe airplanes are.
So, I mean, I'm not an expert in air ventilation, but from what I've read, they are actually quite safe because they do do a lot of air recirculation, actually.
I have seen a case which I think was where they traced the transmission to people going to the bathroom and taking their masks off, and then the next person using the bathroom and inhaling them.
But, I mean, I've got to be honest, I've been on several long haul flights. Every single person was wearing a mask apart from when they were eating.
There's not a lot of people on, especially the long haul flights at the moment, and so it felt fairly safe to me.
Actually, it's not, I'm lying. It's got nothing to do with getting on a plane. It's got, I am not spending two hours in a US immigration queue.
It's that sort of encounter that I'm travelling in general contains risks that I find very difficult to mitigate.
Well, it's lucky you don't want to do that, Alison, because they don't want you to, I don't.
I know they don't.
I don't.
But I'm pretty sure the most reckless thing I have done in the past week is to eat breakfast in Leon in Heathrow eternal too.
On the topic of Disc on three's COVID policy, another convention, as Liz, I think, mentioned that had a similar policy was convergence.
And File 7.7.7.7.7.8 did recently link to a Twitter thread in which they said there had been a COVID case in an attendee, but we believe that this has not led to any at-con transmission.
By which I mean, we haven't found anyone say it has and we feel that if it had done, someone would have said it did.
I think there were two people who tested positive after conventions, actually, because there's, I'll generally think there's two on their Facebook page.
One of whom thought they may have contracted it at the convention, but it doesn't look like it's been a widespread thing.
I mean, it's not like, you know, we're going to have a convergent strain of coronavirus, like you have the whisk on strain of noravirus or whatever.
Do we want to talk about Eastercon 2023?
Oh, yeah. No, it looks like I'm bidding for it with some friends.
Hey, do we want to introduce this better than that?
Or are we happy with that?
So, at Eastercon this year, I said to the convention that it might want to pause before seating Eastercon 2023 with Vanessa and her team and go and have a little think about it.
And as part of the process of having a little think about it, I am working on a bid with some friends.
I don't think we're quite ready to say who we all are and that we're announcing, but it's definitely a bid.
We had a proper meeting.
We're going off to some sites. We have a philosophy, which is that we're going to start to reach out to the Eastercon community and say, "Would you like Eastercon 2023 to look like?"
And we will try and deliver it for you.
And I hate to use the word "hybrid convention."
We are, I think, committed from the off to having both in person and virtual elements if we can.
And that is part of the structure and planning for this event that we think that we are, even in 2023, it is a racing certainty that some portion of our community would prefer to attend the convention online if that was an option for them.
So, that's part of the deal.
Yeah, more stuff coming soon.
Well, soonish.
I mean, I think we'll have a proper launch no later than Nevercon.
Can you, is there anything else you can tell us, Alison, any tidbits that we might be able to exclusively reveal? Can you reveal the first letter of one of the people you're working with?
I'm boldness me.
So, that's Ellie.
So, yeah, no, it's, I think everyone's fine to talk names, but I don't think we're quite there yet.
We've got a team that covers, I guess, kind of site and access and comms and treasury and those sorts of things.
So, it's got the infrastructure stuff in place, but we don't really yet have a program lead.
So, if that's something you'd really, really like to do for these to come, get in touch.
Alison, can you reveal if you'll be having a traditional committee structure or some kind of wild anarchy?
No, it looks like we're going to have a chair who is Caroline Mullen and a set of people with roles.
And my role's probably going to be comms.
As you can see, I'm doing a great job at the moment.
But that's because we need things in place like social media accounts and websites and that sort of stuff.
And we haven't really.
Very important to have a website. I've been told.
So, no, it has a traditional East
Com structure. It's experienced people, but who are not all the same people that you've seen on East Com
Committee before. Yeah, some of them are the same people you've seen on East Com
Committee before, you know, what it's like.
I'm really looking forward to your East Com
2023, bit, Alison. I think it's going to be brilliant.
So, and we've had a chat with Vanessa. I think, oh, this is the thing I did want to say is that we've had a chat
with a visitor or Caroline, a chat with Vanessa. And we feel like we're, what we're doing is offering the
East Com a couple of alternatives for what they want the
commercial to look like. Because I think persistence is going for something slightly different.
Oh, yeah, and we have a name.
So, our name is conversation.
Oh.
Because I think when we were talking about Erl, and we're talking there about the thread of continuity,
that if you're saying, well, you're not just putting on a show when you're on the East
Com, you're actually building something for the community. What you're building is the opportunity to have those
conversations across the, across the community through time, all of that stuff.
That was two scoops. I'm happy with that. That's how many I get when I go to the
e-screen shop.
So, hopefully that's scoopy enough for you without me giving too much. Because we really don't have a lot yet.
We have like a vast pile of notes and thoughts.
[Music]
Before we end the podcast, we are going to talk about, well, sorry.
Before we end, the podcast is just a very quick plug for FutureCon 2021.
This is a YouTube based convention with items in a variety of time zones and with a variety of authors.
It's running on the weekend of the 3rd of September 2021. Allison and I, true to form, will be in the bar,
because we're going on a pub crawl listeners.
We'll be at a totally different bar.
Yeah. No. Well, we'll be in the same bar as one another.
Oh, I hope so. Yeah. Along with some other people.
If we're not something as compatible, we've been a bad pub crawl leader.
What is your feeling about like pub crawls? You know, does your pub crawl have the no man left behind ethos, John?
Yeah, better bloody half.
No man, woman or small fairy creature from the Crab Nebula.
I mean, I should mention that Claire and I have a kind of pub crawl ethos, which was typified by our Reading pub crawl,
where we crawl to one pub and then stop.
A single brewery.
And it's fine. Yes, I will try and go to some of future con because I like that it's not just authors, actually.
They've got some fans and they've got publishers, you know, an interesting looking panel on like small,
pest publishing around the world.
And they are incredibly international and show that by doing things in a, you know, many, suitable for many time zones.
And I think they'll all be on YouTube afterwards. So even if you are in the pub, you can catch up later.
There you go. That was my plug.
Good, good plug.
That was the 39th episode of the Octo-Thought Podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
[Music]
Now, I sold Alison at PlayStation 4 on the day that we did our live recording.
And so for the last two or three weeks, Alison has been exploring Horizon Zero Dawn, which is a game me and Liz like a lot.
Alison, do you like Horizon Zero Dawn?
It's stuck at the moment.
So I haven't actually played for a few days because I got stuck and then it needs a fair chunk of time to get unstuck.
I went down into a cauldron because I knew that there was it from the internet.
There was a snap more at the bottom of it and I was like, I can deal with a snap more.
But it turned out to actually be a snap more under a ravager.
And my child is like, "Ah, no, ravagers, they're like bait. You just knock the cannon off their back so you pick up the cannon and you shoot everything."
And I'm like, "Yeah, no, I'm dead now."
So yeah, so I need to get better at Horizon Zero Dawn.
Horizon Zero Dawn is an open world game that's slightly less open world than you think it is.
I feel like there's always a very clearly defined thing that you should probably be doing next.
And if you're not doing it, then I mean, you can do things at different orders.
It's not that tied down.
But if you're not doing it, then you probably, it's quite easy to find yourself going off stray a bit.
But it's pretty good. It's very good.
PlayStation 4, quite nice.
If anyone wants a second hand Blu-ray player, let me know.
Because...
Yeah, as soon as you get a PlayStation, you do not need a standalone DVD or Blu-ray player anymore, which is good.
Because I was looking at my Blu-ray player and going, "Oh, that's not useful, is it?"
I've watched about three Blu-rays in the last year and it probably is slightly better than the BS4.
But it's also made by Sony, so it's probably exactly the same, really.
And if anyone would like a Blu-ray player, they should get in touch.
I kind of forgot to eat...
Horizon Zero Dawn is very pretty as well.
And it has a heroine that apparently people on the internet think is ugly because she doesn't...
She's living in a post-apocalyptic spoiler.
Post-apocalyptic world doesn't clearly have access to make up other than interesting forms of face paint.
But she does apparently have access to...
Or hairdressing, actually.
She is still doing the obvious thing and cutting her hair short, she wears it in dreads.
She does apparently have access to eyebrow tweezers, which I find quite strange because she has extremely perfectly formed eyebrows.
And I found this incredibly distracting, but otherwise.
I have extremely perfectly formed eyebrows and I do not block them, so she might just be very lucky.
Not like this, you don't.
There's a lot of criticism of Ayloy on the internet.
I don't really understand it because I thought I really liked her as a character.
Yeah, she's great. She's apparently not the sort of video game lead character that 14 year old boys like.
That's the issue.
I will also say I am quite spoiler-overse as many listeners may be aware, but I regard Horizon Zero Dawn being an post-apocalyptic future as on the cover of the video game and therefore not really.
I think if it's on the cover of the video game it's not a spoiler.
Okay, so should we talk about Palm Springs again?
I mean, I am aware that I am more spoiler-overse than many of the people I regularly converse with.
I don't always handle it well.
I don't think it's much of a spoiler to say that it's post-apocalyptic.
I mean, you learn about three minutes into the game that there's giant robot dinosaurs and that there's kind of bits and pieces left over from the previous civilization.
Yeah, I think that very first scene where she discovers her focus in the ruins is like if you don't...
It's like one of the very first things in the game I think tells you pretty explicitly that it is.
So apologies for anyone who's playing it and hasn't.
Yeah, so Horizon Zero Dawn is very pretty. It's a very pretty game.
I took a screenshot and set it to John, so I will find it.
I mean, I had to implement photo mode.
The photo mode thing is quite fun.
It is quite fun.
And Horizon Forgotten West is coming in six months time, so if there is another Hugo Award for Best Video Game, it will be eligible at the 2023 World Con.
And we can talk about sequels.
Yeah, I was thinking much more depressingly.
Like, I played Horizon Zero Dawn during like the first lockdown, so maybe in six months time we'll have another variant.
Another lockdown and I can play Horizon Forbidden West, obsessively for two weeks.
And that's where I'm going to end the episode and do the beat, please.
On that happy note. So hurrah!
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod in Competec.com, used under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beat.
Keep