So, I think that's probably the end of OctaThorpe.
Oh, what? For this week? Oh, okay. Good. Brilliant.
Hello everyone and welcome to OctaThorpe, a podcast for Science Fiction and Science Fiction
fandom. This episode is coming to you on the 10th of June 2021. I'm John Coxon,
I'm Alison Scott, and I'm Liz Batty. And our cunning plan succeeded because people wrote us
letters of comment. They really did. In droves. His droves have secret
negative connotations I'm unaware of. Nope. So we had a tweet of comment from Andrew who said
that she left the BSFA at the point that trying to pay to be a member was incredibly
complicated because she had to pay by check. And that is a good point. I do think the BSFA does
now allow you to pay by direct debit. And in fact, they're encouraging all standing order
members to switch to direct debit because it's easier for them. So, or maybe it's not direct
debit, maybe it's maybe it's like PayPal debit card subscriptions or something. But anyway,
they are moving towards a more joined up digital method.
There was, as I recall, a continual problem with standing orders where people would set
up a standing order for a fixed price and then the BSFA would raise their memberships and people
would completely fail to update their standing orders. And so they had this continual thing of
like a handful of people who were paying at the prices from like six years ago or 10 years ago.
So that's probably why they would like you to do it in a way that allows them to actually
charge their full cost. Yeah. But I will say again, membership organizations where all you get for
your membership is a bunch of paper magazines are a creation of essentially the Victorian age.
And you don't tend to get new organizations that work that way and organizations that do work that
way should consider whether there are other ways they could work. But we're having a panel on this
at punctuation for Shadowy. Join early, join often. No, please don't join often because every time
you join off and I have to write some emails and I don't like that, I have given up writing emails
for Lent. Fair enough. Good to know, good to know. Duncan McGregor tweeted at us to say that he
thinks board games podcasts may be closer to the classic SF fanzine interaction model than many
fanzines and podcasts in SF. Now I have a list and I don't think this is just true of board game
podcasts, Duncan, but I do think it is true because another community that does this is tech
podcasts. I remember of only some tech podcasts. I remember of five discord servers and Slack servers
involved with podcasts. So I am on two board game podcast servers and three tech podcast servers.
I know that listener Andrew January is on a couple of servers for various Twitch streamers in which
they use those to communicate with their communities. So I do think that a lot of this kind of community
interaction is happening on discord and Slack's. And that is that is a good point and one that we
did not cover last time. So thank you very much for your tweet. And this podcast does not have a
discord, but it does hang out on some discord's. So you know, you can find us on discord. Come and
join anonymous Claire. If you don't know how, just ask everyone you know called Claire until you find
the right one. Anonymous Care is a discord server for people who are adjacent to British
Fandom. So it's possible that you might not qualify if your only contact with British Fandom is
that you listen to this podcast. But you probably do. Phil Dyson tweeted us to say on the subject
of Canada and music Spike mentioned back in Montana overdrive. But that overlooks the finest
moment yet recorded by Winnipeg's two greatest musical sons, Randy Bachmann and Neil Young. And
he sent us a YouTube video. And if you go and look at his tweets, you can watch the YouTube video.
And it is indeed loud. We'll put a link in the show notes. Obviously, you don't have we're not
going to put a link to the tweet from which you then have to click through and get the link to the
thing. If we're mentioning the the video on YouTube, we're going to put the link to the video on YouTube
in the podcast show notes. All right, hang on. A YouTube link that Alex note on which Alison insisted.
Done. We also got a couple of letters of kind from people who wrote in saying, thank you for
like asking how we were. We're very well. Thank you. How are you? So Maggie and Karen Shafer wrote in
and Karen talked about her jigsaw puzzles. And she says that she expects that we're not truly
interested in jigsaw puzzles. But I know that Liz and Alison are both jigsaw puzzle fiends.
And I do not have the patience. Oh, Alison shaking her head. But Liz
loves them, Karen loves them. I don't actually do physical jigsaw. But I found that I could do
online jigsaws while doing other things like for instance, recording podcasts. And I just find
it very relaxing. I like jigsaws, but they're in the class of things like Filking, where if I had
an infinite life expected, if somebody came along tomorrow said, congratulations, Alison,
you're immortal. I find a lot more time for jigsaw puzzles in my life and and and and Filking. And
quite a lot of other things actually, like I definitely learned Japanese properly this time.
Karen also says, did you know that Winnipeg is famed for the Ukrainian pierogies? And, you know,
I like Polish pierogies, but I have to look for Ukrainian ones now.
Yes, not to mention walleye, a tasty freshwater fish. If you're lucky you did the
no walleye cheeks, there are only two per fish. So, so if I go to Winnipeg, if Winnipeg wins,
and I go to Winnipeg, I will definitely look out for walleye cheeks. Okay, I've also just noticed
that on the picture of the jigsaw that Karen sent us, it says one piece missing. And I'm not
sure I have the mental fortitude to be able to cope with that. Oh, you'd be really sad if you
did the whole thing. And then there was one piece left over. Yeah, I'm sorry, one piece missing.
If you do a whole, I mean, one of the things you could do if you're a bad human being is to
take a jigsaw and then put one extra piece into every jigsaw in your local charity shop.
Because I think finishing a jigsaw or discovering you've got a piece left over would be
awesome. It's not the way it normally works. As somebody who's a connoisseur of electronic
jigsaw list, you won't have this experience. Electronic jigsaw, you don't tend to get to the
end and discover there's a piece missing. Now you do, because in the platform I use for electronic
jigsaw, sometimes you find that one piece has kind of got hidden under all the other pieces.
And then you can't find it. But it also lets you finish the jigsaw with one or two pieces missing
on the assumption you might have done this by accident. I'm not sure whether to applaud the
platform for having faithfully recreated the experience of a physical jigsaw or to wonder
why they have chosen to recreate this specific part of physical jigsaw. Yeah, so do they also
recreate the status of crushing on we that comes from spending six weeks working on the 2000
piece jigsaw and they're discovering there was a piece missing. Crushing on we is definitely the
name of my next contemplative funk album. I don't mind missing pieces in jigsaw so maybe this just...
Liz! Yeah, I'm just in a completely different zone in the rest of you. Stop boasting about your
excellent mental health. Octa thought the podcast of science fiction and science fiction fandom
at jigsaw's IQ analysis. Why love about this is sometimes when we have letters of comment and we
have topics in the show notes I can predict where those topics will end up. In this case I would
not have predicted like just my or Liz's robust mental health like being the pointer which we
wrapped up discussion of Karen's letter that is most excellent and this is why we need more
layers of comment. I don't know if this was a sign of excellent mental health I will you know if I don't
know where I'm going with this. It certainly seems very very balanced and sensible. Yeah.
Oh yeah I can finish jigsaw there's a couple of bits missing and I don't get upset about that.
That is not my personal experience. Oh I see okay okay. Oh no. Oh no. I've luckily
have given up anger. Listeners writing and tellers which one of us is um which which side you are
on in this debate. If you could write in and tell us the integer number of pieces that you are
comfortable being missing from a jigsaw I will draw a graph of octa thought listeners
against number of pieces missing. Me and Alison are zero Liz what's your number?
Well it's not an integer it's probably a fraction it's probably like a proportion of
missingness of the jigsaw isn't it? Oh shoot good point what's your fact what's your percentage
missing? I don't know I let you know when I've got like 95% of this jigsaw done and see if I'm annoyed.
So as I said I think having zero or one pieces missing would be quite zero is fine one piece
missing is quite distressing finishing a jigsaw and discovering that you had minus three pieces
missing or 2.6 pieces missing or i pieces missing would be really quite
discombobulating. All right if I discovered I had i pieces missing from a jigsaw I would be
discombobulated because I think that's the sign that physics has gone wrong and the elder ones
are invading so yeah Maggie also wrote to us saying um that she liked that um she liked that we did
a little discussion corner for this last episode she can look up jargon but it can be hard to look
up why things are considered important particularly for local fandoms and she asks this is her first
world con and there seems to be a lot of internal politics becoming visible is this typical or is
it just a silly question and I do wonder whether uh I think it's a function it's it's fractal
there's more internal politics the harder you look much like a coastline but also there's more
politics so some of it is internal but some of it is caused by the world con is coming under
greater pressure than it used to because it's becoming more global which means it's representing
more different communities and the hugos in particular are much higher profile than they were I think
even ten years ago but certainly than 20 or 30 years ago and that has really changed the the
whole dynamic of the politics of the world con um that gets me a chance to tick off something
that's further down the um list which is the hugo verter packet is finished I mean my bits are
sort of finished and I'm very pleased about that and it should be with you in a week or so let's
not make any I think there's an official line which is it is in preparation and we will let
you know when it's done okay excellent stuff well done Alison for doing that good good good
she also says I'm looking forward to hearing Alison's take on someone being a professional
enthusiast so if we get to um the phrase rampant self-promotion later in this episode you'll get to
hear DC congratulates Alison on her guest of honor thing that is the week after punctuation so it'll
be just after the next episode and I'll plug it together it is called conspire and it is the annual
general meeting of the British Science Fiction Association and the Science Fiction Foundation
and they also have guests giving talks and there's a panel and um the other two guests are
Tarda Thompson and John Clute um so that all sounds very good to me it'll be a good day and it's free
come along that is pretty good company to be in yeah no I don't know why they've invited me I
know I'm not like yeah god so we've got also a couple of things talking about fanzines which
we're going to use to seamlessly segue into our first topic so um Peter Sullivan sent us a tweet
saying that my point about lack of innovation in PDF fans is fair and notes that at one point
it looked as if high frequency was going to be the new innovation with zines like Vegas fandom weekly
the drink tank and science fiction San Francisco um my wife is fanya was one of the editors of
sfsf when it was a going concern um and the drink tank is chris carseers uh fanzine which went away
and then came back again there's I can't remember how many issues there's been at least 400 but
many many issues and yeah that's a good point there was there was a point of which it looked like
uh high frequency was going to be the new innovation uh I think that has mostly gone away in favor of
I think high frequency is still an innovation I just don't think the people doing high frequency
fan writing and doing it in PDFs anymore like far 770 I met someone who insisted that every single
blog post was an issue and on that metric far 770 has published many issues now um I'm not sure
whether mike glyer thinks every blog post is an issue so we could ask him mike give you a listening
get in touch i'm not sure mike glyer has a radio it's not going to get podcasts on the radio
uh so chris carseer wrote in saying that he's a fanzine nerd no really and he said that jenny
planet doesn't get many letters um but uh they just don't get letters or many mentions on social
media and he says it's weird that apparently nominating us for hugos is how most readers interact
with us which is uh well good stuff chris thank you very much and he notes that um he thinks you
can tell where podcasts come out of fanzine tradition because of the interaction with the
audience which is something we mentioned uh with duncan's tweet earlier but it's a good point
mark plumber says that he is cheered to hear um him and claire described by drona's more innovative
um and talks about the early electronic fanzines um which i think um uh allison has
things she wants to say about i just picked up one tiny little point from this which was when you
say that freq high frequency is an innovation or was looking to be the innovation for some time
and the term electronic email fanzines started in the mid 90s um when i got online which was 1993
the fanzine done by evland and mark leper the empty void had already been around and online for a
very very long time and it was in fact in the form of usenet post i mean it was also a mailing list so
you could get it by email or you could get it posted to usenet um usenet was kind of like
discord for the past framp framp readers listeners whatever um and that was weekly so that was a
weekly fanzine they're still doing and this is the amazing thing because they are still doing it
they have been doing it for over 40 years um it now contains things like update on evland's hip
which you know is i think one of the things that happens to people after they've been doing
fancies for more than 40 years every single week um but it's there it's um and i think the fanzine
and maybe both mark and evland separately either have hugos or at least have been nominated for hugos
this work but yeah so it's not it's kind of a very all all the ideas are new again
it comes round and round but it was all it was always electronic i mean i'm sure you it was
possible to get it on paper if you were in the right place and certainly i know people who get it
probably still get it religiously every week and print it out because you know
but it's there uh we will put a link to it in the show notes because you could go and read it online
it's online he notes that and i went to print only until 2012 when there was a huge
hike in international postage and um mark and claire started doing e-pubs then when people had
e-readers and him and claire both got e-readers and he says he's not aware of anyone else doing
uh an e-pub fanzine before they did it in august 2012 so i immediately sent him a link to a copy
of my fanzine procrastinations which was an e-pub in 2011 uh because i think i was the first i'm
happy to be proven wrong but i it's certainly in like the fanzine circles i was running in
it was something i wanted to uh because i was having this rant 10 years ago and the fact that
the rant still exists in almost exactly the same form uh says a lot i think but yes i do think
you know e-pubs are good more people should do e-pubs don were you sending your e-pubs directly
to people's kindles because i think that is uh an area where i really enjoy that just sometimes
i open my kindle and update everything is on it and a new banana wings pops up it's great so uh
no i would let people download them the old-fashioned way mainly because um i don't have a kindle
yeah i'm not sure if you could i mean i'm not even sure if you could send stuff in in 2011 you
definitely could buy 2012 because that's how i get to my banana wings fix and obviously you lock
religiously liz no i'm a terrible person who's very bad at sending locks yes so john foister
did sent text emails as fanzines that he designed to be read in um landscape because he thought
that most people would be reading them on their computers and that that he is still the case that
quite a lot of stuff you see coming in in electronic fanzine form is nevertheless clearly designed to
be written to be read as as a full pages and now i quite like reading things that are formatted
for a full pages on my iPad but i know that lots of people don't so yeah mark mentions that in a kind
of you know at one point if you were writing if you're making a pdf your fanzine everyone would
be reading it on a computer monitor but now actually pdfs work much more uh work much more nicely on
tablets and quite a lot of people have tablets it's also possible you know with with my phone being
basically a giant thing now with high resolution that i could also read pdfs quite nicely on my
phone how big how big is your phone liz um i mean this doesn't really work on on camera on a podcast
does it but it's this big Alison jesus uh for the listener i think it's roughly
imagine liz was happy was holding up a sort of averagely sized chopping board and then just add
a little bit round the edges and that's how big liz's phone is yeah it's probably
signed that you should not buy phones uh sight unseen uh on the internet um unless you want a big one
which is actually not true for other things that you buy on the seed site on seed on the internet
when they tend to turn up quite small i have google it and it is uh 163 millimeters buying
76 millimeters so it's quite hefty no and i think i think you are probably right that uh pdfs work
better on um on phone screens than they did 10 years ago uh because obviously phones have gotten
bigger and the resolutions have gotten better um i'm going to try loading a randomly selected
phanzine on my phone and it's loading uh so this is 0.1 against pdfs much bigger than e-bubs and so
it's still loading i might just keep all of this silence in i'm not gonna try this
this live phanzine demo the other thing is obviously that you you can't um you can't do things
like if you are um if your eyesight is not very good you can't do things like um adjust the tech
size um in in terms of kind of like doing it automatically with like set of accessibility
features and there's just there's a bunch of little things that make it worse when you can't
assume what someone's reading it on um and i do think in general i'm much more likely to read e-bubs
on my phone just because they have so many little kind of kind of features like that just before we
move on to something else my other thing i will say on phanzine delivery mechanisms is that if you
have the RSS reader feed bin which you can subscribe to at feedbin.com you can have it um
convert emails into things you read in RSS reader and so i subscribe to transfer orbits and
another phanzine uh in my RSS reader and i enjoy that very much um we should probably say that feed
bin is a paid service um i love it three dollars a month something like that yeah five i don't
it's fine it's not it's not huge john how are you going to handle art in your pursine because that's
what i wonder about with sort of e-pubs is they're not really as great for art i mean you can't do
stuff like having the art in the corner and having the text flow around it like you would in a in a
physical artifact but you can do like you can kind of put images in e-pubs like without much trouble
so i don't know whether i don't think it's a problem to have a picture in an e-pub it might be a
problem to have like art uh text flow around it as opposed to having text then image then text um
but i don't know i don't necessarily think that's a big problem i am now holding up my iPad
because art's lovely eyes lovely in i for all i pads i mean it just you get even bigger i pads
than this i believe mark also mentions in his letter the fact that putting together all the
different versions that they do for banana wings is drudge work and this was quite resonant for me
because i've just been doing this work on the hugo voter packet and the thing about the hugo
voter packet is they're not actually more work than a lot of other tasks involved in putting a big
convention together but it feels more a lot of it feels more drudge like and i think that thing
about converting formats and getting things in the right place and making sure that everything is
reasonably consistent is is very thankless work that has as mark says it feels like work and and
we tend to like afanak to feel like not work to feel like things that are fun even if they are
actually taking quite a lot of time and evolve quite a lot of background work so i thought that
was an interesting point i think for me doing the layout work also feels like work layouts
fun bit i mean it can be but no doing the layout in wordpress is obviously extremely painful so
yeah there's that but also like doing stuff like the layout of my taff report which was like a hundred
pages in in design it that very much feels like work whereas doing like a little newsletter in
east conning in pages feels fun and like you just get to like spend two hours mucking about and then
publish it um so i do think there is a the i think the thing that i find doesn't feel like work
is splitting these things into small chunks that are regular which is one of the reasons why we do
a regular sub one hour podcast rather than an irregular marathon which i know some podcasts
especially in the fanish space do but the other reason are like we've transitioned lulzine to
basically being an article a month and that feels much more fun than having it come out
four times less frequently but with four times more articles which and i don't know because
it's the same amount of work but it definitely one feels way more like work than the other and
for me it's that regularity and size of work that that i think but i think you're right that um
it's all about finding the ways in which you have fun while you're doing the fanak because you
don't want it to feel like work um so far as you can make it not feel like work i'd say that you know
a lot of the work i do for conventions and things is quite boring grunt work or at least a lot of
it can be like if you're putting together a program there are some fun bits which are deciding what
you should do and who should go on them and then you also have to send and reply to like
six thousand emails and um you know put things into a schedule and move them about and it's
basically sitting in front of a computer doing a lot of stuff which feels a lot like what you do
in an office job in front of a computer anyway yeah so that programming was one of the other
tasks because i thought probably felt quite a bit like this yeah i don't find i mean i don't find
it super tedious but maybe because i do slightly different things on a day to day basis and i guess
i found i find the outcome quite satisfying satisfying enough that i don't mind basically
sitting in front of my laptop a lot of the time moving program items about and seeing if one of
them turns red yeah that makes sense um i think fanak for me in terms of con running con running
is way more fun when i'm doing the con running while drinking a beer with other people on zoom
than it is when i'm sitting on my own not drinking a beer doing the con running and so i think that's
the other thing like for me the way we've been doing a lot of the punctuation work is that we will
just have evenings where we're not really necessary to each other in terms of like having actions that
rely on one another but we can hang out and like just natter like a virtual office i think what
we're discovering here listeners is that talking to people and personal interactions are important
and good and i think that is a revelation and we should probably publicize in some sort of
psychology journal and liz as chief mental health haver should be the lead author
it's really interesting actually because there are some sorts of work i quite like some sorts of
fiddly tedious work and that i'd include quite a lot of photo choppy stuff and also the air table
air table is the back end database that um that punctuation is using um that sort of stuff i really
like to do on my own with only electronic music or other people's podcasts for company and then
there's other stuff like um i don't know you know i think i've got a long list of things that i might
do tonight like like i spy at punctuation that's obviously going to be much more if it happens
it'll be much more fun done during our drunk connections evening tonight and i think for me the things
that i find super fun even though i know lots of other people find quite drudgworky are programming
computer programming find that enormously fun i can get sucked into that for hours and the other
one is tidying up i can tidy up i love tidying up listeners john please come to my house i have
occasionally tidied things up where people have been annoyed at me for instance because i apply
my tidying up in both the digital and and physical realms and i have learned things about the the
apt times to do that and when i should absolutely on no account be doing that stop it john stop it
why are you still doing that uh see also john and allison had a row which i think we're actually
taking as a topic for next time because i we had a row about something totally different but
the reason we had that row was that i was still really angry about john messing with my air table
in real time the previous day so that was a complete fail in terms of human being interaction thing
don't tidy things up when people are using them that that that is a point of reflection for john
for sure yeah as i got a bit older i would find that sometimes instead of having parties where
you've come down in the morning and find that your house was full of like seven to a dozen empty beer
glasses and you know half sliced lemons that got left on the counter people were actually
spontaneously tidying up the kitchen for us at the parties and this i think was the best thing ever
i've done that new year's day in 2012 i crashed from my friend tony at his new year's party and he
got down in the morning to find that i had put everything in the bin and minced everything out
and etc and he was like what has happened and i was like i was bored i like tidying
though when we went to america in 2003 so it was quite a long time ago my kids were quite little
we were staying with jerry in minneapolis and we woke up in the way of people who have just flown from
from the uk the following morning at about half past three and we went downstairs to discover that
jerry had left out for us some breakfast or some suggestions as to how we might acquire breakfast
at three o'clock in the morning three thirty in the morning and also a parl of 400 fancies that needed
to be collated and stegtled in a sort of i assume that when you wake up you'll want something to
keep me busy until eight so yes also for people who find that people are tidying up at their
put after their parties welcome to middle age this is the sort of thing that old people do
young people aren't hap nicely tidying up at the end of the parties because they were at two
pissed and they were doing inappropriate things and they didn't particularly want to deal with
friends for it anyway i mean i will just say that the story i just told about when i was tidying up i
was 22 you were wise beyond your years young coxern i just f*cking love tidying up alison
you don't understand it's a seriously come round i mean come round it's fine yeah john come and
visit come and visit i can see some clutter in both of my co-hosts um zoom calls i literally think
there's no clutter in this picture there is one open cup of door oh there is the
eight-coloured store it's because it's clean as this doesn't shut on the floor it's an adorable
shot but a possible open cup of pool there is no so i can indirectly observe the effects of clutter
yes but you can't actually see it directly like indeed a black hole which is what steven's
side of the room is like to some extent let's stop talking about your husband's black hole
and move on to discussing tor con uh 2021 which when you listen to this listener if you are listening
on the day it comes out it's today at uh seven p.m eastern time which is midnight in god's true
time zone of england as you know to be fair england's not currently on god's true time zone
because everyone knows that jesus was born in quenich uh there are some panels and whatnots
there are apparently giveaways content drops and more we will put a link in the show notes
there are various authory people and it will be very fun if you like that sort of thing i don't
think it has any of i don't think it has any elephant friendly content by which i mean insufficient
beer parties hangouts even a bit of chat to your author no it's panels and stuff it's would you like
to watch some television about science fiction authors yeah but it's a good set of science fiction
also think oh yeah no no it's fine it's it's i'm sure it's great but i it's not what you think of
as a convention it's it's some television with authors on it's not what cat yeah i'm gonna say i
don't think that events that author a series of author events over a weekend makeeth a convention
i i think that i require some interaction between the attendees for it to be a convention in my books
what does make it a weekend convention for our lesson then what was that so i was trying to
badly segue into punctuation oh you're segue into telling and talking about our convention yes
punctuation will not have insufficient beer it will have sufficient beer in that we have a beer
tasting and you can order your beers listeners we also have a gin tasting and a cheese tasting
so order all of the food and drink and if you've had a birthday since the beginning of the pandemic
we are having a birthday party um to celebrate all of those birthdays we are particularly celebrating
people who've had milestone birthdays but in my book every birthday is a milestone birthday
so we're having a birthday party so you might want to make sure you've got some cake
if you have not had a birthday since the start of the pandemic please also write on tellers
because i think that's one of those are the signs that physics has gone badly wrong
leap babies they won't have had a birthday oh leap babies yes yes we will have a party just for
the beer babies also so if you are one right in so if you were born on the 29th of February and you
had it and you celebrated your birthday on the 29th of February 2020 because you had not noticed
that the pandemic was on the way that a birthday party was not the perfect idea um but it's just
fair enough quite early i was still meeting people in person for another week after that
then death is congratulations you've not missed out on any of your birthday parties i think
don't people whose birthday is the 29th of February actually celebrate a birthday every year
anyway i think i'm pretty sure it's illegal to celebrate your birthday on a day there's not
your birthday so i hope not moving on it better not be because we're definitely celebrating everyone's
birthdays but they weren't at the birthdays party at punctuation
all members of worldcon 76 got an email this week informing them that sfsfc the parent body
which ran worldcon 76 have settled the ongoing lawsuit over the public statements surrounding that
the preemptive banning of an attendee from the event according to the discussion on file 770
this was settled for four thousand dollars and the apology that was sent out to all members
but there were other requests in the lawsuit that were were not they'd not end up in the final
settlement so it appears this is now finished and settled for worldcon 76 and we thought we might
discuss what this means both maybe four worldcon 76 and for other world cons and conventions
i'm a bit worried about it because i think it makes a statement about the
efficacy and applicability of codes of conduct which have become very common for conventions and for
other spaces that fans hang out i mean i quite like codes of conduct i think they're good i
worry that this makes it that now that we have seen a success it depends how you mean
successful lawsuit because it seems likely that the costs of bringing this lawsuit were not
were not less than four thousand dollars because i believe that four thousand dollars were by
about 20 minutes of an american lawyers time so i don't i don't think any was a big winner here but
i i feel like it may mean that other people are inspired to sue conventions that they don't like
for doing things that that the convention thinks is reasonable under its its own rule
so yeah no i'm worried i'm worried about it i'm worried about everything to do with
the business of running modern conventions but that's one of the things
i think i say that if you read the email received they're not actually apologizing for banning someone
from their event under the code of conduct but for the statements they made around it
so obviously there is it kind of room for conventions if they're worried about their settlement then
obviously the way to do it now is to just enforce your code of conduct by you know preventing people's
attendance at the convention but probably not to make public statements about it or to make
public statements which basically are just sort of incredibly neutral statements of fact so it's
maybe uh not quite so chilling there i mean what worries me is that yeah you can't really say who
who has won this one because obviously the settlement is less in the amount that was asked for and
probably is less than the amounts of the legal fees needed to fight it but it also probably costs way
more than that in legal fees for the convention and it's tied up a lot of their time and effort and
basically prevented them from fully winding down the convention over the past few years
so i think it's very much a sort of neutral outcome yeah i mean i think when i've when i've
been involved in code of conduct things at uk conventions the statements from the convention
have been really quite neutral for all sorts of reasons um they've been kind of you know we
determined that a member violate the code of conduct and we've asked them to leave that sort of thing
so i don't know you know obviously if you kind of go well what are people being saying in private
what are people being saying on all the sort of stuff that can be get subpoenaed then there's a
there's more of a risk there that stuff would come out that you really didn't want to be be
public this probably goes back to fanak feeling like work that that sort of sense of oh we have to be
very we have to do everything in a very professional manner all the time makes everything feel much
harder but on the other hand i do feel that things like the separation of listener teams
from the main convention management is quite a good way of of actually making sure that the
people who are dealing with complaints of that kind do treat it very very professionally i think
like it must have been very stressful for world cons 76 to still have this uh hang over them three
years after um the result i think it's notable that this settlement comes after the judge refuse
um summary judgment which would demand that this went full trial and yeah i can understand
entirely why world cons 76 have done this um you know i think and you know i think hopefully
sfsfc can kind of move on and um put this behind them because i think they probably deserve two um
so yeah yeah i think so i think it's a shame because i think they probably went into it with the best
intentions to make a statement you know which kind of reinforced you know that they had a code of
conduct and they had certain values they were trying to enforce and basically i think in hindsight
that statement was an ill-advised statement to make because it left them open to this lawsuit and
this is going to cost them a lot of time and effort and money i mean i think we should mention it and
work it's kind of it's just more it's now another thing in the big background of why it's harder to
run conventions that it used to be on the subject of it being harder to run conventions than it used
to be convergence 2021 is going ahead what are their dates john the fifth to the eighth of august
allison and so this is clearly a decision they've made i think uh because they have contractual
obligations um they basically say they've got a choice between holding this physically or dissolving
their event company permanently and they've decided therefore to hold a physical convention
and yeah they're so they're going to do that and that's happening um so this is the first science
fiction convention to be held kind of in the brave new world in person the first in-person
science fiction convention to be held post pandemic it's being held in minneapolis and my impression
is that the us are now slightly ahead of the uk hunter in terms of second doses so in terms of
fully vaccinated people um so what do we what do we think about this peeps who's getting the
plane to minneapolis you're kidding right well i mean i'm hoping to go to a folk festival in august
so you know i'm not completely averse to it i think it reflects the fact that in the united states
full vaccination it has essentially been available to anyone with privilege for some time now
because unlike the uk and i guess probably tylen but i think certainly the uk the uk is
vaccinated people in a strict order and unless you were really super rich getting vaccinated out of
order hasn't happened you've basically wasted your turn and not everyone has had that turn yet
and not everyone will have had their turn by um this that time in august so i don't think that
would be practical here because i think there'll be people who we like what we want to come to the
convention and we very much like to get vaccinated but we're not able to and i just don't think that's
the case in america i think everyone who wants a vaccination and has the resources to get a
vaccination which probably means has the resources to go to a convention frankly it's not a huge
amount of resources required um will have had them by then um so in that sense maybe they do not
yet have the delta variant they are not in the position where that we are where we're waiting to
see what whether the rise in cases leads to a rise in hospitalizations and deaths including
people who are vaccinated i i feel it's a bitterly um and but i understand that they're going to
go bust if they don't do it so you know i wouldn't go so i i think they do have a few cases of some
of the variants of concern in the us are just not rising or dominating at the the rate they
seem to be in the uk and yeah i can i can see that if you're at the state where you know the authority
is saying if you are vaccinated it is fine to essentially go back and do most of the things you
were doing before you can take your masks off you can meet other vaccinated people then if you can
do that on the small scale then maybe you are ready to do that on the scale of you know up to 3,500
people which is what their maximum participation numbers are and i can very much see that they are
caught between either we do this or there is no more convergence and so we're going to do this
and i think it'll be interesting because i think some people do feel okay i i am vaccinated now
everyone i know is fully vaccinated now if you're in the us you're vaccinated with highly effective
vaccines yeah it's ready to go back and do it it's two months away so hopefully you know the
infection levels will drop even further but when i read it i was like wow that seems incredibly
early because i'm still in the mindset that's thinking can i put 10 people in a room maybe next
month would that be all right so i am a very simple mathematician here not not really a mathematician
but i'm kind of like so i go and see sit in a garden we sat in sequential gardens in Cambridge
last week so we saw about 10 people over the course of the day but in four different gardens so
so the total number of interactions and we were all socially distanced so yeah
to amooraptors so the social number of interactions maybe i don't know 40 or 50
but if we put the same or fewer 20 and if we put the same 10 people into a room then it's 100 and
if you put uh 81 if you put um 3,500 people in an exhibition hall it's a lot and and that
increases the risk a lot but maybe not enough i don't know um i will also just note that
the first convention is on my calendar is the UK Games Expo which is end of July
and will be substantially more people i think than uh convergent would be so i don't know
oh so you're going to one before that indoors you're going to an indoor in-person convention
before convergence yeah i think i'm asking are you planning on going to the UK Games Expo?
oh no i mean so i won't be i won't be um sorry the way Allison said it really confused me
i don't know why um no so i would have gone to the Games Expo if i had been double vaccinated
before it ran but as it stands i will be vaccinated two weeks after and so going without having had
both jabs seems like a bad idea mainly because if i caught covid from a convention two weeks before
my second jab ispania would be so smug that she killed you again yeah uh so anyway i so i don't
think i will but i was planning to if i was double-vaxed and it did look for a while like i might be
but um but no and so this is the other thing because i don't know what the age profile of um
convergences like and the health profile because um i feel as that i'm not that all but i am quite
fat and i think being fat's really big risk factor for this and and i am therefore more
fretful than i might be if i was um the the in the prime of peak physical health in the way that
john is but i don't know what whether convergence because a lot of like world confants tend to run
old and unhealthy but other convention they're probably other conventions where that's not the
case i've never been to convergence but i suspect it skews more towards the younger and healthier
end than a world conf um so the other thing to note about convergence is that because they are
mandating everyone who goes must have two vaccinations if you are under 12 you cannot go because there
is no way you will have had two vaccinations and they know this on the web page um i don't i do think
in their defense it is clear that they are only running this event because they have to and i think
if you have to run an event this is probably the right set of compromises to settle on um but if
you are a parent of under 12 year old children that it's going to have a huge impact on whether or not
you can attend um but yeah very interesting very interesting well speaking of somebody who has
was in this wasn't the position of taking children conventions and um i just feel like
some conventions aren't really very very good fit for children anyway so it's a shame that they
can't have kids at this one but lots of conventions are not really a good place to go with kids
you know you have to think of that all the time when you're thinking about which conventions to choose
world con site selection is now open it costs 50 of your united states dollars to vote and the
options are Chengdu um in 2023 and Winnipeg in 2023 and Memphis in 2033 strangely all winning from
the same year what are the chances i will probably be voting Winnipeg then Memphis then Chengdu
it would be quite nice to have some of the conversations about world consign selection
before the last week of the voting period especially for those of us who are not going to DC
um like what i'm not peeps are you going to be voting in site selection i think if i were to vote
today i would put the bids in the same order that you have but i'm not absolutely persuaded yet
because i really don't feel i've heard enough from either Winnipeg or recently from Memphis i mean
i think the fact that we haven't heard a lot from Memphis is quite telling but but i feel like i'd
want to hear a bit more and i'm hoping that opportunities to learn more about the bids will
emerge between now and um between now in the the deadline for site selection the postal
deadline here's a bit of for people who don't know if you are at the world con physically at the
world con you can vote in site selection right up until lunchtime saturday or something quite
you know well into the con um at a desk you could basically take your money and pay and they sort
you out but if you're not at the world con there is a deadline which is some considerable time
before the convention and so site selection has traditionally been quite a complicated process
even online where essentially you replicate the physical activity of submitting a ballot because
they do quite a lot of work to make sure that the secret ballot is secret because um sometimes
and this is something about the club ability and entrenched it's kind of like balls in an
errness and titties they are working quite hard to ensure that people don't find out that their
mates have voted against them yeah so so um so there's quite a lot of structure in the process
to make that happen and it means it's not that simple and you do need to vote fairly well in advance
in site selection and you need to allow yourself a few hours to get it done you're not necessarily
going to be able to go straight up to the site and vote and but i would hope that more
infomercial emerged about the bids that allow me to really feel confident in voting for Winnepeg
and to support that i believe that um tarry fongs a member of punctuation so i'll probably try and
grab him in a bar and tell him to tell me why his bid is so wonderful yeah definitely i was
going to say fortunately punctuation is virtual and so tarry will not have the experience of having
like allison spot him on the far side of a crowded bar and you know elbow everyone else out of the
way to get there and Amanda Pinten reasons why she should vote for Winnepeg i used suggesting
that you see me act to this way in previous years when we were not virtual i don't think she's
suggesting it i think she's saying with her words i will i will take that as a reflective
point of feedback thank you i should say if i i wouldn't go if i saw allison you're like charging
across the bar towards me i would not go in high but this is partly because i remember
you doing that in Dublin and you had a load of drink tickets so i did basically i found jc who
was the treasurer of the convention and i i hung him upside down by his ankles until i gave he
gave me enough drink tickets that enough groats that i could be fairly sure that nobody left in
the bar would be required to buy another drink for the rest of it would be required to pay for
another drink and then i stood at the bar making sure that anyone who went up to the bar had
sufficient drinks to cover their round uh yeah um it was good i don't remember all of that night
we've been talking a little bit about a little thing called punctuation too which is coming to your
computer screens and um also your televisions if you have a computer that will plug into your
television oh i love this coming to your tv if you can plug your computer into your tv
uh you can also you can also Wi-Fi your plug to your tv if you'd like i don't necessarily need
you to use a cable but yes and it's going to be the 18th to the 20th of june 2021 uh please come along
memberships are 0,5 or 10 pounds depending on how much you choose to pay for one and we would love
to see you there and it will be good we'll be announcing the program sometime real soon now
but we can um exclusively announce i mean we might have announced the program by the time
this episode goes out but we can exclusively announce that one of the program items will be
at 11 o'clock o'clock sunday morning octa thought live because it is about two weeks today and it's
on our normal recording schedule and the rest of our committee said very kindly that they would be
completely fine with us being off podcasting for an hour and a bit so so do come along and join us
for octa thought live mm-mm indeed it will be a good thing and we will be taking questions from
the audience questions such as why are you so wrong about fanzines yes it's it's being recorded
at our usual time which means it will basically be 11 o'clock on the day after john and allison
have partied until the wee small hours i mean i will also have part until the wee small hours
where that will be slightly offset for me yes uh so it will be exciting and we have some tastings
lined up so there will be a gin tasting on the friday night and there will be a cheese tasting
on the saturday night and there will be a beer tasting at seven o'clock on the sunday night
so get your cheese beer and gin in we have already said that probably doesn't have to say again
more gin and and last time some people who had got this virtual convention going down to a fine art
had full english breakfast delivered to their homes and i am going to commend this as a
method of getting your your full english breakfast because i haven't had a full
i i don't think i've really had very many full english breakfast in the last 15 months because i
would have had to have cooked them myself do miss hotel breakfast surprisingly much
i mean i miss a lot of other things about you know not being able to travel anywhere by two
miss hotel breakfast i mean a good hotel breakfast is a great thing a bad hotel breakfast is not
espania espanias first english breakfast was at the radison edwardian at the 2012 east com
she had never let me forget it yeah for one of those coms we um
we actually stayed at one of the one of the hotels kind of two doors down but it's the very big doors
but everything apart from the fact that we had to walk for five or ten minutes to get
home and back everything else about it was infinitely better they had a pool they had
fantastic breakfast they looked after us properly they didn't treat us like some sort of low-grade
scum um sorry just reminiscing about in-person conventions and how i can't wait to get back to
them it's going to be good but not yet god we're going to have so much to podcast about when we
actually owe to in-person conventions it's like do you know that they had a whole room where all
they did was surf beer and chat thank you very much for listening to this episode of the octador
podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
wait for my section on rampant self-promotion later in this episode i like the idea of criscosia
rampant on a coat of arms oh do you know the history of animals rampant on coats of arms
i'm going to assume sex i don't know it's wasn't really the sex it was just kind of rampant and then
in victorian times they decided they were a bit too rampant and so they kind of
rearrange the animals so that their rampant nature was less obvious
chris find a fan like if you could get Vanessa to send us some fan art we will feature it in next
episode and that would be fantastic this could be the new version of the shield of humor couldn't
it i don't know what that is what's that do you know what the shield of humor is okay um so when
we're talking about um classic fandom and why it's not relevant um it was the it was the thing worn
by the you know the night's percent fad to me i don't know what that is i don't know it's just
okay fine sorry i've only been in fandom keep your shield of humor brightly polished i mean i
regularly polish my shield of humor yeah yeah oh you regularly polish your
um coat of arms with criscosia rampant uh and then so sorry chris so i feel like this might have
got out of hand the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud at
ncompetech.com used under a creative commons attribution 3.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep