You could just put it on git or something and we could all simultaneously edit it and push it back.
Yes! The best! We should have a git reef over the showdotes. Absolutely. I love that.
That's hilarious. Because we're not actually a tech podcast. I just feel that sharing text files
on the internet should be simpler than this. I mean, I feel like your computer shouldn't be
haunted, Alison. But like, we work with what we've got. Honestly, as it taunted. Um...
I mean, none of the evidence supports that perspective. Definitely haunted.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very eighth episode of the OctaThorp podcast, a podcast for
science fiction and science fiction fandom. I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Betty.
And we have a raft of letters of comment this week. We're very sorry. We did not correctly set up
our email forwarding and that means that we had inadvertently ignored all emails for the last two
months. So we've got a lot to talk about. And thanks very much to listener Claire Breiley of
Croydon who pointed this out to us helpfully. Also, when you say we felt as head of our email,
John. I'm blaming John. I mean, to be fair, none of us checks and we probably should have done.
It's true. I probably should not just blame John. We'll can leave that bit out. I will not blame
John personally for our rudeness. But for other things. Ha ha ha. It's probably mostly life home.
Right then. So from the top, our first email of comment was on the 13th of April 2020,
which at the time of recording is two months and four days ago. And it is from one Andrew January
of Reading. And he says that he came across a website that does special video chat. And you move
around in a 2D space. And as you get near people, you can have group video chats with them.
And it lets you kind of treat a big group gathering on the internet as a kind of space rather than
just to kind of set of rooms as in Zoom or a set of channels as in Discord. He doesn't mention
what the name of the website was. We did talk about something a little bit similar to this last
episode, which was color. But yeah, that sounds cool. Wouldn't it be cool if it was 3D and you could
do it in VR on your VR headset? That would be awesome. I have been very sad to not discover.
I was expecting to go into the Oculus Store and find all manner of VR experiences of this kind.
But they don't appear to exist yet. I don't really want to spend an entire evening with my VR headset
on much as I love it. It's quite heavy and not entirely conducive. And it would be hard to like
drink one of the things I do on these Zoom chats is drink. And I cannot drink and play Oculus Quest
at the same time. I would need to drink my beer with a straw. And you know there that gets you.
I think we did on a previous podcast. I think Liz suggested one of those beer hats.
I was going to suggest that again because it's such a good idea. A VR headset with integrated
beer hat. I may need one of these. Yes? I'm going to be a billionaire. If Andrew has seen this thing,
has he actually seen it used for a large event? Because I feel like there's a number of people
saying, well, there's a proof of concept of these things. But I'm not sure to what extent
they actually exist. And also whether they're actually being used for large events or whether
they're just kind of tech demos. I'm also slightly worried that the problem we've talked about before
that it's very, it's relatively easy in a physical conversation to say this is amazing,
but I absolutely have to go to the loon now. It's much harder in these video conferencing chats
and it can be hard to just kind of slip off the edge of one of them without people kind of noticing.
Especially if they then see from their VR environment, the engaged conversation with more
interesting people across the room. Differently interesting. It's a good save. It's I suppose hard
to hide at the other end of the bar when it's a 2D space with no hiding places. But I've done
I've done kind of abrupt good boys from zoom calls and people don't seem to have been too
offended. So I don't I don't know I think people are usually pretty chill about maybe I'm wrong
but I feel like people are pretty chill about that kind of thing.
Right on to letter of comment two. So this is from Mark Olson on the 25th of April 2020
and he says that he stumbled across us and listened to our first podcast which he enjoyed.
But he does say that he thinks we might want to mention the date because he did not read it
sorry he did not listen to it close to the time of recording and so some of it didn't make a
lot of sense and I if you remember episode one had we had not fully gone into lockdown yet so a lot
of it was immediately rendered quite dated. Today is Wednesday the 17th of June 2020. It is
and this show will probably be going out on the 24th of June I don't guess. Oh yes we're recording
early that's kind of showing behind the curtain isn't it? It is it is indeed. But yeah he we were
talking in episode one about the lack of a written constitution for Eastercon and he mentions the
Lunarians which were New York fandom and I did not appreciate this but because of a series of very
very rigidly defined rules in the club constitution the club was invalid because they had not sent
notice of elections which meant the old officers terms had expired the new officers had been improperly
elected because the notices had not been sent out and so there were no officers there was no
secretary so there was no one who could send out a notice of any elections and so there could
know it be there could never be any new officers and therefore the club stopped and this was a club
with fewer than 20 people all of whom saw each other frequently so there is a sort of risk in having
rigorously defined systems which is if you don't have the imagination to foresee the way in which
the system could go wrong you can end up painting yourself into rather a corner. The problem was
solved by forming a new club called Lunarians 2.0 and that failed because they couldn't agree about
who they would let into the new club so it stopped. I have thought about this which will come later
in the episode with regards to the Was for Spisses meeting this year but it is a cautionary tale
and what I would encourage people to listen to. I particularly liked his phrase of the club was
what did he say the club accumulated noxious deadwood and I wouldn't like to comment as to whether
that applies to the World Souths Fiction Society. This just feels a bit like you know when I have
an account on a website somewhere and then I forget my password and forget to update the email
address and basically just have to make a new account all over again just keep making new clubs
called Lunarians 2.0 3.0 3.1 4 whatever you like just go for it. Yes there's a good good way of
dealing with I think. I think there's a spectrum of fandom and you can tell which end I am on.
Yeah the East End. Well I mean I've always been on the spectrum of fandom that said we shouldn't
really organise anything and I mean we can we can organise stuff in the sense of making things
happen. It's just the point where you decide that it's easier to make things happen with a
written constitution I'm always slightly skeptical of that because in my experience
things of that kind tend to be used in order to prevent things from happening rather than
making them happen. And anyone who is a co-host on the OctaThought podcast will know how true it is
that Alison is opposed to formal organisation of things. That's harsh. It is harsh. I don't regret
it but it is harsh. To be fair when John got in touch and said are you interested in doing a
podcast I did warn him about this at that exact point. I knew I was getting into it's true. Mark
also wrote to us to comment on later episodes. So he said that he thought our point about
fandom doing virtual socialising from day one was quite perspective and commented on our
talking about the first Thursday and then talked about Conzeland and he is I think quite
skeptical of Conzeland because he isn't convinced that you can have a time zone which sufficiently
sort of encompasses everyone who needs to be encompassed because you need to
encompass kind of traditional world con fandom in the US but also you need to encompass
New Zealand fandom obviously because it's a New Zealand con and so on. And he also says that he's
skeptical of having programming for such thing because you need to have enough program that you
can call it a world con but not so much programming. If you have a level of programming that won't
tie people out it will feel like a much smaller con and he basically concludes by saying that he's
not good sizing Conzeland's competence. He's just not sure that it's a workable proposition in any way.
I think since he wrote that stuff like Baldtecon has happened which has shown that you can I think
get around some of those problems quite well but it's an interesting take as to kind of at what point
do you sort of change things enough to make it workable online to the point where it doesn't
really feel as big as a world con should anymore. Yes I think a lot of the points Mark raises have
possibly been addressed by other virtual conventions in the meantime. So if Mark is not to upset with
us for failing to read his emails in a timely fashion and he has any updates we'd love to hear
them. Yeah definitely. And I think I think I think you can cat hurt. I mean we can cat hurt
panelists to showing up in the right rooms at the right time just about and in the case of the
East of Con usually by bribing them with a free beer if they'd like that. So I'm sure you can you
can get them to show up for the right zoom. You might just need a team of zoom Wranglers. Yes and
send be a sort of two panelists through various delivery services.
And I also think about the Hugo's I think part of the problem with the Hugo's is you do have this
tension between providing the best experience for people in the room and also providing a good
experience for people watching online at home and possibly if you're only trying to do one of those
things at once it will simplify things immensely. That is fair. That's a good point. Alison do you
have anything you'd like to say? I've promised to myself I'm going to be quieter this week.
I mean firstly episode title so that's great. Secondly we like you talking. It's a key part of
our shtick is that we talk. But actually I feel I've probably said all I've got to say
about Conzeland until I see the draft program and their draft plans for social space at which
point I expect to have enormous amounts to say. So I am I am holding my fire on that. But I did
like his final thing saying that we seemed very reasonable and are we sure we're fans.
Yes that did maybe chuckle. I liked that. We've definitely disproved that in subsequent episodes
haven't we? Yep. Yep. Well we've we've we've proven our lack of reasonability both in terms of
having had very wide sweeping wide sweeping wide ranging opinions on future episodes.
But also by having not done a reasonable job of reading letters of comment. So we've neatly
put ourselves straight back into the fan category. Also I will say I edited out all of the really
acrimonious bits obviously. So it's very easy to be reasonable when you can edit out the arguments
afterwards. Yes I was going to say I meant to say it's clearly we're clearly reasonable in the edit.
Yes.
[Music]
Andrew Hogg sent us an email on the 19th of May and he um he was worried that we're mispronouncing
Claire Breiley of Chor
I am 99% certain we are pronouncing Claire Breiley's surname correctly because I have been
harangued on that matter on many times on many occasions. When I gave Claire her Hugo Award I
pronounced her surname incorrectly and so if I ever win my own Hugo Award my entire acceptance
speech will just be to say her name correctly and then Moonwalk off the stage. Can you Moonwalk?
No I'm going to have to learn to know. Okay so you better get practicing that hadn't you?
I'm not going to win a Hugo Alison so I'm not sure it's going to come up.
Are you a Hugo finalist? I am as mentioned by Mark Plummer in his layer of comment from the 23rd
of May 2020 which is addressed dear Alison Liz and Hugo Award finalist the Boy Coxon.
Doctor Hugo Award finalist the Boy Coxon. That's me. That's you.
And so he says he's enjoying the Octa Thought podcast which is good. And he also asked whether
or not we could give ourselves names as according to the style of the kids TV show Octa Norts in
which they're a character called Vegemals which are half animal and half vegetable. Hence
Tuneip is half tuna half tournip and carp preka is half carp and half paprika.
So tell me about Octa Thought. Octa Norts. I know nothing of this.
It's students program about basically a crew of underwater explorers who are all animals and
they have like they have like a set of vehicles a bit like Thunderbirds.
Nice. And then they go on adventures and I'm really watching that much detail but apparently
it is like scientifically accurate about all its underwater adventures and they also for some reason
have these things which are half animal half vegetable and all their names are like a
you know mash up of the two names. So what's a good one? Alba Choy is half bok choy half albacore
going to make me do anyway. It's good innit. Ten out ten I could be had hadtato half hadt
hadtato half potato. That's pretty good. Yeah I was proud or hmm.
Try to think what my favorite my favorite fish is definitely hadtock.
But what's my favorite vegetable? Cógette. Hadet. Hadet. Um yeah so is that good?
I think that's pretty good. Are we limited to vegetables only? How can we have fruit?
No it's vegetables only isn't it? Mmm. But it does say animals it doesn't necessarily say
it has to be fish. That's true but I mean just both of the examples of fish.
I generally the theme of the show is fish related. I say I won't. I've only seen like
snippets of octonauts when babysitting children who loved octonauts. That is fair I have never
seen any octonauts but feel I should now go and look them up. Maybe we should have a special
episode next week. About octonauts and I'm gonna be a crab to choke. Yes nailed it.
Oh great name that is a flippy green name. Love it okay straight in the show.
But Alison have you got a octonauts name? I have been thinking about this I may have to return to
you next week but in the meantime I quite like a moose rot which is a combination of a moose and
a carrot. I like it. But when I first thought that I said a combination of an animal and a
vegetable and I was like oh you mean like salmon and sushi rice but I think I may have
been missing the point there. Also neither of those is a vegetable. Sushi rice is definitely a vegetable.
Is rice is a vegetable? Yeah it's not meat. I mean it's as much of a vegetable as paprika.
Uh paprika's a pepper, chili pepper. Paprika paprika. One of those is a chili pepper.
Plus we are getting that for Wikipedia I'm not sure if that is a fully canonical octonauts name.
Andrew Hogg asked is there a piece of media you waited over a decade for and it actually lived up
to expectations? Um yeah which is such a good question that I think we should bring it back at
a future episode. Not least because I've got a hook to tie it to one of the Hugon nominated
thank-ars. Which talks about books that haven't come out yet which is not is kind of irritating
but they were saying that Susanna Clark's Piranesi lives up to expectations. There was nothing like
Jonathan Strange and Mr. Norrell. And he also says he's looking forward to further updates on
Lough the Liz Only fan fund. It's not clear to me whether this is only for visiting Liz whether
this is only for Liz to visit or both but yeah gotta get that going. I think this is a follow-up
to our previous discussion where I threatened to send you a map and point out where Australia
was if you recall. It could well be. I'm basically my own you know uh fan fund zone for now.
And Mark very kindly described octaphthorpe as similar to listening, sitting in the bar listening
to the three of you having a conversation and being unable to get a word in edge ways.
It's not untrue. To which he said Alison Willard so exactly like that then.
And also I will say that Claire has mentioned a similar sentiment to me but she says she always
wins the arguments she has with us because we can't answer back to her witty repartee.
So this is actually a feature rather than a bug I feel. If you if you want to have the last word
just mutter under your breath as you listen and it will go well. I thought that was a huge
benefit of podcast generally. I mean I'm forever shouting at podcast. And now you shout during them
as do we all. Another man called Joseph Norton sent me an email to the podcast email address
thanking me for putting mp3s of the vinyl albums of the hitchhiker's guide to the
galaxy on my website which I did ages and ages ago because I have the vinyl albums and they're
different to the original radio series. So I recorded them from my dad's turntable using some
audio recording software on a laptop and then because no one else had put them online I thought
well you know that one's gonna lose out. Since then there has been a vinyl release of hitchhikers but
I think it is a vinyl release of the BBC show. I don't think it's a vinyl release of the original
vinyl albums but yes so he said thank you and you're welcome Joseph. Claire you're enjoying them.
And thanks for listening to the podcast it's nice that we have listeners who aren't actually
already our personal friends. It's not it's actually not 100% clear to me whether he listens to a
podcast or whether he found the podcast by googling my name. Either one that's an outcome. That is
an outcome. Because I mean there is so I mean that he might have found your professional work he
might have found your Hugo finalist thing. You know yeah you're you have a wide internet footprint.
Then we have Claire's Claire Breyerley. Get me I'm gonna pronounce it now. And her that's your
comment. Does Eddie do either of you want to go through that? You mean would you like me to do
some some rising because you've done quite a lot of summarizing on this podcast already.
I'm worried the listeners will be very bored of my voice. Yes so Claire centers a letter
having caught up with episodes six and seven wishing all the best to John's microphone which
is no longer unwell and revealing she has drunk a beer called Edgelord. She does not reveal
whether she knew the meaning of the name of the beer at that time. She's also asked if
so shirts make a grumpy old fart cap for a for world con exhibition heads. Anything can be things
can be arranged. They do now. Anything can be arranged with so shirts. So Claire is really much. We we
discussed briefly I think this is how you lose the time war which I think I had read and you guys had
not read correct. Not yet. Still haven't still not read it. It is on my iPad waiting. It's very nice
because I I enjoyed it and thought it was good but it did not speak to my heart. Claire has written
in because it did speak to her heart about the love story and about finding people and how truly
distinct that is from sex and or friendship and also recommended the books by Nick Bantock called
Griffin and Sabine which I have never read but I might look into because they're apparently a
reminder of this is how you lose a time war. Yeah I'm I'm looking forward to reading it because I
have obviously heard an awful lot about it at this point. I'm currently reading the Becky Chambers one
which I do not remember the name of. I think it's to be taught if fortunate. To be taught if
fortunate and the reason I'm currently reading that is that because in the Hugo
Photo Packet it only came as a PDF and I currently have a ebook version on loan from the library
so I can read in a slightly nicer format but I have to read it first but after that I shall
probably do the rest of the novellas so I will hopefully have listened to it by next time.
I'm sure nobody with any influence in these matters ever reads this but I have taken the view that
if your submission to the Hugo Photo Packet only comes in PDF format then I will deprioritise it
in my Hugo reading and seeing as I never managed to get all the Hugo reading done anyway
this means that you are less likely to get my vote. I am sure I'm not the only person but I thought
I wanted to say this publicly so that the people out there who make the decision to put these things
in as PDFs know that it's not actually as efficient as putting things in as ePubs or any other
ebook format and if you're doing it because you're worried that people will par at the e-book then
you're being a bit silly because obviously the PDF is sufficient for people to be able to do that
anyway. I know that this has no effect but I just kind of want to shout into the void occasionally.
Yeah that's fair. Now I will say I do agree with you in that if a book is only available in a format
that I find stressful to read or if a book is not available in full then I will try and read it
I'll try and borrow from the library but if the book doesn't come through by the time the deadline
happens then yeah that that will mean I don't vote for it. Last year that was The Calculating
Stars by Mary Robinette Coel but then that won so I'm not sure that my failure to read it in time
really affected it meaningfully at all. It was a fantastic book. Thoroughly enjoyed it. Think it
deserved to win. Did not read it until after the ceremony because that was when my library hold
came through. I know it's never up to it's really never up to the authors is it. It's decisions made
at a publisher level so I don't know to what extent to what extent back be helped.
I agree with Alison entirely on the PDF thing but I also read 100 pages The Calculating Stars
and decided nope and put it down to read something else so I've had that. I've had that.
Not every book has to be for everyone. No and I felt quite pleased myself for reading it and going
no this is not my thing. I'm putting it down and reading another book and I was on a reading
holiday at the time so there were probably several hundred other books around for me to choose from.
Did anyone write to us suggesting things that we could read or do to improve our
awareness of Black Lives Matter and related issues John? No. Have either of you done anything to
enhance your awareness of your white privilege? Yes I have read Superior by Angela Saini and
that was very good. I think that it helped me see kind of some of the issues around ethnicity as a
kind of categorization system and I read it while on strike as part of the Black in the Ivory
slash Black Lives is STEM strikes which happened a week or two ago now. I've also bought How to Be
Anti-racist by Ibram X Kendi and also looking forward to reading that but I have not yet read it.
I've also started monthly donations to a couple of other organizations that were on the Google
sheet of organizations that we had in last week's show notes so that's what I did since last time.
Why do you do anything? I put a load of books on my hold list for my local library
which are all extremely popular and will no doubt come through in about November but I mean they
will come through and I will then read them. I listened to some podcasts by Black creators.
The one I enjoyed most was it's called Nerds of Prey and hasn't actually had a new episode out
since December so I'm not entirely sure I want to mention it specifically. I like some other ones
but they're more in my kind of normal tech and scientific niches rather than science fiction and
fantasy ones. I'm still looking for some recommendations there and I also donated some money to some
charities that work with disadvantaged people and with legal defense for people in the UK.
So my recommendation would be there is a list posted by so Sirens Conference which runs every
year in the US. I've posted a list of 50 works by Black authors which I am basically working my
way through. I've read some of them some of them going on my wish list a couple of which I actually
owned and will be now coming to the top of my reading list. I am like making an effort to read
more books by Black authors and buy more books by Black authors especially over the next couple
of weeks as I think there was a drive to try and buy them in a particular week and just bring them
to the top of the bestseller lists. So I read The Nickel Boys by Colson Whitehead which is not
science fictional but is another spectacular novel from him. Quite a harrowing read about
two young Black men in a juvenile facility in the US in the 1960s which is great. Like John I'm also
an academic so I'm reading a lot of the Black in the Ivory stories about the experiences of Black
academics and trying to think of ways that we can help in this area and I have also donated to
some organisations from the list we put in the show notes last week.
Claire also sent me, she sent I think many people a short fanzine about Weetabix.
She didn't just send a short fanzine about Weetabix, she sent Weetabix. Have you not had your Weetabix yet?
I have had My Weetabix but I don't want to talk what? I have also had My Weetabix.
Oh she sent you Weetabix as well. There was a picture of an entire carrier bag full of Weetabix.
I don't know to whom Weetabix was sent but I think it was a large operation.
I think I may have failed because obviously I got a Weetabix because I had sent Weetabix.
My Weetabix arrived completely unharmed but it did not go large letter. I think the question of how
you get Weetabix through at large letter rate without arming it is still an open one.
That presumably means that you'll have Weetabix impounded by Thai customs at some point Liz.
I don't believe Claire has sent me Weetabix if only because she's not at any point
asked for my post address in order to send me Weetabix. So unless she somehow intuited my address
or she decided to just put Weetabix care of Liz Bathy Thailand hopefully they have not impounded
a Weetabix. Has anyone tried just sending a Weetabix to Claire Brierley, Fishliffer Towers,
Croydon and seeing if it arrived? It might arrive. The Royal Mail can really surprise you and Claire
Brierley I assume is not a terrifically common name. Right so if you work for the Royal Mail and you
find a package in 50 years when you listen back to this historical record that looks to be some
fossilised Weetabix now you know where it came from. Fossilised Weetabix looks exactly like Weetabix.
Well I will say and I also will say that I did in response to her fanzine about Weetabix
implore her to write three more fanzines about Weetabix so I could nominate them for Best Fanzine
at the Hugo Awards which I think would be brilliant. I'm not super hopeful it would win but I'd
definitely nominate it. I think we should be going for a new category Best Fanzine about Weetabix.
Start the process.
On the subject of Wussfuss procedures. Have we now finished follow up John?
We have finished follow up Alison. Some of you may be aware that Cone Zealand is being held
online this year but this is not stopping the World Science Fiction Society holding a physical
business meeting in Wellington because according to File 770 and I quote "it cannot be moved online".
What do I think about that peeps? The Octa Thorpe rant.
See we've got a new show segment name. Why can it not be moved online? Like I have not delved into
the Wussfuss constitution for a little while so I can't remember like what the exact wording is
is it that we literally can't move online because something says you cannot do it online or we can't
move online because there's not a way of doing all the things the business meeting needs to do
online or it's some other reason. It's possible that we cannot do it online because Wussfuss has a
brush up its collective arse. So here we're in a world where the UK Parliament, the mother of
Parliament's run by Erskine May since the beginning of time manages to move itself online in a couple
of weeks just by basically going "Huh does it make sense to not do this? No it does not let's go
online" whereas Wussfuss run by as we know Robert's Rules of Order goes "Oh no we have to have a
physical meeting in the location specified" because I mean if Wellington was bombed what would they
have done? You know I mean you can see them going "Oh it's ground zero but we have to be there
because the Wussfuss constitution requires us to be there to hold our physical business meeting and
there is no other way to do it and the Worldcon will come down around our ears if we do not hold
a physical meeting now. There is another argument that says actually you know we could have brought
it online but in fact having a micrometing on site is the sensible way forward because otherwise
every rules lawyer in Wussfuss would just I'm trying to think of a metaphor here that's not
extremely sexist and a bit dodgy over this prospect of arguing about this for three solid years.
Right anyway that's all I had to say on the subject. How does that relate to you? How does that
compare to your rad? I don't know it depends how passionate I am about the rant. As far as I can
tell and I am interpreting a constitution and I am not a lawyer and to be honest you'd need to be
a lawyer to appreciate all of the nuances and subtleties of the Wussfuss constitution but as far
as I can tell the problem is Article 5, Section 5.1, Subsection 5 which states that the quorum for
the business meeting shall be 12 members of the society physically present. Now I have double
checked and as far as I can tell the word physically is not actually defined anywhere in the constitution
so I assume that they're relying on a definition according to the dictionary and my dictionary
defines physically as in a way that relates to the real world and things perceived through the
senses as opposed to the mind. So I would argue that if you wanted to and you had the mental
gymnastics present you could interpret that to allow an online meeting as long as everyone was at
the online meeting and you could see them with your senses but perhaps there would be a point of
order raised and people would get very frowny. It does also say in the constitution that any
member of the world cons should be allowed to attend the meeting so I'm also sort of tempted to
arrange some sort of splinter group where we all threaten to attend the meeting in strict
contravention of international law unless they don't hold it and I wonder what they would do then.
But yeah it's disillusioned Chris and it comes down to the point made earlier in the episode
about if you have a set of rules that is sufficiently rigorous that it does not permit for certain
things that may go wrong to go wrong then those rules can end up with silly situations like
having a situation where 12 people have to meet in Wellington to have the business meeting and I
would argue that if it does have to be held at the Worldcon and the Worldcon is in cyberspace
a physical business meeting in Wellington is in contravention of the Wussfers constitution
and should be immediately disallowed. I'm genuinely like this constitution does not provide for the
circumstance so you've got to do some imaginative reading of the rules but given that you have to
do some imaginative reading of the rules well earth not imaginatively read the rules to allow a
virtual business meeting that we can actually attend and participate in. This is the end of my rant.
Because they don't wanna because they think it would be too hard. I feel that the Eastcon managed
to make this happen perfectly adequately and that it doesn't seem I mean obviously we did it without
the benefit of a constitution or rules of engagement we just did sensible stuff in in a way that that
was kind of quite English of us. I don't feel that they've necessarily taken the best option
and there's clearly nothing to stop them having a meeting in which people join physically but the
meeting is also online and people can make comments and suggestions online using some form of Q&A.
I feel that with rules lowering like that John you have a great future heavy at the Wussfers
business meeting. You take that back Batty! How do you feel about mornings? I mean I am I don't like
that the business meeting is held at the Worldcon because he's a cargo to panels or the bar and
to my mind the exciting things about Worldcon are panels in the bar so. So I guess I have less
ranty opinions which are mostly just because I'm I think less bothered. I'm okay with them
deciding this year okay we can't do a virtual one and it says we should have an actual physical
gathering of 12 people so let's have a physical gathering of 12 people do the absolute minimum
and punt this to next year but I do think next year needs to be thinking about this now and working
out how they will do a virtual business meeting if necessary or if not how they can put in place
all the structures in 2021 to enable us to do this in the future because we don't know when
this might happen again but 2021 is a good bet for being online or for when it might happen again.
I mean I think the most likely outcome for the Worldcon next year is not that it doesn't happen
physically it's that most of its foreign visitors are effectively disenfranchised along with a lot
of the older and sicker members of the Worldcon community which is quite a lot of people
and Worldcon has a tendency to be the convention for a bunch of people in the northeastern United
States anyway and having the business meeting only open to those people would be a major problem
that I think they need to address. Is that fair? That's not too ranting? Was that ranting? That was
quite ranting? That ranting and it is completely fair it's not going to land well with Wispus
fandom who regard any attempts to change or modernise anything as if you are literally the devil.
The comments or the Falsheventivity article declaring this are proof of that. I think in general
if the Wispus constitution doesn't allow for this sort of things in these changing and if the
Wispus constitution cannot be changed or if the Wispus business meeting cannot be held virtually
we need to have a serious think about whether that means those two things are fit for purpose
because I would argue it means they are not and we need to seriously rethink them. The fact that
Worldcons were held completely successfully up until 1980 without any formal constitution
rather makes me think we don't need it but perhaps we do and perhaps it's very important
but in that case we need to fix the problems with it. I think any political system that responds to
a crisis that requires immediate and well thought through but nevertheless speedy action with a
decision to delay absolutely everything for a year is not demonstrating that it's not fit for
purpose. It's demonstrating that it does not work at the thing it's supposed to do unless the
thing it's supposed to do is retard change and obviously there are people in the in Wispus fandom
for whom retarding change is a feature not a bug and I don't know I feel like there's something
every episode that causes me to go and you call yourself science fiction fans though they might say
but that's why we want to be careful of change because you know it we've read those books and it
never comes out well. Our email address is octathoughtcast@gmail.com and we will read it we promise. I know
history is not good of this but we will.
Thank you everyone for listening to the eighth episode of the OctaThore podcast which will come
out on the 24th of June 2020 and it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from
me. Yeah hey podcast have a fantastic weekend Liz. Started strong but almost immediately devolved
into passive aggression with a title of your podcast. Yes I'm not sure that was one of our more
coherent podcasts. The theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud@ancompetech.com
used under a creative commons attribution 3.0 license.
Where are you putting these at the bottom? Oh I see. Good for you sir. And it was nice that it's a
comment and they think we've been ignoring them. Is this like for weeks and weeks and weeks?
Well I think Andy Janery knows we're not ignoring him but we do apparently have one from Mark Olson.
Do from Mark Olson. Oh my god. Oops. I am John. I am bad at emails.
Highlives. We're also hello we're also about at twitter. Oh I like the letter from Hulk. It's
very nice isn't it? It is. Oh now I can't hear you at all. Maybe this can be a... oh no. Maybe
this can be an all letter of comment episode. I was actually thinking that because I don't think
we've got a lot of... I don't know if we've got a lot of topics. I've got the big business being
but like I don't want to go on a ballad too much because it's a bit niche. And also at some point
like just complaining about things gets wearing because that's what ATP does. What my favourite
podcast in the whole world? I... yeah and I respect that. I was very confused. I'm like ATP. Do you
mean a dentacy in Trisphos 8? Probably not. All tomorrow's parties. No also not. That podcast
that you know isn't like all right fun. Or the um or the like tennis pro circuit. The problem with
ATP is that because it... the thing that typifies the problem with ATP is because they could play
it all the time. It means that when they're complaining about things that actually need people to
pay attention. People ignore them because it's just ATP complaining again. And the thing that makes this
the most obvious is when they were complaining about the MacBook Pro keyboards, no one paid
attention. And then as soon as other people started complaining about the MacBook Pro keyboards,
everyone was like oh this is a real problem. And the point where you complain so often that the
things you complain about become non-remarkable is the point at which you complain too much. Like
if you're just relentlessly negative about everything, it removes any value to your criticism. So I get
a little bit frustrated. Relentlessly negative about everything. There's this week's title. So what are
our topics for today then John? We're going to look at letters of comment Alison. I've put them in the
show notes. And there are thousands of them. There are four? So we can start with a big old apology. Yes.
Just a new one from Claire. And I don't think we owe a debt of thanks to Claire because if it had
not been for her mentioning that we weren't getting our emails, we would not have known we would not
get a Gary Vels. We would have believed we were podcasting into a void. Yes. Also Mark sent us an
email about John just copy and paste them and we'll sort the like line spacing out later.
As I can see you doing it. And also the vegetables are great. I do not know what that is, but I am
curious. Well, you haven't watched up to notes, have you? No. You have not watched up to not.
Is this the world show that far like? I believe I'm not sure it is Welsh, but you can get it in
Welsh, which is so delightful. Apparently there's some transcripts. We have the other thing in our
Gmail thing is a pile of things from otter.ai saying we've transcribed your podcast. Would you like
to go and look at it? So at some point we will do that.
Are you going anywhere nice this weekend, Liz? Yes, I'm just going to go and sit in a house with a
pool and I am taking my inflatable pool hammock, my inflatable pool drinks holder, and my waterproof
Kindle cover. And that's my weekend. So you're basically having a long weekend in a large bath.
Yeah, pretty much. It does sound nice though. I feel like a holiday, a relaxing holiday
somewhere warm would quite suit me about now. I think crucially, I haven't left Bangkok at this
point for six months, which is probably the longest. Oh no, that's not true. I haven't left Bangkok
for three months and I have spent most of that time kind of in my own neighbourhood with only
occasional visits to any other bit of the city. I am feeling quite cooped up as I assume most of
you are. So it feels like now is a good time to take the chance to go somewhere a whole three hours
away because I don't know how long we will all have that chance to do that. So we've got to the
point where having a weekend away seems like the most enormous luxury. Yeah, so we're all very,
we're all very envious of you. I guess the question is, does our podcast feeling a lot like a
conversation that we've had in the bar put off people who have not already had a conversation in
a bar with us in the past? Right to octa-thorpcast@gmail.com, we promise we'll read it this time.
That actually feels like the title of this episode, we'll promise we really will read it this time.
So Marianne tells me that title of your sex tape comes directly from Brooklyn Dyerdine and had no
antecedents before that and I was quite fascinated by that. That it comes more from that's what she
said and then of course for people who are 10 years older than me, people 10 years older than me
used to say as the actress said to the bishop, yeah, which is exactly the same thing as title of
your sex tape. I think it is the same linguistic construction. I'm not sure that's a pur of anything,
but apparently it's Brooklyn Nine-Nine. Brooklyn Nine-Nine is a fine, fine show which has the problem that
all shows about the police have. Of being a show about the police now, yeah.
And about all television shows about the police have a structural problem with them.
And Brooklyn Nine-Nine is often accepted, which is that they they almost invariably show either
the police in general or the particular policeman who is the focus of the show as being
a very upstanding member of society who does know or does very little wronging kind of
pecadillo ways rather than other swiney I suppose. Well, I mean, I think we have maybe
this is not entirely on the subject of our podcast, but there's been quite a lot of interesting
writing about this, of how like most police things are procedurals and kind of to do a procedural
kind of requires that the police end up being sort of the protagonist. And you know, you can
wrap it up neatly because they catch the bad guys, but then you get things like the shield
where the policeman is definitely not one of the good guys or you get something like the wire
where the police are, you know, sometimes good and sometimes bad, but you know presented as this
force which has all these different effects and ramifications on a neighbourhood. And I think
there's some more examples. I am now going to pitch my lockdown show, which is a wussfuss procedural
drama. They're by previous back on topic.