Chengdu is a shower segment.
Leave yourself plenty of time to nominate.
Don't do it at the last minute because several people have reported Chengdu not actually finding
their memberships or them not being sure what email they're registered or under and it's
going to take them a while to sort out that sort of issue.
And although the nominating website is completely fine, it's not quite as you are used to, so
it might take you a little bit longer.
So do not leave it till the very last minute.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 82nd episode of OctaThorp.
This episode is coming to you on the 27th of April 2023 and I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Ms Batty.
This episode is going to be an episode about the Hugo Awards given that the nomination
deadline is coming up at the end of April.
So as this drops, you will have a few days to get your ducks in a row.
So we're going to discuss what we're nominating for Hugo's that we haven't already discussed
in episode 77.
And if you didn't listen to that, go back and listen to it.
It was probably good.
For load star, I'm nominating Netlombone by Tkingfisher.
It's really good.
I am nominating The Golden Inklays, which is the final book of The Golden Inklays series,
so that will end up on my ballot twice.
And I'm also nominating Unraveler by Francis Harding, which just won the B.S.A.A.
Award for Younger Readers.
And it's basically another great Francis Harding book.
And at this point, I'm just sort of like ranking within a bunch of excellent books as to which
is my favourite Francis Harding novel.
So yeah, I think you should go and read this one and nominate that one as well.
I am also nominating Unraveler, which I liked less than a face like glass and more than
the diving one.
I thought this was pretty good, but I don't think I am disinclined to nominate it for
novel because as so often with young adult fiction, I find I make allowances for the
fact that it's young adult fiction and that parts of the plot feel to me to be incredibly
transparent to an adult reader who is reading with the...
I really, really liked the first half of the book and then I thought it kind of went and
told a very ordinary story for the second half of the book, but I really, really liked
the first half.
So, you know, definitely fine for Loadstar where I'm not expecting novels to do quite
so much.
We're going to very quickly talk about what we're nominating in the fan categories.
So I'll be nominating Hugo Girl, who is an excellent fan cast and who gave us a very
nice shout out when they were talking about Hugo nominated things.
So yes, go listen to them, go nominate them, they are great.
We love you, Hugo Girl.
Yay!
Transatlantic besties.
I am going to be nominating the Fanax series of fan history zooms.
I went to one of these yesterday.
It was very good as a day they all are and they're all on YouTube, which is why they're
eligible for best fan cast because as we know, booktube, which this isn't, is a fan
cast thing.
They're very, very good and I recommend you check them out and we'll have a link in the
show notes.
And last night, somebody said loudly, "I'm so glad to have something to nominate in this
category."
And I was sitting there in the audience feeling very droopy at that point.
Though I think quite a lot of people who liked the fan-lack fan history zooms do also like
octothorps, so shout out to all of those people.
And I will also be donating Ian Clark and Ispania Sheriff and Alison Scott for best fan
artist.
Thank you very much.
And Sue Mason.
So for an example of Ispania and Alison and Sue's fan art, you can check out the octorp
cover art from last year and Ian hasn't done us any cover art and now I'm saying it out
loud.
That seems like something we should probably fix.
Yeah, no, I'm sure if we ask nicely, he'd do us one, don't you think?
Right?
Ian, if you're listening, we'll be in touch.
Yes.
Yeah, this will be embarrassing when he's not listening.
So, yeah, I will also be nominating Sarah Felix in this category whose art I continue
to like very much.
And then it's on to Best Semi-Proseem.
Uncanny probably is going to be on that ballot.
Strange Horizons, nominate Strange Horizons, they're great.
Yeah, Strange Horizons ever won.
Nope.
They're good if they did at some point.
Huge, huge sore point.
Should they win?
They've been close many times, is the thing.
They're usually second, very rarely they're third.
Yeah, Uncanny's very good though.
Yeah.
So I'll definitely nominate those two.
So is Locust.
And Fire.
Fire.
Yeah, very good.
Yes.
Fire are good.
Then there's the Best Editor categories and no one ever knows what's nominating those
because no one understands what they're for.
So then it's the Dramatic Presentation categories.
Let's talk about Best Dramatic Presentation a long form.
I think I've probably seen the most off this list, so I think I should go last.
I have seen very few, actually.
I seem to have accidentally watched no films this year.
Well, I mean, that's not true.
I have not seen no films, but there are some notable omissions like I have not watched
Black Panther or kind of forever, I have not watched The Batman because I have no intention
of watching The Batman.
It's too long.
Oh yeah, don't be mean either.
There's a bunch of potential nominees I have not seen and what I've seen mostly are
the TV shows.
And we need to some extent discuss those when we discussed BDP short form.
But rather than go for the super obvious choice that everyone's going to pick, I am,
in fact, going to pick Turning Red.
I'd see that to me is a super obvious choice everyone's going to pick because that is
a great movie.
10 out of 10 movie.
I mean, I think it is super obvious choice, but I do not think it is the number one choice.
Is it?
I rather liked it.
I'm going to watch Turning Red in time for the nominations because I think that's such
a great pick and I have not seen it.
I've been meaning to see it for ages.
It's very good.
So I really like it.
The director directed Bow, which is a very cute Pixar short film, which I'm pretty sure
made me cry in under five minutes.
Yeah.
So Turning Red, which is about May, a teenager who lives in Toronto with her parents.
And basically she's got her thoughts.
What happens during puberty to her family is that she turns into a giant red panda.
It's great.
Yeah.
And basically she gets it.
It's just great.
She turns into this incredibly cute, cuddly red panda.
And it's all about kind of familiar relationships and family responsibility and diaspora life.
And it feels very kind of also quite specifically set in Toronto and in the kind of Chinese
diaspora in Toronto.
It's just, it's really good.
And I think it ends really nicely as well.
And just the hilarity of this girl.
Like, and one thing Pixar does really well is kind of like the comedy of using the animation
comedy of like making these hilarious figures.
I'm thinking of like, pay max in Big Hero 6, which I know is not certainly Pixar.
You know, kind of these just big cuddly figures or like, um, Sully in Monsters Inc.
But just this kind of great big red panda trying to hide under the bed and hide behind
things is just a really cute visual comedy.
And it was satisfying.
And yeah, it seems to have like gone out in cinemas briefly and then gone away again.
And then I watched it on Disney+.
And I really enjoyed it.
Do you want to do all the ones you've seen all at once Liz?
And then Alison Kanada on the ones she's seen that you didn't mention.
The question is, am I going out in left field and talking about video games since we don't
have a video game category yet?
Because basically...
No, you're not.
No, not I'd do that.
Okay.
But are you actually thinking of nominating some games because you can't, because you don't
have a category for them?
Yeah, because I always used to do this in best romantic presentation long form.
I would always put a video game in and of course it would never get more than a handful
of votes than never get anywhere, but I did it kind of in protest for the fact that there
was no work better to put them.
Yeah, so I will say here that if a game's a proper game, it isn't a dramatic presentation.
But I understand that this is a very specialist for you to be.
I believe we have had this argument before multiple times.
Yeah, but it's a bit like the "Sergai-Luki-enko" thing.
I do have to say it every time.
I am not going to have the argument with you again because I've had this argument previously
about why you were on.
So I'm just going to continue talking about maybe dramatic presentations of the more traditional
format.
I mean, to the obvious one that I mean, I presume it's going to win and possibly win, you know,
a million Oscars as well is everything everywhere or at once.
Yup.
You know, the fantastic tale of another story actually very much about kind of Chinese immigrant
families a lot like "Tiny Red".
But yeah, this again is about, but quite different, I think.
I think quite different in tone, but I do have some kind of similar themes.
Maybe if you watch "Tiny Red", although one is, you know, about more aimed at a child
audience and involves a giant panda.
And I don't recall there being any giant pandas in everything everywhere or at once,
even though there are, you know, rocks and googly eyes and so on.
Banned to be a giant panda, so well, there's a raccoon.
It's probably one somewhere.
There's a raccoon.
The raccoon.
So yes, if you haven't seen everything everywhere or at once, then turn off the podcast and
go and watch everything everywhere or at once.
And of course it's not a giant panda returning red, is it?
It's a giant red panda.
Is that a red panda?
Yeah.
Well, Octothorb, nitpick corner.
I mean, yeah.
But I think it's quite an important nitpick because, you know, dark pandas all get all
the love and red pandas don't really get that much love.
And do you want me to draw you all as red pandas this issue?
I mean, yes.
You know the red pandas, or you can draw us all as rocks with googly eyes that would
also be acceptable and possibly easier.
But yes, everything everywhere or at once.
It's a great film about with Michelle Yeo as essentially a middle-aged Chinese immigrant
woman who gets swept up in an adventure through the multiverse.
And it's quite hard to describe beyond that because it's just really good.
And it's got the everything bagel.
So I just go and watch it basically.
I'm not going to describe it any further.
It's fair.
Oh, I could.
And the show notes to a podcast with the Daniels who wrote and directed it, which I found pretty
interesting.
If you want to hear more about how it came about and the other work.
So what else on this list have I seen?
I mean, I think we kind of covered that there are a few TV shows that I might nominate as
a series.
The ones I'm thinking of is I have seen there is for all my kind, season three, severance
season one.
I'm not sure as any other TV shows I would consider nominating.
And also I haven't seen quite a few of them.
Andor?
Oh, Andor, yes.
So again, a question is like, just which one do I put it in?
But I did think Andor had some very good individual episodes.
So I'm up with those in.
So I guess in terms of films, the other one I was thinking about is possibly don't worry
darling widely.
I think thought of as not very good at both the box office and with critics, but I though
I enjoyed it.
I watched it with John in person.
Yes.
Wow.
And it's essentially got Florence Pugh as a 50s housewife in a glamorous utopia where
every day the husbands got off to work and all the housewives are kind of left, you know,
to live this 50s life.
But it's incredibly unsettling from the start.
Like, you know something is going on.
And it's just got this very unsettling tone right from the start of knowing that something
is going on and not being able to figure out exactly what is going on.
What's so like, one division then?
No, because it's more unsettling than one division because in one division, I think
Wanda knows something's weird.
And in this Florence Pugh doesn't.
And I think that makes it, it's definitely feels more unsettling than one division.
Yeah, it's got much more of a horror tone as well because you're like, you know, these
are everyday people rather than, you know, a super powered woman.
And so then you're like, what is going on?
And it basically uses the idea, it's a very, maybe not original idea that, you know, you
were trapped as a 1950s housewife, but is she literally trapped as a 1950s housewife
and how?
When I would say, it's as similar to what I always say about moon, which is although
I don't think moon is like astonishingly original in terms of its idea.
It is astonishingly original in terms of having that idea in a movie.
And I think don't worry, darling is similar where I think I've seen similar concepts.
But I don't think I've ever seen it in a mainstream movie directed by a woman before,
which kind of is interesting.
It's also interesting because Chris Pine is amazing in it.
And I thought Harry Styles was very good.
Initially, I thought Harry Styles was bad.
And then I understood what role he was playing.
And I was like, oh no, he's actually smashed it, which is always nice when the reveal at
the end of the film makes it clear what an actor is doing.
And you're like, oh, and I will say it was not well received by critics.
I got 38% on Ron Tomatoes, but it has an audience score of 74%, which is quite the divide.
And I do wonder whether people went into it thinking that it wasn't SF.
And then, like, especially the critics went into it expecting something very different
and came out disappointed.
But I think as an SF film, it's quite good.
I enjoyed it.
I would watch it again.
Yeah.
So I think I might also nominate that.
I think almost almost all science fiction TV and movies uses tropes that we've previously
seen in books or graphic novels.
And I tend not to mark them down for that because I'm kind of like it would be a bit
of a stretch to do a completely original science fiction concept as a movie given the budget
that movies tend to need to make them work.
You know, so I don't really mind.
So having said that, everything everywhere, all at once, which is on my list, is pretty
original.
Yeah, and that's one of the good things about it.
I mean, I think I don't want to say too much because I think if I dig deeply into where
I think Don't Worry Darling may have been done on film before, then I will start giving away
some of the interesting things about Don't Worry Darling.
Yeah, no, I need to watch this one as well.
Apparently, I have two to-do lists.
What services is it on?
I don't know.
We rented it off Amazon.
It's now on HBO Go, but I don't think you can get HBO Go.
So it may be on like now TV films or something.
Not now.
You know what I mean?
No TV, but has movies.
Yeah, and I think it does have what I felt was a sort of particularly, it felt like particularly
2020's spin on it.
And I won't say any more than that.
Yes, I'd agree with that.
I think what I would say is even when I thought it wasn't, you know, even though I think it
is not amazing throughout, maybe it has some rough edges.
It did get me thinking more than a lot of the stuff I've seen this year.
So I think that is my initial set.
And you should go now, go through things you might be nominating.
And I might go, "Oh yeah, I watched that and forgot."
So it was everything everywhere I wanted once.
Don't worry, Darling.
And turning red.
Yes.
I wanted to discuss a few movies.
So first thing, I'm not putting any Marvel movies in my nominations.
I thought all three of the Marvel movies that came out, Black Panther, Doctor Strange and
Thor were solid, but I don't think any of them deserved to win.
Hugo, I think what kind of forever will make it onto the nominations list because of what
it represents.
And it's very touching in some ways, but I didn't think it really worked for me as a
film.
It worked as a tribute, but not as a story.
I will be nominating Pray, probably.
Pray was very good.
I've talked about it on the pod previously, so I will not talk about it again.
And I will probably nominate Nope, which is the Jordan Peele movie.
I love Jordan Peele.
I think Nope is the weakest of his three movies, but you're talking like four out of five instead
of five out of five.
So like, it's tricky.
And basically, I just like that there's intelligent, original horror on the big screen.
I won't be nominating Neptune Frost.
I won't see that.
Neil Harrison, friend of the podcast, was like, "Oh, I don't work on Wednesdays.
We should go to the cinema on a Wednesday afternoon and see it."
So me and his fanier took time off and then Neil flaked and then we had to watch Neptune
Frost, which is not good.
So you know, that was a fun afternoon.
Do you think you've used this film or have been coloured in some way by being stood up?
I went to see it excited about the idea of an original sci-fi movie that was like quite
small and like, and I was not.
It was not good.
No, one over.
Yeah, okay.
No.
I nominate Men.
I enjoyed Men by Alex Garland.
Quite a lot.
Says quite a lot about how awful Men are, which I like.
Turns out we're really awful.
And it made me think that in a way that I don't, I know it intellectually, but it really gave
me an insight into how scary Men are.
And also, having watched Men and having watched Ex Machina, anyone who watches an Alex Garland
film is like, "I wonder what Alex Garland thinks about gender.
I wonder if he's a misogynist."
No.
What?
Are you paying attention?
We're awful.
Anyway, the Men are not the good guys in his films, guys.
Like, spoiler alert, the Men are the baddies.
Except in Dred.
But I don't think he's really talking about gender as much in Dred.
He's talking about kick-ass judges and their morally questionable decision-making.
And I also, yesterday, I watched Vespa.
Vespa is interesting.
It's a Lithuanian science fiction film.
It is currently on Netflix in the UK.
It was probably about 20 minutes too long.
It is very downbeat.
It is quite disgusting in places.
But it was, I did enjoy it very much.
I thought it was really good and real nice dystopian movie.
So disgusting.
Is that a gory or like poo or vomit or...?
It's got a lot of blood in places, but it's in a world where humanity tried to respond
to climate change with genetic engineering, and that went about as well as you might
expect, and like everyone left his hold up in Citadel's except for the Paws who aren't.
So far, so like, you know, this is a trope that's been done before.
But like, the design is just amazing because like right at the beginning of the movie,
you see a tree breathing and it's like, "Oh yeah, of course.
If you go far enough down that road, you get trees that breathe.
It's just so gross."
You just see this tree breathing like, "Oh no, no, that is not, no, don't like."
And there's like a lot of genetic technology.
And it's just, yeah, it's very good, but it's very gross, but it's very good.
I did like that a lot.
Okay, so it's actually hitting up that things that make people go, "Oh, this is quick."
Yeah, I think so.
I think it's doing on.
And I think it does it well and on purpose.
Those are my picks.
So men with a question mark and prey and vesper are also like potentials as well as nope.
They are all films I have heard of, but not watched.
I mean, prey and nope are definitely my list of things to get through before the nomination
period ends.
So I will try to get to those.
And men as well, actually.
Mentioned everything I've seen, but this may need to go in an interjection.
Before we stop talking about "Don't worry, darling," which I haven't seen but would
like to, I need to mention something about Florence Pugh that I discovered since we last
recorded, which is that Florence Pugh has a party trick.
And it turns out that her party trick, she's like, "I don't know what it's called, but
it's just the thing that you could do."
And her party trick is the Astral Pole, which long time readers may know is a science
fiction thing.
From the '70s, I think the '70s or the early '80s in British fandom, where you step over
a pole in increasingly implausible ways and don't take your hands off the pole, we will
put a link to Florence Pugh doing the Astral Pole very competently in the show notes.
If I can find it again.
And yeah, if you could do the Astral Pole, please have a video.
I could do the Astral Pole when I was about 20, but it's been a while.
Can't now.
I could never do the Astral Pole.
I did when I was introduced to it in 2005 at the World Con Mining thing, Astral Shark,
which is where instead of using a pole, you use an inflatable shark, which is quite bendy.
And that is how I managed to do it.
But now I suspect I could not even do the Astral Shark.
And we're going to have a 2024 Glasgow World Con rerun of this event in which people who
could do the Astral Pole in 2005 try it again and I'll put their backs out.
Yay!
But otherwise, the only other thing I was going to mention was that we haven't mentioned
the TV shows we're going to, because I am going to put Andor and Severance for sure
on my long form list, as well as having a second bite of the cherry in short form, unless
some Hugo's rule lawyer tells me that's a terrible idea.
You put Russian Doll Season 2 in the show notes and I would describe it as aggressively
fine.
So, Russian Doll Season 1 was fantastic, but I didn't feel like it needed anything more
going on.
And I couldn't see how Russian Doll Season 2 would actually add anything to it.
So it's not that I don't intend to watch it.
I do intend to watch it at some point, but it just seemed like it was not likely to be
as exciting.
I think Season 2 could have been great if they'd done it well.
It doesn't quite come together doing too many different things.
In the absence of a best game Hugo, I have for some years been putting video games into
best romantic presentation long form on the ground so they don't fit anywhere else and
I like nominating video games things.
And we have now passed the idea of best game Hugo, but not ratified it.
And so I'm going to continue the tradition for one more year, probably by putting Horizon
for Bidding West on best romantic presentation long form, because it's great.
That is great.
I've been taking my sweet time.
Yeah.
Isn't it like to finish the first one shouldn't I?
You should.
I think you can get the second one now.
I think it's free on one of the PlayStation Plus tiers, but don't ask me to explain different
PlayStation Plus tiers.
It's good.
It's not quite as good as the first one, but I think it would still be worthy of a Hugo
and so I will nominate it and it will not go anywhere.
But that's fine.
I mean, I feel like Horizon is now one of the best things never to have won a Hugo.
Hot take.
I mean, there will be DLC in 2023, right?
There will be in theory eligible for Hugo in 2024.
The catch is that the DLC is only for PlayStation 5.
So.
And also the other catch is that it will be going up against Breath of the Wild 2, right?
Of the news elder, yeah.
Which should not win a Hugo, but which probably will.
I mean, it might be great.
They might have undone all of the things that were wrong with Breath of the Wild and
made a real great sequel.
But I suspect not.
We'll see.
I mean, I love Zelda, but I kind of think that it's not really exciting science fiction
in the way that Horizon is.
Do you fight any Robert dinosaurs in Zelda?
It really depends on your definition of robot and your definition of dinosaur.
Oh, see now I'm more interested in it.
Generic, it's just generic fantasy.
All of the Zelda stuff is generic fantasy tautel, right?
The backstory is not what you're playing this game for.
Oh yeah.
Well, one of the really annoying things about Breath of the Wild is that it really wanted
you to care about like Zelda's mental state.
And I'm like, I've never cared about any of the characters in this franchise, guys.
That is not why I come to a Zelda game.
I come for the intricate dungeons of which there were none.
For fine and 120 quite poor.
Yeah.
For me, Breath of the Wild is a real triumph of quantity over quality.
There was lots to do.
Most of it was fine, which I didn't enjoy.
Um, we can.
I mean, I enjoyed it fine.
We're writing for Bidden best into best related work.
So that's the thing that people can do.
No.
Right, okay.
So the official, the official Octa thought perspective is you should nominate Horizon
Forbidden West in every category and let the admin decide which one it should have gone
in.
Actually, probably not a short story, no, I'll let on my valet because it probably does
have more than 40,000 words in it.
I am a purist, but I think when best related work says it should be notable for things
other than the fictional text, I feel I should not nominate fictional texts.
Hang on.
Oh, no.
Horizon Zero Dawn is notable for, or Horizon Forbidden Village is notable for robot dinosaurs.
Right?
They are not textual robot dinosaurs.
If you didn't have robot dinosaurs, you wouldn't care about the text as much.
What, they're metatextual dinosaurs or something.
They're literal dinosaurs.
No.
They're not, they're like, they're like in your face dinosaurs.
It's not the text.
But are you interpreting text?
I mean, only text on a page here, Alison.
Oh, no.
Um, maybe.
Yeah, no, I think it is part of the text.
Are you being very purist on your definition of text?
You see, the text is, you know, the work.
And I would say that the, uh, fictional dinosaurs are part of the fictional text.
Mm.
I think I agree with Liz here, Alison.
I'm afraid.
Yeah, no, Liz is right.
I'm wrong.
Fine.
Boo.
Ah-ha.
Put that in the soundboard.
Boo, boo, boo.
I'm just glad that the title of the episode is going to be metatextual dinosaurs.
And no one is going to understand that they're going to think it's one thing from the
title and it will be something totally different.
And then it's best-related work.
I'm not sure I've read any related works this year.
I know that the, um, Terry Pratchett biography by Rob Wilkins is in this category.
Oh, no, shoot.
I have, um, uh, management lessons from Westeros by Fiona Moore.
You should all nominate that.
Nominate it for best-related work.
Management lessons from Game of Thrones is its proper title.
And we have been meaning to have this as a pick for ages, but haven't actually managed
to do it.
So, um, it's very, very good, very funny and also quite illuminating.
And it's now her, it's now her, um, thing.
So she's starting to do management lessons from Star Wars and things of this kind.
So I'm very much hoping we're going to see a lot more of this sort of thing.
Yeah.
I am hyped for that.
And we'll be nominating that when it comes out to, I mean, assuming it's good by a guy,
I imagine it won't be good.
So I know that there's much of a risk.
So the Rob Wilkins book and the Fiona Moore book are both things you could consider nominating.
I've not read the Rob Wilkins biography of Terry Pratchett, but everyone I know who has
read it says it was fantastic.
So, uh, I'm starting the nomination campaign now for next year, next year, all these worlds,
reviews and essays by Neil Harrison, uh, needs to be on that balla listeners.
Uh, so buy it and read it now so you can nominate it so that it's on the ballot in Glasgow
so that Neil can win.
We've got a plan and we're doing it.
Claire has mentioned in this space, um, the Peter Nichols collection, genre fiction of
the roaring years, which I think I had a pick on Octthorpe and which I also enjoyed very
much.
And there are other books in Langford series of, um, fan history books that you might want
to think about nominated in this category.
None of them have any chance of winning, I don't think, but you know, the good books.
They're all good books, Brent.
They're not all good books, but most of them are good books.
Yes, Alison picked that on episode 71, just nearly froze to death.
If you want to hear more about her thoughts on it there, have you got any best related,
um, things Liz?
I don't think I have.
I was looking at, um, because obviously like individual essays and things are, would be
eligible.
Yeah.
Uh, but the strange horizons, criticism, uh, issue that I liked so much is actually 2023,
so that will be for next year's ballot.
And I don't think I read a lot of nonfiction related science fiction that isn't, you know,
book reviews and essays and so on and online sources, most of which are covered by the
semi-prozines.
So, yeah.
So then we go to Best Graphic Story or Comic.
I've really dropped out here.
I mean, I used to read quite a lot of comics and I've ended up reading basically no comics,
so I don't actually have anything to put in this category.
I'm not even up to date with kind of, you know, perennial, what I'd say perennial, Hugo
favourites like monstrous and so on.
Yeah.
I find that my taste in this category is quite different from the Hugo electorate more generally.
I mean, I'll probably look through my Marvel Unlimited and work out what I want to nominate
by strongly suspect that it will not get on the ballot.
If I was going to advocate for one thing from Marvel Unlimited that I've read, it would
be the most recent run of Moon Knight, which I thought was really, really excellent as a
comic.
So I would go for that one, which I believe is Volume 9, which I believe does extend into
it.
It started in 2021, but I believe there is a volume in 2022 because it has been ongoing
and it has won the Golden Issue Award for Best Ongoing Comic.
So yeah, I'm not the only one who likes it listeners.
Oh, and Moon Knight Black White and Blood number one was in May 2022.
So yes, I'll be nominating some Moon Knight.
But yeah, I don't think it'll be on the ballot.
So any comics, Alison?
No.
And then it's Best Series.
So Liz, you have a couple of picks here, I think.
I do have a couple of Best Series, which cross over as well with my picks in Best Novel
and Best in Load Star Awards, which is I am going to pick Robert Jackson Bennett's Foundry
Side Trilogy, which I think was exceptionally good.
The Last Book of Gloatlands was published last year, if you like sort of secondary world,
fantasy series, then why we've mixed it up already.
I will also be picking No, We, No, Big's Golden Enclave series, where the first one's
Color Man's Awards nominated for the Load Star before.
But I think the second and third books are actually better than the first one and do open
out the world in a way I enjoyed.
I mean, I've got some quibbles about them, but I think they're worthy of going in Best
Series.
I'm going to also nominate Probably The Cemeteries of Amala by Katherine Addison, which is a series
of sort of murder mysteries in the Goblin Emperor universe and the work for that would
be Good Grief of Stones that was published this year.
I don't think they're the best books ever, but I do find them kind of always pleasant
and pleasantly fun to read, as they may go in there.
I did also notice that Cora Vullet has pointed out that Elric is eligible for Best Series
this year.
Or is feeling super retro?
Well, there's more published a new Elric novel because that would be awesome.
Apparently he has published a new Elric something.
I'm just looking up to see if it is a novel or a collection of short stories or a short
piece or whatever.
But yes, apparently there was a new Elric in 2022 and so you can nominate the whole of
Elric if you really want to.
I mean, I've read the first one, but not however many other novels are in the series.
So one I will be nominating for Best Series is the Children of Time, Children of Memory,
Trilogy by N. Tricofsky, which is very good and I think would be a worthy winner of the
Best Series Hugo.
I believe Tricofsky's other, the final architecture series is also eligible.
No, because there's only been two out so far and the third one is 2023.
Ah, so nominate that one next year listeners.
That will be next year.
But I mean, thinking about it, I think the Children of Time series may also be eligible
next year because the third book is out 2023 in the US.
So that's going to be very complicated.
I am well, don't split the Tricofsky vote next year guys.
Nominate them both.
I want to fly the plaid for some other British series.
I think that Fractured Europe by Dave Hutchinson is eligible because although the fifth book
that came out in 2022 is kind of sideways to the other four, it's still set in the same
universe and I think that counts for the purposes of Best Series.
And I also want to shout out the fellow sister series by Liz Williams, which is the one
that starts with Comic Weather and the Green Man series by Juliet McKenna, both of which
are eligible and both of which contain books that I have enjoyed very much indeed though
as always with series, I've never read the whole series, not for donkey's ears afterwards,
you know what it's like, but they have both got great books in them.
Retrospectively realized that given that Alistair Reynolds published a new revelation
space novel in 2021, even though I didn't really like it, it would have been eligible
as a series as a whole.
And I do like the series as a whole.
However, he wrote another one that will be coming out in 2023 so I can have this whole
conversation again next year.
Yeah, we should have this conversation at more length next year.
We should make a plan earlier in the year.
Alright, then it's on to short stories.
Alison, how's your short story beading bin this year?
So 2023 has been a thing so far.
So normally I do a pile of short story reading in the first couple of months of the year.
Well, you know, a dozen or so haven't done any.
So if you've ever hankered after an episode of Octa thought where John and Liz do it as
a two-hander and I don't say a word.
The next 20 minutes or so for you.
Moving to short stories.
My first short story is a very short story, cocking in at under 1500 words by Margaret
Dunlap in Uncanny 45.
I really like it.
It's fantasy.
It's kind of in a similar world's toy story in that toys are sentient beings.
And it's just, yeah, it's just very, I just found it very poignant.
And I really liked it. It was very simple, but it was very effective.
Does not take long to read.
As my first story links to all these short stories are in the show notes.
Okay, so my first short story is I've chosen Critical Mass by Peter Watts from Lightspeed
magazine, which is about Leo Gregory, who's kind of a future architect who finds his studio
vandalized and it's partly about trying to work out, you know, who vandalized his studio,
but partly about all these artworks of his that are being vandalized around the world.
And you know, it said in this kind of, I don't know what feels like now a fairly standard
near future dystopia of bio hackers, gen engineering things and refugees and climate change.
But I kind of liked how that was sort of the background thing.
And what I actually, what I really liked about it is I read a lot of short stories that didn't
actually go anywhere on the level of ending.
And this one feels like it has an actual ending.
So this one's going on my ballot.
Nice.
On the subject of stories that had an ending is Transference by Vivian Shaw.
So this was in Uncanny 49.
I really love this story. It might be my favorite of the four that I am going to nominate.
It is a story about magical tattoos, which are subject I've always been fascinated by.
And I'm not really sure why, but like I've always been, always been completely entranced
by the idea of kind of magic that works through tattoos, which I think is why I like the painted
man series quite so much.
And yeah, it's just amazing.
And I then discovered that Vivian Shaw is married to Arcady Martin and I am very jealous
of the amount of story writing prowess that exists in that partnership.
My second and third choices actually are in a way very well linked together.
So my second choice is Rabbit Test by Uncanny magazine.
And you might be able to guess what it's about from the title.
It is essentially again about a sort of future dystopia, but it's about one with control
of women's reproduction.
So the framing story is kind of a girl, Grace who's under 18 and it's 2091 and there's
basically an app that is going to automatically administer pregnancy tests on women in a world
where abortion is not allowed.
And the rabbit test of the title is because that's historically how pregnancy tests were
done before we invented the lateral flow test.
It's Grace's story, but with the interjections from the past of abortion and reproductive
justice and activism.
Yeah, I think it is quite, like it's definitely got a message and it's quite firm in its message,
but I think it feels pretty timely and I did enjoy the story enough to include it.
I really enjoyed the setup and I really enjoyed the beginning of the story, but it was in
contrast to your previous bit where you said the ending really landed.
I thought this was a story that just sort of stopped and that is why I haven't got it
on my list to nominate.
But it has also been nominated for an Ebula, so it clearly struck chords with a variety
of people.
Yeah, I think it feels like that story that comes along at precisely the right time to
land with people.
My next pick is Family Cooking by Anna Maria Curtis.
If I had to, like I think if it wasn't transparent, so my favourite, it would be this one, because
this one is also just so good.
It's about someone who is magic and their magic lets them make great food, but at the
beginning of the story, they can no longer make great food and the story is kind of about
why that is.
And it's about family and about emotion and about whether or not your emotions are something
you can live with.
It's just very, very good and I really liked it.
It made me, and it really resonated with me for personal reasons as well.
So yeah, I just, I do ordered this story.
Do you have magical powers for making great food, John?
No.
So my third pick relatedly, and actually probably my favourite of the three I've got at the
moment is, again from light speed, it's called the CRISPR cookbook, a guide to biohacking
your own abortion in a postural world.
And it is exactly that basically it's supposedly a manual for like how you are going to biohack
yourselves to perform an abortion in the future where it is illegal.
I just thought it was very kind of solidly written.
It's written as though it's like a, you know, a bit like a scientific manual, which as far
as I can tell is also kind of completely, completely accurate as far as it goes.
And it's pretty short and kind of doesn't outstay it's welcome and ends the kind of
this note of like, okay, so if we're going to biohack ourselves to do this, what else
are we going to biohack ourselves to do?
And so I really enjoyed it.
And it is by a pseudonymous author whose name I think is like the start of the CRISPR enzyme
protein sequence, which is pretty neat.
And I also, I very much like the, so light speed has like pages for all the authors that
have written fiction for the magazine.
And I very much like the author page for the author who wrote this.
I've linked it in the show notes.
I won't say it here, but it's very good.
My last one is Lily the Immortal, which is the longest of the four I'm nominating.
And I think I've inadvertently guys, I've picked four stories about feelings.
What?
It was just, I know none of them are about lasers, Liz.
So it's like you have feelings, John.
But this one's very good and is about grief in the wake of losing a friend and about how
technology might help or hinder that process.
And I really liked it.
It kind of feels like it's dealing with some of the same themes as Westworld season three
but I think it does more with them in 60, in 6,000 words.
Westworld season three did over the course of 10 hours.
So there is that onto novelttes.
So full disclosure, my picks for novelttes are, I mean, I think I like all three of them
very much and I haven't kind of tried to find five to nominate because I have definitely
like thresholded at kind of ones I think are worthy.
But like it is definitely true.
I have read fewer novelttes than short stories.
So I think the short stories I picked out are probably a little bit stronger than the
novelttes but you know, your mileage may vary.
Do you want to go first, Liz?
I can go first.
So I will say also that I've read many fewer novelttes than short stories when I was going
through kind of things recommended from online venues.
They were really heavily slanted towards short stories.
And I mean, I read a few novelttes I just didn't think were worth nominating and then
there's kind of this extra investment of time in the novelttes which means I'm kind of
less like you take a chance on like a novellette or even a novella by someone I haven't had
recommended which is a long way of saying that what I did do was I read a bunch of short
fiction that was put together by Amazon in one of the kind of free collections and I'm
going to nominate three items from that.
And I think these ones are novelttes but I'm guessing because I don't actually know how
long they are.
Anyway, so the first one is The Sixth Set Death of the Saint by Alex Harrow which is about
a woman in a sort of quasi-medieval fantasy world who becomes the kingdom's greatest warrior
and it turns out she is basically endlessly repeating her own story and dying and then
getting slightly further or in the service of making a man like the emperor of the world
and then how she takes it back into her own hands and I enjoyed it.
And then there's What the Dead Know by Nivor which is from the same collection but kind
of a totally different feel.
I thought this one had a very sort of eerie feel to it.
It's about a woman who is posing as kind of a spirit medium who can channel the voice
of the dead in a world where the dead do actually exist and rise as ghosts and it's
all about how they go off to one place to kind of channel the voices of the dead and
end up meeting a ghost there.
And I think it's just this one I just felt was really kind of well written and really
well characterised in a short time.
So that is mine.
I'm also going to nominate one of John's as well but I'll let him talk about that.
I'm going to pick Your Eyes My Beacon being an account of several Mr Dventures and How
I Found My Way Home by C.L. Clark.
This is about a lighthouse keeper and someone they meet and they're both quite lonely.
It's quite good.
They also have some genre elements but you know they're good too.
I like this one quite a lot and I thought it was, I don't know, I don't know why it
just spoke to me and it was nice.
I'm going to pick Two Hands Wrapped in Gold by S.B. Divya.
This is a story about a young girl who has a magic power and it doesn't necessarily go
as well as you would ideally like.
Although it kind of does.
I'm good at snopsizing short stories.
Very carefully worded to avoid new spoilers that John and the world on.
And then is my favourite novelt and I believe Liz is also planning to nominate this one
which is If You Find Yourself Speaking to God, Address God with the Informal You by
John Chu.
This I believe also got nominated for a nebula.
I just loved it.
I thought it was great.
It basically like, I guess you find God in the least likely places and this story is
an example of that.
But yeah, and just very human and very low key but also very big.
I liked the juxtaposition of scales.
And then it's onto Novellas.
I've got One Novella which is Radcliffe Hall by Miyuki Jane Pinkard in Uncanny 48.
I quite liked it.
I'm more nominating it because it's the Novella I read rather than because I think it was
like amazing but I did really enjoy it.
It's got, you know, it's kind of a sapphic, creepy, almost Lovecraftian story set in an
old boarding school.
So like it's hitting a lot of things I like in fiction all in one story.
And so I don't know, you know, it might not be high art but I liked it quite a lot.
All right, so I'm nominating two Novellas.
At least I think so because I don't know if undercover by Tamzemir is a Novella or a
novelt.
This is partly because it came from this Amazon collection where I just get page counts.
But anyway, it is the only thing of Tamzemir has I read that isn't, you know, Gideon the
9th which he's obviously come to fame for.
But this I really liked.
It's about kind of, you know, a newcomer in, she comes into town where there's, you know,
the gang leader who runs a burlesque show but kind of one of her star burlesque dancers
is a ghoul.
And this newcomer who comes into town is basically an undercover cop who is trying to track down
and get rid of these ghouls before they start eating everyone.
And yeah, it's just, it's good.
It's, I like all the kind of, you know, it's very evocative when you go and see this ghoul
she seems very kind of non-human and human.
It's sort of got this like saloon kind of feeling.
They're in the burlesque show.
They've got the saloon.
I don't know.
It just, it just feels like a very different setting in which to put this when you could
have just put it in kind of like a city somewhere where she was hunting ghouls.
She's put a lot of effort into the setting as well.
So I really liked that one.
My last Novella pick is the 2-Dock Skorsky by Isaac Falman which is from Tor.com.
This is one of the standalone Novellas and this is, I believe it's what the kids call
Dark Akademia.
It's about a graduate student who essentially is forced to leave her and academic position
and become a student in a different institution under an infamous magician who is known for,
well, he's mostly known for having created a homunculus of himself when younger, which
is something that we just need to do in this universe that kind of splits you into two
parts and takes part of your personality with you.
And it's really all about the student's kind of connection with both of these split parts
of this personality.
And yeah, I really enjoyed it.
We're out of the short fiction minds readers so Alison can come back and then Novell.
I mean, my novel picks are quite, I'm from a quite straightforward.
I already mentioned Robert Jackson Bennett's Locklands trilogy and I'm going to nominate
Locklands the third book in that series.
I don't expect to be on the ballot because the third book in a trilogy very rarely makes
onto the ballot if the first two didn't.
But it's really good.
I really enjoyed it.
I cried on a plane reading this book and I've also had it as a pick.
So yeah, you should go and watch them.
Read them.
Makes sense.
I was sent a copy of Sea of Tranquility by Emily Cintron-Mantle by Roy Kettle who really
liked it and recommended it but said, "Oh, I have passed the point of my life where I
keep all my books."
So I got that in the post and read it just the other couple of days.
If we'd just be doing a normal octothop it could have been a pick.
And I thought it was very good indeed.
I like novels that feel like proper novels.
So I like novels that are sparse and elegant and do what they need to do and do not control
anything extraneous.
And I like it even better when they are genre which this one is and it is a lovely novel
about time travel and the nature of reality and the...and it's got historical bits and
current day bits and future bits and it's just fantastic and I strongly recommend it
to everyone and it's also very short so it will not cause you to give up a fortnight of
your life getting it read.
It's fine.
It's an easy read for an afternoon.
Strongly recommended definitely going on my ballot.
Thank you Claire, Briley, off-croydon for the recommendation.
Yes.
So I believe this is eligible and I think Abigail Nisbahn said that she would be a little bit
but she was nominating it.
But then when I checked my goodreads it said it was published in 2020.
But I think it was published in Finnish in 2020 and it was published in English in 2022
which is why it is eligible and it is the Moon Day Letters by Emi Iteranta.
This is something Neil Harrison and Nick Cloud brought me for a birthday.
I talked about it in a previous octa thought.
I really liked it.
It is worth noting.
It's Panea.
I think it's read say bounced off it because she was like I find this book very difficult
because of how utterly stupid the main character is and I was like I could see that reading.
I think we're supposed to, I think Iteranta is supposed, is trying to bring us to conclusions
about what is going on before the main character gets there and I quite liked that sense of
dramatic tension.
I think if Spani had found it absolutely infuriating that the main character wasn't also reaching
the same conclusions because they were blending the obvious and I can see how that could have
been frustrating if you weren't enjoying that part of the ride.
Yes, I did like it and I will be nominating it.
Oh, back to me.
I am going to possibly steal one of John here because I am going for the spearkutch through
water by Simon Jimenez which is his second novel.
It's a fantasy novel about essentially two young men going on a quest to save the moon
and reset the world they are living in.
But it's also got these kind of layers of framing stories from people who are in the
same world but later which is not our world but feels adjacent to our world and what they
see in dreams and the show they see in a kind of stage show they see in dreams that frames
it all.
It kind of takes what might be a fairly straightforward secondary world, kind of interesting fantasy
quest and makes it so much better by having all these extra intricate layers on top and
weaving them all together throughout and it was quite tricky.
It's quite a long book as well I think maybe a little bit longer than it needs to be but
I feel it does bring all these threads together very neatly at the end and I really enjoyed
it.
I will also be nominating City of Last Chances by Adrian Tchaikovsky which is a stone cold
masterpiece.
It's just so good because it's got like two full pages of dramatic personi at the beginning
and reading that I was a bit like oh god this is going to be one of those fantasy novels
where there are a million characters and I have to keep referring back.
But the way Tchaikovsky threads the plot through the characters and through the settings means
that although you go all over this incredibly intricate city and although you have all of
these different characters and although the world feels incredibly big and incredibly
real you never feel lost within it.
He is so good at bridging between characters and settings in a way that means you always
feel grounded and you always know where you are and it is just it was just so good.
It's not quite like anything else I've ever read and it was amazing and I will be enthusiastically
nominating it.
I am super looking forward to this one.
Oh and one that Tchaikovsky also read which I'll nominate for a laugh while I don't think
will be on the ballot is Day of Ascension which is the Warhammer 40,000 book he wrote about
Jean Stelers.
I suspect most of the Hugo electorate have not read it but oh boy it's a fun read.
Yeah I think of Tchaikovsky's five 22 novels that's probably at the bottom of you know
how many people are likely to nominate it.
I believe there are only four Liz.
Only four I'm sorry okay.
I think so.
Well Garen and Wright are fair so we can have the old Tchaikovsky shortlist please.
I just want to say one quick word which is that there is a novel bable by R.F.
Quang that is incredibly polarizing amongst my friends list.
I have loads of people saying it's the best thing they read last year and loads of people
sing yeah it's not that much.
So I just think if you're interested in books that polarize people that might be one to
read in the next eight days.
It's going to be on the shortlist anyway so it's going to be on the shortlist anyway
but also it's really long and so if you're going to read one book in the next eight days
maybe you don't pick one of the longest options you could possibly pick.
I'd pick a shorter one you've got a better chance of finishing.
Read all of our short fiction picks first.
Yes yes.
That is my plan.
Alright now we're done John.
And we don't get to do best game till next year.
No.
I'm going to play lots of games in 2023.
Yeah.
That was the old thought podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
[Music]
We're not doing picks this episode because we're doing a special Hugo nominations all
the time episode and then we're going to do another episode about all the other stuff
that's happened but we do have to tell you about what would have been my pick if we
were doing picks which is the EasterCon catch up.
So if you're a member of the EasterCon then you probably do know that almost every program
item we did is available to watch for another couple of weeks at the point that we're recording
but it will probably it may well have gone down by the time we record again so we're
telling you to watch it now.
It's great for just watching you can put it on your telly and you can watch it you can
listen to program items while you're doing other things.
I have now seen more EasterCon program than at any EasterCon for decades because I've
picked it all up on catch up and I've seen about seven or eight items now.
It's been absolutely great really loving it.
It's interesting that the program item I have enjoyed most so far has been a purely fandom
based one where it was at some point in the panel somebody from the audience explained
that it was more a comment than a question sort of a panel and indeed these are the program
items I've always liked.
I don't think they should be on at 10.30 in the morning.
I think they should be on later in the day and I wish we had a lot more of that sort of
thing and a lot less of boring panels.
I have to say I've seen a couple of those two.
I've also seen a couple where what was described by Carrie in Moose as every panel has to have
one elderly white man who doesn't know very much about the topic pontificating and I've
seen a couple of those.
If you're that man, stop volunteering for program and if you're the program people,
stop putting about all those program items.
I mean that's a separate conversation as to how you do that so we'll save that for another
time.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Anyway, what could catch up if you've seen off the EasterCon that I was so involved in
creating and have been working on for two years with this catch up in mind as one of the
things we were going to do?
Well, I haven't watched any of it.
I'm very bad at watching stuff on catch up because like, well, there's a bunch of other
stuff I could be doing now I'm home from EasterCon.
But you do go to the program at the convention when I'm in the bar with my friends because
I go I could watch catch up any time but I could only be in the bar with my friends right
now.
Whereas I enjoy watching program, you know, I enjoy watching program at the time but I
think I don't enjoy it quite as much when I'm home and there's a bunch of other stuff
I've been catching up on.
My favorite program item is one of the ones about science fiction that Alison thinks should
be removed in favor of fandom items which was Desert Island Books with Neil Harrison and
Dan Hartland which was fascinating.
Oh, you see, I would have said that was a fan item.
Can't just define them as fan items because you want to define them as fan items.
No, it's a fan item because it's actually a biographical item about a fan told through
the medium of favorite books.
I see I disagree with that because I would argue that most of the things Neil was on highlighted
his critic side, not his fan side and certainly I enjoyed the third row panel to which you
referred earlier.
I was on it but I did have fun being on it but Desert Island Books was really fascinating
as an examination of why Neil does his criticism, how he does it and how his experiences have
shaped that.
It was an extremely good guest of honor item and it's a little bit of shame that they had
some technical difficulties because it was very early in the con but it is great.
I really recommend that.
Very, very good item.
Yes, the one I'm most looking forward to watching that I haven't yet got to is the one about
overshoots which I have not seen yet but I am looking forward to watching.
So I did really like a straight scientific talk.
This is one of the hybrid things that you can do which is Dana Staffs, the lady in the octopus.
One of the great things about hybrid conventions is that you can bring in experts from all over
the world and have them do their thing on Zoom and then into the thing and get, but nevertheless
get interaction from the audience and from Discord and that talk was fantastic.
I'm sure there are other fantastic scientific talks but I really, really like that one and
would recommend it too.
Which was about Jean-Vieux Poure power who invented the modern aquarium.
Oh interesting.
So fantastic talk.
And also a shameless plug.
I did an interview with Adrian Tricowski and I had a whale of a time and I think everyone
should go watch it because he's just great.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod in Competec.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beat.
beep
- Thank you.