Oh, it sounds good. Am I loud enough? Am I in a tunnel?
Is Liz in a tunnel?
And hello? Yes?
Alison, please talk.
Oh, yes, please keep going.
Oh, no, it's just a voice.
Keep talking infinitely.
Don't stop talking.
Keep talking and don't be exposed.
Yes.
It is quite hypnotic, actually.
[Laughter]
Don't.
OctaThop ASMR channel.
Coming soon.
Appartition.
Well done. Can you hear me?
Yes.
Yep, wonderful.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 81st episode of OctaThop, the podcast for Science Fiction
and Science Fiction Random, which is coming to you on the 13th of April 2023, but also live from
EasterCon. I'm John Coxson.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And Alison is a giant head to my left and to my right.
I mean, in general.
So I come along virtually to join this panel because I was feeling completely fine when I went
to bed last night, which was about an hour and a quarter to five in the morning, and then I woke
up at about eight o'clock and thought, I feel just a tiny bit softly.
So I am a tiny bit softly person with positive COVID tests and I'm in my room.
I could have quite a good time this morning, despite being in my room.
And at the green room, props to the green room who have brought me a pint of water.
Yes.
So we all have matching drinks.
So we have a stunt Alison, which Liz procured at the Fan Fund auction,
which we have here to represent Alison in her absence.
And for Alison.
Are you suggesting I'm round?
No. We're suggesting you're short.
It's completely different.
BB8's pretty round, right?
Yes. Yes. For the benefit of audio listeners,
yes, is Oleg the Miacat in a BB8 costume, which is apparently Star Wars Tap that John donated to
the Fan Fund auction. And then I bought it from the Fan Fund auction, which may be the only time
Star Wars Tap has ever gone in that direction.
So Liz, it's really cute.
Liz purchased it and then remarked, scandalised later in the bar, that he is naked under his BB8
costume. So, you know, I mean, I don't know what I expected it to be a cat.
Yes.
Can you not suggest you could add a topically correct me a cat, are you?
I know. No one was suggesting that.
I think it under is naked under his BB8 suit.
And we, yes, we had a good time at the Fan Fund auction.
We sold some Adrian Krakowski books for like 280 pounds, James Shields,
who is in the audience looking very happy with himself.
And that was very good. And I purchased a copy of all these worlds reviews and essays by Neil
Harrison, which came with a free 1000 word review that I can, we can make, Hog and I went
halves on our bid and we can make Neil write a review that is 1000 words of anything we want.
And so we broke the news to him on the third row panel as to what it was he would be reviewing.
So I recommend looking at that on catch up if you haven't seen it. But when the review is written,
we will doubtless talk about it on the pod.
Are we going to talk a little bit about Neil Harrison and his book and in being
guest of honor? Neil Harrison is guest of honor.
He is guest of honor. I mean, that is one reason why I'm here.
Not the only reason, but it made it an easier decision to come back because he's the guest of honor.
He has written a book which we have plugged a couple of times. We'll plug again.
We've plugged all potential options through this convention.
It's a very good book of reviews and essays. It's also very green.
Extremely green.
It's very, I do like the design.
Yeah. And he signed my copy to John, despite shenanigans.
So.
Which shenanigans specifically?
I didn't ask. I left it as an exercise to the reader.
We also have other guests of honor at this convention. So we have a guest of honor in the
audience. Carrie Sparing, give Carrie a round of applause.
I also have all but one of Carrie's books signed by Carrie because I asked how you
acquired them. And I just got a large box in the post the week after I asked with a book in,
but they're also very good. I've picked them on this very podcast.
You have. You know, who else's books we have picked on this very podcast?
No, whose books have you checked on this very podcast?
Guest of honor, Adrian Tchaikovsky.
Yes.
Who John interviewed yesterday.
Yes, today. Yes, today. It's been a long.
A long weekend.
So the convention didn't put me on the program at any point.
So I was a little bit worried that maybe it was all just a giant prank.
So I didn't advertise it on the previous episode of Octa Thorpe.
But again, if you are listening to this and hopefully the catch up
strange will still be up for a while, you can go and watch Mind's View with Adrian,
which I think went very well. He is very interesting.
And we did briefly discuss what a popular worker's uprising in the Mushroom Kingdom would look like.
So if that interests you, that's a good interview to go and watch on the catch up.
And I have a Zencho book here.
Zencho being another guest, one of this convention?
Yes.
And such a good reader.
I went to her reading and it was extremely good.
But she read from Blackboard's sister in her guest world interview
and she very kindly gave me the copy she read from and signed it afterwards.
So yes, it's been a, I now have signed books by all the guests of Anna.
Hurrah.
All the guests of Anna? What about the virtual ones?
Oh, no. No, I don't have.
But they, I mean, I suppose they could virtually sign,
but I don't know if there's a pen that goes across the Atlantic.
Post them a pen.
So awaiting for Alice and to say things, she's being uncharacteristically quiet.
I guess because you're not writing.
Just waiting for the two of you to let me get a worded edgeways
and I was also going, "Oh, virtual people don't count, right?"
It's not normally how it works.
You don't normally wait to get a worded edgeways.
No, that is, I think, it makes sense because you're on Zoom
and like the timings are a bit more difficult,
but there is definitely a sense where we very, really need to wait for Alice and to try them in.
And we might have to adjust our normal podcasting style.
Because it's like a panel format,
I'm very conscious of the people in the room who probably don't want to hear me interrupt you all the time.
Right, you do know they listen to Octa-Thorp.
There's a certain, there's a certain expectation of format, I think.
They may not all listen to Octa-Thorp.
I can't see.
Give me a show of hands.
Who doesn't listen to Octa-Thorp?
Okay, so did you hear that massive crash?
No.
Okay, fine. Somebody is in this room and I said to the somebody who was in this room,
if you stay in this room during Octa-Thorp, you have to be very, very quiet.
So they've just,
why exactly is Adrian Krikowski in your room, Alison?
It's got Adrian.
What's the name of this?
It's by sure it happens.
Who here does not listen to Octa-Thorp?
I'm so sorry.
This will make, I mean, this is, it's like, you know,
I came into Lois McMaster bejold books with Cryo-burn,
which was quite a way towards the end of the series.
You nearly did a swear word.
I nearly did a swear word.
Well, it was nominated for the Hugo's, where I read it.
And I was like, that was very good.
And then it says other loads of others.
But loads.
But yes, this is the 81st instalment of this hot mess.
And yeah, this is, I mean, it's probably a bit more organized
when you've heard the edited version.
I think it's not normally quite such a hot mess as it has been this time.
Yeah, I think that's part of the point.
I mean, we love tech.
Thank you very much.
Only 37 minutes.
Well, no, but we are very awkward.
They were like, oh, I'm pavilion pavilion,
sounds great.
But this is the room that this is a good room.
And I very much like the cabaret seating.
I very much like that tech, instead of doing their usual tech setup,
which works for the audio of every other item at the convention,
for us does like an eight track record and gives us like all the separate things,
which they could.
And I think it would be quite justified.
Tell us where to stick that and they don't.
And that's very nice.
I am on the committee.
So if we could have a round of applause for tech, that would be lovely.
It'd be great this weekend.
I mean, because I think the fanfons auction is also an incredibly difficult.
The fanfons auction worked really well.
So it was like there was a Zoom component and there was like an in-person component.
And I won a thing and I ate a marshmallow.
And I got sorts to tech.
So I've now learned the most.
So there's this series, one of the series that tech had coming into this convention is
that one of the reasons that people don't volunteer for tech is that they think that
the basic in-room tech job, where you do sound and picture and things is too hard.
And JT said to me last night, right, Alison, sit here.
You need to move this lever because Doug is a bit louder than John.
So you need to move this lever a little bit down every time John speaks.
And you need to leave a little bit back on.
I'm going to put it up every time John speaks a little bit back down every time Doug speaks.
Apart from the fact that I moved the wrong lever on multiple occasions and had to try to
guess where they were, that worked pretty well.
And then he said, so you see these two buttons.
This was a lot of Stream Deck.
Now, long time listeners of what's thought was that John had a Stream Deck.
Are you still?
See these two buttons.
If you press this one, which says Zoom on it, you will get the Zoom feed on the screen.
And if you press this one, which says PowerPoint on it,
you will get the catalog on the screen.
And you just keep switching between those two, when Zoom bid has bid.
And I just did that.
It's amazing.
And now I'm a tech gopher.
I'm so excited.
I've got quotes.
It was a lot of fun.
I'm going to do tech or JT in the future because I'll tell you it's a lot easier than being on the committee.
That make, yes, that makes sense.
But no, it was, it was very well, I think.
What was your, what was your favorite program item you went to this?
Oh, what is my favorite program item?
I think, and this surprised me actually, that my favorite program item was the 9am
panel item on, sorry, I'll sit close to the microphone, overshoot and the Anthropocene,
which was a panel sparked by an essay by Neil Harrison, guest friend at this convention,
writer of all these worlds, reviews and essays.
Sparking off an essay, he wrote about the concept of the overshoot novel and how this is
intertwined with more and more work dealing with climate change, the Anthropocene.
And he had a very, very intelligent panel of Abigail Nussbaum, Nick Cobble and Nina Allen to
discuss it.
Anyway, it was a brilliant panel because it basically took a very kind of, it wasn't
broad and let's discuss everything, it wasn't like let's discuss climate change fiction,
let's discuss all of this.
It was like very specifically, how does this particular kind of structure of novels and
other works have the effect that it does and how does this intertwine with the narratives of
place, the characters in the books.
Basically, it was just a really interesting like 75-minute deep academic discussion of
science fiction and I really enjoyed it.
I think there should be more panel items like that, but we might need to maybe clone some of the
panelists.
Fair enough.
Alison, did you get too much program?
No, I went to the fanfone's auction and one of the things about fanfone,
somebody has just said in chat, "If Alison does tech, it's like we will never see her again."
And I was like, "Oh, no, maybe because it didn't look like we had any auction,
beers for the fanfone's auction."
So, and we had done, but I was saying, "I'll auction," but they didn't look like I was doing
tech, so we put John into auction and I went back to do tech and then after about half an
hour, John was like, "You need to auction the next item after this so I can go and have a fee."
And so I had to get Mark Plummer in to do the second so that I could run to the front
and auction the item and then run back again.
So, no, I don't think he thought to be me if I was on the tab.
Yeah, I would be a very different type of tech, I think, so to say.
JT's like, "Oh, but I have 20 years of professional experience."
So, I'm like, "I don't have any of that stuff, but I have a lot of foots for."
I think my favourite item, can I pick when I was on?
Liz is making a face.
So, if it's not when I was on...
Was that an interjection from the room that I couldn't hear?
Could somebody repeat the joke for the benefit of the other member of the Oxford podcast?
It was not an interjection from the room, it was my face.
Yes.
Just imagine this is face and then imagine it's un-unapproving and directed at me,
which to be fair, shouldn't require much imagination.
No, it does not require a lot of imagination.
This being episode 81.
So, I think the one...
So, I really did enjoy the third row panel because we just made Neil very awkward and it was very funny.
But, I did also very much enjoy the Zencho interview, which was very, very interesting.
And I went to a reading.
I very rarely go to readings at East Collins, but I went to a reading which was also very lovely.
So, the programme's been very good, I think.
So, one of the things about being on the course is for an East Confit.
Is there anyone in the audience who's not been on the committee for East Conf?
Yes.
I can't see the audience.
Loads of people.
So, the thing about being on the committee is that you just really run around all of the time.
I was doing comms leave and I carefully organised my job so that every single bit of it could be done.
Virtually all I needed was my iPad and a beer and then I could just work wherever I happened to be.
And nevertheless, I was kind of working all of the time.
So, it was kind of...
I had brilliant, I should say, I had four areas ahead to my four areas.
They all did their jobs fantastically well.
And I didn't necessarily need to do all of that, but nevertheless,
you find yourself being very busy all the time.
So, I haven't really seen programme, but I was...
And then, by about lunchtime, I'll find out, something's saying,
"Oh, that looks really good, but I'll catch it on catch up."
I mean, this is one of these...
This is like your dog's guns, who have happy fears,
to play in happy fields, lie, comforting lies that we tell ourselves.
Because we've got catch up and I have a list of about 35 items I really
want to see on catch up.
I'm not sure what's going to happen, you know?
I might see what I'll do.
You're in the committee. Surely you're in charge of determining how long things stay on catch up?
I personally would...
Okay, so I think...
I'll be told we can now say till the end of the month, we think...
What was the case?
Yeah, no, I think...
Like I told me this morning, I think, that we can now say...
We can't...
There's a kind of not definitely about it, because there's a piece of work to be done
that may not be very easy to do immediately after the convention,
when you think about it.
They explained to me a couple of times,
"Intention is that you'll have until the end of April."
Okay, that's good.
I don't think that's like an official production yet.
So we've been saying all we can at least a few days.
But it doesn't matter, it doesn't...
I mean, they could have just on catch up till the end of time,
and I would never catch up everything, because you go away.
But I'm expecting to have a few days just like around lockdown,
but I'm not sure if you know something I might get to see,
or catch up with you.
Now, I want to watch the...
I want to watch the Andor panel.
I missed that, because I was at a conflicting item.
I want to watch the overshoot panel.
I want to watch Desot Island Books.
I want to watch...
I want to watch Carrie's session,
which I was conflicted with,
a convoy, because I did not spend Friday at the East Conquempo.
I missed all of Friday.
What were you doing, John?
I was at Star Wars Celebration, running around like a giant nerd.
And it was great.
And...
Were you wearing cosplay?
Have you got a picture of your cosplay for the chat?
Erm...
Yes, probably, somewhere.
I might do that in a minute when I'm not talking,
so that I can not try and do two things at once.
Because whenever I try and do two things at once on the podcast,
it goes back to me and then I edit it out.
But I can't edit it out when it's live.
Yeah, sometimes it'll be a pause.
It's just like,
"Oh, John's gone to look something up, hasn't he?"
Yep.
And he's not a multitasker.
Nope.
I'm a single track man.
You want some more, um, exclusives?
The first 10 items of the convention are now available on catch-up.
Yes, James Shields posted it in the...
I think he announced it in the chat for this podcast,
which is, I mean, it's very good.
Um...
JT, rather than James Shields.
I thought, oh, maybe.
Oh, I don't know.
Oh, no, maybe James.
Anyway, Ed and Bob confirmed for catch-up,
and we've got some items live on...
Yeah, so...
You will be...
I would say the program would be so amazing at this convention.
And the streaming speed is so amazing
that we normally act convention as you get
from endless complaints if the catch-up isn't available very quickly.
And for this convention, we have not had any.
And the reason for that is that the program is so good
that there's always something that people want to be watching right now
or scrolling back to see from the same day.
Nobody's like, oh, no, it's tragic that I can't see something yesterday.
Or if they are saying that, they are not saying that on Discord or social media.
And if they're not saying a top Discord or social media,
are they really saying it at all?
I was going to say we also had the BSA awards,
which I think we know, we noted when the nominations were announced.
Yes.
But the winners were on Ravela by Francis Harding for Best Book for Year and Agreeders.
I let the bowdard for Best Short Fiction.
Best Non-Fiction was Terry Pratchett, a life with Footnotes by Rob Wilkins.
Best Artist was Alissa Winans for Red Scholars Wake.
And Best Novel was City of Last Chances by Agent Tchaikovsky.
He was also a guest who wasn't at this convention.
So that Aishim was very, very nice,
him to win midway through the convention.
Yes.
And I now need to go and read City of Last Chances
being one of the Tchaikovsky novels of this year that I have not got to.
Have you read the other three?
Nope. I've read one.
Which one did you read?
The final architecture one, Ayes of the Void.
Okay.
And I got children memory on my To Be Read list,
but otherwise, like 10% of my reading could be fulfilled entirely through
Agent Tchaikovsky novels, and I feel there's like an upper limit.
And I'm probably not going to read the Warhammer one.
Sad.
The Warhammer Eurasia from me.
I've read half of City of Last Chances, which is very good.
I was last to interview Adrian.
Must have been two or three weeks ago.
And his quenix did typography.
And so I read as widely as I could in the time I had.
B.S. is very good.
I have not read any of the others.
I'm assuming that the Rob Wilkins will be on the Hugo Ballot.
So I do need to read that.
And I need to read all of them because they all look good.
They're all good award winners, Brent.
B.S.
Hara.
Congratulations to all the winners.
Yeah, and "Unraveler" by Francis Harding is very good as are basically all Francis Harding novels.
And at some point, you will discover what John and Alison thought of the Francis Harding novel.
I made them read for "Shattering".
And I assume that will also be on the load start ballot this year or close to?
Possibly, possibly.
B.S.
It arrived from the library on Thursday.
After I'd arrived at the convention, I got the thing saying, you have "Unraveler" is it?
On your Kindle to read, on your COVID read.
So I'm really looking forward to the day when I get to read books again.
Which might be quite soon because I'm planning to spend some time holding up not doing very much over the next few days.
No, that's actually not a bad shout.
And then there was an Easter combid session.
Yeah, I didn't go to that.
I sort of went to the end because I was on, there was something else.
There's a lot of clashes at this convention.
It's been slightly...
I mean, I think that is part of having 90 minutes lots is that you end up with slightly fewer slots
and slightly more clashes.
Yes.
But there have been quite a lot of times.
It's like, I want to do only three things in this slot.
And then the next slot, I don't necessarily want to go to any of them.
But I guess that's...
I think they get to eat.
Eating good.
But yes, the big session.
It was good.
Bellfast is going to be the site of the 2025 Eastercon.
The registrations are up.
I remember.
I did like the spoof.
I wasn't there for the spoof.
I heard.
OK, so there was a spoof bid from Catastrophe.
Space leopards will eat your face,
which I believe to have something to do with Funcon,
who I think I like to plug because I'm definitely going to Funcon.
And I want to say that it's like awful,
like a Shepherdsen Rotess or the stage in Illustra.
I'm not sure it is.
I think it might be somewhere else,
but I'm really looking forward to Funcon one next year.
And they did quite a funny bid where the premise of the bid
was that they would go to hold convention in Ikea.
And they were going to have a very large number of space leopards,
which will probably not eat your face.
And it was pretty funny.
And they did not win, but they came quite close.
Funcon isn't Buxton.
It is in the Palace Hotel Buxton,
which regular listeners will know is the site of Novocon.
And so that's actually basically like it even more
because I love the Palace Hotel Buxton
because it is one of these grand old hotels.
It is monumentally shabby,
but has a lot of sofas.
It is very much what I like in a hotel.
It would be nice if there was more than one train to Buxton.
There is more than one train to Buxton.
There's a train every couple of hours.
But there is only one of them.
It just goes backwards.
It goes back and forth between Buxton and Sheffield.
I'm pretty sure it's one track.
So I assume it does genuinely go backwards and forth.
Yeah, I think it's one of these trades
where the driver holds a key.
It has to hand it to the...
Yeah, it has to have a track.
But yes, no, should be good.
Have you bought your Bellfast membership, Alison and Liz?
So I have bought a Bellfast membership,
but I wish to be the non-fun one on the podcast and say,
I have almost no tolerance for spoofed bids.
Because unless they're incredibly funny
and take like two minutes,
most of the time I'm just like,
you are taking up time at the bid session,
which is generally pretty long.
And usually what I want to do is do the bid session
and go and watch some of the programme.
So I did not see the fun con one,
so it may have been absolutely great.
But really you should be like two minutes and then you're off.
They were a little bit longer than two minutes.
They could have typed the hub a little bit.
Pretty funny and have good presentation.
And it's good to have the questions
because it takes some of the attention off the questions
because you get to...
You'll ask the convention,
you'll ask a serious question to Bellfast
because then you'll ask a silly question.
And also, Toby and James did a bit of a bit
where they were kind of like,
"Oh yeah, we can't compete.
We're just going to give up.
Well done folks."
Well done, well done.
Oh, catastrophe.
I hope it's a great Easter time.
That's not pretty funny.
And they're guests.
They're going to have guests.
Oh, they're fantastic guests.
I'm going to get to start with the end first
because Ian McDonald,
who I've spent quite a lot of time with in the bar
with this weekend and also last weekend at Corflove,
Ian McDonald is their bar guest of all that.
Yes, so it's interesting.
It's amazing.
And this actually, I was going to leave this to last,
but he's the first person to be
an East Congestor one or three times.
Some people get very cross about repeat
because East Congestor's a runner.
But I think probably it was.
I'm still very excited because he was often in black
and he's so much fun in the bar.
No, I think, and I think,
I was talking to James Bacon and he very reasonably said
it would have been weird to have the Bellfast East Collin
not have him involved in some big way.
So that seems fair.
The other guests are Lauren Duker,
Sterek Landy, Jeanette Ng, Rebecca Rowanhorse,
and William Simpson, which is a very good slate.
I'm particularly excited about Rebecca Rowanhorse
because she wrote a Star Wars novel.
So that's pretty good.
And also other things that were nominated for awards and stuff,
but mostly Star Wars.
Yeah, but I mean, we've got the name Toastmaster
that the world cons use, that they could have actually used,
they could have found a way to say,
"Oh no, we're not giving ear the third bite of the cherry,
no matter how."
Because he actually has that combination of being
an incredibly brilliant writer
who is also hilariously fun, adding really nice guy.
And this is why people keep having him back.
You can't blame them, can you?
Oh no, I mean, yeah, I think that's fair.
I mean-
They could call him Toastmaster or something like that.
But I think that's why they say bar, guess what,
they understand-
If I have learned one thing reading,
the Discord reaction to the Discord channel
being called business meeting,
is that you absolutely cannot import terms from the world con
without anyone having an absolute shit fit.
So I think I need to do fundamentally disagree with you on that.
I need a sign that says this TVH.
Okay, so I have some-
So regular listeners will know this,
I've had a really hard couple of months,
and as a result of that,
there were a load of times over the last couple of months
that normally at this stage, at least,
because I was off the committee on it,
be kind of looking-
I know it wouldn't be my area,
but I'd kind of be getting my nose into different areas
of convention going,
do you really mean to be doing that?
And it's kind of just not like that time.
So I didn't get the chart,
I didn't notice that until people started saying,
why have you called this the business meeting?
It's the mid-session,
which we call it like 100% agree with.
It's absolutely the mid-session,
but we ended up changing it to mid-session and business meeting
so that people who thought it was called
the business meeting wouldn't be confused.
Yes, fair enough.
And you know, there's a lot of stuff that happens
that isn't bidding, for instance,
I don't think Belfast talked very much about hybrid,
sorry, I had the arts in question.
So you need to do it, right?
When you read comments off the Discord,
you need to make it clear that you're reading them
and then reacting to them,
because firstly, not everyone will be monitoring the Discord.
But secondly, some people,
and I know that this is not something we're used to
having only done 80 previous episodes,
will listen to this afterwards.
And so it's important that they have enough context
to understand what is happening,
which now we don't always have a great job.
So I have huge confidence about your ability to edit.
Every time I listen, because every,
okay, I'm going to do a bit of...
You can't butcher them up like that
to cover up your own mistakes.
John, John, can we have a bit of...
Can I tip that out?
You don't have a bit of behind the curtain music.
So I'm going to do a bit of behind the curtain stuff,
which is actually Sunday morning.
We get to like two hours after we start,
and I'm like, okay, well, we're stopping now.
And that's, we were completely incoherent
for the entire morning.
How on earth is John going to edit this?
And then every Tuesday night where we get the end,
I'm like, oh no, that's not supposed to happen.
- But that doesn't mean you do...
- You're too coherent.
- You can't, but it is nice if you don't deliberately
make it harder though.
- I'm not deliberately making part.
I'm tragically struck down with plague.
- Fair enough.
And the plague is called ADHD.
Bridget asked in the chat, did Belfast talk about their virtual
or hybrid plans.
I think they basically said it would be kind of something
they talked about more when they had a better idea of resources.
And they were very keen on people joining early.
So I think it might be a case that the earlier they know what they're...
Because there's never been an Eastcon in Belfast, right?
And so we have no real idea how big it will be.
It might be, it could be anywhere between 400 and like 1000.
And that's a very big range.
And so I would not be surprised if the reason that they've set their membership rate
sort of quite low initially is to try and work out what their numbers will actually be
so that they can actually plan.
So if you are planning to go and you have the means,
I know not everyone is lucky enough to be able to just immediately
spring 60 quid on a convention.
But if you are planning to go and you do find yourself in that situation,
then I would encourage you to join.
Because I do think, I mean, and we've discussed this previously,
but I do think it's important that Belfast be part of the Eastcon conversation
as, I mean, one of the four constituent blobs.
And I think they said their rates would go up end of May.
So join early, join often?
Join often.
So I haven't gotten fact joined to the convention yet,
because did I mention very, very busy and also play?
But I would have done, have they not said,
"Oh, we're not going to raise rates till the end of May."
So it will be something I do open next month of May,
because indeed it's important to join early.
I think one of the things we're going to see is that many of the virtual
members of this convention have come in in the last couple of weeks before the
call, which is kind of what we expected.
But we weren't sure whether it would happen because of the,
because this is a fairly expensive virtual convention.
It's not like a convention where we're like,
"Well, pay a five, pay a five, if you want to be okay."
Obviously all of the magic stuff that we've been doing on streaming,
and that's allowed me to be here, for example,
because, you know, for most Eastcon's for most time,
if I call COVID halfway through the convention,
I would not be the only further in further panels.
All of that stuff's quite expensive, but it's very exciting.
And I think there's a lot of will to do it,
but there's also this question about what is actually practical and sensible.
And we don't have to look at, you know, how,
how many virtual members we have and how many,
how many is actually spent time online,
and then that's information to go forward.
I believe the tech need for 2025 is JT.
I don't know if anyone in the room can confirm that.
JT, wave, if that's true, he's nodding sadly.
So, yes, I want to say two things,
which is firstly, Meg Mcdonald notes that Glasgow in 2024
has a rate rise at the start of May.
So join that first if you've not already,
because they also need to know how many people are having.
Yeah, I'm kind of an arbodillo member of 2024 or whatever it's called.
And also we have to have a live update,
which is we have now doubled our number of attending guests of honour,
as Neil Harrison has arrived from his previous panel owing to us over running.
And I don't know if we've mentioned it,
but you can buy his new book,
All These Worlds Reviews and Essays by Neil Harrison from all good book shops.
You know, I hate it when you're in a panel of all over the books.
Just go and re-enact him with 15 quid,
and I think he would be really happy not to take all these books home.
Yes. And also maybe you start chanting his name, but like quietly.
Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil, Neil.
He's hidden under a table, ladies and gentlemen.
We've done it, he's under the table.
Have we ever been under the table?
Because he doesn't drink, so this might be new.
I think many of us have, but yes.
So I can't help but notice it's a 1440 one,
which means we're 11 minutes past the end of our slot.
And while I don't mind, there are people in the audience
who have to go to the closing ceremony.
I would quite like to go to the closing ceremony.
So shall we do pics?
What, in like?
Yes.
In two minutes?
Go.
Go, Liz.
You can pick first.
You put me in a printable spot,
I assume that we were running solo.
We would not do pics.
All right, I think it's a film, it's called No Sebo.
It is, I believe, a joint production of the Irish and Philippine film industries.
It is a horror film starring Eva Green about a woman who,
she's a fashion designer, she gets some unpleasant news on a phone call.
And we see her being attacked by a mysterious dog.
And then we flash forward eight months when she's having many unexplained symptoms.
And a Filipino woman arrives at her home and says, yes, I am the helper
that you arrange to come and visit.
And then from then on, it's one of these films where it's like, okay, so how much of this is
actually supernatural?
How much of this is just kind of a woman who is ill and everything is being presented in the
worst possible light?
It is about colonialism, it is about capitalism.
I think it is quite an interesting little low budget film.
And it's worth going out and watching.
Liz.
Alison, have you read or experienced anything?
Yeah, no, my pick this week is plague because there's nothing like the notion that my favourite
weekend of the year is always going to come with ill that's immediately up with.
And I mean, to be fair, I've been coming to East Coast for this is my,
it's not quite my 40th Eastacom but I got into family in 1983.
So my first Eastacom was 1984, it's nearly 40 years.
And I have actually got away from Eastacom with some former villas on all those occasions.
It's just now we're paying attention.
So yes, I play.
It's given me a great chance to experience the Convention virtually,
which I have not really taken advantage of because I've been too busy running around doing
commission things.
I'm looking forward to the rest of the charts to read some books and play some video games
and watch the call on catch up.
Recommended 10 out of 10 with plague again.
Alison's opinions do not necessarily reflect the opinions of the wider old thought post-ship.
Yes, sir.
I am going to pick Adrian Tchaikovsky as a man.
So because I had to read an enormous amount of his book quite quickly.
I kind of read four of his novels back to back to back to back.
And the thing that made me realize is he firstly, he is very good,
which I did already know.
But the thing that really crystallized it in my head is reading four novels,
all of which are hugely different in tone, in ideas, in their approach.
Like the final architecture series is much more action driven.
And then you have like children of time and children of ruin,
which are much more kind of like cerebral, if you're like.
And then you have the Tyranid book he wrote for James Lottachop, which is amazing.
And just very, very good.
And then you have City Last Chances, which is also brilliant.
And it's just, yeah, it's really good.
And I'm not, he's just very, he's just very good.
This is incisive criticism in the "harrisonian mold."
I will say, Neil, just before we do wrap up, you weren't here for this.
But I did just, I went out the way, Alison Liz John Alison.
And I remarked to the audience that this is an example of an overshoot structure.
As proposed by you and your essay.
You'd go, "Hello, this is the Oxford on cast and I've Alison Scott.
I'm on Cox and I've been back here and I've Alison Scott."
I'll edit that in.
But for now, thank you very much to the audience for coming.
I'm sorry we started late.
Will we go to ask any audience questions?
We don't have time to ask any audience questions.
There has to be a closing ceremony.
They should have put them in the discord instead of chatting among themselves.
Yeah, audience.
How dare you have fun.
But yes, thank you so much.
You've got loads of questions in the discord.
Thank you so much to everyone for coming.
We really appreciate it.
It's all you lovely to see everyone.
And yes, thank you very much to my co-host Alison and Liz as well.
And thank you again to Tech, who are amazing.
That was the "Orr to Thor" podcast.
And I'm John Coxin.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
Oh, he has to be that.
He means goodbye to me.
That's my new podcast.
We've only done 81.
B.
We've only done 81 episodes.
It's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me and I'll have a bye.
[Music]
The theme music for this episode was "Fanfare for Space" by Kevin McLeod and
comprotect.com used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beat.
peep