How do I do the beginning of the podcast again?
It's written literally on the first line of the show notes.
Hello everyone and welcome to Octothorpe Live.
I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty. So first up who oh in this episode is episode
130 something 33 and it is coming to you on a day. Thursday? Thursday. Whatever Thursday was when
we were recording this. In three days I get to have to edit it yeah. Thursday the 24th of April
2025 and that will be our longest gap ever between episodes I think. What oh maybe not because we
don't know because we just skip on one. Right so firstly by show of hands actually know by
cheering who here listens to the Octothorpe podcast. Who here has never before listened to the
Octothorpe podcast? Two people. You only watch it live. That's I mean that is I did not know we
had Octothorpe hipsters in the audience. That is really immensely. Hello person welcome I'm John
this is Alison and this is Liz. Okay could the person who's working on the zoom for tech
please do the thing that stops the audio from cutting out whenever there's a loud noise.
Thank you. See I love you tech. Thank you Kat.
Yeah we're gonna have a big cheer for tech to check if it's working now so could you give a big cheer
for tech? Yay!
Sorted. All right um so Liz. Yes. How's your EasterCon bit? Pretty good.
Boy. And that was the Octothorpe podcast.
There are very good reasons why we do this podcast on the Monday of EasterCon usually which is we
get to do a nice recap of the weekend but it does mean we always do the podcast when we're all almost
dead. Yep. We were all sitting around at breakfast this morning going.
Which is fascinating radio. So yeah so there have been panels there have been things that we've done
there's been cosplay so yeah how people found the program should we start the program? Yeah
there's been a program. I think the highlight for me was the Hay Lecture which this year
was given so how many people saw the Hay Lecture?
So this year the Hay Lecture was given by Dr Liz Batty and so if you didn't see the Hay Lecture
you should watch Tom Kachup because it was fabulous and I thought I knew a lot of this stuff
already but in fact Liz taught me lots of things I did not already know and I really enjoyed it
so thank you very much her slides are a bit fuzzy. Next time you do this you could get me to
my slides and my laptop are perfect. That is always the way there are always technical hiccups.
You can tell people who are good at giving talks because they do not let the technical hiccups
jostle them. I also like very good. Alison's admission that I might know things that Alison doesn't know
but she could fix my slides.
[Laughter]
You might be able to fix your slides. I'm a fixer. You've got slides? I could fix them.
I do have tech whispering to some extent because I always cause a lot of trouble for the tech
every year. Hey we you know we're a team. We all... Yes I think somewhere in a
Mac-to-Windows transition some of my images went a bit fuzzy but you know that happens sometimes.
No and it was good it was really good. It might have been my favourite programme.
I think it's very good. I feel it's like if I had a fanning bingo card that would be like a big
box ticked off. Oh oh god you've given me aspirations. Because I've never given the BSFA lecture either.
If anyone from the BSFA is listening I believe that is what they call the hint.
I am not in fact an academic of any type and I missed the BSFA lecture was Fiona Moore who is
also a friend of the podcast I would say and I would definitely have gone to that. Unfortunately
it was opposite the bid session. Fiona I'm going to see that on catch up and I'm very much looking
forward to that. I mean I did go to that instead of the bid session because someone told me the
bid session was full and also you can pick up most of the bid session exciting info on Discord where
it's very hard to pick up an entire lecture on Discord so yeah the the BSFA lecture was great.
Made me think a lot both about diversity management and also made me want to reread Lord of the Rings.
Oh have you never read Lord of the Rings? I'm just going to read it and then she's going to read it.
I've also never given the re-slecture. If this episode is going to be a list of lectures you've
never given it's going to take a really long time. I have to give because we mentioned on a previous
podcast that I won an award in my day job and I have to give a lecture as a result and I...
Can we come? Can we come? I don't know. No you've got to wait a few years until John gives that as
the hey lecture. It'll be the Royal Astronomical Society right because I know where that is.
I mean it basically depends if you want to hang out with Dave Lally because Dave Lally will definitely
be there. It is Dave in the audience. No. Why is Dave Lally following you around academic lectures?
Because Dave Lally is an enthusiastic member of the Royal Astronomical Society he used to
organise the picnic. That is true. He was the person that basically made the society open up to
effectively affiliate members because he just nagged them until they caved which is you know if
you've met Dave Lally you'll understand. Right anyway yes. So Bridget has written in chat you
could institute the Octothorpe lecture. We could. What would I get? Probably not. On the subject of
the BSFA lecture clashing with the bid session do we want to talk about the upcoming Easter
com of which there are there is much news listeners so for people who weren't at the bid session
there were two Easter cons that were seated by the session and then there were two Easter cons
that were kind of announced for future years so we started to chronologically do the beginning
and then move towards the end. We should. All right Liz what do you think given you weren't there
let's get Liz's opinion first. I mean I like having Easter cons so I enjoy having
some Easter com bids. They both sound like good Easter cons. Yes so the 2026 Easter con is iridescent.
Its website is easter con 2026.org the guests of one are RJ Barker, Karen Lord, Emma Newman,
John Wilson and Serena Culfether and the philadel attending is 80 pounds the un waged is 50 and the
support is 40 pounds so yes and they're sharing their sight with an anime convention
which is new. We've not done that before to the best of my knowledge. So I think Phil said that
they'd got about 60% of the site and the anime convention had about 40% of the site there's an
enormous amount of conference space in the Hilton so I think that will probably be fine. Phil is in
the audience so they've just given us a big thumbs up. I mean we're not we're not about to say oh no
so it's going to be incredibly pokey and we'll all be on top of each other. I mean I think it will be
fine and we're looking forward to obviously I was involved in the team the rather rather last
Easter con on the site which was amazing obviously no pressure guys.
Also I like the NEC. I was trying to explain this to someone the other day where the NEC is
objectively not a beautiful place but I have so many good memories of the NEC. Every time I go I'm
like oh I love the NEC and it's just you know playing games getting very drunk eating lots of
nandos that's a good weekend. Is the is the anime con in the NEC or just in the other bits
or else it's a small one okay so there might also be something in the NEC of course because I mean
effectively last time we sort of shared a lot of like the hotel like spaces with people who were
at the con at the NEC anyway so they're all there at breakfast and occasionally in other bits so
I'd rather share it with the anime con and we shared it with a lot of coronavirus. Well we don't
know like yes but I mean we can't really say directionally who brought the coronavirus to who
Alison is that the one where we were worried you'd given me coronavirus and I would get stuck in
quarantine for two weeks. It's the one where we all shared the IPA by drinking it from straws
right next to each other's faces and then our single coat. Yes that was the one where I had to
pass the COVID test the next day otherwise I would get put into like 14 day quarantine. Yes
that was a good convention this would also probably be a good convention. I don't think it was I
think that was reclamation. Oh no I know the other he's so one where we shared where we
drank the same drink with a straw was Heathrow and the one where I was I'd already caught COVID
at the time we did Dr Thought. But it's worth noting that relatively we'll always be outnumbered
by coronavirus because they're really small so there are loads of them but there's only a thousand
of us how many how many coronaviruses are in the given person Liz? Millions. Yeah so they outnumber us
they're just gonna we need to really up our game. So my current practice is to get a private
vaccination two to three weeks before EasterCon and so far that's worked this time so I do know
so far that's worked this time. Oh I see what you mean it's worked that makes me a lot of sense
I'm relatively content with this model of it's very expensive oh and it's in the sewers yeah.
That was something that Liz said in her lecture for those who didn't go and are just like why did
Alison say it's in the sewers? I'm not saying I'm not up for a convention held entirely in the sewers
but I would want to do a good job on the big presentation. Have a great games room. Yes that
was a joke about turtles. Shall we go back to the EasterCon? What do we think of the guests of
honour? I'm excited. I haven't read any RJ Barker novels but I've met them and they're very nice.
I like Karen Lord books I've read some of Emma Newman's books and they were good. I haven't read
the newest one that's which is like a kind of slight departure into with more I think fantasy
pirates I've read science fiction ones so that's good and yeah John and Serena like it's great let's
honour fan it's nice that they both got a fan guest of honour honouring someone who does a lot of
work and gets recognised for it now so yeah. I've also read I read Emma Newman had a series that was
a finalist for best series in the Hugo Awards so I liked that. Right the discord is a
distractigast. The discord is doing what it does and I feel it's a good thing we don't have a
discord stream on most of our regular recording sessions. Yes. So if you're watching the audio
later and can't see the discord I'm very sorry. I mean you could always join the convention
in the future just to read the discord but that might not be an effective use of cash.
So did anyone join this convention just so they could read the comments on Oxford Live?
No probably not. Shall we move on? Can I talk about 2027? Yes you can talk about 2027.
The 2027 Eastcon is unconfined it will be in the Crown Plaza in Glasgow where we have held at least
two Eastcons. I think exactly two Eastcons before and they have both been great so I'm expecting
this one to also be great. I think maybe we also held two cons there but we'll forget that.
P.J.L.E. Clark, L.R. Lamb, Mark Meenan and Tamzin Muir is a Splendiferous Roster.
Right so P.J.L.E. Clark is a fabulous choice of guests and Tamzin Muir is a fabulous choice of
guests. I personally have never heard of L.R.L.E. Lamb have either of you two. I've heard of them
because you know they're an author and I'm pretty sure they have written a book that is in my house.
I have not yet read that book but I intend to read that book. I think there might have been,
I can't remember what the name of it is though but yes I'm familiar with them as a sort of concept
but I have not yet read their books but I will do in preparation for the Eastcon and I have never
read any books by Mark Meenan but I understand that is not his primary. I understand he's more
of a lemon curd person than a writing person. So Mark Meenan was working very hard on conventions
when I got into cons in 1984 and has continued to do so continuously ever since and I was very
pleased to see Serena and John's name come up and I was even more pleased to see absolutely brilliant
choices of fan guests which I actually know guys is something I care a lot about because I don't read
very many books. Somebody has said in the chat Rosanna again I've seen a lot of Americans saying
they'll come just for Tamsen Muhre and once they'll just get a passport from me. No so Tamsen Muhre I
think has not done any guest slots previously. I think this is the first convention she is a
guest at which makes this, I don't know if everyone is aware of how I think they are, they must
have worked very hard to make that happen but I think that will be, I mean Glasgow is a city where
you would get a big Eastcon anyway but I think Meenan would attract a lot of people so I think
that might be, I mean you might be looking back at the Ocons that had some guests that were also
very attractive and they were sort of hitting 1200 which is why the question in the mid-session
about capping was I think a good one because I, I mean I have already joined, I would recommend
join early join often but yes I think that might be a well attended Eastcon.
Yes there was a question in the bist session about what they would do if they filled up the
cramploss because cramploss has got a good amount of comfort space but it's not absolutely enormous
and they have told us that there is other conference accommodation in the near area that they might
be able to use. Well there's a big room in the, not the aloft, what's the one on the other side
of the river where they put the business meeting at Glasgow? The village. The village, yeah that's
got a big comfort swimming pool. That's relevant. There's also the directly connected conference
rooms in the SEC. Don't point out there's also the SEC, have we considered that? That's interesting
but I mean I have no knowledge of whether the SEC would just let you have a tiny bit of the SEC
with that gets very complicated. Yes I, I don't know and they haven't yet picked their venue liaisons
so I don't know how, I don't, because I think if they don't the chairs are going to end up doing
the work and I think that will be quite a lot of work even if you're working with the conference
bureau. But I mean you can see from this Eastcon which for those who are not here is using the
Hilton in Belfast but also part of the ICC in Belfast that they've got to have people doing kind of
the access controls into the ICC in multiple points even though we don't have the whole ICC
and so presumably that gets more complicated and more expensive and as soon as you start going
into SEC which has like six doors or whatever and bits of it are public and bits of it are private
that gets very complicated right? Just going in a hotel might be. Well also I've seen how hard
the being on the committee for this convention I've seen how hard Lisa Macklin who is doing the
venue job she's been working phenomenally hard and so I do think if you're going to involve a
conference enter you are going to need someone whose job it is to do that wrangling so so yeah
but you know I'm excited it will be good I mean Glasgow is great haggis pecora
I mean an absolute belter of a starter at any Indian restaurant. Can we get before 2027
a second Glasgow food joke? Well that's me told. Well somebody one of the things about this
convention is somebody has pointed out that one of the great things about this con has been
Belfast vibrant food culture. I like all food culture but yes Belfast has been very good too.
Belfast full of good food most of which does indeed come with chips there has been this whole
thread of I never expected this year to come with chips. I ordered a soup that came with chips the
other day. I tell a lie I did have chips but I went to a burger restaurant so you know.
Yeah Fran has pointed out on Discord that haggis pecora is not a joke which is true haggis pecora
really exists. It's deadly serious. Sorry everyone.
Yeah the other thing about having Tamsimua as a guest in 2027 means that presumably
she is planning to have written and published another book by 2027. You would hope. So it might
give you a guess about when like a Lecto of the Ninth is going to come out. I think if she hasn't
published another book by 2027 then you may have to have some like a swear box for things you're
not allowed to say at the con. I can't remember when a Lecto was originally slated for release but at
the moment it is TBC so yeah we'll see. But I am looking forward to it because I presume it will
make all of the rest of it make sense. I love the books. I'm fuzzy as to exactly what's happening
in the books but I do love the books. So you think that the next one will make it all make sense?
Oh yeah yeah it will tie everything together and everything will make perfect sense and there will
be no ambiguity at all. John you missed the panel that told you what was going on in the books because
that was the panel on sword lesbians. That's what the books are. Hey I'm going to get that on catch up.
Yeah that was the panel on sword lesbians about that. What? It was about sword lesbians and Gideon
is a sword lesbian right? Yeah so it came up. Yeah I understand. Yeah. Yep okay. Unless people want
to argue Gideon is not a sword lesbian I can see some funny. So no okay she's got a sword so
I'm given to understand that neither of those are sufficient they're both necessary but not
sufficient except for when they're not necessary either. I go into a philosophical debate about
this over dinner and I left more confused than I was when I started. And now I am more confused
than you were when you started. Good. I was when you started. Yep. So I was also very excited when I
saw the Eastercons for 2026 and 27 because they both have teams that include people who have not
previously worked on Eastercons and are kind of coming along to do it and I like that because
the more people wants to Eastercons the better as far as I'm concerned because I only did an
Eastercon last time because no no it's a time before last because nobody else wanted to so
the more Eastercons there are that somebody wants to do them the better as far as I'm concerned.
I really liked it. Talking about new people coming into running Eastercons Alan Stroud announced that
the BSFA are going to try and do a combined Eastercon Eurocon in 2028. I'm going to talk about that a
little bit. Liz what do you reckon? I wasn't in the bid session so I didn't actually hear much about
the 2028 bid but is it Alan Stroud bidding for 2028 or the BSFA as in the person by Alan Stroud?
Alan was the one who talked but he said it would be a BSFA convention. He said the BSFA is going to
bring forward a bid for Eastercon and Eurocon and I thought that was fascinating. I talked to somebody
at the bar who I'm not going to shout out here who's like we spent decades trying to extract the
Eastercon from the clutches of the BSFA and I was like no because it would only be one year it
wouldn't like be a big permanent thing. I feel like I'd like to see the BSFA run raise their website
came quite a lot before the bid and if they don't I think that's one of the things I'd be asking
in a bid session for example yeah you know I'd like to see some evidence that the BSFA can run the BSFA
before they try run the Eastercon. Lightly edited.
I mean I'll keep it in but uh please direct Alison Scott at her. Alison's Alison's opinions do
not necessarily reflect the opinions of her co-hosts. No I think it would be interesting so I have two
worries which is firstly I do think I guess my main worry is that I've never been to an Eastercon
that was also a year ago and I really like Eastercon and my main worry is that a year ago that isn't
Eastercon won't feel as much like an Eastercon and I will miss having an Eastercon.
I mean we don't there's no way to know right but but because Chamorocon was a year ago and that
felt like an Eastercon but it wasn't an Eastercon so I do appreciate it could go the other way but
yeah so so year of cons very quite very quite a lot but they're very a lot less than they used to
actually so Eurekos got a bit of a really solid vibe of its own that's quite different from the
Eastercon vibe so that is interesting. I myself have been to I mean not one that I've been for as it
happens. Eastercons so so I have been to an Eastercon it was also a year con and it was also my first
convention it was Ccon 84 and it was amazing so it was my first convention ever and I know that
there were it was in the Brighton Metro Pearl I know there were a huge number of things wrong with it
but I did not notice any of them because I was having an amazing time because it was my first
Eastercon ever and I did I tried to do everything I didn't quite you know I didn't give the hay lecture
but you know I did despite obviously not being on the program I find myself on the program a
couple of times and and I like filked and I drank quite a lot and I did stayed up far too late and
we were staying in a terrible terrible bed and breakfast and and I mean every it was the whole
of the Cambridge the Cambridge Science Fiction Society and essentially every flat surface in this
bed and breakfast had somebody sleeping on it and yeah it was it was amazing so yeah I think
so I guess my other worry not worry but I think the other thing is that because Alan specifically
named checked fantasy con when he was talking about running an Eastercon and obviously fantasy
con also has a slightly different complexion to an Eastercon and I am that is that is three
different approaches to convention running and it will be interesting to see how they blend and you
know I think that could be very good but I'm also perhaps a little bit more wary than I would
otherwise be if if it was coming from a group that had run Eastercons before as opposed to a
different group but we will see I am so yeah those are my kind of thoughts I guess as they are
but it is exciting to have kind of bid starting to rumble this far out because I can't remember
the last time we had an idea of what the three year hence bid might be like as a public out in
the open thing there's always gossip but like it's kind of nice to be able to talk about it out
in the open and and and yeah yeah I thought it was really good that they could adapt so that we could
put a good pontificate about it all the pod for yes I mean I'm I think the only era kind of been
to is the one in Dublin in 2014 which I did enjoy but I was also basically dead so I just ate a lot
of cookies um no a lot of cookies um I think there's a few things to be interesting like
at the moment I don't have a vision of what a convention organized by the BSAFA is differently
to a convention an Eastercon which is organized by people who happen to be part of the BSAFA
be interesting if that means they can like send to more BSAFA stuff maybe get kind of a bit of a
closer link more members involved in the BSAFA um if the BSAFA is a charity by then I don't
know if that makes any difference to whether a kind of a charity can actually sponsor running
the event and how that might make a difference to our finances and how things run and yeah I
just want to know kind of okay if you're a Eurocom what are the kind of obligatory Eurocom things you
have to do other than the awards and the bid session and I'm sure someone will tell me but
we'll tell you at length that's it very few you can do whatever you like okay from the audience
the BSAFA also as far as I can see is primarily an organization just catering for the needs of
science fiction authors and people who would like to be science fiction authors and Eastercon is a
fan-run convention which is primarily catering for the needs of science fiction fans and I want to
see what they would have to say about that I think yeah I hope the BSAFA caters too I think I've
made this argument before I comment from made it on the podcast but I think there are three kind of
sort of broad things in fandom there's the people who make the stuff the people who talk about the
stuff and the people who enjoy the stuff and by that I mean writers reviewers and fans and I think
the BSAFA in an ideal world represents all three constituencies but obviously the exact kind of
ratios is in flux as the makeup of the BSA is in flux and so I hope that any BSA convention or
an Eastercon would represent all of those groups but it will be interesting to see how that the
emphasis shifts but yeah I mean I'm actually quite excited about the BSAB because I think
if we kind of say things like it would be good if the BSAB did all of these things then they would
probably get on and do all of those things or try to do all of those things and I think it could be
absolutely amazing Malcolm points out that if you had given the Hay Lecture at Ccon that would
have been pretty amazing because they didn't start until about 2000. Yes that was a joke do you think
I should have actually said a thing saying this is a joke before I made the joke? I mean given that
the convention you talked about was when I was minus four and it started when I was 11 you might
find that some of us don't understand the historical context for the joke. I was telling the joke
for the audience many of whom were older than were plenty older than us would be there. Us poor
co-hosts don't get to the other joke. John that was your one and only allowed mention of how young you were
when the rest of us started going to East Cuns. There was a young one when I was first on the
East Con Committee. I think not many maybe less than that. When we did not have a slide deck because
slide decks had not been invented when I first bit the East Con but we did have a promotional
videography I didn't know you went that far. There was another um there was another bid that was
announced by Marcus Streets who I think had also been looking at 2028 and seemed a bit miffed.
So and then he was like I might have to postpone then to 2029 so we will see whether he comes
background to 2029 but I had heard rumours that he was planning but he actually stood up on stage
and said it so so yeah he is also thinking about bidding for an East Con. Does Marcus have a site
in mind? I don't know he just said he was thinking about bidding for an East Con but it's not clear
to me whether the BSFA has a site in mind I can't remember if they said. He was definitely thinking
about bidding for 2027 as well so he's been kind of slipping into the future. There's a song about
that. Yeah at some point you've got to bid and not just be saying your bid because if the problem
with someone saying they'll bid is at some point he needs to become a concrete bid or other people
who might want to bid for that year don't have time to get that together so you do kind of have to
at some point say you know concretely this is my year I am going for it and then we have like
the two years to get something else organised if you fail to get a site. Phil is waving his hand
at me. Hello Phil. Sue Dawson says in the chat that the BSFA site is indeed Birmingham. I assume
the Birmingham LEC is not not any other site in Birmingham yeah yeah how nice is it to be a
East Con in a city apropos of nothing where you actually walk out of the convention there's
restaurants and bars everywhere and other hotels and things like that. Yes it's lovely it is lovely
Belfast is very very nice so and I do also want to note there are rumours of a 2029 East Con which
is not the Marcus Streets East Con but that is not yet public and there's also rumours of a
of a 2030 East Con bid that might be sort of in the vicinity of the north so yes.
And I was trying to argue in the bar that 20 2030 should definitely be in London to be the
100th anniversary of the ill-third gathering of science fiction fans that was the beginning of
organised science fiction fandom. Well I've started talking to everyone about Newcastle so
and if you think Glasgow had a vibrant food culture you wait until you see a little delicacy called
Greggs. So there's a Greggs very close to our hotel as it happens here in Belfast.
All right are you saying Greggs is very outside Newcastle this is scandalous it will never it
will never stand um but yes but yes shall we talk a little bit about Belfast Liz I understand
you had a burger. I did have a burger. Good excellent. I'm trying to work out what John wants
to know about this burger. Tell us about the burger. So after some cocktails were partaken off
yesterday a few of us went in search of food and we went to one place around the corner
and they were full and we said oh do you where do you recommend and they named two places so
we went to one of those and they said oh we stopped serving food and we asked them okay well where do
you recommend and they said how about that burger place across the street is really good so we
went to the burger place across the street and it was really good. They serve burgers cheese burgers
and a variety of types of chips and that is it vegetarians do not go there. Yes the menu was on a
business card which I particularly like and we went to a place called Rattlebag for cocktail
and there were cocktails and my head is sore. Oh the burger place was called Bunsen sorry people
in the chat are asking Bunsen. We are somehow I think all staying in like the trendiest hotel in
Belfast which has a little hidden cocktail bar and a rooftop pizza place and yeah I mean we are not
all staying there but quite in I meant I meant the podcast not the whole room the three of us are
in a room together with beds in the shape of an octothorpe we have pillow fights every night it's
great. Have you been in my dreams again John? So I set up a group chat for the people who were staying
in the in the in the hotel and and this girl was like no you can't have a group chat with
more than 10 people it's got about 25 people on it so a lot of people are staying in that hotel
it does that. So and we we also went there's just Belfast is great like so so the you know there's
bread there's cocktails there's white pudding and black pudding and all sorts of things and it's
all amazing. Oh and I also want to say so you know how conference centres not world renowned for
their food and drink the ICC here the little bar that they've got which is firstly amazing because
right next to the art show in the fan tables and round the corner from the details of dealers room
there's loads of seating so it feels really good but the other thing is that that little bar
has cans of like local Belfast like pale ails and also does great sausage rolls so I am pleasantly
surprised by the ICC's food offering and you know the Hilton bar exists and you can play things from
it. The Food and Hilton bar is not bad actually I had lunch there yesterday. So I have not been
having lunch because I've been having breakfast in the hotel where it's like if you imagine one of
the best breakfast cafes you've ever been into and then an OHS who says oh you can order anything
you like if you want some extras that's fine too or some sides and then you can have as many flat
whites as you can drink which is not a thing that has ever happened to be before and would you like
some juice and pastries as well and so I have felt no need to have lunch on any day of this
convention which is great. When we were checking in I went and I bought a croffin and a coffee and
the guy was like if you're staying in the hotel it's free if you've got the breakfast package and I
was like haven't checked in yet so I think I probably need to pay you some money but there yeah it's
very very lovely and I think we locked it down. Well I think Claire Braley did an exhaustive search
of all the hotels in Belfast and told us which one to book in fact which is like looking out.
And one of the suggestions from the audience was to talk about our favorite cocktail so they made
me a put I don't know how to pronounce it poi poi tin. Pushing. Pushing sour. That's actually
lovely. Cheesy chips. I was gonna go I was gonna go it's not the cartoon cat.
But yeah Pushing sour. That's Pushing.
Lovely. Is that they sound sort of similar. They sound more similar than that poutine but yes
Liz what was your favorite cocktail? I had a gimlet and it was very nice. I also had a cosmo
I believe there is I mean they so they do cocktails with classic names but they're not exactly like
the classic cocktails. There is a photo of me holding my cosmo while I look very excited to have been
given a cocktail. Yes and there's also a photo of all our drinks where Liz looks deeply unimpressed.
Yeah because I came in late and so I didn't have a drink yet. So it was just like seven drinks and
is being like. But I did try all of them so. We went with Tammy Coxon and that was very fun
because for those who don't know Tammy is a expert in cocktails and the picture of Liz has been posted
into the discord chat. So Tammy does. No that's a different picture I hadn't seen that one.
So Tammy does excellent cocktail workshops and has done them for our little online convention
and she has been here and she does a podcast called Tiny Bottles and she came to me on Friday
and said do you happen to know anyone who habitually drank baby sham and I asked Farrah and I believe
that Farrah has tasted a historic baby sham with Tammy and I won't spoil the podcast but Farrah was
like I used to drink baby sham all the time. I am also going to be on a forthcoming episode of
Tammy's podcast and I made her drink a glitter bomb which I was very happy to be able to do.
Excellent. You've got to go and question from the audience do you want to explain what that is
and my answer is you've got to go and watch or listen to the podcast. I'm driving traffic
but yeah it was fun. It reminded me of my youth. We will put a link to Tammy's podcast in the
show notes. My favourite cocktail they there was a very good Negroni on the menu and later in the
weekend because I've been drinking this bar a lot apparently. I don't my memory is not entirely
clear but later in the weekend the chap whose bar it is was like but perhaps you would like a
left hand which is a Negroni except with bourbon instead of gin but actually the bourbon is
cacao infused and I said that does sound fabulous and that was I think my favourite of the
seven or eight cocktails I have added that bar. Yeah no it's um yeah in my head.
So we had all other audience suggestions. What's the best punctuation mark? The Octothorpe.
Yeah that's what I said. Yeah sorry. I do not have a favourite punctuation mark. Liz is well
adjusted everyone Liz remains the one adjusted member of the podcast. Now everyone in the bar
yesterday thought semicolon. I was going to say my actual favourite punctuation mark is indeed
the semicolon I am sorry. I like full stops. I like I yeah now a good dash a good dash. Oh you can't
mean it. And dash. John did you know that I don't know which dash should be used in which place and
so I just use them interchangeably. Liz I had a suspicion. I met Claire Brawley would not be happy
because I have to send Claire things to proofread and Claire has like a physical punctuation mark
which is like someone rolling their eyes and whenever I send Claire anything to proofread
that's the reaction I get even and I know it's there even if I even if I didn't see it. So someone
in the discord and entourage has written semicolon is what I want to be but dash is who I really am.
That's very good. So entourage we had an Octothorpe meetup I should say so there are
a couple people. I think everyone who came to the Octothorpe meetup. It was fun. I had fun. I
hope everyone else had fun. And we met some listeners we hadn't met before which was very nice
so that was good. Yeah. Two to be exact. Yeah two. Yeah. One of the results entourage was as well
I thought of it. Yes. Yeah. Yeah. So hello entourage. And emission was the other one. I don't know
as emission is he? Hello. Yes. And um. Yes. No emission. Yeah. And then I Alison and Liz both
asked for our thought ribbons and I refused to give them them. Yeah. Like where are your ribbons?
No. No. No. No. No. No. No. John. And I was like hmm. So John continued not giving me an octothoribbon
past the point where I stopped finding it funny and up to the point where I started finding it
pretty blood irritating. Yep. This reminds me so for listeners who remember the discussion of the
timing of the meetup where I pretended to think that you were talking about a 9am meetup both
Alison and Liz after I did that edit of the podcast send a message in Discord saying John did you
mean to take to keep the bit in where you're a dick? And I was like yes. Yes I did. Why break
the habit of a lifetime? Yes. Um. All right. Stewart asked us to do some serious talking about
con pricing. Yes. Well I asked a question in the bit session which was like I'm surprised by how
low the prices are for the two upcoming East cons. I want to say they are both higher than.
So the previous few East cons have started their pricing at 70 pounds. And these ones start at
1885 and that is encouraging because I do think it does need to go up a bit. But yeah I still
I guess I don't know. It surprises me that you can do it that low. But I mean maybe I'm just off base.
I don't know and I don't know when I don't know where the rate will go up to. But we've talked
about this one previous episode but yeah do I do you have any thoughts? Well these two conventions
are both based primarily around a hotel. If you base it around a conference centre then the
membership is going to have to pay for that. So that that in itself is I think this convention
is managing with its conference centre. I think because it has successfully
we've built a very large sum of money out of Belfast City Council. And in fact I would say one
of the things about this weekend is have you noticed how the entire city of Belfast is absolutely
delighted to have us here and really everywhere you go people are kind of talking about us and
the convention and being really positive about it. And yeah it's really nice. So and that's one
of the things that is clearly something that's a good thing for Belfast. Very excited to get
get us and that's nice. Mike Scott in the Discord points out the levitation started at 95.70.
Levitation is now LYA. If you look at the other three they were very very consistent price.
I thought you had an early bird rate that was lower than that. I don't think I paid now to five
pounds. I can't remember. I can't remember. But they might was on the committee so I guess
I can't remember which one was levitation the one in Telford. Ah okay. Yes yes. But yeah would you
come back to Belfast for an Easter come? Yes. Me too. Oh yes. I and also people have been kind of
saying the the site is very spread out but I didn't find it very hard far. I think because the
Hilton bar is bang in the middle. So you get to the ICC by walking out of the bar one way and you get
to the functional space here by walking out of the bar the other way. And because if ever I want to
get anywhere it needs to come I have to start by walking out of the bar. It just seemed fine.
It didn't seem unreasonable at all. So I didn't think it was a strong out spite. But it's clearly
if you're kind of at the far end of the Hilton functional space and you want to get to the far
end of the ICC it might be quite well. It's not. I mean I said to like Meg Meg writes in the discord.
Alison walked out of the bar. Okay walked is a strong word but yes.
But yeah so so the... Wasn't the bar with the cocktails. The thing is I think this conference
space. I'm pretty sure I've been to Birmingham conventions where the rooms were further apart
than they are here. Like I don't think it's that bad. Yeah there are some super distant rooms in
that Hilton right. I'm not sure if we've used them in the most recent cons but there are some
words like continue down the long corridor looking for the beware of the leopard sign kind of thing.
When I remembered do you remember the Ocons that the Radisson Edwardian that was that was a mate?
Yes because apparently I am the only person who feels that the Radisson Edwardian is a perfectly
sensibly laid out hotel and doesn't get lost. Liz is well adjusted.
But this is this spizz to be me versus like the entire fandom and Diana
when Jones has was being discussed on on Blue Sky earlier. I mean like yeah.
I think that hotel is pretty reasonably laid out too but I just pretend that I don't
so I can fit in with everyone else. Please like me please. I think part of the reason is that the
the hotel was totally differently configured the first time we used it from the second time we
used it and that makes a big difference. Maybe. So that normally if we go back to like even if
you go back after 20 or 30 years Easter got hotels and much much the same as they used to be
except with slightly cleaner wallpaper sometimes but not that one because of the pool that we
weren't supposed to take glasses into disappeared so we can no longer take glasses into it.
Okay so in 1996 when we're not going to make a joke about how old John was we went to the
Eastcon in the Radisited Waterian called Evolution. Oh and he threw. And he threw. Oh okay. Cool cool cool.
Yeah and we did not take glasses into the pool which is the source of that joke. I guess there
was like comfort space all around the pool in a way that was ideally suited to just like hanging
out with your drink if you'd been allowed to which we weren't. Have we covered everything that we
were told to talk about? I think so and it is half past which means we have the end of hour one.
Yeah. When are we doing pics? Yeah. Okay but we're going to take some audience questions.
Oh I wanted to call out Nicholas but it scrolled out. Nicholas told us about a punctuation mark.
So would you like to tell us about the punctuation mark from a roving mic or something and then
could you take the roving mic to other people Nicholas? Thank you. It's the on button for the
moment. So I don't mean Nicholas. I've been reading the moderator guides the chap in the middle of
the room with the pointy ears. I don't know how you turn it on. The person in the middle of the room
Thank you. Sorry. The parent is on I didn't.
Doesn't the moderator guide say or not supposed to comment on people's physical characteristics?
Sorry. The person in the middle of the room cosplaying somebody with pointy ears.
I think I'm cosplaying a Hugo administrator actually.
But I wanted to let everybody know about the Temerote slack which is used in the Ethiopian
languages Amharic, Gairs, Tigrine, maybe a couple of other ones as well. And it is used to indicate
irony or sarcasm. You can find it on your computer because it looks exactly the same as the inverted
exclamation mark which is used in Spanish for the start of sentences that end with exclamation marks
in other languages. Although then the problem is you have to find all the other Gairs alphabet
letters on your computer which will take a little bit more digging. But I think it's the single best
punctuation mark I've ever come across and I wanted to make sure that everybody else heard about it.
So thank you for calling me for that question. Yeah right.
I do now have a favourite punctuation mark.
Right so does anyone have a question? Put a hand up and we will deliver a microphone to you.
There must be some questions. Come on don't be shy. Oh there's a question person there wearing
gold. No sunglasses with grey. So this is one of the very deep important philosophical questions.
Tati Skones or potato bread which do you prefer?
Okay no less doss. I will have both please thank you.
Like quite like the wheat and bread actually. Yeah the Northern Irish wheat and bread is very good.
I didn't hear the question sorry can you repeat it for me? Do we like Tati Skones or potato bread?
I don't know. I'm not sure I've had either actually.
I've got to take Liz and get her to give her food.
So yes yesterday at dinner I had a starter which was different breads from Belfast and I had the
starter to myself and it was for 10 bits of bread and I was very happy because I love breading in
Ireland it is so good. Did you start to come with chips? No I had no chips yesterday.
What apart from the burgers? No I didn't have a burger. I had the burger yesterday.
Yes I had potatoes. I mean admittedly I had mashed and roast potatoes but that's just you know the
UK. Carbs on carbs with a carb for starter. This does seem to be in general quite a carb forward
food culture. What Britain yes I agree. No no but first comment is "fan you made when she moved
to the UK was you guys really like carbs" and I was like yes yes we do. You put a carb in the carb
and then you have it with a carb. Oh yeah no that's like a chip butty. Yeah yeah yeah. Any other
questions there was one. There's definitely Tony's got a question. He's going to ask us about chip
person over there with the blue tea. Call Tony. Is it tuned to ask your suggestions for candidates
for the next Pope? Yes but I understand Alison has never been Pope so
No um as I think we've previously suggested that Dave McCarty.
Oh right. So I'm not going to take a picture of Paddington as the Pope.
Is there like a Conclave RPG yet? And if not so I want to do one more next year.
And if there isn't well we'll do some Googling. There is a convention called Conclave but I
can't remember where or why but I know that in my head so it must be true right?
It's an American one I think. Yes yes probably statistically that's likely.
That has all the vertical. Well I mean there's a good idea but maybe not in Belfast.
I know I know I know I should probably wash my ears out but I heard that as Battercon.
I mean Battersea Power Station. Can you hold a con there?
Could we call the convention at Battersea Power Station convention in the station?
It's a snappy name but we could workshop it slightly more.
Bridget says can we buy memberships with papal?
And Conclave was in Michigan. I knew I'd do it excellent thank you very much.
Right and also so does anyone else have a question?
Any you can ask anything on your mind anything you've won that includes you discord you can
start with the poke puns and ask a question if you like.
Oh there's someone over there with a lovely blue cardie over a lighter blue t-shirt.
All right so question now what I think you've talked about about in general but
of items you were on for what has been your favourite that hasn't been mentioned.
Shall I start? Yes.
Because I accidentally forgot to fill in the programme form and so I then went oh I forgot
what to fill in the programme form. I should write to them and say it's a bit late but can I be
on the programme and then I went or alternatively I could not do that and it's really amazing.
So the only other item I was on apart from this one was the fan funz auction.
So hands up everyone who's in a cocktail bar during the fan funz auction.
Well done and but nevertheless we had yeah no you definitely I thought you were as well.
I can't. Yeah no I'm okay good.
Like my co but we raised a ton of money so thank you everyone who came along and bid
and what's amazing is that we raised it from one suitcase full of items so that that's so much
less work than normal I mean it was still quite a bit of work but thank you we raised
1100 pounds for the fan funds next year we're having a massive fan funz extravaganza
at iridescent so we will have a voice auction and a silent auction and some direct sales and
something that is like amaze balls or tambola or something so if you are coming to iridescents
bring us like just clear out your cupboards and we might throw some things away but we will also
sell a lot of things for the benefit of the fan fun so thank you very much everyone.
I missed the tambola so much that I was delighted to find that there was another tambola in the
dealers room that I could give my pound coins to.
This have you been on any other panels this weekend?
I've been on one panel this weekend John.
No was the other one where I was that next to you John?
Do you want to talk about that one Liz?
Yeah so we there was a panel on fandom politics and boycotts which you cannot watch because it was
neither streamed nor recorded. Was that deliberate? Yes.
Because we talked about like you know convention bids and mostly talking about world combids
and specifically you know the politics around them and whether we should boycott them whether
we should you know move bids in different countries what sort of standards should we have for bids?
And I think it went quite well but we were maybe a little limited in that we were all people
coming from a mostly you know from different European or American convention running traditions
and when you're discussing like where you should take convention bids from it's nice to have people
from other places that are considering doing that but with that limitation I think we made a good
job of it. Yeah I hope so. I mean we came up with clear answers to the question which can be
implemented easily and quickly. We did not that as a lie. We basically said it's really hard
but we went into more detail than that. I tried to get into that program item but it was very full.
It was full 15 minutes before it started which I is not often and I think I guess because it's not
because it wasn't streamed actually. I think people are using the not streamed not catch up
tags on Conchler and Discord quite heavily to work out what to prioritize so that probably helped a
lot. Yeah so I did try to go to that so one thing for future programmers if you're not if you've got
things that are not streamed and not recorded you might want to up the size of the room those
things are in and swap out some of the things are streamed and recorded into because of room
this size you know. We've got we've got about as many people as we always get for Octothorpe.
We have a very steady audience. Doug says Doug says from the audience is this being recorded? It is
probably. It always has two so you can either watch it on catch up when it's almost exactly the same as
it goes out live or you can wait for the podcast and then you can compare which things have disappeared
between the live show of the podcast. We have a question from Nicholas. I was going to give my
answer to the previous question. I was on a panel which was history in board games and I thought
that was very good. It had a excellent panel of Tim Kirk in more Russell Smith and Estema Count Stuart and it was I think it went really well. There was lots of very interesting chats.
We kind of discussed a very wide range of games. If you're into games history or both then it
I think is on catch up so yeah I liked that one. I went to a panel about 18th century witchcraft
in county Antrim and it turned into a ukulele workshop. So change is the only constant.
Are you going to give us a tune? My fingering is not very good Alison.
Wow I'm not sure I need to know that thank you Nicholas.
Have you considered octothor unplugged? Octothor unplugged. We
did do octothor unplugged at Novicon because there were no microphones and we basically recorded it
on an iPad and tried to speak very loudly. Unless you mean the sort of octothor after dark and we
did that to the bar all the time. Well we just we just gossip too much when we're recording.
There's too much that we cut out because we're not allowed to say it so we yeah I know it's tricky.
But I'm not allowed to say it. I mean John doesn't allow us to say it. That's not true.
There have been things I've said on the podcast that have been. But yes one day maybe.
I still got all of the audio is still on my Synology so when I die people can go back through
and like do all of the archival and stuff right. Don't get ideas. I mean I'll be dead first John
because you're so much younger than I am. Yeah. Name of the episode. Right. Any other questions or
should we move on to pics? I didn't know I was supposed to bring a pic. I know.
We've always wanted to bring a pic. There have been some interesting comments on Discord actually
pointing out that another issue with which items get streamed and which don't is you tend to have
the streaming gear in the bigger rooms because they're going to be more popular stuff for streaming.
And so that kind of affects that you know if you're then putting the on-stream things in the
bigger rooms where you've set up all the streaming tech then that's an issue. So you got a balance
at all. Yeah. Meg points out panelists sort of via the panelists says they don't want to be streamed.
That's another consideration. It is a program is a complex and interlocking thing which is tricky.
Pixar it didn't happen says "British Helpfully". I can't believe we've never made that joke in
133 episodes. No it's good. I love our listeners. Okay Liz you pick first.
Do you want a serious pic or shall I just pick a funny easter con? I will pick easter con karaoke.
Not solely responsible for why I am powered by cough syrup and strep seals this morning
but might be a little bit of it. Because it was that nice mix of karaoke so
tech said it all up so that you could just scan a little QR code and queue up songs on your phone.
So you can you know scroll through the catalogue at your leisure and also see how long the queue
is and when you're up which is pretty good. It had a very very wide range of things and people
sang a very very wide range of things and it was just like good nature and fun and I enjoyed the
slight battlement of different cultures coming together and seeing what other people consider
to be top-notch karaoke songs. Yeah no the karaoke was great that's a good pic. Alison what's your
pic? Well I picked the halexer right at the beginning so I'd have and then we've also talked quite a
lot about the cocktail bar that might also feel my pick and I think I might be running out of.
That's basically what I've done at breakfast. The steak? The steak was good but I mean I don't
really like picking a steakhouse because steaks are expensive and we're very very rarely steak.
It's extremely unusual for us. Steaks are expensive but the halexer requires you to come to easter con
and steaks are relatively inexpensive by comparison. Yeah if you so basically here's how it worked.
I was like we have saved 40 quid a night per room by staying in the other hotel so as we've taken
two rooms and it's five nights so that's 400 quid and as it happened the week a couple of days
before easter con we had an incredibly expensive meal. I was like that's great because that's covered
by the money we've saved on our easter con bill and then I was in the cocktail bar and I was like
well you know these cocktails are pretty expensive but it's been covered by the money we saved on
easter con bill and then we went to have to the steakhouse and the steak's for amazing
which I was like oh it's fine because it's covered by the money we've saved on the easter con
on the easter con hotel bill but in fact it turns out that if you count up the money we spent
at the fabulous restaurant and the money we spent at the steak restaurant and the money we spent
at the fish restaurant and the money we spent at the cocktail bar it is all taken together
quite a lot more than the amount we saved on the hotel room yes but it's always the way
my pick is going to be the last cocktail we got at the cocktail bar so we had we were with
Tammy Coxon who does a podcast we went to do earlier and she when she goes for cocktail bar she wants
to have every cocktail on the menu so she's like everyone must have a different cocktail and we must
each try all of us and so we did that and there were 16 cocktails maybe 12 cocktails but there were
eight of us so by the time we were ordering the second there must have been 12 cocktails because
when we were ordering the second round we ordered the other four off the menu and then we wanted
four that were not on the menu which they and we basically said it would surprise us and the bartender
gave us the most world weary eye roll I have ever seen it was great and said well give me a word
and we all gave him a word and then it was decided that we should have a cocktail for the table and
Meg gave him the word science fiction and he located in is it Diford's guide which is a big cocktail
guide he located the pan-galactic gargle blaster and he brought us a pan-galactic gargle blaster
which had cranberries and raspy puree and was a deep purple and if you go up in the chat that is
the drink that Liz is sipping in the photo that was posted and it was extremely delicious but he said
if you can guess this cocktail you get to be the first to try it and Tammy said is it a pan-galactic
gargle blaster and he said yes and then she went no but it was it was very delightful and someone
in the chat has said maybe we could you give them the word octothorp and see what they made so that
is quite tempting but yes it was it was very good and it was it was not much like a slice of lemon
wrapped around a large gold brick but it was very kind of give one last shout out actually
because I realized what I could have picked which is there are some puzzle boxes or there were some
puzzle boxes outside the fan tables and they come from like a escape room place in Belfast too obviously
hoping that we will stay long enough to go and do their escape rooms and then I had to inform them
nope I'm leaving on Tuesday but they brought two of their 30 puzzle boxes and they are
really good fun I think they're probably closed by now so you can't do them sorry but they were
really good fun I am going to get Stephen to stand up and model his t-shirt which he won by us doing
the puzzle boxes it is a place called prison island they have escape rooms and puzzle boxes
and yeah it was I we did we did the first one in no time flat and we were like feeling really
chuffed with ourselves and then we did the second one and we got stuck twice at once
because it's quite a hard puzzle and the other time because we were very incompetent
I remember because I was in the art show now I remember listening to you playing that little
piano for what seemed like hours well that's partly because we carried on playing the piano
for some time after we solved the puzzle as well but we did have to get a hint for the piano and then
and then I they've gone now so I can say there was a puzzle where you had to pull something out of
the side of the box and we had tried to pull it out of the side of the box earlier
failed and consumed it and concluded it was locked but he was like no it's just it's just
telling that with the we magnet you know it just so it doesn't fall out when we move it
it just comes out so yeah wasn't very clever all right so that was picks and I think that
probably means it's time to wrap up so is there anything we haven't covered I don't think so
audience it's just a shame we didn't have any tables for people to hide under this time
so thank you very much to cat who has been handling the tech for us and has been fantastic
wow how do I force your tech
thank you thank you very much to Nicholas for running the mic thank you to
Meg McDonald and the rest of the program team for putting us on program and giving us a
two-hour slot which is very lovely and thank you to everyone else on the Belfast
concom who have been great input on this wonderful convention and yeah thank you so much for coming
we'll be doing Octothorpe live we can say that can we I think we yeah we're planning to do Octothorpe live
at Nova cons with anyone that so if you're coming to Nova cons they'll be an Octothorpe live that
and maybe with a stunt list and so that was the Octothorpe podcast and it's goodbye for me
it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
[Applause]
[Music]
[Coughing]
You alright Liz? Yeah sure we have a little 10 second break otherwise we'll hear me coughing on
everyone's mic [Coughing]
If everyone wants to cough please cough now
thus ensuring that whole bit stays in the podcast
sorry we're good continue
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by Kevin McLeod in
comfatec.com used under a creative Collins attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep
beeeep
(indistinct chatter)