I mean I was I was being uh a little subtextual.
Metatextual dinosaurs, Liz.
That's a reference I don't get, which means it's probably not from the nineties.
It's from a podcast called Octothorpe.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 150th episode of Octothorpe, a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom.
which is hearing a meow on the radio and going back for the cat on the eighteenth of december twenty twenty five.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And we have
Some letters of comment in this, the last episode of 2025.
Yeah, we're taking a week off over Christmas.
Happy Christmas, listeners!
Or whatever holiday you celebrate.
Or if you don't celebrate a holiday at all, bar humbug.
For the sheep out there.
It's funny 'cause sheep go bar.
You know, we've done this for 150 episodes and yet I still am surprised sometimes.
Yay!
Good.
Alright, we have some letters of comment and the first one we're gonna read out is from Frederick Coulter.
uh who wrote to us to say if Denmark ever wins a WorldCon, the Hugo Base can be a pile of Lego and instructions.
This should make the shipping issue less of a problem.
Now this is a genuinely great idea.
Um if anyone from Lego is listening, uh I think at the time of writing the uh the the LA uh base design contest is still open, so there's still time.
No, no, no.
Um, if anyone from Denmark is listening, you know what you have to do.
I mean you you could do the entire WorldCom bit for a bit.
Of Lego.
Yes.
Frederick also says, in Seattle there was a booth for Czech science fiction that were making a noise about uh Czechia WorldCombid, um, and we're gonna talk about that a little bit later in the episode.
Nicholas White wrote to us and said, I definitely remember math mo as a word current in Cambridge when I was there, nineteen eighty-six to nineteen ninety-one.
So I was there from nineteen eighty-three to nineteen eighty-six, so ether
It appeared sometime just after that or I wasn't paying attention.
Um Answers on a postcard
So in in the show notes listeners, originally when I wrote this email, I put a sub bullet which was Was Alison just not paying attention?
And then I deleted it because I was like, That might be mean.
But I'm glad that Alison made the same joke.
Yeah, there we go.
And
And Nicholas also says, I am very happy to show you round my favorite drinking places in Brussels and Leuven in particular.
So um yeah, Nicholas, we might take you up on that.
Well, as as you know from the photo, I have in fact visited Nicholas uh inn Belgium.
Although due to my time constraints we did not have a beer.
We went to watch a charity fun run.
We also heard from Christopher Jay Garcia who has three thoughts.
Unsurprisingly, he has already seen The Blood of Heroes, which is the film from which Jugger the game is, and apparently there's a documentary called I Am Jugger.
um about it.
So well done Chris.
You are as usual like twenty-five years ahead of everyone else.
Um he says he is all for Nuremberg WorldCon, although he'll have to say he'll vote for Brisbane.
Unless Geelong is down on the footy ladder behind the bears come voting time.
I believe this is an Aussie rules football reference.
Um if we've got that wrong, Chris, please write in.
Yeah, he says The Truman Show is one of the saddest films ever made.
He also thinks Cypher made the right choice in The Matrix, so you know, judge Chris's Chris's thoughts
appropriately.
I mean yeah, I mean mmm I don't think you're supposed to think Cypher made the right choice of the Matrix, Chris, but I respect your attitude to art.
Which I describe as chaotic.
Which of Chris's attitudes would you not describe as chaotic?
Uh okay, no, yeah, that's uh that's a great question, Liz.
I have no good answer
I'm sure Chris does and he will write in.
We also heard from Rosanna Pendlebury, who would like to agree with John about recognition for primarily critical folks.
Um
And say that also conventions don't seem to put on that much content on critical topics.
Uh there yeah, I think I agree there is an occasional tendency to just have a panel which is like, let's talk about criticism and maybe we need to dig a little bit deeper.
But I think it is also sometimes hard to find the appropriate people to pot on them if they don't kind of explicitly say, I would like to talk about all these different criticism things.
So make sure you put that in your forms, people who are uh writing uh panel participant forms.
I think it's also because authors tend to definitely always fill them in with loads of stuff because it's, you know, the best way of promoting themselves and their work.
in a nice way at conventions and possibly all the criticism folks don't feel the need to do that.
I will also say I think different conventions are different on this
I think Neil and Nick did programme for ManCunicon in 2016 and I I imagine that program was chocker block with critical content.
Th is there a distinction between panels which are about thinking critically about things and panels about the art of criticism?
Yes.
That that that was the point I was going to make, that we actually have lots of stuff that's about thinking critically about the matter of science fiction and fantasy.
Also, Rosanna, we all check the emails, but I am one of the people who's checking them.
Ha ha ha ha ha.
Ha ha ha You're just not going to explain to listeners at all.
Fair enough.
No.
I respect that decision.
We also heard from Paul Wiemer, who also loves the Truman Show.
There's lots of love for the Truman show uh out there.
And yeah, I think everyone basically
It's really interesting because uh Paul has written to us about how hard the Truman Show hits because he just wants to have adventures and explore and is kind of, you know, thwarted at every turn.
And Chris wrote to us saying how like the Truman Show is one of the saddest
Saddest films ever made.
He is the center of the universe he lives in and convinced it to give it all up.
I think it's fascinating how like they have two slightly different takes on one good very good film, but it hits them both very hard.
So
Yep.
Thank you for writing.
We heard from Tammy Coxon, who enjoyed our SmothCon speculation episode.
She especially loved the bit where the th about all the things the Pog could go through between now and twenty thirty four, and she said, On with the fight, please.
Let's get that out of the way.
So we haven't had a big dust up for a while, have we, chaps?
Um no.
No, well although I I should say that that Alison was a little bit late today, thus increasing the likelihood that we will run over into my dinner hour and I will get cranky and that is probably how the fight starts.
Twenty-seven minutes late.
So sorry.
I missed multiple alarms and messages.
And then finally, Ivan Sinner wrote in uh with
Other thoughts on our giant bus stop?
He loves the idea in twenty thirty four of Okthorpe Live being like a Fleetwood Mac concert with each of us turning up with minders demanding separate green rooms and the show itself the perfect mix of funny and informative podcasting.
And simmering snide personal hatred.
So yeah.
You should see my rider.
Thanks for writing it, Ivan.
That made me chuckle.
That was letters of comment.
Thank you very much, everyone.
On previous episodes, we have covered Chris Barkley's quest to actually get an undamaged 2023 Hugo Award.
Which, as you recall, they were all presented at Chengdu, but then many of them were uh damaged in shipping and then not sent out by Dave, and then Chris tried to sue Dave in order to get
Here's Hugo.
And then basically it seems like the Chengdu WolCon's American arm took over and said, Yeah, we will sort this out.
And they have in fact now just sent Chris a trophy by UPS.
And there's a great picture of it on file seven seventy which we will link to.
It's got vibes of that picture of uh Timothy Dalton from Hot Fuzz, where he's standing next to a photo of himself.
And it's a picture of Chris with his intact go standing next to a photo of himself with his in-tactu go.
Uh, it's great.
Presumably not the same Hugo, which would make me a bit sad, but there we go.
Um Ooh, it's the ship of Theseus, isn't it
Mmm.
I think I'd rather have an I'd rather have an intact Hugo than the broken one.
The one that I held on stage was beautiful and then it broke, I think.
Also, do we know, like, if they all got shipped to a central point and then handed out?
I guess of Chris we do know because there's only one, but if you were a multi, a multi a multi
a person podcast collective and there were three identical Hugos, do you end up with the same Hugo?
Ooh.
I actually secretly switched your Hugos with each other under the table.
Every SmofCon there is a QA session, and various future bids for Smothcons and WorldCons stand up.
and give presentations and then people can ask questions.
And so the SmothCon next year will be SmothCon 43, which will be in Lisbon and is being run by Esther McCullum Stewart.
So keep an eye out for that, listeners.
And then the two seated worldcons uh stood up and gave presentations.
LA Con 5.
Which is going to be in Los Angeles next year.
And that was very competently done and flowed very well and didn't get very many questions.
Then Montreal in Canada.
uh who did rather less good uh job at presenting and had quite a lot more questions, I think it's fair to say
And we didn't really learn anything new.
They know they need a better website, but they haven't done one yet.
And they're gonna put they want to make everything very accessible, so they're gonna put PDFs on the internet.
So I had to put my hand up and be like, no, no, please do also accessible things, not just PDFs, thank you.
Uh, because I don't want Emily and Andrew to have to be the only ones that say that.
uh it's important that us youngsters uh club together to be grumpy.
But yeah, so they were mostly stuff that we had already heard and there wasn't much, I don't think, surprising in either presentation.
Do you have any questions about that, Alison and Liz?
I I I would what can we do to help Montreal get its act together without actually doing any work?
It is really tricky, isn't it?
I don't know.
How can we influence
Well I'm not I mean I'm not sure it can.
I think they've got the message that the thing they need to do is have a website, but short of someone volunteering to make the website and sort out whatever is are the other things blocking it, there's not really a lot we can do from afar.
I think we can do things like I think they put out a they put out some communication with prices this week that had um some issues in it and I think people did basically quickly point out
Or you probably want to fix that table, it's got some errors in or whatever.
And I think that's quite useful if you can kind of gently do it early on before it propagates.
But on the other hand
I un really there should be someone in the organization double and triple checking things like how much it costs to go to a convention is correct in your newsletters before you before you do it.
So
I I don't know.
That's fair.
I think the problem is that if you run your beard very badly, people won't want to volunteer for you.
And then you continue to run things very badly because people don't want to volunteer for you and it becomes a vicious cycle.
I think
is why bids need to hit the ground running.
And Montreal really didn't.
And I think they're really struggling with volunteer resource as a result.
But I don't know, I don't know, because I don't want to volunteer for them because I think it would be an enormously thankful thankless and
hard thing to do, which is also the conclusion that several other people have drawn.
Um so it's tricky.
Well I think you're I I mean I can say the solution there is at that point you need your
like division heads and deputy division heads to be out there being uh promotional for you.
Basically the way you get volunteers if people don't really want to be a volunteer is you have to go and personally get people to volunteer.
by telling them how they will have a good time working for your division doing this job.
And I think, you know, I am susceptible to that.
So there are conventions I have not volunteered for, except that someone came up to me and said, Oh, would you do this?
You'd be good at it.
It'd be fun.
I'll help you, I promise.
Um, and then I did.
And then resigned.
I forgot about that.
No, I was g I was thinking of different different situations where they in fact you know, I d I did volunteer and have a nice time and it was worthwhile even though it was at times annoying.
So yeah, you I think but I think that's the solution.
And then once you have a few enthusiastic volunteers, area heads in your department, it all trickles down.
But I think you've then got to start from the top and top and work downwards.
Yep.
Well they've got their area heads in although they've division heads in place now.
So I think that's the next stage is for those people to to mobilize their their um baronies.
Uh no, so we're not going to do a detailed accounting of Montreal's division heads, but what I will say is looking through the list, there are a couple of people I think are really good, but most of them seem to be
uh people that I would not want to work with if you paid me.
So I would rather you didn't say that on the podcast because I want them to get volunteers, John.
I mean, the thing is, Alison, I don't want our listeners to volunteer for them and then be like, Oh, that was shit, I'm never volunteering for WorldCon again.
So I do also think
We pro I want to be honest about that's the other thing, which is I think Liz is right.
I think you do need division heads who can um stem the rot.
And I think what Montreal have done is absolutely not put people in those positions that will actually achieve that.
Um and I don't know what to do about that either, other than vaguely complain about it on a podcast.
Alright, 2028 gave presentations.
These were presentations from Brisbane in Australia, Nuremberg in Germany, and Kigali in Rwanda.
I will say that we didn't learn much more about the Brisbane bid.
We learned quite a lot more about the Nuremberg bid, and I hung out with the Nuremberg chaps a lot.
So these are Florian Bailey and Ruben Wickenhauser.
They are a nice bunch of lads.
Ruben writes Perry Rodan novels, which I think is like the ultimate card-carrying credential in German SF fandom.
And um Florian is just a youngest chap who um seems very enthusiastic.
I'm gonna talk about Kigali separately.
I thought it was interesting the difference in approach from Brisbane and Australia.
Brisbane didn't send anyone to SmofCon.
Um and I think they did try and send one person but it fell through, um, but they didn't have a single representative at the convention, whereas Nuremberg, both of the bid
chairs were in attendance and obviously Stockholm is quite a lot closer to Germany.
Um but I also think so Nuremberg chaps were going around saying like we know we need to we we know we need to talk to people in the community, we know we need to volunteer for things.
Like, we know we need to be involved with the next WorldCons if people are going to take this seriously and we're aware of all of that and we want to work with all of you.
And then Brisbane got asked a question in the QA which was, are any of your bid committee volunteering for upcoming WorldCons to build
uh capacity and the answer was I don't know.
And the thing is that that is code for no they are not and you've asked this question before so I definitely know they're not but I don't want to actually admit it
And there's a real disconnect there where I think Brisbane thought they were gonna have this handed to them on a platter, and I think it really showed them up that Nuremberg were being much more
We had clearly realised they need to be much more plugged in, and Brisbane don't seem to have realised that.
And that is, I think, a problem for Brisbane.
Um Nuremberg came across, despite being a much newer bid, as being much more keen on actually working with the community, which is odd given where the two bids have come from.
You'd expect it to be the other way around, perhaps.
So Brisbane has had a number of sage advisors who have previously run Australian WorldCons and
some of those SAGE advisors have suggested that they may not be taking on board all the Sage advice that has been provided, or even any of it.
Yeah, I think I think that does come across.
And then there was Kigali.
Kigali did try and send someone to SmothCon, uh, which was Michael Kabunga.
Um Michael was denied a visa, I think, and so um
could not attend the convention.
They had to give their presentation virtually as a result.
And there were some technical issues, mostly because there was a very large lag on the call.
But there were also some dropouts which were a problem.
Um the convention looks interesting um and the site looks great and I would really love there to be a WorldCon in Africa.
And I feel sorry for them because unlike Brisbane who didn't send anyone but could have done and Nuremberg who did
Kigali tried to and were prevented, and that's a massive problem, right?
But after the WorldCon I heard that they were looking for people to be involved with a sort of sister organization who would be the global north.
part of their convention should they win the bid.
And I think what they probably actually need to do is do that in advance next time.
I don't think they're going to win in LA Con.
I'd be very surprised.
But if they're serious about wanting the WorldCon in Rwanda, I think they probably need a Western team who are able to go to conventions, represent the bid, take pre-supports, do all of that and not be solely reliant on dialing in through Zoom.
Um, because I think it really hurts them.
And I don't know how they build that network and that organization if they can't actually come to the conventions where they could make those links.
So it's really difficult.
And I just feel so
So I feel so sorry for them because like and even if they do bid, getting f money into Rwanda is extremely difficult.
So it's not even clear how they would take
money from people given restrictions on monetary transfers and things like that.
So it's hard.
Yeah.
I mean the Chengdu WorldCon had all of these problems and solved all of these problems because of course China has an enormous, enormous resources that
that I suspect the Kigali Bid doesn't have.
Well even then you say they solved all the problems, but they were not taking pre-supports they were not taking memberships at Tricon 8, because they hadn't solved these problems.
Yeah.
I don't know, they d they solved the problems eventually, but they did have these problems.
It's not unique to um Africa though I think
I think the internet connectivity is worse.
Um so uh I seem to have consistently
terrible terrible problems with like a Zoom call to Africa that we don't get.
You know, the the Chinese fans did a pretty good job of of being engaged in
in WorldCons virtually.
Given that the Chinese WorldCon with local government support couldn't solve this problem easily, I think a Kigali bid might really, really struggle without having Western partners in advance.
And so I think
the advice I'd give to them is you need to recruit a Western team stat sort of two years before the bid, the vote.
'Cause otherwise it won't work, I don't think.
Which is sad but I think true.
Yeah, so that's I mean basically
Having just said, you know, Montreal, you need to get your division heads out there doing outreach.
One of the things that it is a thing I don't particularly
Oh, I don't know how we change it, but I'm not sure it is a great thing.
But basically a good showing at SmothCom's, which is really a gathering of like a hundred and fifty people.
Which is a very small number of the people who might eventually go to a WorldCon is usually like a key thing to actually getting your con be voted in and successful.
And I think we're really seeing what the issues can be because Brisbane have the issue of they don't seem particularly plugged in but they also have enormous distance.
Kigali have the problem of they can't physically get to where the Smofcons are, and I suspect they're bid
had to spend a lot of money on non-refundable travel arrangements in order to even try for a visa, which is then denied.
They end up losing a load of money doing that.
And then, you know, the internet is probably not gonna be as good in most bits of Africa.
I'm sure the conference center likely has pretty good internet.
I would not be surprised by that, but they may have been relying on
unreliable broadband or variable quality phone internet and it's just really harsh because if the answer is how do you currently get a WorldCom bid is basically
you have to set up a satellite organization who can get visas, who can take money on your behalf, who can go and out and be your ambassadors.
I think you're right in that that would probably be the way to do it, but it's just really a really sad situation.
Because then we have the situation where the bidders for Nuremberg who sound lovely and are doing absolutely the right thing by popping up and saying, Yep, we're here, we want to learn, we're keen, we're enthusiastic, but they just have such a big advantage over the others.
in terms of like finance and distance, um they do.
That I think they might win.
Yeah, I think it's worth noting that I'm less
I feel less sorry for Brisbane because the other thing is that Brisbane I think has ignored a lot of advice from people who have given them good advice.
Um, but Kigali I I don't know.
You're right, right?
It shouldn't be incumbent on African WorldCon to basically have a second American organization that can m let them win
Because that's the thing, like I have a friend who works in the university sector and they had someone who's doing genocide research in Rwanda and it was funded, but you can't send money to Rwanda.
You just can't.
There are there are global
impediments to doing that in the fabric of how we do banking.
So what they were doing is they were coating themselves in money before getting on the plane.
And when the university found out about that they were like, Absolutely fucking not, this is a risk assessment nightmare and now they have to Western Union
Not Western Union.
They they use couriers to take the money into Rwanda to deposit it with the person and the amount of money they spend on that significantly reduces the amount of funding.
And so it's like, well and that's not fair.
If that w research was happening in, I don't know, France, it you wouldn't have that.
And I don't
That's a problem, right?
Because we're limited in what we can solve and these impediments are global geopolitics which are UN level and we can't we don't have any power over that at all.
So it's like what do we do?
The only thing we can do is work with the system as it exists, but it's it is really sad that the system as it exists is so stacked against an African world combat.
Yeah, and there's such a big barrier, like, you know, if Brisbane come to someone in Europe and say, Hey, we can't make it to Smofcon, can you be our ambassador?
We'll send you all the information, that's totally different than
Someone saying, hey, we can't, you know, we can't take any money into Rwanda.
Can you be our financial agent is a whole extra like level of responsibility that's gonna be hard to hard to find
I don't know whether we really have um have gathered the information on on best practice on visa acquisition because it doesn't seem to me to be
impossible to get these visas and I'm slightly surprised that they keep getting turned down.
I mean I know I know it can be difficult.
I
think based on, you know, anecdotal and experience from people I work with that you are uh vastly overestimating
the ease of getting visas.
I've been to I've been to scientific conferences with like high level people there and there are people presenting on video who said, Yeah, I got refused a visa by this EU country to come and present at this large global international conference.
Many, many of them.
It's just like uh you don't know and it could be any one thing.
Once you've got one, I think it becomes easier to get the next one and the next one and it's snowballs.
But it is, I think, very, very difficult.
I I suppose also if you've got a team in Rwanda or
They're not actually in Rwanda, but if you have a team bidding for Kigali of Africans, then perhaps we need to be they need to be planning on three or four of them applying for visas in the hopes that one of them will get one.
Yeah, but then that's four flights, four sets of hotel bookings, etc.
Yeah.
Scandalous.
No, I mean that's uh yeah.
No, it is.
Uh just just fills me with impotent rage, really.
Okay, change the law.
It's outrageous.
Oh my god.
So yeah, so the 2029 and 2030 um presentations were also relatively unremarkable.
Both bids look extremely capable.
I don't think there was a lot of extra information in there that we didn't really know.
They both seem to be pretty plugged into the community.
Both of them had representatives in the room.
Um and yeah, they seem to be doing well.
Um and I don't really have much to report.
And for those for those who don't know those 2029 and 2030 bits.
And then I think we get into the interesting bit.
Do either of you have anything on Dublin or Edmonton?
Looking forward to both those conventions.
Sounds good.
Um so 2031, Sarah Felix stood up and said that she supposed she was the bid chair for the Texas uh bid in 2031.
I think there is an open question here, which is you might not want to be putting a lot of effort into a US WorldCom bid until after the presidential election in 2028.
So I think I'm gonna wait till
uh that happens before I see whether that bid explodes into life or um quietly um fades away.
But there wasn't a lot of
Detail and then twenty twenty twenty thirty-two Nantes in France stood up and declared their intentions
And I've linked in the show notes listeners to Nantes Utopials.
Apologies to France if I'm pronouncing it wrong.
And that is a big kind of science fiction festival which is held
In Nantes.
And yeah, they had a video.
It was very shiny.
They were like, we want you to come to France.
And I thought very hard, I'd love to come to France, but I have been burnt before.
Um and for listeners who don't know, there have been a lot of French WorldCon bids that have kind of announced for eight years in advance and then
sort of quietly died away.
And so I'd love this one to be the one where there's actually a world con in France.
Oh, this is different though.
Yes, it's not Nice.
Two and a half thousand guest authors.
Yes, it's giant.
So this is a big, this is a giant festival.
WorldCon would be as a tiny pimple on its side.
Yeah, so is it is it a commitment to having a thing separ a WorldCon separate to the Utopials from the same team, or just some other people in Nantes who would like to run a WorldCon?
I think it's definitely one of those, Liz.
It's unclear to me exactly what I I think they're bidding for a WorldCom.
They're not bidding to make this festival into a WorldCom.
Um but I think they're showing that like they have the genre links.
But I confess the
There weren't any slides there was just a video about this festival and all of their promo stuff.
I mean, I they gave me a baseball
hat because I sang them the alphabet in in French at the international party.
And so but that has nonce uto utopials on it.
Um so I think I I think it's fair to say that at the moment they're quite heavily leaning on this branding.
But I didn't get the impression that the idea was to make this event a worldcon.
But I might I might have been wrong and I'd be I'd I'd be interested to see more concrete details in the future.
This is
twenty thirty two and if we're quick we can get our fight and our breakup and our makeup and our next hundred and fifty episodes in before that, can't we?
So they've got a while.
Yeah, but I think I think it is crucial to know because Utopiales I have seen lots of authors saying they're going to Utopiales and they had a great time, but I think it is a big thing with like a big city promotional effort.
And it looks to me like I suspect it's like a professionally run thing and there is a professionally run organization behind it.
So I think it's important to know whether it's those people who wish to use some of their professional expertise to run what I think would be a, you know, great WorldCon.
Or is it some people who are also from Nantes and then want to put something else on that might be then competing with the same people?
For locals?
I think I can say I'm pretty sure that w at least one of the people on the stage was involved with this festival.
Uh the other person on the stage was Anouk Arnal, who is a French fan that I've seen at WorldCons and stuff before.
So I think there is like a there is a traditional fanish component to the people who want this to happen.
And I think there might also be some involvement from the from the festival um people as well who would quite like WorldCon to happen in not.
So like I think it
I think it might be kind of a a hybridization of different influences coming together, if that makes sense.
They did get asked whether the festival was professional.
And they gave like the most wiggly answer, which w which but we basically boiled down to, yes it is, but we also use volunteers.
And it's like, okay.
Well, I think we've discussed before that if you there is a situation where you have some people paid to put it on.
I'll work full time on it, etc.
And then some volunteers who fill in the gaps and we've discussed, you know, the pros and cons of that.
But yeah.
It's twenty I mean it's twenty thirty-two.
You can like we'll come back to this in ten years' time.
Not quite ten years down, but you know what I mean.
Five years.
There was no interest expressed for twenty thirty-three, so that's still wide open.
And then twenty twenty th twenty thirty-four
Meg McDonald stood up and told us about the Glasgow 2034 WorldCom bid, which we talked about quite a lot last episode.
I don't think there's much new here.
They've got a couple of dates booked for the SEC and still think a 2034 Glass Region WorldCon would be great and think Meg would be great at running it.
So no notes.
Oh, uh Meg wants everyone to write a postcard um and give it to her so that they can be let like messages to your future self that you can read at the convention.
Oh, that's quite fun.
Because the theme of the convention is planting seeds for the future and like building a future that you might not be around to participate in, but trying to build that future anyway.
Um and it's in the vision statement on the SmothCon QA page.
Um but it's it's quite beautiful.
I think it's quite a beautiful, quite a coherent vision.
Of of like what they're trying to achieve, which is neat.
It is, although you've just made me think, right, how many of those people who write a postcard to their future self are gonna be dead by twenty thirty-four?
Liz!
Sorry, it's the way you phrased it, John.
Liz.
Uh, okay.
Any questions on Meg?
I think we approve.
Good.
And then more excitement.
Uh so twenty thirty-five, Poland stood up and basically said
We're not a hundred percent sure, but we kind of want to do it.
And if we do do it, it'll be that year because it's a centenary of Polish fandom.
So yeah.
Like we're looking at it and we're thinking about it and we're turning it around in our heads.
And Polish fandom are incredible, so if they do decide to do it, I suspect it will go well.
And then Checkia stood up a couple who uh involved with the Festival Fantasy, which is a Prague-based comic-con.
have said that they would quite like to uh run a WorldCon.
And I say this is a Comic Con, but like I saw some of the con publications and it looks quite comfortably in our
Put it this way, I recognise a panel when I see one and they have a lot of panels.
Um and um and yeah
So I think I think that would be really good.
They had um little armbands and I got a lanyard and it was neat.
And they also had rum and the rum was very good.
But yeah, no, so that would be exciting.
So I think they're thinking of Prague.
I did also talk to at least one other Czech fan.
Who thinks they should have it in Berno?
So I don't know.
I've put um I I'm not sure whether they're far enough along to have a a defined venue.
Um, but I'd be all over a Czech WorldCon.
I think that would be great.
Prague Prague is lovely.
I've never been to Brno.
Um, I'm sure it's also great.
I am sensing a theme in the people who were standing up for future years.
Yes, I would uh describe them as European.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah, so it's interesting, right?
Because if Brisbane if Nuremberg won in twenty eight
That would mean 28, 29, 32, 34, 35, and a s unspecified unknown future year might all be European world cons.
And that is quite a reversal from historical trends.
I don't know whether an Antipodean bid might come up for twenty thirty-three if Brisbane doesn't win in twenty eight, 'cause that would be five years later, and that is possibly enough time to
sort of reload and go again.
Or twenty thirty-one to be fair, depending on on whether Texas decides to move into high gear or decides to
decides not to do that.
The real question is you need to have it's not enough to have one WorldCon in Germany, right?
Or one WorldCon in France.
What you ideally need is you need France or Germany to run want to run a WorldCon every decade.
But you need like um you need people who want to do this
decadally to maintain you can't rely on a completely new group of people doing every single world coin.
It does not that will not work.
And so
Ireland and the UK have ended up like doing decade apart world cons, and that seems to be continuing.
Um, but I'll be very curious to know whether
France, Poland, Czechia or Germany can end up in that situation as well, or whether it'll be like Finland, where they're like, that was very fun, but we're not going to do it again.
Because it would be great to have a situation in which fifty percent of world cons were European, but it it does require those countries to keep on bidding decade or decade.
Yeah, and I think it's an interesting question about whether
the fact that, you know, Australia was twenty tw two thousand five and then there was New Zealand in twenty twenty, which I think mostly due to the pandemic and not their own
uh fault has kind of burned quite a few of those people out.
But basically has it been too long since there was one in Australia?
And now all the people that you might previously have tapped to like help are twenty years older than they were and don't want to particularly
get involved at a high level might make your life more difficult.
And so I think you're right in that, you know, trying to do it every ten years, then you'll have some junior people who step up, some people who are still there from the last one, et cetera, et cetera.
enough kind of institutional knowledge to keep you ticking along.
Yeah, y there's a reason why y if you look at the conventions, it tends to be about a decade between cons.
Like it's not always you know, sometimes it's nine, sometimes it's eleven.
Um but if you have a break of much longer than that, I do think you risk starting to lose some of that some of that momentum.
But I think the other thing you do, and this is something that came this is an opinion I have that came from Tammy in the bar at Smothcom.
is one of the things that European Worldcons do well or or perhaps do better than North American World Cons is that the teams running divisions in European World Cons tend to be bigger.
So you have like at least one division head and at least one deputy division head.
And the deputy division head will often be younger, uh, or newer.
Uh and so you have this thing where you're building capacity every time you run a WorldCon, whereas in the States or well, sorry
In North America, if you have one person running a division, you're not building any capacity.
And if you have one person running a division and you only hold them every 20 years, you're definitely not building capacity.
So that that's the other thing that's happening, like Luncom three built a lot of capacity and the people who came in in Luncom ended up running Glasgow.
And then Glasgow will have built capacity that Glasgow thirty-four will use and so on.
And so I think we need to think more and I think North
North American cons are doing this badly, and that comes back to the thing we mentioned about Montreal right at the start.
Like you look at that DH list, and there are very few DDHs and co-DHs mentioned, and that means that
those people are not building capacity and are not looking futureward, and that's a problem.
And I think that's why European fandom seems to have a lot of youngsters or newer people who are keen to run worldcons, and North American fandom seems to be
aging out of common running in a way that Europe isn't.
So yeah, or burning out might be a better way of putting it.
I do think I do think Trump has all made it a lot harder for America though.
Oh yeah.
So so that deep-seated lack of enthusiasm to go to America.
That's true, but even before Trump, like
It's notable because I don't think if Trump had been elect if Trump hadn't been elected, I don't think there would be US bids.
There'd still only be one US bid, right?
There might be ones for like the mid to late thirties.
God, it's weird to say the thirties.
But like I don't know I still think there are fewer US bids than you'd expect, even with that.
Yeah, and also Montreal, you would you might think that there would be some people who would quite like to run one in North America but don't want to do it in the US who would be um on that.
I mean I think uh the to the D D H thing, I mean they could still be recruiting them, but I think one nice thing London had is that it had a lot of those deputy division heads in place really early on and then you actually get to kind of shape everything.
You don't feel like you've come in halfway through the process and everything is already set and all you can really do is like run someone else's plan.
LunCon 3 was a very good convention in lots of ways and one of the ways is it bred a generation of European conrunners.
Don't make me look at the Luncon list of division heads and figure out how many never ran a division again.
Well, I mean I I kind of did.
Death three of us.
I I because I was a D D H at Luncon and it kind of
convinced me I was never gonna do a job that big on a work on ever again as long as I lived.
So, you know, sorry guys.
Well it's good to know
You're always the thing is that literally everyone on any WorldCon committee will eventually stop running Worldcons.
The the key is to make as many of them want to run at least one more before they stop.
I I I'm happy to do things at WorldCons and do smaller jobs at World Cons.
It was just that the way that I personally
reacted to being a D D H wasn't necessarily mentally the best way to go about it, as a result of which I
I spent four months literally waking up in the morning and doing nothing but work on things until I went to bed and and that's not good.
Speaking of SmothCon, John went SmothCon.
I did go to SmothCon.
I'd like to thank Glasgow 2024 for a bursary that enabled me to attend.
Thank you very much to those lovely people over there.
It was in a place called Stockholm, which is in a country called Sweden.
It was chaired by Carolina Gomez Lagoloff.
and uh very capable committee of Swedish folk.
Any gossip, gossip from SmofCon.
Gossip that you can tell everyone and then some gossip you can't.
Gossip or interesting thoughts, John.
Either one.
I very much enjoyed Smothcom.
It was a very good group of people.
who I enjoyed spending time with.
The meetings I had were great.
It really made me enthusiastic about come running and want to get more involved and that was very good.
And the programming was very good.
I will say there were two things I noticed, maybe three things.
which I thought were less good.
And basically I think it's there were there were a lot of technical issues.
Like and so sort of
There were there were no roving mics, so if you have hearing problems, the convention just did not care about you, I think.
Like moderators were generally repeating
questions, but that is error prone and hard and puts a lot of pressure on the moderator.
And I don't think having a roving mic in this day and age, like you do do do that.
And I think part of that is also that I think this convention should be modelling best practice and I don't and so I think it sends a real message
If the convention doesn't prioritize that about what the convention thinks about access, and it's very difficult to see panel items about access at a convention that has decided to sacrifice access.
at it sort of in its own case.
It's like, well, okay, but eh.
There was no green room and the programme was left very late.
And like, I mean listeners last episode heard me find out I was on a panel live on the podcast because I checked.
And if I had not have checked, like I would not have known because there was no email.
And I think in general, panel items were interesting topics where the moderator and panelists did not seem to have really prepped in advance.
I think that is partly because the convention did not
aid you in doing that in any way.
But I think that's very distressing because like I am privileged in this situation that I got a bursary to attend
But like if Michael had managed to come from Rwanda and managed to do the visa and managed to spend the thousands of pounds to be there like
We should be trying better to give him like a good time when he's there, like give him a productive time.
And like it felt really privileged in a way I can't quite put my finger on that like
people didn't that the convention didn't take itself more seriously.
It felt like a convention where it's like, well we all know you're just here to chat to the people that are here.
So we don't need to put as much effort into the convention side.
And I'm like, but there are people for whom this is their entry.
And I think taking that attitude
is really problematic and privileged in regards to newer people in the community.
And that disappointed me really a lot
And and yeah, those are my two big points.
But I had a great time!
It's amazing how how much you enjoy a convention is not necessarily connected with how well run it is.
But I the reason I had a great time is because I was there with loads of people I knew already.
And if you don't know people, how good you find the convention is directly correlated to how good how well we're on the convention is, and that's the thing.
Oh yeah.
Oh yes.
The people who are less privileged and less connected are gonna have the worst end of this stick.
So it made me angrier.
Oh I was so cross at points.
I was so cross.
You'll just have to run a Smofcon, John.
I mean, I'm on the committee for the Lisbon one.
Oh, okay.
I'm doing their Discord.
So there will be a Discord and it will be good.
Good.
Yeah, because I I feel I really want the virtual parts of SmothCon to be excellent.
If we're trying to foster and grow a global community of conrunners, yeah.
They obviously aren't gonna be able to go to Stockholm or Lisbon or Seattle or wherever the next one is gonna be every year.
You know, and we can't say yes, there are some people who do, but we can't say that that's the only way you get to be involved in this conversation about conrunning.
Yeah, I think that was what I was saying.
Like at the moment it feels like success at bidding for a whirl con is not completely but quite coupled into uh coming to SmofCons.
And if we can't decouple that then we
have to make sure the people who come to SmopCons are getting a good opportunity by putting their time and effort into coming.
It's the same in academic conferences, right?
Like, if you want to build collaborations, academic conferences are where you go to do that largely.
And so, like, I don't think this is unique to SmothCon per se, but I do think the more we can do to help
People attend and come from outside the traditional com running community, the more inclusive we are as a community.
As someone who is currently recording the 150th episode of a podcast, which is
primarily inspired by a desire to bring people in.
It distresses me when other people don't put the same effort I put into trying to include people.
And maybe that's just holding everyone else to a very, very high standard, but I hold myself to that standard, so I'm not being a hypocrite at least.
And we will hold the twenty twenty six SMOFCON to that standard.
Yeah.
But Esther will probably meet that standard, so that's good.
Yeah, but the self-fulfilling thing, right?
Like you probably wouldn't have signed up to be on the committee for the next MofCon if you didn't think the Next Mofcon was capable of doing a good job.
So Yes.
See everything else we've been talking about this episode.
Round and round we go, yeah.
I think when I first got into fandom there was an exp there was a belief that if you wanted to run a WorldCon
you needed to be to have the wherewithal, i.
e.
the money, to travel around the world bidding that it wasn't just you need to go to Smofcon, but you need to be seen at multiple
international conventions.
And obviously you could do that with having a big team who will run tables for you.
But I still think it's not just Smofcon.
I think you do have to be at other international conventions to to progress your bid.
Um, I don't think
I I think that's probably got slightly better over the years, but I don't think it's yeah, you know, I don't think it's gone away at all.
I don't th so I SmofCon is at least putting a focus on the place that you have to be
I think when I think this is the thing so people talk about academic conferences and they're like we need to expand virtual participation.
And they're not wrong.
But the other thing is that like as someone who's done virtual particip participation at both academic conferences and science fiction conventions
I think it is still, despite all of the work we have put into making it as good as we can, it is still harder to network virtually than it is in person.
And so the other thing is that like I think this is actually a phenomenally difficult problem to solve.
And the way you do that is to try and do bursaries and to try and invite people.
But I think you do also need to try and do the virtual participation for the people who can't attend physically.
like the Kigali people where there is international geopolitical reasons where they can't and so we need to make sure there are avenues for them even if those avenues are
not perfect.
They need to be as good as they can be.
Yeah, what will be interesting to me is the first time we kind of have a WorldCon bid which
basically does things in a totally different way and it's a success nonetheless and that will be a really interesting model.
Alright.
So that's my SmophCon gossip.
Oh and also the hotel did breakfast, very good breakfast, the creps were amazing, but also did fika and dinner.
Oh
Mm-hmm.
And given it was a hundred pounds a night for a room, that was quite good.
Cause it meant you didn't have to pay Sweden prices for dinner if you didn't want to.
You could just eat in the hotel for free.
It's quite nice.
Yeah, so I got to have Fika with friend of the podcast Anna and I got to have a cardam bun and it was a big bun and it was it was very lovely.
There was also infinite free coffee, which was great.
Um I think that's everything I had on SmothCon.
Oh I met a man called Tim.
Tim's great.
If you're listening, Tim.
Hello.
Is Tim a listener?
Or did you just convert him on the spot?
I think Tim's already a listener.
Uh Tim listener Tim is also working with us for gaming on LA Con 5.
And he has ideas about scavenger hunts that link virtual and physical uh participants uh in sort of ways where you have to work together in order to do the scavenger hunt.
And I'm excited.
Ooh, that sounds very exciting.
Yeah, he also runs board game conventions and video game conventions like in his spare time, so um he's a he's a triple threat.
Yeah.
Should we do picks?
Picks.
I'm not gonna pick Tim, but I was tempted.
I think that that's a lot of lot of expectation to put on one person's shoulders, Sean.
Uh who wants to pick first?
So I picked a book, John picked a book.
So shall we do books a book sandwich of Alison's book?
Alison's also picked a book, right?
A booklet, yes, sort of book.
A a waffer thin book.
Oh, it was kind of ordinary sized for reasons that will become apparent.
In that case, yes, Liz, you go first.
Uh I am gonna pick a book.
The book I have picked is The Buffalo Hunter Hunter by Stephen Graham Jones.
It is
A historical Western vampire novel.
I mean, yeah, it's defin it's definitely a horror novel, so I think it might have been off the radar of some of our listeners, but it should be on their radar, I think.
Um it's essentially it's
follows it's one of these novels where there's like uh a framing story within a framing story and then so there's the framing story on the outside which is an academic from 2012
uh who is looking at the rediscovery of her great-great-grandfather's journals.
That great-great-grandfather was a pastor in Montana, and his journals basically contain the oral retelling of the story of
Uh a Blackfoot named Goodstab, who as we as we get through the story, um i he's never named as a vampire, but bec he becomes a vampire essentially, and this is all tied up with the kind of
uh historical massacre of the Blackfoot Nation and kind of the the cultural position of Goodstab versus the the Western uh colonizers of the the West in the
late 1800s, the extinction of the buffaloes.
And yeah, it's really I've I really enjoyed it.
It's got kind of three distinct narratives that have very different voices, which I really enjoyed.
And it's clear that like the native voice here, there are like interesting stuff around the word choices and what word choices he uses when he's retelling his history.
versus when he is talking to the pastor in the framing story and it just does a really nice job of then tying up all these three individuals and you you kind of figure out what is going on.
I really enjoyed it and I think it is definitely worth a read.
It is quite gory and it's definitely a horror novel, so that might put some of you off.
But if you're happy with kind of a lot of blood and gore and revenge, then it's definitely worth reading.
Nice.
I like vampires.
It makes me think like a bit of it, it makes you think, you know, it makes you it does have a reference, like it's got a reference to Dracula in there.
It knows it's kind of doing the the Dracula like
uh uh novel through letters and it also kind of has resonance with like interview with a vampire which I confess I never finished but does have the framing story of like
you know, he is doing an interview with a literal vampire.
So it definitely kind of knows the tradition it comes from.
Yeah, but I really uh yeah, I just really liked it.
But yes, there is a bit of like
I don't think it's like gratuitous.
It's just kind of a fact of Goodstab's story is how much kind of blood and gore it involves in the nature of how he is a vampire.
Ah
So when I said I liked vampires, I did once read a story on Uncanny that made me pass out because it had too much blood drinking in.
So like on a scale of one to ten, how drum friendly is this book?
Mmm.
Like a zero.
I'm gonna I'm gonna claim I'm gonna claim a trigger exception to my um still theoretically occurring, but perhaps not as
uh successful as I would like Project to read all of you guys' pics.
'Cause I don't want to pass out.
Yeah, I think uh I'm scared to even like tell you what happens in it in case it makes you pass out.
I mean I've
The thing is it's I can watch things with gore much more easily than I can read about them.
Yeah, it's also like Goodstab narrative is his very like, you know, he's it's an oral history, it's all first person, so it's all about him personally, like
Feeding on blood.
So that might be quite tricky for you, John.
Alright, this might be just a book for me and for the listeners.
Enjoy it, listeners.
Tell me if it's good.
Alright.
Alison's picking a booklet.
Sort of, yes.
My pick is The Lost Nose by John Sladek.
The text of which appears in his collection maps of the uncollected works of John the previously uncollected works of John Sladek.
Um this was a book that John made for his then girlfriend, later wife, Pamela.
Sometimes towards the end of the nineteen sixties and it's it's handmade, it's con it consists of like paper collages
bits and pieces of things that are stuck in.
Um it's the most it's about thirty pages long, but they're quite f
thick, so when you actually pick it up it's quite a thick book.
I believe it is now in the Science Fiction Foundation.
But at some point it came to me because I had the cunning plan to
create an internet version of this.
This I feel like about the time of Jeff Ryman's two five three.
Um
So early, early internet times and I scanned the entire thing.
I don't think my scanner was quite as good as the scanner I have now.
Um, but I have scans and they're not terrible.
And nothing ever came of it because, you know, projects.
And now on a Discord somewhere we occasionally play through game books and we're playing through this one at the moment so that I can
And I've kind of gone back to all the scans and processed them so that they're now individual sections of the book.
And after that I might go back to um
the Sladok estate and the places that have this book and say, Maybe might we put this on the internet somewhere because the tools to do this now
this thing that was would have been an enormous amount of work when I first had the idea and so I didn't do it.
You know, there are now websites that allow you to create interactive stories in this app but just by kind of clicking and dragging.
Um so
We'll see.
Um many people have said, Oh, what we need to do is do a facsimile edition and and make money at it, but I'm not sure if it would ever make any money.
It's very strange.
Fred has lost his nose.
And it's a game book.
It's actually in the great internet archive of game books, which I didn't know existed, but was very pleased to discover.
Um so if you're on said Discord, you know, you can come and play it with us.
And if you're not, um, then watch this space.
So is is the copy you had and scanned literally the only copy in existence?
There is only one.
It was a present.
It's it's it's a handmade book that he made as a Christmas present for his girlfriend
That's pretty cool.
You know, it's extremely cool.
Uh and it is I mean I I I ha I haven't looked very, very closely.
There may be a point where I'm gonna have to put a trigger warning on it saying
You know, this was made in the late nineteen sixties and they did things differently then.
Um, but I don't think I haven't sp seen anything like that yet, so um fingers crossed it'll be all right.
So very exciting.
That sounds interesting.
I'm looking forward to playing through it.
And it is it it's not i it's not
great science fiction or anything or even a great gay book, but it's just very funny in places.
So there we go.
Um and I've linked to that book uh in the show notes.
It's on it's on Blackwells, so like it's not
Not too tricky to get top your No no no that's the that's the version that's the chat book produced by Big Engine that doesn't have any pictures in it.
Oh.
So it's got the s it's it's got the text, but no art.
Because the art
Because theoretically there was always going to be some sort of facsimile.
I see, okay.
I am also gonna pick a book.
I am gonna pick a book called Your Wish Is My Command by Dina Mohammed.
Uh this was a finalist for the Hugo Award in Glasgow.
Um so this is a book which is about wishes.
And it's a graphic novel set in a alternate Cairo.
It's a world where wishes exist and there are first class wishes and second-class wishes and third class wishes.
And a third class wish is more likely to go wrong.
So like you wish for something and the wish is creatively interpreted and you get something that is not at all what you wanted.
But first class wishes will give you exactly what you wish for when you wish for it.
And they are so much more terrifying because they will give you what you've asked for regardless of whether or not you've thought through any of the implications of your wish.
And it follows the three first class wishes that a street vendor has to sell.
And it's and it follows three people, each of whom come into contact with one of these.
Um, wishes.
And yeah, it's beautifully illustrated.
It talks about various aspects of identity.
The
The character I resonated with most is the character who's struggling with anxiety and mental health for obvious reasons.
And I thought that arc of the book, which is the second act basically, um, was incredibly beautiful.
And it's just it's just awesome.
And I originally borrowed it from Neil and Nick, but I now have my own copy.
And that means that next time I see Liz, I can force Liz to read it.
I'm in agreement with the plan, I should say.
John is not allowed to just force me to randomly read books.
Oh yeah, no, because if I was, you'd be reading the entire Star Wars expanded universe, Liz.
You too will know who Corin Horn is and why.
I feel I have learnt everything I ever needed to know about Corin Horn.
But Liz, he's the Galaxy's best fighter pilot, detective, Jedi, and lover.
This is still like Garth Rekki's Dark Place.
It is it is a lot like that, except it's played entirely straight
Um, so sort of.
Um, but yeah, so it's it's just really good.
I would highly recommend.
I mean, I suspect several readers will have read it when it was um a Hugo finalist, although I will say
The version in the Voter Pack, I believe, I'm remembering correctly, ha was like a PDF with massive watermarks on it.
So I just found it completely unreasonable readable.
Um but like yeah, if you can get your hands on a proper copy, um then I highly recommend.
It's really good.
Oh that would that would explain why I haven't read it then.
No, it does annoy me when they do that, 'cause I'm like, it's just I know you don't want people to pirate it, but if people really want to pirate it, they'll pirate it anyway and uh
Alison made a noise while I was talking about it and I couldn't tell whether that was because she had Googled it and thought it looked cool or something else.
No, I I had
Gone down a rabbit hole.
So sorry John, I zoned out.
I am a terrible human being.
That's right.
And that was the Alt Thought Podcast.
And it's goodbye for me.
It's goodbye from me.
Was it also very cold?
No.
It was t-shirt weather mostly.
Oh.
Sort of hovering around nine degrees.
See, I was thinking, wow, that sounds really hot for Sweden in December and then John has uh recalibrated it to t shirt weather that uh you know, of a man who lives in the north of England.
I was gonna say nine degrees is not t-shirt weather, nine degrees is fleece weather.
No.
I would not put my big coat on, but it is definitely not t-shirt weather.
It was it wasn't shorts weather, I'll grant you that.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod in Compatech.
com used under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.
0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.