Please note, we have recused ourselves from consideration for the 2025 Hugo's In the
Category of Best Fancast.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 129th episode of Octothorpe, a podcast for
Science Fiction and Science Fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 27th of February 2025.
I'm John Coxon, I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty and we have some letters of comment.
They're not very many. We heard from DC on Blue Sky, some comments on the follow-up to our
follow-up. DC says that Prisma Dec or Blind Chance, the Polish sliding-doors version film we talked
about the other week, is available on DVD and Blu-ray. So that's our jungle watch it but
apparently you should on no account read the back of the box on account of it having a big
spoiler on the back. Yeah there's a film that's been in the cinemas recently that I didn't
quite manage to see where there was a spoiler on the, a massive spoiler for the big reveal on the
poster. It's, it's 24 quid. There are so many movies that I don't have to spend 24 quid to watch.
Well this is just a sign of the fact that we've all basically become accustomed to having lots and
lots of stuff on streaming, more stuff they can ever possibly watch except it means that classics
of Polish cinema are now only available if you buy the Blu-ray for 24 quid, which is a kind of
sad indictment of streaming media. What I would say DC is you should arrange a screening of this
at a convention. Oh we used to do that. Yeah. DC also mentions that the day our last episode was
released, Agent Tchaikovsky was on a UK political podcast called The Bunker discussing whether
politicians should read science fiction and it's apparently it's a 13th February episode. Have I
listened to this yet? I have not. Do I think politicians should read science fiction?
Mean if they fancy? That. Yeah. DC also calls us due to typo "octothorope", which I also quite like.
Fair enough. And finally DC asks why on Octop 128 John felt he maybe shouldn't pick a book?
So I don't know if I said, I don't know exactly what I said, but I can't pick a book because I've
been reading for the Clark and I can't pick any of the books I'm reading for the Clark.
Here's why. I'd also now Liz and I can't pick anything that is eligible for the Hugo
so anything from last year and all of the books I'm reading are books from last year
and I can't talk about them for two reasons. It's only going to be a few months though.
Yeah, then I'll be able to pick things again. And meanwhile I can pick books from last year.
So because I am not I'm not reading for the Clark or in the I am in the Hugo team but not in this
bit of it. I have no knowledge of the nominations. We also heard from Farah Mendelsohn who says
"thank you for picking up that the word written is in the definition of the non-fiction
categories" that is a mistake and they are going to get it sorted for us. Thank you for
Farah. I say for us for truth and justice and the BSFA way. But yes. So the reason we were confused
was it was a confusion and it's not just because we weren't paying attention properly, which is good.
Not always the case. Thank you very much Farah.
Doug Faunt wrote to us a subject dear to my heart and said "some media just flaked,
not all real stand up to time. I discarded some real to real tapes because there was a lot of
brown dust in the boxes. All tapes should be archived to other media. That is completely true.
But also tapes are plastics and plastics have a tendency to collapse over time
for certain plastics. Somebody said to Vraupton tells which things collapse and which things
don't. He gave away his media just recorder in the player when they were still popular."
Thank you very much for writing in Doug.
Do we want to recreate Chris Garcia's recreation of him and Bella and JP listening to
Altsop?
Yes. Who wants to play Bella? Who wants to play Chris and who wants to play JP? I will play Chris.
I will play Bella.
That means Alison's JP.
Yeah. Okay. Do you want to introduce it, John?
So we heard from Christopher J. Garcia who wrote in with a dramatic, well,
wrote in for a script for a dramatic presentation of Bella JP and Chris Garcia listening to Oct
thought waiting for school to open. Oh, key dokey. So I think Bella starts and ends the scene.
This chai is still too hot. Blow on it and stir.
Does John Cox win right science fiction?
Coxon and yes under the pen name John Scalsy.
You're lying, Papa. We've met Scalsy.
You've met actor Will Wheaton playing the character John Scalsy.
Coxon likes his privacy.
Cox Wayne.
Coxon.
Sure, Papa. You have no credibility and NC.
Okay. I just want to state for the record that the word
C-O-X-S-W-A-I-N is pronounced Coxon and I was forced to pronounce it incorrectly
so that the dialogue would work.
We thank you for your method acting.
Yes.
It doesn't surprise me somehow that Chris Garcia says he is a fanatic for brutalism.
But he can only watch so long a film between all the wrestling he needs to see.
So it may have to wait a bit.
Yeah, I think probably he can watch it later on streaming and do six other things at the
same time. So he doesn't need to actually watch all the bits where it's lovingly panning over
architecture which are considerable.
The only thing to know obviously is that if it never comes out on streaming and only comes out
as a £24 blue-ray.
It's a bleeding Oscar nominally. It's bound to come out.
It was a sort of joke, you see.
I've never been very good at them myself but I've heard they can be politically effective.
We should maybe try one or two sometimes.
On the podcast.
And that was letters of comment.
Is that literally all we got?
We should try being more interesting.
No, we don't need to be more interesting.
We need to be more contentious.
Oh no.
See what you're making us do listeners and by us I mean Alison.
Yes.
Thanks to everyone who wrote in and everyone who will write in in the future.
We have some brief news about the Belfast Easticon.
So firstly PR4 is almost ready so keep your eyes peeled for that because I suspect it will
wing its way to you before the next episode listeners.
Excuse me.
Before the next episode listeners and we will discuss it when it does.
But also the programme is currently going into Plan Z.
If you're planning to volunteer to be on programme keep your eyes peeled on your emails.
Because that is where the news will be.
I think that do you mean if you've volunteered to be on programme
because are they going to take new volunteers at the stage or?
Well but this is the indication of interest point right where you go through the panels
and put your name down.
And remember the lessons we learned from doing this for World Cons which is
don't tell yourself short.
Yes.
You can put yourself down for stuff because if you don't put yourself down for things
someone with less imposter syndrome probably put themselves down for it.
Indeed.
And then you will find yourself at the convention sitting in the audience going
why have they put this idiot on the programme when I know so much more about the topic than they do
and that'll be the answer.
Yes.
Well it might or might.
It'll sometimes be the answer.
Yes there has been a report that people trying to cancel their rooms with the Hilton
who went for a non-refundable room are not able to get a refund which is not enormously
surprising but in fact they're not being able to get a refund for the entire stay
rather than the much more normal practice of charging you for the first night.
And this is new.
So if this is happening to you that I'm very sorry,
the suggestion at the moment is that you use something like the Eastacom Facebook group to find
somebody else who wanted the room that you are on the hook for at the moment because obviously
there will still be people looking for rooms at the moment.
So it does seem a bit harsh of the Hilton and I think I'm going to do a shout out to Phil Dyson
to watch for this in next year's contract because they are not there also with the Hilton.
To be fair there are two reports.
There's one from someone saying that they tried to call and book and they were trying to be
charged the entire room rate and someone saying they will cancel it and are being charged for one
night's stay.
So it might just be a mistake and it may have been sorted out by the time you listen to this.
The first comment was that they've waved the additional because Nick Whitehead who is the reporter
booked early and they've let them cancel on health grounds so they've charged the deposit but not
the other or they've charged one night but not the other three but that sounds like a
exception has been made because it's a disability issue.
So it doesn't sound like it's a mistake of it doesn't sound like it's differently
applying the same policy.
It sounds like differently applying two different policies to me but maybe I am wrong.
I do not work for the Hilton.
It's not clear to me whether they have like waved it on health grounds or whether they've gone for
what the booking conditions actually say when you book.
Okay.
We need more data points I think.
So but it, right.
So but the one that Cheryl Arvits and Keating is trying to cancel they say the terms of the
booking were that it would mean that you didn't get a refund if you cancelled.
So it sounds to me like the non-refundable hotel room turned out to be non-refundable.
Assuming they booked on the con rate I posted in Discord where it says when you try and book
a hotel with the con rate which is that it will keep a one night deposit.
But it's not clear to me that they did book at the con rate.
So in the UK if you book a hotel you can check out early at which point you do not
normally have a further liability.
So this is Hilton trying to stretch what can be done under normal custom and practice for UK hotels.
It might be legal but it is a huge stretch to charge one more than one night.
Oh also it's daft because the hotel will be full.
So what they're probably going to do now is resell this but not actually refund the original person.
But yes agreed but when I go on hotels.com and book a non-refundable hotel room
I do that on the basis that if I need to cancel it I won't get a refund because that's what
non-refundable means. If I book a plane ticket that's non-refundable and I have to cancel I'm out
the cost of the plane ticket. If I book a train ticket that's non-refundable I guess I'm struggling
to see it's non-refundable. That means it-
Yeah I think the issue is that the Hilton normally do a whole bundle of different things right?
You can do completely flexible or medium flexible or completely non-refundable.
But if you book on the con rate there's only one option.
It sounds like this person must not have booked on the con rate then because they say
he was unable to help which is fair enough because that was the terms of the booking.
At the point where the person making the booking is like fair enough that was the terms of the booking.
Am I angry? Like they read the terms understood the terms and the terms have been upheld.
Like I mean it's shitty I'd much rather get my money back if I had to cancel
and my heart goes out to this person who has had to cancel because I must suck.
But also if a business says that if you give the money they're not going to give it back.
Do you see what I mean? I don't know.
Yeah it's tricky because I think there's two things. So one it's not clear what- whether this
person has used the con rate. If you had I think you'd just pay one night and so then I guess the
thing would be do they then try and charge the rest of your card which would be a bit naughty
under what I would- how I would interpret the con in terms and conditions or have they accidentally
booked under another rate which was totally non refundable in which case yeah fair enough
transferring it is a reasonable solution there. And then we have someone else who did appear to book
on the con rate and has been charged the one night that they said they would charge you
when you booked. That I think is what has happened. Right so the law in the UK requires
customers not be charged unfair charges and there is specific case law for hotel rooms which says
that if a hotel room is if somebody has to cancel then a consumer as opposed to a business so if
you booked as a business you will be straight out of luck but if you book as a consumer the hotel
may only charge their reasonable loss which is the loss to them if they cannot re let the room
which they obviously will be able to do in this case or and therefore a small admin fee
so. But that's insane. No it's not. Okay so although there are a load of things that are
making life much worse for people in the modern age because consumer law isn't as strong as it
used to be you don't need to throw away the rights that you do have the UK and the EU have
quite strong consumer protections and this is one of the areas where they apply. Why doesn't it
apply to train? And indeed if you cancel your train ticket well in advance to say I need to
cancel you will often be offered a voucher and also with airlines and this is why.
I have never been offered a voucher for cancelling a train line trip in my entire life. Yes I called
train line and argued very strenuously and they would not. I viewed the words non-refundable as
meaning non-refundable and maybe I am out of touch on that but I just always assumed that was the deal.
I mean does this mean every time I book a travel or dupere premiere in which are very distinct booking
classes for you know advanced non-refundable and completely flexible then I should always
book the events non-refundable and then if I don't want to go I should get all my money back anyway.
Well they can charge you one night is very accepted. Charge you more than one night is the question.
I must confess this doesn't drive with my lived experience at all but maybe I just don't argue
strongly enough. I think this is me being old I think this is just a way in which the world has
become more shitty. Quite possibly. I mean what will inevitably happen if that is the rule is all
hotel rooms will get slightly more expensive. I don't see how they can get more expensive than
the Hilton over about Easter weekend. I mean that is the other problem 185 pounds a night.
I didn't think they could get more expensive than the Hilton in Birmingham in 2019 and Alison
they managed it so I am never of the opinion thing can't get more expensive. It's tricky isn't it
because I do take the point about consumer protection I think it is very good but also like
the that's the trade off you make right you gamble that you won't have to cancel and will get cheaper
will get a cheaper price and it's a gamble versus not gambling and paying them more money and I don't
know if that's good. We might have gone off topic. Yeah it's a bit weird because I mean that's it
like with you know hotels and trains to some extent and and airplanes I see okay there are various
options. Some of them are refundable some of the non-refundable and pick one based on based on which
one I think is best for me and it seems weird that if this is the actual situation under like
consumer guidance that that has been persisting so possibly we all need to start booking non-refundable
things and attempting to get our money back from them. I invite you to try that one with say BA
whose response to oh you've got COVID and you can't fly all right well that sucks then doesn't it?
Now Northern Stage so the theatre on Newcastle campus is called Northern Stage and I had to
cancel two tickets to see a comedy gig and they were like well we're not going to give you money back
with the with the net effect that whenever they're like would you like to donate some extra on your
ticket? I'm like no absolutely not you can sort off but when I called the stage in Edinburgh to let
them know I couldn't go to my Wozniak they just gave me a full refund no questions asked so I like
the stage and I go back there very often. Yeah I mean I basically think that you phone and if they
still say no then you write them a letter citing the law the consumer law which is quite clear
and say the law doesn't allow you to do this. Yeah now I know that that is now that I know that
that is a thing we've educated our listeners hopefully. I have a really good page on canceling goods or
services and advice for advice for customers and I'm going to put it in the show notes. I don't know
if it's true. I mean I know what the law says but I mean what you do is you write a letter saying I
will take you to I am prepared to take you to the small came's court. When you take them to the small
claims court that costs you in a map which is not very high but when you win if you win which you will
you'll get their money back. So generally speaking writing a letter saying I am intending to take
you to the small claims court will cause the money to come back. Now whether it works for things
like trains where they I think the train companies may argue that they cannot resell your ticket.
But I think it probably depends a little bit how far in advance you cancel. If I'm like at the
station having just missed the train I would be sympathetic to their argument but if I cancel it
three weeks in advance I'd be a bit less convinced. Can you link that in the what's names? Also if
this is consumer law so if you're somebody who runs a small business that is you and you're inclined
to book things as of your business that as soon as it's a business to business transaction none of
this applies. Businesses are expected to read contracts.
I will note that on Anonymous Claire there has been some discussion and there's at least one
person who basically said that they decided not to say in the Hilton as a direct result of reading
the Hilton's terms of conditions. So I think I think the Hilton's terms of conditions may say
all this but as Alison notes it might be worth arguing because you might be able to successfully
argue those terms of conditions are unreasonable. More generally if you're a consumer and a term
is in fine print then it doesn't actually apply if you take it to a small Cables court because there
is case law that says consumers can't be expected to read the fine print so they have to put it in
nice big print if they're going to do it. It has to be like on the face of the thing which they may
say it is because it says non-refundable so you know but I mean it's worth trying right?
It's in like big letters as big as any other letters on the page in bold.
Yeah I mean if they've made you tick through a box I understand if I cancel for any reason I'm
not getting my money back you probably you may be out of luck. I don't know it's worth going.
Well I'll leave all of this in anyway. Yes threatening to take things to the small
Cables court has always worked really well for me which I'm also doing I'm also going to give you
a link to that it's not even called small claims anymore I think.
No it's called money claim online I think. Money claim online. Make court claim for money
but anyway consumer law it's good because it's very easy for people to say oh no no all of that's
very old fashioned and we don't need it anymore our consumers are so much more knowledgeable than
they used to be. I definitely don't think we should erode consumer protections unlike you know the
government. Unlike the government yeah but I just didn't know this was one I guess.
Well it's contracts generally. My will be that I can choose to enter into a variety of different
terms and conditions and therefore I've chosen to enter into the cheapest one under those conditions
would be an interesting thing to discuss. Yeah I think I think I do think yes I do I think that is
the way I was thinking about it. Right shall we move on from British consumer consumer protection
law? Yeah I just don't think we should take it lying dad. We said we were going to have a short
this is what happens when we have a short episode because often we get to a point where John goes
we've got a lot to get through this week so this is not one of those weeks. And also you said about
being more contentious and I think opening a kind of worms as to the relative merits of protecting
businesses versus consumers in British consumer protection law that will definitely get us letters
so this is good. Next episode just letters about capitalism. What do you think about capitalism
listeners right in? No don't don't don't don't but if you try to take the Hilton to the small
or hotel to a small claims court for non-refunding your non-refundable thing then they do let us know.
I'm also right to like the Guardian and Martin Lewis um tell them. No there are pages about money
saving expert but I think I've linked directly to gov.uk because I think the gov.uk play just
pretty clear. Yes there are links in the show notes listeners. Non-refundable deposits should
only be a small percentage of the total price. Cancellation charges must be a genuine estimate
of the businesses direct loss. Oh I'm deep in annex A unfair contract terms now so yeah.
Anyway shall we move on to something that maybe is of interest to people who have not
recently booked Hilton hotels in the UK. Uh that is true yes sorry to our international listeners
if you have better consumer protection good for you and if you don't we're sorry.
Let's move on to discussing a different convention which is in this case the Seattle World
Comp because things have happened. Seattle announced in December that they will use virtual business
meetings instead of the at-con meeting and at the time they announced the dates that the meetings
would be on but they have now announced some more information including the platform and the
timing. So they're using a platform called Lumi Global which honestly looks very like corporate
which could be could be a good thing here right. It appears to be the thing used by a bunch of
corporations to like run their AGMs and so on with thousands of people and has lots of solutions
for doing virtual hybrid meetings having voting having authentication having a way to manage the
Q&A and so on. So it's interesting I mean I never heard of it but then I have never tried to run
an extremely corporate AGM. What will be interesting is to know whether what works for say Tesco can
be applied to WISFS because I would venture to suggest that not many people are at like
the Tesco annual general meeting because they plan to stand up and make comments six times and
go up to the microphone. So it'll be interesting because it's obviously a platform that works for
massive corporations but massive corporations work in a slightly different way to WISFS but
you do need something that people trust to kind of do all the authentication and the voting stuff.
So yeah that looks pretty good to me. I mean obviously I'm looking at their webpage but
they kind of say helping more people engage with your statutory meetings is a bonus so they
they have increasing engagement and making it easy for people to engage as one of the
good features about their platform and and they say a low latency environment which is great and
I like because WISFS is quite a high latency environment because there'll be people who want
to intervene all the time and deliberately sit at the very back of a very big room so that when
they are called to the microphone there's then approximately a 45 second wait while they walk
up and go to the front as if they just want a bAFTA. The thing is I think that is a cynical view
but it is very funny and it probably is a little bit true so yeah.
I watched the bAFTA so there was somebody who was extraordinarily surprised to win their bAFTA
and there's this look of absolute extreme shock when he wins and one of the comments on this I think
in one of the newspapers said it wasn't just a surprise to him it was also the surprise to the
person who'd worked out the seating plan for the bafters.
Oh man you know I never thought of that but you've occasionally got to put people who might win at
the back right otherwise it's dead giveaway. Yeah so they put people who they know are coming up
like the winners of the the winners of the achievement towards and things like that always gets
get aisle seats but you can't know with nominees so they have to kind of they have they basically
do a guess that's who's most likely to be called up but those people do the edge.
There is interesting we look forward to seeing how it goes. I love the fact that people hadn't
prepared speeches at the bafters and I'm like oh we've knocked that out of people to the hugos
after incidents like Alison in 2006. To be fair I do assume that a lot of the people at the bafters
have had a bit more experience in this whole awards thing and also many of them are better at
public speaking off the cuff than we are and yet maybe not so much actually it does that.
We're quite good at speaking off the cuff Liz on account of how we've now done 129 episodes of a
award-winning podcast. Did you deliberately pronounce that in the style of Matt Berry?
Yeah. Okay. Speaking of participating in the business meeting the other thing they announced
along with the dates of the virtual business meetings if they also announced their time slot
and all the business meetings will be running 9am to 12.30pm in Pacific Daylight time which is
seven hours behind UTC. That is and I think I've done the time wrong conversion correctly this time
11pm to 2.30am in my time zone so I predict I will be going to almost none of the business meeting.
Oh I think you could go there with a big sign of sign-up saying tard and angry.
What is not clear about their platform is whether you can actually see all the people who are there
are only like invited you know the head table and invited speakers as would be sensible
so there's no point me cosplaying. But yes so when they when they said back in December that they
would be taking into account religious observances work commitments and time zone differences
they've taken account of it and they've picked a time zone that works basically for everyone from
like east coast so for everyone from west coast US through to probably Europe and an hour ahead of
mainland Europe and they will all be accommodated by this although some of the meetings are on a
Friday morning in the US so some people are going to meet work so basically I can exhibit it basically
a picture time zone that I think will accommodate the most people possible. Unfortunately by doing
them all at the same time they are going to systematically exclude everyone who lives in
Australia, New Zealand and anywhere you know east of about India so you in some you lose some.
So I was sort of hoping they do one maybe at a different time. I think probably it's 85%
USA and Europe at least possibly greater though maybe if we had more access to business meetings
then it would get a greater global participation. I feel like also people who care enough will set
their alarm clocks and get to it no matter how difficult that is but I understand that that's
that's quite a hard barrier. But also that's the that's the argument that's always made about
the business meeting at conventions with people who care enough will be there and it's like no
they'd sometimes are busy. This is yes this is way more accessible than business meetings at
conventions. Yeah but I'm just skeptical of the more I think about it the more I think the answer
is not to have an audio visual component and to have it work more like Python where you have like
proposals made to the community and voting and it is done in text and over the period of like
several weeks per proposal because it would take a lot longer in terms of going from start to end
of any given thing but it would be a lot fairer and you wouldn't have to do it. It's not it doesn't
have to be in real time so it doesn't really matter but I need to work that opinion out some more.
I love that opinion and I'm going to amplify it by saying you don't have to not have an audio
visual component because you could ask people to record short videos where they speak for or
against items and then you can have those available for people to look at if they would like and I
think that would be quite useful. I mean we already do do the business meeting thing where you know
someone who the people for it against the amendment right a short thing about it which I agree we
should do more of. I quite like doing that with audio visual because I think things like
diagrams and actually having people standing up and speaking might be quite useful in this context
you know presentation is a good I'm starting pushing back against that because I do not want
to watch a bunch of random pieces meeting attendees. Yes please you can have a transcript too.
That is the problem right like we do a podcast and I don't mind listening to things but I know
that there are some people who are ferociously against video content and so yeah but I quite like
the idea but I'm sort of conscious of how not everyone might. I mean I will just say that one
of the things it does look for is the official Chinese time zone I think is an hour ahead of me.
I was going to note this. Given that we just had a large world con in China I hope
you guys like staying up till 3am but A you got it better than Australia.
Oh is this a Chinese time zone ahead of you? Because China's all on one time zone.
I maybe don't understand where Thailand is. What what are the dates? July the 4th,
July the 13th, July the 19th and July the 25th so roughly a week apart but space you get two Fridays
a Sunday and a Saturday. I feel like I'm going to be on a holiday the whole all of those again.
Which is the other problem. Oh that Friday is July 4th so although it is in the working day for
people in America nobody in America will be working. It will be for Canadians though.
It will be for Canadians. Because Canadians don't celebrate American Independence Day on account
of how they're Canadian and Mexicans and people in South America. There's a lot of people in that
time zone for whom it will be a working day. Right that's time zone sorted out listeners.
Let's move on to Hugo nominations. Oh not by any means like a girl for hours. No. No thank you.
Seems you're not even sure where Thailand is I think no passing judgment on our time zones.
Savage. Got an idea of some cover art though. It's a map.
Pin Tyler donna map with three little silhouettes and like three Tyler donkey tails. Hugo nominations
are now open. I'm going to record a little thing for the start of the every episode.
Like it was just a little sentence because of what happened with Hugo Girl and because we can't
expect people to have listened since last year but it will have been at the beginning of the episode
listeners you will have heard it. I'm going to record it now. Please note we have recused ourselves
from consideration for the 2025 Hugo's in the category of Best Frankast. Fabulous. Right and
Liz and I can't talk about anything that was published last year now so we won't. Please do go
and nominate things for Hugo Awards. I am allowed to say that nominating things for Hugo Awards is a
good and valorous activity. The system is very easy and the thing that we do say every year but
it's really important that you know if you haven't nominated for the Hugo before you can nominate a
few things and then you can go back and nominate other things it's okay. When you nominate when
you save out your nominations it will save what you've done so far but it's not like a once of
raw things. So if you're kind of like oh I don't know what I want to nominate for the Hugo but I do
know about these two things in this one category go and nominate them and then if you and then come
back and nominate other stuff later because every nomination is good and important and helpful.
Actually that's probably to take you to bit far but you know and you could nominate for the
Hugo's if you are a member of the Seattle Wilcon or if you were a Wussfuss member of the Glasgow
Wilcon. I think also if you're a Wussfuss member of the LA Wilcon is that right guys?
No I think maybe we just called for it once. I thought we got rid of that. Hang on
while I find the Wussfuss Constitution.
Yeah I don't know if it's gotten old for listeners but it hasn't gotten old for John or Alison.
Hey I mean I should just have this open in a tab before the start of every every episode really.
Ah each member of the administering Wilcon or the immediately preceding Wilcon
shall be allowed to make up to five weighted nominations in each category.
Yeah we got rid of the thing where it's next year because it was kind of pointless.
Thank you Liz. I can't imagine there were very many people who were Wussfuss members of the
following Wilcon but not either of the previous two. Yeah basically if you're a Wussfuss member
by 18 months before the convention then yeah you probably won't. Still get two years out of it so
yeah. But this means guys if you were a member of Glasgow but you haven't joined Seattle because
you can't possibly get to Seattle this year. You can still nominate and I bet there's a lot of
listeners in that category. So you can get all those cool British things onto the ballot except
not but you might get some of the cool British things onto the long list that comes out after the awards.
What do we want to do now? Some picks. Picks or do we want to do... What else are we going to do?
That's a great question. I don't know. I don't think I have anything else. Oh I would say one thing.
Last time we discussed the town hall that the 2026 Eastcon was going to do but I don't think
any of us went. So if anyone else went please tell us what was said and whether it was good.
Thank you. Also happening after we record but before the episode goes out is the BSFA's EGM. So
if you went to that write to us and tell us what we said. Also I have the agenda for that which is
what they were going to talk about if that would be interesting. So there's five things.
Draft proposal for BSFA charitable status. The process guidelines for the best translation
award where they're planning a jury award. Member ballot matters arising from the AGM 2024 succession
planning BSFA chair at AGM 2025 which is I believe the thing that we talked about a little bit on
the last octothorb and AOB. I don't imagine there'll be much of that famous last words.
So that is happening after we record but before this episode it goes out.
Okay.
Pics. Can I go first? I'm not going to pick a book from this last year because of matters
discussed earlier in the episode and I've not really played any new games or watched any new
movies. So instead I am going to pick Star Wars Galaxy's Edge the official Black Spire Outpost
cookbook which came out before 2024 and is not therefore Hugo eligible this year listeners.
It's quite good. The reason I pick it is because yesterday I made Hutti's slime pods which are
very lovely and they go squish squish squish but they're basically gnocchi and cana-lini beans
in a sort of spinach and pistachio and lime and avocado pesto with parmesan and double cream
and it's very nice and it's very yummy. The notes for it say that it serves two humans or is a
small appetizer for one young Hutt. So now you know and it's very lovely. So yes that's my pick
a surprisingly good cookbook. It also has a recipe for black bean hummus in it which is quite lovely.
I am super skeptical about themed cookbooks of this kind. I wanted it. I didn't buy it as a gift
but I asked for it because I wanted for my Star Wars role-playing games to have like some
in-universe examples of food that exists that I could say to my players existed rather than like
they've got space apples which is often what you end up falling back on. They're like apples but
spacey. Spapples. Oh yeah no that sounds good and somebody said oh and if you're having like a
May the 4th party then this is great for your food for your May the 4th party and I could get
behind that. Yes but I also think I don't know how many good recipes you expect in a given cookbook.
Three. That's fair. So I've got two out of this one and I haven't made it all yet so I actually
think like as themed cookbooks go because the great thing about the Hutties slime pods is that they're
very easy to make in advance and they're also very easy to make completely vegetarian but they're
chock full of protein because they've got pistachios and avocados and cheese and cream in them and
beans so like they're very filling and if you use vegetarian parmesan then yeah it's just they're
good. I like them. So yes I'm surprisingly pleased with the experience of having that cookbook so far.
I have not bought any other Star Wars cookbooks though. But yes I did already have an answer to
your rhetorical question about cookbooks because I have a lot of cookbooks. No it wasn't it's not
actually a rhetorical one it's like a genuine like because obviously they're not all going to be
bangers but I don't know it's an interesting three. Three. All right. I'm also decluttering
cookbooks this week or next in the next few weeks certainly. If you have any Star Wars ones let me know.
Obviously not and also my cookbooks are a mess. I mean most of the ones we're throwing away will go
in the bin. Liz. I have two questions. One does your Black Spire outpost cookbook include those
rather nice wraps that you get in Ronto Roasters and Galaxy Zech. Yes. I suppose I don't really need a
recipe for a breakfast wrap with like eggs and sausage in but they're quite good. Also I would
like to share my sleep off Hugo Girl because I found a goody on goodreads for this book.
Which is from Julie. No pulled pork sandwiches seriously.
What? What? Pogs. Oh pulled pork. Yes. Sorry do I need to repeat that to you?
It's a joke that works better in text I feel but pulled pork sandwiches. That was another non-verbal
joke. Yes. Sorry. Sorry to Julie from Goodreads we did not fully appreciate your joke there.
Well you did but we didn't. All right shall I go next? Oh can I read a goody from Goodreads?
Goodreads. Yeah yeah you can. Mike Kennedy says this cookbook just seemed like marketing for the new
Star Wars land opened in Florida and California. That is some astute criticism. I wanted to say
something about this which is that actually the fact that it is not really a Star Wars cookbook
is it? It's a Star Wars galaxy's edge so therefore Disneyland cookbook which means that they probably
serve some of this stuff at Galaxy's edge which means that there's some chance the recipes have
all been tested which is the problem with IP themed cookbooks in general. So you know when I asked if
they had a recipe for the breakfast wraps they serve at Ronto Rosas in Disneyland. They have a Ronto
wrap recipe but it's not the same Ronto wrap and I don't quite understand why because the one that's
actually in there seems like it's more involved than the one they serve in the park but I don't know
but if this Star Wars cookbook is not your taste there are many other Star Wars cookbooks
but this one came with the Star Wars apron. I'm gonna pick a book. Oh! Since I am not talking about
things from 2024 I thought I would go back a little bit and pick Nova by Samuel Delaney which
was published in 1968. I have somehow got this far without reading it so I thought that was a thing
I should rectify and I'm glad I did because it is still great. It's basically Space Opera. It's
about the spaceship captain Lok Von Ray. He is looking for a Nova because it will allow him access
to a massive source of Illyrium which is the Galactic power source normally found only in tiny
amounts and essentially Lok Von Ray is from one very rich galactic family and he's having an ongoing
feud vendetta rivalry with the science of another enormous extremely rich galactic family and so by
scoring a massive shot of Illyrium he will essentially upend the entire galactic economy.
So it's got, I mean that's just a kind of very basic idea of the plot but that really does not
cover it at all. The tone is just really excellent. It's kind of got a lot of like there's a lot of
tarot in there. Everything is like you know the backdrop is that no one eats anymore we just use
IV drips basically everyone is a cyborg and that's how they fly the ships and there's like fictional
fictional philosophers and psychologists who decided that making everyone a cyborg would make everyone's
work life happier. I really enjoyed it. It's very well written. It does not feel like it was written
over 56 years ago and it was apparently nominated for the Hugo for Best Novel but it lost two.
What did lose two? Okay it lost to Standon's Anzi Bar and to be fair I also really like Standon's
Anzi Bar so I can't argue about that one too much but yeah I just I love finding all the classic
works because we all know that like sometimes people go and say oh what should I read in some
more suggested classic work and it is terrible and they just have a load of nostalgia for their
childhood or whatever and so I really like going and reading classic works that get recommended
and they are really good and this one is really good so there you go. I have read this book but
it was a long time ago and my memory is gone now. Took get all, getting all this terrible.
Sorry I can't hear you Alison. I have also not read this and I have not read Standon's Anzi
Bar so I guess I have homework. Oh yeah no you do because Standon's Anzi Bar so you pick that
next time John. The forum big serious Bronner books about kind of things that are going along
in the world. They're all good and Standon's Anzi Bar is probably the one that has survived
best. Interesting okay I'll add it to the big list after I finish my cloud greeting.
Yeah though obviously brother can be a painter for because you know did you meet him?
I have never met John Bronner. As noted he died in the middle of the 95 Worldcon.
He did yes. Oof. He was at Easter call and I spent quite a lot of time drinking with him
and Bob Shaw at the 1995 EasterCon Bob was a guest of honor and Bob and John were obviously friends.
I've just checked and I think my memory is correct. When Peter Weston started up his well we started
up his fanzine relapse in I think the early 2010s. There was the best article that ever appeared in
relapse was The Home Life of the Bronners by John Nielsen Hall. Yes yeah no it is if you've not read
The Home Life of the Bronners by John Nielsen Hall listeners it is one of the finest fanzine
articles ever written and I'm sure it's on fanact.org you can go and get it. I'll find out when it was
either prolapse or relapse yeah. Yeah I was looking for that and I also found a memory of
John Bronner from Ian Watson as well so yeah they're all I think they're all on there.
Alison what's your pick? So my pick this week because I am the one person on the pod who can talk
about things that were published in 2024 but I'm not sure I'm going to get any come back from my
fellow hosts. We have discussed this book. We already discussed this book in a previous episode
so if you want to hear our thoughts go back and listen to the last couple. It was in the episode
where they talked about what they were nominating at this point I have not read it. I have now read
it. It is The Ministry of Time by Kalyan Kalyan Bradley. This makes it three sci-fi romances
in a row for me and singers and I don't mean romance sci-fi romance in the way of Jules Verne. I mean
actual genre romance sci-fi blends which is I've definitely not read three of those in a row before
so this is actually quite a good sci-fi show. I think so the premise is that we are following a
young woman who has acquired a job working in the time travel branch of the UK civil service
where her colleagues are about to pull five people out of time and to see if a time machine works
because they have got a time machine. They've got a working time machine and they pull five
people out of time who would have died quite quickly anyway. One of them is Lieutenant Gore of
the Franklin expedition and our main character is set I guess looking after him while they keep him
on house arrest or near to house arrest for a year which is kind of the main part of the book.
She gets the job because she's a linguist and expert in refugees and one of the ways in which
this book is really good is it talks a lot about what it is like to be out of place and a refugee
and also have some constraints on what you can do. Nevertheless I was very light-toned in the first
part of the book because they're kind of doing the rom-com bit with a whole lot of odd couple
with time things like oh this is the internet you know I mean how does that work if you're from
the Franklin expedition and so in case you don't know what the Franklin expedition is the book has
helpful flashbacks in time because I do know quite a lot about Franklin already because I've spent
afternoons hanging out with a friend who is fairly obsessed with it. These didn't maybe land
as well for me as I have done for people who weren't already familiar with that but they will they
will clue you in on what he was doing and what happened to that expedition if you don't already
know and that's it for time travel for the majority of the book so it's enough because that is you've
got your fantastic setting but the time travel just kind of happens at the beginning and then sits
there and then there is a bunch of timey-wimy stuff at the end when they're wrapping everything up
that bit at the end didn't quite land for me and I think it may not land for quite a lot of
genre science fiction fans because you might have read things a bit like this before
in a way that that slightly undermines the novel but overall I thought it was very very good one of
the best novels I've read this year will be on my Hugo Ballot and yes it's kind of got quite a
bit of genre amounts in it but it does have all of the trappings and it doesn't do everything you
might expect to happen so yeah it's really really good and I would recommend it to everybody and I
think the other two have already said this in previous episodes so. Liss and John have no comment
at the present time. Liss and John have no comment on the present time but did make comment on this
book in previous episodes. That's a funny funny business isn't it so go back in time and listen
to what they had to say and not forget. That was the Octothorpe podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me.
[Music]
I'll have to separate them out in the edit listeners because in real life you wouldn't be able to
tell what I thought what I was saying unless you'd recorded 129 episodes of a podcast with your
co-host. Yeah I didn't hear Alice and Tom. I just stopped because I clearly was getting anywhere this time.
Hey I got a word in edge ways ahead of Alice and...
Okay okay it's been 129 episode journey.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod in Competec.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license. This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.
[BLANK_AUDIO]