Oh, have you know, I've carefully booked my holiday between recording dates for once.
What? That is some commitment. That is that very impressive. My holiday's in Glasgow,
guys, I don't know about the rest of you. Oh no, no, this is my one of my other holiday.
[laughs]
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 109th episode of Octa Thorpe, a podcast for Science Fiction
and Science Fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 9th of May 2024. I'm John Goxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty and we have a bumper mailbag this week and I'm going to hand
over to Liz to start us off. Yes, so we got a letter of comment from Abigail Nussbaum
who is talking about our discussion of best related book nominations and big
or less decalises withdrawn nomination and she would like to support an ad to our reservations
where the point we didn't make which is that this tweet was also a marketing tweet and she says
we were in a period which authors have been forced by the publishing industry to become their own PRM
marketers and this is often translated into transforming critical and fandom spaces into
marketing spaces. So basically her objection is on an extra level of saying, okay, here are some
critical works engaging with the genre and here is basically a piece of viral marketing and we're
putting these kind of on the same level which is very interesting and so she says she finds
the choice to decline the nomination very classy. Also says, "P.S. many thanks for mentioning my
forthcoming book but I was a tattle armed by John's Dark Tone when he admitted to typesetting it
something I should know." That's just a reflection of my general grim take on the universe and my
pessimism about the world as we know it which I think really comes through on Octa Thorpe. Abigail's
book is called Track Changes and I believe it is launching at Glasgow so if you're interested in
books or conventions look both of those up. We forgot to say that last time but I think the
name Track Changes is absolutely brilliant and excellent and excellent name for a book. It is good.
We heard from Ally Baker Brooks who says as our infrequent children and YA correspondent
she recommends a collection called Lowborn High by David Barnett Anna-Modersova and Mike Walters
and this is a comic. If you enjoy the Chilling Adventures of Sabrina Wednesday and other magical
school stories but wondered what happened to the kids whose families couldn't afford private
school fees this one's for you and yeah that sounds pretty great thank you very much for writing in
Ally. We heard from Caroline Mullen we got a long letter from Caroline on three topics. Firstly
she says that she chose which items to go and see in person at the convention having noted that
they would not be available on catch-up which is very clever. I did not think of that that would
have been a good thing to think of. She pointed out that we had at least one talk where the person
who gave the talk was constrained by their employment and so it was going to be available on catch-up
and points out we'd much rather have stopped like that than not have it and she's quite right.
She also mentioned it would be good to know when your category of stream statistics how many people
are not watching the program because they are chilling in their hotel room watching the program
and as somebody who's actually done this now I I can confirm it's quite a good way to watch
program but it's probably not so good for the people who are at the actually giving the program
who may get a room full of nobody while people are watching from their hotel room which is not as
much fun. Liz and I have done this we watched the opening ceremony from ChaiCon 8 streaming from our
hotel room on account of how the room was well busy and that was one instance where our presence
would not have helped necessarily. To spoil Andrew January's lock which is coming up listeners
slightly Andrew says out of 181 program participants one program participant opted out of live streaming
and seven opted out of catch-up which led to 18 out of 157 items not being on catch-up and I found
that really interesting because it's four percent of participants opted out which resulted in 11 percent
of items being unavailable and it is interesting how that can have a like disproportionate effect I
don't know what I think about that yet but I found it interesting. That's because of panels and I
would be preferentially selecting people from for panels unless it's a panel that will not work
without an individual. I think we should be making it clear to people that they are less likely to
be selected for panels if they've chosen not to choose to catch up but you know this is just me
and I'm like a mad catch-up enthusiast so. Yeah and you also don't have any problem being on stuff
that's on catch-up. I mean I don't want to say that we would deparatise people because people
have different reasons for not being on catch-up and at the moment is the majority of people who
are happy with it so the ones who are not either the you know possibly they're not used to it or
possibly they have really serious reasons for not wanting to be on catch-up and you would miss
might miss a whole segment of people if you said that. I think it's fine it's just
so you'd want to make a decision on an individual basis. I'm not saying don't use those people
I'm saying if you've got person A who's great and is happy to be on person catch-up and person B who's
roughly as great in a slightly different way and not happy to be on catch-up then use person A.
Do you ever really have a situation where you have two people who like you might have that
individual panel basis but if you look and say okay all the people who are worried about say
potential harassment on the internet for their gender presentation say they're locked out then
you end up with a situation where you you end up with a lot of people a whole population who are
not there in the program even if on an individual level you can replace them with other people.
I don't know who's opting out yeah that's the thing we don't know and it would be interesting
to know why if anyone does opt out of catch-up and is happy for us to discuss it then please
let us know but they may also not want to email into a podcast and discuss it.
Caroline also talks about great benefit of streaming programs is for the people who for those people
who sometimes need time away from all the people during the con therefore streaming program is an
aid to accessibility and I think that's probably true and the third part of Caroline's lock she maybe
has a unique perspective on accessibility in that she uses scooter for the first time at levitation
and so she said she had the best of both worlds a relatively small scooter that fitted into the
public lift and the ability to get off it easily when she needed to because she's somebody who just
uses a scooter to help with the fact that her knees are not doing what they used to do she
found it very difficult to bring it back to the international hotel in charge and I think that's
something that is an issue for wilcon as well and there I know that they're talking about scooter
management and how they deal with people who might not be in an immediately local hotel but are
going to have a scooter and she says that scooter users was probably slightly better served at the
easter con she chaired which is probably true but I'm going to go haha this is the thing that easter
con chairs do for the rest of their lives in my experience and one of the things that comes out
of the discussions we're having is that you can have different perspectives on what there can be
two venues two people with very similar access requests can prefer one venue or the other venue
depending on very slightly different priorities and this is one of the difficult things it is not a
linear space of just not too accessible it is some very non-linear 3d space where there are lots of
considerations and there is no venue that meets all of them perfectly and so yeah I think I think
Caroline noting that from her perspective the Hilton Metropolitan was better is useful feedback
thank you very much Caroline yeah I mean I would say a venue on one floor does cut out a lot of
access issues but then I had some extra ones with people who cannot walk far enough for the long
distances so yeah we also heard from DC who sent us the very nice lock we read last time
and they just wanted to point out that the calm was very supportive and it was clearly a priority
of the calm and they did excellently intricate at gold star Andrew January wrote because we talked
about his hard work on the East Com last episode and said a couple of things he was very quick to thank
other people on the team including including the tech and the rest of the committee which of
course is fair it was not something that he did alone he has done a write-up of the
members portal and why he thinks it was successful and we will link to that write-up in the show notes
he thinks that we should have a software engineer on the East Com committee and I think one of the
things we'll be talking about in a future episode is the way in which the requirements for East
Com which is not that big a convention continue to spin larger and larger and how practical this
is and then he talks and this is the thing that's really interesting about the stats on streaming
and ketchup which is a decision taken by the committee he says speaking personally and not for the
committee there are a lot of factors that contribute to why something does or does not get a lot of
people watching it and very few of those factors are how good a doubt how good individual participants
are on the panel and he would recommend against releasing the full stats publicly but he has
passed they have passed the full stats on to Glasgow and intend to release some summary statistics
I don't know whether they've done that yet but this would probably be quite a good time because
the East Com ketchup has now closed thank you very much for hanging in Andrew that was very
interesting stuff and it was good good context yeah good stuff thank you we heard from Mark Plummer
a fan historian researcher extraordinaire who says that he liked the site more than he expected
and was surprised by how well the holiday in bar worked Ailes points out that at 450ish it would
be the smallest East Conson 2007 and that was in some ways a special case because it was the kind
of emergency rescue Eastacom and that he thinks before that you'd have to go back to 1974 to find
an Eastacom of that size which is interesting I had registered it was small but not registered
quite how small and Mark says it might be useful to try and find out how many people didn't go
for site related reasons and how many for for other reasons you know then if we go back to
Telford we know how many people didn't go just because it was Telford he also looked it up and
the Telford International Centre dates from 1987 ages ago that is interesting thank you very much
Mark we had an email from Jacob Holder who writes in saying my name is Jacob and I'm interested to
know of what a first timers view of Eastacom would look like I'm a massive fan of science
fiction and fantasy books but not so much TV shows and films is it basically still worth a punt for me
yes yes it is Eastcon skews much more towards books than um TV and films especially relative to
other science fiction conventions um so yes I would say you might very much enjoy Eastcon Jacob I was
slightly shocked by this lock because I think it reminded us that we don't talk a lot about what
Eastacom actually is but because it's the national convention and because it's um there'll be 75 of
them at the point where Eastacom started there weren't any sites I have very few
science fiction films um and no science fiction TV shows so TV and Filmers had to sort of catch up
with where the Eastacom's at and the Eastacom has had to catch up with the fact that a lot of
people get their science fiction ways out of the books but there is a still a ton of stuff there
for people who read books which of course all of us do and I think most people at the Eastacom are
people who get a lot of science fiction from books that they obviously also see yeah no if you like
books definitely come to Eastacom you also might like to come to Wollcon Jacob just saying yeah but
it also looks like if you went to uh your own literary con at London Comic Con you could add on
a photo with Colin Baker she probably won't get a Wollcon I got a photo with David Tedda
to London Con was that primarily because you were on the committee and I did not have to pay 10
pounds for it at the Hugo reception yes so this leads us very neatly onto the second part of
Jacob's letter which is a question about volunteering any views on volunteering for Eastacom would be
appreciated as I do enjoy volunteering every Eastacom does volunteering slightly differently I think
that's fair to say um if you'd like volunteering my suggestion would be either email uh the East
Quantine Advancees say I'm interested in volunteering what could I volunteer for because there's never
enough people signing up in advance of the convention but if you are at the convention and you want to
volunteer but I think starting with registration Green Room or ops as like central places where
people exist and can give you help might be good good starts I'm going to say registration or ops I
think Green Room probably don't want random people coming in volunteering but you know they probably
won't buy that much but they might just take you round to ops there's a sort of what do you like
question about volunteering because so Green Room has a lot of being nice to programme participants
some of whom will be quite stressed out um tech has a lot of fixing cables and stuff um ops tends
to have a lot of kind of looking sitting in places and making sure that people are wearing badges or
or checking or taking things from one place to another so you have it's kind of what sort of
things do you like to do newsletter has a lot of um trying to write short funny articles against
considerable time pressure it when when people have given you long boring articles you know that's
sort of thing. Farra Mendelson wrote in to say that on an episode of the Critical Friends podcast
which is the Strange Horizons podcast about criticism. Paul Kincaid joined them to discuss
various things obviously Maureen Kincaid's brother came up and Paul said she resisted any
suggestion that she should publish a collection um so that closes the loop on something we mentioned
last episode thank you very much Farra. I wonder why I need to start listening to Critical Friends
because I I love podcasts about criticism and about about you know about sausages you know about
sausage making for any of the sorts of sausages I make does that make sense um and we also heard
finally from Meg Mcdonald who says that she thinks Liz also has a dirty laugh but she can see how
it might have just seemed she meant the live show um so Liz you're dirty thank you Meg I feel like
you should deliver a dirty laugh that's funny yes don't we get we also heard from my ex-husband
okay and that was letters thank you very much everyone for writing in yeah we did get a bumper post
bag
Dave Langford has received the Dockweer Award which was delivered to him in a carrier bag yeah we've
got a photo here yeah I will put a photo in the show notes I do very much enjoy that in the picture
Dave is holding a Tesco bag for life they could have literally anything in it there there's no
evidence that the Dockweer Award is in it let's start the truth the conspiracy here where is the Dockweer
Award Alison do you want to talk about Guff? Yes I do um so we have a winner in the Guff race who is
Cat Clay congratulations Cat Cat will be attending the Worldcon she's going to be arriving in the
country uh a little bit over a week before Worldcon and she will come to London we will have some kind
of fanish event and by that I mean we will get together in a pub so that if you're in London and
not going to the Worldcon you still have a chance to meet Cat or if you're in London and going to the
Worldcon you can hang out with such fiction fans before the Worldcon that probably be Monday or
Tuesday of Worldcon week and then she is going up to Worldcon on the Wednesday so she said maybe
we should have some sort of event meet-up event on Wednesday night and I said I think you will find
that meet-up events exist on the Wednesday night before Worldcon um and and we will just tag on
to one of them um I bet they'll be I bet they'll be say a pub crawl that seems likely doesn't it
and other things of that kind and then Worldcon and then the following week she's going to
the thing about Cat is that she writes novels that are kind of
Regency novels based on the ksuhoo mythos which is a word I cannot pronounce and which is very
interesting and so she is desperate to visit Buxton which as fans will know is somewhere that we
often have conventions so the week in the in the time after Worldcon she's probably going to visit
York and Buxton and Manchester so if you're in any of those places do um write in and we'll
we'll tell you what's going on there and then she is going to be going I think we haven't actually
sorted all the details out but we are expecting to go to the Eurocom in Rotterdam so she will get
to meet European fandom there and then she is planning to go on to Beuland and meet some
bonish fans before flying back to Australia so that seems pretty exciting to me well done cat
commiserations to Ian Nichols who was the losing candidate and was very sad for about 48 hours
because he was like well this was going to be my last chance ever to attend a Worldcon
unless it came back to Australia and then then he worked out that he can actually come to Worldcon
by buying the world's strangest and cheapest airline tickets so he is coming to Worldcon as well
so that's great so we will see Ian at Worldcon too so hey thanks to everybody who voted or has
contributed to the fanfans in any way whatsoever and I'm looking forward to hanging out with Kat in
August and hopefully introduced her to as many of you as possible hey
on the 2nd of May Ersatz Culture friend of the pod posted a or sorry sent an article to Farsatz
70 entitled the PDU district of Chengdu announces a 10 year science fiction plan and this has made
a lot of people very angry and been widely regarded as a bad move that's a riff it was posted to Farsatz
70 by Ersatz Culture but Zimozi Natsuko a Chinese fan posted it onto the Worldcon business meeting
discord a little while before so I don't know if they found it at the same time but that was the
place where I saw it and just because to say like when this sort of stuff comes out obviously I am
not scanning for it I would never see this it needs someone to read it and go oh hey wait they're
talking about Worldcon and Hugo's and maybe we should try and translate this just say this was
posted on April 8th you know we are possibly missing out on a lot of announcements that get made
in websites we're not reading this is another one in Asatz Culture's Strandon file 770 of
finding interesting Worldcon and Hugo related stuff which is posted on websites only in Chinese
and then he basically machine translates and tweaks them so bear in mind that this is all coming
from a machine translation but it is called notes on the action plan what's on the issuance of the
action plan for the construction of Chengdu Science Fiction Centre in Pidu District 2023 to 2033
so this is a very long plan about essentially boosting this part of Chengdu into a science
fiction centre and a lot of is about kind of integrating with technology branding business
stuff etc but there are some bits which Asatz Culture has accepted which are probably relevant
to science fiction fans and specifically the ones reading file 770 because they include things
like Strive to Create or Introduce More Than Two Hugo Award-nominated works and 100 science fiction
themed IPs within three years broke top domestic and foreign IPs such as the Hugo Awards extend the
brand effect of the Worldcon implement the conference brand inheritance plan I don't know
what brand inheritance plan is strive for authorization from the World Science Fiction Society and
strive to apply for the Worldcon again within five years so basically this is a kind of
official local government plan which involves bidding for Worldcon again and getting nominated
for Hugo's which is a really interesting thing to see in a local government plan it is but also a
worrying one yeah so so I think it's fair to say that there's quite a lot of fans in the west
who were already before they saw this doing everything they can to make sure that the
Worldcon that China does not successfully bid for the Worldcon again in the next five years or
possibly indeed ever I think that's fair but I would also say specifically I'm not I'm not worried
by the prospect of China bidding for Worldcon as much I'm worried by the prospect of essentially
the PDU district people's government office bidding for it because obviously they have a large plan
yeah which uses which essentially uses Worldcon and the Hugo Awards as marks of how successful they
have been on establishing themselves as a big business center and that is not how I think of
Worldcon and the Hugo Awards indeed yeah I think I think the problem here is not that there is a
Chinese bid for Worldcon the problem here is that it is explicitly a Chinese local government authority
bid for Worldcon and like I would feel the same if I don't know less to share bid yes those
though remember we're translating from Chinese so you don't know whether it's actually saying
we are we we the PDU branch of local government are bidding or if it would be the same as
say Glasgow saying we successfully attracted the Worldcon's fiction convention to Glasgow
and the SEC and we would like to see them return within five years which I don't think people would
have a problem with I think I'm not saying this isn't worrying because I think it probably is
worrying but I'm saying the amount of nuance that could be lost in translation is very great yes
but obviously the difference in your hypothetical is that the Glasgow Worldcon is being run by
volunteers and we have it we have a number of reasons to think that the Chengdu Worldcon was
largely co-opted by business and local government interests 100% and also they would like to sweat
the Worldcon brands and fun fact chaps Chinese IP means that they could just get on to do that
and there's probably not very much that the bot protection committee or anybody else can do about
it though I'm sure Hugo Boss will have a go so that's news bit orks yeah I mean there's also a bit
I mean the bit that says continue to operate the online space of the Worldcon which is quite funny
because it didn't really operate as an online space during the Worldcon build a regular online
communication space between domestic fans and core members of the Worldcon and senior foreign
fans which I think is just making a bit explicit in their business plan what happened before the
Chengdu Worldcon anyway which is trying to bring over senior Worldcon con runners basically to get
them to see what they can do and I think get some of their support which I don't think is going to
work half as well in the future as it did before this Worldcon but it is in the plan so if anyone
tries to contact you for the through the wormhole plan it's because they think you are an influencer
oh I shall keep my eyes out yep no I'm sure we should be waiting for our invitations to
Chinese freebies I will link to the file 770 version because not all of our listeners will be able to
follow a link into the business meeting discord presumably oh I think they can all join if they
want but I wouldn't necessarily recommend that they do so but you know don't self exclude if you
think that being on the wisps business meeting discord will enhance your quality of life you
should definitely join if you think that the wisps business meeting discord will enhance your
quality of life then then there are people you can talk to about this it's going to say help is
available if you have been affected by any of the issues raised in this broadcast
have we already mentioned that the final ballot for the hugos is now available and you could vote
oh I don't know if we have actually because if not we should probably do that yeah
vote early vote often you can do that it'll just overwrite your previous vote
yeah yeah actually that sounded funny but that is actually the recommended technique for
hugo voting which is to vote straight away just for the things you already know about so then go
back in later and and amend your vote once you've become more familiar with more of the categories
yes we especially recommend as always everyone please votes in the fan categories obviously we
are eligible in fancast but please vote for the fan casters you think are the best and vote in all
the other fan categories so they continue to be awarded and we continue to recognize excellence
in fan they took out the thing where you don't want them if you get below a certain number of votes
so they'll still be awarded yes so but nevertheless I think the hugos are quite unusual in that they are
kind of the leading awards for a genre but also contain awards for fan activity and that reflects
the historical and ongoing relevance of the things that fans do to the genre as a whole and I think
that's incredibly important for the field and I think the fact that the hugo has fan categories is
really a good thing about the hugos and I would think that even if I wasn't a finalist and hadn't
previously won them but you know it is special pleading clearly but there you go we will be doing
episodes on the hugos we'll probably do one on the books and one on everything else because in the
summer it's hard to sit down and record and so having filler is useful no having excellent content
that isn't timely is useful I'm told we've never managed it have we mentioned the town halls yet
no I'm in 20. Glasgow's doing town halls they did one on site selection they're going to do one on
the business meeting and they're going to do one on the hugos but I think the one on the business
meeting is the one that is most likely to be um it's not most likely to be of interest but it's
most likely to explain something that people aren't already familiar with even if they are
listeners to this podcast whereas I think people probably do know quite a bit about the hugos and
how they work already which is good because they already had the hugo and the site selection one
so you missed them I will put it in the show notes a link to the town halls on the hugos and on
the site selection which are on the youtube channel thanks laze
we're going to talk a little bit about money more specifically we're going to talk about the
cost of the east corn and its ramifications for the people who can go um who wants to introduce this
should I mean I can but I don't mind if someone else wants to I want to talk about the past of
east corn's a little bit because the historical model for east corn was that you went to a big hotel
and said oh we'd like to fill your big hotel over a weekend when east over east weekend where it
will otherwise be empty because you're mostly a business hotel and in return would you mind giving
us all your conference space for free and I mean there's some kind of slight bits and bobs there
that's not always the exact thing they normally require that we didn't just sleep in the hotel we
also spend a lot of money on food and drink there which we do so it's okay and what seems to be
happening post-covid is that hotels are way less comfortable with that sort of deal than they used
to be now they may return to be uncomfortable with it but at the moment they are saying no you should
play for all your conference space and the conference space is very expensive because we use a fast
amount of it because unlike a business convention of the same size where you'd have one massive room
and then drop people into a few spaces for breakouts but maybe three or four and then bring them back
to the massive room and you probably have no more than one backstage room we actually have
enormous numbers of things that need to be put into rooms so we use enormous amounts of conference
space and it costs a lot of money and so I think inevitably that means the membership of east
con is going to have to rise and rise a lot um is that a good introduction and what does this mean
for the con yeah I think so I think I mean it's worth saying that this all might change
but I think it is notable that like things have changed or seem to have changed in the post-covid
years so yeah I think that's a fair summary Liz you've got some numbers yes so I did get some
numbers essentially just because I noted when the telefoot bid was announced that the membership
was quite expensive so I did go and look at some historical numbers as far as I can tell these
other ones these are the numbers for kind of buying a membership quite late on or on the door
and they're all post-covid times ones and so in 2022 a full membership was 70 pounds in 2023
it was 100 pounds and in 2024 it was 140 pounds and we don't know what 2025 will reach but they're
currently at 70 so I would assume it's going to be somewhere maybe 90 or 100 by the time we get to
the convention so basically costs are going up of a membership I mean cost is the cost of a
membership is not the only factor of pricing of east con's but I think it is a big one especially
for people who might be able to commute from the local area you've or people who are new to east
con's we've gone from it's 70 pounds which you might be willing to take a punt on for the weekend
to it's 140 so maybe you will only come for a day or not at all I know hotel rates have also gone
up I don't think my nine pound hotel room is ever coming back again but I think that is quite a
big gap and the second thing I noticed is that east con's usually have a concessionary rate I
think we seem to have settled on the right approach which is basically rather than having to prove
eligibility of some long list of categories that is eligible for concessions we just say if the cost
is a problem you are eligible for a concessionary membership but I do note that the concession
membership has been going up 10 pounds a year and since the full membership is moving up way more
than that we're at the point where in 2024 a concessionary membership was 60 pounds and a full
membership was 140 which is a much bigger difference than k 40 70 pounds in 2022 if we do think cost
is an issue for the east con the second problem is going to be that if we have a lot of members who
cannot afford the full rate and can only come if they get the concessionary membership then it
kind of will force the full rates up even further because a smaller number of the convention are
actually paying those rates and we're also tended to have local memberships Glasgow has local
membership three connectors local memberships that's the Belfast east con Dublin I think had local
island memberships and so that's great for getting new people in but it also means that when you're
doing your cost estimations you may need to push the full membership prices up again just because
you know that only a smaller amount of your members will actually be paying that if we're paying for
function space then we know we have an amount we have to pay and we probably can't set the rates
too low so we don't risk falling below that especially if you think you might only be a 500 person
east con not an 800 person east con so I think that is going to just it's going to be interesting
to see where it goes in the next few years and if that that has to push further up so I also wanted
to say a little bit about early bird rates it's traditional that you get a very good deal on the
east con two years later if you buy it immediately after the bid is one or within a couple of days
that's often half the cost of buying it on the door or even less in some cases compared to other
things I go to like festivals that distance difference for a festival might be 20 pounds on a 100 pound
ticket but it's not going to be anything like the discount we give and one of the results is it that
the people who are financially able to pay for their membership early and know that they will
definitely go get a vastly better deal than the people who can only decide at the last minute and
I think that's something we should be talking about a bit more openly because it's possible that a
smaller discount would be sufficient to get those people joining I think I'm going to say a couple
of things I'm speaking for a position of wealth privilege like I am I'm not rich but I'm not poor
I'm thoroughly middled and so like I will say that for me my decision to join east con as soon
as memberships go up I mean I know I get a cheaper deal but it's also about you know I can I know
the money is coming out of my account I can spend the money immediately knowing the money has already
gone makes it easier for me to see how much money I actually have and so I'm not doing it primarily
because it's cheaper I'm doing it because it makes my budgeting easier as well I will say that if
conventions did make that initial rates less of a good deal than it currently is it would not affect
my decision personally but obviously I cannot speak for all fans who do that if you have an
opinion please get in touch because I'd be interested to know I've been interested to know people's
reasons for joining early I mean there's another reason why the starting rates are low right because
if you start off low then you can have more rate rises and rate rises are a good way to
advertise we've got a rate rises we can remember to join you know the east con if you start higher
you also don't have as many of those but maybe we don't need quite as many of those I mean I think
they're often time to you know be like Nova common the previous east to common so on or just raise it
by five pounds or something instead a five pounds rate rise probably isn't enough to motivate people
to actually bother so I do see that there's a psychology there of putting the rate rate up
enough that people who have just been a bit lazy are actually motivated to do it and that and that's
that's part of the thing right because I understand why conventions do this model but Alison is also
quite right that this model does not act in a way that increases the equity of the community it's
hard but this is why it's important to talk about it because it's not if it was trivial easy to
sort out we would need to talk about it I just want to say the thing is a lot of this is
kind of I think wealth is sometimes in in the eye of the beholder like because John says he's not
rich he's not poor solidly middle but I suspect from the perspective of someone who's rich that
they would think John is definitely not solidly middle and the perspective of people say with
zero income would probably say that John is quite rich yeah I don't I don't know how we get around
that but basically you're deciding if you need a concession membership and I think most people will
be not taking concession memberships unless it genuinely is an issue but there might be people
who kind of go oh actually I can buy 60-pound memberships for me and my family but not 140
pound memberships for me and my family yeah I mean I did I did buy concessionary memberships for my
unwaged children despite the fact that I was paid for their memberships but I was like they are
children and they are unwaged and they have no income and they clearly cannot possibly be paid
with all about so you know when I say children I mean young adults okay so yeah well I think we
should be clear that your children are not dependent children on day to 18 they are your adult children
-fecless ex-students and I should say that one of my earning less money than so the part of this
was people who were retired automatically assuming that because they were pensioners they were therefore
entitled to concessions which if anyone has been paying attention to income distributions in the
United Kingdom is not always the case and it's all obviously very complicated because if you just
because part of the thing is that if you don't introduce a strict set of rules by which you know
if you meet these criteria you can apply for the concessionary rate you end up in situations
where you're cutting people out who should be able to apply but if you don't have the strict
set of rules people will self-sensor and they will not think it applies to them and so there is a
thing here about I think I'm not saying we need strict sets of rules but I do think examples
of if you are if you read this example and you think oh that sounds a lot like me you should get
the concessionary rate and we are not saying that this example means that if you don't recognize
yourself in this example you're not eligible and there should be multiple examples obviously
I am not retired obviously so I have no insight into that but that's like when it used to be that
it was an unwaged membership I remember when I was first in fandom that was the deal and obviously
that is one where that explicitly includes people who are retired so I wonder I don't know how much
of that is a hangover of the way we used to do it it's just hard to decide but certainly when I was
a student I used to buy unwaged memberships because I was broadly unwaged yeah I also
worry there are people who select out because they think oh well you know I've you know maybe I lost
my job but I'm sure I'll get one soon and we're just having kind of temporary issues like that's
also why it's there I will also say that I don't think I can only look at Belfast East Gun I don't
want to single them out but they're the ones who currently have a registration page we don't have
like a family membership or anything like that that might also help because the cost of bringing
four people don't need to come much out of the cost of bringing too we actually have a lot we used
we had a spell where we had quite a few kids at the East Gun and we've got far fewer now and some of
that is demographics but I wonder if we're losing our family our young families again because I think
it is it is incredibly expensive I wanted to talk a little bit about how the need to make sure we
don't price people out of the community affects the way in which we look at venues and the knock on
impact that has on access because one of the things that we covered last episode was that the
Telford International Center was built in the 1980s and if you had built it today you would not
have made some of the same decisions that they made but obviously the other side of that coin is
that Telford was one of the cheapest if not the cheapest venue that levitation looked at and so
presumably there is also a thing here where going to Telford cost more money than any East Con has
previously and that was an old cheap venue and so going to a modern more expensive venue would
consequently cost even more money and that's a really hard tension right because I don't want
to exclude either group from the East Con and trying to resolve that tension is really difficult
as someone who does not have any physical disability and considers themselves to be
in a position of relative wealth. I want to have the conversation while simultaneously
recognizing I am not necessarily the person who is impacted by it. Discuss? I think I'd like to
pick up on the suggestion that Telford is an old venue given that it dates from a time after I started
to go into East Con so it feels like a pretty modern venue to me but also we have several sites in
the UK which are pretty well suited to East Con but which we are not using that much because they
are old and very very shabby and there are some other reasons why we're not using them.
These some of these are gradually being modernized and at the point where they modernize that's the
point where they go we are there is no way we are going to let people have our function space for
nothing because we have to get back the cost of modernization that cost very many millions of pounds
and so we are seeing that this in the discussions that people are having there that we know that we
have good modern function space will you pay for it and the places that don't are just kind of
gradually deteriorating until well-known outfalls are completely be turned into modern hotels that
we cannot afford. They tend to be listed buildings that makes it even harder to make them accessible.
I don't have a great answer here but I think we may find ourselves paying quite a bit more for
East Con and yeah well the privilege. There is a sense in which because East Con's got a lot cheaper
that's the other thing that the the cost of attending the East Con has not the membership cost has
got more expensive over time even with inflation but the hotel room cost has a pre-pandemic hotel
rooms in the UK were much cheaper on average than they had been for the for a quality of hotel
room than they had been. Certainly when I started going to conventions for many years before that
and so what we're seeing post-COVID is a kind of the hotels are trying to re-establish the order
where they where they make a lot more money selling rooms. I don't know how successful they will be
in that. I think they will be successful for a while and then they will all still have to try
and fill all their rooms by whatever mechanism they can. Yeah I think I mean you may be right if
you look to historical you know thing hotel rooms have not risen in line with inflation they dipped
and are now kind of bopping up again but it is definitely a lot more expensive than probably any
time since I started going to East Con's. That period of expensive hotel rooms is probably 20 years ago
so there are a lot of people who are not thinking oh this is rebalancing to a historical level
they're thinking wow it's really expensive. I mean I've just looked at my Glasgow hotel
and it's going to be really expensive. And that is another one where the hotels that were better
that were not as pricey those rooms sell out the first. Those rooms sell out before the other ones
right? So like if you are someone who can't commit to the convention in the near term then then you
end up in this situation where you know you either end up somewhere rubbish or somewhere expensive or
both. And that yeah I don't obviously there's not a good way of fixing that necessarily other than
I mean I guess the convention in some cases can keep some rooms back and I don't know whether
I know conventions do do this for access needs but I don't know if they do it for
sort of concessionary memberships but maybe that's something we need to start thinking about is you
know if you've got a hotel that is cheap and nice maybe you keep some of those rooms back
for people who are less financially able to go back to Allison's point. I'm not saying that
Telford at 1987 is like you know ancient but I am responding to a comment made by Allison on
last episode where about specifically like it's not modern enough to be perfect in terms of accessibility.
That is true but it's way better on accessibility than the majestic in Harrogate.
Yes! And I'm sure I keep saying this we are using enormous amounts of space and
and we may one way to make East Kong more affordable would be to have less program
way less back office functions with their own room. Fewer access rooms actually I'm afraid
East Kong this year had a quiet room and a silent room and I think that was you know presumably
that we had the space for it but now people will be going but can we have a quiet room and a silent
room and I'm like well yes but that's going to be an extra five pounds on everyone's membership
for that one thing and there are 20 things like that. I do agree there's a lot of things where we
think oh we need to put this in a small small room and we probably need to kind of think about
whether we could put them all in a big room. I mean there's some stuff for yes which you need like
a small private room people can go to but some stuff could just be like okay let's stick all of
these functions into one big room and see how it works and you know if it turns out to be a total
failure one year then we have learned something but I think we are going to going oh you need a
room for x room for y room for z and some cases like okay but if that means ruling out 10 venues
let's see how it works without them. Well and like and not not wanting to be funny but like
there are some functions that probably don't need their own room. You'd have to experiment and
one of the problems is that people don't like it when you experiment and so there's a human
cost here where if you tell people who are used to working in a certain way that they have to work
in a way that might end up being worse to see how we can save money those people will react poorly
and I'm not saying that's wrong it's entirely understandable but I don't know how you implement
some of these things without annoying and upsetting people which is something you don't
necessarily want to do to people who are doing unpaid volunteering that is also hard in its own way
but like so for instance the example I'm thinking of a lot of the work we do on news that could be
done sort of on a laptop anywhere in the convention space as long as you've got somewhere to put
your printer but then we'd have to share a printer probably with ops and ops might not enjoy us
monopolizing their printers for a couple of hours twice a day and so like is that fair on the people
who are used to volunteering in ops I don't know is there a hard question. Yeah you do want to
minimize the number of people who are in the same space as a printer that is exceeding its duty
cycle. I mean maybe maybe that means we don't do printed newsletters. I've just I had this conversation
at some length with Shana Werthen in the context of the EastCon you need to I don't want to get into
a whole kind of maybe we shouldn't have that function but that's true for quite a lot of things that we
do. I would never use news as there is an example for this because the fact is if you want a good
newsletter you need to give it a quiet space and if you don't give it a quiet space you won't get
a good newsletter but you might not want that so you know. I mean I I think I disagree as someone
who's edited newsletters I think I can happily hyper focus in a corner of the bar and it's fine
but what I will say is I think if I was going to make a list of the backroom offices we have
I think newsletter is the one that most easily comes out and the reason I'm picking it as the
example is because I know Alison will have to re-contextually some of the things she's just said in that
light because I think you can't you can't put ops in the bar you can't put green room in the bar
I mean you could get rid of the games room. Well I think we should scrap green room but I know it's
just me. Well no no no no it's the best the single the single best thing about English conventions
and Alison's like get rid of it absolutely not. No I mean that's that's absolute that's absolute
lunacy. We are using a lot of space compared to other sorts of conferences of the same size
if I was running an Eastercon again which I'm definitely not going to do I would be running into
on I you're going to have way less program streams guys which is kind of what I did last time.
I think part of the problem is that we don't have a good idea of what parts of
Eastercon people like the best but the problem is that when I think about how I would start cutting
I can see a number of places in which I know who I would be upsetting by doing that.
And it's me. Yeah well that's kind of the point of making I think I think that's that's one of the
things is that you and I have very different visions of what makes Eastercon good. I think
that's very useful in this discussion because it makes it very illustrative to be like well I would
cut this this is this and you're outraged and you're like I'd cut this this is this I'm outraged.
Don't think I would but I don't think I am outraged. I mean outrage might be a strong word but
I think that if you were going to start cutting I'd rather get rid of newsletter than ops or green
room and so it's like well I don't want to get rid of newsletter but if I was told I had to get rid
of the small rooms for confunctions that's where I'd start and then that makes me think getting rid
of the small rooms for confunctions isn't the answer. And so that might my actual I think that's why
I bring it up because I don't think the problem is that Eastercon has too many small rooms for
confunctions I think Eastercon works well as a result of that and that's hard because it limits us.
But and I guess I guess in in total the thing I come to is that where we are as a community in
terms of the venues you we're using and the prices we're charging is probably I mean it might be a
local maximum but it is probably a good compromise between all of these tensions that we have sort
of marshalled into this space where we are happy with the sorts of things we're doing and I'm not
sure whether disrupting things too much to try and find a new maximum is worthwhile if it takes us
too far away from the local maximum for too long. I guess that's my main point is that right now I
think we might be navigating these tensions the best we can without making Eastercon something very
different to what it actually is. I don't know whether you two agree with that but I certainly
I think my perception at the moment I've cut out a long silence here listeners where Alison and Liz
thought about it. Yeah no I think I think that's interesting but I was more thinking not that we
fundamentally changed the Eastercon but if there is a venue and we're like oh we're a bit squeezed
for small rooms let's try it out and see if we can cope. Yeah we are already doing that to some
extent so this Eastercon had the ops hub model model where techies run out of ops. Well actually
my top target for small rooms we didn't need to have was the gopher hole and in fact the last couple
of years that has been absorbed both that and tech having its own space have been absorbed back
into ops to a single hub so we are doing some work in the right direction there. A newsletter
runs out of a very small room and can normally run out of the one of the hotels own admin spaces
or the business hub if the hotel will let us and we have had that work a couple of times.
No and actually I'm glad you mentioned that because gopher hole is an obvious one where I
hadn't even really noticed it not been its own space. Shall we move on to picks? Who wants to pick
first? This is first on the list. Only because I wrote it down first not because I necessarily
have to go first. So my pick is a book sorry John you're going to read on my picks right?
One day. Yeah so my pick is a book which is Starling House by Alexei Harrow. I thought there was a good
chance this might end up on the Hugo Ballot I suspect it will have been bubbling under when we
get the long list and basically it is a story about a small town and a mysterious sinister haunted
house and a woman named Opal who's been raising her half brother since their mother died which
may be all connected with the sinister events in the town and the sinister house and the sinister
heir to the house who lives there. Basically it's a solid haunted house novel where it's all connected
with like the how the house has been influenced by and is influencing what happens in the town
which is kind of small town America no one has any prospects it's just a mining company which is
kind of slowly destroying the environment. I don't think it's amazingly good you must all run out
and read it but I think it is very solidly done and you get a lot about Opal who is the young woman
at the center and yeah in a kind of she could feel like you know she's led this existence where
essentially she they live in a motel she has a dead-end job she's raising her brother but it never feels
like super depressing it always feels like yes she's doing this hard thing but she's coming to
realize she does maybe have some support in this and I like their relationship with her brother who
is well smart and ahead of her and doing that kind of thing where yes I know what you've been doing
and I've been ahead of you all along obviously the house has its own secrets it's got this quite
kind of a conceit at least at the start where you get these little footnotes in the tail which are
obviously like historical footnotes so someone is reading it and putting in a footnote of like
here is the historical thing behind this thing Opal is saying in her narrative which I really
liked and at the start I was really into that because I'm like oh we're going to find out like
who's actually writing the book and then it ends up being a bit disappointing but that's really good
at the start to have this perspective of someone who is putting little comments on what the author
is author is writing almost like um unreliable narration-y yeah yeah nice I like that it's good
I like things with unreliable narratives yeah and I mean I liked I liked the 10,000
dollars of January as well I think Alex Harrow is just like a good solid writer I may not have read
the book which make me think this is like the most amazing thing but I think they are all kind of
really worth a read yeah no I really like Alex Harrow's stuff as well and I'm looking
forward to reading this one just as soon as I don't have a long list of required reading for
the podcast that I do yeah my pick um so this is um Hopeland by Ian McDonald which we mentioned
several times but which none of us have previously picked I thought this novel might be
might have been appeared on the Hugo Shatlist like expect to see it bubbling under whether
long list appears it has had near universal acclaim so Hopeland is kind of a 20 year chunk
out of the middle of a family saga you learn a bit about the past of the family and you learn
a very small about about the future well there are two families but there there is a family which is
not really a family in a traditional sense it is a loose non-geographic gathering of people who
kind of help each other out and put each other up and sort things out for things I'm not entirely
sure I believe in the Hopeland family and how it works it kind of reminded me a bit about
science fiction fandom but you absolutely never meet any of the people who totally wind you up in
that and you don't meet you know you don't meet any of the people who would be very annoying elderly
uncles in this you only kind of meet benevolent elders in Hopeland but I still loved it I loved
the idea of it you meet some of the characters you come from this family some of the other characters
come from another family that is absorbed into the Hopeland family over the course of the book
it's a near future climate change novel I think it is reasonable that a lot of science fiction
books are dealing with the kind of likely disaster of that time and and I think it is good this
doesn't entirely deal with it it just kind of is the backdrop to the action in at the heart of the
novel you in spent 23 years writing it and that is reflected in the novel because there are some
bits that were clearly written in the past and so reflects some things that are about the past I
and as somebody quite recently tried to write something set in the past and discovered it's very
very hard because your language changes quite a lot even within your own lifetime I thought that
was quite interesting so that's one of the things that happens in the novel is that the language
that is used changes as Ian was writing it I love this like I mean I don't think it's perfect because
I think it is too ambitious I think there are things like it doesn't really deal with climate change
it just kind of the epilogue to the novel kind of assumes that it's somewhat cured without ever
quite saying so in quite a strange way some of the things that happen in the middle are not entirely
realistic some of the you meet characters and I think one of the things that is very good at
is that there are a lot there are a lot of characters in this book and a lot of them are sketched very
briefly and they're nevertheless kind of jump off the page as individuals in a way that I think
lots of authors do not manage to do I am looking at you John Scalsey and I loved all of that and I
really really enjoyed reading every page of this novel and I feel I'm being slightly more defensive
of that than I might normally be because I know that one of my co-hosts really didn't like it so you
know it's been you did not finish this novel because she got too frustrated with the main characters
and I I finished it but I thought it was a triumph of ideas over characterization in in the in the
style of old-fashioned science fiction and one of the things I felt the reason it's been you did
not finish this you got very frustrated that one of the two main characters goes to Iceland
and basically tells the Icelandic people exactly how they should do all the things to be really
great and they're like oh yeah we hadn't thought of that and it's like come on come on like what
we what we doing here and the other one is that the other main character is just someone to to whom
things happen and he never really does anything he's just sort of there while things happen around
him and I found both of those characters very difficult and the book wants you to be invested in
the relationship between them but I just was not oh I was very I was very interested in both of them
so you know and and also I think I don't really think of it as being two main characters because I
think there are a lot of other characters who get almost as much screen time as either of these do
certainly yeah and I I liked all of them as well you know I thought they were all quite interesting
as well yes there are some there are some supporting characters that are interesting I think my
my goodreads review I think does a better job of saying this than than I have here in this book
but they're marred by ideas which are best ambiguous and worth worst poorly thought out there are
interesting depictions of cultures which don't often take the spotlight but they're marred by
saviour narratives in which protagonists from Britain go until natives help us to tackle their
problems and there are fascinating characters which are marred by the two perspective characters
who are deeply uninteresting. Ian McDonald's a man from Northern Ireland and he writes a novel
that is in part about a man from Northern Ireland and I'm not I'm not actually going to
criticize people from writing about characters of their own culture rather than as their
protagonists rather than inventing other ones. I think what we've done here is is reflected the
range of views on the novel which it's not and I wonder if thought that it would be a massively
divisive novel and obviously some people like some things and other people like different things
that is good because you know it would be very sad place if we all like the same things but I
did think this was really good one of the absolutely best-knocked things I've read in the last year
I have sad look I was I am even sadder that it was not on the Hugo ballot now that I've actually read
it so I went to CEX and I took with me a rock band guitar and I swapped the rock band guitar
for a copy of Dredge on PlayStation 5 and that is my pick this week. Dredge is everything I like
an interactive fiction in that it uses its time to tell a story by introducing you to various
characters all of whom clearly have knowledge that they are not sharing with you and I don't think
like the the game does not make the point that this is deliberate but like there is clearly
something happening you are washed up on the rocks of an island and they are like brilliant we
need a new fisherman please have this boat and go fish and you do this and you go around fishing
and it's a lovely game where you go on the ocean and you sort of you sort of dupe around and you
fish and then you take fish back to the shore you get money for the fish you upgrade your boat
and etc so far so so good and I must admit like I played this in his spaniel was watching me play
and she was like so um so this is this is science fiction is it I was like no I mean okay for
it but there's also whenever you're fishing at night there's a weird eye that follows you around
and then sometimes you fish up fish that have weird mutations and you take them to the fish
manga who appears to be experimenting with them oh and there's a weird red beam of light in the
sky and when it goes away people are like oh the red beam of light in the sky has gone away and
you're like right and they're like oh good it's back again and you're like I don't understand
what's happening and I haven't got to the point where I know what's happening yet so I can't
spoil it but there's clearly something going on and it kind of reminds me of welcome to night
veil in terms of vibe it's got that kind of insidious sneaking suspicion that things are not
as they seem in quite a pointed way I think quite a rye way which I'm enjoying and it's just I just
really like it and I'm a sucker for this kind of slow burn everything is not right story so so yes
I have been thoroughly enjoying it to the point where I did I sit down to play it for half an hour
and I looked up at the clock and I was like oh no it is bedtime I must now go to bed because I
have been I have been very much enjoying it so yes that is my pick um drench I get to go because
Alice is still finishing her cardamom bum I did enjoy drench I did finish it I think I came to the
end of it thinking I had done maybe a little too much kind of grinding for the payoff so I enjoyed
it but I did feel some of the fishing I kind of did as more of a background thing while I was doing
other things that did not sustain me quite through the whole plot that's fair seeing as John introduced
to Spaniards perspective on on Hopeland I will introduce my Charles perspective on drench as well
as mine I've played about I think 75% of it um based on where I am through the plot you know
it is obviously a slight spoiler for this game to say that this is on the Hugo shortlist so therefore
despite the fact this is not immediately obvious at the beginning it has some science fiction
fantasy or in this case horror elements um oh that's clear from like five minutes in though I mean
it's not really a spoiler yeah that's right it's very early on in the game you cut that kind of like
you may not want to go fishing at night but you very quickly realize that if you want to make any
money you're going to have to go fishing at night you will quickly discover that um all is not as
it seems I really enjoyed actually the the story of it but I personally when I have the because I
like games where there is a tight little gameplay loop and a bit of story but I find the actual
gameplay loop a bit tedious frankly the fishing is very basic and I would have liked to have seen
a bit of a better game in the gamey bits because I quite like the game bits of video games as well
as the story bits of video games and then I kind of started about 75% of it all at once and then I
just kind of stopped so I probably will do the rest of it at some point but um I did not finish the
game um and it wasn't because I was horrified I was just like oh no I'm not done enough of this now
my child however who is a completist of games of this kind not only not only played it obsessively
but also started a new game when they'd realized they hadn't got a maximally good fish on some one
of the unique fish so they could save scum until they got the maximally new fish in their course of
acquiring 100% of all of the fish and I'm like well oh that's a different way to play and they were
like it's a collecting game mum it's a it's a it's a game about collection and completionism and I'm
like that that may be another reason I don't like it but that slightly surprised me so if you are the
sort of person who likes grinding pointlessly in games for very for very many as a deed then I
think dredge is a game for you I think dredge does I don't see myself seriously collecting all the
fish for the same reason I have never collected all of the pokemon which is pokemon is an amazing
game the the part of pokemon I find interesting is not in fact the collecting all the pokemon aspect
it is it is all of the game around that and I think the same is probably true of dredge
a very worthy game to have on the final on the ballot I was very glad to see that
well we'll talk about this when we do the Hugo episode but I was very glad to see that we once
again have a mixture of indian and AA titles this is good and that was the orked thought
podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
you
you want to hear my latest proposal for a special episode by the way go for it we're
going to have to do I think a business meeting special once all the proposals are out to explain
what's going on and whether people should should turn up to vote for against them oh I mean you're
probably right but I don't want to the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by
kevin mccloud and competec.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will
end at the beat beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]