Hello everyone, it's John here, just to let you know there are some audio oddities on this episode
due to circumstances beyond our control. I've tried to do the best I can to make things work well,
but basically, Alison's track might sound a little different than what you're used to.
Hopefully it doesn't impede your enjoyment of our quality content. Onto the show!
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 76th episode of Octa Thought. This episode is coming
to you on the 2nd of February 2023. I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
And today we have some letters of comment for you all and the first one is Tammy Coxon who says
that she was all set to bring "If I ran the Zucon" to EasterCon for us, but you all went and bought
it instead. But Liz, I believe you have some news on that front. Yeah, so what I have is a tab open
to the page where I will buy a copy of "If they're ran the Zucon" and I just haven't got around to it.
I've got a lot of tabs open to be fair. Liz's approach to life is just to have tabs open and
hope by osmosis they will translate into action. Yeah, pretty much. No, I just keep opening tab
and thinking I should do that and then doing something else is dead and not quite getting around to it.
That makes sense. That makes sense. I have too many tabs open by which I mean one, but I am going
to action it. Is this a cue for me to send you a screenshot of all my tabs or definitely don't do
that? It would probably make me sad but you can. I can use it as chapter art.
Every so often my daughter walks by my iMac and helps press the little button that
spreads all the windows across the screen and then laughs. Unfortunately, that doesn't actually
expand all the tabs so you don't really get the full glory of why I need 32GB of RAM on my desktop.
What I like about this is that it's basically like I could use my computer slightly differently
or I could throw money at the problem and I respect that. Yeah, I mean, I feel like I'm
old enough and absolutely there are certain sorts of things I'm not about to do differently.
Fair enough. Liz doesn't have it yet but she will do when we record our filler episode probably.
Yeah, I mean if we decide we're going to do an episode based around the zucan,
ooh maybe that's foreshadowing, then I will just go and buy it.
Yes, so but thank you very much, Terry, for your kind offer. I think if it wasn't available as a PDF,
we would all enthusiastically take and carry up on on her offer but because it is available as a
PDF, we are all internet gremlins. I mean I would accept that bringing a copy to
EasterCon is spoiler alert. Not going to be useful to me either.
Liz.
Liz. It's a long way. I believe they have aircraft in the future.
Oh yes now. We had a letter of comment from a listener called Liz Batty.
Liz, do you want to read out the letter of comment from Liz?
What?
You've wrote us a letter of comment.
About the future and date.
Oh I did write your letter of comment about the future. Yes, the letter of comment to say was that
while I proudly proclaimed on last episode that I was in the year 2565, I am actually in the year
2566. No listeners noticed but it is basically like how you will habitually write 2022 for a
few months after it's become 2023. It's like that, except worse.
So when does the tie year flip over?
Well first of January.
Okay, interesting.
Yeah they have big big big parties. Bangkok is one of the cities that we go to at the
Zoom New Year party.
Very nice.
Because there's always lots of stuff going on.
It's fireworks basically yeah.
We also had some letters of comment from actual listeners.
We also heard from Christopher J Garcia.
Yay.
He sent us a lock on episode 72-ish.
Yep that's right, correct. Hold on Chris.
I mean it is 72-ish.
That is correct. If you said it was episode 72 you would have been wrong.
Yeah and it also says they have haggis in a can.
It's good. It's good stuff.
I assume it's vegetarian haggis in a can.
I don't know if it's vegetarian haggis in a can.
It's got to be right because they're not allowed to meet you on because of the lungs.
Well I think they are. They're just not allowed.
It's not the lungs, it's the brains.
And I think you can get haggis in American now.
It's just not necessarily made to a traditional Scottish recipe.
We're probably going into too much haggis at this point.
One of my pals who is in California posted a picture of her child holding any
enormous haggis which wasn't enormous meat haggis.
It may also be the brains but it is definitely the lungs.
Lungs are illegal to eat in the United States of America.
So anyway the point is that they're using different bits of sheep.
I think British haggis may no longer have brains in this as well.
Yeah I don't think it does.
Yes I did it for it.
Because I don't eat brain.
Possibly more timely.
Chris also mentioned that they were putting out another issue of
journey planet about Chinese science fiction.
Time to coincide with the Chinese New Year.
Which is now out so we can link to that in the show notes.
That is the second part of the special on China.
With a ton of interesting looking interviews and articles.
Nice.
Chris also says that he thinks there should be a smoughish RPG system based off gurps.
And words cannot adequately express how much I disagree with that statement.
So I'm not going to try but we can hash it out at a convention Chris.
I feel like that's a combat.
Next time you should put these things on a little list.
The next time you interview Chris for the podcast.
We should actually have these topics as just have like topics in a barrel that we can pick
out and talk about.
It would be dreadfully unfair to ask Chris about things he said in the past.
And Chris also says he brought a palette of board games.
Yes.
But and it was rubbish.
I don't think my palette of board games would.
Oh I mean my palette of board games probably would have been rubbish but it wouldn't necessarily be.
That's I'm still a bit sad about the palette of board games.
I've put it down as my when I have a future organized house so that I have like an entire
spare room in which I could put a palette of board games for for for sifting and managing.
Then then maybe I will.
But obviously if I hadn't in to spare room and I started buying things like a palletons
a bookcase I soon would not have an entire spare room.
I'd have a room full of junk again.
So you know.
I wasn't going to say that.
I know also like.
So I'm glad someone else did.
We also heard from Erwin Hirsch who asks whether Alison is moved house.
Oh I haven't moved test but for shadowing I've been thinking a lot about the process of
getting ready for the later part of your life over the last few weeks.
And one of the things it struck me that is that at some point we're going to want to move
house and when we do that we are not going to want to have a house full of rubbish that we don't
use. We are trying to go through everything in our house keeping only the things that we need,
use or love and getting rid of everything else.
And when things don't satisfy one of those three categories I'm looking at them and going
why am I keeping this?
Also for shadowing.
And also I would strongly recommend that a time when you absolutely don't have to move
anytime in the next few years is a great time to do that because you wait till the time when
you are moving really soon.
You will do it much more effectively but it will also be way more stressful.
Whereas it's not really stressful at all if you just do it bit by bit as you do it a lot.
I'll let you know.
And we've played about one percent of the rubbish in our house so far.
There's a lot more to do.
Yeah I think that's the thing.
I was going to say no it's quite good to have some like a time deadline to focus the mind
but I also think I have something like 10% of the amount of stuff you do so maybe less.
Oh we should have a stuff off.
That could be a filler episode.
We're all on our phones and we all just count things like one thing to two things.
I have way more stuff than either of you pretty sure but I also have way less stuff than some
people I know.
Oh yeah yeah yeah yeah I'm just saying you know it's a lot more feasible to do everything and
they're like oh I'm moving in three months I better get rid of a bunch of stuff when you have
only 10% of the stuff.
Oh I probably had like 20% of the stuff and I have 10% of the stuff and it's creeping slowly upwards again.
Well the longer you live in the same house the more stuff you can be like.
Yeah that is fair.
And then finally we heard from Claire Breiley of Croydon who basically said
"The legend that is Claire Breiley says her local bar."
Says that the poem by Sandra was spectacular and the only things that were bad about it were
me and Alison which is fair.
Basically she says it could only have been improved by full-on performance accents from
Alison and John and that that is true I did not do that I just tried to read it out.
Basically I shot for acceptable rather than failing to achieve amazingness.
I think Alison did better than me.
I did go for what I went for was an accent that had some of the rhythms of Stanley Holloway without
actually trying to do that in a way that would come over as a caricature so I don't know whether
I managed it or not but anyway.
I can't do accents.
I feel my enjoyment would not have been improved by having you do comedy accents I'm just going to say.
Well Liz and Liz is actually like extremely familiar with my comedy accents on account of how
I used to use them when we played "I'll come home with a card game together" so
Liz is familiar with the level to which they enhance your experience or not.
*laughs*
So we'd like to introduce you all to our regular segment of "Why is the Chengdu World concert a shower?"
Is that all we have to say about Chengdu?
For this week.
There have been various reporting, I think Falstam and somebody has done some sterling work
and Liz posted the images of the proposed museum in our chat.
Liz do you want to talk about this first?
I can try and give an overview.
So essentially we were saying last week how you know the Chengdu Worldcon had a few things they
needed to do and it didn't appear that there had been any updates for ages and the website wasn't
really very good and you could join and all this.
Well they've solved at least one of these problems and they've solved it by entirely changing
the date of the Worldcon and the site where the Worldcon will be held.
Hey!
So they sort of announced which I would just say solves the problem of the fact that site selection
should open soon because that is tied to the date of the Worldcon and therefore it will now open
and close later than originally intended.
But basically they sort of just put out like an announcement on Twitter saying by the way the
Worldcon will now be in October the 18th of 22nd at the Chengdu Science Fiction Museum in
Jingruong Lake, PD District Chengdu and we'll put some links to the pictures in the show notes but
it looks like a fantastic building except that I have realized that all the fantastic building
pictures are like those nice 3D renderings you get of buildings because they when they're like in
the planning stages and that's because the new Chengdu Science Fiction Museum has not yet finished
being built.
On the other hand it does look like a spaceship I mean it looks amazing so if it actually looks
like that in real life it will look well cool and possibly be one of the like the coolest venues
for a Worldcon especially if it is like all in that one place.
Narrator it wouldn't.
So I have been told that the Chinese are extremely good at getting buildings up fast.
I think it is interesting to see whether they will be able to achieve this.
I mean so it'll be interesting because you know of course the the picture of the building has all
the kind of landscaping and foliage back around the building which you know may not
necessarily be all completely finished but I suspect if the building does not have
anything like it looks on the renderings it will be nice.
However does this mean it was a good idea to move the date and site?
Well I guess if you're going to go to this new site and it's not actually built yet then you
have to change the date but there's a further post on file 770 who've been doing a load of
reporting on this so we're going to link to all their reporting where it sounds like it's not
really clear kind of why this decision was made or who made this decision or kind of who in China
is running things and so I think there's a bit of sort of general unhappiness there because
this does I think move it out of the holidays for university students and so university students
will have a much harder time arriving.
So they announced that the dates and the site would be changed to this shiny new place.
I did manage to find it on Google Maps eventually although it uh I will confess it took me a little
while because I was using Google Maps and it turns out Google Maps is not very good in China and so
if you didn't turn on the satellite view it just had some roads and then I turned on the satellite
view and I think I found like a man-made lake where it is.
I looked at a quick look at the hotels nearby and they do look you know super nice and the rates were
super affordable.
On the other hand it's not very clear because I don't know enough about the site how you get from
the science fiction museum to the hotels and so on.
I'm hoping there'll be like a lot more information put out.
This is the sort of time when you want people to be planning ahead if they're going to come to your
convention.
That is currently difficult because China just reopened, most of the flights haven't restarted.
I don't think it's actually possible to get a visa yet for tourism but if any of that does restart
and they'd like people to go they probably do need to be saying things like this is where the
hotel is.
This is where the site actually is on a map.
This is how you will get to between them.
This is how you apply for a visa and whatever.
If you need letters to be provided this is what we can do etc etc.
Probably some of this the basic stuff that you would expect to be ready to go with your new site
information is not there yet.
So we'll see.
And they also announced that they would be opening Hugo Award nominations soon
and that you need to be a member of Chengdu Wokan as a WISFIS member in order to nominate if
you're not already a member or a member of Shai Kahn.
You can apparently now purchase a WISFIS member through their website with a credit card.
We have not tried this because we all have memberships already but it has been verified by
a friend of ours on Discord that you can apparently do this.
This is not reusable information because if you haven't already joined by the time you listen to
this podcast it will be too late to join and nominate but you will still be able to join and
vote.
Yes.
I think it's particularly sad that students may not be able to go as it's the students who
were responsible for getting the WorldCom for China.
They really mobilized all the students, all the students, science fiction club
and all the universities to get the vote out that was part of what they did.
And they had lots of pictures on their website of like student clubs in different states.
They bring the WorldCom to China and stuff like that and talking about how much, how excited they
were to be going.
So I think that's particularly sad.
When it's interesting because last week we talked about how China can get the WorldCom
wherever they, whenever they want.
And what's really interesting is by doing this, the way they did that was by mobilizing their
student vote.
And the students like from what we can tell from peering into the Chinese internet,
the students seem to be really really unhappy with this which is entirely
understandable because it basically massively disenfranchises them because many of them won't
be able to attend now, both from the perspective of it's at the wrong time of year for them and
the location is much harder to get to.
And so it's like, well, I don't understand, it just seems like a giant own goal from that
perspective because, yeah, I don't know why you'd annoy the people who got you where you were.
It's very strange because the tempting thing with this is to assume that they've done it for
reasons that make sense to Chinese attendees but don't make sense to us.
But like everything we're seeing from people who are Chinese attendees is also very annoyed.
Well, I think it probably makes sense to the Chinese government and to support there
and the Chengdu tourist board.
And we know that the Chengdu tourist board was a big part of, so quite a lot of people involved
in the bid were people who worked full time in the Chengdu tourist board or equivalent thereof,
which is kind of a bit of government.
And I don't pretend to know anything about how the Chinese government works.
But there's clearly there is something which is semi-official about this team in a way that you
wouldn't see normally for a well-come.
But it could be even simpler.
I mean, it could be that they had a plan to use a particular venue,
which maybe would be quite expensive.
If they're having difficulty getting sponsorship or indeed many members,
and this venue was cheaper or they could do them a good deal because it's a great
cross promotion with the science fiction museum, maybe kind of for financial reasons,
they had to go for it.
I mean, I think the thing is we don't really know and we probably will never find out,
except, you know, maybe in five years time a smuff con, you know, we'll find it all out on
a panel or in the bar.
But yeah, there could be lots of reasons.
It's just since we don't know, we kind of are free to make up any reason we like.
So it doesn't seem to have been a choice made because the attendees wanted them to.
So we know at least that there is something funky going on somewhere,
because it's not like DC where they were like, we can have it in August,
but if we move to December, we might be able to have more of an in-person convention
and like they asked the members.
Like it definitely isn't coming from the members.
Oh yeah, it's definitely not a case, you know, like for, you know, DC did,
I think everything they could where they went and surveyed the members and said,
okay, what difference would this make to you?
You know, what would you like to say?
But I think it's also, you know, just because of the various translation barriers,
we're probably only ever hearing from a subset of the membership.
And I think nearly everything that Will Kahn does,
you'll be able to find a subset of the membership who disliked the decision.
I'm sure, speaking, you'll be able to find a subset of the opt-of-for team
who disliked the decisions, you know.
Yes, that may be true.
But yeah, it does seem like, you know, they had a lot of, you know,
it is a big issue if you had a lot of support from students who essentially have invested a bunch
of money in and get themselves to get themselves set up for voting at discount
and now can't attend.
And I don't know if you can transfer a Chengdu membership,
but we know you can't transfer Wispers memberships anymore, right?
They probably can't transfer their membership to someone else and recoup much of the cost.
Yeah, I mean, it is worth noting that you can't transfer a Wispers membership,
but you also can't buy a membership that doesn't include Wispers membership,
except of course, you can for Chengdu.
So if Chengdu wanted to, they'd just do it and hang it all,
which is like, I do, like, which is not necessarily me criticising Chengdu,
is a observation of the facts of how Chengdu and the Wispers constitution are so far into intersecting.
While we are talking about memberships, though,
so the Chinese students have attending memberships of the WorldCom
because they were supporting and voting members of Discon.
Now, although I don't think there's any doubt about whether they were individual voters,
I think it's very clear that they were, which is partly why they're angry at.
I'm not convinced they paid for their memberships.
I think that was all coming from a central block of money,
which as we know, the Wispers rules do not forbid.
So they may be upset that they have their attending memberships and may not be able to use them,
but I don't think they necessarily pay for them or many of them pay for them.
So, you know, I want to talk a little bit about the architecture.
This is a very exciting statement building.
You know, it's indeed building. There aren't that many of them still.
It does look as if it's being built just for the WorldCom.
So just kind of as a prestige building that is kicked off by the WorldCom
in the way that you might get for a World's Fair or the Great Exhibition or something like that.
This is pretty exciting stuff for the WorldCom to be involved in.
It's kind of strange and not the sorts of things we normally do.
Normally we are in hotels that have been around for a very long time,
or conference centers, where we are just one visitor amongst many.
I think that's quite strange.
I mean, when you say "built for the WorldCom", you mean it exists and it will host a WorldCom
as one of its first events.
No, I don't think so. I think it has been built for the WorldCom.
Because they've named the buildings after Wispersmarks.
So no, I think it's much closer to the Olympic Park mode than it is to a...
I mean, I might be wrong.
Yeah, I think this is an Olympic Park model.
Where do we get that information from?
Because I think if there's something written in Chinese and we translate it
and it says Hugo Awards Theatre, it doesn't necessarily mean the theatre
is being named for the Hugo Awards.
That makes sense.
The fact that the mock-up of the building in one of the File 770 awards
has a massive sign on the side saying Hugo Award.
Yeah.
Oh, I text your daily, this is.
Yeah, but if I go to a convention, it's got usually, you know,
going to have a great big sign up and things.
So I don't know.
I think it would be interesting to see what we get.
But they never...
I've never been to a convention where they've taken down the sign that says
Excel and replaced it with a sign that says Hugo Awards.
I've been to one where they've got a banner, but this doesn't look like a banner.
This looks like it's on the building.
Yeah, I think...
I don't know.
I think we're reading a lot into a very small thing on the building,
which could potentially be temporary signage for the WorldCom.
So I don't know if this is going to be actually branded after WorldCom service mark.
Sorry, it was for service mucks.
Certainly, if I was going to bet money, and I'm not,
but if I was going to bet money, the way it is described does not seem like it's temporary.
And it may be, it may be that every time this comes up and all of the renderings
are just, I'm getting the wrong end of the stick,
but all of the text and all of the renderings are very much designed
to get me to pull that end of that stick.
And it might be that that isn't what they're doing.
But I would quite like to know that for sure.
And if they are doing it, it is a giant enough problem
that I feel like me stay in my opposition to it early and often is probably good.
I absolutely do not think they should be using these marks in this way.
And if it's not clear, I think it's quite cool.
I think it's quite cool.
And I think you could probably do it in a way that did not use the mark.
You should work with the Mark Protection Committee to find a way of saying,
"Oh, this is a building that has been created to hold the world con,
and then will go on to be Chengdu's Science Fiction Museum."
I think that's completely cool.
And they should find a way with the Mark Protection Committee
to celebrate the fact that it held the world con as its first event,
provided it's still not a building site, which of course it might be.
Great.
I think that if the Chinese government or the Chengdu tourist board
or whoever has made this decision has basically decided to appropriate our marks
in order to drive tourism to the area that is crappy.
And I think if it was not, I think if it was a US state doing this,
you'd be up in arms.
So I think that is a bit of a double standard.
I think, no, I think I could 100% get behind it.
The trick is finding marks right.
So you basically say it's the 2023 World Science Fiction Convention building,
like the Royal Festival Hall.
Well, no, because China is currently not doing it by asking permission.
I tell them to get on to the Mark Protection Committee,
which I think they should be doing.
Don't get me wrong.
I'm sure they are.
I'm not sure they are.
Wish not.
If you're on the Mark Protection Committee, you should get in touch.
The Mark Protection Committee learned about this when it was released in Fall 770.
I know this for a fact.
Well, I think everyone learned about this when it was released in Fall 770.
Yes.
And so this partly links to the whole thing about copyright in China.
Which is quite a big deal.
And eventually, eventually, people probably get sorted out,
but hasn't been yet, which is that there really isn't any.
So that makes everything, you know, we talk about our understanding of
intellectual property and property marks and Chinese artists and designers and manufacturers.
And everybody really is like, well, that's very interesting,
but that's not how we do it in China.
I hope Liz is right and I'm reading too much into it.
I just at the moment, it doesn't seem like there's any,
I don't know, everything seems to be leaning in the same direction.
Yeah, that also means, of course, that
I'm locked, so to apply in China because China has no copyright law in the way that you think of it.
It feels like it's a thing that's certainly worth the Mark Protection Committee going,
hang on, I did you think about talking to us, but I also wonder, you know,
we have said how like, it looks amazing in the rendering,
but the rendering also seems to have drones everywhere shooting the
material blue glow into the sky.
You know, I wonder if the person who is in charge of making some nice 3D models
got excited and looked at a website.
I think it's worth like doing that, but maybe waiting to see what it actually does look like
when it's constructed and seeing.
If they constructed without on it, that's staying there.
The point is to make sure that our opinions on this are known before that point, not after.
Oh, I just don't think that'll make any difference, so.
Well, maybe not.
I mean, but nothing we, I mean, in that case, we might as well wrap the podcast up, right?
Because we're just talking, I don't have any power.
I don't have like a link to the Communist Party to register my complaints.
We're just talking about our opinions.
It's, let's not pull on the thread off, does it matter what we think?
I know, I know, I know, but I'm saying, you know, I don't really see whether, you know,
if we disagree with it now, or if we disagree with it in eight months time,
I don't think it'll make really a lot of difference.
I just think we haven't really seen what it's actually going to look like,
and it's worth investigating.
I'm not too fussed about some 3D renderings at this point.
I mean, we started this segment saying, you know, well, the rendering's look very nice,
but, you know, the actual museum may look completely not like that when we get there.
I think they look like us as renderings of a building, and my experience is that
the actual building in real life really, really matches the artist's pictures in beautiful 3D
renderings.
But the main structure has been topped out.
It looks like it might happen.
That looks like...
Oh, it could, like, yeah, no, it could well.
How many months has worked?
Not that... eight months?
Nine months.
So, that's a segue onto Alison's guff trip.
It is, it is.
So, last time you shared news of your guff trip with us, Alison,
you were planning to go after King Charles the Third's Coronation,
but that changed, and then Chengdu changed.
It was, I was trying to free the country the day after the coronation,
because the Australian nap con is happening.
I understand.
It still doesn't have anything that you could describe as a website,
but I believe that the nap con is,
conflicts will be happening in person from 29th of September, first of October,
I think, in the dates.
And we've had some confirmation of that from people.
And so, as there is an Australian national convention happening this year in Australia,
I feel like my guff trip needs to go inside with it.
So, that is what we are currently planning.
I'm still doing the previous plan, which is to fly to Perth,
travel west to east across Australia, go to the Lacon,
then go to New Zealand, visit at least Wellington and probably also Auckland,
and then fly home.
But it is not impossible that I could fly home via Chengdu for the Worldcon,
which is 18th, 22nd of October.
So, we're thinking about it.
And I think all the things that Liz has said about not actually having the ability
to book flights, it not being anywhere very convenient even in Chengdu,
it being impossible to get visas and so on,
probably will put pages this scheme because I probably will want to have my flights booked
before those things become clear.
But I might just book some of the other flights and leave it open.
I don't know.
I am getting help with flight booking from Clare Brawley,
who is very good at flight booking because flight booking gives me the most hideous
heebie-jeebies of anxiety.
And I am very worried that about the whole business of booking a complicated
itinerary, it seems impossible to me.
But you know, so theoretically, I could go to China on my
duff trip, which would be kind of wild.
But yeah, if not, I'd like to come to Bangkok, please Liz and see you.
Well, if I want to go to China.
Oh, Liz, are you going to China?
I mean, probably not.
But again, it's like one of those things where currently it is impossible to plan.
And so I can say, no, I'm not going.
It's impossible to plan.
If it becomes suddenly possible, then I might have to rethink it,
depending on whether we actually see a picture of the building or whether it looked cool.
No, I mean, it very much depends, doesn't it?
I mean, I suspect, just for this, has benefited that there is absolutely no sensible
routing from the UK to Australia, which goes directly via Chengdu.
You'll have to do it as a side trip anyway.
Yeah, I suspect it won't be part unless you want to book a trip with a kind of
wobbly date or with a massive layout of somewhere.
I don't think it will work, but I guess it's theoretically possible.
So then it's time for Bangkok instead.
Yeah, it is a possible stopover.
Again, it may not be the most sensible stopover given current, you know,
state of the flights in the world and so on.
So I think you'll have to see.
There's you two reasonable.
Yeah, so my decisions get slightly different here, because although, obviously,
I have a duty to spend the guff money carefully.
It is the guff money and it's the sort of thing that might be quite exciting for the
fanf... you know, so it's an exciting opportunity for the fanfants.
So it's not ludicrous.
To segue from guff to talking more generally about fanfants,
in 2007, there was a one-off fanfant that sent Chris O'Shea to the Worldcon in Japan.
Does anyone know if there is a Chinese equivalent being planned for 2023?
I have not heard anything about one.
I think it would be a lovely idea.
I'm not personally going to get involved in it for reasons.
That's fair, because it's a lot of effort and you've got another fanfant to administer and run and dig do.
And I'm on the East Concomacy, which is the exact time when you would want to get this ready.
And have my life been citing this year?
So, you know...
That, yeah, no, those are all very fair comments.
So I think it would be a lovely idea.
If you're out there in podcast land and you don't have enough
fanak at the moment, then this would be a great thing to set up.
Also, Chris O'Shea, where's your trip report?
Just saying.
I guess it's a nice idea, but I think you will not meet with great enthusiasm and also
like it's again very difficult to plan things when you don't know who will actually be able to go.
So I suspect there's not going to happen.
No, yeah, I mean, I'm not saying.
Yeah, I just say, I think even if you aren't used to asking about running it, I will, you know,
get some, you know, try and take the general temperature of fandom for, you know, giving money for that.
They might be like, eh, nah.
Maybe then we could have the fanfant theatre.
Is that a trademark?
No, fanfants you can do whatever you like with.
Right, so we don't have any trademarks.
I mean, there's customer practice.
So you have the TAF room and the Gough room and the Dough room.
The Gough room would be very smelly.
Wouldn't it all be a confusing way to name like your function rooms?
Okay, fix fix. Do you want to go first, John?
Yeah, I'm very rarely go first. This is a treat.
About probably two years ago or so, I started trying to watch a movie every week with my
darling wife because I'm not actually very good at wanting to watch movies.
And my wife very much loves movies.
And so I was like, ah, how I kill you need to make an effort and watch more movies.
And so I've been watching a movie a week.
Yeah, like I say, for probably about the last two or three years.
And that's been very good.
And obviously at the end of December, beginning of January, you start watching the movies.
You didn't watch from the previous year that you think might be on the Hugo Ballot and other things.
And so with a view to this, we watched Pray.
Pray is the latest entry in the Predator franchise.
And it is really good.
It is a movie which understands what made the first Predator a good movie,
which is lovely.
The other thing it does very interestingly is it twists the narrative.
So in the original, it's Arnold Schwarzenegger and Carl Weathers.
It's kind of good, but it's kind of very, it's a very surface level film.
There's the alien and there's two very burly men and the burly men have guns.
And let's see what happens.
This one is a native American woman who wants to be seen as a hunter by her tribe.
And she is the kind of main protagonist of the movie.
And so it kind of uses all the things the original Predator did very well.
But it kind of layers on top of that a commentary about colonization and about
sort of the hunter's relationship to the Pray.
And it's very interesting in that sense in a way that I don't think the original movie is.
And so I actually think this is probably better than the original Predator by quite a way.
I really enjoyed it.
I thought it was very, very good.
And yeah, I highly enjoyed watching it.
I would recommend it.
It is on Disney Plus.
Probably not for Liz, but for most of our listeners.
No, it isn't Disney Plus for me.
Well, it's on Hotstar Disney.
It's just a very tight, just a very tight movie.
Everything, everything was there because it needed to be there for something to happen.
And that was, I like that kind of movie.
I'm going to do a sticky second pick.
We also watched last night Invasion of the Body Snatchers,
which is a movie from 1956.
Googles.
Did you like it?
Yes, it's Bloody Brilliant.
I don't know if anyone here has seen Invasion of the Body Snatchers.
But yeah, no, it's really, really good.
Firstly, it has more than one woman in, and I don't just mean two women.
Like there's loads of them.
Admittedly, I don't think it passes the Bechtel test, but it was 1956.
So, but it's kind of, it's just incredibly tense.
And all of the characters do things that you can imagine those characters might do in that situation.
And like, it's just so good.
And very much better than a lot of movies I've seen from
the list of classic genre movies we are working our way down.
This one really holds up.
So I enjoyed it greatly.
That's really good.
Films.
Yeah, films are good.
So, I'll be putting prey on my list for the hugos.
Yeah, we are going to talk about the things we're putting on our hugo list.
Some point, but not this week.
Nope.
All right.
Liz, do you want to go next?
Um, I don't know if I really have a pic.
Should we just let you have two?
So is that not in the spirit of things?
That's it.
I mean, should we just go with John's second pic as being a pic?
What I should have done is picked for you and made you talk about
invasion of the body snatches, having potentially not seen it or not seen it recently.
Yeah, that would have been quite funny because you have indeed not seen it.
It's really good, Liz.
I highly recommend.
I feel like I saw it about 35 years ago,
but I was thinking about another film I saw about 35 years ago.
And I could literally remember two things about it, which was that
it had a submarine and somebody had a beard.
Home from red October.
Home from red October?
Correct.
This could be a game show at a convention.
People give clues to movies using like the least information they possibly can.
I mean, it is one of those games where you give the least information you possibly can,
and you get points for everyone who gets it right.
But you lose points if everyone gets it right or whatever.
Dixit, which has the mechanic where if nobody gets it, you don't do well.
And if everybody gets it, you don't do well, you have to be somewhere in the middle.
Have you played Dixit, Liz?
I have played Dixit, I think.
One.
It's not a lot.
Someone invented a version of this that's like the Elon Musk game,
where you're all trying to like come up with an invention and you all know what it is.
I have to find this, but there was definitely like an Elon Musk game that was very funny
that someone invented on Twitter.
Hang on.
I'm pretty sure I've got it on my computer somewhere.
Put it on Discord somewhere, let's make them find it.
Sadly, there's a lot of things for Elon Musk being rubbish.
That probably segues quite nicely into her.
So my pick.
So I have to say this in a way that's not going to generate a vast number of
sellers.
Don't write, guys.
My mother died last week.
So, and this has kind of been in train for a little while.
So I've had a bit of a torrid time so far into 23, but hopefully it will start to get better now.
And one of the things I've done to deal with this is engage in a lot of
sorting behavior and craft projects and things of that kind.
And I have discovered prints and play games and they're amazing.
Who knew?
And it turns out that you, so the idea is that people who want to sell the games cheaply
or who are prototyping games that might not be in a finished form,
or who just like to do a lot of games far more than you could ever ship through real publishers,
like to release print and play games, either for free or for bobbins.
And then you at home cut them and stick them out and stick them together and play your games.
And it turns out I really like them.
I like both, I like two different sorts of these.
I like the ones that you, actually, if you're me, have to print anything at all,
because you can play them entirely on your iPad, because they are designed as kind of
rolling writers in a typical game where you roll dice and then mark things off on a
game sheet, having rolled them.
And I have played dozens of these and some of them are amazing.
And some of them are terrible.
And a lot of them are kind of somewhere in the middle.
And then you also get games where you do actually have to cut out and stick together
stuff. And it turns out that I really like that kind of cutting out stuff.
There's a rabbit hole here.
Many, I think rabbit hole is a small thing.
They're kind of like great big kangaroo holes, where you have these,
you can spend an enormous amount of money printing and cutting out and making decks of cards,
where you work out how to make them as close as possible to real cards.
If this is you, then you probably just need to buy ball games.
But what I'm doing at the moment is making fairly cheap sets of printed play games,
and then saying, well, if I play them a certain number of times,
I will then go and buy the actual box set.
Well, some games I really like.
I like a game called Polyhedral Park Planner, which I think John recommended to me,
which is a game where you...
I did.
You have a...
There is a convention happening in your city.
Your Chengdu, say, and you have been charged with making a park that has an extremely beautiful,
I don't know, convention hotel in the middle of it, and you have to put other park elements
around your game.
And I like this one because it is a sort of game where you can have
numerous players, and they all play with exactly the same board and exactly the same dice rolls,
and nevertheless make completely different games and parks out of it.
And then you will compare your parks at the end and go,
"Ooh, that's interesting." And also, "Ooh, Jonathan is one because Jonathan is better at working out
how to do this than everybody else or whatever."
And for those ones, you don't even have to have friends because you can put the die rolls in a
list behind a spoiler tag on a website, and then people can go and all play the same one and
compare them.
So, you know, all you could just play on your own because there are solo rules, and this is great.
And another game I really like is in this one, is one called Chronicles of Stampedeo, where
somebody on the website is procedurally generating a dungeon for you to explore every day.
And there's a little bit of legacy because some of the things that you do on one day
will have an effect on the following day, which is, I mean, quite like even more of that.
I kind of look at that game and go, "Ooh, you could really lean into that much more with a roguelike
that it's a board game or it's a rolling right, but you could actually have lots of legacy material
working on the website.
There's nobody's making any money, so who knows?
There's only so much you can do without making money.
And then in the print and plays, another game John recommended in a very thoughtful way
is a solo journaling role-playing game, which is called Why the F Star, Star, Star,
did they keep this? Where you journal and develop a story of why your imaginary relative
kept a load of junk in the house.
And that's cutting a bit close to the bone at the moment, but it's still a very interesting game.
And today I discovered that they've got a competition,
"Borgame Geek", which is a website full of board games, has a competition at the moment
for in-hand games that I don't know, I understand that this tabletop gaming covers both
games, role-playing games and board games, and even some sterility games like Caram and things like that.
And those games are all played on tables, but in-hand games don't even need a table,
and I'm not sure their technique is covered, but anyway, so I've now tried playing it,
cutting up and making in-hand games, which can actually play E.G. in the car, if you're stuck on a
very long and boring car journey. You can be making and playing little games, and this one is called
Galdor's Grip, which I think is a great name for a game that you play in your hand all of the time.
I didn't want to pick, I mentioned some particular car, but this really is a pick about how the
entire hobby is amazing, and if you are a complete cheapskate, you do not need to spend any money
at all, apart from obviously on your iPad Pro and Apple Pencil. Obviously it supports more gamers,
so you can often buy these games for the price of a cup of coffee, some of them are demos
for games that you can actually go and buy, and this is a good way of finding out and learning
a lot about what sorts of games you like, because if you play a load of different sorts of game
genres for not very much money and in not very much time, it's very easy to work out what sorts
of things you like and what sorts of things you do not like. Print-of-play games, they're awesome.
I would just like to note that I suggested that game before Alison's mother died. I didn't hear
the news and be like, "This journey game is for you." To be fair, he suggested that game
while we were pet clearing out my parents' house, so you know. Yeah, well that I think is just
well alright, Ferra. Yeah, but you're also clearing out your own house, so yeah, and I'm also clearing
out my own house. I want everything in my house to be something that somebody could pick up and go,
"Oh, I know exactly why there are 38 Prince and Play games in little jiffy bags here, it's because
Mum went through this really difficult patch after her own mother died and she just made a
Prince and Play game every day for a bump and then stopped. Now I'm just wondering, "Are you going to
kick these forever or are you actually going through them and getting rid of the ones you
pin out and stick together and realise you don't actually like very much or will not play again?"
I haven't yet, but what I'm going to do is say, "Here's like a batch," right, and compared with big box
games, I have to, that was a visual clue, sorry for everybody, on the odd cast, but I'm typically
putting them into a A6 size bag and that's enough for like a deck of cards and the rules and a
sticky label and they don't take up very much space. One of the things that's actually discouraged me
from giving some of these game designers money is that I have my tiny little Prince and Play game
and I go, "Oh, but there's a box game of this," and then I look at the size of the box game and I go,
"Oh, why are they not selling me a game in a box?" I mean, I know the game economics are really
complicated, but I do like tiny games. You're much more likely to sell your game if it's small in general.
That's fair. I mean, Prince and Play games are a good.
No, no, no, some of them are excitable.
Oh, well that's true.
I think we should clear here. I've played some absolutely appalling games, really
hardly function of games in it, but that's, I still quite like it. I like a lot of
bad hobby where you can just play loads and loads and loads of different games.
It's like listening to music, some of the music you listen to will be terrible as well if you
listen to lots of different music, but it doesn't mean that listening to lots of different music isn't
fun. And also there's somewhere, there's even one where I've paid money for. I'm not going to name
it, but every time I look at the files and think about the amount of work that would have to be done
to actually get it to the point where I understood the rule set and was playing it.
I go, oh no, maybe I could just play a really short one instead.
I think I might be wrong, Liz. I found Steve Dee's game from 2018, which is called Elon Musk's
iPod submarine, where one player secretly writes down a terrible problem the world is facing
and they have to sum it up in six worlds or left. You write this problem on all the pieces of paper
except one and on the one that you don't write on, you just write Elon Musk. And then you put all
the pieces of the paper in a hat and each player draws one randomly, and then every player has to
pitch their two noun solution to the problem. And so Elon Musk has to basically pitch two nouns
without knowing what the problem is. And you've got to try and work out who Elon Musk is
because of iPod submarine. I mean, it's very similar to the game, the chameleon and like other
folk games. But I think I would, I would play that game. I'll put a link to iPod submarine in the
show notes. I think it was iPod submarine that I was thinking of, or someone's done a variation on
iPod submarine where it's not maybe the world's problems but an invention for something you have
to come up with. But yeah, I think it was very similar to that. Like one person is kind of hoping
that no one realizes you're just saying random words put together. And yeah, it's that like,
you know, you need at least one person to not get it to get the points kind of aspect.
Yeah. Yeah, it was the, it was definitely the, the iPod submarine game I was thinking of.
That was the Oct Thought Podcast. And it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me. And it's goodbye from me.
[Music]
Well, because guff means far, Alison.
That's the episode title. Brilliant.
I'm amazed you've not used that before, actually. I was, I thought you should go
for it. Let's not pull on the thread if it doesn't matter what we think.
I mean, I just, I don't, I mean, uh, it's tricky to, uh, really, you know,
kind of keep it quiet. Um, yeah, maybe I'm just more apathetic about anything having meaning.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod
and Comfatec.com used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.
Keep.