I mean, I think Liz gets hangry before I have to be at the cricket, so we're good.
Probably not, because it's 3pm.
Oh no!
She's already eaten.
I will just get angry, if that helps.
Well, I'm glad I'd started recording before you said that, Liz.
Hello everyone, and welcome to the very 140th episode of Octothorpe, a podcast for science
fiction and science fiction fandom, which is wending its merry way to you on the 31st
of July 2025.
I'm Jon Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
We have not got many letters of comment.
Lots of people said Tammy was great.
It's because Tammy talked a lot of sense, and it is also the summer of fun.
Summer of fun!
Tommy Ferguson was one of the people, there were many people who said Tammy were great, I'm
not going to list them all, but Tommy says that Tammy was very entertaining and knowledgeable,
like our good selves.
and says he has a real blind spot on the WUSFUS and the business meeting.
To him it is interminably tedious and not his thing.
But he's glad that we talk about, he says he's glad that people he's met or know of and trust
are taking that stuff seriously so he doesn't have to.
So yes, that is a service we aim to provide, so I'm glad it works out.
If you find the business meeting dull and tedious, well, we've got a great episode for you.
Summer of fun!
Sorry, Alison is eating an enormous croissant.
Yeah, she is.
It looks good.
It does look good.
It's got almonds on.
This will shock the listener.
Almond shocked her teen.
It's very good.
He also says,
The discussion of the retro Hugos and new Hugo categories piqued his interest.
What's the point?
Is the point to get works more visible to people by them, or is it to reward the creators for
excellent work?
And I think that's an interesting one, right?
Like, is the idea to raise awareness of these things to voters?
Is the idea to make more money for the creators?
Is the idea to reward the creator?
I think they're all interlinked.
But it's an interesting thing to think about, I think.
Certainly, one of the things with the Clark Award is that you know that whichever book wins
the Clark Award will see a bump in sales because it will suddenly get a lot more oxygen.
And that's not, like, a consideration on which one we picked, but, like, it was something
we were aware would happen, if that makes sense.
But it wasn't the point.
Any thoughts on that, peeps?
I mean, maybe we'll get more into that as we go through business meeting stuff.
We will.
We will indeed.
Foreshadowing.
I will hold my opinions.
I do have a thought on that, which is that as a fan creator, the notion that you might make
more money from winning an award is irrelevant.
But the fact that you get a lot more exposure and also that sense that people like what you
do and approve of it, that's there.
Yes, I can confirm that we have not made more money since winning an award.
But we get more downloads.
Kind of.
Probably at least two people.
Yeah, that's good.
If you're only listening because we won an award, write it.
Oh, God.
Okay.
But send them just to Alison because she needs her ego, boo.
We had a comment from Costanza on Facebook.
Costanza says they agree that it would be great if continental Europe could run a Worldcon
every five years to complement the UK or Irish ones.
But they don't see the institutional knowledge to make that happen.
But like looking at this, as she says, looking at the staff lists for Dublin 2019 and Glasgow
2024, the committee positions for non-English speakers is basically one each for those two
conventions.
David Bamford wrote in on Blue Sky with something related, which was, with the potential best
translated work, Hugo, give impetus to other countries to want to run a Worldcon because
at present it feels like very much USA and Canada or Ireland and Scandinavian countries and
basically no one else.
So I've got like a few things here.
Firstly, I don't think a Scandinavian country has ever run a Worldcon because Finland isn't
Scandinavian.
So I don't think Scandinavia is in the mix and Finland's only run one.
So I think let's let's occlude that for now.
David misses out the UK, which is very funny because he worked on a UK Worldcon.
But the UK is also running Worldcon.
It's not just Ireland, Scandinavia, USA and Canada.
But we talked last time about how the UK and Ireland seem to be comfortable at the moment
with one each every five years.
But the thing is, if you look at the places that we might expect a Worldcon to come from
based on previous years, those places are Germany, the Netherlands and Finland.
Germany, I don't think, is in danger of running a Worldcon anytime soon.
I think it would be great if they did, to be clear, but I haven't heard any rumblings.
The Netherlands Worldcon, like there are there have been rumblings, but those rumblings seem
to be quieting down.
So I'm not sure whether there will be a Netherlands bid this decade or not, but I rather suspect
there might not be.
And then Poland is thinking about a bid.
Finland is conspicuous by not thinking about a bid and seem to be very happy not doing it
again.
And so, yes, I think that is a good question is like, where would we get continental European
bids from?
And I think something we're going to touch on later this episode and maybe discuss in
more detail in a future episode is that US fan run cons seem to be dying.
And so continental Europe is we are going to need to develop that if Worldcon is going to
survive, because I don't think we can rely on the US to run the majority anymore.
So, yes, that is a consideration that is interesting to think about.
Yeah, it's interesting how Finland ran what I felt was a great Worldcon, but a lot of the
people who ran it seem happy to have run a Finnish Worldcon and are not kind of thinking,
oh, what will we do in five years time, 10 years time?
Whereas I think there's a bit more crossover between Dublin and London and Glasgow and future
Dublin and whatever future next UK Worldcon there is.
And I say that in like the feeling that there's going to be another UK Worldcon at some point,
whereas for Finland, I don't think there's a prospect of that.
So it's interesting how those ones seem to kind of build and build people up.
And you can see people who came in at 2014 then being like division heads and chairs and things
in later conventions.
Johnny Badley said, apropos of fan awards, why do we not say Hugo award winning podcast on all
of our social media?
I mean, it's possible because we set the social media up before we won a Hugo and we have not
bothered to change it.
Do we not say that?
Wait a sec.
I thought I changed our blue sky bio.
Yeah, I did.
I think I changed our blue sky bio the morning after the Hugo ceremony at Glasgow.
I think I view Facebook as Alison's domain.
Dirty secret listeners, Alison is the one that uses Facebook.
I just use Facebook once every two weeks to post the thing.
Not much.
You use Facebook way more than once a fortnight, Alison.
I do.
Hang on.
I am just going to amend our about info in Facebook in real time.
Actually, I won't do it now.
I'll do it while you guys are getting into the weeds on the Whistler's Constitution.
Listeners, I will bet all of you a shiny penny that Alison will forget.
So when you listen to this, have a look to see if she's forgotten.
And if she has, you owe me a penny.
John, you realise you have to leave that sentence out when you send it to Alison to listen.
Otherwise, she's going to do it on Wednesday or something and ruin all the shiny pennies.
Look, Liz, I cannot confirm or deny that I am using advanced psychological techniques to get things changed on Facebook.
We had a couple of Facebook comments from people about Hinkley.
Farrah Mendelsohn points out that Hinkley is one of the places that was probably an inspiration for Diana Wynne-Jones' novel Deep Secret,
which is set at a science fiction convention and is very funny.
So thank you very much, Farrah.
And Ali Baker-Brooks write in saying Hinkley Island would be a four-hour journey involving three trains, a bus and a walk for me.
And that's fair.
But also raises a point we didn't raise last time, which is Ali would be concerned about food options outside of the hotel, given how remote it is.
So if you were going to do a convention at the Hinkley Island, I think it could work and I think it could be a good idea.
But you'd have to make really sure that the hotel was going to make food that everyone could eat because you can't just nip out to the metropolitan hub that is Hinkley to get better options.
So last time, and I admit this was a very long time ago, there were two Indian restaurants, one of which was not bad, within walking distance of the Hinkley Island Hotel.
And that was it.
Yeah.
I've got a friend who can't eat garlic and Indian food.
Great for most dietary restrictions, but not that one.
I mean, I guess it could be like, do you remember the Plot de Con you ran at the civil service college?
It's not called the civil service college.
We just got...
Yep.
It's gone now.
It's all been turned into a...
It's a luxury weddings venue and a load of housing, I believe now.
We got a pizza delivered, I'm pretty sure.
So if you had a venue that were kind of, like, we will happily look the other way if a bunch of delivery stuff turns up, that's not always a surefire option, but it does give you a bit more flexibility.
If your venue's relaxed about it, which they are not all.
Yes.
But if you said, look, you are in the middle of fucking nowhere, off a motorway service station junction.
Can we get some pizzas delivered?
Depends to what extent they're willing to do that.
Can people order in food?
I don't think we should go back to Hinkley Island if we can avoid it, though.
I have never had a problem with getting delivery to a hotel.
This might be a...
Generational issue.
Yeah, I'm going to say I'm wondering whether...
Is that, like, is that something that was more true in previous years?
Because delivery...
I mean, delivery has exploded.
There's just so many ways you can get things delivered now and there didn't used to be.
So I wonder whether that has shifted as Deliveroo has risen.
Other delivery mechanisms for food are available.
Just Eat Plus.
$5.99 for 90 days.
I think it's also a case of the finances, though.
Like, if we have deals with hotels that rely on us selling a certain amount of food and beverage that we normally make anyway,
that then over that we end up with people getting pizzas, then...
Alison is looking furious at me but can't respond because she's eating croissant.
I'm still eating almond croissant, which is quite good in terms of the reducing interruptions thing.
You do not need to worry at the moment about the F&B spend because Easter cons...
You know, it's not unknown for them to hit their F&B target on Friday.
Yeah, we eat and drink far more in the hotel.
Open brackets, particularly drink.
And I'm deliberately not closing the brackets here because, you know,
there's been a whole bit about that in Discord.
Discord?
So we normally hit our target on Friday or Saturday lunchtime
and this is a nice, safe space for convention negotiators at the moment.
I mean, as long as you're aware of what people have previously done.
But the food and drink offering doesn't have to be great for us to hit it
because the people who are happy to eat in the hotel and happy to drink in the hotel
will eat and drink more than the hotel are expecting, even now.
No, and I think, just to go back to Liz's point,
unless the Hinkley Island has a restaurant that can seat like 800,
that's the other thing, right?
Like, there's going to be some eating outside the hotel
just from a hotel-get-full perspective.
Shall we move on from letters of comment
and talk about the Wusfus Business Meeting?
Summer of fun!
Did we all have a fun summer at the Wusfus Business Meeting?
I had fun at the Wusfus Business Meeting.
I got to half of one of the meetings in person.
I mean, I followed on to with a couple of others kind of text-wise.
It turns out that if you hold all of your business meetings, all of them,
on Friday or Saturday evenings in summer,
the chances I'm going to be able to go to them are quite small.
So when I filled in the feedback form,
I was having to try and find a way of saying,
it's also true, I'm digressing slightly here,
that if you hold your business meetings in person at a Worldcon,
I'm not going to be able to get to them because I have other things to do.
So this isn't worse than the Worldcon,
but when I filled in the feedback form,
I was kind of like,
yes, I really, really want to attend the Wusfus Business Meeting and yet.
So just to fill in listeners who were not keeping up with the Wusfus Business Meeting,
there were four virtual business meetings
and they were held on Fridays and Saturdays
or possibly Saturdays and Sundays,
depending on your time zone.
And they were held at 9am Pacific Time,
which is where Seattle is.
And to be honest, I looked at time zones
and where we reasonably want people to be able to attend,
which is, you know, there's people across all the US time zones,
across multiple European ones and some other ones.
And basically, I think this time might be the best time you can pick
because it is at least when people are awake.
And it's basically pretty good until you get kind of east of about the Middle East.
And then it's really early if you're in Australia and New Zealand.
But if you're going to say, OK, there's a chunk of time zones
where we think fewer people are even members who might want to attend,
then they probably excluded the ones that have the fewest people.
Yeah, there's no...
I don't think there's a way of being more enfranchising with a live meeting.
One of the reasons I suggested an asynchronous meeting
in my part of the relevant committee
is that I think live meeting is always going to disenfranchise people who can't attend
because they can't make that time.
And the only way to get away from that
is if people can make the decisions at different points in the day,
which is impossible with a system like this one.
But I think Seattle did as well as they could
while sticking with a synchronous meeting.
And I don't think there was any way they could have done differently this year.
So one of the things it clashed with had been in my diary for over a year.
So it would be quite good if they could...
if future WorldComp's could get these dates out even earlier.
Yeah, but a thing that's been in your diary for a year,
that implies to me that that is something which is so important to you
that you would not skip it
even if the WorldComp business meeting dates had gone in there first.
Yeah, what was it, Alice?
What was the thing that had been in your diary for over a year?
The cricket.
Yeah, so you would have gone to the cricket
because they weren't going to move the cricket for the business meeting
even if you'd written to the ECB.
No, but I might not have gone to that game.
I would probably...
If I'd known that the business meeting was going to be there,
which I could have done,
not all cricket tickets come out a year in advance.
It was only because of an international.
And I think I might choose the business meeting
over any particular cricket match.
Yes, fair enough, fair enough.
I just say, I think we reach out that there were issues with the timings
because basically you're always going to have...
If you have it on a weekend,
which is what you kind of have to do
in order to have people who can attend across time zones,
then you're also going to run into the problem of
you're going to clash with the Sabbath in some places.
And also, I do believe they moved at least one agenda item
because the person who wanted to speak about it
couldn't make it on that meeting.
So if you've got a bit of flexibility like that, it helps.
And I guess having some on Friday and some on Saturday
helps a bit with that.
But it was an experiment.
How do we think the experiment went?
Well.
Very well.
I genuinely do.
I think it went really well.
Oh, I thought you were saying well,
and then you were going to finish with the whole sentence.
But you know, you're just saying it went well.
It was a whole sentence.
It was just a very short one.
No, yeah, I thought it went really well.
I think it is...
And actually, I'm going to say something controversial,
which is if you're going to have it be a meeting,
Robert's rules in a virtual space, they work fine.
I'm not sure we need a big evaluation of the process.
Like, it's still a bit annoying.
It's all right.
Lumi seemed to work quite well.
I thought, you know, there were some minor technical issues
with the Zoom, but nothing that isn't, you know,
nothing more than other webinars I've been on for work
or for fandom.
And it meant that you could sort of...
There was a transcript you could follow along with as it was going,
which was lovely.
So that, like, if you, you know, had domed out for a bit or whatever,
you could go back and work out what had happened.
If you needed the loo and you were wearing Bluetooth headphones,
you could just keep listening to the discussions in the loo.
You know, lots of benefits.
I didn't have to miss any WorldCom program to go.
I mean, that's a big one, isn't it?
Yeah, it's quite good.
And yeah, I got to three of the four meetings.
The fourth one, I had a prior engagement.
But also the fourth one was probably the one I didn't have as much
I wanted to see.
Although I will say a couple of things went the wrong way.
And I do, in hindsight, I'm like, oh, maybe I should have gone.
But certainly I got to way more of it than I would have done
had it been held in Seattle, which is zero because I'm not going to Seattle.
But even if I had been into Seattle,
I would not have got 75% of the business meeting.
Yeah, I went to roughly 50% of the business meeting.
And by that, I mean, I went to about the first hour and a half
of two hours of all of them.
And then I fell asleep.
So there were certain time zone issues for me.
But that's, yeah, again, that's still more than I would have got to
in Seattle in person.
And since I'm not going to Seattle and I'm a virtual member,
I would have got to see zero of it.
So yeah, that worked for me.
There were consistently, I think, somewhere between about 140 and 160 people
whenever I checked the numbers.
So that seems to be like the number we can get.
And it did seem to be pretty consistent.
And I saw a lot of the same people each time.
So I think that is like the business meeting constituency
who are prepared to do it virtually.
seems like a good number.
It seemed to me that most of the people who I think of as business meeting regulars
were in the mix there.
I don't know.
There probably are people out there who hate the idea of online meetings
and hate the idea of things online, but go to the business meeting in person.
And I may just not know those people very well.
Yeah, in which case, they're probably not on the Discord to complain about it
not being in person because they're also probably not big Discord people.
And we should say there was an official business meeting Discord,
as well as there still being the unofficial business meeting Discord,
which, yeah, maybe we'll talk about a bit more, was quite interesting.
I think it's going to be interesting because I think if this business meeting
managed to get like a thousand people, everyone would be like,
yes, this shows a resounding success of virtual over live.
If there'd only been 20 people, that would show that maybe there is not an appetite
for doing it virtually.
But what we actually got is a number of people,
which is more than you normally get at business meetings I've been to,
but probably a little bit less than absolute peak attendance at any live business meeting.
So I think that's enough to say it's a success,
but not enough to say it's so successful that we should immediately adopt this for everything
and never do anything else.
Oh, I think we should immediately adopt it for everything.
I was really impressed with it.
I love the fact that the business has been done without it
disrupting everyone's world cons.
I hope that we've got some kind of decompression chamber for business meeting junkies
who don't know what to do at a world con these days.
You get that conclave LARP in.
There's ways we can do things for those people.
I think that's fine, but I think that is a more of a,
Alison thinks this is great than a,
we can look at the numbers and say this was a resounding, overwhelming success.
I think we can just say it was a success.
Oh, okay.
So you're saying that vibes are less important than statistics.
In some issues.
I'm just saying it's interesting, right?
Which is out of step with some scientists,
but me and Liz are both pro stats, anti vibes.
Hmm.
But I think before the meeting, there was a bit of discussion,
like, is there this big untapped set of people
who would want to go to business meetings if they're held virtually,
who don't go to see them live?
And I think what this demonstrates is that this year,
there were those people, but maybe not hundreds and hundreds of them.
So I don't know.
So, okay.
So I think there's a problem here, which is that we don't have the stats.
I don't know what the attendance for the in-person business meeting usually is.
And I would be curious to know.
I think, I think you're right that it's not like we got a thousand people joined the online business
meeting.
We got a reasonable number.
And I think there is a, probably an inherent cap on how many people want to attend a business
meeting, even if it's online.
I will say though, I think there's a couple of other things,
which is you look at the numbers for the Glasgow consultative votes versus the numbers for the
Seattle consultative votes.
And you can see that members are generally less engaged with the mechanics of things at
Seattle than they were at Glasgow.
And last episode and the episode before, we talked about how we think that's probably at
least partly due to Seattle's communication strategy or to be provocative, lack thereof.
And I think it's difficult because what I don't know is if you do this for five years and
get people used to the idea and get people like talking about how this is it, how it works,
does that number go up?
Because the in-person business meeting has had, what, 40 years and has capped at maybe 100
odd.
And the virtual business meeting is starting at 140.
And so in two, three, four years time, does that number stay there or does it rise?
I don't know the answer to that, but I guess that's my, that's my wonder.
And I will also say, I don't think it's possible to say, you know, it's such a resounding success
on a numbers basis, but I think philosophically, it so clearly wasn't a failure and it so clearly
does open the franchise to more people that I would want them to move to this going forward
because it's been shown because there was nothing that went wrong and there was a good number
of people.
I'm like, I don't see a reason not to continue with this.
And I would want there to be, I think my assumption would be that this should continue to be how
we do it going forward unless there is a good reason that it proves not to work.
I'm assuming, and I don't know, but for listeners, Jesse Lipp, who is the presiding officer of this
year's business meeting, is also the presiding officer at LA.
So I'm assuming Jesse will make similar decisions next year as this year, unless, unless they
think there is something that's changed massively between the two years.
And I will also say that Jesse is putting together a survey to circulate to people who attended
the Seattle business meeting to canvas for opinions and stuff.
So it may also be that kind of, we get some more, I don't know, I assume the results that
won't be public, but presumably that will, that will feed into their decision as to whether
to do similar or different things at LA.com.
So those are my thoughts, I think, on that.
Yeah.
And I do, I do largely agree with you.
I just thought it was interesting to look at the, the numbers having, you know, that been
hotly debated before.
I think the number of people speaking who were European was higher than I would have expected.
And I think that is illustrative.
I felt that a number of people who I know in the past have complained that it is extremely
difficult for them to get to Worldcon and expensive.
And therefore they cannot participate in the business meeting as much as they would like,
because they're rarely at Worldcon and where they are, it cannot be their top priority.
We're actually active and engaged with this one.
And I thought that was quite good to see.
Yeah.
So about the people speaking, I think despite there being kind of 140 to 160 people, I felt
like I saw maybe 20 to 30 people who would speak in favour of motions.
Apart from maybe there are, you know, a few people who maybe spoke for on one motion and
then quite a few people who spoke up for quite a few.
And I think that sort of replicates a bit the dynamic I see in the live business meetings.
And I wonder if there is a way to encourage more people to speak.
And I'm as good as this is anyone.
But that's also because I was usually watching the business meeting in my pyjamas and not inclined
to, you know, I do not have the brainpower really to speak coherently and concisely in favour
or against motions at past midnight.
So that's partly my reason not for doing it.
But on the other hand, I'm not sure everyone who speaks at a business meeting is coherent
and concise.
So maybe it wouldn't be worse.
Did you know that you can write down the thing you're planning to say and then say
it from the thing you wrote down before you give your speech?
Because I had my mind.
It never occurred to me to do that until someone was like, I've done this.
And I was like, what?
So yeah, anyway, top tip.
I can't tell if that's...
That sounded more like a burn of Liz than I intended it to.
It was a burn of me.
Yeah, I can't tell if that's really patronising or not, John.
It was intended as a burn against myself.
It was intended as a self-burn, Liz.
You are much more considered to me in general.
I think it works really well if you're maybe the first or the second person to speak for
or against something.
But a lot of time I might have been speaking in reaction to someone else or you need to
change it on the fly because someone's already made your point.
And that is a bit more difficult if you write it down.
But no, you're right.
If you have something you want to say, you can write it down and that probably would improve
a lot of speeches.
Speeches should be reactive, but you often find that they're not.
That people do read out a prepared speech that largely duplicates or contradicts other things
that people have said, even on their side.
I feel I benefit quite a lot when reacting to things on the fact that I'm doing it on the
podcast and it gets edited.
And so I'm now far less likely to ask questions or intervene or make speeches or any of that stuff
in large group organisations, which may or may not be good.
probably is good.
But yeah, and I think obviously, I think whichever way you do this, there is going to be a core
of people who are more likely to comment because you see that replicated in every community you
make.
Like, it's a big, like, I mean, it's particularly magnified in newspaper comment sections.
I think it's like 0.1% of readers comment, like 99% of the comments or something like that.
There's some, I mean, I don't ever quote those numbers readers, listeners.
But like, there's like a big gulf.
And I suspect you see the same thing on Anonymous Claire, where there's some people who post a lot
and there are some people who post very occasionally.
There are some people who have, as far as I can tell, never posted.
But like, I don't know how, I don't think that's a unique feature of the business meeting,
I guess is what I'm saying.
Very roundabout way.
Should have written it down before I started.
No, that's interesting because I was, again, there was a kind of professional Slack that
I'm on and someone did basically post some stats, which is saying, you know, about 10% of people
were reading every day and maybe 1% of people post.
That might be good rule of thumb.
I have two more points.
One is that I thought the Lumi platform did work well.
I think one slight issue is that you, it's through Zoom, but the Zoom is in a browser.
And I think a lot of people would love it if you could pop that Zoom out, because then
you could have that on one window and have everything else in the other window.
You would also, I think people are more familiar with how to get like their sound connected to
Zoom that's not in a browser, because you have this thing where you have to get the browser
based permissions, right?
And the Zoom permissions that I think was causing some issues.
So that would be nice.
I think the other thing is that we discovered that the Lumi platform is quite expensive.
So it's going to be, you know, if other future world comms want to do this, they are going
to have to budget for the Lumi platform.
And I think that's because we had two people sitting in on all the meetings who were like opening
polls and stuff for us.
So as well as all the volunteer time needed from like the top table people and from like
the people adminning the Discord and so on and helping with tech support, we also had Lumi
time.
So, I mean, I think that is a worthwhile investment, but it is something that comms need to find the
money for.
Whereas I think business meetings themselves are pretty cheap because you're using space that
the con already has.
And I don't think not having an in-person business meeting means you can save $20,000 on your
space requirements because you'll just use it for something else.
Not $20,000, but Glasgow certainly had an entire extra negotiation with an entire extra hotel
to use its conference space for Worcestershire.
Oh, that's true.
Yeah.
But they were part of the hotel block.
So it's unclear how, I don't know how that worked.
And no one liked that anyway, because we were in a different place.
I liked it a lot because it was near the pool, but that's not germane.
I think I'm going to say something here, which is, I think Lumi is a really excellent example.
And I'm going to ask Alison what she thinks here.
But I think that you could do that meeting without Lumi.
I think, yes, what we do is we set Andrew January to designing a Wusfus portal that links things
like in exactly the way that Lumi did.
So I think there's two options here, which is I think you could probably run some volunteer
written software that would do this as well, if not better than Lumi, because Lumi was fine,
but it was a little bit clunky.
But I also don't quite understand why you can't do pretty much all of that just within
built Zoom webinar features, because Zoom webinars have the Q&A.
So you can like let people request to speak and tick them off when they've spoken as you
can do all of that functionality straight in Zoom.
Obviously, you couldn't do the presenting of documents, but having a like document channel
on the Discord would have worked for that because the Discord was gated.
So you could have had all of the agenda and stuff like that on the Discord.
You could have done voting on the Discord with the inbuilt Discord polls feature, or you could
have written some voting system for that.
I don't know if Zoom supports STV.
Discord doesn't support STV either.
But like, and I'm kind of like, is this software worth the money for what it does?
And I think the answer might be, if you're a massive corporation or a city council, absolutely.
And if you're fandom, we could actually make it work quite well without spending the money.
But I don't know.
$5,000 a session.
And I feel like, yes, I feel like Discord, the good old fashioned Zoom and Discord with lots of
faffing about stuff will get you most of the way.
I mean, I think it will be interesting to talk to the Worcestershire team.
If you were involved in the decision to buy Lumi rather than using a Doom and Discord setup,
please write in.
I mean, I think it was absolutely correct to use Lumi this year because you want minimal
friction.
Oh, yes, I agree.
The part where I think it might be a little tricky on Discord and need some software is that
they had a lot of votes in Lumi and they obviously had it so you could just push a button and
pop the vote up.
So I guess you'd want to basically be able to have pre-written stuff that you just push a
button and it puts up the appropriate poll.
Like if you know you're going to be voting on debate times or whatever and you have a click.
I'm sure there were some polls where there were multiple options, but maybe I'm...
I don't think there were, but I might be wrong.
No, the elections, but the elections weren't being done that way anyway.
Oh, the election system was pretty clunky.
Yeah, I mean, even in Lumi, you were copying and pasting a...
Yeah, some poor person had to write like a Perl script or something to like split on underscores
or whatever.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I think there's also a consideration here, which is the cost of the Lumi was covered by the
Scalzi Foundation.
And I guess it sort of depends whether or not John's up for just doing that forever
because he is super rich.
But maybe, I don't know.
If they could get this to be a sponsored thing where you're like, if you're an organization
and you give us $20,000, the business meeting is sponsored by your organization.
I don't have a massive problem with that.
And that would defray the cost.
And I know sponsorship is a fraught thing, but that is the secret other option, which
is we could get someone else to pay for it.
And maybe that's OK, rather than burning all of our people points.
This is a classic example of an area where you might well be able to get sponsorship and
nobody would be very offended.
I think if you go to a business and say, would you like to sponsor this?
What you'll get is basically 150 of the really nerdiest nerds who ever nerded will see the
name of your company four times.
We might not get $20,000.
Depends how engaged the people attending the business meeting are.
And I would argue quite.
We should be very engaged in Robert's Rules of Order.
So we have to get sponsored by whoever publishes Robert's Rules of Order because we must be selling
a lot of copies.
Now you're thinking with portals.
No, because this is how the people who make Robert's Rules of Order make their money,
right?
Oh, let's see if we can get sponsored by rival Rules of Order.
Ha ha!
Oh, that'd be hilarious!
Amazing.
OK.
This is a conversation we could defer.
However, also, I mean, I probably wasn't paying attention, but when you mentioned it there,
that was the first I'd heard that the Scalzi Foundation had sponsored this.
So it's possible that we didn't quite get the word out about making clear that that was
a major sponsorship.
And thank you.
The fact that you went to half of a business meeting and attended it the latter half.
Yeah, it was mentioned at the start of the meeting.
I think everyone who was there for the start of any of the sessions had heard that.
I don't know how many people did sort of only attend one and only attend from the middle.
But I wonder whether you're quite a long way towards the edges of that bell curve.
Yes. So I was transcript only.
One of the things about the transcript is that we had live transcripts that were, in general,
pretty good, but they clearly hadn't been fed a list of terms that we were likely to use.
So they struggled with some of our words.
And I suspect one of those words was Scalzi Foundation.
Oh, I have a further thought on the Lumi Discord thing, actually, which is that if all the polls
and stuff ran through Discord and people were just on Zoom, then you could easily vote in
all the polls without actually being at the Zoom. And I don't know if that's a desirable thing or not.
You could do that anyway.
But you'd have to be logged into the Lumi, right?
You have to be logged into the Lumi, but I don't think you have to click join audio or join meeting
on the embedded Zoom.
Oh, yeah. I suppose you could just be in the Lumi and voting and not listening to the audio or video.
Yeah, that would work.
I think that is a risk with using anything that isn't in the Zoom meeting directly.
I think. I might be wrong.
And it's certainly true that there are people who could log into Lumi who would not want to use Discord.
And, like, I'm not saying it's perfect, but it comes down to that question of,
is it saves you $20,000 and a lot of volunteer effort perfect?
And the answer to that might be different.
But, like, I agree with the point you made a while back,
that I think using Lumi for this in the first instance was very wise.
Buying in the solution for the first time you're doing it, I think, is the right call.
Do we want to say anything else about Lumi and the business meeting platform?
I think we're good. I will just make...
I have comments about, like, the Discordiness,
but I think they will come up as we go through items on the agenda.
no-no-no-no-no-no-no-no-no-no-no-no-no-no-no-no-no- about Liz.
As if it hasn't already been about Liz.
This was Liz Batty, now it's about Liz.
So we did some business.
I don't think we're going to go through all of the motions.
We are not.
Unless this is going to be like the six-hour business being special.
Listeners, if we opened a Patreon, would you?
What do we want to pull out?
All right, let me go through in order.
The first meeting didn't do anything particularly interesting or daft,
so I vote that we don't talk about that in detail,
but we've put a link in the show notes listeners.
And the second meeting was entirely an executive session,
which means we can't talk about it,
because if you wanted to know what happened, you had to attend.
There was a brief summary made,
and it was posted on the Seattle website itself,
and we've got a link to that in the show notes as well.
So if you would like to go and see what happened, you can.
But basically, you know, we...
Mostly the thing that happened of note there was that a trial committee was formed
to litigate a thing which I can't tell you about,
and we created a committee to look at whether or not we might need some ethics
here and there in WUSFUS.
Yeah, you can see the minutes do say kind of which motions were passed or referred or whatever,
and in the agenda you can see the motions that were passed,
but you won't be able to ever see or watch any of the discussions on those
or the committee report that led to a lot of these motions being proposed,
unless you are a member of the Worldcon.
So we therefore can't tell you any of it.
I mean, I think it is okay to say that the trial committee related to actions of the Chengdu Worldcon
and some of its committee members, yeah?
We can say what it says on the website, which is,
the business meeting voted to impanel a trial committee to evaluate the evidence
regarding whether the conduct of certain members of WUSFUS,
as part of the administration of the 2023 Hugo Awards,
tends to bring WUSFUS into disrepute, disrupt its well-being or hamper its work.
And that's on their website, so we can say that.
And I guess we can say who's on the trial committee.
Yeah, we can.
The trial committee will be Dr. Science,
Espana Sheriff, Ian Stockdale, Kat Corbetti and Chris Snyder,
who's also known as Enchanter.
And that was announced at the fourth installment of the business meeting,
which was the third main business meeting.
I know that's confusing listeners, I apologize.
And there's something I want to discuss a little bit here,
which is I, one of the things that was discussed a little bit
at points.
And I think I can say that because it is in the Seattle summary.
There was a discussion about conflict of interest,
and that led to some verbiage on the website,
which says,
acceptances to the trial committee should be accompanied
by a declaration of any existing conflict of interest
or a declaration that none exists.
And I think one of the things I'm hoping that the committee set up
to look at ethics looks at is what,
WUSFUS does not have a definition of a conflict of interest,
and I think it would be useful if we had some guidance as to what means you should consider
yourself conflicted.
But I will note that Chris Snyder, Enchanter,
is the partner of the presiding officer of the business meeting at which this committee
was constituted.
And because that is the same presiding officer as 2026,
it is that presiding officer that will preside over the report of the trial committee
and its implementations.
And that was not disclosed in voting,
and that made me uncomfortable,
because I think that is a conflict of interest.
Other members, I think,
did a better job of disclosing where the conflicts were,
and certainly as an academic,
the mode is very much these days to disclose
and let the editor work out whether or not they think it's a problem
rather than to assume it won't be a problem.
But no, I didn't like that,
and I think we need to do better.
I think it's not clear,
because there are two people named as being the manager for the WUSFUS case
at the trial that the trial committee will be working on,
and so I can't tell kind of how much stuff is delegated entirely to them
versus how much still comes under the auspice of the,
like, presiding chair of the business meeting.
But probably we should have some kind of list of examples of conflict of interest.
But you're right,
normally if I'm doing a conflict of interest form,
it will have like,
okay, do you have any of these specific financial ones
or these specific personal ones
or, you know, these are the ones.
And then at the end,
it says,
please disclose anything else that you think might be relevant.
And I think that probably means you should err on the side of caution
and just disclose everything,
but we don't actually have any sort of examples for this.
And I think I've never seen anyone have to declare conflicts of interest
for anything else in WUSFUS.
I don't think we declare them for things like the Mark Protection Committee
or people who are in proposing motions or whatever.
So it's hard for us to,
it's a thing where we,
I don't think we have any prior art to look at.
Oh, I'm going to go off at a tiny tangent then as my first response here
and say, yeah, but I think we should.
I think if the person proposing,
just to take a random example,
a best audiobook, Hugo,
is the president of the US Audiobook Publishers Federation.
I think that is a useful piece of information
which people should know when considering what to do.
And go on, Ethics Committee,
please look at this.
And I think in this case,
I feel like I'm not as convinced as John
that you shouldn't have somebody
who's got a relationship with the presiding officer necessarily.
But I think I probably do agree that
it is something that you'd have expected them to disclose.
And maybe the fact that other people didn't expect them to disclose,
they clearly didn't think it was relevant to disclose.
I think that is where an Ethics Committee could be useful.
I think, yeah, I think that's the thing, right?
I think that I don't know if I think this is a conflict,
but I do think that I'm concerned it wasn't disclosed.
The fact it wasn't disclosed makes me much more suspicious of it
than I would be if it had been,
which is the other thing with disclosing widely
is that you set up a, you know,
I am not hiding anything from you.
Here are all the things you might want to know.
I don't think any of them are a problem,
but you can make your own mind up.
That is how I've been trained to treat disclosures.
We were in some back chat where we were all going,
who from this back chat ought to be,
ought to put themselves forward for the trial committee?
And we concluded that the answer was Espania.
So thank you very much, Espania.
We appreciate you taking a solid one for the team here.
Yeah.
Is that fair?
Is that a reasonable thing to say?
I have a, I will disclose a conflict of interest.
I'm married to Espania.
So I also think it's good that she's on the committee
because I think she has good judgment.
Very sensible person who will say what she thinks.
Yeah.
I mean, I know or have worked with most of the trial committee
and I think all the ones that I know or have worked with are very solid
and I'm quite happy to see them on the trial committee.
That works for me.
And also at this point it's 2025
and I am not personally interested in spending like another year
litigating the 2023 Hugos in depth.
So thank you to those people who are still prepared to put that effort in
because I think I've discussed it to death.
Let's get it done.
Wrap it up.
Move on.
I assume you voted for the trial committee to be founded, Liz.
Because there were some people who were like,
this is dragging on too much.
We don't want there to be any more discipline.
Let's just forget it all.
And I am very much of the opinion that I don't want to think about it,
but I think someone should think about it.
I went to bed before we formed the trial committee.
Oh shit, Liz.
Life hack.
Liz formed a trial committee in her sleep.
Well done.
Yeah.
If anyone asks me, how did you vote on that one?
It's like, I'm worth a sleep.
That is an interesting thing in that because all the votes on Lumi,
you just see the totals.
Whereas in the room, you can kind of see who has their hand up and who doesn't.
It does give a level of anonymity to the voting.
John does not know what I voted for and what I voted against,
or even whether I was in the room for the votes unless you're paying a lot of attention,
which is kind of a little bit of a different dynamic to being in the room.
Whereas if I'm sat next to John, he can see whether I've got my hand up and scowl at me
if he agrees with me.
Yeah, I don't know.
I can't work out if that is good, bad or indifferent.
I'm going to say it's bad.
It's a parliamentary system and there's a lot to be, you know, they are normally,
you have voting conducted in public so that people can see which way people voted.
I think if you're going to change that kind of as a,
oh, this is a thing now,
I would have liked to have seen voter lists on both sides for every motion
as an output of those meetings.
I've got a proposal.
Did anyone who had a Wii ever play the Everybody Votes channel?
Endlessly.
Our family did that a lot.
I have little kids.
And you know, the little people with like your me face on that wander about in the votes.
I would like that for the business meeting.
I would like everyone to have a little animated avatar that wanders from one side to the other.
Andrew January, if you're in there, get on this.
I better find a video of that for everyone who is aware of the Everybody Votes thing.
I remember it.
It tells us what Everybody Votes was like.
I'm just going to say one thing,
which is my idea of having the voting be on Zoom or Discord would address this
because then it would be public again.
And that's why I'd already thought about it.
But I don't know.
I think I think I probably agree with Alison that it would be better to have the voting lists
be out in the open.
And I do think we probably need to be careful that we don't change big things about how WUSPERS works by accident by going online.
And that probably is one of them.
Mark Protection Committee or anything else on Trial Committee?
Mark Protection Committee.
So Mark Protection Committee.
Nicholas White, Alan Bond and Chris Rose have been elected to the MPC and will therefore be protecting marks.
And Nicholas White inadvertently had quite a big influence on this owing to a shortcoming in the WUSPERS voting system where basically something he warned about back in 2022 came to pass where if you have a sort of one person who has suggested a slate and lots of people agree with that slate, that slate will basically be the winners because there's no way of ensuring diversity in the results.
I do want to say one thing, which is Nicholas has suggested multiple motions to the business meeting since pointing this floor out.
And as far as I can tell, has not proposed a motion to fix it.
So, Nicholas, I would quite like that to be something that happens.
I don't know whether you need help with that.
Liz has some good ideas.
But if you do need assistance and co-proposers, please write in because it needs fixing and we should probably fix things when we notice they're broken.
Liz, you went to Cambridge.
Yes, which is completely irrelevant.
Except that they recently did an election for the new chancellor of the university, which, by the way, you can now vote for online rather than having to go in person.
And so I voted for it.
And the vote is done by single transferable vote.
And so I ended up digging into like the Cambridge University statutes to try and figure out why under their mechanism of STV, they double eliminated on one round.
And they had a pretty good like explanation of how like STV works.
And I wonder if we could look at some of their wording of how you do STV because they have it set up.
So it's STV for single winner elections and multi winner elections.
Yeah.
And there might be some good language there that we could use as a base to write something for the business meeting.
But yeah, I mean, I think the other thing is, yes, Nicholas did point this out a few years ago.
But the fact that he pointed it out and maybe just because he hasn't proposed anything, no one else has proposed anything.
So maybe it was felt at the time that no one thought it was a priority to update this.
And so no one is on it.
But I think we probably should be at least proposing to make it work how multi winner STV works in other situations, which seems a bit more sensible.
Yeah, I think that would be good.
And I think, you know, Nicholas Allen and Chris will be good people on the NPC.
But I do I do think given that there's a flaw that has been noticed and subsequently has had an effect.
I think we we now fix it.
That's how that's how Wusfus works.
We're quite good at that in the Worldcon community.
Thing went wrong.
We fix now.
We're not always good.
Not always good at things not going wrong, although we are quite good at things not going wrong generally, despite the memes.
But yeah, I think I think this would be good to fix.
And then also on the NPC very quickly.
There is now a way to remove members from the NPC, which previously was not possible.
Shortly before this was ratified, Ben Yallo resigned from the NPC.
It is an exercise left to the reader as to whether these two things were connected.
They were.
To be fair, I have just looked again at the regulations for single transferable vote and they're quite long.
And there was some I mean, the fair enough is that we also do have like a lot of definitions in there as well.
But there was some issue that people saying, actually, we may have issues with the length of motions for Wusfus business meetings.
And people probably prefer short ones to long ones.
And so if we say I would like to take this one line explanation of voting and replace it with this three page explanation of voting about how you move a surplus as long as, you know, round up to the next whole number or maybe round up second decimal place.
It's going to possibly need to be simplified a bit.
I think there's no reason that the Wusfus constitution couldn't have appendices.
Absolutely.
You could just say as described in appendix A and then have appendix A be full Wusnames.
Yeah.
We're also going to discuss E.2.
So E.2 was a change to the Wusfus constitution that made it so the words Wusfus member were struck and replaced with supporting member throughout the constitution.
And the words attending supplement was struck and replaced with the words attending member throughout the constitution.
I started out thinking that this was silly and then it became clear that it was very, very silly later in the day.
This is something that was coming up for ratification at Seattle having been passed at Glasgow.
And I don't think I was in the room when it was voted on at Glasgow.
There is a great infographic by Andrew January and I have posted it in the show notes.
It goes through 11 scenarios and it explains how the processes used to work in the old days.
And it explains how they do under a Wusfus membership with attending supplement model, which is the current mode.
I want to say a couple of things, which is firstly, Nicholas White pointed out that technically speaking,
E.2 would mean that only supporting members could vote in the Hugo Awards.
And that was clearly not good.
I think that was a fair point.
But I think even without that, this was a poorly motivated change.
And I think reading Andrew's infographic, it becomes very clear.
Buying a ticket to something like Comic-Con is easy.
You buy a ticket, you go to Comic-Con.
That is the end of the process.
That is the end of the explanations.
Everyone is happy.
Everyone has had a good time.
The problem with Worldcon is that Worldcon is an unincorporated...
Well, no.
Worldcon is an event run by an unincorporated member society called Wusfus.
And Wusfus membership gives you certain rights which you have if you are a member of the Worldcon.
If you are only an attendee of the Worldcon, which would apply, for example, if you bought a day ticket to Worldcon, you do not get these rights.
And Wusfus members have these rights.
And it used to be that if you sold your Worldcon membership, the rights went with it.
And if you'd already used the rights, then they didn't go with it.
And that was viewed to be bad because no one should be able to have a Worldcon membership without being able to exercise their rights.
So we made it so that the rights were non-transferable and that was considered to be better.
And the core problem here is that Wusfus is complicated.
The core problem here is that running an event, which is technically speaking, an event run by this unincorporated body,
which gives you certain rights and is run as a democracy and has business meetings and awards and site selection, all of these things,
is more complicated than hiring some people to run an event and then selling tickets to the event.
And there are some people who are like, no, the problem is that we're using the words Wusfus membership.
No, that is not the problem.
That is accurately describing the actual situation.
The situation is complicated.
It does need explaining.
I would argue the complication of the situation is one of the strengths of Worldcon fandom.
I think it's a real strength that we have this thing called Wusfus that is quite complicated and gives you rights and is run as a democracy.
And I do not want to see us abandon that because I think it's one of the hallmarks of what makes this convention good.
But I think if you think Wusfus is a good thing, if you think the Hugo Awards are good,
and if you think running Wusfus as a democracy is good, and you think site selection is good,
and you think the Worldcon moving around the world is good, then it is very difficult to work out a way of doing this that is less complicated than describing how it works accurately.
And that is my basic opinion.
And so I'm glad that we have repealed this because I think what we need to do is just work out how to explain it well,
and then people will understand it.
Because I don't think it's rocket science.
It's just more complicated than buying a ticket to Comic-Con.
But that's fine.
But also, if you buy a ticket to Comic-Con, you buy a day pass to Comic-Con,
this is only for people who want to come to the Worldcon, which is the vast majority of our members,
want to come to Worldcon for the entire five days of the thing.
Because our day tickets are still day tickets.
I mean, sometimes we call them day memberships, but they're not really, you don't get Wusfus voting rights with them.
You can just turn up and buy a ticket for the day and enjoy a day at the Worldcon.
It's only when you want to shove your face fully into the trough of Worldcon that you need at that point to know,
oh, actually, not only is it fan run, but it's run by an Athenian democracy, essentially,
that everybody has an equal say in what is done.
That is not actually true, but as we know, but it's in theory.
And it should appeal to the sort of people for whom that's not actually a bad thing.
That's actually quite a good thing.
I was quite taken by the arguments that were proposed that actually supporting attending was easier to explain to people on desks,
which some people were in favour of and some people weren't.
But I mean, I think that's fair enough.
But basically, I don't particularly care what it's called as long as we can explain it to people.
But I do take the argument that we, this was like a one line motion,
which would then have knock on effects in about 20 other bits of the constitution.
And so you really shouldn't pass that.
And I was quite glad we then reconsidered it and voted against it.
I think rather than have a big more debate about what we should be calling memberships and so on.
I think the interesting thing to me is that because the business meetings were a week apart,
what happened here and also what happened on another motion is that you could basically go and spend a week thinking about it
and talking about it on discord with people and then come back again.
So, for instance, there was a proposal on generative AI, which basically went to committee and they totally rewrote it between sessions and came back.
And I think was a much better proposal that was then voted on.
And in this case, we could then go away.
And Andrew had time to make a flow chart and go, oh, actually, we've accidentally made it.
So attending members could no longer vote in the Hugos.
And then that was quite a powerful argument for reconsidering it and then striking it down.
And that would be quite hard to do at the live meeting because you don't have a week.
You have like a day or two during which time a lot of people are very busy being at a WorldCom.
So I suspect if we'd done this live in Seattle, we might have passed that and never reconsidered it and got ourselves into a pickle.
So I have like I have I have I have three things to say here.
I think the point about explaining on desks, I think if you go to Andrew's page and you read through, it was complicated before and it's complicated now.
And the thing that's actually changed is that people were familiar with the old system and people are less familiar with the new system.
And I certainly find when I teach physics in my day job, listeners, I am better at teaching the parts of physics that I use every day than I am at teaching the parts of physics that I basically only think about when I'm teaching undergraduates or when I was an undergraduate myself.
And familiarity has a massive impact on how easy you find it to explain things.
But I think this is a clear indication that what we actually need is to work on how we explain it, because I don't think there's a fundamental difference in complexity, because I think the complexity is an inherent property of the WorldCom.
I think it's just how we explain it changed.
And I think this was a point made very well by Meg MacDonald in the business meeting itself.
She pointed out that the business meet in the business meeting, she pointed out to those who might have been recalcitrant to reconsider E2 that Glasgow had 1390 First WorldCom members in the first year that this new system was under effect for a WorldCom.
And they did not find it too complicated.
And that's an underestimate because the Scottish rate was cheaper.
So there were people who bought that rate who were also First WorldCom.
I think the same might have been true of young adults.
So that is, there were at least, there were at least 1400 First WorldCom attendees.
I don't know how much I think this complexity puts people off.
And it might be that if we get rid of all the complexity and made it a ticketed event, we'd hit like 20,000 attendees every WorldCom.
But I sort of doubt it.
But I think if people are leaving the desk thinking that it's complicated, that reflects badly on us for having explained it badly.
But again, I think it's inherently complicated.
And I don't think there's a way of changing that without making WorldCom into something it isn't.
And I do think we probably need to think quite carefully about how to explain this.
And we probably need to like practice.
Which I know people don't usually do like role plays before going on a comm desk.
But maybe we need them too.
On short motions, I agree with you.
Short motions are bad.
This motion should have gone through every single place it touched the Constitution.
And should have done the strikeouts and replacements explicitly.
Because that's how a good motion is drafted.
And this whole, well, we'll just do it shortly so that it's not a lot of words.
It's like, no, do not.
Do the work.
Do not make other people do the work.
And do not open it to be bad if you've done the work and missed something.
Thirdly, completely agree with you.
Having meetings a week apart is great because it means people can actually think about things and have discussions.
And you get that development.
And I think that's really good.
And I think being able to do that like on Discord and stuff is also really good.
Those are my three responses.
But maybe we should be asking people who don't come to business meetings because they haven't been to 27 World Cons.
Is this one more complicated?
Yeah, I'm not suggesting we do a big survey.
I'm suggesting that we do have a pool of people who've obviously managed to buy memberships despite them being probably a bit complicated.
And if you had some wording, you could like test it on a handful of people.
We got rid of the retro Hugos.
Yeah, we did.
We got rid of them.
I mean, I think my views on the retro Hugos have been given at length.
It does seem to have made some people a bit unhappy because they felt there were not many years left to go.
And so we should just go with it.
I did feel the point that while it's optional for each World Con and a lot of them have chosen to stop doing this,
it means that maybe they will naturally die out unless there's a con who are really keen.
But in the end, I'm happier to just get rid of them.
Yeah, I think that's fair.
Basically, I was very un... I didn't really mind either way.
They don't offend me, but I also don't pay much attention to them.
So I was quite happy for it to be either.
And that was basically reflected by the consultative vote, which was, you know, largely... I think it very slightly edged one way towards keeping it clear that the members are roughly evenly split.
Yeah, and I feel it's one of those things where we can't give them out as retro Hugos officially.
But if a con was really keen and they were 75 years after a missing year, they could still have some program about them or even, you know, run some non-world con awards if they wanted to,
or do something to raise awareness of the science fiction of 75 years in the past, which would maybe be a bit less of an administrative thing than running a whole retro Hugo process.
And then having a bunch of retro Hugos where you have to work out who should get the trophies and so on.
How many special Hugo awards is one convention allowed to give out?
I think it's one.
One.
I don't think you're allowed to sneakily run 27 extra retro Hugos.
Boom!
I see where you're going, John.
But you could do a special Hugo award for best novel of 19, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Ooh, no, but because if you could, you know what you could do?
You could run all the previous retro Hugos that we haven't already done in one year and just be done.
We'll just have one year with like 100 Hugos.
You could also make them committee awards. You could just award them.
Not more than one special category may be created by the current Worldcon committee.
And I assume you can't award multiple awards in that one special category.
I assume they've thought of that.
Voting to be the same as for the permanent categories.
So you can't suddenly turn it into multi-winner STV.
Boo!
Well, I tried.
And I believe we're not supposed to put anything else on the ballot with the Hugo awards apart from the not-a-Hugos.
Oh, yeah. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So you can't sneakily put them on the Hugo ballot and then give them a Hugo award.
Glasgow has announced their Smofcon 42 bursaries.
We were going to talk about Worldcon finances, but we've run long this time, listeners.
So we will discuss that in a future episode.
But we wanted to mention the bursaries because there is a deadline of the 31st of August.
There is a link in the show notes.
And we encourage people to go and check it out if they're interested in attending Smofcon.
Yeah, and I mean, I think I want to say a little bit, which is that I applied and got a Smofcon bursary to the Smofcon in Lisbon,
in least in part because the chair of Dublin 2019, James Bacon, said, do not self-exclude in general.
I took his advice to heart.
And it doesn't matter how committed, you know, you need to want to run conventions of some types,
but it could be from the most simple to the most ginormous.
And people from all backgrounds are encouraged to apply.
And I'd strongly recommend it if you think you might like it.
Also, Stockholm is nice, but that shouldn't necessarily sway you.
Stockholm is perhaps not as nice in early December as it was in late June.
But it is crucially a European Smofcon.
And I'm not sure when the next European Smofcon bid is at the moment.
So if you want to go to one and you're a European, this is a good year.
Yeah, Lisbon one was fantastic.
And just some very quick updates from a previous episode.
The Montreal bid has now announced that the co-chairs for the Worldcon, should there be seated,
are Bruce Farr and Darren Briskman.
And if those names seem familiar, that's because they're the bid chairs, listeners.
So yes, that has now been.
That is now official.
Demonstrating the benefit of people sniping on the internet
because we and other people said it would be good to know who these are.
And now they've announced them.
No doubt because people were saying you should announce this.
Are we on to picks?
Mm-hmm.
Hey.
I rather think we are.
I'm going to pick that little known indie film, Superman.
Great.
Just because I went to see Superman and I thought it was really pretty good.
And a lot of my other reading and listening and watching has been Hugo finalists.
So they'll get more commentary when the Hugo finalists are announced.
Sorry, final results are announced.
Yeah, I went to see Superman.
I don't know if you two have seen it.
No.
No, not yet.
It's on the list.
Odd for me to be the most timely and topical one by watching a film three weeks after it came out.
Superhero movie.
But people say it's very good.
It is.
So I think it is pretty good.
I mean, I was not a big fan of the DC era where everything was a bit dark and gritty.
This just feels like a sort of fairly like classic Superman film.
And I think it makes a few interesting choices.
So cover your ears if you don't want to hear anything about the interesting choices from the very early on in the film.
One thing it does is basically it cuts out what might be the opening act of the film, essentially.
We start in with a lot of stuff already having happened.
We already have the situation set up that Superman essentially at a low point.
He's just been defeated by a hero.
He's lying in the snow outside his fortress of solitude.
He's at a low point.
And we don't do origin story.
We don't do any of that.
We sort of skip straight in at this point where we learn that in the past Superman has tried to stop a war between two countries and then been defeated by the supposed hero of one of these countries who've come back.
Of course, we find out pretty quickly this is all Lex Luthor's plot.
But it's interesting that by choosing to skip all that, it means we can spend two hours on Superman.
And it makes what might otherwise have been quite a long film into something where they have a bit more space to explore with Superman already established.
I thought that was interesting.
The second thing is that we kind of open with, and this is a tiny spoiler, we open with basically see that Superman and Lois Lane are already in a relationship and she knows that Superman is Clark Kent, which is an interesting choice as well.
And I felt they both work pretty well.
I don't think we need to do the whole like, yes, he landed on a farm in Kansas.
Obviously, we do see the farm in Kansas and we do see Superman's parents because he goes back there at a low point.
And, you know, they give him a we'll always love you.
You'll always be our son kind of thing.
So it sticks very much to those sort of classic, classic beats, but it has space to do a bit of stuff around them.
There's maybe a little bit too much of Crypto the Wonder Dog.
And I'm surprised I'm saying that because I'm like Crypto the Wonder Dog, that'd be great.
But maybe a little bit too much of him.
I think Luthor is pretty good.
But you miss a bit by by not having any like of the prior relationship between Luther and Superman.
You miss out a bit there.
There's not a lot of Daily Planet.
You only really see Clark Kent once and you maybe don't get enough of like, I thought Perry White, you'd like to see more of him.
You don't get a lot of that.
But it's just a sort of pretty classic tale.
And you spend a lot of time like with Superman in the sunlight, brightly lit in a bright blue suit.
Fucking good.
And that is enjoyable.
And it made me laugh.
And it's got enough nods to other other bits of DC that you'll enjoy it.
It does a little tiny bit too much set up for future films.
One in particular that I won't go into too much because I think it probably is a bit too much for a spoiler.
But it's a bit like, did you really have to do that?
That kind of undercuts some other stuff.
But yeah, I just liked it as like, OK, here is Superman.
He is this big, bright hero who is trying to make good choices and do the best he can and gives you that for two hours.
Oh, and you get Mr Terrific and Mr Terrific is great.
Surely he's terrific.
I nearly said Mr Terrific is terrific, but I thought, is that too much of a joke?
But he just is.
He's just played very well.
And, you know, he has his T-spheres and his T-craft and all this sort of stuff.
And he gets what is probably the best action scene.
One of the things I love about the Marvel films is where they bring in obscure people I've never heard of.
And I'm like, well, this is clearly great.
And I've never heard of Mr Terrific, but that makes me really want to go and see Superman.
There were characters in it that I never heard of that clearly established DC figures.
There's ones where I'm like, oh, I kind of recognize that name.
You're a DC person.
And then they was also bringing the engineer who I am aware of, but only from when the engineer was still off in like the Wild Storm universe in the authority.
And then at some point they came back into mainline DC.
And I have not paid any attention to that.
But that was kind of interesting that they are bringing in some of these slightly minor characters.
But you also get Superman, Lois Lane and Jimmy Olsen and Crypto the Wonder Dog and Lex Luthor.
And yeah, it's got enough classic stuff.
I'm looking forward to seeing it.
I think I'm going to see it next weekend, but we shall see.
I'm going to pick One Soul, which is a graphic novel by Ray Fawkes, which was released in 2011.
So I've got my finger on the beating heart of the genre.
So what this is, is a book which starts.
So every page is a nine panel page.
So every spread is 18 panels of this comic.
And it's drawn in black and white.
And each of the 18 panels in each spread is a separate person.
And the book takes you through each of these people's lives from their sort of inception up to their deaths.
And so you can just read it as a normal comic where you like read one page at a time until you get to the end.
But I found that what I ended up often doing was I read it like that until something happened in a story that caught my interest or that like I didn't quite understand what happened.
And I would go back and read that, like reread that person's journey up to that point to remind myself what had been going on.
And as a consequence, I don't know how many times I read each page.
But like it's the first time I've ever, other than like adventure game books, it's the first time I've ever kind of skipped backwards and forwards and had my fingers in multiple pages.
And like it's really interesting how it encourages you or it's really interesting how it doesn't encourage you to read it non-linearly.
But I did anyway.
I don't know if it's genre particularly, other than obviously there's like a cross-section between graphic novels and genre generally.
It's, but it is really, it's really interesting.
And I, I very much enjoyed it.
The author, Ray Fawkes, has worked on various versions, sort of, you know, worked on Constantine, worked on various Batman novels, like worked on Justice League.
So it has done a bunch of work for DC and Marvel and Dark Horse.
But this is like his own thing.
And I went to the launch of this graphic novel on my TAF trip.
And I fully intended to read the copy that Colin Hines bought while you're at the launch.
And then I did not.
And I have gone back to it many years later.
And I'm glad I did because it was really, really good.
Sounds really nice.
Sounds like it might be a terrible one to try and read digitally.
Yeah, I really think you would want to read it in physical.
I don't really know what the experience of reading it digitally would be like.
But I think it would lose some thing.
Actually, and I don't know whether it's for sale digitally because it was published before that, like before Comixology had gotten really big.
So it may well be that it's hard to find.
Although I haven't looked, so I might be wrong.
You are wrong.
Am I? Excellent.
Yeah, you can get it on Kindle or rather, which presumably turns out to be like in the Kindle read or whatever.
So I mean, and.
Ah, they did it.
They did a tan.
Only Press did a.
So it's published by Only Press, but Only Press did a 10th anniversary edition.
Ah.
That makes sense.
So, yeah, because 2021 was after Comixology was popular.
Actually, it's it's on Kindle Unlimited at the moment.
And I bought Kindle Unlimited for the month because I was doing a lot of reading last month.
So I might just read it.
Is that the end?
No, because Alison needs to talk about beer.
Oh, Alison didn't do a pit yet.
Oh, I forgot Alison was still thinking about beer.
No, I'm going to.
I have.
I'm going to talk about beer.
I've been in the Lake District and I was going to do lots of reading, but I didn't because what am I like?
But I did do lots of walking and a lot of sitting around in the sunshine.
And what's even nicer, sitting around in the light cloud, which is is what perfect English summer weather is like so that it doesn't get too hot.
And one of the things about the Lake District is that you find excellently preserved examples of things that have largely disappeared from other parts of the UK.
And one of them appears to be Cask Bitter, where there are lots of microbreweries in the Lake District now or close to the Lake District.
They're probably not mostly in the Lake District.
We found one where I was like, are they really brewing in this valley?
And they said to us, oh, no, we ship the water from the valley to Kendall and then they make beer and ship it back, which I thought was quite funny.
But yes, so all of the pubs practically had really good beer and all of the pubs had really nice Cask beer, including Cask Bitter, which is obviously the best thing in the world.
And there is nothing nicer on this earth than to go for a nice walk and at the end of it have a nice pint of bitter.
And, you know, I might be biased, but you know, you should all do this.
Lake District continues to be very nice.
Everyone keeps going, oh, but it's just got a good press agent.
And there are other places that are just as nice in the English countryside, but aren't the Lake District.
And I am here to say I looked all over the UK for places with lakes.
And Scotland's got some big lakes, but the countryside is more rugged.
And other places, whenever you zoom in on a lake, it turns out to be a reservoir and they are not as good.
So Lake District is the best.
It's also a bit crowded, but we found some non-crowded parts of it.
So and you can always go at a time that's not July.
So, yes, bitter.
It's good.
It shouldn't die out.
You shouldn't let it die out.
You should go and drink it and ask people to make it well and serve it well.
And it doesn't transport terribly well, which is one of the reasons it's not as popular as it might be.
It comes in casks and it needs to not travel too far and the casks need to be looked after.
But it's so nice when it's done well.
Fair enough.
That was the Octothorpe podcast.
And it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
I've got to reboot because Audacity is not working.
Oh, that's hilarious.
This is the air I always get, which I know is fixed with just rebooting my laptop.
So see you in a minute.
Ta-ta.
The cursed episode.
Summer of fun.
I nearly made Alison choke listeners.
No regrets.
Hashtag YOLO.
Sorry.
Just to make it very funny, which you'll remember on the edit and it will make you laugh all over again.
The theme music for this episode was Surf Shimmy by Kevin MacLeod and Combatech.com used under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.