Right, so shall we talk about the retro hugos?
There are links in the show notes.
Now I confess I haven't read them.
So my plan is...
Your plan is for me to start this one off because I've read the links, right?
Yeah, I think so.
I think that makes sense.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 37th episode of Octa Thorpe,
a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom.
I'm John Coxon.
I am Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
This episode is coming to you on the 5th of August 2021,
but it was originally recorded over two sessions in August and September 2020.
Since we are not recording this episode live,
although we have had lots of lovely letters of comment,
we will not be getting to them this week,
but we promise we will next week.
So feel free to lock this episode as well,
and we will have a Schmorgas board later in the year.
Because after all listeners, it is the summer of fun!
Hope you enjoy the episode and see you all in a fortnight.
Yeah, so we previously had some discussion of the retro hughos,
where I think the general consensus was,
I'm against them,
Alison's against them, and John thinks they're kind of neat.
But there's been quite a lot of extra discussion
from a couple of different angles that I thought was interesting actually.
So some of it took place on file 770,
which I read occasionally, but I don't read all the posts because there's way too many of them.
And so I became a parent that I missed quite a lot of retro hugho discussion
before the Worldcon.
So this one, this discussion kind of hinged off the Memphis Worldcon,
announcing that they would not run the retro hughos,
which they announced as part of their statement on their commitment to diversity and inclusion.
And there were a fair number of people noting,
and this is something I hadn't really picked up on,
that they were basically explicitly saying that we don't run the retro hughos
because we think they are not favorable to our diversity and inclusion.
Which I think is reasonable given that there are people who feel that essentially that if we're
going to have an award ceremony where we give our official Worldcon awards
to people where we just renamed another award because we don't feel there should be anything
named after them, it's maybe not helping our diverse inclusion.
But I can see how if you're a person who feels strongly about the retro hughos,
and who also feels strongly enough about the retro hughos that you've spent quite a lot of time
trying to diversify the nominees, that this does feel like you're announcing way in advance
that you're not going to do the retro hughos as part of this statement.
And it kind of undermines what these people have been doing to try and get a more diverse
set of nominees. And there's a couple of separate blog posts from
Hampas Ekerman and Cora Boulart who have been doing quite a lot of work to try and
find lists of nominees for the retro hughos each time they're held to make sure that they're
really getting a view of the field to try and give people more things to read and more options
beyond just naming the people that always come up because they're the names that for
whatever reason have been passed down as common knowledge.
I hadn't really taken on board how much work people were doing to try and diversify the nominees
and to try and make sure there is good information out there for people to look at
because it is quite difficult I think to research some of these things in the older magazines and
go through all the science fiction of 1945. And it does seem like people have been doing a lot of
information gathering and reading and recommendations for this that I was not really aware of. And so
to have someone say no we're just not doing them we're claiming that three years in advance.
Feels like they've been doing a lot that work for nothing. I think I like the retro hughos in
concept I think that there is a definite argument and one of the arguments I've seen online is if
you look at some of these states from say so basically like the first hughos were awarded in 1953 and
if you look at the things that won in 1953 and then you look at what wins retro hughos around 1953
there is an obvious difference where a lot of things that won in 1953 are things that the modern
audience would have no idea existed or has not stood the test of time and would not have won if
it was done as a retro hugho which is an interesting thing. And I think the thing I've thought for a
while is it would be much more interesting if you had the retro hughos be a juried award where the
jury was the winners of the modern hughos in that category. So you had like if you wanted to award
the retro hughos in 2020 you had the six nominees for best novel in 2019 be the jury. That I think
would be a really neat way to tie it to the modern hughos and make it clear that it's not trying to
it's not trying to put ourselves in the shoes of the 1950s hugho electorate and award what would
have won the hugho while taking out the impulse of the wider community just to give best editor to
John W. Campbell for a year. But I will say in general old science fiction should probably read
it right like new science fiction is way better like science fiction properly started in about 1995
even everything before that's not really worth reading snow crashes are classic that probably is
exempt. Okay so Alison is vibrating with rage. That was very wrong. That was clearly clearly a
statement. You just froze on a grumpy face of Alison and it was hilarious. Sorry, Karam. Yeah.
Old fiction generally and old science fiction in particular. Once you have got over the fact that
you that every so often there's a an opinion or an assumption made that is hugely antithetical to
the way we live now is nevertheless often of considerable merit. And you know but that's the
thing about reading historical texts. It is a matter of reading historical texts. You are doing
it in a different way. If you are reading purely for entertainment you are definitely going to be
better served with modern stuff. But if you are actually interested in concepts and ideas and the
fact that so the ways that people thought 100 years ago are not the same as the ways we think
now and that doesn't just mean because they were racist and sexist and anti-inclusionary. There are
lots of good things about that as well. And you could broaden your mind by visiting the past in
the same way that you can broaden your mind by visiting other countries or other cultures. Anyway,
that was not the point I was going to make about the retrohugas because I've been waiting very
patiently to say that it doesn't. Cora Boulat has argued very cogently that they've been doing
all this work, that they've been trying to show the breadth of the field that it's not just about
the people we've all heard of. If you want that and as John says the last thing you would want to do
is a popular award. Popular community awards are not good at nuance, they're not good at having
everyone read everything or think hard about it. That's not what's going to happen. If you call
it the retrohugas and have a popular vote of the Hugo of the World Club membership,
you're never going to get that nuance. It's not going to happen and it doesn't matter how much
work you put in to make you the nominee list interesting. People are still going to vote for
name recognition and they're not going to bother to read your nominees either before they do it.
Some people will but the majority of voters won't and it's all, you could have a jury
award but I feel like the Hugos are ineluctably a popular award. The Hugos have been awarded to
a load of crappy things over its time. That's kind of what the Hugo is and it's not always going to go
to the best thing because it is a popular award and popular awards never do. So if you want to have
an award for old science fiction though I can't think of one absolutely any reason why you would do
that. Then by all means go ahead and do one but it shouldn't be called the retrohugas and it
shouldn't be anything to do with the rest of the hugos or the world credits. It's just a nonsense
I dare anyway I despair. Liz do you despair? I don't I think I'm naturally predisposed not to
despair too much certainly not about retrohugas. I agree with Alison that Coribulets Brog is
very cogent and actually I think you'd be interested in it John because I think it makes a good
argument about why you should read older science fiction fantasy and also makes an argument that
what you may have read is what has been placed in the canon maybe by people at the time or
shortly afterwards and maybe what they canonized is not what is most interesting about the science
fiction of that time to a modern audience. So that I found very interesting actually and there are a
bunch of stories she links in there that I'm quite interested to go and read but I also agree with
Alison that a popular vote award is probably never going to do what we wanted to in this arena and
having it be not a popular vote award makes it not the retrohugas because it makes it not the
hugos. So and I think that's the second argument here is Nicholas White the Hugo Administrator for
Conzeland has posted some more details about the nominations for the retrohugas and what he says
is there were two categories where we allowed the final ballot to proceed with one finalist who had
received only three nominating votes. In cases where the final ballot would have had to include
more than one eligible finalist with three or fewer nominating votes we determined the category was
not sufficiently supported by voters to proceed and I think that is an incredibly low threshold
to be giving awards on. What we're saying is if you've got three people to nominate something
then as long as we had sufficient nominees with three or more votes and that was enough to run
the category and I think if we are going to do retrohugas and given that they do seem to be an
awful lot of time and effort and money we should definitely restrict them only to categories where
there seems to be a genuine interest and I think I would have to say a genuine interest means
more than three people thought someone should be on the ballot.
I think in general that having the barrier for a that having retrohugas be awarded to things the
Hugo Electric thinker worth awarding makes sense and saying that that means that more than three
people had an opinion on who should be on the ballot probably also makes sense. I think those
are both imminently reasonable. I don't know what the actual threshold should be. I haven't done enough
research into the actual nominations and stuff to have a qualified opinion on that but yeah I think
that does make a lot of sense. I think the problem here is that if you want like Coribulat's article
is very interesting. Coribula in her post says that she is equally frustrated by the fact that
retrohugo voters vote for familiar names like John W. Campbell and Wheat Curly Stories by Futuristars
at the Drawerow River better works because she is also frustrated by that and so to combat that
she started the retrohugo recommendations spreadsheet and retro science fiction reviews to help
potential nominators. I think that's very laudable. I think what it ignores completely is that people
it's not the the people voting for John double Campbell aren't doing it because they are like
well I don't really know anyone but John W. Campbell I've heard of him I'll vote for him. I think a lot
of the people voting for him are voting for him because they think he was a titan of the genre
that deserves recognition and I think the problem is that if you think those people are wrong
in a popular reward it's not enough to say well I'll make it clear there's a load of other options
you actually have to have the arguments and so she's saying like I'm very frustrated by this and
here is the action I have taken but but notable in its absence from her blog post is she has not
argued with people and she has defended the retrohugos from criticism and got frustrated with people
criticizing them because she's like well educate yourself and vote and it's like I don't I think
this by and large misses an awful lot of the truth that in a popularly awarded award you can't do it
by just saying oh people should just be more educated that doesn't work because that's not
how popular rewards work if you want it to be a more educated award that that surfaces more of
the genre it needs to be a jury reward and the problem with a jury reward that has the huco award
name is how you make a jury reward that does have the huco award name while keeping it in the spirit
of the huco awards which has always been the award awarded by the worldcom the only way I can
think of doing that is to have it be reflective of the nominites or either finalists for huco awards
and what they think should be recognized from the past because I think that links to the world
comp fandom and the huco awards nicely and is a jury reward and so I think you could make a case
that that is a good way of doing it that doesn't um occlude the tradition of the huco awards but also
doesn't run into the problems that are being discussed here but I just don't really see her
argument that you can make a spreadsheet of all the nominees and that will help I'm just like I
don't think it does I'm sorry I agree with you and but I also think the jury reward juried by recent
huco winners sounds like an amazing idea and if you decide you'd like to take that through the
wussfuss business meeting as a suggestion I will bring popcorn I thought you were going to second
to Alice and bringing popcorn is much less helpful I am not going to second it I think I think it's
pointless I think they should be scrapped I think hugo administering is a lot of work already and
it's twice as much work and I think it's a magnet for dissent and disagreement that that is
wholly unnecessary and I think as I've said before on retro hugos I'm pretty sure the fundamental
nature of the retro hugo is fatally flawed because it is actually wrong to say the hugos were not
awarded in year x so we will put ourselves the modern world con community in the role of the
world con community of 1943 and and make awards and I just feel that's a bad and wrong thing to do
because we are actually denying their their personhood of their community
partly because we don't like it and I had one more point which you might want might not want to
edit out which is that I spend a lot of time I am all the new guys and I spend a lot of time
talking to people on the internet who are a lot older than me and I think quite a few people who
are voting in the retro hugos are doing so on the basis of what was very exciting when they were
13 years old and were reading pulp magazines and and that is a problem that is creating some
inertia of the retro hugos that is probably not get overable you know having just said oh we
shouldn't put anything on the ballot which are the only three people supporting it
the numbers in the regular hugos are not incredibly high and there are people and works on the ballot
with nominations in the 20s but I still think that is a significant leap so I don't know where I would
put the floor for the retro hugos but I if I was Hugo administrator which fortunately will never
happen I would probably chop it off at a higher bar of this is not a category you can run I mean
obviously you can't really run things like best semi-prosy and best fan cast on as you can find a lot of
radio shows and things like that but I might be harsher on chopping things out I was going to say
that on John's idea of having the Hugo finalists do this I think the question is how would you decide
what material from that year the Hugo finalists have to read to do the jury award because I think
if you went to many of the current Hugo nominees and said right what I want you to do now is read
the entire output of like a sounding in 1945 this would not go down particularly well presumably
that is a thing that has been solved for other jury awards I imagine that the people who judge the
clerk don't have to read like every they don't each have to read every single book that was released
in the year right because that would be more that they would have to read constantly for a year
without sleeping and that seems unlikely most most jury awards are submission based so the publishers
pay to submit a book to the clerk and they end up with a number of books ah okay and that's how you
get around the problem at which point the jurors do indeed read them all but I think they kind of
read the first couple of chapters and if it's an obvious stinker they do not carry on with it unless
one of the other jurors says um this is a book that deserves your attention I understand this
how it works when you've got 80 to 100 books then you just have a sort of lower threshold saying
no I've read 100 pages this is a stinker I'll put it to one side unless everyone else loves it because
in the end you're only going to pick six any one juror could say no I'd like everyone to read this
one please one and I think and I think the other thing is obviously like there is no reason that
you couldn't have this be on the basis of um if it receives a nomination it goes on the list of
things to read um or you could have some cut off above a nomination if that ended with an
implausibly high number of things to read um but presumably there are clearly people who are seeking
out and nominating the stuff that is actually good versus the stuff that is famous and so there
is presumably some way of of doing that so that you mean that the vetting process doesn't have to be
the finalist it's only the jurying process that is um I confess I don't I just had this idea now I
haven't like thought through all of the mechanics and it might be that it completely doesn't work
but I do in general I think it is worthwhile despite what I said earlier about like old science
fiction being not worth reading I think it is in general good to recognize like the stuff that
was good of yesteryear and I don't necessarily think that the retro heroes is a bad framework
in which to do that I just think that you have to decide what you want the output of that framework
to be and if you want it to be a nuanced look at the forgotten gems of the genre having it be a
popular awarded vote is clearly not going to achieve that goal um one other argument that
Bueller makes in her blog post is that she notes a lot of the people complaining are actually angry
about the um Hugo Ceremony and Martin's Toastmaster ship and they are not actually really angry about
the who the retro heroes I am not sure to what extent that is true but I would be interested to see
how much discussion there was on twitter about the retro heroes like in between them being awarded
and Martin Toastmastering the regular Hugo's it would be it would be interesting to see whether
it ramped up afterwards but I don't really know how you'd do that um but the impression I had was
that people were complaining um even before Martin was Toastmaster they were but not very much
they were just kind of isn't it weird that we're still um giving awards to these men
whilst also stripping their names off our awards
and I will say like I have read like I've just bought a lot of old um Lovecraft mythos fiction so
I've bought the three volumes from the Penguin Classics collection of Lovecraft's work I've bought the
or I've bought the Robert E Howard collection from Penguin Classics and I've bought the Clark
Ashton Smith collection from Penguin Classics so like I am currently embarking on a big old
romp through the classic Cthulhu mythos and I've read um I've read The King in Yellow by Robert
Chambers which is fantastic really really really good sounds up really well um so I will say like
I'd be slightly sarcastic I just I'm always suspicious of the logic that everyone should have read like
all of the classics because I'm like read the classics that are interesting and don't read
the ones that aren't there's no you don't have to do homework when you're reading for leisure it's
fine yes that's right you you you can't when people say read all the classics they're essentially
gatekeeping and sometimes they do it for the best reasons um but when you're old you go oh but I
understand that because I was there and I lived through it and that is not necessarily useful to
anyone who is not old it does not mean that they should have had all of the experiences you
you did that you did because it is not possible for them to have had that set of experience this
actually came up when I was talking to a sister-in-law yesterday um on Valentine's Day a few years ago
a car of a boy year it was um Ispania and I went to see Casablanca at the local cinema because they
had a Valentine's Day showing of Casablanca and I'll say two things about having odd to see Casablanca
the first of which is I understand an awful lot more about cinema now that I have seen that one film
because the amount that later cinema borrows from that film is quite large and the amount of
cultural references made to that film is quite large and I feel like I have an awful lot more
jigsaw pieces to um there are conversations where people say things I'm like oh I understand what
that means now because I've seen the movie you're referencing which is a famous movie that people
often reference and it's a bit like people would say I haven't seen Star Wars or I haven't seen
Aliens and I'm like you don't have to I'm not saying you have to but I am saying is that there
are things people are saying around you that you don't know what they mean because you haven't seen
them which may be fine and it's not important you're not like missing you're not gonna not notice the
wife's left you or that your boyfriend's proposing if you haven't seen Aliens probably I can't think
of any examples where that would be true but what I will also say is Casablanca is fantastic
really really really really enjoyed it we'll also say I was the only person laughing at the jokes
because everyone else was there to respect a serious classic film and I was there to watch a
movie on its own merit and Casablanca is a funny movie that you should laugh at the jokes in
quite a funny film I've seen it seen it more than once and there were just a lot of people
sitting there po-faced and I was like he just did a joke why are we not the it was weird people
have this reference classics that there are classics that don't work as modern entertainment
because they are too far away from from what we recognize as modern entertainment or classics that
don't work as modern entertainment because they are not to your taste and you're forcing yourself
to read them because you think you walked to add a some weird sense of obligation to the canon
but what this also means is that people don't let themselves enjoy the classics when they're
enjoyable which I find bizarre it's whatever really complicated opinion and and relationship with
old art because I don't really I think if you're going to go and see something for me I do that
because I think it might be good in modern terms and I don't tend to read the stuff but I think we
crap um or more accurately I don't tend to engage with stuff I think I won't enjoy which
probably more since but yes I I want to respond to that with two things the first is that I discovered
that brief encounter which I had never seen was on YouTube and I thought oh you know I should
watch this and I watched it about the first two minutes of it and it was so fantastically it's
not the first two minutes but the first the setup probably about the first six or seven minutes
and it was so fantastically good I thought right I'm gonna stop this I'm gonna watch this on my
television with my daughter who will also enjoy it and and we did watch it and it's fantastic you
should see it but also it's very influential and also some of the things in it are not at all quite
what I expected them to be um and and I had obviously a lot of received information about what happens
in briefing count a lot all of which is correct um because these classics have kind of permeated
our world but the other thing is that I've just started to watch for the first time um one of the
most influential works of the last 30 years which is Father Ted um and I don't know whether it's any
good or not but I do know that for much of my adult life people have been quoting bits of it at me
and and in fact the set of stamps um celebrated Father Ted has just been released in Ireland
and I thought it might be time to watch it before it completely descends beyond the pale I observe
the stamps while having many good quotes that I knew from the series like it's an ecumenical matter
do not include small and far away or or um arse feck girls drink arse feck girls which I thought
were very memorable quotes from the series that I've not seen I don't think I'm ever going to be
able to watch it because whenever I um think about Graham Linen's art I think about Graham Linen
and then I want to punch things okay so I'm not going to stop using Gil's Sans and I'm not going to
stop the difference is that Gil is dead Graham Linen still has a huge following on Twitter I think
when he dies I might be able to come back to it but for now it just makes me too cross the death
of the author is a lot easier when the author is dead which is surprisingly coherent both in a
metaphorical and a literal sense that's quite clever isn't it um I'm quite proud of that you
know that's quite good um but yes so I am I'm not going to stop using Gil Sans no but I I take the
point I do take the point no I mean I have I have some father Ted DVDs that I have bought in charity
shops because I'm clever by um I haven't watched them I dare to it's not but I don't think you can
enjoy the output of horrible people um he says having recently purchased an awful lot of HP Lovecraft
fiction uh an HP Lovecraft as we all know uh problematic in the uh to say the least I think we
say racist John so so readers write in that listeners write it and tell us should I wait to
watch father Ted until Gravelin has his dead or should I watch it now so I can catch up with
the jokes my friends have been making for 25 years in Lovecraft's defenseless he wasn't only
racist he was incredibly sexist as well so he was off his time he wasn't off his time his wife left
him because of how objectionable he was for his time he was an odious racist sexist twat even in
the early 20th century and you're obsessed with his product well now I'm obsessed with with the FFT
take on it which does an awful lot to reclaim the sexism and racism and make it not that um but
this is a discussion that comes up in in the Arkham community every once in a while and there was
always the hardcore saying oh but he was he was for the old days everyone was like that no no they
weren't that's the that's the that is that is number one rule of old racism sexist but not everyone
was like that and so I can't remember all you are but I don't think Raymond in his that much older
than you are so even assuming that you have a slightly longer life expectation um as woman I would
probably uh watch it now rather than watch it when you're on your deathbed
do you think I should not watch it at all because of him being a dick I think it's hard
to say because I watched it he's younger than me the f***er sorry I would do that again he's
younger than me the f***er I I mean I I think it's hard to say because I watched it multiple times
I think unloved it but I haven't seen it for several years and I'm not sure now if I re-watched it
whether I would feel it had been permanently tainted by linen I guess I'd have to try and re-watch
some too disarveed but mostly mostly I've been re-watching the father-tared Christmas special
every Christmas for a few years because it's on 27 times every Christmas I just I just want to
say like I'm not saying Alison shouldn't watch father-tared I'm saying that it makes me angry
which is not a reason not it's not a reason for other people you should feel free to watch father-tared
because it will not make me angry if you do it's just that I feel angry about Graham
Linnehan and so I avoid things that remind me that I am angry about him which is slightly I think
a slightly more nuanced take I hope you know how we were talking about the retrohuko originally
I was going to say one benefit of kind of decoupling this effort of people to go and reevaluate the
science fiction of the past and put a lot of effort into saying which ones are still worth reading
and which ones may be a less worth reading um if we decouperate from the retrohuko's then there's
no reason you can't just keep doing it the problem with the retrohuko's as the the hook for it is
we've nearly finished doing the retrohuko's there's like three years left to go there's no reason
why you couldn't say right we want to have this general effort to get people to read and reevaluate
the science fiction of 50 years ago and to have it as some kind of group effort and award something
if you want to but you could keep going maybe we need to introduce the retro retrohuko's where
we go back to years where the hugos were rewarded and do them again properly that could be interesting
as like a break off property yeah I think I said that with a straight face yes
um yes so we were discussing um reading older works of genre in light of the retrohuko awards
and one thing that has kind of become apparent is that sometimes in today's modern world one can
end up in a situation where one needs to have a think about the extent to which the attitudes of a
creator behind a piece of art one likes affects one's enjoyment of that art so we've already discussed
Graham Linnerhan and Father Ted in light of his recent um discussions on on twitter um and there
are other myriad examples um so do either of you have kind of instances in which something you are
a fan of has turned out to be the work of someone who you might not personally be a fan of oh yes good
yeah I mean that was not the perfect open question oh I was very afraid you might just not say yes
I but I will hold up my hands I should have done a battle I do actually I remember the first time
I discovered that this was a thing because I was a great fan of a YA author called Jan Mark
who wrote a number of excellent science fiction stories for um for young adults I mean that are
actually quite stretchy and I was a young adult at the time I mean not a child which is what we
but you know I was kind of in my early 20s and she came to one of the mexicans and turned out to be
really pretty ghastly in a number of respects um I was I was quite taken aback because we didn't
have the internet at the time so you you didn't know whether the people who stuff you liked were
nice or not but and she wasn't kind of horrible in the kind of I have horrible views on the internet
way because we don't didn't have the internet then she just was kind of not very nice in person and
I think I hadn't really addressed this question of whether you should um divorce people's work
from how they are as a person um death of the author when we talk about it normally means
more generally the question about whether you should take the art as it stands or take into account
the things that the author has said about that art um so it's not just about whether the author is
somebody who you would not want to spend any time with but I mean what I took from that there's of
course I should ignore what people are like as humans when enjoying their work and I have mostly
tried to do that ever since um but actually there's some really horror people out there
and feel free to not read any more Harry Potter books um I like Harry Potter even less than I like
the Marvel Cinematic Universe if that's helpful so um one of the really like so so recently we were
having a discussion in a in a discord somewhere we were having a discussion about um I I was
disappointed that Retri-Hoo goes had not been awarded for 1939 because um it would have been a
good chance to um give or to nominate the Enchanted Wood which is the first in the Faraway series by
Enid Blightiness like it's the first book I remember reading as a kid and I I've always had
enormous amount of enormous amount of affection for it and obviously Enid Blighten is like a very
very divisive figure in terms of her frequent use of golly fucks in her stories and like her stories
are um overtly sexist um because obviously you have George who has a short hair and is therefore
a top boy and wants to be a boy and then people keep telling her she can't be as good as a boy
because she's a girl and it's like you know I don't know the extent to which that reflected the
thinking at the time versus the extent to which that reflected specifically Blighten's thinking
um but it's certainly not a opinion anyone should hold in modern times and those books still selling
and have been edited like revives to make them slightly less egregious but um but it's still
potentially a problem um and certainly one of the things was but you know Blighten was famously
sexist and racist so she probably shouldn't be awarded or or um fated by the community um and
it's really interesting because I haven't really thought about Blighten's um the problematic nature
of her I haven't read her books since I was a kid um and it does it does really reflect like
yeah to me those books weren't ever about what she thought they were about like the stories in
them and I really did kind of jar because obviously as an adult I read things with uh bearing in
mind what the author is trying to say and and kind of like who the author is as a result um but as
a kid I didn't really read like that and so yeah it was a bit of a kind of oh yeah I guess that's true
um I mean I still I still think the far away tree books are amazing um but I haven't read them for
20-25 years now so perhaps I am wrong good plan yeah I mean that's the thing isn't it
I mean especially when you're reading like children's books as an adult I'm not sure that I would
benefit from doing that um Liz how has your affection for work's been ruined by learning more about the
world? Hmm it's a thing you had to frame this so like you I read an awful lot of Enid Blighten as
a child um and the one thing I remember that really kind of I see in a different light now is there's
a set of books called um The Secret Something so they start off with The Secret Island where they
run away and uh hide on an island and I remember they end up with a cow in a cave but the main thing
is that there is one called The Secret Mountain um where they accidentally like crash land in a
remote part of Africa and you know go and befriend a tribe and the way they do it I remember something
like they they remember there's going to be an eclipse and so they pretend to get out of
gun and shoot the sun and you know the the people there are so amazed by it and so terrified by it
that they you know um let them go and you know when I read it while I was probably you know eight or
nine I just read it without blinking but now of course it's a ridiculously stereotyped view of
Africa as a place you know where these um you know primitive tribal people live which is completely
wrong so I don't know quite where I'm going with that but like that's completely wrong then I think
exactly I think this is when you're thinking about Death of the Ortho because obviously
some of the things here are historical work that you're reading in contact and you do draw a
distinction between um well I draw a distinction between um so Kipling is often criticized for
this sort of thing but Kipling was very much reflecting that A his his depictions of both
Africa and India are quite nuanced in many ways but also he was reflecting um the the
moorings of his time and then other things like oh is it tintin in the Congo?
Tissin in the Congo is the racist one terrible even if we're brand new you know they and and
so there is a thing about when you're looking at historical things um people who are writing in
their time will often write things that you look at now and go oh well that's that's extraordinary
it's extraordinary that anyone could have had those thoughts um but when you're sort of reading
as an adult you should be able to set those thoughts into context um it's really you know I've
talked about this before I think possibly on podcast about reading um reading the Roman philosophers
and and how at one point they'll be writing something that completely resonates with the way we think
today and then in the next point they'll be um talking about the proper way to admonish your slaves
and and it moves seamlessly from one to the other and you just have to kind of be able to say oh
but that is a thing that is a thing that is a way that our thinking has changed um I always wonder
when I'm when I'm reading people complaining about um this sort of thing whether it hasn't
occurred to them that I think you might change back and historically it will change back humans
don't aren't endlessly progressive yes no and I think I think um I don't know it's difficult like
I know that I know that this is this is often used as a defense of people like oh they were you know
they were a product of their time and I think that it's true you do have to bet that I'm not
very and I but I do also think that there is a tendency to use that as an excuse not to interrogate
the problematic aspect aspects of works sometimes and I think you've got to be careful to use that
as a way of interpreting the text without forgiving it um if that makes sense and I think you know um
I think in terms of like the three of us like where we say oh but that was like reasonable for
the time we're not saying and that means it should be read uncritically now um but I know I've seen
people in some internet for a being like yeah but it was fine then so just don't think about it and
it's like no those two things are actually separate arguments which are not um there's not a not a
good argument for each other um when I when I first read the Harry Potter books I was starting to become
concerned by representations of slavery and fabcy and science fiction which is something which has
continued to concern me I don't know whether I've talked about it here but whenever you're reading a
genre book you well I feel as well as thinking of course what role do women have in this in this
work which is the thing that drives me so bananas about the MCU um it's not the only thing but the
other thing is how is the work getting done and the answer in a lot of fantasy is oh it turns out
we have some slave class that does all the work and that's not good and the answer in a lot of
science fiction is um it turns out that ais are doing all the work and which is a slave class and
that's not good and when I first read Harry Potter which is a book which our books intended for
children I I think it was about I read about the first four and then I said to a friend of mine
who was very knowledgeable in the field but there is a slave class in this book there are happy
slaves and I don't like books with happy slaves in them um and my knowledgeable friend said look
how good a writer rolling is and look at the way in which she has brought these disparate elements
this is clearly something that she has introduced to the novels in order that it will be turned around
by the end of the arc and anyway I'm here to say in 2020 no it wasn't and no she didn't and you need
to be every time there's every time there's a slave class in a book designed for children you need
to go what is this saying what does this person mean it is not convenient to say oh we have happy
slaves or women or or ais who do all the work quietly so that the important characters get
on with the plot um the work has to get done and if it's not getting done there is a thing that is
wrong with your books now and I do think in general like the problem that that I think that the
problem with rolling in a lot of ways and I'm kind of ignoring for a moment the recent problems with
Rowling is that I think for a while she wanted to be seen to be much more progressive than her works
actually were stuff like saying Dumbledore was gay or saying like Hermione could be black
all felt like unearned things that she had just decided oh yeah like if I just say that's true now
without having done anything to substantiate it I'll get all the plaudits for being progressive
without actually having to have made any progressive concessions in my work and I think what we're now
seeing is that she is not as progressive as many people wanted her to be but I don't I was always
highly skeptical of the fact okay so so nobody as progressive as many people would want sure but
you knew what I meant so it was a fine sentence I do um the but I think what we're finding now is
that or sorry I think what I'm finding now is that my skepticism about her attitudes towards
social progress um and whether or not she was actually um just kind of hitching her um riding a
bandwagon versus actually reflecting things she thought in her works I think I was right to be a
bit skeptical of that because it does turn out that perhaps she's not um her works I think reflect
how she thinks and I think other people interpret them and say oh this could be true she's like yeah
why not that doesn't hurt the narrative but I think it's almost like the author trying to make
the work look more progressive than it is it as opposed to sort of almost in opposition to the
author's views outside the work tarnishing your view of the work if that makes sense and then
obviously recently she's kind of turned out to be a bit more transphobic than one would ideally
one a writer of hugely popular children novels to be I think it's progressiveness um so so there
is a kind of there is an issue with people on the internet and particularly on twitter expecting
everybody that they like to be perfect and people are not in fact perfect and rolling has many good
points like for example um she's given a lot of money away and she's relentless in her support of
progressive economic policy and um supporting um actual left-wing politicians and things like that
and all of this is quite good and like many she's not that old but like many older women who
um have an understanding of the history of feminism particularly in the history of feminism
Britain they've got some they've got a transphobic edge and that's where that's coming from um
who knows if she'll come to her senses I suspect probably won't but there we go um but
I think it's quite odd to say oh people have to be perfected everything before we'll um
before we'll say we still like their stuff I think my main feeling is that there is kind of more
stuff out there for me to watch and read and engage with than I will ever get to and I think it is
perfectly legitimate if people want to say actually I don't want to read this person's books I think
this person has views I find a warrant and that is basically fine with me I think we all get to
choose what what we engage with and if that's your reason for not engaging with it then I'm
completely fine with it if you decide that you don't want to read Harry Potter books or you
never want to read the cormor and strike books because of things JK Rowling has said then that's
okay with me I do find it difficult when people who make works I really like later on turn out to
have been in some way just terrible people um I think the latest example of this was uh Shane
Karuth who has you know made primer a film I like very much um but then then basically sort of leaked
kind of leaked in a and a tweet with a picture of an album in he left a piece of paper in there
what must be deliberately leaking the fact that his um ex-girlfriend had a restraining order against
him as her new film was coming out um which is just a really icky thing to do and kind of makes
you think a lot less of him and it makes me I think now less interested in what works he will make
next but I'm not sure it makes me less I'm not sure it makes me like the film he's already made less
no that's I think that's fair because I think and I think this is like a thing I think we need to get
I think something that it will be healthy if we can arrive at is a way of forgiving ourselves for
liking things that are problematic in a way that doesn't mean we no let me I am worried that
sometimes we alienate people who like things by saying you're not allowed to like that thing
because the person who did it is an idiot and they're like but I like the things or I'm going to ignore
you and I do think that it will be good um people do I think there is a benefit to be able to say
I appreciate you like this thing and I'm not judging you for like this thing but I do think
you should think about the fact that the person who did it is a cockwombal and um you know you might
want to um you might want to think about like what it means to actually support them and stuff
without saying but that while still saying but that doesn't mean you can't like the thing you
like because I think if someone says you can't like that thing and you like the thing your initial
reaction is we'll go away whereas if you say you could like that figure that's fine but like
there's this other thing that maybe you should consider perhaps that's like a good way of getting
people into thinking about these issues in a way that's less confrontational so perhaps that's
actually like a healthy thing but I'm also um open to the um kind of counter-suggestion that if you say
well if I had to like things that are made by problematic people then that does open the door
to continuing to financially support those problematic people in a way that may not actually help
social progress in any meaningful way so it is a it's a really really really difficult tightrope I
think um and it's really really hard and so I do sympathize with you Liz because like there are
people who are problematic who made stuff I like as we've discussed um I love I love the book end
as game I do not love the author of the book end as game um there are things in end as game that
I realized were problematic after I learned more about the author of the book end as game but like
that's that's true of all of card's writing that I really really liked a lot of his early short stories
and some of his early novels and I again I benefited hugely from then not being an internet at the time
because I had read a lot of card before I realized how generally odd he was as a person and then
once you know that it is actually hard to reread this stuff without bearing that in mind he is
someone whose worldview colors his work to a degree that's I mean I can't believe I didn't
notice it in the first place to be honest but there you go I wasn't a very subtle reader
I'm probably still not that's fair no I didn't I didn't notice there are things where people
are like but how do you not notice this and I'm like well now you've said out loud and linked it
like that I see that it's a problem but at the time I was just like oh this has lasers in that
was the secret episode out of time of Oct thought the podcast but for now it is goodbye from me
it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
I think that probably wraps it up right we appear to be recording for an hour and 51 minutes
and there's cricket on later so I got to start getting my uh got to start getting my cricket
cricket mood I was quite amazed by how much I enjoyed the cricket when I watched it I happened
to be in a house where the cricket was on I kind of enjoy watching it I enjoy watching it when it's
on and I think you're kind of like it's on and you're part of out doing other stuff and maybe
you chat to people as well and then there'll be like a flurry of excitement and then you go back
to other things the fourth day of the first test against Pakistan against Pakistan it was
absolutely riveting throughout from the beginning to the end there was no there wasn't really any
time apart from lunch and tea when you might have done something else because it was it was
extraordinarily good you know this was my realization in the two 2005 ashes I saw I was vaguely aware
of cricket and I thought it might be something I could be a fan of but I hadn't really thought
much about it and then I watched and then I I decided I was going to put the cricket on at 11
and just watch until I got bored and at 6 p.m I got up and thought oh I should probably eat something
and I think for me there is something about that asymmetry of the game and the way that the strategy
unfolds over such a long time that just makes it riveting in a way that other sports don't do for me
I think it might be the same reason I really like board games because I liked Netrunner and that was
an asymmetrical board game and I liked it a whole lot and I do wonder whether cricket scratches a lot
of those same itches but in with sexy men uh so yeah not that quins from shut up sit down isn't a
sexy man because um I'm at Lee's whoa sorry what's that got to do with I'm just daydreaming about sexy
men now Alison oh well that seems perfectly reasonable I'm I was watching Black Panther
speaking of sexy men and I was like why why are they doing this ritual combat by the edge of a
waterfall and Marianne was like because it makes them wet mum yeah I'm gonna go and watch the
bicycle racing which is good if you like men with a very particular body shape and extremely bad
tan lines I don't like I find because Australia Ozzy Rules football the men were really lovely
and I think it's because it's a very good whole body workout cycling they're not quite my type
but I do like cycling is another thing that that some people think is boring and I'd watch kind of
highlights of cycling and found it boring but then if I go and watch the Tour de France I find it
it's completely fine so I can watch it for hours and hours and hours and hours that is indeed what
I'm going to do this evening while John watches the Gricket the theme music for this episode was
Surf Shimmy by Kevin MacLeod and CombeTech.com used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license
this podcast will end at the beep beep