Sorry, sorry, did I just make you? Did I just make you choke on some ice? I did not mean to.
No, no. I have very long ice cubes at the moment because...
Of the heat.
No, because I bought some trays that I thought would work as like single serving soup...
...freezing.
And they're too small for that, but they do make basically giant ice cube cuboids.
[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 108th episode of Octa Thorpe, a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom...
...which is coming to you on the 25th of April 2024. I'm John Coxon...
I'm Alison Scott...
...and I'm Liz Batty.
And we have some letters of comment.
In fact, we have a bumper mailbag due to not doing any letters of comment while you guys were at EasterCon.
Yes.
We got some quick comments on Blue Sky.
Nula got "Why don't you love me out of the library?"
And I think we made them sand.
I'm sorry, I hope you enjoyed it as well, but yeah, it's quite traumatizing.
And we also heard from Raj, who is recommending a place where John can go and get pizza crunch.
What's pizza crunch?
It came up.
It's something I heard about on a podcast I listened to called Octa Thorpe.
They had a recent episode in EasterCon where they discussed it.
But it is where you deep fry pizza.
Also deep fry pizza has a name that's not just deep fry pizza.
Yes.
It's pizza crunch.
OK, I understand that.
I'm a bit slow and I'm old, so it's hard for us to adopt new vocabulary.
I'm looking forward to eating some bar-spark crunch when I'm in Glasgow.
Oh, we're done with it's called "Milesbar", yeah.
Think it's only pizza.
It's not a specific name.
Yes, Scots people, right in.
I think it's just for pizza.
It's not like a generic "Anything Deep Fried" is something crunch.
Fish crunch.
If listeners are interested to hear a detailed discussion of the deep frying of chocolate bars in Scotland,
the episode of the Off-Menu podcast with Ian Stirling has a detailed discussion of the form
and is thoroughly interesting.
Are the glass regions going to write in or are they just going to be angry at John quietly?
Hi, Meg.
We had a letter from Andy Openshore.
Long-time listener, first time writer, maybe, said he finds Octa thought really helpful to get
insight, which seems strange to me, but there we go.
And he's coming to Glasgow, so we will see you there, Andy.
He said, "Based on our recommendations, he has started watching For All Mankind,
and he observes its similarities to Mary Robblett Coals, the Lady Astronaut Series."
I don't think it's as similar as all that, but yes, I think he says the similarities are evident
and was one inspired by the other.
And I think many people have talked about this on the internet, who know a lot more about it than we do, Andy.
And do you think the existence of For All Mankind might prevent a TV film adaptation
of the Lady Astronaut from happening? You can never tell really, because sometimes books that
like each other make it more likely that adaptations happen, and sometimes they make it less likely.
That wasn't very profound.
And said one of the great positives of the book is the inclusion of a trans character,
and appreciated that about the adventures of Amina L. Sirafi, which I have not read yet.
But we'll be reading soon, ready for our Hugo episode, which has become a tradition now, I think.
Andy asks whether or not there are other examples of historical SFF that have
sort of foregrounded trans people in. I confess I do not read much historical SFF.
I mostly read the SFF with lasers in, so if anyone does and has any recommendations,
please write in, and we will convey them to Andy.
Finally, the only other Hugo novel he's read yet is Some Desperate Glory by Emily Tesh,
and he thinks it's fab and has wondered, wonders if any of the Octa thoughts have read it,
and if so, what do you think? And I would refer you back to the episode where I picked it,
which is...
And obviously you have used the spreadsheet to work out what episode that was, because you saw
that co-egg and thought I need the episode of... Well, though. All right, so fun fact, as Alison says,
Liz picked it in episode 100, because Alison picked the coral bones that episode,
not Some Desperate Glory. I read it after Liz picked it, Pollock. Yes!
I am the trendsetter here. You have mentally decided you picked it because you liked it.
I did like it. Good. We will come back to the Hugo finalists in a future episode before
the voting deadline, so that we can tell everyone what we thought.
I will note that, um, For All Mankind fails to get on the Hugo ballot this year, which I think...
I mean, I didn't like the series very much, so I can't really argue with it, but I think it
probably got knocked off because there's several Doctor Who's and Strangely Worlds on there.
Yeah, no, no, um, I think when we discussed this in our nominations episode, you said you didn't
like For All Mankind season 4, and I was like, "Oh, I can see that it might not be quite as
sharp as season 3, but I think it's... I feel like it's setting things up for a season 5 that might
not happen." So, you know. That will happen. They announced that season 5 Anna spinoff, did you see?
A spinoff? Yeah, Star City, which sounds interesting.
Spinoff of Russia leading up to the Russian moon landing. Oh, that sounds so good!
It sounds way better. I'm way more excited for that than for season 5 of For All Mankind,
to be honest, but... But despite just being you going, "Oh, you loved it when it was kind of
alternate history," but now it's like possible future, it's less exciting.
I think it's that... It's not because it's possible future. It's because the characters are
no longer as interesting. Because this is the problem with For All Mankind, right? It's
trying to basically do a very long time span by keeping in familiar characters,
and it just leads to ludicrous situations. And then when they've introduced new characters,
I don't think they've been done half as interestingly as the old ones were.
So... And the original characters' natural arc has very much come to an end in most cases.
Yeah. I've not watched... I've not watched season 4, but having been watching season 3,
I am genuinely baffled that they are doing a season 5, because it does very much feel like
season 3 could be the end of the natural arc of most of those characters. And I don't really
understand how you get two extra seasons out of it, but we will see. Yeah, six seasons in a movie.
It feels like a roleplay campaign that no one really wants to end, but the best days are behind
it in a way, coming from a perspective of sheer ignorance, obviously. We also heard from Christopher
Jay Garcia. Thank you to Chris, among other things, he's never heard of Maundy Thursday,
we'll way back before he's to come in Chris Letter, chronology, by the way. He's never heard of Maundy
Thursday before, and he says it's also WrestleMania Thursday. So I do propose that we rename Maundy
Thursday to WrestleMania Thursday. He has that in common with Whisper AI, which also does not
recognise Maundy Thursday. Ask me how I know, transcription software. Does it think it's
WrestleMania Thursday though? Yeah. It does not change Maundy to WrestleMania, however, I'm going
to go and do a global search and replace on previous transcripts, which will now confuse people.
Where do you get that pull request, John? I'm not accepting a pull request. John, can I have
admin rights? Then I can turn down our listen, pull request, please. Chris also points out that
transcripts are very useful for historian types because they're very easily searched. Yeah.
He also says that he is starting to record podcasts again, but in true Garcia standard,
he doesn't listen before he publishes. Chris also emailed in on Octor Blive.
Shall I do just selected quotes from Chris's email? British people are just weird.
Burn down the business meeting. I'm infinitely funnier in my head, and is Telford in San
Jose. Did you explain that last one? Yeah. The last one is because he says a
town full of low to mid-range chain restaurants is Telford in San Jose. I just thought it was
funnier to leave out the context. You were correct. I'm sorry. I did suggest on an
anonymous Claire, the Nando's Index for Eastcon bids, and I'm sticking by it.
A hypothetical Newcastle Gates head, Eastcon venue would have a Nando's Index of four. So this is
proof if needed that this is just a very good indicator of quality of venue. He throw gets zero.
What is going on in Newcastle Gates head? Why do you have so many Nando's? I thought you would
be very high on like the Greg's Index, but not the Nando's. I have already said surely it has a
Greg's Index. Oh, mate, you want to know how many you want to know how many Greg's are there?
God, I'll tell you the answer to that. There's way more than four.
Can you never more than a six foot from a Greg's in Newcastle? I'm proud. There are also a variety
of very lovely restaurants, but it is a big city and therefore it has Greg's and Nando's
in many equal measures. I think the Greg's Index would be one, two, three, four, five, six,
seven, eight, nine, ten, eleven, twelve. I think it'd be thirteen walkable, although some
are more walkable than others. Right. I hope John is now investigating a Newcastle Gates head
bit where we can all go out for a cheeky Nando's. Raj wrote to us on Mastodon as well. It seems
like Blue Sky is for Pizza Crunch and Mastodon is for serious commentary. I don't know whether
that's true. Raj says he enjoyed Nicholas White as stunt Liz and loved the April Fool's Hugo trophy,
but then says, "I do think declining the nomination is a classy move on Bigelest
Ticklers is part, but I'm not really sure how it got nominated in the first place. That whole
thing was funny, but I'm not convinced a tweet was worth the best-related work nod."
It's just such a weird grab bag category, and I think the more weird grab bag things get nominated,
people think, "Well, this is a grab bag for anything I liked in fandom last year."
But in previous years, we've had stuff like Firecon and Conziel and Fringe get nominated,
the judge are marching, can fuck off into the sun, SA got nominated, and various other things
have been nominated. And certainly over the pandemic, that got more common, it seems to me,
and this just seems to be another example of that. I'm very glad that the eventualist to finalist
is mostly things I can engage with as art and then work out, which is the best, which this is
actually the strongest slate, I think, for some time. I agree with that. I think 2021, it's possible
that there were fewer of the serious overarching books that we think are great in this category
than you would normally expect published in 2020, and that was the reason for more of the
memey things getting on the ballot in 2021. To the long list. I think it's just, you know,
there are things that people want to celebrate, but I still think of best-related workers being
like, you know, it's the one place on the Hugo ballot we can celebrate essays and works of
criticism and art books, of which there are, you know, a good number of really interesting ones.
And so it's a shame to kind of have like a tweet that went viral in a very interesting and fun,
but totally random manner. I don't know, it's how am I supposed to judge that against an actual,
like retrospective book of critical essays across someone's career?
And fortunately you don't have to. Fortunately I don't have to, so I favor keeping it towards
that end of things.
When I was saying 2021, Firecon and Consi-land Fringe pushed Liam McCormack's biology and manners,
essays on Lois McMaster-Bajold and Burrows is the magic of Terry Pratchett off the ballot,
both of which I think would have been better presences on the finalists late than two conventions
that were never going to win the award. And indeed they did not. So yeah.
Because that's the other thing. When voters get their hands on best-related work,
Alison is right. Like the memes tend to be unlikely to actually clinch the win.
Consi-land Fringe came below no award in Best Related in 2021 and Firecon did better.
But this year it seems good.
Yep, no it's got some great things on it. It's a good award. Oh sorry, it's a good slate.
And I'm very glad to see a travel in time, the critical practice of Maureen Kincaid's
speller on the ballot. But I do wish we had celebrated Maureen Kincaid's speller when she was alive
instead of waiting until it was too late. So one of the nominees for Best Related Work is a
travel in time, the collected works of Maureen Kincaid's speller. And unfortunately, obviously,
Maureen will not be with us at the time of the Hugo Awards. So I think it is a shame that there
was no collection of her work during her lifetime. But maybe this is going to change in future with
criticism because I noticed that Briardine Books, Friends of the Podcast, have announced their
second collection of essays. That was the exact point I was going to make, which is that the sad
thing here is that Maureen's work wasn't collected in her lifetime despite being eminently suitable
for it. And I think had Neil been publishing books, these amazing books, she's obviously
one of the people that he'd have looked at to publish. Yes, but now we can also plug to let his book.
Yeah, so he's publishing Abigail's book, which I think John has copy edited. Is that right John
or laid out or both? I don't- I type set. Type set. Yes, it is coming. Yeah, no, I have pre-ordered it.
Oh, we have had a lock in real time. Do you want the real time lock?
Meg McDonald. Oh. In chat, she says, "Letter of comment from the Peanut Gallery. I appreciate
that you all have suitably dirty laughs. This is presumably an opt-to-thought live."
So, presumably you two and Nicholas have dirty laughs and I have a very clean one.
Yes, I mean, I feel like it's that- because Nicholas does have quite a- quite a dirty laugh,
in fact. Well, that's the feedback we are getting from our audience. So, is Nicholas regretting being
on opt-to-thought live yet? He probably was at the time someone climbed under a table.
I like the use of the word "yet" as if it's a foregone conclusion that he will regret it.
It's just a matter of when. I do understand that he has written to the other lovely podcast
find list. Hello, lovely, other lovely podcast find list if you're listening, offering to go on
their podcast. Oh. That is screw-pulously fair of him. That is very fair. It's tricky, right? Because
yeah, no, that is fair. I like that. At the live show, I asked people to write in with their thoughts
on the accessibility of the EastCon venue and I specifically asked DC in a chance encounter in
the hallways before that and DC is very kindly obliged and written as a lock. I will publish the
full lock on my website and I will link it from the show notes because it'll be good if people can
go and read it in its entirety but I will pick out some key bits and bobs here and we can go through
it and then we will segue seamlessly into wider discussion of the EastCon and the EastCon venue.
DC wrote in to say, the first thing to say is that there are problems. If you're a non-ambulatory
wheelchair user, if you need assistance in the toilet or if you need a hoist transfer, then there
are real problems with the venue and yet this remains one of the best venues, if not the best
in total for wheeled users and then they say deep sigh. And so yeah, DC's perspective is very
much this is a flawed venue. This is a venue that has problems but it is probably the best venue we
have been to as an EastCon if you require access in a wheeled conveyance and then they go into more
details about that. So DC says, the location of the centre has challenges, it's in quite a hilly
area and some of the road and footpath surfaces aren't even, the routes to the centre of Telford
and in the other direction to the onsite hotels both involve in places steep gradients and the route
to the onsite hotels is not well illuminated at night, there's a lot of unevenness in the surface.
There is at least one curb which is supposed to be dropped and isn't. People have been talking
about this in some conversations I've seen but this does seem to be a recurring feature of the
criticisms. They did seem to be doing work on the path from the conventions enter to the onsite
hotels so I assume that that will improve things but I don't know. Some of these factors are relevant
to other people as well as people with disabilities so the fact that the night time routes are badly
lit is relevant for lots of people, not merely people who are who have mobility issues and that
all of the routes to the all of none of the hotels are quite on site so everybody has some
walking to do to get to their accommodation but again overall I thought this venue had a lot
going for it for people with a range of needs.
And I think it's also, Levitation had like an access audit on their website. I think it shows
the importance of doing the access audit not just in your venue but someone ideally needs to like
walk from the station to the venue at night and see if it's got unusual humps on the path or it's
on lit or anything like that. And then I guess ideally someone would also go to the site just
before the con to see if anyone has moved things around or if there is engineering work or if there
is building work or anything like that. Because yeah it's not just having an accessible venue it's
where the people can actually get to your accessible venue with any sort of ease.
It was clearly easier for people with mobility issues to be in the attached hotels rather than
the budget hotels that were a little way away. They were only about a five minute walk, a 10
minute walk late at night. But that might be something that a bursary that bursary payments are
useful for is bridging that gap for people who do need to be in the more expensive hotels
but would otherwise choose the cheaper ones.
Yeah I think Bradford, because we used to have split hotels for Bradford and I think there was a
process where if you had access needs you could be guaranteed a room in the main hotel but I don't
know how much help Bradford gave fans with the cost of that. Well the same for the Helsinki Worldcon.
We routinely give people access to close hotels but yes they're the most expensive ones and
and that's the that could be a significant for Telford it was a significant extra cost because
I always stay in the main hotel and I was like oh Prebirin looks good.
I was saying it was the same for the Helsinki Worldcon which has that one hotel attached to
the convention center which was quite expensive and everyone else was basically a train ride away.
But we did do some work going on to the trains and trams with wheelchair users
to see how easy it was to use those to get around and things like that. So then you could recommend
okay well if you don't want to stay in that expensive hotel this hotel is also suitable and
we have tested that there's a step free route on the trains and things like that.
No DC does say jumping towards the end of the lock. They didn't have a lot of interaction with
venue staff but when they did it was clear that the staff had had training about how to help people
with wheels and especially how not to which is also better than an average venue in DC's experience.
DC talks a little bit about the inside of the venue so the first unpleasant surprise is that
there are slopes in the building and you can't get to the passenger list without going up a
slope on the ground floor. They're not very steep but it's a bit of effort that would really be
better and then on the first floor there's another slope which is on the first floor there's another
slope which is worse. It's steeper and carpeted and DC needed help to get up it every time they tried.
They say fans are pretty good offering help but it's not good that it's essential and I know Doug
Spencer has said on various places like if you need access to be provided like on request then it's
not access. I think the thing that as someone who is not disabled it's not helpful to say that in a
vacuum like if this venue is better than other venues I assume in other venues you also have to
ask for things and if you have to ask more than this one this one is still better even if it's
still not perfect and I guess part of the thing here is coming back to DC's point that this is
probably you know in the top tier of accessibility as far as East Comm venues go so like do bear in
mind listener that like you know if this sounds awful this is... think about how bad the other
places must be. I guess it's the point like think about the challenges that other venues must hold.
Telford seemed quite flat to me with the exception of the hill up to the town but I don't know why
they've put slopes in on the on the floors it might have been an unavoidable thing based on where
they were building. I felt one of the things I felt about the venue in terms of access provision
was that it was clearly built just before the point where all of this would have been done in
quite a different way and so things like there is no escalator from the ground floor to the first
floor and clearly there ought to be just staircases. The very small lift the internal slopes there
are quite a lot of internal places where you had a choice between us a fairly steep slope actually
or or steps and you just think well this is all the sort of thing that's been designed out of
buildings of this kind in the last 20 years so I don't know when it got built but it feels like
it was just before we started to take accessibility of this sort of space seriously.
So living in somewhere where access is I think a little bit behind the UK and probably where the
UK was you know 20-25 years ago they are in some places putting ramps in but the ramps are just
incredibly steep and I can't see anyone ever being able to self-propell up them and to be honest
they'd be quite hard to push a lot of people up them. Sometimes ramp is not ramp. Going to lift
there's only one passenger lift and there's a goods lift so the passenger lift is like a problem
because obviously if the lift breaks down a goods lift would be the only option. The goods lift was
the route people using mobility scooters had to use because the passenger lift was too small if
there were no staff they had to phone for someone to come and work the lift. I gather this went
mostly okay but sometimes there was a delay and they just had to wait for someone to come
and that is like another clear negative of the site. They do have planning permission for an
extension which would include a second lift but we don't know what the status of. That is but
DC does say in asterisks this is not the smallest lift we've had at an east convenue that is worth
bearing in mind again. The radison at e-throw has some tiny lifts. I do remember a site visit
watching someone basically maneuver a mobi in there to check you could actually get them in and it
did require a bit of skillful driving but I don't remember us breaking them at any point so we
probably did a quite a skillful job but they were kind of just big enough some of the lift at the
back. Then DC wraps up by saying they have a lot of detailed thoughts about toilets. Basically saying
the toilet provision is not great. They weren't terrible for DC but for someone significantly less
mobile would have much more of a problem and goes into a lot of detail on that and notes. I won't
go into all the detail but I will pull out this is the one aspect in which the TIC seems worse
than most other east convenues which is bizarre given the scope of the place that there really
needs to be an accessible toilet on each floor which is twice the size if not larger than any of
the existing toilets. So that is I think as far as I can tell that's the big criticism DC has of
the size is that the toilet provision is not up to snuff. There were some discussions of accessibility
in the lead up to the convention but I don't think anyone was annoyed about the toilets but
as far as I could tell the toilets are one of the worst bits so I did not know that thank you DC.
It's probably very easy to go oh there is an accessible toilet great and nothing quite the
fact that if you're on a different floor and you're only access to the toilet is a good
lift where you have to phone someone to get them to use it and that's also a big barrier to that.
DC sort of has some generic notes on east cons which is basically if a room has two doors
don't bolt one of the doors shut that seems like good coherent advice makes sense
and then the other one is when you have program rooms that are laid out in cabaret style that
can make it a lot harder for wheeled users and so when you do that I think we probably need to
have someone try and navigate the layout in wheels like prior to the convention starting to make
sure that it isn't pain in the arse for someone with wheels but yes those are good points as well.
Yeah I mean normally when we lay out cabaret style it's because we're expecting things to have
a slightly smaller you know an audience who will appreciate that but as maybe smaller than it
would be if you laid it out theatre style so it should be it should be possible to put a big
island there I'm just saying I mean I don't think we necessarily say oh access requires us to make
every every seat in that room capable of having a wheelchair at. I'm not a wheel user and I don't
have a lot to add to this I mean I think this is something we should take seriously I do think
as with everything on access it has to be balanced with the other access needs of the of the members
that you know we know that it's not always possible to accommodate all of the things that
everybody needs we we we took a view with conversation that we would be quite clear about what we could
and could not accommodate as a standard in advance and then if people needed more than that we would
see what we could do to help. And so that kind of segues into something the 2024 committee has
said that Telford was the cheapest venue they looked at to run their east con in and I assume
that it is true that if we were using a more expensive venue it would be more modern and it would
have less of these problems and part of this might get into a discussion in the future on a future
episode on the expense of holding east con then you get into a thing of kind of discussing very
carefully the implications for wealth privilege in the community and that is a discussion we will
have in the future if you have any thoughts on that please do let us know.
We've been talking about Telford listeners Telford Telford.
I had never been to Telford I don't think. I've been to the KFC in Telford on account of how
it's a convenience stopping place when I go cotaging it turned out the hotel that I had booked for me
in España and that near the nick then decided to book was opposite that KFC so I felt right at home.
Telford's fine like you know. Well and that's the other thing transport privilege right where
Telford is three and a half hours away from everywhere which sounds great until you realize it's not
that it's up to three and a half hours away from everywhere it is literally three and a half hours
away from everywhere. It says it's within three hours of 90 percent of the country and people were
like oh they don't mean Scotland but in fact 90 percent of the population I can believe but
it's kind of perfect travel time most people it's gonna take longer than three hours much of the time
because it'd be telling us I think two hours 48 minutes right up until we left the house on
boardy Thursday. How did you find traveling to Telford Liz? It was good I just opened up
my members portal and I clicked on the link and I could wait for people in the auditorium
in several cases I WhatsApp them to say I can see you which probably did not go down as well as I
thought it would have. Yeah I think people maybe did not realize that the streaming was streaming
the panel rooms before the panel opened and they were showing the audience but it was nice to see
people. We did that last year too. I think we might be moving gently into the online bit but we do
want to say a little bit about the members portal because I've been doing catch up and the members
portal which was put together by Andrew January and means that you have a kind of seamless
integration that means you're logged into the discord and the ring's central events and the guide
all at once and you can just carry on watching your catch up without having to continuously
re-authenticate or wonder where you left it. It was one link that had links to everything else.
It was great. Well done Andrew. Yes I've having done some like online stuff for punctuation.
I am a little bit in awe of how much Andrew has done for levitation and I think he has an
eye towards trying to make some of this available for other conventions to use. So yeah it is but it
is like stuff like having a discord bot that can authenticate your discord account and then
make sure that you're always in the convention discord and building like the members portal as
you said and all of that is just very impressive stuff. And they meant that they didn't I was
watching the discord moderator's channel and they did not have to they were only like a few
a handful of people who had problems getting into the discord and everyone else found it smooth so
that's kind of good. Yeah it was great. Remember how much time and effort Acecons have had to put
into like checking everyone is actually on the members list and cross checking and making sure
everyone can join and making sure no one has two discord accounts in the wrong name.
It was so smooth I just clicked on it. I mean I've played it several times because discord is not
that smooth integrated but it did work. It's great. The other thing I really liked about the
members portal is it had a link to a tip jar for tipping the TIC staff without needing cash
because I always feel guilty when the hat comes around but the closing ceremony and I haven't
got any coins in my pocket because I haven't done fiers so having a place I could like tip
without needing any coins was very good. Yes that was great. I felt bad for several years
that I never managed to be organizing off to have a tip because yeah you never pay in cash anymore.
Unfortunately they closed the tip jar before I thought well I started to watch the catch up.
Oh there's a tip jar I should tip and discovered it was closed already so next time guys leave
have a tip jar that stays open or probably a second tip jar for people who are doing the catch up
and remembering that they should have tipped because that would be good. It may just be me
but I bet it's not. So I have been watching the catch up though this is a convention that
like a cheeky nandos has been repeating on me for weeks. I've never had members repeat on me
how dare you. Actually nandos is lovely. Wont hear a word said again but I would say
younger people have castor iron stomachs and older people just saying. Okay I've seen now. Fair enough.
Yeah so I have watched more easter con program than not merely at any time for the last several
years but possibly for every easter con combined but probably not quite. I used to watch quite a
lot of program at the beginning but I've watched a lot of program this year. I'll catch up. I've watched
I think about 14 or 15 items which is lots. I'm not counting octa thought live which I
woefully said I was listening to for the fifth time the other day but I think I am done with it now.
Only one of those was optional I think. The other four were mandatory. Yeah because
Alison does the transcript so has to listen to it to make sure it's okay to go out and then has
to listen to it to edit the transcript so. Yeah and then we also listen to it to the car coming
and then I listen to it with somebody at some point so there we go. Five. A lot. Two. Wait you
listen to it in the car coming home from easter con. Okay. Listeners cannot see lizzes absolutely
baffled face but take it from me it's great. Right so I have to force myself to listen to it
once to check it's okay and then I'm like no I never want to listen to myself again so. No no no
it wasn't wasn't me. We worked out that so one of the things that was good about re-essential
events is that it would stream the not all programs do this but it would stream the audio to the
car for carplay and I said right so we've got the catch up what does everyone want to listen to
and there was a chorus of oh could we do octa thought live please so it was my choice it was
my family I played my family I mean I enjoy that they were listening to it on catch up because
because they did not come to your program item. Stephen did come to the program item but don't
think Marianne and Jonathan did. Marianne and Jonathan didn't come to the program item and
Stephen I said Stephen to run some errands because we were trying to sort out the newsletter I think
at the same time yeah yeah so I don't really know what to watch on catch up because levitation has
not shared the catch up stats and I I mean this is a choice but in the same way that there was a
point where Nicholas said last time that the hugos belong to the voters I feel like these to come
belongs to its membership and it's clearly useful information for members to know what things are
getting views on catch up in the same way that they can see what program items are busy when they go
into the program room and I think that convention should release the catch up stats a take I mean
I think I think I agree I don't think I think it's a philosophical point for me so Alison when
you're trying to pick what program I used to watch live do you go into all the program rooms and
search one has the most people in and go and sit in that one sorry I feel like you you suggested
the time I choose to watch a program item live the time not actually on or required to be at yeah
no I'm just making the analogy if you're saying you know you should have the stats like you can see
how many people in a room is that how you actually pick program and I can also see the view that if
you are on an item and the catch up shows that basically no one has watched it then that could be
quite demoralizing just like if you're on a program item and two people come to watch it
except then the stats are there for everyone to see so I can see the argument against no I'm doing a
little bit of but actually if we're going to have convers I know that they've got the data and they
got the data on people in rooms as well if we're going to have conversations about what sorts of
things should be programming in particular what sorts of things we should be programming when
because one of the things about the convention is that they programmed a lot of very serious panels
really late in the evening and they program quite a lot of lighthearted stuff at 10 o'clock in the
morning and I would like to see more more thought when people are likely to want that sort of thing
so and this sort of data is useful I just like data really that's the thing I mean I like data
obviously but I think there is a philosophical argument here which is how much weight should we
put on what people want to watch by how much they watch on catch up and how much weight should we
give to what people watch when they are actually physically at the convention or indeed watching
not on catch up but live streaming from the con because they'll kind of give you an idea like do
if you put something serious on very late at night and no one actually goes to the room physically
but a bunch of people then watch on catch up later it probably still wasn't the right decision to
put it on at that time also I note that if I go to the conversation website there's no stats on
program watching on there either so no what we did last year was release was release the kind
of greatest hits we released the top ones which I think is is is a compromise here so there must
not miss items yeah I could see that it would be interesting to see kind of how they compare to
you know things watched on site versus things that were streamed and certainly like do more people
stream science program is there bits of program that no one ever wants to stream because that all
my I also be if you need to choose how many items you're able to stream then you can pick which one
people are less likely to watch and not stream it that kind of thing yeah I haven't seen your
the conversation list of top ones I would like to see that I think some of the information is
being shared with Glasgow which I think will be quite useful because I think they do have these
counts they know how many people streamed live and how many people were in the room and how many
people are watching on catch up and I think this is quite useful interesting data for program teams
yarrick yeah so I just had to guess and I have I've this is part of our kind of general argument I
have in general enjoyed the talks more than the panels I I would observe that most of the 157 items
on catch up are talks or panels there's not a lot of alternate things there are a few but there aren't
all that many I think it's worth noting that the room where a lot of the items that were happening
that were not really talks or panels was not being streamed also if one person if I have
person panel doesn't want to put on catch up then it's not on catch up whereas for talks only one
person has to grieve for it to be on catch up I mean I I'd be quite I think we're now at the point
where it would not be unreasonable to say that unless unless you've got something absolutely
amazing you can put on the program but with a with a person who won't let it be streamed or
catch up then I think that's okay but for everything else the rule should be if you want to be on
the program you're going to be all streaming and catch up I think my opinion on that is dictated
a little bit by percentages of how many people actually opt out very few because if like only
yeah like because like my impression of it is that it's less than 1% of people actually have a
problem with it and so yes I think that's probably fair but if it was like 25% I'd be like well no
you and that gets tricky I mean basically I guess my worry is if the percentages high enough that
you suspect it might be acting to remove diverse voices from program I'd probably think it was
problematic but I don't think it actually would do that so I think it would be fine I would be
paying attention to whether or not I thought my opinion on that was changing I guess is but
it's an interesting it's definitely an interesting sort of thing to talk about and also I think
obviously the benefit to widening participation in the people who can actually engage with the
program probably acts in such a positive way in terms of diverse voices that that probably
outweighs any penalty I'm not sure yeah I would say conversely the number of people opting out I
think is small enough that you don't bother about it we just have a handful of things that aren't
streamed that's okay or rather I think a lot of things there were in in this case it's not that
they weren't streamed I think it's that they were streamed but they're not available on
catch-up in some cases so you had to watch them live and I think that's fine how was the bar though
did everyone just go to bed when the bar closed no it's it worked really well it was great I have
a whole thing about this can I can I have a theory so Liz it was amazing I think it might have been
the besties to come bar I've ever been to and I have a theory as to why which was basically what
would happen was everyone would be sitting in the TIC and they'd be having a bevy and there was some
real ale until we drank it all and then like come half 10 or half 11 depending on the night we all
had to go over to the holiday inn and that was really good because it took everyone who had been
sitting where they were sitting through the evening and it jumbled everyone up and you saw people you
hadn't noticed we're in the bar and you got into new groups and then you went to the holiday inn you
sat down in different groups and you had entirely new conversations with different people and it
was so dynamic and great and I have no idea if it would scale with higher membership numbers
because the holiday inn is a finite space but the international hotels bar was almost empty so I
don't know whether we'd be able to sort of spread out I will say the beers in the hotels were fine
to pour but that was also quite good because it meant after I'd had sort of 15 beers by 11 I could
just switch to tap water and then when I got to bed I was only mildly pissed instead of utterly
stinking so yes I thought it was good the holiday inn were also pretty nice to us they clearly have
very great experience of people turning up after they've been kicked out of the TIC that is clearly
their entire business model and unlike some hotels that are in that position they just basically
were there they were very happy to sell beer to a lot of different people and it was comfortable
space I think yes a larger reason to call would have had to use both the bars the bar in the
international as well as the bar in the Hilton they stopped serving kind of two-ish it was fine
it was good what was your because my theory about the real ale was that they bought the right
about and it sold out and that's what should happen because it sold out about seven or six
o'clock on the Sunday which is about what you want I think um I think thought they probably needed
a little bit more real ale I agree with you that selling out of the real ale on the sunday is
probably desirable but I was a little bit grumpy that they sold out of all the nice real ale on the
Saturday and I feel that is a bit early it's the lopean brewery is fine um and it's the local brewery
so I appreciate I think having the local brewery is good but um but they don't necessarily have the
range of beers I enjoy as much claire brierly on the other hand did and then I was quite drunk
and I blame claire brierly okay oh oh that that night when we just locked ourselves in the newsletter
room and drank beer very rapidly for some time until all the lights went out Liz and then we were
like oh we should probably go to the holiday in that did you almost get locked in the newsletter
room oh we're light that'd be quite funny oh so pissed that was the night that I basically oh I
got I got very bawdled in the holiday in and and mowed at people and and totally because I believe
I'm quite a cheerful drunk so being a miserable drunk was very bad I I think um I think you're an
intense drunk I think you've definitely been a slightly mordling drunk at me I used to come
I'm afraid really sorry it's probably like in this like post-covid era whenever one was a little
bit more you know intense I would quite like the bar to be slightly more comfortable I mean not
the bar in the holiday in which was fine the bar in the self-ditch national center I like I like
proper chairs but I mean like any chairs are better than no chairs so you know yeah and wasn't
there a big faffet long-come that like convention centers are not filled with like a big abundance
of comfy chairs for bars yeah there were the same chairs that we had at long-corn in the bar area
but we had a lot of different seating options in that big fan village space so I think I do I do
wonder whether a larger East con would have been able to put more budget towards having some
comfier spaces but I think that's the sort thing that is fixable but might be tricky um
what was the membership by the way I maybe didn't read all the newsletters on site was something
like 450 yeah it's a really good size oh so quite but quite small as East con's go yeah very small
for at least god there are numerous venues that we don't look at because they're too small for
at least a call that you could have put that East con in practice because it ended up smaller
than we expected yeah how did you find the social side of things liz online or not really I didn't
mean you anything cool this was because I did not time shift so functional i was going to bed at
you know 6 p.m before anyone was really into party time but I also don't think there was much
arranged it was just I could join a discord voice channel and I am not sort of person to randomly
join discord voice channels while sitting at home and doing that if you want if you want social
events on your discord or or online spaces you have to actually have somebody whose job it is to
make those things happen it's it's quite a lot of work it's not something I could do whilst actually
going to a convention if I ever find I cannot go to conventions because of injury or illness I will
definitely volunteer for that job if I ever catch if I ever test positive for covid on
body Thursday I will spend my weekend sorting out online spaces at least god I mean it did feel that
the virtual vision was good and they had discord channels to chat in and I happily watched items
and chatted on discord with people who were in the room and that was all very nice
and so I felt the virtual option was quite reasonably priced for what I got but if I wanted like a
full social kind experience it wasn't really that on the plus side no one called me drunkenly
from the calm so I am winning there I mean I will drunkenly call you later thank you John
we kind of texted you during the panel though didn't we um I think I uh message John with
some jokes that didn't go in the port no no but you did not at any point you have in the past for
example phone me up from a calm at like 6 a.m so 6 a.m my time I should say we're great friends
yeah and it was nice but also no so I'm viewing it as a plus that no one wants up to me at 6 a.m
well there was probably a good reason right there was a good reason and we planned it we did I still
regretted it yeah so so if anyone wants the jokes that we edited out of the or that John edited out
of the live version of optophobe if you're an easter con member it's still available in its
unexpagated form on catch up yes so go watch it there for another couple of weeks couple of weeks
I've watched some catch up but I need to watch more about 10 days by the time it's you're actually
listening to this so yeah get over yeah do it do it now now stop what you're doing pull over watch
the program do I want to do we want to recommend any particular items that people should watch or
can I do ones that I watched in person yeah or is that cheating that's okay like you were to watch
them on catch up but you'd already seen them so that's fine I can recommend ones that I watch
when they were streamed live so yeah if I'm just going to recommend one of the ones I've watched so
far it would be Esther McCallum Stewart on the history of the board game of board games and how
it relates to Doctor Who that is not the title I thought that was a great talk I really enjoyed it
and it also has lots of um slides of shoota get wa so you know that's good I enjoyed watching
John Clutes Be a Saffay lecture which is about a subject I knew nothing about namely the fact
that the British library has been discarding uh book jackets for many years and he had some
really interesting examples of where the book jackets are very like historically important to
the presentation and marketing of the book and that we wouldn't know any of this except that
some people have saved the books with the book jackets so I recommend that I have been thinking
about that talk ever since watching it because as in passing he said that the British library now
accepts an electronic deposit as a deposit of a book and electronic books often do not have all
the front matter that a book would have and I wonder if we are losing critical things by as a result
of this policy but also I wonder whether electronic books should have all of the stuff that a paper
book has as part of its front matter and back matter. Esther's talk was called Good Men Don't Need
Rules, Game of Play and Doctor Who. I mean I'm probably going to slightly spoil this talk by saying
her argument was that Good Men Bend the Rules and Bad Men and Villains Cheat. Yes I was going to
recommend a panel I saw but unfortunately I don't think it was streamed so I'm going to recommend
the same one that I've been recommending all along which is Strange Worlds Strange Games
which was Stuart Haughtsons talk which I thought was very good you can see me wearing my Garth
Meringue cosplay in the stream but it was very interesting and I think the other one if I was
going to I'd tell you to watch the business meeting if you're interested in East Cons and
you weren't there because there was stuff about the next East con which was also interesting.
I thought the panel that John was on about mega constellations was really excellent and you should
go watch that. I met Bill Ray he's very interesting hello Bill if you're listening.
I met Bill Ray at Lisa Conrad's 60th birthday party and we had a conversation during which it
became clear that he had run the games room for the East con I chaired in 1995 and I mean I did
know that at the time but 1995 is a long time ago and I can tell you Bill looked very different in 1995
and I did not recognize him and it took us some time to work this out and he did not recognize me
either. On the subject of games I this East con I spent more in the dealers room than I have
at many East con's because this East con did something very clever they had a stall that sold
games and so I bought games and it was good. I feel like it was the it was the games company that
did something very clever by taking stall at the East con but did East con reach out to them?
I don't know I just think I remember at my first no sorry my second East con there was a game
stall at Heathrow in 2008 and I remember buying a copy of a Star Wars RPG supplement from them
and being very happy I'd found it and ever since then I've been surprised by how many
science researchers and competitors don't have games stalls I am always confused by this because
if you want to part me from my money I have games in the dealers room but they did and it was good
I bought a copy of cyborg which I'm very much looking forward to playing and I also bought a
copy of Lucky for None which came with a D13 which I'm very excited about. Chris Lowry who was
representing Beyond Cataclysm games at East con and around that stall was very good value
generally in that he was on a panel that I was on that had a and John was on that had an interesting
it went through numerous changes before the event because Chris came along and said well this is a
panel about James journalism and I'm a games journalist so maybe I should be on it and and
it took a little time but we did actually manage to get him onto the panel yes in the end but also
he played games with me I had to play a game every day I am playing a different game every day in
2024 which is quite a strange way to behave but there you go and Chris helped me by playing
coup with me at East con and me I was there too yeah but you're not trying to play a different
game every day in 2024 which is the bad thing no but I still I still count as a person in your
anecdotes Alison sometimes boo boo depends yeah so no he was good he was good fun to hang out with
and good fun on and good value on panels and yeah yes I think that tabletop games panel was
interesting but that's mostly because I like games if you like games you might also find
interesting if you don't it's unlikely yes I'm quite blessed in that a couple of people have
said that panels that I was on were interesting so that was quite nice we didn't have any reports
of covid over the weekend and that is partly because the venue was extremely spacious that there
was plenty of room for everyone it's also because we understand that the ventilation system doesn't
recirculate any of the air the air comes in is used once and goes out again and and they believe
that that reduces infection in the building Sandra Bond commented so it comes in once and then
goes straight back out again you mean like Dave McCarty that is very good there are no reports
of covid from the con I got a bit of a tickly cough but I tested like seven times and it was negative
every time I had a pretty bad cough and two days of fatigue but I probably have had two days of
fatigue anyway it felt it felt much more like traditional conchre than it did anything else
there was no covid might be because of the good ventilation might be because of lower rates
impossible to tell but hurrah pretty much yeah okay let it's about embraces if you you don't know
you need the base braces till the belt falls off yes something like that do we have anything
else to say about Eastercon oh we did the newsletter we should say that you could go and read it on
efansies probably we'll put a link up when it comes up which might not quite be by Thursday
shall we move on to pics I have started but not finished watching the new Amazon Prime series
Fallout which is based on a video game I have only played I think the first and maybe second
fallout to any degree I really really like the first one when it was isometric but then it went
first person and I get lost in first person games because they're like real life and I get lost in
real life but in real life people don't keep shooting at you the thing about Fallout the video
game series is it is a really set in a really strange retro future as if the world had got stuck
in corny 1950s America and then everywhere got nuked and a bunch of people went and hit underground
for 200 years and now they are one of them is coming out and having a look at society
what's been left on the surface and the tv series captures all of that pretty well I think so it
doesn't feel realistic in maybe the way that the last of us did it's clearly quite arch all of
the time and that's quite unsettling in a television series in a way that less so in a game and I am
enjoying it a whole lot I like I like being the first person to watch something for a while it is
on Amazon Prime so and Amazon Prime is now annoying in Britain because they have started putting little
ads in everywhere and that's pissy and I might have to spend £2.99 a month to get rid of the ads but
that kind of is very annoying so I don't want to. Well I have not watched it yet it is on the list
you span your love to Fallout games I don't like them very much but I'm hoping I'll like the tv show
I've played a bunch of Fallout 3 quite enjoying it and what's tv show yet?
I think we had Fallout 4. Yeah so my pick is that I haven't read as much because they released a new
patch for Stardew Valley and then I realized I hadn't played the whole patch and I can now get
out of my switch which the controls are a lot better than they are on the Android phone and so I
have been farming it's very nice it's very relaxing apart from when you're in the mind if anyone's
not played Stardew Valley it is a farming simulator sort of it's farming simulator and you're in a
village and you go and make friends with all the villagers in my case by giving them a present
of jam every time I see them and you're just kind of collecting more and more you know materials
and metals and vegetables and farming cows and so on so you can get more money to buy
more vegetables and then you get a nicer house and yeah it's very addictive really
and each day takes like 12 minutes or something to play so you can just think oh I'll just play
through like one day of of farming sim and then it's three days later of real time obviously that
makes sense that sounds good I have not played it in the same genre as Harvest Moon I believe
yeah it's got the cute little eight bit e-bick graphics I bounced off this game quite hard but
lots of people I know like it quite a lot I mean that might be good for you because I think you would
play it a lot well I mean I I have tried and and I would love I love nothing more than to find a new
game that I fall into and and play obsessively for a while but the outcomes aren't sharp enough
for me it's it's too you've got a whole set of options that you could do every day and they're
all a bit fluffy is that because they're a sheep in it I am going to pick a game I'm going to pick
Thunder Road Vendetta and very dramatic it is it's basically Mad Max Fury Road for a board game
except without the character based drama and with helicopters so basically this is a race game in
which you are racing along a big desert and there's a road and you've got three cars each and you
roll some dice and you have to put dice on the cars and the dice you put on the car tells you
how to cast the car goes and you can slam other cars and shoot other cars and etc and it was good
I played it with three friends it was quite quick it was quite strategic and it was just a fun little
dice game that oozes theme and I thought yeah I was quite good after we played it and then my
friend showed me the expansion and some of the characters in the expansion and I was like oh I
wanted to play as those characters now please so I am excited to play again which I think is a good
sign not sure if I need it in my collection but it's sort of thing I'm quite happy to play with
pals and that was the old to-thought podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me
and it's goodbye from me
so you're young people right?
vaguely to use send people long incoherent voicemails instead of text messages
no but people send me voicemails instead of messages because my daughter did this for the first time
last week and I was like oh no this is not an improvement this is a thing that young people do
I think I actually quite like it because if because I listen to podcasts it's just like getting a
podcast from your daughter I mean not your daughter but you know people yeah like when my friend
Bella sends me like loads of voicemails I just put them on what's happened just like you know
did the ironing or something it's nice I will do it occasionally but if you send me one at a time
when it's not convenient listen to voicemail message I will send your grumpy text message back
saying please put message in text not listening um I can see they're useful notes if you're going
to type a really long message yeah fair enough in this case she was telling me a delicious anecdote
and it was much better as an anecdote such as you might you might tell someone the theme music for
this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in comfatec.com used under a creative
Collins attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
Thank you.