I know I've got the right.
So the question is, do you want flow first or do you want women first?
Oh, I have opinions on women.
So let's do women first.
OK, should I do women first?
So when John said I have opinions on women is title of the episode.
That means I've got to put that in.
That's got to go in now, Liz.
So.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to a very special episode of the Octothorpe podcast, which we're recording out of time in which we will be discussing the movie Dredd.
I am John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
We will today be discussing.
Dredd.
So Dredd is a movie from 2012.
It was directed by Pete Travis and it was written by Alex Garland and it stars Carl Urban, Lydia Thelby, Lena Headey and a variety of other people.
I watched this, I believe, when it was in cinemas.
I might be wrong about that.
And I've always thought it was good for two kind of key reasons.
Firstly, it's an incredibly tight film.
Which does not overstay its welcome and tells a simple story with great skill.
And secondly, it is Dredd is one of the great British science fiction institutions.
And it is nice to see one of the great British science fiction institutions get its turn on the big screen, especially after the previous one was somewhat less well received.
And also, I've always been a massive fan of Alex Garland's work.
So that kind of gives you some idea as to why I might have quite liked this as well.
And then I made Alison and Liz watch it.
I should say this is the first of a new series.
We made each other read books and now we're going to make each other watch some movies.
And this is the first of those movies.
I thought from reading the Internet that Pete Travis started directing it.
But Alex Garland more or less took over before the end of the movie.
I don't know where I have that in my head.
I was very much just doing the credits as they are reported at the end of the film.
But there is there is quite a lot of online discussion.
There is a lot of online discourse about how much Alex Garland ended up doing.
And I think it is it is greater than zero.
You are true.
You are correct.
Yes.
I mean, this is posts like, quote, Alex Garland actually directed Dredd, says Carl Urban.
Yeah.
And I think that is relevant because while Pete Travis has gone on to have, you know, he's got quite a long and illustrious career.
It's not really been in movies like this one.
Not that there are, I think, very many movies.
Like this one that I can't claim to have done a full study.
So let me do let me do the patented Cox and Vibes recap and then I'll actually talk about the plot.
So Dredd is a story about a woman who is doing rather badly on her test scores.
But presumably we find reacts better to coursework and ongoing assessment than exams.
And she is paired with a kindly mentor who brings out the best in her.
So Dredd is a movie.
So we open with Judge Dredd pursuing three criminals through the streets who are driving dangerously while under the influence of narcotics.
And as the sort of scene goes on, that escalates and he eventually decides that they need to be dealt with more harshly.
And they kill a civilian and things go kind of up from there.
And that really sets the scene for Dredd's color.
And the level of hyper realized violence we're going to see in the movie, which is very much drawing from 300 and Sin City.
I think those are clear influences on the film.
And then brought into the Hall of Justice.
And he's presented with a new recruit, Judge Anderson, who has scored sort of slightly under the passing grade for a judge.
But it's a powerful psychic.
So they want to put her in the field and see whether she can cut it.
And so he takes her and does.
And she decides they're going to go and visit a triple homicide in peach trees.
And they do that.
And through the course of the movie, it turns out that the homicide was perpetrated by a man who they sort of catch quite early on.
But then it becomes clear that actually the narcotics that the three people at the beginning of the movie were using are being manufactured and distributed from peach trees.
And the gang boss who is in charge of the manufacturing shuts the entire block down and motivates the three people.
And so we have this thing where the judges are trapped in this block and everyone in the block wants to kill them.
And they are also keen to go up and deal with the gang boss because because, yeah, there's this big distribution network in the block.
And then, you know, it all ends happily ever after, sort of.
So that's kind of the basic plot synopsis.
I'm doing it a drastic disservice because the film loops back like everything that comes up comes up again later.
And I have not really done a good job of encapsulating how any of that sort of thing works.
But but that's the kind of basic plot.
Did I miss anything?
Do you think Alison and Liz?
I don't know if you explain the peach trees is a giant apartment block tower, like almost small society of its own within this giant city, Mega City One, which is where Judge Dredd is set.
And so that's how it can be locked down.
Essentially can go into a war mode.
Peach trees is an arcology to use the sci fi.
Term of art and and is one of many.
You see that in the establishing shots of the city, you see that there are many towers like this.
Yeah.
So so I have some backstory.
I've been obviously very familiar with the idea of Judge Dredd since being quite a small child because I don't know when.
When was the first appearance of Judge Dredd in comics, John?
Two thousand a day.
Eighty one, I guess.
No, it's Prague, too.
He was in issue two.
So, yeah.
So 1977.
But I've never really read the comics.
I never followed 2000.
And just all my knowledge of Judge Dredd has kind of soaked in through the skin of being a British teenager and having a lot of friends who read Judge Dredd and 2000.
Yeah.
But nevertheless, quite a lot had soaked in.
It turns out there have been 2400 issues of 2000 AD approximately at the time of recording.
And yeah, Judge Dredd has been in the majority of them.
But like so 2008, he's been written by writers like I mean, it's been written by Alan Moore and a variety of other writers that ended up going and being much more well known for working in American comics.
So like Grant Morrison, Garth Ennis, people like that.
I was gonna say, I think I have probably the least exposure to actual Judge Dredd than you do.
Obviously, I've picked up a lot by osmosis.
But all I really know is Judge Dredd is a chin that dispenses justice in a dystopian future.
And has a motorbike.
And that is it, basically.
One of the things I love about this movie is the range of emotion Carl Urban can convey with just his downturned mouth and chin.
Yeah, so I think he does a good job of that.
But he is by necessity incredibly limited in what he can do and kind of makes the most of that.
And it is an interesting problem to give your film when you have a main character who is basically unable to emote apart from with like the bottom.
20% of his face.
And I presume this is why Judge Anderson has this basically contrived thing where she leaves a helmet behind because her psychic powers won't work as well as she's wearing a helmet.
But that is also because if you had your two lead roles both wearing helmets, then I think that would be too much for the film.
So I can go behind that.
I think Judge Anderson doesn't wear a helmet in the comics either because it was the 70s and she was a girly.
So I mean, it's complicated, right?
But it's the same thing.
It's the same issue.
You know, you've got this issue.
If you're going to say Judge Dredd never ever takes his helmet off, then it makes it hard for both comics and movies.
Yeah.
But it's probably easier in the comics because you can have him think things.
You can have him, you can have like little comic doohickeys where they say, where they refer back to things.
No, that is fair.
So I guess the next question is, what did you two think about the movie?
Shall I say, well, thank you for suggesting I watch this because it is.
Absolutely not a film I would ever have watched without the prompt.
Wasn't keen on the subject matter.
Wasn't keen on the ultraviolence.
I did.
I was realized I was aware of it when it came into the cinemas because this was designed to be the first kind of 3D ultraviolence film.
I wonder whether you saw it in 3D when you saw it in the cinema, John.
Oh, I mean, it was it was it was 13 years ago, Alison.
Maybe.
I don't know.
Who knows?
But there are a lot of shots that are designed, especially with a connection with the slow-mo drug.
They have been designed to kind of look exciting in 3D.
And so not just watching it on a flat screen, I kind of went, oh, well, that's interesting.
So maybe I will at one point put my helmet on in the form of a of a meta quest and watch it again in 3D, because I think that would be quite interesting.
And and resonant.
And I would have to make my reactions to the film solely with my chin at that point.
Yes.
Instead of my reaction to the film.
And I apologize to listeners because this is a visual joke, which was.
So it was not bad.
Stephen started and said, oh, it's it's only 95 minutes long and about two minutes into the movie.
I was like, yeah, but it may.
I feel a lot longer.
So I don't I think it drags a little bit in the middle.
It's not very draggy.
And the second act could could be tightened up.
But I think in general, yeah, there's not a lot of not a lot of fat.
So I do not like ultraviolence and I did not like the violent bits of this and the bloody bits of this.
But apart from that, I think it's not a bad film.
Liz, what did you think?
I thought it was pretty good.
Way.
Yeah.
I mean, I think if I was star rating it, I'd give it like a solid three and a half.
Yeah, that's fair.
Or two.
I don't give star ratings, but two.
So we're definitely on a gradient where John likes it most, Alison likes it least.
And I am somewhere in the middle, as is with like nearly everything.
Right.
There's always a great.
And for some reason, I'm always in the middle.
That's not true.
You like there's at least there's been a couple of episodes where you've liked something.
Me and Alison have been like, nah.
So, like, it's not always the case that you're in the middle.
But on my.
My private scale, I use the board game geek rankings, board game geek like rankings in my head.
And for me, a three out of five is like the lowest ranking at which I would watch a film again.
Is that true for you?
Would you watch this again?
I would watch it again, but not for a while.
That's fair.
In 3D on goggles for the bit.
If I was around at someone's house and they were like, let's watch Dredd, I'd be like, yeah, fine.
I will watch Dredd again.
It's 90 minutes.
It's quite fun.
Oh, no.
If I was around at someone's house.
They said, let's watch Dredd.
I'd be like, oh, that's good because I've got some little solo games I need to be playing.
You know, I'll go off and do that.
I was going to ask Alison.
So you've you gave it two out of five.
So for me, that would be two out of four, two and a half out of five, two and a half out of five.
OK, so that for me is the lowest rank at which I concede that something is good, but just not my cup of tea.
Whereas one half star below that, I'd be like, I don't think this is good.
So what's going on here is that this is a this is a movie that is.
It's absolutely not made for me.
Yeah, I am not the target audience for this film.
Nobody is making films like that thinking, oh, gosh, we're going to get the seniors going to a movie on a Tuesday afternoon crowd in to see this one.
Yeah, no fair.
Yeah, but they probably were hoping for the people who have been fans of 2008 for a long time crowd.
But I haven't been a fan of 2008 for a long.
So.
So one of the things about Judge.
Dredd the comic strip that I'm not sure comes out sufficiently in the movie is the is the satire in the sense of how awful this society that is being depicted is.
I mean, obviously you get that, but it's kind of pushed backwards in the movie.
The reason that the people at the beginning of the film kill a civilian is not because they want to kill a civilian.
It's because they're being pursued by a judge who is going to hand down very long sentences.
Oh, yeah.
So I think that's that is.
In the movie.
But they kind of they kind of get away with it.
They kind of get away from that as a concept.
When when the building gets locked down, it allows them to just say, oh, at this point, the Dredded Anderson are fighting for their lives.
So anything they do is OK.
And I feel like it doesn't.
It just kind of lets all the actual science fictional content slip away in favor of.
Oh, no, we're going to have a lot of gunfights now.
Liz, do you want to talk about that before I come in?
Like, I don't want to.
Yeah, because I would kind of agree with Alison.
I thought it would be a bit more satirical and it ends up playing it a little bit straighter.
Yeah.
So I think this is something.
So I've got two.
I think I've got two thoughts on this, which is firstly.
Firstly, I think you're right in that.
I think the movie doesn't try and grapple with the wider satire very explicitly.
It's absolutely we are not supposed to conclude.
I think that first chase we are supposed to notice what Alison noticed, which is that the reason that this has gone wrong is because of the way it is being dealt with by the judge.
And then.
But the movie does also want us to simplify with its main characters.
And so the reason it locks the block down is because then it can be like, well, there are problems with Dredd and Anderson and the system they represent.
But we can root for them because the people they are going up against are so much more reprehensible.
I will say.
I think there's a moment.
There's a moment.
I do think the movie tries to hang.
I do think the movie tries to talk about this to an extent.
So one of the things that happens right at the end of the movie.
So there's a good there's like a sequence where Dredd and Anderson is sort of clearing people out in the first act.
And Anderson is very hesitant and they are not working well together as a team.
And then at the end kind of climactic sequences.
There's a scene where they're kind of moving into the gang leaders lair and they're clearing out and they're working.
They're working very, very well together.
And it's a nice kind of shadowing of kind of how that relationship has evolved and a very good show.
Don't tell.
But there's a point at the beginning of the movie where she struggles to kill someone who is severely injured,
but is clearly going to try and kill her if she doesn't kill him.
And you can see her struggle and you can see like the kind of the difficulty she's having with that.
And then at the end, she shoots someone in the back on a staircase because they're there and they're still alive.
And I think the movie is being quite clear that she has by becoming.
A good candidate for the judge program.
She has lost something about the humanity she had at the beginning of the movie.
And I don't think the movie makes that incredibly explicit, but I do think the movie is aware of it.
And I think a careful reading probably doesn't come out in favor of this system of of of of legal.
What's the word I'm looking for?
Law and justice.
I think it's something where.
If there's a lot of people who would like this to be a sequel to this movie,
but I think if it was an eight part Netflix show,
you could really get into like a lot of that in a much more satisfying way than you can in 95 minutes,
probably.
But I do think it's something worth thinking about because I do think I do think it's less pronounced in the movie than in the comic.
And it is.
And I do.
The other thing I wanted to do do that here is I think there is also a parallel between Judge Dredd and Games Workshop and Warhammer 40,000.
And Space Marines.
Where the two kind of big, big British grown universes are both incredibly pessimistic, incredibly sarcastic looks at the future.
And also both vehicles which have been taken distressingly seriously by some of the fans.
Because I think there are people who probably like Judge Dredd who are just like Judge Dredd is great and not really thinking about this side of things at all.
And there are definitely those fans in the Warhammer 40,000 fandom as well.
Well, both both Judge Dredd, both 2000 AD and Warhammer 40K are trying to catch their fans at an age where they might not think too seriously about what it is they're being served up.
So I think that there is that tension.
If you if you catch people at 10 or 12 and they're not thinking very hard and then they could maybe get a more nuanced understanding of the of the whole system.
At the point where they're already bought in and buying all your extremely expensive little plastic objects or whatever, then that suits you right?
Or you have people who are 2000 AD readers for life because they absolutely loved it and then realised that there was so much more to it than they had thought to begin with.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
When I was 11 and getting into 40K, I did not have anywhere near a recognisation of what the franchise was doing compared to my sort of 36 year old.
interpretation of the universe.
Yeah.
Also from the comics, but also they did do subtle.
There were subtle, subtle differences in the costumes, which helped a little bit.
But that that that names in big letters on the on the other thing is from the comics.
And you have to do it because otherwise you're going to it's going to be really hard.
Yeah.
I think Liz is right.
Liz is right.
Obviously, that part works really well.
I also want to say they make a couple of other good decisions here, which is firstly the judges they get in the four actors.
Two of them are notably bigger than Carl Urban, and one of them is a relatively petite woman.
So it is quite easy at a glance to tell the silhouettes are very different.
But the other thing is the colouring of the uniform.
So the movie repeatedly uses a kind of primary colour comic book palette.
And one of the things that I think is really important is that the colouring of the uniforms.
the things they use yellow for is very interesting because they use a kind of sickly green yellow
for sequences with mama and with gang members and with like the corrupted cd or parts of the block
and they use a kind of like golden angelic yellow to reflect like to reflect the kind of the better
parts of things and that's one of the reason anderson like has blonde hair is because she is
fitting into that color palette but the other thing is if you look at the bad judges uniforms
they have this kind of like sickly yellow tint and judge anderson and Dredd both have a kind of
bluish uniform and blue is also used to kind of reflect purity ish in the movie and i think the
movie is very subtle i think the movie is making overt choices but i think it is they have also
thought very carefully about a lot of very detailed things to try and make it obvious to the reader
or the viewer i guess in any given scene like how the colors are fitting in with the story
and i thought that was very effective
you
I did not spot that at all so thank you john no i mean liz i have seen this movie it wasn't until
like watch seven that i noticed this so i cannot claim too much and the other thing that was
pointed out to me since last time i talked about drag Dredd or podcast is similar which is the
movie does a lot of comic book frames and i think it's a really good movie and i think it's a really
good movie and i think it's a really good movie and i think it's a really good movie and i think
it's a really good movie and i think it's a really good movie and i think it's a really good movie
and there's a lot of squares and rectangles and every time you look up the block that's kind of
a very classic comic book panel kind of style shot um and and that's very effectively done as well
i think those corrupt judges also like i think they did quite good character arcs for anderson
and Dredd and the corrupt judges are part of that because then you see Dredd at the end kind of
recognizing that even though anderson has failed by the objective measures he set out at the start
and i think that's a really good movie and i think it's a really good movie and i think it's a really good
movie and i think it's a really good movie and i think it's a really good movie and i think it's a really good
she would actually be a good thing for justice and so he's prepared to go along with that
yeah and maybe he has unbent a little bit there is a tension in the comic as well where
they very much like if you read recent synopses like Dredd resigns in protest about like the way
mutants are treated in the city and there is a plot line where the city is like we will treat
mutants better so Dredd comes back i think the comics do have this tension of well we've got
this character that we've been using for 2400 issues and we've got this character that we've
and so we do have to have him take principal stands and sometimes he has to be right and he
has to be the goody but sometimes he's like they're also the instrument of this incredibly
repressive regime and i don't know how you as a sort of thing it's very difficult to square and i
don't think the movie i think in the comic you probably have a lot more room for that but that
goes back to the movie does want you to sympathize with Dredd even while the movie is not condoning
this method of um sorting crime out yeah i feel like they were hoping to start a franchise i think
you're probably right um but the movie was just too violent too sad too too much that the franchises
have to have more more light-hearted characterizations and settings i don't want to say
i don't know if i would say you need that for franchise but i would say it feels like yes this
is the first film and i think in some ways simplifies the complexity in order to make
a tight 95 minute film with one pretty linear plot and
where it can deal with introducing the world and introducing Dredd and the judges and also
have all that in there and then you know for the second and future films you'll be able to take a
step back make them wider make them a bit more satirical but they never got to that point well
i think even though i'm not sure what the financial status of the movie is i think carl urban has said
he'd be quite happy to do more but i think the part of the problem is that alex garland did end
up doing a lot of the direction and the production was not a happy one
so i think a lot of the key people from the creative that like um a lot of the key people
on the production side probably wouldn't want to revisit it because they don't have good
memories of it is the impression i get from kind of reading interviews and stuff
it is an amazingly tight film given how unhappy it was in post-production in production and
post-production um i had two i have two big chunky lumps of things to say about this movie
the two reasons that john cited for why this film is good were not because of the
Not the reason that I expected him to cite, which is the critical analysis of this film has focused on the fact that it, for a tight 95 minute ultra violent action movie, it has a bunch of well-constructed female parts.
This came three years before Mad Max Fury Road, but shares with Mad Max Fury Road the fact that it's named after its male character, but the lead character is a woman and the story is the woman's story, not the man's story.
Judge Dredd doesn't have a lot of character development through this movie.
The primary villain is a woman.
The chief of police, the Lord Chief Justice or whatever she's called, is a woman.
Head judge.
There's a bunch of women in this movie.
The judges are shown as being a mix of men and women with no particular hierarchy there.
That is fantastic for a movie of this kind.
And having said that, it only just passes the Bechdel test.
So despite the fact that it's got a bunch of female characters in, when they talk to each other, they talk about men.
Anderson has a long conversation with Kathy about her, basically about her husband.
Yeah.
People believe that there's a conversation between Anderson and the chief justice at
the beginning of the movie, but there isn't.
It's all conversations with Dredd about Anderson.
There is a little bit right at the end.
So it does pass the Bechdel test, but it's kind of like, well, there are women in this movie,
but they're all kind of put in little boxes where they can't really actually get too uppity, I guess.
I don't know.
I mean, so I think it does great for what it does, but it doesn't really quite do enough there.
That was what I want to say about women.
And John has thoughts about women.
Yeah.
I didn't bring this up because I expected it to come up and, you know, I thought I'll let the women on the podcast bring it up.
But no, I think you're right.
I think, I don't think this movie nails the women.
And like, there's a few things I'll come to in a second, but I do think it's notable that this movie has multiple.
I would argue the women in this movie have more agency than the men in general, because the person that I think the only man in the movie that I think there were, well, other than,
the corrupt judges who have quite a lot of agency, but are then summarily murdered.
Executed.
Dred is the law.
Yes.
The bit where he says, I am the law.
And he's like, he said the thing.
He said the thing.
Yeah.
It would be great if he'd never said that at any point in the movie.
But no.
So in general, Anderson has quite a lot of agency because she, you know, she's getting to decide her path.
And at the end, she actually rejects it.
The head judge has agency because she is the head judge.
And Mama has quite a lot of agency because she is at the top of her hierarchy and everyone under her.
Is basically entirely at her whim.
And so actually, I think this movie is surprisingly strong for its female characters.
I will say there is a couple of parts where the movie uses sexual violence.
And I'm torn on that because on the one hand, I kind of wish it hadn't.
But on the other hand, in both situations, Anderson, who is the kind of intended target, so thoroughly fucks the guy up that it's difficult.
Like the bit at the end where he's trying to shock her and she just stands up and kills him by kicking him in the head.
And.
Breaking his neck.
And you're like, oh, this, this, this, this woman has had enough of the men around her.
And now she is doling out justice.
And so it's tricky because I think there's probably a reading where you didn't need the sexualization of that violence.
But I also think the movie is being quite clear that the women in those situations are not going to be actually receiving any and have all the agency in those situations.
Liz, what did you think?
So, I mean, Alison says she thinks like maybe the female characters.
It's kind of a bit put in boxes.
But I think kind of all the characters are put in boxes by society, not just the female ones.
And I think I agree with you, which is that I always kind of think, oh, did we actually need the sexualized violence in this bit of the film?
Could you get away without it?
And I think in this case, yes, you could get away without it.
But again, it is in the situation where realistically in this world, it probably would be a part of the backstory of Anderson and Mama.
And yeah, they're both women who one is the main villain.
And is clearly in control of her own destiny until Judge Dredd shows up.
And Anderson gets threatened with it.
But then at the end, she is not super affected by it.
And she gets to kill all the men who have been suggesting it.
So I didn't find it too bad.
I mean, I don't, you know, I'm old.
So I'm used to movies having a lot of sexualized violence in them.
And it didn't seem to be excessive.
It seemed like it was consistent with what's going on in this place.
Yeah.
No, I mean.
My reading of it was that what you've just said, which is, you know, it's a present thing.
But I think the movie does a good job of kind of centering and giving the women agency.
But I'm just always a little bit worried as a man when I make those decisions in my head.
That I might need to chat a little bit around them before I come out strongly with those opinions.
But yes, that basically dovetails with the conclusions I had drawn.
So I am glad I wasn't.
The one thing I don't like is I really wish Anderson didn't get shot at the end to give the to make it just Dred and Mama right at the end.
I kind of think Anderson has shown enough competence by that point.
I do think the movie does slightly do her dirty right in that last scene or the penultimate scene, I guess.
But it's a relatively minor, relatively minor quibble, I think.
So I think one of the ways they.
Are stuck by having Dred wear a helmet is it becomes harder to make Dred vulnerable because in a kind of martial arts or action type film, you tend to kind of see the hero deteriorating over time.
You know, they get wounds, they get scratches, they get punches or whatever.
And it feels like you don't really see that with Dred.
He kind of despite getting shot and having to do this kind of emergency in the field wound repair, he never feels particularly vulnerable or like he's going to lose a fight.
I think is one thing I felt.
And so again, when.
Like Anderson gets shot, it feels like.
But Dred would be just continuing going on.
It doesn't seem to affect him that he did get shot.
So I think that is one one problem they have with him again wearing the helmet all the time.
He feels a bit too invulnerable.
I know what you mean.
I do think the point where he gets shot and he slowly goes down the thing in the cinema.
I remember thinking, well, how on earth?
Like, how are they going to get out of this?
Because I was like, he does seem like.
And then when he says, wait, and Lex decides to monologue and you're like, and they've.
Lex is such a piece of work and the way he's tearing into Dred.
I'm like, yeah, OK, I would imagine that this guy would do that.
And he's like, wait for what?
And then Dred's like, wait for her to shoot you.
And I'm just like, yeah, that's why he's Dred, bitch.
It made me so happy.
I think that's why I didn't mind that it's just Dred and Mama at the end because Anderson's had her rescue the hero in a clinch bit there.
Yeah.
This all ties in, though, to my the other major point I want to make, which is why this.
This film is like flow and John's review of flow, which I'm not going to spoil flow too much for you.
I hope.
But John's review of flow was that the BBFC said that this was very mild threat.
And so flow is a U rated film with very mild threat.
And I'm going to say that Judge the Dred is an 18 hyper violent movie with very mild threat.
And when my daughter was about, I guess, three, she was just kind of learning.
About narrative and how narrative works.
And she was very scared in movies like flow.
And I said, it's going to be all right.
You know, the thing about films, especially films that are made for people like you, is that, yes, the main characters are put into peril, but it is going to be OK for them.
You know, there are there are characters around them like senior mentors who may die off a bit.
But but but, you know, the cat is going to be all right in flow.
And you know that.
If you're above the age of three and you go to see flow, the cat's not going to die.
And the thing about Dredd is Dredd's not going to die.
Anderson's not going to die.
The villain is going to be brought to justice.
And Anderson's going to get a badge.
You know, those things all the way through the movie.
If you're above the age of three, because it's not the sort of movie where those things don't happen.
Anderson could die in previous versions of this.
But but in fact, if you've been reading 2400 issues of 2018.
You know that Anderson is a big major character who has a lot of a lot of agency in this world.
And that's the thing.
It feels like a very mild threat to me because I didn't think these people were in danger.
And when Dred got shot, as John said, he was thinking, how are we going to get out of that?
He wasn't thinking, oh, no, this is where Judge Dred gets it.
And this is actually a movie about the death of Dred and how the world reacts to that, which an adult movie could be.
You could have a movie like that.
But this was never going to be that movie.
So the BBC, BBFC rates Dred as strong threat.
Yeah, but they just mean they just mean threat with more blood in it, really.
I think the thing with Flo is you repeatedly see the main character nearly drown.
And I would argue that is at least at least moderate threat.
But I think I mean, obviously, the main character in a movie such as this is unlikely to die.
It is.
And it is.
Yeah, there's there's it would have been an interesting choice to have Dred kill him.
And I was not in any kind of point of the movie seriously worried that he would die.
But yeah, no.
So I take the point.
I guess I am more sceptical that that's the definition of threat.
But yeah, how you help children cope with narrative is to explain that there'll be a happy ending.
And not all movies have happy endings.
But I'm not really sure that's relevant to Dred unless you were showing your Dred to your three year old.
I mean, I think this is just the narrative conventions of.
Action movies at heart.
It is an ultra violent action film.
And, you know, I don't go into like action films expecting the hero to be killed off 20 minutes before the end.
But I do expect to at least give me the illusion that this might happen.
So it is indeed not common in action movies.
And spoiler.
I really like Rogue One.
You know, spoiler for a movie that's a long time ago.
There are movies where where that don't do this, where part of what they do is go.
No, we're going to tell a different story here.
You know, if you see a lot of movies that are kind of made for adults, they won't all follow that sort of three act narrative of of of a simple action movie.
They have they do a lot.
Movies can do a lot of different things.
I think Rogue One is not the best example here because the reason Rogue One works is we already know the end of their story.
If Rogue One was a standalone film and ends up with them dying and we don't see what happens.
I don't think it works as well as we know this is going to lead into Star Wars and the triumph of the rebellion.
Maybe.
Yes.
I want to bring up something that neither of you have brought up.
Have either of you seen the film The Raid?
Yes, I have, Liz.
Tell me about The Raid.
So The Raid is an.
I have not seen it.
The Raid is an Indonesian martial arts action thriller movie in which a policeman goes into a tower block in search of a drug dealer and is locked down in the tower block and has to fight his way to his home.
He has to go through the top of the tower block to confront the drug dealer.
And it came out in 2011.
So obviously it was in the works at the same time Dredd was in the works, basically.
And they just have coincidentally very similar concepts.
Yeah, it's like it's like is it ants and a bug's life?
A similar thing where you end up having you presumably got someone who's been shopping an idea around Hollywood and it causes divergent threads.
I have seen The Raid.
The Raid.
Firstly, I've got two questions.
I've got two comments on The Raid.
Hang on.
Maybe I should say that I don't think in that case it was that because The Raid is like a low budget film that was made by a British guard.
But in Indonesia, I think I think it's just coincidentally they were making this super tiny film that they never expected to actually go wide.
And then probably Alexander had already written Dredd at the time they were shooting this very small, quickly shot type film.
Yes.
So the poster for The Raid said one ruthless crime lord, 20 elite cops.
30 floors of hell.
And I think that encapsulates my two main criticisms of The Raid.
The fact there are 20 cops makes it a lot harder to grapple with any of them on an emotional level.
I found the movie less.
I found the characters less compelling to me.
But secondly, the poster clearly depicts an apartment building, which is less than 30 stories high.
And if you're going to put 30 floors of hell on the poster, pick a 30 floor apartment building for the poster.
Which is not the filmmakers fault, but just absolutely baffling.
Maybe they couldn't get the rights to a 30 story building.
I'm always very sympathetic to things that low budget movies have done in order to get made while being very low budget.
And that sounds like one of those.
No, because in the movie, I think it's got it's just the picture they picked for the poster.
It annoyed me.
But yes, I mean, it's a very minor point.
A lot of people very much like The Raid.
I will say that.
So Dredd has a rotten tomatoes.
Dredd's Tomatometer was 80 percent.
And the Raid's Tomatometer was 87 percent.
So they are both well received movies in general.
I know Tomatometer is not a perfect measure of film quality, but it's not.
It's not.
You know, 80 percent is pretty high.
I am now looking at this poster and I believe that what they've done is the.
The apartment building is buried eight eight floors into the ground.
So there is a pit around it.
Yeah, there's a lot of headcanoning.
It's really weird because it's obviously a drawing of apartment building.
They could definitely have given it more stories.
I wonder why they didn't.
No one knows.
It's baffling.
But like I say, it's a minor.
But it is.
It is.
It is good to talk about because they are in terms of concept, extremely similar concepts.
I mean, obviously.
The Raid didn't have Judge Dredd in it.
I have one remaining point about this movie, which is a tiny trivial one.
This is Dredd, not the Raid.
Uh huh.
Which is that they have a narcotic slow-mo which causes your world to slow down.
So you experience things at a hundredth of their normal speed.
Everything's in slow-mo.
It's a useful narcotic for the plot of the film in a couple of ways, but it doesn't make any
sense as a narcotic.
Why would people do this?
What is the benefit of this particular drug?
I mean, I know I'm probably overthinking this, but I spent the whole movie going, well, why?
Oh, I see.
It's because it suits the movie because they could use it to do things they want to do
in the movie.
And otherwise, it was very unconvincing to me.
So that was the only, it seems funny given the context of the movie, but that was the
only time my disbelief suspenders really snapped during.
Yeah.
During this movie.
I went, I don't believe that.
I think.
Okay.
So I'm going to say one thing, I guess, which is I can see, I could see an argument that
it is unrealistic narcotic, but I think for me, the idea that if you're in an unremittingly
hellish world, a drug that you took it and it gave you a nice time, but also slowed down
time for the duration of the nice time.
So you spent longer outside of the hell you actually exist in.
I can see that.
I can see that as a kind of.
Compelling thingy.
Except it doesn't give you a nice time, does it?
Unless you make pretty patterns with the, with the water and stuff.
I mean, if they make you take it and then shove you down a 200 story drop, it gives
you a less nice time.
I will concede that.
Spoiler.
That's not.
Well, that's the first.
That's like very early in the movie.
So, but yeah.
Yeah.
So that's the thing is that, that the, um, are they saying that you, you, part of the
experience of taking this drug is like, oh, I'm going to take it.
It's like the bath or whatever.
The, the bit that I went, there was a bit earlier in this movie when I turned to Stephen
and went only the crunchiest, flakiest chocolate.
Liz, what was your view on the narcotics?
They done it because it'll let them do a cool slow-mo fight scene.
Fair.
And I accept this as a narrative convention of action films.
I don't, I don't watch a lot of action movies.
I'm sorry.
It's probably why it's good to give me action films to watch so I could go, oh yeah, no,
that's the thing.
I'm now like, can I?
Can I turn, sell Alison the raid as any kind of science fiction?
The answer is no, but, uh, is it science fiction?
No.
So the other thing I will say about slow-mo is I think the things it lets you do is not
just that it fits in with the action movie tropes that Liz highlighted.
I think it also lets you do a lot of shots that look like panels from a comic, like the
way that she brings up the water at the beginning that you can imagine being drawn in a comic,
but also the bullets going through and seeing the water.
And I think that's the thing that's so important.
I think that's the thing that's so important.
the blood spatter in slow motion.
That is exactly the way you draw that happening in a comic.
And so I think you're right that it is primarily a decision made for visual reasons, but I
think it's specifically some of those visual reasons are to do with the source material
and representing that style in the movie.
And I guess if you're going to make up a drug for your movie, why not make one up that
helps you tell the visual story you want, right?
That was the only thing I had in my note that we haven't covered.
Can I swing back briefly to ultraviolence?
Yes.
Do you think the ultraviolence, do you think loving shots of bullets going through cheeks
or people being skinned and splattered adds a lot to this movie?
Would the movie...
Does it improve the movie?
What is the purpose of doing this?
I think you can't...
The whole thing is a hyper...
Hyper-realistic is the wrong word, but the whole thing is taking what's going on in the
real world and ramping it up to 15, right?
So like, you know, you've got these mega cities which are explicit ghettos and you've got
this justice system which is dispensing justice without proper oversight and you've got a
city in which you can't do anything.
You can't do anything in which people are suffering because there's basically no hope.
And none of that is true.
None of that is wholly true in our society or in, you know, 70s Britain from whence this
franchise originated.
But you can see the things that made them want to talk about this.
And so I think that it would be weird to have a realistic level of violence in a movie which
has ramped up all of the social commentary to quite as ridiculous an extent.
And so I don't think you could make this movie...
I don't think you make a 2000 AD based movie if what you're shooting for is a restrained
look on the issue you're tackling.
I think you're going there for the...
With...
Yeah.
Unlike in Warhammer 40,000.
Like, again, they're both commentaries on 70s Britain.
But like, in 40K, they made Margaret Thatcher into the boss of the Orcs.
And that isn't what she was like in real life.
But you can see how they got there.
But they, like, had to twist a lot of dials very high up to make it work.
See, I don't know.
I think it's a tendency for the source material to go very extreme.
And I think if you don't represent that in adaptations, you sort of think, well, what's
the point?
I think I am kind of between you two again, which is I'm not fully convinced by the ultra
violence.
But I can see it is part of its stylistic choices to try and be a kind of...
more satirically over the top dystopia.
And also that it does allow them to replicate shots from you would get in the comic books
of those very static, violent shots you can get by doing kind of extreme slow-mo ultra
violence.
So while I wasn't super keen on it, I am trying to think of the film with that removed.
And I think it would make it just more of a straightforward, like, action-y thriller
type thing.
Although there are action thrillers where they just, they don't even need like a slow-mo
drug.
They just go for like, okay, this is going to have...
big slow-mo John Woo sections anyway.
Hmm.
Oh, yeah.
Like in The Matrix, no one was huffing a narcotic that made bullet time happen.
It just happened.
No, but I mean, there's a reason for bullet time in The Matrix, right?
You can say it's because they're manipulating the underlying Matrix where...
And I think you're right.
And I think that's why maybe I like the way The Matrix and Dredd do it is that they have
a reason for it to be happening in universe that isn't just, it looks cool.
And like, the reason in universe may end up being because they wanted it.
It's supposed to look cool, but they've actually woven it into the story in a way that I like,
which they didn't.
A lot of action movies do not do.
So that is probably...
I hadn't thought about that.
That's interesting.
Do we have anything else to say about Dredd?
Don't think I do.
I will also say I talked about this on a previous podcast, but it wasn't this podcast.
It was Become the Teapot.
And I will put a link in the show notes to anyone who would like to hear me talk even
more about Dredd, which seems unlikely, but is, I guess, theoretically possible.
Yeah.
I think we have more to say about Dredd than I thought we would have to say about Dredd
when I was watching it.
Maybe it's because John has watched it seven times.
I had to prepare for this podcast, guys.
I did have to sit down afterwards and go, okay, so what is there to say about this movie?
Oh, no, we made you do some preparation for the podcast, Alison?
Yep.
I know.
It's not like me.
And on that bombshell, that was the
Octothorpe podcast. And it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
How you help?
How you help children cope with narrative
is to explain
that there'll be a happy ending.
And not all movies have happy endings.
But
this sort of movie nearly always does.
But I'm not really sure that's relevant to Dredd.
Unless you were showing your Dredd
to your three-year-old. I mean, I think this is just
the narrative conventions of, like,
Eisen's
coffee spreading.
Oh no. Contagion.
The theme music for
this episode was Fanfare for
Space by Kevin MacLeod at
incompetech.com, used under a
Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
license. This podcast
will end at the beep. Beep.