But as if this is your first episode, I recommend going and listening to a different one first,
because this one is mad.
One, two, three.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 38th episode of Octa Thought, a podcast for science fiction
and science fiction fandom. I'm Jon Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
This episode is coming to you on the 19th of August 2021, and we are live and in person and next to
each other sitting around a table.
Big hug!
Yeah!
No actual hugging, because we haven't got that face yet.
But also, yeah, like, you know.
Yeah, I'm not sure about this.
Yeah, you slide those.
But we are at the same place. It is amazing.
It is good.
It's very nice.
We went to a brewery, yes, Tain drank beer that people brought to us.
Yeah, we sat in a bar with lots of people in a bar.
It was good.
Well, sit for us in a bar and then as soon as we finished recording this podcast,
we're going to go back to the same brewery where our friends already are,
and we're going to drink more beer in the same brewery, which is why
today's episode is going to be very, very short.
Every minute.
Okay, thank you.
That's just not too full of 30 minutes.
I'm being else's daughter.
So we have to apologise also.
The sound quality will be rubbish.
We will interrupt each other a lot and it is very short.
But that is because we are recording lower eve before going to a brewery.
We have one studio mic in the middle of the room set to omni.
It is true.
It means that John and I are going to be even louder than usual,
and Liz is going to be even quieter than usual despite the fact
that we have put the right narrow list and don't make it.
Hee hee hee.
We will lean in and then my chair creaks.
So I won't do that.
No, it's good.
Chair creaking is all part of how all the sausage is made.
I don't know if people remember the chair creaking from early octa-thorps,
but maybe people miss it maybe then he'll stop jig for the sign of my chair going.
So there is a concert warning for this episode,
which is that we are likely to be vague and unfocused,
even more so than usual.
Yes, we would like to have a photo for the last episode.
We should have put a content warning in for discussion of entrenched social injustice,
and also I should have used the word "golly" instead of the word I actually used when discussing
"eaninged light inspection", which I am truly sorry and has been bleeped now
after a listener suggested so doing.
I mean the listener was Liz, but Liz did listen, so it counts.
Didn't we get a lot from disgusted of Tumbridge Wells?
No, I consulted a crew of people.
I think of them in my head as the woke squad, which is whenever I need to know whether
I've done something wrong, I contact a certain group of people and say, "Hello,
I have a question about why I should have done in this situation and they tell me."
And so...
So I use my children for that function.
Whenever I think, "Is this something that is going to be adequate for today's social
lorries?" I ask my daughter and she says, "No."
Or sometimes, "No, mum."
Or sometimes, "Mum, why are you even asking?"
"John, you're really loud. I haven't seen you for like two years or something.
I don't think I realized how loud you can be."
Zoom, Zoom automatically modulates my life to normal human levels, but in person my
laugh is too loud.
It is ear splitting.
It's amazing.
Yeah, so this is actually bleeding slightly from Ollieur at the moment.
People have on multiple previous occasions found where I live by going to the street and
listening for my laugh and just knocking on that door.
Like in three different places, different people have employed that method for finding my house.
So I know my laugh is loud.
And if I go to Radio 4 recordings, I can hear myself on the recording in the laugh.
That's like when live music is recorded at festivals or folk clubs that I'm at,
I can often hear my voice in the edit when they're singing on to the chorus.
I'm like, "Oh, that is Nature's Way of Telling You. You are singing too loudly on choruses.
You should stop COVID-19 was also Nature's Way of Telling Me. I sang too loudly on choruses."
No, you should sing along to chorus very loudly.
That's what the chorus is for.
I mean, not right now, obviously.
It doesn't take a lot.
But anyway, yeah, me and Alison are loud.
Who knew?
I did.
Yes, that is very funny.
Are we now doing a person online?
Yeah.
Well, online I can pull my headphones away from my ears.
And it works and that doesn't work.
Well, you can wear headphones while we record.
I could wear earplugs, George.
None of us are wearing headphones today.
We just all have naked ears.
Yes, we do have naked ears.
But oh yeah, we're in person.
It's weird.
We went to a brewery called Double Barreled.
So thank you to them.
And thank you very much to Steve and Julia for hosting this punctuation
committee meeting and also making very good food and bringing beers and coffee and
just generally being fantastic hosts.
Yes, generally this podcast is fueled by Double Barrel Brewery and also Steve and Julie.
And his family.
Happy tears.
Julie is tartafled.
Tartafled.
That's so good.
I understand you're going to the brewery this afternoon.
So I thought we might have a dish made from bacon and potatoes and cheese and cream for lunch.
I mean, I've got to say this morning I watched Johnny to full English breakfast
followed by a hash brown sandwich.
Followed by three pano chocolat which will be in the in the chapter art listeners of this
chapter.
They're only mini.
I think but I did.
I got two slices of toast and I had two hash browns.
I had some mushrooms and I met myself for toast sandwich.
It was very nice.
I have no regrets.
I recommend it to anyone who likes hash browns and toast.
Well, we'll like we'll be having anything to talk about because we've got no topic.
And all we're going to do is talk about what we're doing this weekend,
which is being in person with all the people.
Yes.
You have no idea.
It is so much fun.
People, although we were inside in the bar, the bar is very large.
It's like an industrial unit.
I mean, it is an industrial unit.
It's a brewery.
Yeah.
This is using the like in the modern down with the young people way where I mean is.
I'm using like to mean the brewery is like a large industrial unit.
Sorry, I didn't assume you were using like in the modern young person way.
I should be using it in the like regular old person.
Regular actually English English uses for a year.
Well, you know, I do.
So the brewery is an industrial unit with benches and beer and the other thing about
seeing John in person, which I haven't done since we started doing octa-thorb.
And I feel like I didn't know John as well.
No, yeah.
And I had not realized that he just he interjects the most appalling
thumbs into conversation.
Yeah, yeah, do.
In the manner of somebody who hasn't been trained out of it by the mates yet.
Well, my wife finds it funny.
She encourages me.
So I've been all on her.
Love you, honey.
Yeah.
So, um, yes, we are in person and this episode, we're not going to do letters of comment.
Gonna say we're going to say all the letters of comment on both episode
did 7 and 36 for a bumper podcast next time.
I was going to talk about the brewery and say it was, although we were in person
and with all of us on a table, it's huge and has high ceilings and is very well ventilated and lofty.
And so it felt very comfortable.
And in terms of Stephen Julia's house, we all did lateral flow tests and we have all been
at least double vaccinated and we are being super careful in the house.
So, you know, and hey, you know, we've been petting cats because there's cats and they are
less scared than they were last time we were here.
So one of them is still pretty scared and one of them is scared, but we'll do things for food
and the other one is scared, but we'll, if you start playing with them, they go,
"Oh, this is a scary monster who dang was a cat toy."
No, it's good. It is very good.
So we're being in person is fun.
I feel like being in the same place as other people and having fun together is fun.
It is. You are not wrong.
It is. I mean, I still feel, personally, I still feel slightly cautious about it
whenever I end up in a group largely than about four.
Yeah. So this is a group of nine, which is my biggest group yet indoors, definitely.
Yes.
I mean, it's not mine. And also I did, I mean, it's been not as long for me.
I mean, I went to a New Year's Eve party where there were like 20, 30 people,
because that was all perfectly fine. And within, you know, the restrictions at the time.
So it's not been quite as long, but I am feeling slightly cautious even with vaccinations.
That's fair.
So, but it's, yeah, it's going to be interesting to see where we go from here.
Because the next day...
The brewery.
Well, where we go from here is going to be back to the brewery.
Yeah, it's not beer.
Where we'll go to drink beer.
And oh, the other thing I was going to say about the brewery is that
since the last time I went and hung out in a pub with my mates over the afternoon,
they've introduced a process where by you sit at a table and you just order the beer
that you want on your phone and they bring it to you.
And that means that you can order the beer that you want and pay for it.
And there are no rounds. There's just a kind of beer drinking system.
Yeah.
It's good.
They unfortunately email you...
Twice.
A list of exactly what beer you bought, which when you're looking at it afterwards,
I think I prefer the pre-COVID methodism of waking up in the morning.
What we used to call it a visit from the gorilla.
Are you familiar with this?
No.
Don't do so.
Okay.
But Steve, you've just tagged us on Untacked.
Yeah.
He's just...
You wake up feeling that you've had a visit from the gorilla by means that something,
something very large and unfriendly, has beaten you around the head,
rifle your wallet and peed in your mouth.
I mean, that's...
Yeah, that is not inaccurate.
So now you get a set of emails going,
"I am your friendly gorilla and here are the seven beers you bought yesterday after the evening."
Yeah.
We should pay for them.
We should discuss the summer of fun.
Oh, yeah.
This is actually this weekend is my summer of fun.
So listeners, astute listeners will have noticed that this episode and the preceding two episodes
had a different theme song to our usual.
And that is because it being summer,
we're all busier than we would usually be.
It's a preceding episode.
The one...
I mean, I know episode X had a different one,
but the one before that I have a different one as well.
I went back and edited it retrospectively to Gaslight Alice-norship,
but don't tell them.
Uh, sorry.
John went back retrospectively and edited it to Gaslight Alice-n.
Well, I know, because I told you straight away as soon as you watched,
is that Gaslight-n?
It's very...
It's more sort of like candle-lying.
Anyway, John is very taken with this idea of the summer of...
Summer of fun?
No, we have to have sort of surf guitar instead of our regular.
Yeah, I think it's quite nice.
I like surf guitar a lot.
I mean, John knew when he sent me the cheesy surf guitar music,
he knew that it was right up like...
Yes.
Ali, because we've been talking about nerd surf guitar tunes.
So we will.
In chat.
We're going to discuss one lock,
because we did get one lock on the last episode,
which we recorded about a year ago, saying it was our best episode yet.
And as Liz pointed out, that means we peaked in September 2020.
So we're very happy about that, obviously.
We know that it's all downhill from here.
But last episode was an episode we recorded ages ago,
and the episode before that was a episode we recorded,
like as soon as dropping the previous episode.
And so this has all been kind of very around our schedules in a way that
normal lock-stalk is not.
But next episode,
we will discuss lots of letters of comment,
and we promise we will cover the important
vanished topics of the day,
which there are definitely going to be by then.
This time, I think I want to talk about how doing things in person with people is fun,
and so maybe we'll be going to in person,
Corflu, and so it will come on.
Liz, are you going to go to Corflu and overcome?
No.
Cool.
By the time we record the next episode,
I'll probably be back in quarantine again.
In July?
Yes, I'll probably be back in quarantine again,
and you know, things as they are,
the idea of quarantining on both ends of a trip is currently not fun,
so no, there's basically no chance I will come to Corflu and overcome.
Yeah.
I will definitely be going to know the quarantine.
You said this in the previous thing,
but you said that quarantining is no fun,
but then we were like,
we're really sorry for Liz who is stuck in quarantine,
and you sent us a photo of the most beautiful garden,
so you know.
Yes, it was a beautiful garden,
and that was all I was allowed to do for today.
Yeah.
So,
Hades?
Not yet.
Yeah.
Don't have a PlayStation 4 with me in quarantine.
Oh.
That could probably be the right to read,
if we thought about it early enough, actually.
Shall I have a Liz squad who just came and gave you like entertainment?
So, it re-naded you.
It was fine, but basically,
it means all trips have to be long trips,
and it is still, you know,
it is still a lot more complicated than it used to be and involves.
It is lovely to see you and so on,
so I'm happy to see you.
Lovely to see you.
Yes.
Very glad I have done it, but I will not.
It is not something you can just leap on a plane and do,
and still.
Yeah.
So, for those who really don't pay attention,
or for whom this is your first episode,
Liz is in the UK, and usually Liz is in Thailand,
so this is very exciting, and it's been very good to see you.
But how you set that?
If you think this is exciting,
wait till the issue when all three of us are in Thailand.
Because John and I are going to be bouncing off walls at one point.
That will be good.
Well, it will be very hot,
so I might not be bouncing off walls.
It is very hot all year round,
or is there a time that we can kind of be on the beach in Thailand,
and it is not so very hot?
What you consider to be...
Above 19 hot.
On a beach.
Yeah, but what temperature do you consider to be very hot is a question.
If I'm on a beach, I'm really comfortable at 90.
What's 90?
I don't know what that is.
Hey Siri, what's 90 degrees Fahrenheit in sensory grade?
The 90 degrees Fahrenheit is 32.2 degrees Celsius.
That's far too high.
Oh yeah, if you like 32 degrees,
then you can get that probably 9 months of the year.
So, but if I'm,
of course I don't tell I could get a hotel with air conditioning.
Yes.
So I get a hotel with air conditioning.
Air conditioning.
At the beach.
Yeah, that's fair.
Yes.
I'm fine with weather in the mid 80s, sorry.
Up to about 30 or so.
I'm British.
The normal British way to do weather is cold temperatures in Celsius is fine.
So if it's down about like two degrees or three degrees,
you do it in Celsius.
So if it's hot, you do it in Fahrenheit.
I think this might be a generational.
It is very much a generation.
In the middle of the scale somewhere.
No.
Anyway, we may have digressed.
Okay, you can.
You can.
You're going to get letters from readers because there are other readers.
No, you can swap.
You may not.
I withdraw any implied permission for you to do so listeners.
And if you have been doing,
I demand you cease now.
Okay, because John is the arbiter of what we do.
That has never been true, even a octa-thole.
Yeah, in this case, I agree with John.
Okay, so on octa-thole, apparently we use the Celsius.
Yes.
That's so useful.
That's actually almost like hugging.
Kelvin would also be acceptable.
I could do Kelvin.
I can't do Kelvin for ordinary UK weather or even Thai weather.
It's pretty complicated.
About 200 and something usually.
No, I think we're kind of like 300 and...
No, true.
Thailand.
We'll be 300 and something, right?
If you could plot the distribution of temperatures in Kelvin in Thailand at different times of year,
and just send it to us for the chapter, I'll be great.
You probably want to get me to do that.
Am I doing crayon?
Yes.
Yes, please do that.
It's crayon.
Program or do you actually mean crayon?
No, I mean with a crayon.
If you draw a barf chart of temperatures in crayon,
I will put it in the crayon.
It's going to be mostly a straight line.
That's fine.
Every minute we spend digressing is a minute
we are not digressing in the pub.
That's true.
I'm sure it's the podcast, isn't it?
I'm sure.
This is too far.
John, this is too far.
So one of the things we have been discussing on this weekend of punctuation
committee meetings is the prospect of future punctuation.
There may be more punctuation.
Yeah, we're thinking about whether we want to do another punctuation.
We're thinking about whether we want to do another virtual punctuation at a time of year,
when although we could theoretically get together and meet people,
nobody's going to want to.
And all we could do a punctuation in person sometime.
And all of these things are possibilities and punctuation too.
Okay, so I need to do a little bit of explanation for punctuation too,
which is because we made too much money for punctuation one.
For punctuation two, we explicitly said that people could pay zero pounds or five pounds or 10 pounds
depending on what they wanted to spend.
In fact, lots of people gave us 10 pounds, so if we make more money and that is paid for our weekend.
But you know, I don't know.
No, it's paid for the grocery.
It's not like we haven't gotten like caviar and cigar.
So we have got the convention to pay for the groceries for our post convention committee meeting,
which is the day.
And by groceries, I do not include the beer of which there was very large options.
Yes, rest assured listeners, none of your money has gone on beer.
Yes, we have not been spending your punctuation funds on double barreled.
No.
No, double barreled is quite good.
Yeah.
Because that's like got a hyphen in the middle and that's punctuation.
No, it could be.
And doesn't they have a hyphen in the name?
Oh, damn.
What was that?
I don't think they have a hyphen in their name.
Really?
I think they're just double barreled.
Too much.
The Spaniards just sent me a picture of some beer.
Oh, no, they do have one in there.
Yeah, it's interesting.
Hey, it's got a very good logo.
Yeah, everything about double barreled is lovely.
We are considering an in-person punctuation or as I think we should call it, in-per-ulturation.
Yeah, okay.
Listen, I like that one, so I can't get away with it.
I'm going to have to cut that one out.
Yeah, no, that don't think that was very good.
I think we're considering it but I don't think we are anywhere near.
Oh, we have no plan right now.
No, other than...
It's a future possibility.
So, what are we all doing on our summer of fun?
Because I have... I got another video game into the Hugo packet, so if you are a Hugo member
and you haven't yet hit us up for free copies of Hades, Spiritfarer, and Final Fantasy 7 Remake,
please do so.
The instructions are in your Hugo packet and if you haven't downloaded the new version of the
Hugo packet, you should do so and get the stuff there.
They're quite good.
Because they're all very good games and I would...
Yeah, so now you can play four of the six games for Nothing
and the other two are The Last of Us Part 2 and Animal Crossing.
Animal Crossing is quite a bit more than Nothing, certainly, because that's how Nintendo do.
I think both of those are quite a bit more than Nothing.
Yeah, they are quite...
They're both lots of games.
I was kind of looking and getting them second-hand but even then they're quite expensive.
Yeah, but then if you buy a second-hand physical copy, you can then take it back to your video game shop and get money.
I have sold Alice in a PlayStation 2, PlayStation 2, PlayStation 4.
I wrote on a tray.
But she's going to go to a PlayStation 4 and I'll play Final Fantasy 7 Remake.
That's the important thing.
You're going to be able to play this Hugo award finalist-ed game.
Yeah, using John's old PlayStation 4 and I have some other games to play and so you won't be hearing
much from me because I'm going to be playing games with the next couple of months.
That's my plan for the next two weeks.
So your plan for the summer fun is...
So in games we're going to see Hampshire tourist attractions that we haven't seen yet.
And cricket.
And cricket to go and see the Southern Brave play Welsh Fire.
So what are you doing the summerless?
Well, I've come to the UK and I've been on holiday and now I'm doing some work and then I'm going to go back to Thailand.
So yeah, my summer is over.
Weirdo.
This is the beginning of my summer-
And your summer is really interesting because most people's summer are hot and sunny.
And Liz.
And Liz is basically deciding to have a cold wet summer as an interjection in the middle of a hot sunny lifestyle.
Yes, I'm wearing a jumper right now.
Yes, but also shorts.
Yeah, that was a tactical error.
My summer of fun is just starting because this
Yesterday marked two weeks since my second jab of the Fonzer vaccine.
So I am now immortal and I can go to places, obviously wearing a mask and
compulsively sanitize my hands and try to say outside where possible,
except for the hotel breakfast this morning, which was less socially distanced than
all of the things I've done in the previous 18 months put together.
How long have we recorded in Freshland Check?
Some.
Oh, yeah, about 30 minutes.
Yeah, so it's very much that lovely.
That was a lot of fun, but beer is also fun and yeah.
And on that bombshell, that was the Hooked to Thought podcast.
And it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
And we are off to the double barrel brewery for hijinks.
I'm getting that out.
We're not but that in the middle of the rest.
What?
That's definitely going.
That will like pick up on the podcast and it's also going to be a nightmare to edit.
Sorry, John.
The theme music for this episode was Surf Shimmy by Kevin McLeod and Combertek.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.