Okay John, I am very very sorry, can you work out why I am very very sorry?
Have you recorded the first half of the podcast on the wrong microphone?
Nope, I've recorded it on the right microphone but it was about two foot from my face.
So...
And so, I'm gonna put this at the start of the podcast and this is gonna function as the apology.
So when you're wondering why Alison is down a well this week, it wasn't my fault listeners, please don't @ me.
Okay, it was my fault.
I will do my best at the edit.
[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 75th episode of Octothorpe, the podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom,
which is coming to you on the 19th of January 2023.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott. And I'm Liz Batty.
And it has been a while since we all sat down and recorded a proper episode.
We have some letters of comment.
Happy New Year everyone.
Happy New Year.
Happy 2023.
Happy 2565.
It's 2565 here. I'm in the future.
I always forget that but yeah, no, Liz is in the future.
[Music]
Is it good in the future?
Both in terms of the fact that she's ahead of us in time zone and ahead of us in year number.
Have they cured COVID in the future, Liz?
No, but I feel I am less likely to get it in 2565 than I did in 2022.
So we had a letter of comment and it came from Sandra Bond who said,
"You've heard of Elf on a Shelf, but are you ready for meeses in fleeces?"
Thank you very much, Sandra.
10 out of 10 loc, made me guffaw.
We also heard from someone who is described in the show notes as Chris
"the legend" Garcia.
And Chris "the legend" Garcia wrote in to tell us things.
He sent it from the Journey Planet email.
And in fact, it's not signed Chris Garcia.
It's signed John Coxon's soulmate.
So John, can you confirm unambiguously that that is a letter from Christopher
J Garcia?
Having read it, yes, I can say that it is a lock from Christopher J Garcia.
But yes, he is my soulmate and he does say that he loves graphs or (dare he hope) charts.
What's the difference between a graph and a chart, Liz?
I don't know John.
Why is the difference between a graph and a chart?
Well, a graph is a thing that you use to show the visualization of data
and a chart is a thing a pirate uses.
Arrr. To visualise data. Yeah. Obviously. He says that he was kind of bummed that Providence didn't get Smofcon.
He really enjoys Providence, especially when they host WrestleMania.
Raj on Twitter.
He says, loc for number 73: graphs!
Hurrah!
Unfortunately, I can't remember why I wanted graphs now.
And then those graphs are pretty interesting.
I hope the fan categories get more love and then bean dice?
Ew.
No, the bean dice are great.
And then he's not read any Stephen King except maybe the odd short story,
but he doesn't like horror.
And so yeah, Stephen King has two modes.
And when I've been listening to people talking about King's most recent book,
a lot of them have been kind of distinguishing between King the horror writer and King the fantasy
writer.
My understanding is that he's very talented in both modes.
I have not read any of his fantasy mode.
I basically imagine him a bit like Optimus Prime, but for books.
I mean, it's fantasy is mostly, it's mostly Dark Tower, I guess.
Which I haven't read, I think is most recent one.
Yeah, it's as similar as I guess you might say with fantasy,
but I primarily read the horror wands.
Oh, well, I've read the stand, which is, you know, kind of post-apocalyptic science fiction in a way.
Post-apocalyptic fantasy?
I don't know.
I mean, there's a play.
Yes.
11/22/63 is science fiction.
But no fairytale is the one I'm thinking of, which came out in 2022 and is very much in his fantasy
oeuvre rather than his horror oeuvre.
Let's continue. This is a boring digression.
Raj and Hugo Girl also sent us a flurry of mentions on Twitter,
which Liz will now summarize.
Yes. So they were discussing a previous episode of Hugo Girl, which was their one about
Callocaine.
And basically to summarize it, Raj told the Hugo Girl team that if they're coming over to Glasgow
for Worldcon, they need to try it iron brew, which is correct.
Yep, true.
And this has spiralled into possibly a sort of American versus British food tasting item at Glasgow.
So if you want to suggest anything that should be included in this episode,
you probably have about a year and a half realistically to suggest them.
But I do think that if they come to Glasgow, we will be making them have iron brew and maybe
deep-fried Mars bar?
Deep-fried Mars bar? Yep.
Haggis.
Oh, deep-fried Mars bar.
Yeah.
I really like deep-fried Mars bar.
I also like deep-fried Mars bar.
Deep-fried Mars bars are great, is why.
Quite hard to get Haggis in the United States because of food safety law.
Laurie and Kevin are vegetarian and vegetarian Haggis is easier to get because vegetables are
less dangerous. You heard it here first.
But vegetarian Haggis is also very nice.
I mean, basically it's the spice mix that makes Haggis nice and you can put that in pretty much
any edible food.
So, um...
I would concur that vegetarian Haggis is not a pale limitation of meat-based Haggis.
It is almost identical and doesn't have weird bits of sheep in it.
So, you know, that's quite good, isn't it?
So Kevin Stanley wrote to us to say you had difficulty finding information about
smofcon and I had put all of the smofcon big presentations in a video on the...
on YouTube, on the smofcon 38 YouTube channel.
And it is fair to say that we didn't go hunting out videos,
though we might have done a few people to link to them. But, um, we don't really like long videos
of the base in presentations as a mechanism for acquiring information because it is very slow.
And we would prefer to get nice, tight news reports.
So, you know, South friction journalists do your bit.
What we don't like is when in order to get the information you have to listen to one or more
people blather on instead of just being able to read it nice and concisely off a webpage.
Oh no, wait.
We do put links in our show notes to be fair.
Yeah, we do. No, and I would also say,
I think smofcon, as a convention full of people who run conventions,
should in many ways be modelling best convention running behaviour.
And I will leave the rest of that sentence as an exercise for the reader.
Have you ever heard the proverb about cobblers children?
No, I'd haven't.
Um, it's about cobblers children and not having shoes.
Yeah, and I'd say the floor here is that, I mean, one thing about YouTube videos is
they're not very indexable in searches.
So when I went searching for stuff about smofcon 40 bid sessions,
I didn't find the videos basically.
No, and it is interesting.
Like, even if Kevin or, well, not Kevin, it's not going to stop necessarily.
But even if someone had sent that to far 770 and far some 70 had literally just linked it,
saying here is the video, I would have found it then.
It's basically a problem with linking as much as it is a problem with anything else.
Like, if you have information, put it in lots of places,
because then you maximise the chance of people finding it.
Kevin does note something interesting, which was that the vote was not obviously split,
kind of US versus rest of world.
There are clearly US and Canadian attendees who voted for Sweden and vice versa.
He basically says that getting to providence from large parts of the US is a little bit of a pain,
because it's really far in the corner.
And I guess it's not a big airport.
So he notes that from where he lives in northern Nevada,
it's almost as complicated for him to travel to providence as to Stockholm.
And that is also a fair comment.
Do you still want to go to both?
I've been to Stockholm.
Want to go to providence?
I mean, Northern Nevada is one of the remotest places on the planet.
You might as well send from the depths of the Amazonian jungle.
It is the earliest part of getting stuck over to get to providence.
I've been to Nevada and I've not been to the Amazonian jungle.
So one day I hope to get to the Amazonian jungle, I suppose is the point.
And then we had another lock, which is from Dave Mansfield.
Dave did some great AI beer recipes, one for each of us,
and then one that combined elements of each of the three together.
I won't read them out, but I will put a link in the show notes to Dave's tweet.
What was the tweet you wanted?
No, it's a letter.
Oh, no, shit, it was an email.
Basically listeners, just imagine a great email.
What I like is that they look as a non-brewer.
They look like they are plausible beer recipes,
but the one for me suggests that you make the beer,
and then you mix it basically equal parts beer,
sweetened condensed milk, and I had a bag of Thai iced tea ricks.
And listeners, I don't think this is a drink I can recommend.
But if anyone wants to try it, I'll bring you a bag of Thai iced tea mix.
How about that?
Yeah, I assume that, you know, Dave will brew all three of these in time for Glasgow
in 2024, and we'll have them on the pot.
Kurt Phillips wrote to us, so Kurt was the only person who mentioned the poem,
and he didn't mention the poem, but he mentioned the picture,
and said, "Why is, why is Greg Thulu behind bars when John Cox said he's on the loose?"
And I think that's a fair question for you, really.
But it's all a matter of perspective.
I did enjoy reading Sandra's poem on the podcast.
I also enjoyed finding out from Alison's reading of the poem
the pronunciation of the word jibber.
That is how you say jibber, is it not?
I think so.
I was trying to channel Stanley Holloway,
and I am not very good at it for anyone who was confused by a poem.
It is a pastiche of the Larnard Albert.
The Larnard Albert is the most famous monologue written by Merit Edgar,
and was made famous by Stanley Holloway.
And we'll put a link to a YouTube video in the show next,
so you can see how it's meant to be said.
Duncan McGregor also got in touch to say that he has not yet finished his Christmas pastiche
due to work, so it might need to wait till next Christmas.
And it's always good to have a bank of forthcoming Christmas pastiche's.
Do write in next year, Duncan.
Obviously, feel free to write in before that as well.
Either Lillian Edwards or a chatbot doing an extremely good impersonation of Lillian Edwards
wrote to say, "Oh damn, I meant to do something about that poem business,"
which is about as perfect a summation of a Lillian Edwards lock as you could hope to get.
We've got a couple of sort of follow-outs or follow-ins or whatever you want to call them,
about our discussion on semi-prozines from a few weeks ago.
So firstly to note that the Locust fundraiser is doing well.
I mean, I think we discussed the Locust fundraiser,
but I think our discussion was less about whether we thought Locust would make its target
and more about whether we thought like the Locust model was sustainable.
But they made their target.
It's very difficult for me to tell because Indiegogo likes to convert everything into your local
currency and I cannot do the back conversion in my head.
They have made $92,485 out of a requested $91,978.
Hang on, that seemed weird.
Oh, I see, but it also says there's a $75,000 goal.
So I think they've added a stretch goal if they get there.
Yeah, I mean, this is good because it means that there will be Locusts for at least another year.
But they do, they have stretch goals, which are basically, if you give us more money,
you'll get kind of some special issues and things, which is interesting because it basically
means if they hit their stretch goals, they have to put out even more issues,
which presumably they also have to print and so on and pay more contributors for.
Ends up giving them basically even more work.
It's interesting to see how that's going to work.
One of the things that is clear, or one of the things that I know from having followed a lot of
board game kickstarters and kickstarters in general, most of the tabletop kickstarters,
is that doing those stretch goals that require you to do lots of extra work is kind of a trap
because quite often what ends up happening is you in no way accurately reflect the cost of doing
the extra work in the extra amount you got from the stretch goal.
So I'm a little bit surprised that they did stretch goals.
It seems like quite a fundraising 101 thing that you might be like,
actually, let's just get the money we need.
And then let's worry about stretch goals next time.
I guess it is a very common thing in, for instance, the semi-prozine kickstarters, all right?
Whenever you have one for, you know, uncanny or strange rather than something,
it's quite common for there to be a stretch goal, which is we will do this special issue.
So maybe it's just kind of conforming to what backers expect.
Maybe, yeah, could well be, that is a good point.
Shall I do a segue?
You could segue.
Because segue's nicely into the next topic, which is over the kind of holiday period,
Amazon announced they were stopping doing magazine subscriptions through Kindle,
which is potentially a big hit to quite a lot of magazines who have a lot of subscribers through
Kindle. And it was interesting that the editor of Uncanny, one of the witnesses of Uncanny,
Michael Thomas, pulled out the numbers of people who were supporting kickstarters for different
semi-prozines, which all come in at basically about 400 to 1000 backers, I think,
locus and out about 1,165 backers. But he's saying that is a relatively small number of people
compared to, say, Amazon's an analog, which apparently have about 10,000 subscribers through
Kindle periodical. So it could be, there is this kind of core of maybe 2,000, 3,000 people who
were supporting a lot of these kickstarters, and they're exactly the people that locus kind of
were appealing to, and have gone for the thing you kind of expect to see on a magazine kickstarter.
But then it's kind of how can you expand that to a wider audience? And obviously the Kindle
periodical was a way of getting maybe a completely different set of people to subscribe to you on
a different platform, and that is now, now gone. It's going to be interesting to see if that has
any effect on sort of the finances and the income of these magazines.
It sort of reminds me a lot of the discussions that were had around sustainability, not from a
profit perspective, but from a reader perspective when Google Reader went away, because a lot of
people were like, "Oh, we should not have relied so heavily on Google to do this because now a lot
of our readers have gone away." And I think a lot of the magazines are going to be like, "Oh,
we should not have relied so heavily on Amazon to do this because now a lot of our readers are
going to go away." So my professional advice here would be if you are reliant on a single platform
for more than about a third of your income, you probably need to have diversification on your
forward plan fairly quickly, because this happens all the time. You know,
bits of platforms that you rely on stop doing the thing you were making money with all of the time.
And it goes double for Amazon, because Amazon, some platforms quite care about their creators,
but Amazon really doesn't give us stuff about you.
This ties into a lot of the reasons why I make sure there are always non-Amazon links in the show
notes every episode, because I don't think we are currently as readers very reliant on Amazon,
and that seems in the long term to be a fool's errand to me.
Yeah, and I'm not going to criticize everything magazines for being too reliant on one or the
other, just that obviously, or on kind of leg of the stool got kicked out over Christmas,
and it's going to be interesting to see if there's a way of replacing that. You know,
does something else pop up where you can subscribe to magazines through it. You can do it through,
say, weightless books website, but obviously there's like a much kind of bigger gap of getting
people to go into weightless books and register for that, and buy the subscriptions and set them
to email to you, and so on. There is to just like clicking a button on the Amazon website,
and it pops up on your Kindle.
Chengdu! Liz, do you want to go into Chengdu? Chengdu! Chengdu! We have talked about the Chengdu
WorldCon before. We're going to talk about Chengdu WorldCon again, because it is getting increasingly
close to the time of the Chengdu WorldCon, and like nothing is happening and no one knows what's
going on. So a brief digression into Wispers Constitution mode. Thank you, John. There
aren't many deadlines in the Wispers Constitution, but there are a couple, and one of them is that
you have to be a member of the WorldCon by the end of January in order to nominate. So it'll be
being a member of Chengdu, or being a member of Chengdu, because they get nomination rights from
the beginning of the year. So basically, it is pretty important that you are able to actually
join the convention by January 31st, if you'd like to be able to nominate. And it seems that you can
now join Chengdu, although I haven't tested it because I have a full membership by voting at
Discord, and I think John and Alison do as well. So I'm not sure any of us have actually tested
this, but it does appear that Chengdu have had an awful time trying to set up credit card payments,
essentially because like the credit card systems and the systems used in China are not well
integrated with the systems used in the rest of the world. And I would assume setting up a bank
account in China to take credit card payments from overseas is not a trivial job. But the outcome
of this is if you would like to nominate in the Hugo's and you do not currently have a supporting
membership, you'll have to try and join. And then I think do a direct bank transfer to someone and
send the receipt to them, and they will check over and then give you a membership, which probably works,
but I don't know like where the bank is that you have to transfer money to. I don't know
whether it's your costs involved with this. Basically listeners, if any of you have tried it,
let us know because I'd be interested to know how it works. But this is one of the things where
it is currently like, I guess it's fulfilling kind of the requirements of the Constitution,
which is you can allow people to join. It doesn't say you actually have to allow people to join
easily or without a large international wire transfer markup or anything like that. And so
it's going to be interesting to see if anyone, you know, does try and change the Constitution
to make it so that, you know, you not only have to allow people to join, but allow people to join
relatively easily. Now the counterpoint to that might be, I have no idea how easy it's been for
anyone in China to become a supporting member of Worldcons for like the past 15 years, possibly
also extremely difficult. But it doesn't seem ideal that this is your solution when you're getting
very close to a deadline. And there's just like, there's a sort of the hand done, like, I don't
think I've actually had any emails from the Chengdu, Worldcon, even though I am a member. We haven't
got any progress reports. There is another petition against their guest of honor,
Sergei Lukianenko, who we'll link to in the show notes.
Confirmed Rotta Sergei Lukianenko. I feel like we should always introduce him with confirmed
Rotta in Starwood name, because he's confirmed Rotta letters.
But yeah, so they are tweeting. And I mean, I can log into their website and see some things and
click on them. And they are tweeting quite a bit, but not thing particularly relevant to
say joining the Worldcon. It'd just be nice to see a little bit more activity. Now,
it has been, I'm sure, extremely hard to deal with the COVID situation. And I'm aware that now
is also basically a holiday. So I don't know if we're going to hear from anything from them soon,
but it would be nice to hear a little bit more from them kind of outside the times when they
absolutely have to say something like at the, you know, smothcon, vanishing position and so on.
And this is something that slightly worries me because I am, although I was not a huge fan of
China's bid specifically, I am in general a huge fan of countries bidding to host Worldcon's
that are not the usual suspects. But I do worry that part of the problem with having a convention
do a bad job of that when they do it, as Chengdu currently are, is that it sours the
pot for sort of future people trying to do the same thing. Like every international
Worldcon that is a complete shower hurts the chance that we'll get more international
Worldcons in the future. And I don't like it when that happens. And it's not fair that it happens,
but it is true, I think. But I will say, like, given that it is a Chinese holiday at the moment,
or coming up very soon with Chinese New Year, they did need to make sure they had all their ducks
in a row before that happened. And they very clearly did not make sure they had their ducks in a row,
which is pain in the butt. Yeah, because nothing is going to happen during Chinese New Year at all,
so which if case anyone doesn't know, it's quite a long holiday, a couple of weeks. And it's normally
a couple of weeks, but a bit of travel. So it takes people a bit of a while to get back into the
swing of things afterwards as well, typically. So when, as I haven't checked, I'm just talking
out of my hat here, but I do wonder if when they say, oh, people have to make a direct payment to
a bank account, that means a direct payment to a US bank account, thereby disenfranchising everyone
who is not in the US or China. But I don't know, somebody, people who do know, write in.
Yeah, I mean, it's not insurmountable to make a direct bank transfer to a US account from the UK.
It's just bloody expensive. Yeah, I mean, there are websites that will allow you to do it for minimal
costs and so on, but it's like an, it's just an extra hoop to jump through. I mean, I will say that
I pay for a lot of things in Thailand by direct bank transfer, like a lot more than ever used to
the UK, because really easy to do. So they may have been thinking, well, we do direct bank transfers
to each other a lot. Let's just set one up so people can do a direct bank transfer to the other
person. I can't test it out because I can't kind of get in and do it without buying a membership,
basically, which I do not want to do because I've already got one listeners, we are guinea pigs.
Yeah, it's also tricky, because all of the things we just said assume that they are,
I think we're Chinese people who are like, well, maybe it works fine for us if we do it like that.
So maybe it will work fine for everyone else. But like, I have a question, which is,
Ben Yalu is the co-chair, and there are other non-Chinese fans involved with this world gone.
And my question to those fans is, what are you doing? They're trying to touch Chinese people.
I mean, it's difficult from the outside. It might be that they're all doing exactly what
they're supposed to be doing. And it's all on the Chinese fans who are involved being horrible
at communicating that means that they're not. And I mean, I don't even care if it is a formal
PR1, to be honest. You could just put a blog post up, title PR1. But it needs to include things like,
when we expect to do stuff, like let you be able to buy a membership or open hotel bookings, or even,
you know, put an informational page up about what you might need to do to get a visa if that's
even going to be possible, that kind of thing. Because this is a time frame when if people were
going to go, they would be thinking about planning their trips. And possibly they are not so bothered
about getting anyone from overseas. But if you don't get anyone from overseas, then I don't really
see the point in having the world come up with just a Chinese science fiction convention, which
would probably be a lot easier to administer for them. And you wouldn't have to muck about with all
this constitutional stuff. It's a mess. Yarrr. But there's still time to fix things. So it's not
like an irreneumable mess. Yeah, it's just a mess where we're saying, yeah, it's probably time that
you started doing a few of these things. And hopefully they will buy that in mind. You know,
when they're listening to us, fountains of all, fanish knowledge.
[laughs]
Yup.
But yeah, it just, it frustrates me greatly, because I would quite like, I would like things to be
different. I'd like it to be a really good Wilcon. And then like, there might be more in
non-traditional Wilcon places. But it's probably not going to be. So...
Nope. So bear in mind that China at the moment can get the Wilcon anytime it wants. So, you know,
it just might not want it. But I think you are wrong in so far as if this is a huge and
shambolic mess, the Wussfish Constitution will be modified to make sure that it is harder
for China to win in the way it did last time. And do you have any suggestions for that modification,
John? Siggly, sickly. Well, though, I mean, firstly, I think there will be modifications,
stuff like you have to have your own email address in your own address. But the other thing I did
wonder was whether it was worth or whether anyone would propose an amendment to the Wussfish
Constitution. So there is 4.6.1. And I'm taking advantage of the Liz Bat's work here, because I
believe Liz posted this in a chat I was having elsewhere and I copied and pasted it into the
show notes. So this is Liz's research. So for what this one one basically says that any convention
that wants to be eligible for site selection has to do three things. They have to file documents
that say that they are intending to bid, they have to have evidence of an agreement with the
facilities such as a conditional contract, and they have to have rules under which their committee
will operate, including stuff like replacing officers and so forth. And I wondered whether
it would be possible to introduce a fourth thing where you have to be able to take card payments
to let people join. You have to show that you can do that, because I don't think it's good, as Liz
said earlier. I don't think it's good for the world con if world cons who are not in
traditionally world con hosting countries end up not being able to have anyone from the
wider world con community attend, because that just seems like it's siloing in a different way,
which I don't think is all that healthy. But yeah, there are arguments for and against probably.
There are lots of places where credit card use is very is quite uncommon, including quite a lot
places that you might have thought that credit card use was relatively common and some places in
which you might think a welcome might happen. I'd be concerned that we don't go for a solution
that has the effect of disenfranchising some countries where credit card uses uncommon.
I think some of the Eastern European country, I mean, I'm probably talking politics again.
But I think we've got to have a balance here, which is I want to make it so that people can
join easily. But I also don't want to put the barriers up for potential bids so high that they
can't meet them if there might be an alternative. I'm thinking of say the proposed Ugandan bid,
who might find it difficult to get, you know, be able to take credit card payments from people
from the US, but they may be able to have an alternative like possibly take them through
PayPal or take bank transfers and have a local agent or something similar. And the reason is also
that, you know, it's possible that some of these places like China will have to bid several times
and I don't want them kind of out of the running of being able to kind of dip their toes in the
water and bid if they have to also be able to demonstrate that their kind of credit card infrastructure
is up and running before they start. So maybe if you said a mechanism to take payments worldwide.
Well, from that perspective, China's got one. You can wire transfer to the states. So that's fine.
And they've already met that. But not at the point where they bid. And this is suggesting we have a
little extra hoop at the bidding stage at the paper filing stage, which has traditionally been
kept very minimal where possible. But if the reason we want to make that change is because
it's very difficult to join China, making it a change that would not make it any easier to join
China seems daft to me. Might as well just not change it. Because you argued earlier in this very
episode that wire transfers to a US bank account were also exclusionary for large numbers of the
world's population. I think I may just be saying that the convention has to absorb the transfer costs.
So they need to bundle in transfer costs for global for global payments into their convention,
design and budgeting. No, because like, I don't know much about the finances of like
conventions in less well off countries. But I imagine that they need lower budgets and asking them to
spend large amounts of their budget that US world cons don't have to spend on that seems very unfair
from an exclusion perspective. The thing is, I can't think of a way of doing this that isn't
massively disenfranchising. And so I think you have to ask a question, is this a big enough problem
that it's worth the risk that it is disenfranchising, which it may or may not be, I don't know.
And then you have to ask the question, like, how do we do this in the easiest possible way
that disenfranchises the fewest people? And I think the more you tie yourself into not trying to
avoid disenfranchising people, my worry is the more you risk doing it. I'd be quite happy if
Chengdu had just said to try con, can you keep your credit card payments open for a little bit
and take some memberships for us, please? Or even to Glasgow? I don't know. I don't see a reason why
Chengdu couldn't say to Glasgow, do you mind taking memberships for us and give us the money?
Is there a reason why not? I think getting the money into China might be the issue, but I don't know.
But I don't see how that's not a problem with wire transferring to an agent in the US.
We don't know if it's a wire transfer trade in the US, I'll just say we were speculating. It might
be that actually when you do the wire transfer on this site, you wire transfer to a Chinese bank account.
So we all speculate a bit there. Oh, I see what you mean. I did read, I'm sure I read somewhere
that it was an agent in the US, but I can't find a source for it. So do write in if you know
listeners. But also, but also, I think the thing is, I don't know if I think that doing memberships
the way Chengdu are doing it is not exclusionary. Yeah, they're planning to open a corporation in
Wyoming. So I think that answers quite a lot of those questions. And they should have done that
in 2021. And it is tricky because I don't know how you square the circle, as Liz says, of making
it difficult for bids to bid. But I was going on a notion of most bids wanting to be able to take
pre support. I appreciate that wasn't true for China because they don't need the money. I'd be
interested to know what listeners think right in, let me know if I'm being hugely unreasonable.
Let me know if I'm not. Let me know if let me know what you reckon. I'm sure we're going to talk
about Chengdu a few more times before the summer. But one thing that has emerged is that I think
they were expecting almost of the entire cost of the convention to be picked up by sponsorship deals.
And I don't think they've actually got those sponsorship deals yet. So I am. I am watching
fascinatedly to see what happens there. So I think that's all we have to say about Chengdu. Is
that all we have to say about Chengdu? For this week. Well, we said we said quite a lot. So
we know I mean that is true. We said quite a lot. And basically you did not come to any strong
conclusions because I think we are balancing the two things of, you know, it should be easy for
people to join your convention foreign country. And we shouldn't make you jump through a lot of
very expensive hoops. Yeah, it is a genuinely difficult. I want there to be a solution. I have
no idea what that solution is. So this is right in. Yes.
Liz is going to do the Run Along Wombl TBR challenge and we'll mention it here for accountability. Liz.
Thank you, John, for reading out what I put in the show notes.
Basically, the Run Along Wombl blog has a challenge to tackle your, you know, to be read pile in 2023,
which is basically a different suggestion for every month in 2023 of how you might read some
of those books that you always buy and then never get around to reading. And I have quite a few of
those. So I thought I might give it a go. So my January, my January project is to read the most
recent book on my TBR pile, which I will get around to eventually, but it's a paper book. So it's
taking me a bit longer than usual. And then for every month, there's like a stretch goal. And the
stretch goal is to read the oldest book. And the other thing I quite like is February. It suggests
that you read 28 short stories, which would work quite well for preparing for Hugo nominations,
assuming the Hugo nominations actually happen and so on. And so I thought I might try following it.
And I thought if I mention it here, then someone might remind me at, you know, intervals throughout
the year that I plan to do this and see if I've actually done any of it. So you heard it here
first, listeners. No, it's a good, it's a good idea. I did on the subject of the stretch goal,
I did see someone in a chat, I'm in, say it's bold of them to assume that I know what the oldest book
on my TBR pile is. And obviously the solution there is to clear your current TBR pile before
starting the challenge. So you do have good data. It doesn't really matter, does it? I mean,
it's in the spirit of things like if I read, Oh, the third oldest book on my TBR pile, who cares?
Some people would, I do not, but actually what I'm doing is I'm reading the book I can find
my, the earliest book in my Kindle purchasing history that I haven't read, which I think is from 2017.
So yeah, might read that. I'm going to, I'm still decluttering. And one of the things I am decluttering
is almost all the books we own on paper that are, that just have text in them, that we are keeping
a few, but very, very few. But I am going to offer an alternative stretch goal, which is to look at
your oldest TBR book, conclusion never going to read it and delete it and then continue with this
process until you get to one that you actually fancy reading and then read that one. Because I
think there's a whole thing about the way in which having a very large number of books you haven't
read, particularly paper ones, weighs your mind down. There are plenty of new books to read guys,
only keep the old books if you really still want to read them. Don't fall foul of the sunk
cost fallacy. Why, why we don't need a book that I've already bought? I have this with steam.
I have so many steam games that I've got in bundles that I'm never ever going to play. I wish
there was a good way of just being like, I don't want this anymore, get rid of it. But every time I
am like, because I can't sell it for like, if I could sell it for a penny, mentally, but like
brilliant, that's good. But just deleting it feels wrong. Like, no, I own this, deleting it will be
wasteful. And so there is a real like tension there, but it stresses me out that I've got all
these games in steam. I mean, also listeners, I did my 2022 steam end of year stats and steam
says I played one game and that game was tabletop simulator. So I think it's time to conclude that
maybe I just don't play games on PC anymore. That phase of my life has passed. Yeah, so I kind of get
both points. I would like to say two further things. One is that obviously I don't actually own my
books because they're on my Kindle. So technically Amazon owns them and could delete them at any time.
And the other thing says, when I said 2017, I didn't mean 2017 at all. I meant 2011.
Oh, oh, that is that is a delightful little coder. I love it. For those who are following along at home,
I was just finishing my undergraduate degree in 2011. I expect Liz, you were finishing your PhD?
Yeah, just finished it. So of course, it didn't read anything during my undergraduate degree or
my PhD that I started reading in. I think I found that my undergraduate and PhD did do a number for
my leisure reading as well. My youngest child had just started secondary school and all you think
people who think that a PhD does a number on your reading habits, you should try having children.
Oh my god. So no, it sounds like a good ploy, Liz. I'm kind of trying to do something similar
with board games, not as a result of this challenge, but the board game app I use to log my board
game plays has so it has like a challenges expansion you can buy in app and you set yourself challenges
and they've recently announced a new type of challenge, which is you can set a challenge to bring
your cost per play of each of your board games down to five pounds. And so I have set that up
basically. So if you spent 60 quid on a board game, you would need to play it 12 times in order
for each player to of course five pounds. And I set myself the target of doing this by first
January 2035. And also, I'm not going to worry if I don't like it's basically just for data. I'm not
actually pushing to try and do it, but it reliably for me, I need to play 287 more games in 717 days.
So that's good. It's got a little graph. Hoorah. John, if you have a game and you know, it costs you
say 50 pounds and you've played it twice and then you sell it on eBay for 50 pounds, do you get 10
pounds in credit? No, but I will say if I buy a game, play it once and hate it and then sell it,
I delete it from the stats completely. So like, you know, I'm making out like a bandit, they're
worthless. Obviously, there's a solution here, which is to never spend more than a five or on a
tabletop board game. But I did notice that board games stats has spaces for how much you pay for a
board game, which I'm trying to fill in. And it doesn't really have a note of how much you
realize when you get shot of it. So I am trying to buy most games, either cheaply or second-hand.
And and so that should reduce the cost per play. My New Year's resolution is to get rid of half
of my possessions pretty much in 2023. But we started early, we started in November. Yeah,
that's a lot. Physical possessions. So I will end up with a very large number of books on
Kobo. And I think that just means that Rakuten owns them all. I don't think it's any better,
though I have a kind of bit of a caliber thing going on. So I do have copies of them all that
Rakuten does not own.
[Music]
Should we do picks? Yeah, suppose so. I can go down the pub. Who wants to start?
I want to start. So like last year, I put a note on my Facebook page. This is a public post,
so we'll link to the show notes saying, "Tell us one good novel written in 2022." And lots of
people did, and about most of them were written in 2022. I'm going to do another post, which will
be out by the time you get this saying, "Recomend me one thing that's not a novel that was new in 2022
that you enjoyed." And so hopefully that will get me a lot of recommendations and things that are
not novels. In the novels, several people said, "Ah, you should read Cold Water by Dave Hutchinson."
And I said, "I cannot do that because I haven't read the first four books in the series." And they
said, "Oh no, you are so wrong about that." So I picked up the first book in his Fractured Europe
series, which is "European Autumn." And I read it, and I liked it very much indeed. And I'll talk
a little bit about why I liked it, which is that it is a near future spy thriller. And I had just
read one of these that I didn't like very much at all. So it was quite nice reading one that I
liked ever such a lot. And the reason is that the balconyization of Europe, it is set in a
Europe which has fallen into lots of little bits as a result of Brexit and not Brexit, but a pandemic
and the independence of Scotland and all of that sort of stuff. And Hutchinson seems to be
seems to be quite prescient because he wrote all of this before all of the shenanigans that have
happened over the last few years. But the book derives a lot of its power and interest from
the way in which these different little bits of Europe are different, and the way in which
increasing borders everywhere makes life difficult for everybody. And it's all very good and very
entertaining, but you kind of go, well, as a spy thriller, this is strange because everything here is
a bit more weird and off-kilter than you would expect if it was a spy thriller, and about 80%
through of the way through the novel. You discover that something entirely different is also going on.
So it kind of takes a very dramatic turn to the left. I absolutely loved it. But it was amazing.
And Dave the first time on Wednesday and said, "Ha, your book is amazing. Oh gosh, it's amazing.
I've met a lot of authors, so I know that if you meet authors and tell them their books are amazing,
they never mind, and it's true he didn't." So that was very nice. If you're listening, Dave,
love your book. I also have Europe in autumn on my To Be Red pile. It's one of my older books on
my To Be Red pile. So maybe I should take Liz's Wha ha. One-bling challenge and use it to read that
other probably not before Easter, because I have reading to before Easter.
I really liked it. Very much looking forward to the rest, although it's a series. So traditionally,
I read the second and I'd like them. Yeah, that's okay, but not as nice as the first, and then I read
the third and go, "Oh no, I'm done with this series now." So I don't know because I've only read the
first, but the first one's amazing. If you haven't read it, you definitely should. It's very timely
because it was published in 2015. There's a thing in the TBR challenge about finishing your series
that you previously started. Did you know, Alison? Oh, I should bet your accountability,
because I said that on this podcast a year ago, I was going to watch all of the Expanse
Television show in 2022, and we are nearly all the way through season two. So that went well,
better than the average New Year's resolution. Very well done, very well done. So only four and
half seasons left to go. I will put a link to, well, assuming Alison is comfortable with me doing this,
I'll put a link to Alison's year in review, exaltation in the show notes, and I will also
put a link to the Strange Horizons round up of the year, which I read and got some good
recommendations out of as well. Liz, do you want to go next? Or do you want me to go next?
I can go next, if you like. Hey, do it. I've picked a book which, I don't know, it's maybe not my
favourite book I read over the holidays, but I thought it was quite interesting and might be
interested in this. It's a book called A Game of Birds and Wolves by Simon Parkin, who I think
has previously written quite a lot of stuff about video games, but this is actually about,
it's about the battle for the Atlantic during World War II, which was a battle basically between
the German U-boats and the merchant shipping that was trying to desperately feed Britain during the
Second World War. And the bit I was completely unaware of is that there was essentially a unit
who came up with, it's actually a big board game, that they used to plot out strategies to,
you know, beat the U-boats quadrants. And so that was interesting and it's got a bit about like the
history of, you know, war gaming and it's not the first time that war games have been used to
train people in more time, but this appeared to, you know, be pretty successful. Came up with several
strategies that were used to even the odds between these merchant convoys and the U-boats. And the
other interesting thing is that a lot of the participants in this were the Ren's, so the women's
role-neighful personnel and because a lot of them were involved, essentially in setting up the game
and in managing it and also ending up becoming very, very skilled at it to the point where you had
these Ren's playing as submariners against like the captains of Royal Naval ships and beating them,
essentially because they become so good at kind of the rules of this game. And that is very
interesting. Unfortunately, it's a little bit underplayed because it's quite clear that,
basically, not a lot of them wrote memoirs or things like that. And certainly not the same degree
that kind of high up male Royal Naval personnel were. And so there's some sort of tantalizing things
where we maybe don't actually know quite enough about what their thoughts were at this time.
But it sort of blends kind of a high level of view of the battle for the Atlantic,
the Ren organization, and a few of the specific ones who took part in this, and some of the
also officers who were doing it because they're the leading officer with someone who couldn't be
on active service due to illness and disability, but was able to kind of take this part of training
thousands of ship captains to try and defeat the U-boat tactics. So it's goes great and frustrating
in that obviously there's a lack of some of the primary sources you really want to be in there,
and maybe it could go into a bit more detail in places. I kind of wanted more detail on what the
Ren's were always doing in the military, and you'd get quite a bit more about what was documented
about, say, when they fell in love with Royal Naval Naval Naval so married them because I think
we've got a bit more documentation on that. But it was a pretty satisfying read, and certainly I had
no idea there was this board game that was being used to game out tactics against submarines that
seemed to work pretty well. So I recommend it. On the topic of board games, yes, so there's been
like board gaming in war, and board gaming in defense is really interesting. There's like
been a bunch of stuff on it. There's like a few FBI board games as well that are used to train,
I'd say FBI or CIA, but one of the one of the federal US agencies still uses them to this day,
but it's fascinating. Well, that is mentioned in the book actually briefly. He goes to, he's allowed
to sit in on one of the kind of war gaming exercises that they do at a miniature base and not give any
details but kind of give like a kind of general overview of it. My experience of playing games
that I used for scenario planning for all sorts, it's not just war actually, games turn out in all
sorts of planning exercises. I don't think that's in any way secret is that they're not fun like
real games are. It's a bit like fitness games or things like that. As soon as you apply actual
purpose to the games, they're way less fun than the games we like to play for fun.
I had to think about picks because we haven't recorded for a little while, and I have consumed
media like I've consumed more than one media since last time we got together. And so I had to
consider which one to pick. Obviously I did consider picking the cricket book. I can't remember if
I've mentioned the cricket book on the podcast. I'm not picking this obviously but if I were to pick
it, I'd be picking a hit against the spin which is basically quite good because it uses data and
it has parameter spaces in it. And if you have any interest in data or sport at all, I would
recommend it. Even if you're not specifically interested in cricket, I think it has enough to
say about data in sport is good. Claire's gonna lend it to me. But in fact I'm gonna pick something
asefnel. I'm gonna pick the Moon Day Letters by Emmy Iteranta, which was given to me by Nick
Clark and Neil Harrison from The Birthdate. Thank you very much. Peeps and is really good.
It's an odd ten book. You're good. It has more? Yeah. It's about a woman whose spouse is on a
work trip and it's about how that goes. And it's told in the form of her journal over the course of
some time. I'm not quite sure exactly how much time but kind of certainly several months. And
the setting is effectively the way I put it. So Neil and Neil didn't think I was being
horrendously daft. Was it a bit like a magical realism version of the Expanse? So like it's
kind of a solar system where Earth isn't doing so well and Mars and other colonies are kind of
overtaking it. And the character we follow is from Earth originally and we follow her kind of
throughout the solar system as it were. And it's really interesting. It's really good. I liked it a
lot. Neil and Abigail both raved about it and I've seen other people raving about it too.
And that was the old thought podcast and it's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
It's basically what we need to do is we need to develop a convention board game.
Well it's if I ran the zuc on which which we've recommended to you multiple times in the past
but it's quite dated now. Which I have previously thought actually well there's a new edition which
I've never played. It's still quite dated. Yeah but I wondered if it was worth getting the updated
edition and making you and John be convention committees for a podcast one day. How do I play
if I run the zuc on? Because when you have previously talked about it I have thought it was like
oh there is this thing. I didn't think it was a recommendation of you should go and find it and
play it. It's a board game. It's not a recommendation of that and it's not really a board game. It's
like a like a scenario. I am on the board game geek listing. I've been on the board game geek
listing and in files it says no files found and in overview it says propose official link.
So it is now on my it's on my want to play and I want to play it make it happen.
Well you can get it from the nest for press website but I'm not sure if you can I think you can get
the PDF. Let me check. You probably wanted to have a PDF. I love for a PDF. There was also a
British version of this. Have you ever played Mystic Wood? No. Okay so Mystic Wood's a classic
board game and there is a convention version of that called Mystic Con which is kind of like if
I ran the Zucom but for Britain and also very old. I work Old Avalon Hill game. Yeah I mean the
the first edition of If I ran the Zucom is 1986 which I'm sure not much has changed
it aboard con running since 1986. I only played it once at a one of the pre-world con con runner
things and it was hilarious because we spent a lot more of our money and people points on booze
and were like does this stuff we need a sweet really? Nah. And then you like it basically doesn't
really work I think for it did it was it was both quite dated and quite American so. So fun fact
I'm now on the nest for press website because like having now realized I can play this I do
and ironically want to but there's no search function which I feel like if you're running a
website that sells things you should let people search for them but I can purchase if I ran
the Zucom for $15 in the fourth edition and it is 146 pages. Well I assume what? They used to be a
t-shirt produced by Offworld Designs. Oh well the t-shirt. If anyone's got that t-shirt my address is no
um oh cartoons by Steve Styles. I think we should see if anyone has like if anyone honestly does
have a copy of the fourth edition I mean I'd love it if there was a PDF version but I don't think
there is like if someone did have it I presume it's still the same as the first edition it's sort of
like a team game and then you have like a games master reading out a scenario of a thing that's
happened at the convention and you have to decide how you're going to deal with it and you have
finite amounts of people points and money points and something else points and if we could find
one I would play it with you guys as a podcast I think it could be quite funny but also we might
just be mean about it because it's very dated at this point. If anyone has a copy of um Mystic
Con the British one and would like to lend it to us that would also be quite funny I think.
Bring it to a fan fun dog shit and I will spend an unwise amount of money on it.
Yeah if somebody could bring a copy of um Zucon to a fan fun dog should that
would probably be on that too I should think. Now that I know that it's available from
Nest4Press for $15 like that does put somewhat of a um upper limit on why I might be willing to pay.
It does say it's got some kind of additional scenarios added in the uh
oh in the 2015 update um sorry I just found a website which is claiming it will sell me the
PDF for $5 now I have to see if they're actually. Linky, Linky or look at the page.
Oh all right so I guess this is Nest4 have put it on a print on demand tight.
Oh no that looks legit. Yeah yeah we probably do want this as a new book right?
I mean we're all about to buy it I assume all three of us are currently creating an account on
the book patch.com and you know they say that just listening to people doing things in
silence is not podcasting gold but I think in this case it might be. I've tried to buy it on PayPal
and PayPal has said that it's gonna review my thing for security reasons. Why is that?
I know why that is it's because they got three purchases for the same item
two different countries all at the same time. No I've bought it so uh oh okay fine.
Liz let the side down. Well I'm gonna do it later.
Top Encouraging to meet a multitask while on the podcast don't. Yeah.
Sometimes I ask you a question you sort of have zoned out and I'm like John is reading
something right now so stop encouraging me to do that. eBay who clearly knows what I like
has just sent me a link to a palette of 200 random board games. Oh board game.
I know we were talking earlier about cost per play and never spending more than a certain amount
per board game but I do think there is some merit in selecting the board games you want to play.
I think this is probably if you would like if you like opening that board game pub that I'm not
gonna open in 2023 I would actually go for something like that as a way to have a lot of games.
When you say it's a palette of 200 random board games are you sure they're 200 different board
games. They might be 200 copies of cocoson. In which case you've got a very boring pub.
Palot job loved over 200 assorted board games. Games will differ to those in the photo but will
be similar games are all unchecked. I sorted he's doing a lot of work there for 200 pounds and
and they look mostly like 200 pounds for 200 board games here. That's a pallet board game it's deep.
The theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in compactec.com
used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license. This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.
[ please sub and ring the bell for no supports. ]