Yes, because we segued to that some time ago.
Hello everyone and welcome to the 22nd episode of OctaThought, a podcast to science fiction and science fiction fandom.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
Happy New Year.
Yes.
We're into the second year of OctaThought, well not quite the second year if you count 12 months, but the second year counter-chronologically.
Yeah, anyone who is not using an OctaThought-centric calendar is clearly a Ronan.
I mean, that would be true if we only recorded two episodes, so...
That would be true if we'd only done two episodes.
Yeah, I mean, if we'd still... it's either podcast in like November, then it would also be true that we'd be into the second year of OctaThought,
but I don't think it would be a particularly great achievement.
Okay, so I feel like OctaThought was one of our reactions to what 2020 was.
And so here we are in 2021, which means we have survived 2020 and 2021 will definitely be a different sort of year.
It's true.
We have survived 2020 and I think it is definitely true that while I know John had been talking about podcast for a while,
it took actually being stuck in his house for us to actually sit down and do it.
Is that fair, John?
I think so.
It is difficult to argue with the facts, which doesn't necessarily always stop the three of us, but yeah.
OctaThought really helped me in 2020 and apparently also, Klebrile from Croydon, who was written to tell us so...
Oh yeah, that's a great segue.
And I have really cemented it by noting that it was a segue, so that's good.
Claire says that she liked episode 21.
Claire made an excellent joke in her letter of comment, which was...
When we were discussing what could be nominated for best games or interactive experience, you go.
Claire has then thought about what could be in a future best interactive experience, you go.
And then moved on to make a very good joke about what could be the best inactive and experienced, you go.
And owing to the problem several weeks ago, where I read out the first draft of Claire's letter and did not correct her typo,
I then emailed her to say, "Oh, is this a typo?"
And she was like, "No, it is a clever joke."
So I'm very sorry, Claire, for doubting that your clever joke was a clever joke and check if you made a typo.
But it's because I'm now paranoid about reading out the wrong versions of your letters.
So I don't know. Maybe you should put a deliberate mistake in your letter so I can transport it next time.
And in that sense, Claire's locks will become an interactive experience.
Oh, Roman Ozansky wrote us a letter of comment, kind of about our discussion about interactive games.
One of the things he said was, it wasn't until the podcast ended that I realized that the long game was Claire's brilliant gameplay
in that by interacting with the Octa though creators, she has altered the tone and content of the podcast.
And surely this then counts as an interactive game.
And so, yes, Oxford thought, vote Oxford thought for best interactive experience.
If you would like to vote for Octa thought for best interactive experience, turn to page 34.
If you would like to vote for Octa thought for best podcast, turn to 41.
If you would like to vote for people not self-upercising for the Hugos, please turn to 2001.
If you would like to vote for Octa thought for best fanzine, please turn to 2005.
Are we eligible at best fanzine?
No, we would have been in 2005, though.
Hence, the joke.
Oh, I was really sorry.
Was that a joke?
I thought it was a typo.
It was a joke.
No, was it?
Was it 2006 that best fan cast came in?
Yeah, I think that's right.
Yeah.
Please nominate us for several of the non-existent Hugo categories that Alison invented in the previous second of the podcast because it would be quite funny.
Exactly.
And then Dave Mansfield is going to nominate the spacebar from punctuation for the Hugo because the Ludo narrative was much better
than the rehearsed plots that have been played out beforehand.
So thank you, Dave.
I am enjoying the number of things that the Hugo movie straight is going to be like, what?
What is that?
And why has it been nominated just from like two people in the UK?
I'm looking forward to it.
And if Claire and Mark are helping with the Hugo's again this year, I'm really sorry, Claire and Mark.
On the subject of Mark, Mark sent me an email, not the podcast.
We're going to take the liberty of mentioning something he wrote.
So Alison referred to Outworld 71 in the last episode of Octthorpe.
It is a fanzine.
You can buy it off Amazon for the Princely some of 15 currency units.
I will put a link in the show notes for anyone who would like to discover more about Alison's mysterious references from episode 21.
Thank you for letting me know, Mark.
Can I actually buy 15 currency units or is that only certain currency units?
It is definitely a currency unit.
I forget whether it's pounds or dollars, which is why I suspect it's 14.
$0.99.
Okay.
Andrew Hogg has also asked about the disc on Hugo and he asked on a discord how it will cope with early access games and such like.
So for those who aren't familiar, video games sometimes come out in an early access form where they're not finished, but you can buy them, which is a delightful mechanism of commerce, which I love.
Well, and so those who aren't familiar. So for instance, the kind of the best example I can conjure is that Minecraft when it became really big in about 2010, 2011, Minecraft was in early access and it was only officially released quite a few years after it had become a worldwide phenomenon.
And so the question is like, would Minecraft be eligible again when it hit 1.0?
Would it be eligible again when it hit beta?
Would it have been eligible in alphurks?
It wasn't properly out yet.
And that is actually a good question and one I intended to bring up last week, but we had been talking about the Hugo category for about 50 minutes solidly at that point.
And I thought perhaps having more was not desirable.
And I love the fact that Mark and Claire having volunteered to help with the hugos at having zero interested video games will get to make judgments of this sort of fine detail.
I was going to say that as brought up by Listen Joe on a Discord elsewhere, probably the real issue here might be Stardew Valley because that had a big patch this year, which introduced a whole bunch of new content.
And it is also a game which is, which can plausibly be nominated for the best video game Hugo this year.
So this you will be does having a big patch with new content qualify it to be kind of nominated as a 2020 game.
So we're going to enter all kinds of discussions of how much new content was there because it's not done as a standalone.
It's not a standalone expansion or anything.
It's a, oh, we have dropped the new content and there is a different farm and some lots more content.
So no, it's interesting.
I think this is the thing I'm the least convinced about by this, this Hugo category.
There is no proposal to have a hard and fast set of rules about this, which is probably in some ways very sensible because doing a high.
Hard and fast set of rules about this seems like it would be incredibly difficult because it's so woolly, but equally I do want the extent to which different
administrators are going to have different takes and the extent to which the fandom is going to be one of the other things Claire mentions is a Hugo voters known for their restraint or their ability to not nominate things for the memes.
Perhaps perhaps she has a point.
So we'll see.
We'll see how it goes.
It may be that it takes a couple of years for the best interactive experience to get into stride and for people to get a sense of what should and should not be nominated.
I also have a tiny bit of follow up on best video game, which is that a podcast which I listened to, but which is not on the subject of video games had a set of awards for the year, which quite light hearted, which included best video game and
44% of the nominators nominated animal crossing New Horizons.
So I think that's the extent to which, as I suggested last time, that this category is going to be dominated by that game in this year, not necessarily in every year.
I'm looking for the Upgrades website and I can't find it.
It'll be an upgrade somewhere.
I mean, you could you could link to the upgrade is, but I don't think it's terribly relevant.
The reason I was looking for the upgrade is was because the other thing that was really interesting, which comes down to something I mentioned last episode was that the runner up for the game of the year was among us, which is not a game that was released last year.
Because it is very popular and it became very popular last year.
And so I think that's the other thing we did highlight, which is among us is going to get votes and they're going to have to decide whether or not it counts.
And I think that is actually a hard choice.
And so I do, I do wonder the extent to which we need to start having conversations about, you know, these are games which are clearly going to get nominated.
And we probably ought to have a discussion about whether or not they're eligible in advance of, you know, the Hugo administrators who may not be particularly plugged into the video game scene, making those decisions on Vanden's behalf.
No, but I think they are plugged into the podcast that talk about the video game scene like ours.
Oh, yes, I mean, obviously all of the Hugo administrators will be keenly listening to what we say about this.
And I will, I will put a link to the upgrade is in the show notes.
Maggie sent us a letter of comment.
I don't know to either of you know, she's just signed it Maggie of Glasgow.
So Maggie of Glasgow sent us a letter again discussing our discussion of the special Hugo category for video games and discussing also the fact that as well as triple A game,
being quite expensive, they also, some of them require quite a large time commitment.
Do I think we discussed a little bit and some AA games are incredibly long and some are quite a lot shorter.
Maggie says they have been playing the Witcher 3 for about two years now on and off and are still only halfway through.
So I guess the issue there is, yeah, how many of the likely nominees are games that take an awful long time to finish?
And also if the AA game has taken over a long time to finish, how quickly do you know whether you would feel happy nominating or voting for them?
Because if it's a game that I'm willing to think about 150 hours into a playthrough of, then I probably know after the first like 20, whether I'm thinking this is a good game I'm going to nominate.
And the answer is probably yes, because I'm willing to put 150 hours into it.
Yeah, I think, I think that's fair.
I think if you're reading like the people who read the people who nominated, for example, like the S.F.
Encyclopedia for best related work.
I suspect they hadn't read the whole thing, but they had read enough of it to know that they thought it was worth nominating for you.
And I think the same thing will apply with longer games.
Like if you have any blast, like it's fine just playing her eyes as a redone.
And I think I speak for her where I'd say if it was eligible, she would nominate it and she hasn't seen the ending yet, but she has been playing for like over 100 hours at this point.
So I think that would probably indicate that she's enjoying it enough to nominate it.
Lots of games don't have endings and lots of games.
Nobody ever sees the ending because there's so much content.
If it has an ending, that ending should be moderately satisfying, but they're off a lot.
They're off a just this is the point where the content finished.
Well, that shouldn't that doesn't necessarily matter for games.
Yeah, I would also say there are games with fairly unsatisfying endings.
And I'm thinking of Mass Effect 3 in particular where there was a massive campaign to get from people who wanted their money back because the ending was so unsatisfactory.
And actually, I agree that the ending is not great, but it's still a pretty great game anyway.
And the ending doesn't actually ruin that.
So yeah, the ending is maybe not the destination as much as if I'm reading a novel.
The ending is just a point along the way where I then go back and finish all the side quests.
Yeah, and I think that gets a little bit until I will be talking last time about like new,
Lou Donerative and stuff like that.
But thank you for very thought provoking email Maggie.
And thank you for everyone who wrote in.
It was a bumper roster this week.
Okay, so the attentive listener may have noticed that it is 2021 now and therefore that means that 2020 is over.
So we're going to talk about 2020 as it was.
So 2020, let me review the fan act that happened worldwide lots in the UK, mostly Alison.
Alison, do you want to talk about that?
Is that a helpful way of framing it?
I'm not sure if it is helpful.
It's not just me, but I think one of the things to have to Christmas is that I had a party, which I might talk about a little bit separately.
But lots of other people in fandom also had parties, but also lots of other people who are not so connected with fandom.
Had parties and I started to notice that the things that science fiction fandom has been doing for the last nine months to have fun online have not really percolated through the wider community and a lot of things that when people are saying, oh, 2020 has been appalling.
It's because they're not doing the things that have made it less appalling for me and for I think a lot of other science fiction fans.
But I made more new friends in 2020 that I have done in any year, I think, since I left university.
And that's that's kind of not what you would expect really.
Here it is.
It's a pandemic and I'm stuck in my house.
What am I going to do?
I'm going to make friends with a lot of new people.
I know that you feel uncomfortable about.
I think I think you are reticent stake all the credit, which I think is to your credit because obviously it was not just you and I am being slightly facetious.
But I will say that you have done a lot more.
You have been a driving force in British fandom this year to an extent that I think you are slightly unaware of.
I think without you, my 2020 would have been a lot less fulfilling.
So thank you, Alison is what I'm saying for making my 2020 much better.
Yeah, OK, so that is kind, but I was doing this because I'm not working in a hospital or volunteering in a food bank or changing the world by doing making big political change or that sort of thing.
You know, I kind of was stuck in the house trying not to get sick.
So it's kind of, well, what can you do if you're stuck in the house trying not to get sick that will be moderately helpful.
And it turned out that for me, the answer was run parties on zoom.
Yeah.
So I don't know.
Yeah, I've run some parties on zoom.
So it as it happens every year, it got to the end of the year and people started saying it's 2021.
Where am I jetpacks?
And for those of you, I don't think we talked about this in, we might have mentioned it in the last Doctor of Thought, but quite a lot of you will have been at.
And many of you will have heard of a party that I helped run over New Year's Eve, where we had, I think, almost 300 individual actual people from all over the world, partying on zoom for 24 hours.
We had a few program items that just kind of slipped in there, just in case 24 hours of just hanging out on zoom was too much for you.
And we celebrated, we had Laurie Mann finding firework displays from every time zone to display at the top of the hour and other bits of the hour, because actually not all time zones happen at the top of the hour, as you'll know if you paid attention to guff.
And yeah, so we, so, so, so, I feel like this is one of the most science fictional things I've done in my whole life.
This is one of these things where, if you've said to me when I was 10, oh, people from all over the world will be able to get together for a drink.
In, when you're 55, I would have gone, oh, that's pretty cool, listen to it.
And yes, we don't actually have teleport devices or anything, but, but seeing as we were kind of the sort of people who were mostly living in our heads anyway, it's not such a big problem.
If we, if science fictional fans were more visceral people, it might not have been as much fun.
I think I've done some things in 2020, like I did anoraptories, a TAFTRIP report interviews, which were a good thing to kind of get Vanish people together and kind of have a chinwag.
I edited a few van zines, I did a journey plan, a couple of shows with Lolsene, which was, which was cool.
And obviously I've done this podcast, which I think has done something to kind of foster communication in British science fiction fandom.
And I flat myself that I think all three of us contribute a lot, but I think probably I am the driving force behind this, like probably 40% me, 30% both of you.
It's like that adds up to 100, right?
Yeah.
I mean, I think John Zessner, 40% John, 30% the turbos for the podcast is extremely generous because, oh, it is mostly John.
Sorry, I didn't mean to say that.
John's done a ton of stuff this year, actually, yeah, because he is absolutely the driving force behind this podcast.
It would not happen if it were down to me.
And I don't think it would happen if it were down to Liz, but it definitely wouldn't happen if it were down to me on a couch of how all of the editing and making it happen stuff.
Oh, yeah, I just turn up Waffle for 90 minutes, try and stop you guys going wildly on to off topic and failing, discussing the orbit of the sun.
And then if I'm very good, I remember to send the file to John.
I think I'm just saying that I, if it was down to me, this podcast would not happen because I have no concept of how to do audio editing.
Now, I think, you know, Alison obviously became basically the party maven of the entire UK fandom, and I popped into many of her Zoom meetings and her new year party, which was very entertaining.
John made multiple TAF reports happen, I think, and wrote bunch of fanzines.
And I didn't do very much because 2020 was a less weird year for me.
And because, yeah, let me think of that phrases.
I've put in the show notes Liz had a 20, chill 2020 owing to having a toned toes done and swimming and whatnot.
I did do a bunch of swimming and I did have my toes done a few times, that is true.
But yeah, it's partly that I had a more chill 2020 than many people did, which I'm very grateful.
I also had a very busy 2020 work-wise.
And also, I do feel a bit of a distance because of how the Earth orbits the sun and we have time zones.
It does feel a bit isn't basically you have to plan a lot more.
Like if you want to chat to people, you have to put a bit more thought and planning into it because you have to have to have that happen during the eight hours of the day when you're both awake.
So I think it's a bit easier if you don't have those problems.
So really in terms of fanak, I already did not do a lot.
So maybe 2021 will be the year in which I do more fanak.
But let's not go too far.
I think obviously I know that you are in Toyland as we may have covered on this show previously.
Many times, yes.
And like Alison and I are, and we try not to get deeply into politics on this show, but Alison and I are in a country where it is possible that the government have not had the best ideas about how to deal with COVID as COVID has unwrapped around them.
I think that is probably a thing I can say out loud.
You know, we're in a category along with the US and Brazil that are completely making the most complete meal of this, I think, that is possible to imagine.
Anyway.
But what I will say is that although I appreciate low, obviously, if most of your friends, if you are in a country where that is not true and most of your friends are in a country where that is true, it must be a bit surreal to be like, well, you know, Thailand's cooked with it quite well.
And I'm not too impacted, but I think I don't, although me and Alison regularly listeners take the piss out of Liz for how Liz is allowed to go outside and have fun and we have to stay in our houses and just be, you know, sad.
I think in general, you know, I'm glad that you are in a place which is less completely up a creek than the UK is at the moment.
And I am happy about that.
Yeah, I am happy for all my friends that are in places where, like, where everything is more or less OK. And, and I'm also, there's some people who've been going, well, 2020 was not at all about here for me and I feel guilty and embarrassed about that, because I've had, and I feel like we should,
there are plenty of people for whom 2020 has not been bad, including, I have to say, me, lots of good things happen to me in 2020, like making loads of new friends, like running a load of parties, like discovering that, that I was much better at being a party host if I don't have to tidy my house in order to run a party, which, you know, who knew.
But Liz, you were saying you might do more fan act next year. Have you got any concrete plans or do you just feel a vague sense of guilt that me and Alison have been cooped up and so we've been lashing out creatively and you've been living a more normal life and have therefore, you know, been out living.
Yeah, I basically just feel a vague sense of guilt until I have done what I usually do whenever I say I'll write a fancy article for someone which is say yeah yeah I'll definitely do that I feel bad for not having it, but then not do it.
I mean, this is partly because what I quite enjoy doing is helping run conventions and I do enjoy helping run online conventions but not as much I enjoy helping run in person ones, especially when there was online conventions involved me either getting up very early or staying up very late.
And I think the one thing we have all forgotten to mention in our fan act is that we did run a convention and Liz did run the convention.
It did not. Yeah.
So, see, I was on the.
I actually have a set of notes.
But I think I'm not, I'm not over egging the pudding where I think Liz probably put.
Liz did more work with anybody else on punctuation. Let's be clear here. Liz did the program.
Yeah, I think I don't want to, I don't want to, I don't want to offend Stephen, but I feel like he would, he would agree that Liz probably had the most to do in the con running.
Yeah, don't you remember that Steve was gearing up at the point where we were really, really up against it for punctuation and he got a new job.
Oh yeah, that's true.
Congratulations on the job Steve.
Yeah, which is going quite well, I think.
So yeah.
Hey, that's good. No, but no, Liz did, Liz did an awful lot of the punctuation prep for which, you know, we're very grateful because it was a, it was the bits that Liz did were very good, the bits that I did were fine, but the bits that Liz did were excellent.
So, you know, hurrah Liz.
Thank you. I think it all went well.
It's very hard to tell actually who did, it's very hard to tell how much people have done, I think, but I guess we could go and look through all the little actions I ticked off into.
I ticked off in Discord.
In my journal, I had a load of outward focused and inward focused things that I did in 2020 and there were five outward focused things which were the Zoom coffee mornings and the parties, all the Zoom stuff, the first Thursday and the, the
party, which incidentally I did with Karen Ward and Mike Schafer, who normally have a big in person party. So they just invited the whole of their list, who are calif, mostly Californians and, and West Coast, USians to the party to, and that kind of gave it a whole lots of different people who don't necessarily already know each other, which is good.
Octothorpen punctuation, which I think we've spoken about a bit, and the guff trip.
Oh yeah, you did a guff trip.
Oh yeah, you did, you did do a guff trip.
Which I only just mentioned sideways. I did an entire three week virtual guff trip at a writing about it.
And then, and then the last thing I had down was that I've done a load of tissue paper art, which amused my neighbours and incidentally my friends on the internet.
It did, it was, it was very good. Yes, I think you had not made the Octothorpe tissue paper art last time we published an episode, so you should send me a bit of it so I can put it in the chapter art.
I did a number of inner growth things in 2020 as well, and the most notable of which was that about a month before everything kicked off, I, I decided to give up anger almost by accident.
And although, obviously I've not always succeeded, I've given up anger in the way that somebody gives up smoking, but occasionally bumps cigarettes off people.
So like that. So I occasionally bum anger off people.
I don't know what to say, that is the logical conclusion. That, that is the episode title, bum anger off people. I don't know what it means.
Yeah, no, no, no, so I occasionally discover myself having a little bit of angry rage, but I'm much, much better at going that thing where you just stay angry or become very angry or do stupid things because you're in a rage.
I'm not doing it like any more, I'm done with that.
In 2021, one of my things I'm going to do, one of my three New Year's resolutions, what I posted on Facebook was to release an issue of Lolsim every month.
Yay!
So Lolsim is the comedy focused science fiction podcast I do with my wife, it's by Nisha.
Sure.
Yes, sorry, let me start again. Lolsim is the comedy science fiction fan scene that I do with my wife, it's by Nisha.
We did four episodes on our website, Lolsim.net, and then we decided that issues.
[Lolsim laughs]
Sorry, cut in red flow there.
No, no, it's entirely my fault. That was a sigh of disappointment at myself.
[Lolsim laughs]
This has to stay in, this has to stay in.
It's Fanny and I did four issues of our "franzing" on Lolsim.net.
Before we decided that doing a fan scene on a website is really quite a lot of effort and doesn't really encapsulate most of the things we enjoy about writing fanzines.
We've transitioned to a tiny letter, a newsletter.
A tiny letter is a product that has been bought by MailChimp, which lets you do small, simple email newsletters for up to, I think, a thousand people.
I don't think we're going to get to a thousand people.
We are doing Lolsim on there.
We're reprinting the articles that we did on the website, and we're printing new articles, and we're putting some art in each issue.
If you'd like to sign up, there will be a link in the show notes.
It comes out once a month.
It turns out it's much more fun doing an email fanzine than a website fanzine while getting away from.
I really don't like PDFs as a way of reading things, and I think it was great when people were beginning to go online with their fanzines, but I think a lot of fanzines just thought, "Oh, we could put PDFs on the internet and that will be fine."
BananaWink does an e-pub, which is much better, because you can read it on a phone and it's not like in tiny writing, and I think e-pubs are great.
I did that when I was publishing Procrastinations way back when.
And Alison did a fanzine or a perzine, I suppose, on an email mailing list, which ran for us.
Yes, it's tiny letter. I thought you were also tiny letter?
Yes, we are.
I was just listening to you talking about Lolsine, and I'm like, "I don't have New Year's resolutions, but I'm actually going to do some more of those since I monthly sounds good."
They were really good, and I think they really neatly encapsulated the feel of a fanzine going to a small group of people, and the feel of the issue by issue nature of fanzine without replicating the kind of annoying technical limitations of paper fanzines or PDF fanzines.
And so I kind of feel like it would be cool if a lot more fanzines embraced email as a potential medium.
And I'm surprised that more haven't, but, you know...
There's a problem with the... This is probably a bit abstruse.
There's a problem with my fanzines as it was constructed in that it was very remit.
It was very requiring of external links.
It had a lot of links in it, and you were expected to go and look at them when they interested you.
And this is fine in terms of a thing that is current, but links break at a massive rate.
So for archiving purposes, I was very keen to have a sort of secondary document that, for me, that said all of the...
That explained what all of those links were and meant, and that's tedious.
So it kind of ended up in a... It basically disappeared up its own ass, and I need to find a way to do it that does not involve it disappearing up its own ass.
But I do have a third issue, nearly done or something, so, you know, I could do that.
That sounds like a... I'm not... I don't do resolutions. I'm having a yearly theme in the way that my lovely, lovely tech bloggers like, and tech podcasters.
They're not bloggers, they're podcasters. Sorry. My yearly theme is automation.
I don't really have any gold for the year. Don't have any fan-ish plants for the year.
I'm not really a sort of like resolutions and gold for the year kind of person.
So...
Maybe. Let's see.
Let's see how 2021 goes. 2021, I am not looking forward to the first three months of 2021, but at the end of the first three months of 2021, we have an Eastercon!
Yay!
Easter time! Looking forward to Eastercon. How's that for a segue then, Sean?
I mean, great segue. I think all the segue is a great...
The segue is a bet if we don't keep saying, "Isn't that a great segue every time we do a great one?"
Which is just going to call attention to every time we do a crap segue.
Which is quite often.
OK, so, Eastercon. For those who were paying attention when we started our podcast, Eastercon is a national convention run in the United Kingdom every year, usually at Easter.
And there was a bid session at Easter last year, which elected the 2021 Eastercon, which is called Confusion.
And at the time, Confusion did not have planned to go online, but then COVID continued to happen over the course of 2020, and now Eastercon have launched their Discord this week.
So who put the Discord together?
So I had, prior to punctuation, I volunteered to put together an Eastercon Discord, and I kind of wanted to go in one direction, and the committee, entirely reasonably, the committee, slightly, slightly,
disagree with me about where is she go. So I said, "Well, for enough, I've set it up."
But then I will let you enlist it, and I will step down and do punctuation.
And I think they kind of continue to tinker with it, and continue to make it what they wanted it to be, and now it is up.
And you can go and join, and we will put a link to it in the show notes.
But yes, and...
I don't think it's quite as clear as it may be ought to be, but it currently has quite a small area that is accessible to everyone, and then a rather larger area that is accessible to the members of Confusion.
And I think the other thing we should definitely make sure we haven't shown it is how you could go and buy your virtual membership of Confusion.
If you haven't done already, as soon as they had out virtual memberships, I joined, because obviously I want to be a member of the EastCon, but also because I had not previously joined, because I've been very sure for quite a long time that I was not going to want to go to a physical convention at Easter.
Yeah, so...
I joined as soon as they announced...
So I can't remember when this happened, but there was a point at which they did the refunds from the 2020 EastCon, and they opened membership sales for 2021, and I got my refund from the 2020 EastCon, and I immediately spent it on joining 2021.
And the cost of an adult attending membership is £70, and the cost of an adult online membership is £50. Online membership rates were announced in October, and the plan is for the EastCon to either be hybrid or virtual.
There are reports from people such as John Bray that their rooms for the convention have been refunded, because the hotel has told them that they won't be open, so it looks rather like clearly the EastCon will be virtual, but as far as we understand, the hotel has not yet informed EastCon that it will not be open, and so there might be some more wrangling to do there.
This is all coming from Facebook comments and our reception of Scuttlebutt, so please do listen and take all of this with the requisite large pinch of salt.
I had a memory of EastCon having announced that it was going to go hybrid or possibly virtual. Yes, but in that announcement, which I went back and read the other day, it said we are planning for a virtual or possibly hybrid convention.
So, I am slightly wondering if they have edited that or if it is my memory that is at fault, but they had a lot of talking about the exciting things they were thinking of doing with hybridization.
I think it always said hybrid or virtual.
It definitely says virtual or possibly hybrid, and they are saying we have always planned for a virtual convention.
Liz, have you bought an EastCon adult online membership?
I have not done so yet.
Do you think you might?
I probably will. I just sort of want to know a bit more about what they are planning.
They have asked for volunteers, including volunteers for program items, and they are asking us to tell us what we would like.
I think the root of the problem is that I had a membership for 2020, which I was thinking about selling in February when it was clear that I was not actually going to make it to EastCon.
And then clearly I should have flogged it slightly, then I did.
Because obviously then the convention was cancelled due to COVID.
And I decided not to get a refund because I felt I was happy for it to go towards the costs of future EastCons.
And in times I didn't ask for a refund, partly because they didn't read the email they sent me in enough detail to note that they said they didn't need the money to cover their costs, because I was thinking they probably had some costs that still had to be paid due to the last minute cancellation.
And I thought that would help them with that. I probably should have read it because it said they didn't really need it, and it was going to sort of future EastCon pass-alongs.
But I think it has sort of tainted my view of buying a membership for the latest one, because I'm like, well, last time I bought a membership and then I couldn't go and I just didn't do anything about it and I didn't get a refund.
And so I essentially gifted a bunch of money to future EastCons, which is fine, but it means I'm now in the kind of like, oh, if you want my 50 quid, what am I actually getting for that 50 quid and can I have a little bit more detail on it?
Because if they have some great plans, then that's fine, but if what they plan to run is a sort of, you know, Zoom Discord, Streamyard-based convention.
Well, I've got some experience now of doing that, and I know it really doesn't cost a lot of money.
And I'm sure you need more Zoom licenses and bigger Zoom licenses and probably some more tech, but if we can do it for what was basically about two pounds a person,
then I would like to know kind of what is in the planning that will cost 50 pounds a person.
Yeah, I mean, I've said I know how to spend 50 pounds a person on a virtual event.
I'm just not sure it quite represents good value for money for people yet.
I also need to know that what they're planning for that 50 quid will work for me, because if what they mean is they're going to have lots of excellent evening program item extravaganza, which you could spend quite a lot of money on that.
That's nice, but I'd have to, you know, upend my own personal time zone in order to watch those, which I might not be willing to do.
And I think it also ties into my feeling a bit like the finances of EasterCon.
I don't really have any feeling right now about how much money there sort of is in a general EasterCon pass along slash crisis fund,
how much we've been putting into that, how much has been used by past EasterCons, and whether we're just, are we just sort of setting a price because it's similar to what past EasterCons have done,
but we're now at the point where, say, if we're up to a regular thousand person convention, we could make it a little bit cheaper or offer more targeted discounts, all things like that.
So what I think I'm saying is, yeah, I'm probably going to join EasterCon. I'm just being excited, I'm going to be about it.
I think Boscone has got a page on its website, which we will put a link in the show notes to, which says, why is Boscone costing $25?
Why is Boscone not free?
And they, I think, are very clear about what it is that you get for your $25 and why you might want to spend $25 rather than having the convention be free,
and I think it is a very good note, and I would like, and in fact, I asked EasterCon way back, maybe September, this September or October, to do this roughly for EasterCon, and I have not really seen them say,
because £50 is a lot more than $25 for one thing, and I think it's a lot easier to see what a convention might cost $25 than it is to see why it might cost £50,
and I have not yet had any reply to that, but as it was a Facebook comment, there's a sense in which I don't necessarily deserve a reply to it, so, you know, if you're involved in EasterCon and you're listening to this podcast then,
I think I am speaking for a lot of people who quite like to know roughly, not only great detail, but roughly what their £50 is paying for.
Is that fair?
I think that is fair, I don't know what the best way to call on EasterCon to do that is.
Facebook message, obviously.
I would also like to see that, I mean, because I do understand that there may well be costs that mean that they are kind of covering the costs they have incurred running this convention for the £50 they are charging,
in which case, absolutely fair enough, and they may be worried that some of those costs will be perceived by the fandom as kind of costs that should not be covered by their EasterCon membership,
so, for instance, if some of those costs are costs like we have incurred money that needs to be paid to the hotel, then maybe they're worried about saying, well, part of the reason we're charging this is because we need to pay off the hotel contract.
I don't know, obviously that's all inside Facebook, and none of us know, but I do think that
although I can see a way in which they might need to charge £50 for memberships, I think it is reasonable to say, right, but why are you charging that?
Because ultimately they are asking fans to become members at this price point, and if they don't make the case that it's worth that much money, they might not get that much money, and, you know, and most fans might decide that it is fine and put down their £50, but
I just think more transparency can't be a bad thing, and so, although I am sympathetic to these costs that they might need charge this much, and there might be things that I haven't thought of, you know, if that's the case, then tell me what they are, and then I'll be happy.
And I think it is probably a fair comment, but I don't know what the best way to kind of persuade them that that's the case is, and this is, I don't know, Alison, you'll know, and presumably as you will do too.
Do Easticons tend to publish their finances after the fact, or not really?
So, for Follicon, we asked Claire Breiley and Mark Plummer of Croydon to do our programme book, which they did extremely well, and as part of that, and not actually asked for by us, Claire, they went round and hung the treasurers of, I think, 11 previous Eastercons upside down by the ankles.
Until their accounts fell out and published, and I just think this is a great credit to the treasures and to the conventions and to Claire and Mark, especially, and published a load of accounts that had not previously been published, which is good for two reasons.
The first is that it does tie up that accountability and show where the money went, and it's not a really great detail, you can't actually look and say, well, they paid that about this guest cost £6,000, this Gus cost £29p, or anything like that, it's very high level.
The things that conventions, the headings that conventions choose to group accounts by are not always comparable, so some big expenditure chunks go into one heading rather than one account and a different heading and a different account, but they are very, very useful both to see what sorts of things we think are important and what sort of things money gets put into, but also the different choices that different Eastercons make,
and they're also useful for budgeting purposes, because it means that if you're thinking about bidding for an Eastercon, you can actually look at the budget and have some sense of where the money is going to come from, where it is going to go, and what sorts of choices you have around that.
It was a wonderful piece of work by Clara Mark, it just reinforced for me the importance of doing that of every Eastercon, actually getting to the point where it can publish up counts, there are reasons why it sometimes gets delayed for a few years, but it's a bit like trip reports really, it's extremely welcome when they do turn up.
So yes, Eastercons are in the practice, the reason, and the reason I'm kind of, and the Eastercons are not in the practice of publishing their budgets.
So the reason why I'm, so when I'm asking confusion to do a little bit of publishing its budget, it's a way of saying I feel we're in, we've moved into a different phase of Eastercons existence, and so therefore, although it would not be normal for us to look at your budgets,
we think it would be interesting and valuable for the community to have a conversation in the highest level terms, not in any sort of detail, about what your budget looks like.
I think actually I'm not even really asking for a budget, I think what I'm asking for is just a bit more detail, because I know what to expect from an in-person Eastercon,
and I think by this time before an in-person Eastercon, you'd be starting to leak a few exciting program ideas and tell people a few of what the big things are going to be that are coming up at your convention,
and I don't really have a feel kind of what this Eastercons committee are going for, because there are different flavors of online convention.
So I just want them to tell us a bit more, I mean I suspect basically they're very busy, and obviously it is a terrible year in which to be planning an Eastercon.
It has been a tricky year, and it's a tricky year to try and pivot to an entirely new mode of Eastercon going,
and I'm really just grumpy and I will join eventually, I just want to know a bit more about what's going to happen.
I think that's entirely reasonable, and I think I am hopeful that it will be good, but I am a little bit worried by the lack of detail,
and maybe that is just because they're communicating badly, or maybe it's a sign of something worse, but if it's a sign they're communicating badly,
then asking them to communicate more openly I think is a reasonable thing to do,
and hopefully all of the many members of the Eastercon committee who devoutly listen to Octa thought will write in and tell us,
or whatever, that would be good.
They have an email address for volunteers, which we will put in our show notes, or we'll put a link to their volunteering page,
and they're volunteering, as far as I can tell, if you are interested in being on the program or are interested in suggesting program ideas,
then that is also the email to write to for, I'd like to be on the program, or I'd like to run this thing for your program,
and I have basically written them an email to this address that essentially says,
"I will do anything, please get in touch. I particularly want to help with running Zoom parties, because you know that's the thing I do,
but obviously there's a load of other things you might want me to do, and I'd be very happy to help you,
and I will let you know at the next Octa thought whether they have got back to me,
but I would also suggest that my co-hosts might want to also do this,
and not necessarily say they'll do anything, but to say they will do the things that they would like to do,
or help with making the things they would like to see happen,
and I would also suggest that all of our listeners fill in that thing if they're interested in Eastercon,
as I suspect many, but not all of our listeners are.
Yeah. I shall say, Anna Grump, who has actually not volunteered for Eastercon,
so I should go and think about what I might want to do.
That was the 22nd episode of the Octa thought podcast, and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me, and it's goodbye from me.
[Music]
It's happened again. It was daylight in Liz's house literally ten minutes ago, and now it's very not.
No, no, because last time this was like a half an hour, I'd like...
[Laughter]
If only we knew, if only we knew how the sun worked Liz.
It's dark. End of question.
I spent two or three hours reading through this and discussing discussions of it,
and at the end I believe that it is a combination of atmospheric phenomena,
physical phenomena, and the way the brain works that causes it,
and it's very interesting, and...
I can't find one thing that it turns out to be more complicated than all that.
Oh yeah, it's always... anything is always a mixture of things that happen to add up in the same way.
It's like whether or not you put milk in your coffee,
like how quickly does your coffee cool, and it says that there's like four different processes,
but they all lean the same way to combine into a notable process.
It turns out if you leave your coffee lying around for three quarters of the hour,
because you're reading interesting articles about the way the sun goes down,
your coffee is stone cold, no matter how you put your milk in.
I will also say...
And your coffee is cool slower if you rinse your mug out with boiling water before making coffee.
That makes sense.
I will also say, atmospheric processes are physical processes.
Yeah, but okay, so there was a set of things about...
No, I don't.
The way in which the earth is moving, I know we had half an hour on this,
you cut and tuck it out of the podcast.
You meant atmospheric processes and orbital processes.
I did, yeah.
But, yes, anyway, right.
I'm going to start podcasting from a cupboard so you can't see the sun.
Why love is? So I love two things about that,
which is firstly your dedication to preventing the ass and going off topic,
and secondly your dedication to not closing the curtain that covers your window,
because that would also work.
But it was day like, I would have done that.
If she'd like automated, the presses were curtain pulling, they were the curtains.
Yes, but then we would notice.
And we would get sidetracked by Liz Watt, um, fancy.
[laughter]
I'm so sorry, Liz.
We're terrible co-hosts.
Even with also with the curtain straw,
you'd still know it was day like outside.
It's quite sunny.
That's fair enough.
That's fair.
Anyway, onto the letters of comment.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod at Encompetech.com,
used under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.