that fair yeah although i did like your eyes and joke well but then alison sort of made a face so i
thought maybe i should not make it on the redo i'll make a face with lots of things and you still
say it jump well 100%
hello everyone and welcome to the very 126th episode of Octothorpe a podcast for science fiction
and science fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 16th of january 2025 i'm john coxin
i'm elison scott and i'm liz batty and alison and i haven't changed microphones it's just that we're
both ill i'm definitely getting better because if you because you live you live in the land of
gold and blakes everything is terrible i mean it will get warmer one day i think yes in my case
tomorrow where it will be 10 instead of minus one yeah they've been saying that for a little while
though so hopefully it will be warm tomorrow and everything and all the ice will melt and i will
start feeling better happy new year everyone yes happy new year and we have some letters of
comments uh jonathan kawi wrote in uh jonathan wrote a very long and eloquent lock about how
annoyed he was that glasgo didn't mail out souvenir books to supporting members and he points out
that the constitution and the matters of continuing effect mandate that this be done i'm gonna say
i'm gonna say a couple of things here firstly i apologize very much jonathan because i don't know
that you know this but as the long con three deputy division head for publications it was me who first
disobeyed the wussford's constitution by refusing to do a physical copy of progress report four and
therefore i may not be the sympathetic shoulder you hoped your words would find in this email uh
because i pretty much entirely sympathize with glasgo's perspective here i think there is a reason
glasgo did that and i think it's because most people probably think it's fine we do it and then do
we want to do mike scott and every time we say mike scott can we pronounce it great scott
in the style of doc brown it's mike scott doctor scott is the doctor no okay
asked and answered rocky horror reference sorry oh but i thought maybe he was a doctor and i just
did not know that mike has written rather pedantically and and as well as being known as doctor plottary
was also known as captain pedantic for a while so you know and this is why to say that maltham
stow is not remotely in central under which i think is what i said really um and that it is
quicker to get to central London from excel than it is from maltham stow because there's now an
Elizabeth line station on the excel uh erstec cell which i didn't know he then says that the journey
time on the dlr from custom has to tower gateway was basically the same as um the victoria line for
both of social central to uster which might be true but on the other hand used as much
closer to the central London tower gateway is by almost any standard but never mind and he does
point out that he has some credentials in this area because he maintains it spent many years
maintaining a database of all the locations in which people might want to search for houses
and who experimented with having public transport journey times as a search criterion
but did not succeed in that you probably could do it now because the public transport journey
times are much more a matter of record than they used to be anyway thank you michael i would like
to say that this was an unsuccessful reference to a lot who received from claire bryley of croydon
in episode 15 in which she said and i quote i haven't been to allyson's not very big house only the
five bedroom one in inner london now this opens up the question is the word inner an exact synonym
for the words central and i guess not no one of the bits i've just cut out of it said
walthamstone not even in a london which is much bigger than central london i think claire bryley
mike scott might have to have a panel item discussing the exact nature of london's geography
well i mean croydon smiles out i think we could all agree on that none none of this is none of this
is disproving the notion that fandom may be you know overly centered on london is fandom more or
less centered on london that is uk fandom more or less centered on london the uk population
discuss oh no i'm not saying it's not a bad thing for the whole uk yeah i agree with liz i mean i
was thinking this came up a while ago it years ago i'm sure this came up in the context of the bsf a
running like a pub meeting in london and not anywhere else and i think there were efforts to run pub
meets elsewhere which may still be ongoing whereas john is actively contributing to the decentralization
of uk fandom by having his own pub meet in your castle with like gregs and parmos yeah i had a
parmow to ring in the new year liz it was great thank you for it again mike we also heard from
well not quite from our regular correspondent chris vajay arsea but from our
infrequent correspondent bella who centers a waffle of comment which we will put in the show notes
it's a waffle in the shape of an octop it is very much appreciated i'm very excited by this
and hashtag waffle thought yes i thought this might be our first food of comment but then i
realized that was the whole weetabix thing so probably not yes given alice and sent me a
weetabix globe yes yeah we still got the weetabix is still fine yeah i've not had to break the
classroom urgency yet well i thought the humidity might get to it but it is actually fine yeah i
thought the mice might get to mind but it does indeed still seem to be fine lizards seem uninterested
in weetabix and can you blame them silly lizards niel ottenstein wrote in to ask how my science
conference went post-covid much the same as it did pre-covid it is not much different yeah
basically i did not get ill but i did use lizards magic spray every day so that probably helped
so we also got some discussion on facebook on the post-burda last episode i'm not gonna read
it all you can go and have a look what we did here from tami coxin who is one of the people
behind the proposal for a 2027 european smofcon somewhere sunny along with i think some of the
european con runners so if anyone's picky interested in helping with that you can contact tami
there's also some discussion of the virtual business meeting and the fact that last year's
business meeting set up a committee to look at the rules by how we run the business meeting
and it is in a way a little bit weird that we have a committee running on that
while at the same time this current year's world conner just like yeah we're going to do
in a different way but i think the problem is that because the cycle for committees is so long
you know you have a committee they will hopefully report back next year but some of them
actually don't manage report that that year and report back another year after and then if
they're reporting back at the con you can't actually introduce any proposals based on that
until the next con usually like the cycle is too long i think and i can understand why people
like no we're going to actually have a go at changing things now the other thing is that if
your committees have not actually got themselves into action yet which is understandable because
they're going to be a pause post gone when everyone's a bit tired and then you might think oh there's
no point starting it like in december let's kick it off with a new year the fact that the
business meetings are now starting in july means you have a shrunk window of time to actually get
anything done them's me thoughts i think that's all fair i agree with Liz yeah no that's all
sounded perfectly sensible to me on the subject of online business meetings far out notes that
they don't know whether high-level con runners actively want an online business meeting which
something we discussed last time but they do note that a lot of people who attend the business
meeting have told con runners basically well if you care you come to the business meeting and you
don't so clearly you don't and i think that's the other thing which is if you have been in a situation
where you've been told you don't you know the reason you don't come to the business meeting is
simply that you don't care enough you are quite annoyed at the way the business meeting is constituted
and you do want to change it and i think that is a example of con sort of actions having consequences
like you don't get to gatekeep and then obviously gatekeep and then be annoyed when the people you're
keeping the gate from start mounting at your gate because that will happen and typically speaking
if you're the one behind the gatekeeping it shut you are not on the right side of that debate like
there's very few examples i can think of where the gatekeepers were lauded years later as being on
the right side of things so that is i think also food for thought we got any more bits to add to
your gate metaphor because it's stacking up it's good there's a stacking gate it's more like a
style at this point in terms of gatekeeping christmas movies uh we heard from multiple
commentators that diehard is not a christmas movie we didn't say it was a christmas movie
uh but also that the muppet christmas carol is very good i watched it with the song in it makes way
wasn't for the song in i don't understand how how anyone could watch it without the song in i have
very strong opinions very quickly we watched it without the sogging because we had not paid
close enough attention and then we went back and watched the song and went oh that makes quite a
lot more sense but of course we knew the story um i i thought it was okay because the thing about
it is that it's a christmas movie and i clearly don't like them very much and also it's dickens and
i really don't like dickens and then i went oh but i like that david copperfield and that was the one
that was scripted by amanda in an inuchu which is why i liked it probably because normally i
really don't like dickens apart from that i do like muppets a whole lot so the muppet bits are
quite good but it's never going to be a kind of classic for us we all kind of got to the end and
went eh meh so i just wanted to do a dissenting a dissenting opinion on that we did see wallace
and crobert and we thought that was pretty good i liked muppet christmas carol a great deal i think
probably yes you are right if you know the story the um the the lack of the song probably doesn't like
it's not as important as it might be but no i really liked it i thought it was good i thought
michael canes was very good and then we heard from raj on mr don who says he'll definitely say hello
at reconnective he can find us we'll be on the alt-to-thawp paddle raj and we'll probably also be at the
bar but there will be at least one place we will be very easy to spot uh and then he also says cons
out with glasco the thing is he's a very lazy person and it's so much easier he can just stay at
home and still attend the con which is fair but does beg the question are you commuting
glasco to Belfast every day raj right in i suspect the answer is no but it amused me to think that he
might be we heard from andres devore who wrote in say it was interesting to hear details about
east con budgets and con costs glad you found it interesting andres and also said they might
seriously consider some international cons with virtual memberships and ask us to keep pushing
the idea and i'm sure we will continue to talk about virtual memberships we also heard from
june young thank you for the festive greetings june uh june does ask did jon ever do a panel at
dublin con in 2019 if he did i think i spoke to him afterwards a panel about tv shows failed on
the ending jon was that you could well have been it is the sort of panel i probably would have
said i would be quite good on do you remember someone having very negative opinions about
balsar glad to cuz ending because if so that could have been me the other thing is if you
remember someone who was being very contrary about the ending of game of thrones that could
also have been me i mean when we say contrary do you mean that you liked the ending of game of thrones
i yeah i don't really see how it could have ended any differently i think they rushed it because
they were told to rush it but i think it was clearly the ending that um george alway's intended to
write yeah i can sort of see that having a few extra episodes in there would have probably been
better for the show but dennaris is clearly set up to be terrible the whole way through and the
fact that emilia clark is very charismatic i don't think undercuts that and so i was a bit
surprised when everyone was very shocked that she turned out to be terrible which i know is
something if you're in a more also writes in her management book on game of thrones which i
highly recommend everyone to go read beer and i think part of the reason george alway's in is
ground to even more of a stop might be that that was exactly where he was heading and now he knows
everyone hates it so i don't know but that's my contrary opinion so june if you remember someone
with that contrary opinion that might have been me we heard from consanza on discord because you
couldn't find the facebook post which is fair it's hard to find anything on facebook um saying that
to participate in seattle's virtual business meeting you need an attending membership or a
virtual attending membership so you cannot participate if you are a supporting member i guess we don't
call them supporting memberships anymore do we call them wispless memberships sorry so basically
you now buy a wisvers membership which does not enable you to take part in the business of wisless
we call the wispless members which is it's an odd one i think i would rather you didn't have to
but i can sort of see the logic it would be really hard to gate just the business meeting yeah i
can see it's also i think it'd be interesting to see does anyone can't do people buy virtual
memberships just to attend the business meeting i might i don't think i have a full membership for
seattle so i should not think i have any membership for seattle okay rambling now but i should probably
buy a membership for seattle so don't i there is some worry about like okay if everyone come to
the business meeting then the business meeting is very susceptible to bad actors and you keep the
cost a little bit higher and that keeps them out but it is still keeping up people who can't afford
to do the extra thirty five dollars yeah it's this is the sort of very difficult conversation i think
we sort of got into this a little bit last time you do want to keep enough of a gate that you
discourage the bad actors and it's not clear how you do that the price of supporting membership is
artificially constrained for the worldcon but my general view is that the supporting membership
and the membership that gets you all the virtual should be the same because i think it solves a lot
of those problems but then it would also be more in this case so we have a we have a taf race
which is open and you can vote now and we will put the link in the show notes there are three
candidates who are z graves mikleiko lasky and jan vanich jr junior and they all have their
platforms online and you can go and vote for them so i think it's quite great to have a
taf race with three candidates that's quite good we do not yet have a guff race um for reasons but
hopefully that's becoming along quite soon and um in other news the Canadian unity fan fund has
given up so this is a fan fund that exists to send Canadians to other Canadian
conventions and they can't find anyone to run and they're having trouble getting conventions to host
um so the the administrator has announced that he thinks it might be time to give up the ghost
which i think is a shame because i always liked the fan funds that sought to increase the
conversation between people in like a country i always thought that was a really good idea and
so i think it's a bit of a shame that that has uh that that has wrapped up um or that it looks like
it might wrap up i mean so first i didn't know this fan fund existed it sounds quite fun when you
are a giant country with not that many people in i do think sometimes the best way to get people
to step up to run things is to say we're gonna fold and then the people who are like oh really do
i want it to fold might appear it's not always means you're going to keep going for a long time but
it could be a good way to didn't work for the dovers no it doesn't always work but it is a way to get
people to think about like okay seriously we do need to step up and do something otherwise this
is going to fold do i want to do this work more than i want the whole thing to fold there's not
like an inter-us one is that they're like nothing that sends people like from the east coast to the
west coast or vice versa no there really should be a fan fund called nath
the north american fan fund but and yet there is not i always thought i think the european fan funds
a very good idea and i would like to see i would i thought i think that is very good and i hope that
that does not go the same way as cuff um and i think there's also you know i i do i think this is
a sort of thing that's very very good and i think it would be nice to see cuff kind of come out of the
ashes reborn but um i don't know whether that will happen don't know enough about the canadian
scene really canadians right in yes
a nice thing happened this week which is an esteemed member of north american universities
world leading solar and space physics research group has been recognized by the royal astronomical
society and received the fan award uh and that esteemed member of uh north american university is
dr john coxant so well done john thanks liz and we'll put a link to the press release and i guess
the fowler award is an award for early career scientists in geophysics is that right john
that is correct we're going to put a link to press release so that i don't have to explain
what john's day job is but we know he's professor of aurora science at north umbria
space stuff dunder space stuff and it's very cool i'm not a professor i'm only a doctor professor
the boy john coxant nobel prize winner ove
i do do space stuff though that bit was right i'm very careful about this because i know i think
at least oxford have like rules about one who is ladcon's health professor and it's definitely not
people are not better i know it's a joke but that is probably next for john then sir john
so john cpe no i don't think i mean i don't think i mean right next for john is finishing his fellowship
and becoming a proper lecturer let's not skip all of the intervening stages
it's true the next thing john is that you age out of early career things and a force to consider
yourself mid-career yeah i mean yes that is true in other news about cool things john and i are doing
i'm going to segue here hey that's a nice segue so this episode we are going to talk about things
we are nominating for the hughos in 2025 and the reason we are doing this staggering the early
is that john and i have become members of the wis
site selection but i am going to cease to talk about the bob the podcast for a little while
yeah it's going to be interesting because what are we going to talk about all through
like the summer leading up to the atl if it's not hughos it's going to be difficult i'm going to
have to think about other stuff beaches parties weather whether or not it's dark where lizz is
not yet so thanks as usual to the big 2025 hughos spreadsheet of doom
spreadsheet of doom run by the lady business crew which as usual has been collecting
potential nominees a pretty big set of them in most categories and also it means that other
people can look at them and help you decide eligibility and stuff like that so thank you again for them
because i'm going to be relying on that to make sure that things i nominate for 2025 are actually
you know things that came out in 2024 and not things that came out in 2022 and i didn't notice for
example so we're going to start with best novel i've read some novels a few guys read some novels
i'm not sure i've read in 2024 novels yes i have read some novels i have opinions there's
i'm ready for novels do you want to go first or shall i go first because you also have read
short-form stuff right lizz uh yes some but what lizz has done is she has made the mistake of writing
what she's going to say in the show notes so i can immediately snipe her and be like alien clay
by ogio trikovsky that's pretty good yes this is now making a face i've made the mistake of telling
john what i was going to say and now he's still a lip that's fine i've got other ones other books
all right shall we do one one one two one book from john and then one book from me and you can
have alien clay if you want i will yeah so i think we can both talk about alien clay alien clay is
really good is i've also read service model by adrien trikovsky which i would say is also very good
but i would say it is not as good as alien clay so i think i will probably nominate alien clay
and obviously adrien trikovsky does all also have house of open wounds is it that one i thought
that one was al because days have shattered thingies is this year isn't it so house of open wounds is
2023 in the uk but 2024 in the u.s is what i think it is there are actually a surprising number of
kind of edge cases this year of things which came out in the uk a year before they came out in the
u.s and so i might end up nominating them if i have gaps in my uh nomination ballot yes so the
tyrant philosophers is eligible for best series yes john you are jumping ahead
which is fine but i was going to say we do have the possibility to do something very funny
which is that in 2023 asian trikovsky was nominated for children of time in 2024 adrien
trikovsky was nominated for the final architecture and in 2025 we could nominate adrien trikovsky
for the time philosophers meaning we'll have three successive series in best series in three
successive years which is kind of wild let's make it happen people but i like all those series so
yeah for novel i have not yet read house of open wounds but i will be reading it with an i to
nominating it because i really liked city of last chances and i suspect i will love house of open
wounds and i suspect it is the one that will be nominated more than days of shattered faith but
i will also be nominating the tyrant philosophers for best series as long as he doesn't screw up the
second and third novels which again i suspect he will not and alien clay i have read and is brilliant
and will be going on my ballot and service model is very very good but given i'm already looking
down the barrel of two or three trikovsky knobs i might not make it three or four i have read i
have read house of open wounds and i liked alien clay more i did like house open wounds but i preferred
city of last chances is alien clay are standalone by any chance it is yeah yeah i have
a alien clay ready to read so i'm quite excited you can visit like a loose sequel could occur at
some point in that universe but i think it stands alone satisfyingly yeah and like children of ruin
is not a direct sequel to children of time it's in the same universe and it's playing with similar
themes but like i don't really think you have to have read read time to read ruin and i don't think
ruins existence spoils time as a standalone so i think that's the other thing trikovsky is very
good at i mean john coxin in quite likes adrien tricovsky chocker news at 10 yeah we know what this
is podcast likes so are you guys thinking of nominating anything that's not by adrien tricovsky
this year yes i'm going to nominate the tainted cup by robert jackson bennett because as we well
know i love robert jackson bennett he's very good though i have heard great things about this
now but that's tricky right because i might have heard the great things from liz liz do you want to
tell me great things about this book i think i did it as a pick didn't i so you could just go back
and listen to the episode yes so this is the locked room mystery yes which is why i'm so excited
about reading it it was this is pick in episode one two three listeners so you might actually
remember it but if you don't you can go back and listen to it but i was um very much excited to
read it the tainted cup is currently 99p on high eve dot code at uk which might mean it's 99p on
other e-book vendors so if you are interested in it go look it up now listeners and purchase it for
cheeps in terms of things that i'm nominating that i may not have already banged down about on the
podcast at length i have just finished the ministry of time by calian bradley which will probably be
on there john's reddit i don't think we have discussed it on the pod it's essentially a novel
in which a very limited amount of time travel exists and the narrator ends up being the bridge
the sort of link to our world for time travelers who have a time travel has been snatched from
his the past because they would have died and that is thought to leave least damage on the timeline
so basically she ends up being the kind of 21st century guide to um graham gore from uh the
franklin's lost expedition i really liked it like there's there are different ways you can go but i
think it manages to do quite a lot of sort of light fun stuff about the sort of fish out of water
21st century person who the housemate of a victorian sailor plucked out the ice but it manages that
very well with the kind of seriousness that is also in the in the premise i think and that's what
i liked about it it feels very british it's thinking a lot about empire and colonialism which is
obviously you know there's a lot of that in britains history but also feels quite universal
some of it is just funny in it feels very set in london it's feels kind of set in sort of british
bureaucracy and i think it kind of very satisfyingly takes that fun comedy romance aspects but then
ties them into the the deeper story which is a lot more interesting and a lot more serious and
thinking but i do like the you kind of 15 pages in and she's already trying to stop graham gore from
breaking the toilet and chain smoking everywhere i liked it a lot to echo i think everything liz
said i think it has interesting things to say about gender and ethnicity which i think ties
into its opinions on colonialism and empire but i also thought the characters were extremely
well drawn and i liked them very much and yeah i just i really liked it it may well be on my ballot
it is one of the ones i have very much enjoyed this year so i i would echo liz to go on to
another one i enjoyed from this year i'm going to pick the life impossible by matt hake i think i
might be this i would describe as magical realism but the magic is science fiction in that it feels
very much like other books in the literary tradition that i've read that i kind of in the magical realism
vein but it's explicitly science fictional rather than fantasy i think and it's set on the island of
i beetha and it has things to say about parenthood and relationships and what it is to belong and what
it is to reject belonging yeah i really enjoyed it i thought it was very good it made me cry in an
airport i i would highly recommend people read that i think it was lovely and i've also heard
not a huco recommendation but i've not read the midnight library but i've also heard very very good
things about that and just a pick up to play somewhere else has any other review read any matt hake?
no i've i've heard people saying good things about matt hake and i'm trying to remember
what else they've written yeah i will do one more recommendation i've actually not quite decided
on everything i'm going to nominate especially because in ascension and cochokia jazz which came
out in the uk in 2023 or 2024 in the u.s and therefore eligible again Alice is making a
face because i said in ascension i think literally that that's fine you don't appreciate uh mop
at christmas carol so fine we're gonna have to differ hated it hated it i liked in ascension
more than Alice and did i i i can't tell you how many reviews i've read of it which say that one
of the horiest plots of the history of satsalts fiction was profound it's not it's rubbish anyway
on so i was gonna uh just briefly say i might nominate the siege of burning grass by premy mohamad
which is essentially a novel about war and pacifism and how you can end conflict by pacifism
and i don't think it quite manages an ending but i did think it was very interesting
Alice and there are any books you liked i don't think i've read any 24 books i'm
gonna read the ones you tell me to before i get rid of lomelating maybe i've got two more i'd
liked three more i'd like to mention if that's okay Liz no obviously yes John keep going
i read jumpknots by how jingfang um and i really liked it it is it's a chinese novel in translation
by kenlu so if you don't get on with kenlu's translations then um this will not be the book
that changes your mind i don't think and it has a number of hallmarks of chinese sf for instance
the plot primarily revolves around a love triangle with one woman trying to decide between two men
and it all feels just a little bit old-fashioned from a western lens having said that i thought
it had some wonderful ideas it is a book that was written in china in 2010 so like some of those i
think old-fashioned-nesses are probably just because it is 15 years old in the original text
and also it's a reaction like an explicit reaction to the three body problem um so i would commend
it to anyone interested in in in that um so yeah i enjoyed it greatly the other two i would commend
our absolution by jeff fandamir which was brilliant i talked to neel harrison about this in the pub
and he said the only thing i know about it is that the end bits weird and i asked andi he said
andi's read it and he liked it so i said andi you've read absolution he went yeah what did you think
at the end bit and i was like it was weird and near when you see and uh and yeah but i would recommend
absolution if you liked annihilation or if you haven't read annihilation i would i would read absolution
and the other one i really liked is uh we are all ghosts in the forest by laren wilson which i
thought was powerful and bleak and anger making and hopeful in sort of different ways in different
measures and i think might end up on my ballot and i will also say i've seen people mention the book
of love by kelly link i i just thought it was quite long and plody so like if you're seeing other people
recommend that listeners i i would take those recommendations with a grain of salt but um
liz what did you think of the book of love uh it's a bit long and bloody yeah
good reads at the end of the year in my reading challenge sum up said the longest book you read
this year was the book of love and i was like i know it's i really wanted to like it and it had
some really great bits and it just needed an area to rank 200 pages out hmm i think i was just
gonna say that i have not yet read ricks fall by vajor chanda sekara and i did like the saint of
right doors i haven't read that yet because it's not out in the uk or we are in the uk in 2025 but i am
expecting that maybe to make it on the ballot it's out in the u.s yes there's also um i was
it called i asked a friend to get it for me uh the sentiments by garten batia yes we should recommend
that because everyone who's read it says it's great and there is like one indian bookshop who
will ship to europe mmm yes they mean this is not our it's obviously not a list of like the
absolute best year this is things we happen to have read which we think are the best year and there
are gaps this is very much not a slate guys yeah we're discussing books we've read and liked and
books we've heard other people who we think might be worth listening to read and like and we're like
here are some ideas for places you could start but if you have already started and you have opinions
please write in and tell us them because us conveying your opinions to the podcast doesn't count as
us having opinions and is therefore a loophole i think that's fair isn't it don't you'll have
to check with your division head nicholas if that's not okay writing i just can mention uh the
blog mr philips library who does an annual sort of prediction of what will be on the hugo shortlist
does have a set of six current front runners of which uh the calian bedley and the jackson
bennett are both in there along with service model by adrien tricoski and novels by tikin
fissure kaffronard and james s a quarry which seems like a reasonable shortlist and quite a
possible shortlist so there you go yeah i can see that i'm currently reading the book of elswear
by kyarderibs and china maville um but the james s a quarry book is on the pile i think it's the
next one or the one after yeah all right that was novel yeah best novella i would just say that over
christmas i bought some stuff from the neon hemlock e-book shop because they had an end of
your sale and i bought two that everyone had recommended which were um north continent ribbon
by ershla witcher and a morning coat by alex jeffers both of which i liked a lot
north country ribbon is actually a kind of set of it's sort of linked short stories but it's
published as a novella um and so that's where i'm going to nominate it it's just linked short
linked short stories of another world which i liked a lot and a morning coat is well there is a
titular morning coat in it it is about a costumer who is mourning his father and it's all about kind
of the process of mourning in this fancy world and i also really enjoyed that so those are two i
have read so far that i liked nice very quickly i also had a couple of nominations for best short
story one of them is grott marta by tomah's ha i found this on a recommendation list it's a nightmare
magazine which i wouldn't normally read because it's a bit too horror for me but actually this is
again a kind of story of colonial world and mysterious deaths and yeah kind of about how the
planet is linked to them anyway it is i read it a while ago but it has stuck with me so that will
probably be on there and my other recommendation is actually flash fiction from light speed and
it's called five years of planetatris by rachel k jones it is very short it's under a thousand words
but again that is one way the images and the payoff of really like stuck in my mind since i read
so i think it is worth a look and that is all my short fiction recommendations i have not read any
short fiction but i have read some best-related work now i haven't read an entire best-related work
but i am going to commend to the listener track changes selected reviews by abigail nussbaum
which is eligible and which is very good also i'm currently typesetting the next
brianine books book and i now know what the one after that will be and ho ho there's some good and
exciting things coming up in the best-related work category guys i'm i'm just delighted that
brianine books is going from strengths and strengths and publishing lots of books i think it's a great
thing and we're getting you know in in years in future years people will look on this as a really
good series of science fiction criticism john has once again stolen my nomination but i'm not
really surprised there i did typeset it you did yeah does that mean you get to nominate yeah fine okay
i will i'll mention that there's a book i am halfway through and if i continue liking it i will
nominate it it's a much more serious and academic book than i would usually really best-related
work but i saw something about it on blue sky i thought i would give it go it's called speculative
whiteness science fiction the alt-right by jordan s carol and it's kind of an academic work showing
and talking about how the alt-right views science fiction um to advance their agenda and so far it's
pretty interesting i mean apismet is also uh sparking off because there was a book called
speculative blackness the future of race in science fiction a few years ago and it's from the same
press so apism it's kind of also sparking off that uh which is not huio eligible but also looks very
interesting i don't know whether interactives go here or in best game i i really really enjoy
bridge command which i did this year i saw some a sorry tell somebody's list of games of the year
a podcast i listened to somebody had it on their list of games of the year and i was like oh yeah
no i suppose it is interactive so maybe it's an interactive it's not going to go on my best games
list for reasons i think it's a game yeah probably is it's complicated yes it's a repeatable
interactive experience right which i think qualifies it yes i mean they're all different but i don't
think they're any more all different than you know when you play a game where there's a lot of
different ways set up the scenario i think it's it's as different as that is so yes no it's probably a
game it's a roguelike discuss it's absolutely absolutely not a sodding roguelike
well this this uh if anyone has strong opinions on roguelikes or interactive theater please write in
because i think this might be a fanzine article brewing i'm going to talk about best series so we've
already mentioned the tyrant philosophers but i'd like to commend two other series to the attention
of our listenership southern reach by jeff fandamere is eligible because absolution renders it so
and i think it is a good series that i would recommend and the horace heresy which is a series i would
not recommend anyone read or interact with because i think it's a bit pants but it is also a 64 book
series chronicling the history of one of britain science fiction universes wahama four thousand is
something that's very special to a lot of fans hearts especially in the uk and so it is eligible
this is the last year it will be eligible it is finished it is 64 books long and i would argue
it's not very good but but worth mentioning yes i will say i've only read the first two books
it got better off to books 26 and you should really work through it till then any graphic stories no
not yet the other one is warp your own way which is the star trek lower decks uh graphic novel by
ryan north yeah haven't haven't done it yet which is apparently amazing and is on my radar but i
have not yet read but abigail nussbaum's review at strange horizons is apparently a work of extreme
genius so i will link that in the show notes right so about halfway through the year i resolved to go
and see a movie every week and i did not quite manage that but the result is i have seen a dozen
genre movies from 2020 or approximately which is sub-glider record for me um and i found it quite
easy to pick my top five which will probably not be the top five on the hugo um ballot for all
sorts of reasons i think the one that's most likely to get on there is the substance and the one that
is second most likely to get there is on it is wollison grommet vengeance post foul but i think
it's chances of doing so on nill and then the third my third fourth and fifth are all of us strangers
which the guardians said was the movie of the year and wasn't really the movie of the year and it's
probably my least favorite of these five but there we go um times stalker which nobody except for me
as ever seen so that's not going to get on the ballot and miles ass which might not quite be
science fiction it's got some science fictional elements um but it's certainly genre enough the
hugo ballot which is quite inclusive in that thing and and the fields i'm seeing this year that are
not in my top five are wicked beetle juice beetle juice due to gladiator to megalopolis and inside
out to and i would have thought most of those have a better chance of getting on the ballot
than any of my top picks except for the substance yes i will echo allison saying the substance and
i think that is all going to be on my ballot the other ones on my ballot are probably going to be
fieriosa i saw the tv glow and then the other ones i've seen that i might consider nominating are
late night with the devil which i did quite like a quite place day one which i also did quite like
and when i haven't seen but i want to watch before the nomination deadline is the wild robot which i
heard a lot of good things about but did not manage to get to before it came out of the cinemas i want
to pick up most of those certainly the wild robot um people liked a lot but i didn't go to sit in
the cinema deliberately because i thought it would make me feel a bit sick all the way through
and i would rather watch that at home it's been like christmas movies right it's gonna it's going
to be far too sentimental for me shall we do short form yeah i have a lot to say on the looking
through the spreadsheet um for short form the ones that i've seen that i don't see represented here
like the show i've been watching is sunny which is on apple tv plus and is science fiction and is
not on the spreadsheet and then there are some others which like i don't know there's one from the
acolyte which you know might be good there's one from star trek various star treks which might
be good but yeah i i i think i i i'm clearly not well read in short form either of you no i will say
that i i do like to use the hugoards uh sheet to pixel fat for me but i don't think it's particularly
comprehensive this year no it's quite early i think i have seen less startlingly good television
in the last year than in previous years we're mostly watching the expanse but it's not like we're
having to stop because of marvelous incoming television shows i don't think there's been any
well i haven't i mean i haven't watched silo or fallout or the acolyte we do we did quite like
for like but the fact is we've watched half of it and then stopped so it's probably not quite as
compelling as i'd like it to be yeah it is you are coming up on like the probably the third anniversary
of watching the expanse it's more yeah indeed okay but i don't have a lot to say about short form but
i think the short form does not be grateful i just told this list is it i thought it was isn't
not they'll have mentioned a particular episode work there and i don't know oh no there too the end
in the beginning are the four episodes that they've recommended someone's put every single episode
of the three body problem except for episode six and i want to know what went wrong in episode six
like was episode six just real bad if anyone's watched episode six of three body problem please
write in because i'm fascinated i mean i have Liz what was wrong with it why is it the only
episode that doesn't deserve to be all the spreadsheet i don't know it's not like episode six is a
a special flashback event or anything like that it's just another episode shall we talk about best
interactive yeah why not do you want to go first john i'm not sure i've played any 2024 video games
i know star wars outlaws is eligible but it is on my shelf and i have not got to it yet but what i
have done is played some board games and i will enthusiastically recommend a couple of those
so the board game arcs by colverley published by leader games is very good and has been making
waves in the tabletop space so imagine a cross between hearts and twilight imperium there's city
of six moons which i have not played but the rulebook is in an alien language that was invented
by the designer and to play the game you have to translate the rulebook first which like i think
just sounds absolutely fascinating and i think deserves a shout out but also i if this is a board
game i'm going to say i play so many rulebooks where the rulebook has been written in an alien
language and you have to invent it by the designer and you have to translate it first and then the
other one that i think is good is undaunted 2200 colisto which basically takes the
undaunted game and updates it to a science fiction universe where instead of playing axes versus
allies in world war two you're playing striking miners versus corporate security on the moon of
colisto which uh astute listeners will recognize is probably more my cup of tea setting wise
but those are probably the games that i will consider uh nominating oh and um i think mothership is
technically eligible because its first edition came out in 2024 and i will also nominate that
that's a role-playing game but i picked it uh in the episode before last episode 124 so uh if you're
interested in my thoughts on that you can go listen to that episode um played any of those yes so
for best game interactive work we have the rise of gold nidl as i mentioned on a previous episode
episode 124 listeners the thing is i bought a playstation 5 and i was played dragon age vale
guard i haven't started yet but unless it absolutely sucks which is possible by a way a swing from
high to low is quite a lot then it's going to be on my ballot on video games i have a top six i'm
not quite sure what i'm going to hound gonna narrow it down my top six are um animal well uh which
you know is a game about animals falling down the well as i picked it ufo 50 which is a collection of
50 games that prepared it to be retro games and i picked that um slice and dice 3.0 which is uh
great development of slice and dice and i picked slice and dice but maybe in its 2.6 format
caves of could which finally had its release after 15 years of development um at the end of the year
and then the last two one of which is going to get on the ballot one of which isn't art
blackro which is an incredibly um addictive kind of game that simulates is a deck building version
of video poker that probably picked that as well and you know anytime you've got a free weekend
with nothing in it i would recommend downloading blackro and seeing if you like it because it
you know might fill up your weekend and um Zelda echoes of wisdom which wouldn't be my pick this
episode okay i'll talk about it when we do pick while i do enjoy blackro i would not consider
it to be science fictional in any way i would like to be the party poo per and say that i just
don't like blackro that's fine i play it and then i put it down for bit and then i play a bit more
so it's obviously not like hooked me in yeah the other five clearly are well that's solved my
problem though because blackro is not science fiction there you go not really apart from the
planets it's got planets in it it's got cards which are planets so for those who want to know uh
allison picked animal well in 113 uh ufo 50 in 120 caves of cud in 124 and legend of Zelda echoes
of wisdom later this episode and and i think i picked slice of dice at some point and if i haven't
i must talk about it sometime nope it doesn't appear on the spreadsheet as far as i can tell slice of
dice is a deck building with dice um i'm excited about best poem uh and i imagine i'll nominate a
bunch of stuff by sandra bond and someone really ought to go through on the spreadsheet and put
some of her good poems on the spreadsheet because so far they are not there and that is a crying
shame and it might be me but it also might not be me so if you're listening and you've got a spare
weekend get on it fan categories i guess i will be nominating banana wings because banana wings is
great i'll be nominating the unofficial hugo book club and i'll be nominating nerds of a
i'll nerds of a feather accused i will not be nominating those of a feather i will be
donating orna fopter by lee Edmonds i will nominate some of those other things you mentioned but
probably also and siri review of books in fan writer i will nominate kamestros falapton because
i believe he he recused last year but i think the reason he did was because he was worried people
would give like give him too much kudos for the stuff he'd done in 2024 so i'll be nominating this
year for the things he did in 2024 which i thought were very good i'll be nominating
er sats culture because i think the stuff he does is also very very good i'll be nominating
rosanna pendelbury because i think her writing is very lovely and i would like to see her on the
ballot and probably others i'm not thinking of at the moment but yeah that's why i kind of start her
for ten i need to think about this in more detail probably some of the nerds of a feather
collective as individual fan writers even though they are not nominatable as a fanzine this time
and then for a fan artist i will be nominating is spany and sherry and allison scott i haven't
i haven't thought about the fan categories properly yet that's fair well you do have more time it's
just that don and i should probably stop endorsing things i do so you may just have to have kind of
drop in allison talks about the hugos elements and then we could have john and let's talk about
slight selection elements
our fan cast i thoroughly commend that everyone uh nominates hugo girl who are our transatlantic
podcast besties and they are great and i will remind people that they can nominate the series of
phallak fan history zooms which in 2024 did include one on the plucked cabal which yeah i was on
but otherwise lots of interesting stuff still happily once a month and they're very good i will
again plug going road by tansy garden as i have been several years and a meal of thorns which is
kind of the podcast of the ancillary review of books hosted by jake seller bookins and most
of their episodes are a deep dive into a single book but they also do a 2024 wrap up episode which
i quite liked do we have any astounding or load star picks oh yes so um monocle black goose
who wrote shaper dragon's breath uh will be in uh their second year of eligibility this year so
they're still eligible hey do you think you're any reason eligible
it's quite funny i but you'll know in a month
shall we do picks i feel i'm opinioned out quick picks liz quick picks pick quick
i'm gonna pick earthborn rangers which i think i did talk about this time last year because it
was eligible for huco it is a lovely little game it's basically in terms of theme in terms of setting
it's along a similar line to horizon zero dawn in that it's kind of set in a post post collapse
world where humanity is kind of more in tune with its surroundings and living with kind of ruins of
the previous civilization and that kind of thing uh in terms of gameplay it's quite similar to
arkamhar the card game but it does some tweaking here and there which is kind of interesting in
places and um and yeah it's just a very lovely game and it's curiously aimless um you can be
basically wander around for 30 days and then that's the end of your campaign and if you want to
devoutly ignore the plot and just do your own thing you can uh which is not the sort of thing you
can really do in arkam so yeah it's an interesting game and i am so far very much enjoy again um
so i'm going to pick it i'm looking forward to showing it to other people too don't know
as i'm trying to bully me into picking things even though i've just spent the like the last
hour and a half giving them my opinions on things so why don't i pick the fact that they remastered
horizon zero dawn so you can play on your playstation 5 now and it looks pretty hey oh it did look
quite pretty to begin with looks even pretty now i've been replaying it oh that's a great show
especially because um we've never picked horizon zero dawn on the podcast which is weird why didn't
i pick it because i think probably we had not started i don't even know if we'd started the
podcast but i don't think we'd started picking ah we put it in done picks i played i definitely
played her as a zero dawn after we started the podcast because i didn't get a ps4 until you
sold me your old one john which was after we started the podcast so true it came out in 2017
yeah but i definitely played it in 2020 because i bought a playstation in march 2020 having you know
seen them writing on the wall and then just hold up inside playing horizon zero dawn for like a month
it's i mean it's very good listeners like i think we've probably mentioned it before even though
we've not officially picked it but horizon zero dawn i i would commend to you as a thing that is
worth experiencing we also need to do the traditional mark alerts because allison is about to make it
three games from three go allison go am i yeah no i might be um i am picking zelva echoes of wisdom
which is the new two-d zelva which is kind of weird because it's actually a really 3d game
i mean i'm quite old and by my status this is quite a three-dimensional game but anyway
you play it's a zelta game and because of that you play as zelva which obviously you have done in
the previous 19 000 delta games um nope this is the first time you've got to play as zelva and
zelva has a bunch of skills which are not the same skills as link who is normally the
protagonist of the zelta games instead you make copies of the things that you find in the world
in particularly you make copies of the monsters you kill which is then sent into battle for you so
zelva is actually a necromancer in this game because she revives all the corpses of dead things
she's fought i'm sure that's that's proper law right in many ways this is because i didn't like
zelva breath of the world very much um see pug cost passing because it was kind of a an open world
sandboxy type thing where you could go all over the place and do everything but it didn't have
sorts of things i really like about zeldens which are dungeons and puzzles and a little
tight things that are gated so echoes of wisdom doesn't have the gating you can still pretty much
go anywhere as soon as you work out that the purpose of your old bed is to make stacking staircases
of old beds that allow you to go all over the map but otherwise it's quite like proper zelva it
has dungeons it has bosses it has lots of puzzles and it has lots of side quests and interactions
with the people in the world and it's it's a little bit simple maybe i deduced from this is
because i'm managing to defeat the bosses rather than bashing up against them multiple times before
go to the internet and finding out how i was supposed to have done it but i'm really loving it i'm
enjoying every minute of it it's a delight i got shamed into buying it by my offspring who was like
i didn't buy it because i wanted to play it i bought it because i wanted you to be happy with
zelda and zelda again and i do like playing as zelda i'm quite um i'm quite shallow and getting to
play as getting to play as the princess is pretty good i would like to say i would like to don my
mike scott cosplay and note that in fact the first time you were able to play zelda was zelda the
wand of gamelon which was for the phillips cdi in 1993 i have not played that game have you played
that game i have not played that game it has a reputation for being extremely poor it is not
canon it was not on a nintendo console and the gameplay was apparently atrocious but it does exist
and i never thought i'd get to mention it on the podcast but yeah i don't even know if there's a
cdi emulator for mak that means i can play it but i think there's a there's a video play through
on youtube which i am definitely good edge magazine noted that zelda fans consider the cdi
games tantamount to blasphemy and the other thing i want to say about zelda recos of wisdom is that
you can you can whip out the zelda's princess bed to have a kip in the middle of boss fights and
get your health back which is a new one on me brilliant i want to play it i am also not a big
fan of breath of the wild but i really liked the remaster of links awakening so i'm hoping that
echoes of wisdom is more like links awakening for me people say that echoes of wisdom is quite a
lot like links awakening which i have not played so yeah at least if you haven't played links awakening
is good that was the Octothorpe podcast and it's goodbye for me it's goodbye for me and it's goodbye
for me
hang on a sec while i load the Dublin program from the way back machine it must be possible to find
the Dublin program yeah yes is exactly what i am doing while you are chatting about the ending
of game of thrones oh there we go okay speakers oh no it's archived like the list of all the people
who are on program but not the links of what they're actually on you must have an email with it in
i have well i found the pocket program pdf on Dublin 2019 dot com ah so i was on 40 years of the
force fab or fail i was on fanzines now i was on dc tv versus film and i was on the comics galaxy of
star wars i was on latest results from asteroid missions and that was my list so if it was the dc
tv panel but i don't think i was one about on one about endings do you think we might be getting
into the weeds i want to know who the john doppelganger is okay i'm sorry this is gold i was wrong i'm
looking for the word television in this program guide and do you know it comes up quite a lot
but i can't find one about how shows ended do you think it's possible the panel went slightly
off topic from the stated subject during the panel could have been i also think it's possible
like june if you ever been to any other conventions because i have been to others right in
she's in new zealand though have you been to any new zealand i've never been to one in new zealand
but i i don't think there was a panel at dublin on how shows ended as far as i can tell from
looking through not a bad panel idea though if anyone wants me to be contrary about game of
thrones put that uh put that panel in your program uh on the subject of program i've got some hot
goss which is that um the belfast east god have recruited to do people to their committee
which is margarita smith and megg but donald have both uh been recruited i think megg's heading
up program i'm not sure what margarita's doing but you know very good stuff do we think it might have
been narrative in the dollar understanding contemporary tv which is about how contemporary tv shapes
like how tv structures work but i don't know if any of the people on that are doppelganger johns
yeah i was gonna say am i do you reckon abigay or nussbaum was the me the june met or
no i reckon it's adam whitehead could be adam whitehead anyway we may have gone off topic a bit too much
yes because we didn't get fun we didn't if there was a fun explanation for who the john doppelganger
was this would be fun but i don't think there was long i choose to believe that me and abigay
on usbound are very easily confused i mean i i i i confused you and abigay i only do have the
week till listeners liz liz liz looks less sure than we do on this matter i think it's fair to say
yeah i was trying to think of some funny way to tie this all together and i could not
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in competec.com
used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]