Hello everyone, welcome to Octo Thought Episode 1, a new podcast brought to you by Boredom
and Self-Isolation. I'm John Coxon, I'm a fan from the UK and I am joined by…
Hi, I'm Alison Scott, I'm also a fan from the UK.
Hello, I'm Liz, I'm also a fan from the UK but I currently live in Thailand.
We decided to do a podcast about fandom from a British perspective and we're going to
be talking about a few topics today in a kind of first episode stab at podcasting.
On the morning we record, it's the day after the EasterCon cancel, so EasterCon is the
British National Science Fiction Convention and concentric 2020 was to be held in Birmingham
this year but it has been cancelled as a result of COVID-19.
Now Alison was the fan guest of honour and I think all three of us are keen EasterCon
fans. How are you guys reacting to the cancellation?
Well, I am as they say gutted. I was obviously hugely looking forward to EasterCon anyway
because it was the EasterCon and it's my favourite convention of the whole year but
also because I was going to be fan guest and I was very much looking forward to that and
I had a lot of ideas about fun things we could do and so now I guess we're going to spend
our spring doing fun things indoors instead.
And I'm also, I think, worried because it makes me wonder, will we have an EasterCon next
year? Will we have more conventions? Is this it for the practice of travelling around the
world and meeting our friends?
So I've been assuming it was going to be cancelled for at least two or three weeks.
We were just waiting on the final legal coverage so it could be cancelled without the committee
being at a huge financial loss. I mean, I'm selfishly a little bit glad because I wasn't
going to make it this year and I really wanted to go in the year that Alison was fan guest
of honour because I think it would be hilarious and fun.
May never happen again.
I like hanging out with Alison because she's such a ray of sunshine. I'm assuming that
there will be future EasterCons although of course I have something of a vested interest
in global aviation that's still existing because I would at some point like to return
to the UK and not live the rest of my life in Thailand.
But that may be a deeper question than the cancellation of EasterCons, I feel.
I think Alison's point about whether this will presage the changing of how we do travel
and socialising is a really interesting question and probably would take longer than we have
on this podcast to properly answer.
But one of the things I have seen a lot in my professional capacity as someone who goes
to science conferences is people discussing whether or not conferences are still a viable
thing to do. But from my perspective, conventions are so much about the social aspect that I
kind of feel like after all this has gone away again, we're going to be even more keen
to go and see our friends because we're going to have missed out on that so long.
So do you do you two think that this will be a portent of the end of conventions or do
you think it's going to be a reason to continue conventioning with even more women vigor?
I think I should clarify that when I said may never happen again, I was referring to
my never being guest of honour again. But I promise to do everything like being guest
of honour, staying up too late and drinking in the bar and meeting everyone at the East
Con and all of that stuff anyway. I'm sure we're going to have more conventions. I'm
certain of it. I think that everyone will be well ready for a convention once we're all
vaccinated against this pandemic. And I'm sure there won't ever be another pandemic, isn't
that right Liz?
Oh yeah, absolutely. This is the only one. This is never going to happen again, viruses.
Don't jump over from animals on a regular basis or anything like that. Is this the point
where I inform our listeners that I work on tropical infectious diseases and so I might
have a slightly skewed view on global pandemics?
Yeah, I think of the three of us, you are the one that is most similar to an expert.
So that's probably relevant information. I think because we've been having conversations
about EasterCon up to the cancellation and I think most people assumed that it would
eventually be cancelled once the government announced that mass gatherings and pubs and
restaurants were no longer going to be allowed. It was just a question of when they would
do that and therefore when the cancellation would come. I think to go back to your point
earlier Liz, I was also expecting this to happen. I'm very relieved that the government
has come out and taken steps that allow pubs and restaurants and places like that to close
because I think until a couple of days ago that was something that was very difficult
for a small business like that to countenance and obviously the Hilton being a small business.
That's important.
Yes, yes, I'm going to be definitely with the Hilton on this one.
My sympathies rest with the committee and with the management of this hotel. It's clear
that the hotel didn't feel they were in a position to cancel for some time and I'm
not privileged to any particular information here. The committee did say, please don't
talk about what might happen as if you were a member of the committee. So I think we could
talk about what might happen with absolutely no knowledge whatsoever and making it completely
clear we have nothing to do with the committee and I would like to see us spend part of our
Easter weekend getting together, having some online discussion groups and Zoom chats and
Zoom parties which are just like room parties except with social distancing.
And with a pun, can't be a good pun. I think I agree with you, Alison. I would like to see
British fandom kind of rally around on Easter weekend and put some online stuff on whether
that's the convention committee or whether it's just a kind of a grassroots effort. I
don't know because I haven't had a free Easter weekend since 2006 and I've forgotten how
they work.
They're boring.
Yeah, exactly. I'm just, I'm not sure I'm going to appreciate a double bank holiday
weekend in a time when I've not been allowed out of the house for three weeks. So do you
think that will be something that gets organised as a grassroots thing or have you seen people
start to talk about that?
I've seen people on Twitter starting to discuss it but nothing concrete yet. I think it's
also feeling that maybe we need to give the committee a few days to kind of process that
yes, the convention is actually cancelled. All their effort is not going to result in
an event and to decide whether they feel like they can redirect that into trying to do something
online involving some of what they had planned for the actual event or whether they'd rather
sort of hand it over to fandom and say, "Sorry, we cannot do anything in person this weekend
but we give you our blessing to organise your own social gatherings online."
I have one more thought about EasterCon which is that I'm very glad that in the great game
of past the parcel that is running the EasterCon, the parcel didn't land when I was chair.
So I have nothing but sympathy for this committee and what they're having to put up with now
and deal with and I just, all my heart goes out to them really.
I think that as a fandom we need to give the con-con space to do what they want to do if
they still see the Easter weekend as something they want to head up and organise even in
an online capacity that I am thrilled and I'll be super behind them. But if they are
super crushed by the fact that all this has happened and they just want to go and kind
of have some time, then I think that's another thing we have to be super supportive of like
in either direction because I can't imagine how stressful the last month must have been
for that convention committee, it must have been awful.
Alison, as a former EasterCon chair, can you give us a little bit of an idea of what the
EasterCon committee is financially on the hook for every year and the sort of risks
that you take when you do commit to running one?
I think that the primary problem here will be twofold. The first is that they will have
given a commitment to the hotel that pending disasters of which this is clearly won, they
will have taken a number of rooms in the hotel, quite a large number of rooms. And then the
second thing is that they will have guaranteed a food and drink spend for the hotel. So you
say not only we will bring in so ever many people to your hotel this weekend, but also
they will eat and drink a lot of food and drink. And that's how you get the rate on
the conference space is by promising to spend a very large amount of money on food and drink.
That will have been considerably more than the cost of hiring space.
The government mandating that restaurants and bars closed was the, I think, final straw.
The impression I get from the convention announcement is that the hotel would have been unable to
let people eat or drink in the hotel common areas. And so as soon as that happens, you
have real trouble with your ability as a hotel to fulfill your contract from that, kind of
holding a big event perspective. So I think that's why the cancellation happened now,
because it was that that meant it became completely unworkable. I can't remember what
the typical food and drink spend for an Easter con is, but I know it's usually five figures.
I'd expect them to have a figure for a guarantee for food and drink in the high five figures.
Which is a mad amount of money. So there's not...
Have you seen how much beer costs? Yes. At five pounds of height, it doesn't take a lot.
That's true. That's true. When I was an undergraduate, I used to complain about that very vocally.
Strangely, now I earn more money. I've complained less. There's no seated Easter con for 2021.
There's not an Easter con constitution. If we've got any US listeners who are used to
Roberts rules of order and Wussfuss constitutions and all of these things, the Easter con is an
anarchic collective of like-minded fans who sort of run conventions by gentlemen's agreement
as much as by anything else. And so there's not any provision in any written document for
what happens now. So how do we select the next Easter con and how does all that work?
When you say that Easter con is run by a collective of like-minded fans, if enough former chairs of
Easter con put their weight behind a proposal that comes forward, it will just be agreed by a claim.
I just don't think there's a... I think this is much more of a problem in the minds of
rules and urge than it is in practice. I also don't think people are going to be lining up to run
the Easter con. You know, it would be a problem if you had a lot of contested bids.
No, I think it's going to be very difficult,
if whoever does step up and decide they want to run one next year, because they really won't be
able to make any concrete plans for quite a while at this point. They can try and find a hotel,
but they can't go and visit a hotel. They can't really make any commitments to guests or anything
like that. I mean, I think you're probably looking at least the somewhere, if not early
or before we even know if we'll be able to go and have an Easter con next year. So I think it's
going to be a very difficult task. And frankly, if someone steps up to do it, then I will vote
for them wholeheartedly. The most recent analogue is probably the 2007 Easter con,
which was held in Chester after the Liverpool Easter con, folded. And that, I think, was a case where
the convention was organized on about six months notice, if I recall correctly. I think convoy
folded in the summer and the convention was in March 2007. And so it can be done. I don't know
whether it will be the size of Easter con you would expect, because obviously Chester was very
small for an Easter con. And it might be that if there's only a six-month lead-up, you do get a hit
to attendance. But last time something even remotely similar to this happened, we still had an Easter
con even if it was a much smaller one. So I'm hopeful that this is all resolved. And I think
Alison's point is right that this is much more a problem in the minds of rules nerds than it is
in real life. Because if enough people want their to be an Easter con, they'll be an Easter con
regardless of any other considerations. I think that's true. I mean, I wonder how much of the 2020
Easter con the committee might want to try and roll forward into 2021. Because presumably there's
been a lot of planning done already. A lot of organization has been done. It's possible that
some of it can just be sort of jumped forward a year if they wanted to go again for next year.
But I would also understand if they really want to take a break. I think my question would be that
we compare this to 2007, but it's not really the same situation as 2007, I think, because
it's a completely different background. But question is, it seems like Easter con has rolled
along as a sort of very loose collective gentlemen's agreement different from year to year for a long
time. And possibly actually it's a ticking time bomb we have been passing along for a while and
happens to explode in 2020. Do you think this will lead to a long term change in how we organize them?
I think this is a great topic for another episode of Octas thought. Tune in next time
when we talk about Withery's to go. I think that is a long discussion. And I think it's a good
question. And I think we will come back to it in future episodes. And we would love our listeners
to write in with their thoughts. So on the subject of Easter con being cancelled on the topic of the
fan funds, Michael Larry, who is this year's TAFtelegger has cancelled his trip. Fortunately,
TAF, which is the transatlantic fan fund, has enough money in the bank that it can run another
trip next year. And this shouldn't be too much of a problem of speculative of the fund. But
obviously the other fan funds such as the Down Under Fan Fund and the Going Under Fan Fund will
be affected. And projects like Connel Bust, which gets people of color to conventions, may also be
impacted due to have any thoughts about how this is going to affect that kind of thing.
Fair full disclosure. I am one of this year's Gough candidate. So I am running to be the fan
who goes from Europe to New Zealand for the New Zealand Worldcon. I think at this point,
the New Zealand Worldcon must be in doubt. July time, I don't see how it's going to happen,
but it might do. And I particularly wanted to run this year because it's the first year
after my youngest child turned 18. So I can actually go off and party in New Zealand for
and Australia for weeks on end without having family responsibilities. But I'd be very happy to
run for Gough at some future date. The Gough has always found it harder to raise money than
TAF has, just because the expense of a trip is very much greater. And the number of fans in
Australia and New Zealand are slightly smaller. I think Gough this year, I think it's going to
be cancelled because we won't be sure if there is a Worldcon in time for anyone to seriously plan.
And also, I think the finances are so difficult, especially given that there are a lot of
teams wanting to run for Gough this year, that it might be reckless to make any kind of concrete
reservations that can't be cancelled for full refunds, because you might just sort of take out
all of the Gough reserves and then you won't be able to run again. I also think, speaking as someone,
you know, in a country I live in which I am not a citizen of and where it's obviously becoming
increasingly difficult to leave, I think people might be quite reluctant to go to New Zealand or
Australia this year because at any point we might have more lockdowns and you might find that you
can travel there but make it very difficult to travel back again. So for this year, I think
it's a non-starter. In the future, I'd like to see it continue. It's a huge shame that we're going
to miss having a race when there is a Worldcon, potentially in Australia and New Zealand,
but hopefully it can continue in some form in future years.
I do feel sorry for New Zealand 2020 because even if we completely eradicate the coronavirus
before that convention goes ahead, I can't imagine this is going to do good things to their membership
curve. And as the first Worldcon in New Zealand, I think that is a huge shame. And I think your
point about Gough running to Australasia is another facet to that being a huge shame.
But I think hopefully we can keep the fanist connections going online. So should we talk about
consolation? Are both of you on the consolation Facebook group?
So I am but I'm not really reading it. That's fair.
Because I have a look and I don't know. I think I must have just been in completely the wrong
frame of mind but I didn't find it very funny. It started off quite funny because it was all full
of con runners and con runners that the group of people are on like journeymen of fandom which is
the primary Facebook con running group have a certain mindset and they have a lot in common
with each other even if the sorts of conventions they're running are very different.
But now consolation is bloomed to about 20,000 people and a lot of those people
aren't, they don't share the same context and experiences as say Easter con fans do.
I mean there's a reason why we're saying this is a podcast from a British fan
fanish point of view that we know that the people that we are speaking to are going to have much of
the same interests and influences as we do. Consolation is now beyond that point.
It's covering a lot of different fandoms not all of which are my fandom.
I still find it's got some quite funny things in it from time to time.
It's an incredibly difficult thing to balance when you get to 20,000 people you can't all share a
sensibility and in a venue like well in a real convention where you can have different programming
streams and different rooms and different corners of the bar that works fine because
not everyone has to share a sensibility but a Facebook group with no separate channels and no
kind of different corners can't replicate that. Although I will say the last few posts on that
group from my perspective have been from British con runners so I have been appreciating those
quite a lot but I don't know what the main oofra is. I mean it's at times like this I really miss
live journal. I know live journal is still there but in terms of its fanish presence it hasn't been
for years and years now but the communities and the different people's blogs were a very good
way of emulating that kind of series of corners. Facebook just doesn't seem to do quite the same
things. I think that's going to be a problem for ending attempts to kind of have fanish
activity online while we can't have face-to-face conventions. Seems like Facebook is not really
the best space for it just because you can't scale to that many people and also it's so hard to see
what's new, what you've read, what you've already seen before but someone's posted lol again and
so it's popped up to the back you know the top of your feed again. I think it was obviously a great
thing to start at the time but I think it's going to be a useful lesson in how we do and don't run
these things over the next six or twelve months while we can't have face-to-face meetings any
time. I know a lot of fanish activity happens over on Twitter as well but I think Twitter falls
into a lot of the same problems where if you if you follow mostly people in fandom you can
replicate that kind of fanish experience but if you've got quite a very Twitter timeline it doesn't
do a good job of clumping everything together into coherent structures as it were.
I also I really value longer form writing and although you can do this on Facebook to some
extent and you get quite good feedback don't get me wrong when you write in a longer form
it's not the same as fanzines or even the the longer form writing on live journal and Twitter is
really hopeless for this even though this whole I am now going to write a thread one of 48.
I think a lot of the efforts to long form writing on Twitter are putting a plaster over
some pretty big hurdles and I guess the size like Tumblr are not widely adopted enough.
Well that's not true of of many fandoms but certainly the kind of Easter ongoing fandom has
never coalesced around Tumblr in the same way it did around live journal and so I think
I think you're right that the difficulty of doing long form discussions especially on Twitter but
on Facebook as well is a real problem and I am wondering whether this will encourage fandom
to discover better venues for that kind of interaction than we currently have but I don't
I don't know because I don't know what options there are and how easy those venues are to find.
I would say that Tumblr also is quite difficult for this kind of interaction
not because you can't post quite long post but the only way to really interact is to sort of
repost it with your own comments on and then the discussion just forks into a million different
pathways and you can never follow them all. I think it's a good broadcast medium but not a
good conversational one so I think that the choice is going to be do we find a medium which is
better suited to how we want to communicate or do we continue sort of lodging communication
in the platforms that people are already on even though it doesn't work that well but I guess in
the early days Twitter didn't even have @realise and hashtags people sort of came up with those
on the fly and got them incorporated into the system so maybe someone will come up with a
much better way of doing things on the platforms we already have. That is true and I should say
there are many people who do use Facebook and Twitter to engage in an awful lot of fan activity
and I suppose it's entirely possible we will get letters of comments from those people
criticizing our take because I am aware that I'm on Twitter but I'm nowhere near as engaged as
as some of the people on my timeline are and the same with Facebook. I think you Facebook a lot
more than me Alison especially in terms of long form writing. I'm we're about to move on to how to
keep sane during an apocalypse. I think I may have noticed we were going to have an apocalypse
likely before average and I started doing a lot of things around self-care. I'm a very
atheist person but I think spiritual self-care is incredibly important for people which is odd if
you believe that we're all basically animals who will go into the dust so I've been doing a lot of
meditating and a lot of journaling and a lot of that then becomes journaling on Facebook because
I write things that I can then share to a public audience or a near public audience.
Yeah because you've been trying to whittle away all of your earthly possessions or at the very least
carefully examining what earthly possessions you need. Yeah that's just gone so wrong I've
just bought a pair of Joy-Cons but that's that's staying sane in the apocalypse that seems entirely
fair to me maybe this is why this does not work well for my personality type which is more things
loved things. And I ask what Joy-Cons are because they sound quite like sex toy. Switch controllers.
They are a sex toy they're the things that fit onto your switch two days ago Nintendo released
Animal Crossing New Horizons which is the video game for our time you and your friends can build
a lovely island paradise where you pick fruit go for long walks do not observe social
distance and conventions I started to play it using my son's switch and I was like but this is
hopeless and he said this is Joy-Con drift which is a thing apparently and I was like well
your joysticks don't work and he was like no I need new ones but I can't afford 62.99 so.
So to stay sane you have bought switch controllers and Liz you have purchased a PlayStation 4
and acquired a much larger television. Yes I should say it was actually coincidental that my
television which is in my rented flat and so I don't own it basically went tits up at the same
time I bought a PlayStation and it got instantly replaced with one about twice the size.
It was quite fortuitous really I think it's about 55 inches kind of my sex tape obviously.
Family show Liz family show and that is what as mathematicians call exponential growth.
No I look greatly in which my life where I spend most of it you know sitting in between the same
four walls because I don't know the fact that people are almost people sized on it seems to
make a huge difference. I hadn't thought of that but that is interesting if you buy a
television large enough to have people sized people on it does that make you subconsciously feel
less lonely I don't know. When my daughter started at university we got into the habit of just
leaving Skype video on for hours on end and I thought about the future this is back when I
thought that the future would be good and I assumed we'd all have essentially video walls and you just
set up permanent video links to all of the people that you care about on your video.
I should say we have been in lockdown for about 24 hours here so I'm not quite as
starved as human contact as I will be in 12 weeks time.
That's fair my work advised us to work from home from and they just gone so I'm at the end of my
first week of lockdown and I don't know how long you've been
locked down for Alison at the moment. I've been working from home for about four years
but my family are also working from home and my house turns out to be quite small
if everyone's trying to work from home and it wants that's a real problem for us so my
my week has been having much about home much more if you can contact them normal.
We're still also walking out every day at the moment we can go to parks we can go
anywhere but that's I think isn't that by next Friday that will have stopped I'm sure.
I stopped doing main social interaction from Wednesday last week because it was obvious that
it was going to be necessary. Yeah that's fair. This is very depressing John we need less depressing
death stuff in our podcast and more jokes. That's fair that works. Lots of people are putting
entertainment online. Yes yes. So lots of games are free. The metropolitan opera and the royal opera
house have an opera every night. You can go and stream there's loads of television. I'm already
in television bankruptcy so Disney+ launches in two days time in the UK. It's a lot large in two
days time for the Asia region. I'm very grumpy about that. How long do you have to wait?
We don't have a firm day. I think they said spring 2021 or maybe it was pulled forward to autumn 2020.
Maybe they will pull it forward now all the theme parks are closed and no one's going to
the cinema because that will get them more cash but it will have to wait and see.
All of the streaming services are reducing bandwidth so they're reducing quality on the service
which seems fine to me. Because you're about to have a huge uptick in the amount of streaming so that
I think makes a lot of sense. I'm also a child of the video age. I remember VHS. I remember
long play recording on VHS. I remember long play recording on VHS. It's not that ancient.
Yeah so the quality was not that good but we coped right? We did cope but I also remember
bit torrenting TV in the smallest possible files. Actually not bit torrent. Probably before bit torrent.
Downloading TV in the smallest possible files so I can get away with them on my back.
And you know we just live with it. Okay boomers. These people today. Obviously I have never
bit torrented or downloaded anything. I have no idea at all what you're talking about obviously.
This is a golden opportunity to catch up with all of the TV shows that I have been letting.
Lacking. I am approaching the season three finale of Buffy which gives you an idea of how
behind I am. And I've also been playing a lot of board games. A bunch of print and play board games
have been made available for free online. I contributed to a GoFundMe for a gaming podcast I
listened to who has some contributors who are struggling to stay afloat at the moment.
And they've been giving free games to people who donate. And so I put a couple of links in the
show notes to a couple of free games I've been thoroughly enjoying over the last few days.
And I also spent most of this weekend playing the DLC for Horizon Zero Dawn on PS4 which I
had no idea got around to and I am thoroughly enjoying. Have you started playing your PlayStation
Atlas? I have. It came with a free copy of The Last of Us which obviously is a near future
dystopia after a pandemic has taken hold. And then as a chain from that I got a game with no
shooting involved. So I bought everybody's gone to the Rapture which is a game about wandering
around a structure village in the 1980s after everyone has been raptured in some way after that
and they've closed all the roads because they're saying it was a flu pandemic. So I picked really
the worst possible games to start my PS4 gaming experience with. I've got to try something more
jolly for next week. So obviously reading's also an option and I'm currently reading The Journal of
the Plague Year by Daniel DeFoe which turns out to be very it has a lot of messages for our times.
Is everyone buying toilet paper in Thailand? So not so far. I mean there were stacks and stacks of it
when I went to shops today but also my supermarket has not been hit by shortages. Really the buying
has just started because they've closed all the restaurants out of this weekend. But also I've
got a B-day sprayer and every toilet in Thailand has a B-day sprayer. Are you aware of these?
Do you want to describe them for the listeners who aren't? So the best description I've heard of
these is that your toilet pees back. So it's not a B-day seat but basically it's just like
a sort of showers break on on a hose with the idea being that you can like wash things up a bit
and then usually like wipe and so on but in an emergency you'd probably be okay.
So that may be behind the lack of panic buying of lural so far. I'll keep you updated on the
lural status as we go along. Thank you very much. On the subject of books I am reading The
Laundry Files by Charlie Stross. I am reading the most recent I think which takes place in a UK
after the government has been supplanted by a literal elder one. So it's not quite as relevant
as the reading material you two are reading but it's still not a barrel of laughs. I'm also not
sure whether I'm going to be able to return it to the library anytime soon because it is now over to
you. My library has automatically extended return dates till the end of April so you should check.
Oh that's really good. From the library I have the audiobook of Hillary Mantell's The Mirror and
The Light all 78 hours of it so that's keeping me busy and also from the library I have Europe
in Autumn by Dave Hutchison which apparently there was a pandemic in that one as well but people
have been recommending the Europe books to me for years so I'm quite pleased to finally be getting to
read them. I have bought a book on the Great Flu pandemic of 1918 but I have not brought myself
to start that one yet and maybe I shouldn't while I am home alone I might stick to more
theory reading. I said I'm reading Bare Face Messiah which is the biography of Elrond Hubbard.
Oh okay. Which I believe got its author followed about by Scientology for many many years.
I have no opinions on Scientology while I'm on this podcast. I also have no opinions on Scientology
and opinions on obviously bit torrenting. I just have strong feelings on B-day sprayers.
I have just checked and my library has extended my book reservation. I can exclusively reveal
I am reading The Labyrinth Index and yes I have until the 17th of June to read it now so they've
extended that by three months. Hopefully that is pessimistic but we shall see. I am very lucky
my local library does a very good genre selection. I was able to borrow some of the Hugo finalists
last year. So just before we wrap up what would you say your one top tip for surviving the apocalypse
is? I don't know yet honestly I think I need more time in isolation to develop those habits.
I have started doing online YouTube workouts in which a cheery guy tells me you know to push it
to the max and we're going to push through this and every workout is a step towards your goal
and it turns out I quite like that at this point in time. At the moment my life is very much
I think if you do live with other people spending time working out how you're going to
share your space differently I think is going to be very key to staying sane and has been a very
big part of our week. While I can I'm getting out every day because I'm fairly sure I will not be
able to get out every day in another week or so I'm thinking of taking up gardening.
What sort of world are we in where things like walks and gardening and jigsaw seem like sensible
uses of anyone's time? My wife has in fact mostly been gardening and doing jigsaw puzzles both of
which are activities she loves so she has been very happy. I do think the siloing of personal space
and being very strict about that has helped me in a span near a lot over the last week.
So that brings us to the end of the first episode of the Octa Thor podcast. Thank you very much
for listening to episode one. I think the lifeblood of a podcast is the interaction with our listeners
and obviously we don't actually have any listeners so if you're listening to this we really want
you to know what you think of the podcast and what we should be doing better and what you think
about the topics we've covered and what topics we ought to be covering next time.
And you know get another ground floor before we become a big deal and we won't pay any attention
to your feedback obviously now is the best time to send a selector. No cut there that's a line.
Oh and if you're interested in sponsoring the podcast we have sponsorship spots right.
Oh wow okay yeah so we're super keen to hear what people think what people think we
can do better what people think about the topics we've covered what people think we're doing well.
So please send us letters and clips of comment. That brings us to the end of episode one of the
Octa Thor podcast. I'd like to thank my co-host Liz Matty and I as a Scott for joining me. If you'd
like to send letters or clips of comment to us please email OctaThorpcast@gmail.com. If you'd like to
tweet about us or use other social media then hashtag OctaThorpcast and we will see you in episode two.
So for now it's bye from me and it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me.
Nailed it.