John, I think you are noticeably more um not with it today.
I think you're not well.
Um yeah, no, I'm gonna go with John's not in a great shape today.
It's not impossible that I am not firing on all cylinders.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 160th episode of Octothorpe, a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom.
which is doing a fist bump with the man standing next to them at the urinal on the 21st of May 2026.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Lisbatty.
That's another reference I don't get.
It's a reference to a Hugo Award finalist
Mm-hmm.
And also, I think a Hugo Award finalist you would detest A Hugo Award finalist this year
Yes.
Listeners, I have been playing Dispatch, which is very good, but I think it would Alison's not a big fan of big old uh cutscenes and games and games that are more plot than game.
Oh no.
And um Dispatch has many fine qualities, but I I do not think it meets the Allison definition of a good game.
I am finding it very compelling.
Well well I I think I have a I believe I have a code spoiler for few later in the episode.
Foreshadowing.
Liz, have you ever done a fist bump with someone peeing next to you at your own?
No.
Okay, cool.
Letters of comment.
We heard from Christopher J.
Garcia, who, as he says, he managed to drop a lock two minutes
after the episode went out?
It's impressive.
I'm not sure how, Chris.
Because he's clearly either listened to it very, very fast or read the transcript very, very fast.
I don't know.
Chris, tell us how you did it.
Is it time travel?
He listens to it on sixteen speed.
He gave us some opinions on the Hugo Shortlist because he was commenting here on our Hugo Shortlist episode.
And he says he's never been to Nannos.
Mmm.
So
Chris, you gotta come to an Eastercon, preferably one in Birmingham, and we'll go out and have a cheeky nano's and we'll record a podcast designed to be listened to very, very sped up.
Also, congratulations to Chris, who is a 27-time nominee
That is quite an indevent.
Congratulations, Chris.
Tied with Shaunen and Brad Foster.
Oh, that's a lot.
Well done.
Yes
Several people have been in touch with us since Easter to tell us about their various Nando's experiences and where they've eaten Nando's.
Um so you know, keep them coming guys.
Laurie Anderson of Hugo Girl is genuinely very confused at the concept of a cheeky Nando's.
She's going to go to a Nando's in Atlanta and she's going to report back.
And I assume that will be on a future episode of Hugo Girl.
Thank you to our global Nando's correspondent.
Tammy Coxson went to a Nando's in Zambia?
Yeah.
Tammy Coxon did go to a Nando's in Zambia instead of going
to an international rights conference because China got the conference cancelled but didn't get Nando's cancelled.
Nando's more powerful than China.
Yeah, don't let the Chinese
government hear that.
No.
It's not a challenge, China.
Yeah that.
Yeah.
Do you do you want Nando's to be cancelled, John, 'cause that's how you get Nando's cancelled.
I do not want Nando's to be cancelled.
Another letter, Alison?
Well I was gonna say Chris Garcia uh I thought you were doing the first Chris Garcia, but I think I've got the second Chris Garcia, where he says, Much like Alison, I read pretty much only coffee shop based books
Yeah, there's only one thing I like less than coffee shop-based novels and that's talking cats.
I will say that some coffee shop-based media is very good.
I would present as an example Reservoir Dogs.
Chris Gussier also wrote to us on the twenty sixth of March.
Is that the one?
Yes, that's the one.
Did I not lock last time?
I could swear I previously made a lame joke about Prometheus, says Chris.
You can always make jokes about Prometheus to us, Chris.
It's fine.
They're evergreen.
Yes, except for the one Prometheus Defender.
I believe Chris is a Prometheus defender, isn't he?
He is ensorceled by Prometheus.
What he says is Prometheus is a brilliant but not very good movie, which is
One of those things I struggle to um unpack.
I actually need to rewatch Prometheus because I had an argument about it in the pub with someone and
One of the things I really disliked about it, I wonder if it's satire.
The thing that really annoyed me was that when spoilers for Prometheus listeners, there's a plot point where she needs to get like the alien cut out of her at one point and she needs to use the
medical tube thing a majig, but it's only programmed to work on a man.
And I thought that was very stupid at the time 'cause I was like, but it's in the captain's quarters and she's a woman, so like why on earth would there be one that only worked on men?
And then someone said this is satire about modern medicine and I'm like, Interesting and I need to rewatch it from that lens.
Yeah.
Is Ridley Scott just a massive feminist about healthcare systems, or is he bad at movies?
Which is it?
We don't know.
I mean we do if we judge by the rest of Prometheus.
You're not gonna rescue it with this new feminist reading.
Yeah, we'll see how far this feminist reading can take me in uh recontextualizing the film.
So so you're going to re-watch Prometheus from a feminist lens and tell us about it?
Yes.
Apparently.
Okay.
Well, Godspeed, Jum.
Thanks, guys.
Chris also says he doesn't know when Easter is anymore because they have moved WrestleMania.
Which is seems quite strange to me because I feel that my culture gives me very many references to when Easter is not just Easter con.
And he has to get he had to stop writing because he had to get back to scanning issues of Playboy for work.
He's an archivist.
Yep.
We got a letter of comment from Kate McDonnell entitled Newcomer Here and I believe she is a new listener.
Uh I've been coming to EastCon and BristolCon as a dealer since twenty nineteen, but has only just realized that Old Thorpe exists.
Welcome Kate!
Be trapped in the dealer's room means I float around on the outside of Cons and the Phantom without being able to go to panels unless I'm in them.
Expense and being an introvert means I almost never stay after hours, so I miss out on bar conversations and many things are unknown to me.
I still don't know what filk means and mister Dyson has been urged to explain groats to dealers' property as no one ever has to me, so please can be explaining things on the pod
someone will always need it.
Um we will will try and continue to explain things.
I am going to explain some things.
I I do try to stay late if you can, Kate.
I know it can be hard
I really like it when introverts hang out in bars because I can I can be extrovert at them and it's good.
So Alison wants you to be in the bar, I think from the perspective of a target rich environment, Kate.
Yes, that's right.
I asked what we should explain.
And Kate got back to me.
Kate's things that she thinks we should explain.
She wants to know about Groats.
Groats are mmm Lil Tokens
Um, and they're given out to you for doing things.
Um, and I don't know where the tradition started.
Before my time they were already in use when I went to my first convention, which was about twenty years ago now.
But effectively you can spend them at the hotel, you can spend them at the bar or the restaurant, you you can spend them at the dealers.
And you didn't always used to be able to spend them at the dealers.
That is an innovation that has come in since my time in fandom, I think.
But they're good because it means we can reward volunteers in a way that isn't problematic and let them have like some stuff that they can maybe get some chips or a beer or a wine or you know
a mug and they're nice.
And and because our volunteers are actually paying their own way to come to the convention, the growth are just essentially giving them a discount on that rather than in any way actually reflecting money.
I think it's really important to say that
GROATS stood for Gopher Reward Tokens and they don't predate my time in fandom, so when I first came into fandom, you did a gopher shift and you got a drink for it, in the same way that programme participants get a drink on their panel.
But this is better.
Uh what is a fan fund or Yes.
What is a fan fund and why?
In the nineteen fifties, everyone wanted to send an Irishman to America and they all clubbed together and put some money in and they did it and it was good.
Uh and then Framfunds were born and TAF
Which is the Fan Fund the first Found Fund uh was founded officially in about 1955, I believe.
And basically it exists to send
people who we think would be good to go and talk to other people to the other people.
And this sort of originated in a time before the internet, so that was how really unless you were writing fanzines, that was how you
communicated with other communities of people.
But I think it's still very important because even despite the fact we have the internet, there's something about sending people to immerse themselves in the other culture which I think builds those bridges magnificently
So that's kind of the aim of a fund fund, I think.
Yeah, it's to build links.
I'm gonna gloss on that in a couple of different ways.
So the first thing is um the Walt Willis Fund wasn't the first fan fund.
There have been a few before that, both um successful and unsuccessful, to get people I I it was very expensive to cross the Atlantic and most funds could not
Fans could not afford that.
John's kind of like, unless you were doing fanzines, but at the time all the active fans were involved in fanzines 'cause that's kind of what what fandom was
Um that's changed obviously.
So it was a matter of trying to trying to get people across the Atlantic because people wanted to meet their friends that they'd known for years in print but hadn't had never met.
And there are what we talk about
three big triangular funds, which are the TAF, which is the one that takes people across the Atlantic, um, from Europe to the US, DUF, which takes people from North America to
Australia and New Zealand and GUF which takes people from Europe and the UK to Australia and New Zealand.
Yes.
And back.
Well, not always.
There have been fan funds where the person stayed
Uh I think Kylie Ding might have gone back and then come back again, but like there had definitely been fanfans where the person was just like, Ashley it's quite nice over here, I'm just gonna be over here for a bit.
Filk is singing about science fiction and stuff, sometimes to the tune of existing songs, sometimes to entirely new and original songs
Alison's done some folk.
Yeah.
Science fiction and fantasy folk music.
It was originally typo for folk.
Um there have been music events at conventions for a long, long, long time.
I mean I guess I ran a filk convention once, so I probably am slightly more of a filker than either of the other two.
But I don't really do filk anymore because I'm too busy at conventions to sit up all night singing.
You sit up all night.
Doing other things?
Yep.
Sorry, I'm too busy drinking to sit up all night singing.
Yeah.
And John has won a fan fund and Alison's won a fan fund and Alison has done filk and I've done both of those things.
But I did buy some stuff at the auction.
Kate also asks some questions about dealers.
Two ways.
If you want to get to something and still operate your stall, you can either
find a mate, this is why you should stay off drawers a bit, and say, Will you cover my stall for an hour 'cause I really want to see something Or you could just kind of throw a cloth over your stall and say, I've gone to
Um see such and such an item and I will be back afterwards if you like to put um people do both of these things from time to time
I think ideally you find another dealer in the same situation as you, see if you can get sat next to each other and then you can cover for each other.
Yeah, that's good.
Yeah, yeah.
Make friends with other dealers.
Historically, the dealers' room used to close at the EastCon for the Guest of Honour speech.
But it doesn't do that anymore 'cause we have more guests.
Yeah, I mean historically when when when how far are we going back here?
I mean certainly this is this is before my time.
Hmm, let me think.
So not within the last twenty years.
Yeah.
That's probably about the amount of time, isn't it?
I think it's good to impart knowledge of these things but also uh sometimes they're like, Well historically this used to happen and I'm like, Yeah, but
A long time ago now.
Okay, I I will remind people again that I am very, very old.
I think it's useful to understand where
Some things came from like the groats.
Yeah.
But with the dealer's room, I don't know how much of the modern dealer's room is informed by those previous things.
Really some.
I think that's right.
I think the other thing about this is that in the ver in the olden, olden days, the dealers were mostly fans who had decided to sell some stuff at conventions to defray the cost of getting to the con.
rather than people who were professional traders who were coming to the convention.
So that's a thing that has changed over the last, I don't know, seventy years or so.
That that had changed certainly by the time I got into fandom, which was quite a long time ago.
Yeah, okay.
That makes sense.
All right.
Thank you very much for bringing in Kate.
Um let us know if you have any other questions.
Let us know how many follow-up questions have been sparked by things we randomly said in this session.
Yes
The other thing I smaller conventions so so for example at Novicon the dealer's table fee is only twenty quid, so it it
So if you wanna run your c your table for part of the time it's much easier because you're not you don't have a lot of table fees to cover.
You do obviously have the other cost of getting to the con.
Yeah.
Alright.
Patrick Garvey wrote in to let us know that the Anglerfitch sketch is actually on YouTube and was broadcast on the radio.
Uh thank you very much, Patrick.
Um Tobes Valoir did point this out after the live show had concluded and I did put it in the show notes.
Um so that link is there.
for listeners who would like to go back.
I meant to record a pickup for the audio and I forgot.
So thank you very much for writing in, Patrick.
We also heard from Paul Wima.
Who talks about donations of fan funds and uh they are looking for donations to the fan funds.
Uh Duff is sending Erin Underwood to SwanCon in Australia for hood
duff trip and so they would love donations for that and Paul is the unofficial unoffici official unofficial treasurer of the fund and so you can get in touch with him if you have anything to donate or money to donate
Fun fun fact, Erin won Duff just at the same time as I won Guff in twenty twenty.
So I think this may be one of the longest gaps between
winning a fund and taking a trip.
Ever.
Readers write in.
Duff has had some hiccups and I'm glad that they're doing a trip.
It's good.
I'm really pleased Erin's making her trip.
I think that's great.
And you do the trip now and then I guess is then the idea is that we'll have a reverse trip twenty twenty seven and then we'll be ready for a twenty twenty eight trip to Brisbane if they get the Willcom?
Yes.
Oh I guess we'll see because if they give the Wilk on to uh Nuremberg you might want to do a trip the other direction twenty twenty-eight.
Anyway, let's see.
Doesn't matter for Duff.
Because it doesn't go to Europe either way.
Oh, it's Australia.
Yeah.
Sorry, Australian America.
Alright, you should cut that whole thing out then, John.
No, but it's a good point because Guff it's a bit of a headache for Guff, because Guff will have to try and do that maths and might have to do
uh a two in a row but Duff doesn't have the problem.
But I think it's a good point for Guff.
I don't think it's an enormous headache because
the new administrator.
When Fora gets back from Australia, you know, then then they'll be the WillConn and then we'll know and they can make their choices.
It'll be fine.
Yes.
And it's not unheard of for a trip to run the same direction twice
It's a little bit sad for the administrator who has to take like 50% more work, but like most people volunteer.
I mean, administration is not famous last words, administration is not too much work.
He said having administrated once and like it's not the end of the world to have to do it for another year.
Yeah.
Well
I mean the thing with Duff is you might have to do it for another decade, but let's hope not.
Um, again, uh I have been administrat uh administering Guff for a little while now.
I'm ready to hand it on
No, that's that's the thing we didn't say to Kate, which is the person who wins the fund administers the fund for the next race.
So um there is no free trip.
Uh you have to you have to work afterwards to raise the money that you spent back.
But I think that's one of the things that has led to um the Fan Fund's longevity is that it there's that kind of momentum carrying on for all of the funds
Yeah, 'cause if you don't run another race, you can't get out of being the admin.
Yeah, exactly.
And also they every so often there's like a there's like a panel item at a convention which is like, Oh the Found Father's dead and it's like no, next question
Clearly not.
People still vote for them.
Yeah, I mean, I think we've discussed this before, although I'd have to go and fish whichever episode it is out, but I mean
Basically the fan funds are a self-fulfilling thing.
As long as people vote for them and pay the voting fees to vote.
You didn't mention that you do have to pay to vote in the fan funds, then they will keep
being a thing.
If we get to a point where people stop being interested and stop voting, then they will naturally stop due to lack of funds.
As long as we do it in an orderly way, I think that would be fine.
Yeah, I think that's right.
Uh we also heard uh from Paul we met again.
Uh on our Hugo Finalist episode it says congrats on being a Hugo finalist.
Thank you very much, Paul.
He has been watching uh actual plays of Citizen Sleeper 2 and Dispatch on Gregory A.
Wilson's Twitch channel, which is not one I'm aware of, but
Spoiler for later, I don't think I'm gonna end up playing all of the uh best game Hugo finalists so I might go look for some actual plays.
He says about best related work, the lack of hard boundaries.
When was the last time a Hugo administrator actually knocked something out of best related work?
Hmm.
That's a great question.
I don't know.
I can't recall any.
I mean I wonder if there's a point where they've been booted because they sh actually fit better in another category.
Yeah, but there was I think I was reading Heather Rose Jones's essay on File 770.
Oh yes.
Um, A Theory of Relativity.
which is very good.
I will say I think it starts slightly too low.
It explains what a Hugo Award is.
And I'm like, I think if you're reading a twelve part essay on the best related work category, you do not need to know what a Hugo Award is.
I think you're already you're already covered on that one.
Um but it's very interesting.
Um but one of the things is that I think most Hugo administrators are the will of the voter is an important concept in Hugo Award voting.
So if a lot of people have put something in a category
it tends to be put in that category unless there is a cast iron reason not to.
Um and like the Apollo eleven news coverage is a very good example where despite the fact it's not
fictional dramatic presentation, it ended up in the category.
And so I would be curious because I think the administrator would have to be extremely confident it was ineligible
to remove it and I I don't know, I I wonder whether that has never happened.
If anyone knows, write in.
If John finishes reading the essay you can report back.
Paul also notes, and thank you to Kathy Bond on Blue Sky who sent us this as well, that Brandon O'Brien's pro poem uh from the Seattle Worldcon opening ceremony is in the Seattle Worldcon uh
daily fanzine from the event.
So it is online.
So when I said you couldn't have seen it, I was wrong.
It was online.
So we'll put a link in the show notes and you can go and read it.
It's also in the Hugo Award packet.
So Andrew Thompson wrote in about different science fiction prequels.
He says Prometheus is better than Attack of the Clones.
That is a low bar, Andrew, because Attack of the Clones is one of the worst movies ever made.
And then basically says, do note that
The assembly cut of Alien Three is actually a different plot to the the theatrical cut of Alien Three, and having watched Alien Three and then Googled the differences
Yeah, there's definitely some narrative beats that are cut down in the theatrical release.
I and I haven't seen the theatrical release yet.
I I will I will say the assembly cut is very good.
It's not as good as Alien and Aliens
But given that Alien and Aliens are two almost perfect science fiction movies, that might have been an unfair bar to expect Alien 3 to clear.
And Charles Dance is very good, Sigoni Weaver is very good.
Paul McGann is having a good old time doing whatever Paul McGahn does.
It's not perfect.
The assembly cut is a little bit slow, and like I do understand that having the characters die at the beginning is a bit of a bummer.
But like, I thought it was a solid three and a half star movie.
I enjoyed it.
Coxson's hot takes, Alien 3, not completely terrible
I will watch the theatrical release at some point.
Apparently it has a very distressing dog death in it.
But thank you for writing in, Andrew.
Uh we also heard from uh
Kiesa on Mastodon who uh appreciates having a podcast about the nominations immediately after so they can obsess about them doing their lunchwalk.
Yes, this is what we wanted
Instead of just being able to obsess about them on the blue sky for several hours after the the nominations are announced, you now get to do a real-time listening to a podcast and then obsessing.
Yes.
Our goal.
Indeed.
We also heard from Raj on Mastodon, who has found an old copy of the Worldcon 2005 Souvenir CD ROM.
Wow.
Oh wondrous things.
Um Do you think anyone would want the content for an archive where they're common enough not to need it?
I mean I went to this convention, I didn't know there were C D ROMs.
So I certainly don't have a copy.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Um if you are listening to this and go, Oh my god, I would love to have a copy of the C D ROM from Worldcon two thousand five
These do turn up in FanFund auctions periodically and they sell quite well.
The other convention that had uh CD ROM on its
uh uh on on its programme book was um Plocter.
Plocter.
com we did that once and it had all sorts of marvellous things in it.
I surely someone's archived this already though.
Both of these things.
You would think, right?
I'm looking on fanac.
org and it's not it doesn't seem to be they've got like the flyers
And they've got the newsletter, but as far as I can tell, there's no archive of this CD-ROM on Fanac.
org, and that seems like an obvious
Oh there's a scan they've got a PDF which is a scan of the front and the back and the disc.
But I don't think they've got the I don't think they've got I don't think they've got the contents of the disc.
And that is extremely funny to me.
I know that the the Plocked.
com CD-ROM had some things on it that where we specifically had a release to put it on a CD-ROM, but not to put it on the internet.
this being the sort of time that you might do that.
And that might also have been true for two thousand and five, so that might be the issue.
Read us right in if you know.
If if that was the case, I would have thought you'd have archived the stuff that was on it that did not have that and then put a note saying this is not because of copyright concerns.
The fact that they don't mention it at all on the main page
and the only thing Google can find is a scan of the cover of the DVD.
Makes me think they probably don't have the contents on so I would email Fanactor or Graj and ask.
Um the worst they can say is no.
But you will have done your fanish duty
Delightfully well trying to see if there was an image out there.
I have found the website of uh the fan Susan Stepney
Uh Ubumi has had a website at the University of York for a long time and that's why it still has an Interaction Worldcon 2005 review.
Uh, and says that the CD contains, including, among other things, historic photos from the previous Lung Cons, PDFs of all the progress reports, etc.
mirrors of websites, mini bios of all the program participants, the entire Ansible website and zillions of other easy fanzines, artwork and more.
So yeah, sounds like there was a lot.
Lot of stuff on there.
What did I do with mine?
Did I use it as a coaster?
Did I throw it in the bin?
Who knows?
I've got two big boxes of CDs in my uh spare room, Liz, and if I have one, it's in those boxes somewhere.
And if I don't, I think I'll make my peace with that.
Raj auto emails to say that I am right.
Thanks Raj.
Uh basically, um thank you John for speaking out about sites that make you provide a code for an email from login.
I too hate them.
We should start a support group.
Um and he also says uh another Northern Irish Eastcom would be great.
He really enjoyed the last one and would definitely go back.
Agreed on both counts, Raj.
You are a sensible person
And we also heard from DC on Facebook who said that they agreed with my thoughts on email login.
We also heard from Jake Sada Brookens on Blue Sky.
We mentioned last time that the ancillary review of books were doing a f
fundraiser and indeed that fundraiser is now completed and they went past their stretch goal and ended up with over seven thousand dollars which is pretty good.
So congratulations to Ancillary Review of Books uh who will now be able to
keep the magazine sustainable and develop and keep doing more of what they do, which is really good.
He also says, and the rest of the episode has me rolling out my old timey map of the Atlantic, scanning with my antique chart magnifier, and sighing once more at the distance to Eastercon.
Oh When they have airships, Cosella.
Yeah.
I mean just just set us get a big jar and put ten dollars a week into the jar.
And if you stop eating it, avocado toast.
Yeah, Casella.
Yeah, no, I mean it's not gonna buy you house, is it?
But it could get you to an Easter con if that was a thing you wanted to do.
It couldn't get you to an Eastercon
You'd have to not you'd have to be eating avocado toast like once a week and then you'd have to get rid of it for like a year.
And that's just to cover the transatlantic flight.
Yeah, yeah.
But you could do that.
People do eat avocado test every week.
I mean, not me personally, but you know.
If you go out for brunch every Sunday morning
So I I think this is a game we could call Spot the Boomer.
Fuck you, I'm Generation X.
I am definitely Gen X, I'm not a boomer.
I know, I know.
I also believe that it is possible to save up for some things that you want.
It is not possible to save up for everything you want.
Cassella says, He genuinely likes and respects the incremental or consensus model of changes to Hugo's structure, but every year he's struck by how things have misaligned a bit, and he does fantasize about radical constitutional overhaul.
And if you are fantasizing about radical constitutional over overhaul, then keep an eye out for our special episode which we've recorded but w w won't be out for a bit yet, where we we sort out the Hugo's casella.
Asterisk, Hugo's may not actually be sorted out.
Yeah.
Boy do we have a bonus episode for you, Casella?
Yeah, and and and also uh second asterisk
Uh our our way of sorting out might be quite a lot worse than the current state of affairs.
Um, it does remind me that we are swiftly approaching business meeting time.
And I have not really paid any attention to when the deadline will be for business being business, but if you're the sort of person who might like to submit sweeping constitutional amendments
Don't.
Uh it's time to get your ducks in a roll.
What do we want?
Incremental change.
When do we want it in due course?
Uh we also heard from Farah on Facebook uh about our discussion of accounts for Eastercons and the BSFA and so forth
And yes, FECOP, I do not know a lot about accountancy as I think we discussed when we were doing like the locus accounts.
I think what had confused me a little bit is that the BSFA does have to file like financial statements
as it's a limited company, but they're very kind of minimal because they're a micro company.
Well I hadn't noticed because I wasn't at the AGM is that there is like a big much more thorough
breakdown of the accounts.
In fact, incredibly thorough breakdown of the accounts.
And so if we have something like that, then I think we will be absolute like that's a
going b probably beyond the level of countenance I would like to see from Eastercon, but it is very thorough.
But I'm not sure kind of what is been done voluntarily and what is kind of mandated to release and what they choose to release to their
membership.
So I think all we're saying really is that if there was an Eastercon also done by the BSFA, we would probably be pushing to keep that level of um detail in the count so we could kind of see uh how it compared to uh a non-Eurocon BSFA Eastercon.
Is that fair?
I think that's fair.
But yes, thank you to Farah for pointing this out.
We also heard from Mike Scott
who noted that so there was a discussion of Welsh East Congs in the comments on our previous episode on Facebook and Mike Scott noted venue cumri in Clanderdot seems to be a suitable size, but it's just a convention centre without a directly attached large hotel.
Although of course there are plenty of small hotels in Hlandadno.
They're all damp though.
They are all damp.
I mean it was certainly the one I stayed in.
So I w the National Astronomy meeting in twenty fifteen, or maybe twenty sixteen
was held at Venue Camry and it is a very lovely convention centre.
But because there are no large hotels in Clanderneau at all, as far as I can tell, you're basically
you get in touch with the tourism board or the or whatever it is in Landon.
They put you in touch with A B and B and you stay in that B and B.
And like the B and B I stayed in was, I would, I would say, fine
The cleanliness was a solid three or four out of five, I would say, and there was a bit of mould here and there, but it was alright.
But like I think venue cumri would be great and they really need to build a hotel because it worked okay.
But I probably wouldn't rush to go back and I think we would have trouble from an Eastercom perspective.
Not least because a lot of those smaller venues are
harder for access requirements than might be strictly speaking ideal.
So I think Mike's right, it is a potential, but I think it has problems.
And if they will if they ever build a a a a a hotel there
I think it would be great.
I I'm gonna say one of the very most comfortable places I've stayed in North Wales and I've stayed in bunches of places in North Wales is in Mike Scott's spare room.
So I think that's um a great shout for an Eastercom venue if you're listening, Mike
I think Mike can put up four people in comfort, or maybe three
The Hugo Votorpack is out.
This year it is really quite comprehensive.
It also downloads very fast.
It's got
l like the majority of the stuff in there I would say.
I mean I haven't tried downloading everything because some of them I already own.
I already own, for instance, most of the best
Best novel nominees, but there's quite a lot of stuff in there.
For example, also some of the editors have put in works that they have edited, which I think is quite a nice touch, even though I'm still not sure I can tell from that how much they edited, but I do appreciate it
I would like to do a public service announcement.
If you want Hades 2 on a platform other than Steam, you can email them.
Download the PDF bit and find the email address if you don't want a Steam code.
because the scene codes are in the packet TOC, but you can get it on other platforms if you email.
Um so that's a good tip.
It does have some game codes.
I will say I have sent an annoying request to see if they can fulfil my need for a Claire Obscure Acquisition 33 code in a different region
uh because region locking is annoying and we will we will see even if they don't I mean fair dose.
Yeah and it downloaded really quickly.
Last year I had a problem where it was incredibly slow
Um but this year I managed to get the whole thing in a very reasonable amount of time and have been loading it all up onto my Kindle for future use.
Yeah, so I've been I've I've gone through and I've done my usual pass with the packet, which is stuff like
Renaming everyone has a different personal style for how they submit their EPUB, which is called something like name of person
2026 Hugo voter packet and so I go through and I standardise them all before I put them in my ebook library so that they're a consistent style
I do not, and that's why my ebook library is a total mess.
Yeah, I cannot cannot be avoiding uh that
But no, and I also in the process found out that I s didn't I never finished last year I struggled a bit more to stay on top of Clark and Hugo reading than I have done this year, apparently.
um because I found the Hugo packet from last year, which I did not finish putting in my uh ebook library.
Uh and I there are several things I just didn't read.
So um so yeah after I've done the twenty twenty six reading I might go back to the twenty twenty five reading.
Anything that jumps out of you from the packet, Liz, that you're excited about?
Uh let me just open the packet and have a look.
How about you, Alison?
Have you have you grabbed the packet eagerly?
Um, I have grabbed the packet eagerly and I want to channel f well, sess first of all, I
Although I don't think that um Ada Palmer's Inventing the Renaissance should win the Hugo, I would say there's not just the EPUB in there, there's the audiobook
of that which I'm quite excited by.
It's it's as one MP3 file, so it's nearly a gigabyte long, so I have had to break it into tiny little bits.
Why?
Uh because I want to take it okay.
I'm gonna go off topic now because um I'm taking it swimming with me and my incredibly good swimming headphones do not have fast forward or rewind, so they're very good in some respects, but not that one
And I'm gonna channel friend of the podcast, Claire Brawley, who was very impressed by the fact that the Max Gladstone series is on there in full.
Um
Yes, I um Meg keeps telling me that I need to read Max Gladstone books, so I am glad that now I have some Mad Gladstone books
I'm glad I have some of those books to read.
So it is on there in full, although it's in there in full for the new series which I haven't read yet, which is a follow-on from the previous Craft series.
I'm not sure if you I think they're it like nominated as a separate thing because there's enough volumes, but you could argue about whether they're actually a completely separate series.
But yes, there are three of those.
There's a whole of Elizabeth Bears
Space Opera trilogy, there's all of Catherine Addison's books, which are great.
Uh there's uh also like the whole of Old Man's War if you haven't read
those and of course I think the whole of October Day which is now like eighteen books or something, so it's a lot of stuff.
There there is a link to the full movie of Frankenstein
Which I thought was quite good 'cause that's one of the few things I haven't seen.
I believe in the UK it is on Netflix, but yes, I think it is very good and I believe
I don't know if I can put this in the podcast.
They had got streamer links for Superman and Mickey Seventeen, but I don't know if those have ended up in the packet yet.
Mickey seventeen says the PDF has a link to the
Yes, this is very good.
Three out of the six have streamer links, like which is Ah yes, so those were updated on fourteenth of May.
So when I first looked they didn't have streamer links, but now they do
Oh.
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
So if you're listening to this and you downloaded it if you if you downloaded the packet as soon as it came out and then you didn't do anything else and now you're listening to this
If you want to see those movies, go back and have a look.
Mickey seventeen is flawed, but a deeply interesting movie.
I I would it's not perfect, but it's really worth your time, I think.
I picked it on this podcast.
I thought it was well worth seeing.
Yes.
I think it's a good year for direct presentation.
Also, every single dramatic presentation finalist appears to have given us stuff for the packet.
Which is like, it's not that long since they didn't even acknowledge they'd been nominated for a Hugo or send somebody to the ceremony or anything, you know, and now
Here we are.
That's that's fantastic guys.
Thank you, studios.
It it's really interesting because Silksong, Hollow Knight Silksong, appear to have completely blanked us, which is a bit interesting because they're a Nintendo blanking us kind of makes sense, because they're a massive
corporate entity that tends to ignore people who are Nintendo.
But Hollow Knight is like a little indie game, so I was a bit surprised they hadn't submitted anything.
Even if it was just some screenshots.
I thought it was a bit sad that Blueprints didn't give people codes.
I bought blueprint off Argos on disc for the princy sum of £28.
Wow!
Well it was only three quid more than buying the digital version.
I was like this one I can sell to Kex after I finish it.
I I used ten pounds of nectar points.
That's what I use my nectar points on PlayStation 5 discs.
So the best thing about coming to Cornwall, John?
Our seven hour train journey was forty minutes late, so we're gonna get some money for board games.
And that's enough to day repay to buy a PlayStation 5.
I remember when we went to I mean there was a plava but we went to Novicon and we were our connection at Stockport was ten minutes and the train was eleven minutes late so we missed the connection and then once an hour.
And we had already planned to go into Stockport to get some lunch and cat the next train, but that eleven minute delay meant that we got like 200 quid a delay repay.
And I was like, yes.
Fun fun fact about changing at Stockport for Buxton, which is that that all connections always get mixed miss so
So you will always get delay repay.
I mean you may not always get delay repay, but we have every single time.
Right.
I know we have previously discussed delay repay, but maybe we could go back to the Hugo packet
Yes.
In the category of best delay repent note, um but yeah, I know I know we, you know
I can understand why they probably don't want to say on the official count, come and become a voter in the Hugos, you can like freely watch Superman.
But that is very nice.
I would also draw note to the fact that as part of the best editor packet
for Joe Monty, you will get Ken Lu is All That We See or Seam and Stephen Graham Jones the Buffalo Hunter Hunter, both of which are very good.
So the you and you get those as a bonus, they're not even nominated for a Hugo.
So Yes
I want to say something which is so I vote in site selection every year and I become a supporting member and I get the Hugo packet when it comes out.
And some people wait for the Hugo packet to come out before joining.
I I would say if you
Almost every year join the Worldcon because you're going to want the Hugo packet.
I would highly recommend that you take part in site selection because
It really helps the conventions in question if the money comes in early enough for them to make decisions about it
And so I I and I and I am also aware that I'm financially privileged enough to be able to to vote in site selection every year.
Um, if money is an issue, this is less relevant.
But if you're someone who always wants the Hugo voter packet and for money and for whom money is not a barrier to that, I I would recommend voting insight selection
Because then you are just on the train.
And it and it means that the convention can use the money to the best of its um impact because they can budget earlier and make decisions earlier.
I it it's normally a fiscally efficient way to get the Hugo you know, the y i i it's not gonna be more expensive than waiting.
It's normally a bit cheaper.
I think it's the same price constitutionally.
It's no more constitutionally.
So
Ah, right, okay.
But they can then up the price of site of supporting membership between then and when the Hugo Voter packet comes out.
I mean, and I don't think all conventions do, but some they can.
Good packet.
Well done.
Jed Hartman does a lot of work on the packet and has done a lot of work on the packet in previous years as well.
And he is a good egg and he does good things.
Thank you to Jed.
Yeah, and it came out like
It was very quickly done as well.
It was rapid.
Given I submitted our submission on the last day.
It was pretty quick at turning around.
Sorry.
I have one minor nitpick which is I think I can understand why there are word documents in there.
Um because I think from some perspectives that's very good, especially from certain exp accessibility perspectives, but I do think having some PDFs of those documents in there as well would have been good
Um, because like I don't have Word on my computer and someone on a Discord I'm on reported that when she opened it on her Mac in a non-Word program, it looked a bit funky.
And so I do think
More formats are better, but I do appreciate that there is a tension there with file size.
So um so yeah, I think it's uh it's like you know, it's a little bit tricky, but um, but yeah
Yeah, but if there's a if there's a file size tension then you just have to stick like the complete audiobooks and stuff in a different bundle.
I don't think a PDF is a massive issue.
I think the I think the fact that they've got fast internet this year wherever they're hosting the packet, I think that makes a big difference, right?
Yeah, it was.
I mean it was really a total pain last year, like it was gonna take three days to download
Something like that.
And so I end up just selectively getting the ones I knew I would want.
Whereas this time I could just hit, yeah, download the whole thing 20 minutes later, done, and then I can sift through it at my leisure
I I presume this was just a me problem of being many uh you know, geographically far from wherever the packet lives.
I don't really know if that's a thing.
That's fair.
Anyway, I've nothing I think that's it for the packet for me.
I was just gonna also mention on the subject of uh Hugo finalists.
Um we mentioned we basically our hottest take was probably on best related work.
We kind of didn't really think some of the nominees should fit, and we did kind of point out the Hugo spreadsheet of
Doom as being not a you know a pretty self-referential one.
And I thought it was very nice of Renee to point this out in Intergalactic Mixtape and agree with us.
We'll put a link in the show notes to go and read it.
But I th I think it's very gracious, especially when, you know, I was a bit like, Oh, we're doing a podcast about the finalists.
We don't actually want to be like mean about our fellow finalists and I think we stayed on the right line of that, but it is nice that people kind of take it in
The faith we intended, which is we like this thing, we're just not sure it's a great fit.
Yes.
Well also I think Intergalactic Mixtape is great and I'm glad that it's been nominated.
I will also say
Renee also mentioned us in a uh subsequent um Intergalactic mixtape saying that uh we deserve cute tiaras and slash or lanyards.
I mean I I could have a cute tiara.
It could have an egg on it.
She says that we are the global Easter con ambassadors because they they are the people who talk the most about Eastercons in the global
Fanish discourse.
And I hadn't quite put that together, but that might be true.
That's because EastCon is the best convention.
It's our home con, so I think it makes sense we've got a lot of affection for Eastercon.
My my first science fiction convention was an East Con and I've gone to nearly all of them since then.
I think it also says something that there used to be like a vibrant
discussion of Eastercons and things on live journals when we all had live journals back in the day and more on Twitter back in the day.
And I think now we have
Official com discords, a lot of discussion has ended up moving to discords, and so we might be the most visible discussion
But I also think that even on Twitter, one of the things we lost when we moved away from Live Journal and moved away from when kind of your your PDF fanzines became less popular was that we moved away from deep dives on con culture
In general, I think.
And I think one of the things we try and do on Octhorpe is bring that back because that's the milieu that I came up in.
Like I was I was on the live journals, I was reading the PDFs.
And um an octhorpe is an attempt to hark back to that time.
So the fact that you mentioned Live Journal is, I think, is I think that's what we're trying to do.
Right, shall we do picks?
Picks, picks, picks.
Before.
Shall I go first because I am one hundred percent certain my pick has not been picked before?
Uh I'm a hundred percent certain that you have Are you gonna pick Worm Charming?
Yes.
Yes
Listeners, it may not be very apparent, but when we were calling Alice in a room and she was saying Gen X, she is the only person on this podcast who has a temporary tattoo of a worm on their face.
Yeah.
That's true.
It is true.
It's true she is down with the kids.
How do you know it's a temporary tattoo?
You're not that down with the kids.
I did inkjet tattoos one of the plot.
cons we did inkjet tattoos of pirate themes that Sue Mason drew for us, so so I'm I'm very familiar with the genre of inkjet temporary tattoos.
I am in Cornwall um this weekend and Cornwall is somewhere where if you live in Walthamstow you you take the train to Cornwall because um driving to Cornwall will be
completely insane and flying to Cornwall's probably not very good for the planet and there aren't very many planes anyway.
And anyway, here we are on the train on the way down.
We were sitting next to a young man who had a very large worm
Had a di giant model of a worm about four foot across.
I said, You have a you pit up a very large worm and that way that you do to strangers on trains.
He said, Ah yes, I'm going to the worm
worm charming championships in Falmouth tomorrow and we were like, Oh, well we're going to Falmouth and he said, Well what are you doing in Falmouth?
And I went, I I think we're probably going to the Worm Charming Championship
But obviously our intention was merely to come to Falmouth and drink beer with our friends, which we've also done quite a lot of.
But we also went to Worm Charming, which is
a hilarious thing where people are given a three f a three metre square plot of ground and half an hour and Tolter without doing any digging
Extract as many worms from the ground as possible.
This sounds great.
And you might think that that's quite dull.
Apparently there is a Worm Charming World Championships in Cheshire, which I think is probably on either a ground that is ground that is much soggier than the playing fields they do use in Falmouth, or
or possibly they tip a couple of buckets of earthworms over before the conven before the competition starts because they get hundreds of earthworms and and
Um spoiler, they did not get hundreds of earthworms in Falmouth.
But um so the lad with the giant remote controlled worm, he said, I can't use it 'cause you can't do anything that's electronic or
m mechanical vibrations.
You're allowed to like play musical instruments to the worms or bash on the ground or or things like that.
And um
And so everywhere we went, everywhere we've been in Falmouth, people have been talking to us about worm charming.
Um we met some other lads who were going to the worm charming, and then we met Callum again, um, with his friend and their seagull costumes in the pub.
getting ready to to go worm charming and um when we took a cab down to the site where they're doing the worm charming the driver explained how he gets worms out of the ground and that his
method of getting worms out of the ground will be illegal because if you w use a liquid on the worms you have to drink a swig of it first so that the judges know that it's it's um not
bad for worms.
Um so but you could like tip beer on the ground to get your worms up.
I don't know whether that would work.
And so we kept going and there were lots of people in fancy dress and playing a wide variety of musical instruments to the worms, um, with varying degrees of success and and people running worm
Like say Early Bird Loans Company was one group that we saw and it was just all hilarious.
And they did, amongst other things, have temporary tattoos of worms, so I now have a worm facial tattoo.
Probably until but we're going somewhere that's not Falmouth, um, for lunch after this podcast, so I'm expecting Comment.
I'm expecting people to just think I have facial deformity
Not a worm on my face.
So yeah, worm charming.
Highly, highly recommended pastime
I mean I I d we didn't actually charm any worms ourselves, we just watched people charming worms.
The winner had forty one worms and we ran into them later in town because this is what this is what Falmouth is like.
Um we we ran into them walking through the town
carrying their uh really, frankly, it do not look at this do not look at this trophy if you're vermaphobic.
Um they're they're fairly hideous worm trophy.
That sounds excellent
Which they won for digging up the for for charming the most worms.
So that's it.
Worm charming, it's a thing.
I've put a link to the Falmouth packet in the show notes, listeners, and you can see some photographs from the Worm Charming.
Is this yesterday's?
Yes, including um including a picture of the trophy which is uh I would describe it as quite wormy.
Oh oh yes, so the third photo there, Ely Eli Burney and Callum Richardson are the Seagulls and they um they're the guy that s Callum is the guy I met on the train
Nice.
Good stuff.
Yes, no, that's a this is a great article that is full of full of wormness.
Uh that accurately reflects what it was like.
Have they got a graph in which the graph is a worm?
Ooh, yeah, I've seen the worm trophy now.
Yeah, yeah.
The worm trophy's great.
It's very wormy.
Oh yeah.
It is very wormy.
But I think you've got to lean in, right?
You you can't you can't be having the Falmouth Worm Charming Championships 2026.
And being like, let's let's try and elude the worm part of things.
You got it you got a full worm.
Yeah, so they have prizes for the for the longest worm and the most innovative
Worm charming method.
I think the most innovative worm charming method is the loans company, in fact the early bird loan company
Who who I saw and this is probably getting off topic.
Someone on Anonymous Clare t saw my selfie and said, So what is that person doing?
And that person in the back was the early bird loan company.
Yes, that is off topic.
Um they don't have a photo of the remote control 'cause what happened when it uh when Callum set his remote controlled worm off
large numbers of children started running behind it like the like the Pied Piper of Hamlin but with worms.
And every time he set it going, more children were following him.
That is interesting.
No, it was good.
It was it was so anyway, absolutely bananas.
So and I've never been to a worm charming
contest before, so that was very exciting to me.
Oh me it does sound like a good day out for all the family.
Uh i yeah, yeah.
With with extra worms.
Oh it's free.
I mean it's um i I think it costs money if you wanted to actually enter, but not very much.
You know, enough to cover the cost of running it.
That seems reasonable.
Shall I do a pick?
You should.
My pick is finalist in the Hugo category for best game at interactive work, Hades 2, because I've played a lot of Hades 2 and not done a lot of other stuff.
So Hades 2, if you played Hades 1,
Uh Hades 2 is the same but there's more of it.
If you didn't play Hades 1, uh it's a roguelike game in which you are running around in a sort of Greek mythological world
You are trying to defeat the Titan Kronos, who has um taken over the underworld and imprisoned your family.
and you basically keep fighting and fighting every night until you make it to the top and kill Kronos.
And then the second phase of the game begins.
I never saw the second phase of Hades because I never got to the end of the first phase.
I was not good enough at Hades.
Now, I will say that I was feeling surprisingly good about my Hades 2 abilities.
I was like, oh this boss this boss is down already.
This is not too bad.
And this is because it turns out there's a whole extra like phase of the game which is much more difficult.
And
I have resorted to God mode, which makes it easier for you every time you die because it was just taking it was taking long enough that it was not fun for me as I am not very good at games.
But with that turned on, I would say it is still a challenge.
It's just for me a manageable challenge, not a completely manageable challenge.
And if that is too easy for you, you can make it more difficult in many, many ways.
Yeah, but it's fun, like
All the details are very nice.
Like yes, you are running this kind of same style of thing night after night but there's a huge amount of dialogue going on.
Like they must have recorded huge amounts of dialogue because the characters are will respond to
a lot of very different aspects of how you've like equipped yourself and what you're doing on the run.
Um I think I'm not far off getting to like the main ending
I think.
At which point I may call it a day and not do every single other thing.
But if you really wanted to, you know, go go to town blueprint style on this, you could you could play for
you know, weeks and weeks.
So I recommend giving it a go.
If you if you liked Hades 1, you will like this again.
If you already played Hades 1 and you didn't really like it, this is not going to convert you.
But it turns out I do quite like this kind of thing.
For some reason I like this and I don't like Hollow Knight.
I think it's because Hollow Knight is slightly too difficult and Hades is manageably difficult.
So that's why.
Yeah, Hollow Knight, where I played the first one
I think it is just it's too hard for me and there was no uh mechanism in the game to to include me in it
I had about three hundred and thirty hours in Hades I have not started Hades II yet because I know what will happen, but I'm gonna start it probably on Tuesday.
We'll see.
What I'm gonna say about Hollow Knight is that I didn't
stop it instantly and I went through a couple of buses and I'd kind of got to this is this feels to me to be mostly the same over and over and not in the way that
roguelikes 'cause Hades is a roguelike, it's the same, but it's also different.
Um and I'm I'm I'm absolutely up for that in a way that I'm not up for.
Oh, play the same play this Metro Vonier over and over.
I don't like that at all.
Yeah, that's a good I I got to a point where I was just like, I don't I don't substantially feel like I'm seeing different things in this game anymore.
And I think I've seen everything I need to see and that took me maybe three hours in Hollow Knight.
And like in Hades I stopped because I was finding it too hard.
But I definitely didn't stop because I was like, I've seen everything this game has to offer 'cause it was it was quantifiably untrue.
I did not see everything that Hades has to offer, but I did see a hundred percent of the dialogue lines, which was something like a hundred and five thousand dialogue lines, so
You know, that's a lot.
All right, so if I mean it it's too late now, but I would say if anyone wanted something off Allison in the next few weeks they should have emailed before this, because by now she's gone.
Okay, my my pick.
Uh I'm not gonna pick a uh finalist for best game or interactive work.
I'm gonna pick the prequel to a finalist for best game or interactive work.
I'm gonna pick Hades One.
No, I'm gonna pick Citizen Sleeper
So this is a role-playing game.
You are playing the titular citizen sleeper.
This is set in a world where
Sentient AI is illegal, but there's a way around that, which is if you get someone who's heavily in debt and you get them to sign some paper, you can put them into cryo sleep and you can emulate their mind in a robot and that's completely fine.
And you play a uh person who is an emulated mind of some being that is in cryo sleep, and they are called sleepers because they're sleeping
Uh and you roll you roll virtual dice and you assign them to virtual actions and then the plot unfolds.
It I got really invested in the plot.
Um the gameplay loop is fun.
In the end game, there is a point where you can end up in a situation where you're waiting for things to happen because some things take like a certain number of cycles in-game to occur.
So it was a little bit of of a point later in the game where I was like, oh I kind of I know I just need to wait for this to happen uh and I'm waiting for that.
But yeah, I sa I say I I have platinumed it.
I've played a lot of it um because it's right at the
level I can cope with while I'm sick, which is lovely.
I cried at two of the endings and I just really liked it and I'm very much uh looking forward to playing Citizen Sleeper 2
which there are only Steam codes in the packet, but there was a half price sale on Switch and PS5.
So the PS5 one went on sale I think two days ago, three days ago as we record in the UK.
Um so I've bought it on PlayStation 5 and I will
uh play through that.
But yeah.
Hmm.
Sorry, it's just weird.
I was like, okay, I should look up Citizen Sleeper.
Uh it's not in my PlayStation Store.
Citizen Sleeper 2?
Yes.
Main Citizen Sleeper.
Uh not there.
Maybe it was so indie it never got um sent to my region.
I think Citizen Sleeper was their big breakout game, so Citizen Sleeper 2 may well have had more
resources when it launched.
The designer, um Gareth Damien Martin, is still making video games, but their next video game will not be a Citizen Sleeper game, and the next Citizen Sleeper game is going to be a tabletop game.
So that is intriguing
Well I'm gonna try playing Citizen Sleeper 2 and see if it works without having played Citizen Sleeper One.
You play a different character, so I'm sure like I'm sure I I there won't be any directs
Like there's not gonna be anything where you're like, what is going on?
I don't think.
That was the Old To Thought Podcast and it's goodbye for me.
It's goodbye for me.
And it's goodbye for me.
But yeah, and I saw an I saw an Elvis impersonator last time I was at Venue Cymru, that was why we were there.
He filled the quite large auditorium there.
Nice
And he kind of shook it all about, I guess.
Whatever it is that Elvis does.
So you went you went Have you seen the Tim sorry, Liz, you go.
No, I was just gonna quiz Allison further about
going to Wales as the Elvis impersonators, but I think no, let's just move on.
I I mean I think probably leaving it there because I think the actual explanation of why I was seeing an Elvis impersonator is not that exciting.
But Yeah, so let's leave it.
We will draw a veil and move on.
Did you see that Tim Vine is in a movie?
Okay, come on, you can do better than that, John.
I know you're not well.
Tim Vine, who is a noted uh English comedian, made a movie
So the poster says Tim Vine is Plastic Elvis as Sam Solano in a brand new motion picture musical called Rocker Brella Fella.
And there's a lot going on in that ser sequence of words, and I think he's doing an Elvis impersonation parody
Plastic Elvis and Umbrella Mender.
Yeah, but he looks like Elvis.
I'm just I'm like, I'm not I'm not against
I'll put a link in the show notes, listeners.
Sam Solano refer returns home to Wide Stairs because the family umbrella business is in trouble.
I'm just curious.
Sorry, I'm just hold on a minute while I watch the trailer.
No.
No, no.
Doanna turned a blind eye to John randomly googling Elvis impersonators during the pod, but no watching of trailers.
Let's get move on.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod in Compatech.
com used under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.
0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.