Alison, stop responding to Laurie on Discord, we're podcasting.
Fair.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 111th episode of Octa Thorpe, which is
ringing its way to you on the 6th of June 2024. I'm John Coxon, I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
And we don't have letters of comments today listeners, because we are going to be discussing
the Hugo novel finalists. That is right, the six finalists for Best Novel in the Hugo Awards
to be presented at Glasgow in 2024. The first novel we are going to discuss is The Adventures of
Amina Al-Sarafi by Shannon Chakraborti. I believe we have all read this book. The synopsis is
basically there is a woman who has a family and then she is put in a situation in which she must
jeopardize that family in order to do something for someone and that she doesn't really want to do
and in order to do that she has to do a lot of other things just to get the gang back together
and the gang getting back together takes some time and then she has to do a thing with a person.
I don't want to spoil it. She has to meet two people, one of whom wants some bathroom remodeling,
on the way there are birds. That is, yeah, simultaneously accurate and completely useless done. Well done.
It's the Coxing Guarantee. I quite liked it. I thought it was too long but the things that were
in it were good and I think if it would have been, if it was shorter I would have enjoyed it a great
deal more but I did enjoy it regardless. What did you peeps think about it?
I mean do we want to give a little bit more of exposition here which is, you know, say the woman
going off and getting the gang back together is a notorious pirate. Yes. And she's off for, you know,
more pirate adventures and there's sea creatures and monsters and then a kind of swerve into magic.
It is basically a piratey adventure novel and I like piratey adventure novels. It's a good solid one.
I would agree that it is a piratey adventure novel. I did not like this book very much.
I thought it was too long for the story it was telling. I also, it spends about half the novel
getting the band back together and then it spends the last quarter of the novel setting the gang
up for the sequel and so there's only really a very small amount of novel for it actually to
have this novel's plot in it and even so everything is very spun out there.
A kind of, every so often she'll describe something and some of the other novels on this list have
quite a long descriptive passage. You really feel you inhabit them whereas in this you kind of feel
like it's a tourist guide to the city that she's wandered up into or the place she is now. It feels
like an observer looking at it in a way that I don't think you ought to. I think it should
come much more from her own experience. I think there is a problem with writing pirate novels
which is that you have to find a way to allide the fact that pirates are actually quite nasty
people and this woman is an notorious pirate and they really don't show you why she is a notorious
pirate because this is a very cozy novel and that would kind of distract from the coziness.
There wasn't enough here for me especially not for a novel of 150,000 words and I understand that's
because I'm old and I have to divide my remaining life by the novels I read but I would really have
liked this to be tighter and shorter and just not this so sorry shall I interrupt you? You're
probably not the novelist for me. I think I want to say I never felt like she felt like a tourist. I
always felt like she was a tour guide. I really liked how it felt like it was introducing me to
this area that both the character and the author clearly have a lot of affection for and it kind
of feels like when you go and see someone when they've just moved into a city they love and
they're telling you all the things they love about their city it felt like following a friend
around a wonderful place and I really did like that. I liked the sense of place very much.
I don't know how much of that is the actual history because this is kind of a fancy novel but
it's very much based in kind of the at-hall past history of around the Indian Ocean but there's more
magic and crockons and stuff and it's not a feel that I know a lot about so I can't tell you
how to whether it does have this much historical accuracy going on but it does feel like she's
kind of taking all that and using it's very interesting kind of set-dretting/world building
for the plot. This is not a criticism of the novel but in the front matter there's a blurb and one
of the people who reviewed it favorably said oh this is really giving you a chance to be immersive
in a fantasy version of the 12th century around the Indian Ocean which is not an environment that
most of us know very much about and I'm like well one of the world's most famous story cycles is set
in this time zone and indeed also has plenty of magic and fantasy and this is the raw stuff from
which with which Chakrabarty is working and I'm sure she has added to that with historical research
but I think you just do better to go back and read chunks of the thousand and one nights which is
very good reading and remains so. I think two things to say there one is that you know there
is room for more than one historical fantasy novel set in the 12th century we don't kind of go to all
you know retellings of Arthurian legend and say oh well just read the original one you don't need
to do anything else and yeah also like we're judging 2024 books I mean are we judging where these
things go in like the pantheon of all books ever that seems a bit harsh because nothing's going to
end up judging well on that right I mean I think I like this better than both of you so that's why
defending it a bit more. Oh I sorry I don't mean to imply that I didn't like it I liked it a lot I
thought it was too long I did think it was too long and part of that is that there is a part where
it diverts into the and this is going to jar for listeners against something I say later I think
but there is a part where it diverts into like the specifics of exactly what is happening in terms of
the pericourt and stuff which I won't explain what it is because it's a bit of a spoiler but
those who have read it will know and I just I didn't really think I needed that trunk of the book
like I could have quite happily just excised that and I could have gotten rid of transgressions
with a capital T and I could have and it might have felt a bit less like a fetch quest but other
than that I really enjoyed as I say the sense of place I really enjoyed the adventure it is the
first novel in a trilogy but I will also say I thought it came to a pleasing end like I am not
going to be upset if I don't read the other two books it doesn't feel like there's too much dangling
in terms of the character arcs and and yeah I really liked it and certainly
sort of yeah I have I have I have criticisms but they are not huge criticisms I'd be quite happy
I'm quite happy that this is on the ballot like I don't feel like it's a an imposition or anything
like that there was something else we're gonna say as someone who has read so I've recently
watched our flag means death and I listened to a podcast called campaign sky jacks and pirate
fiction tends to include the fact that pirates are you know rapists and murderers but in the same
way that superhero fiction tends to include the fact that vigilantism is bad like there's
this is a fundamental temple of the genre I'm not sure I don't know I'm unwilling to
level that criticism here because I don't want to read about actual pirates because they were awful
but this was great so I'm happy with with that um generally this is just clearly not the sort of
book I'm much up for but I mean I've had times in my past when I read a quite a lot of books that
were quite like this and really enjoyed them and I might have times in the future that 60,000
good reads reviews on this book some enormous number it's hugely popular hugely successful
I think you know all those people can't be wrong it's clearly doing a lot for a lot of people
I'm just one of them. Spiler I am going to say later all these people can be wrong not in this one
but later it's reminded me of something else I want to say about this book which is absolutely
not the author's fault as well so in the e-reader versions of this book whether it's
Kindle or Kobo there are sections of the novel which are text which are rendered as images
which is the most annoying thing ever and it probably won't matter to you if you're already
if you normally read books in the font size that those sections are in you might not even notice
but if you are older and you read books in a larger font you have to basically go into the image and
then and then zoom in and I'll read those sections of the actual novel they are not illustrations
they are sections of the novel which should be rendered as images it's very bad yeah because I
think one of the good things about you know we can lock over or e-book in any way is you can set the
text size however you like while we're on the subject of things that are annoying it's lovely
that publishers put things into the Hugo packet we appreciate it very much please don't put it in
as a PDF with a watermark because that makes it almost impossible for me to read because I'm
I'm older now I need to be able to manage the font size on my books and I'm not the only one yeah
Witchking by Martha Wells is a story it's about a witchking the witchking is a demon called
Kai we are in a secondary world fantasy where there has been a great war and upheaval and we are now
following Kai and some of his allies telling the story of what's happening the present of this world
as well as telling Kai's backstory and kind of how his character came about and how this world
came about and how the war ended that's what I'm going to say because I admit I have reached only
65% ish just because I got it from the Hugo packet and it came out pretty late and it's quite a long
book so it's possible that anything I say will be rendered wrong by dramatic upheaval and revelation
in the last 30% but I can give you my views on the first 65 again like the else roughly it's a
competent example of a book I'm not super interested in it's a good secondary world fantasy I think
Kai is a pretty interesting character he is basically a demon who can suck the life out of mortals and
jump between bodies and has a kind of set of magical powers and he is allied with people who
have different magical powers I think the world building is interesting but sometimes you get a
paragraph which is something like and the immortal blessed and the immortal marshals who do their
power from the well of you know Tess Fassian who you know and then they fought for the higher arcs
in the battle of the summer halls where Kai was allied with third prince baschasha and the rising
world you've forgotten the rising world I forgot to say this is in the rising world like you get
paragraphs like that and I think it is to Wells' credit that I kind of understand what's going on
there but it doesn't make it for me uh super interesting and easy read it feels like a good
secondary world fantasy but I probably would not pick up secondary world fantasies unless they're
astonishingly good and this one is merely pretty good I have something in common with this which
is that I am 65% of the way through this book um so just two thirds of the way through the book
because it came out in the Hugo packet I nevertheless had given it plenty of hours I really like the
structure I like the fact that she's telling the story now and then she's also got this very
interesting character Kai and she's kind of telling the story of how he got that way and now the
time two thirds of the way through the book I am quite enjoying it but for the first
quarter of the book I was finding it pretty tedious the writing is excellent throughout the world
building is good you believe in the situation that these people find themselves in but I'm finding
this book to be like pushing a large boulder in that I have to keep pushing if I if I my attention
drifts for a minute oh I'm off like looking out the window or wondering about lunch or you know it's
it's just not it is not compelling for me I have to continuously engage in the process of reading to
keep reading this book and normally when that happens it's you know if it's like a classic and
I'm going to know what people like about it by the end of it or I I will at least be able to say
well I have read Anna Corellina or whatever or if I am reading a non-fiction book and I'm expecting
to learn something as a result of the process or even when I'm reading science fiction and I am
expecting science fiction to tell me something important about the way we live or the way we
should be living I just generally with fantasy I'm like eh the job of a fantasy books to tell me a
good story so if it's not keeping me reading it's not quite doing that yeah so fantasy fans don't
write it this is a problem with me I know fantasies can do all of that regular listeners will know
that fantasy is not my favorite bit of the genre I think that I like fantasy more than you I liked
this book I thought it was interesting that it tries to do something a bit non-linear with the
storytelling and I really liked how it starts in the thick of the action and like you're
starting with someone who is being called a demon and you're like well are they the good guy are
they the bad guy like what's going on how does it source lot together why is he so worried about
his friend why is this happening and I I very much liked that as the book went on I found that
sense of urgency diminished a little bit and I think that did make it slower for me to read
I suspect is also quite a long book but I can't find a word count anywhere on the internet but it
felt long when I was reading it to go back to what Liz was saying about kind of like the rising world
and all of the proper nouns I found it sometimes a little bit confusing what was actually happening
Wells would mention a character I'd be like who is that and I'd like search for it in the text of
the book and I'd be like oh they've been mentioned three times in the entire novel and the last time
their name was mentioned was a hundred pages ago so of course I don't remember their name I wonder
if part of the reason it's hard to read is because it sometimes gets a little bit muddled and I wonder
whether actually having fewer characters and having more explicit kind of remember they're doing this
but done better than like a little text box would have made it a lot easier for me to read because
there were a few bits where I had to go back and be like okay I think I've lost the thread here
slightly what is actually going on before all of that I did like it and I do like the two main
characters very much I also quite liked I thought the world building was intriguing in some ways
it was quite vague and it's clearly set up so that more stories can be told in this world by very
much liked how complete their character arc for the two main characters felt by the end of the book
I wouldn't be surprised if she writes followers follow-ups in this universe but I'm not sure I'd
be surprised if she didn't tell more stories about Kai although there is definitely room to tell those
stories yeah I think part of it was I think she wants to tell a really deep world and part of that
is having like the different types of magic and powers that are available and you know the different
ways that the people are getting their energy you know some people are fed by deaths some people
are fed by kind of the power of the under earth some of the people are fed by natural wells of power
that get focused or something and it's got these characters called the immortal blessed in the
immortal marshals who are kind of this vision of like white and gold coming down from the sky
and so obviously maybe that's contrast to the witch king or whatever but it just felt like the
slightly too many things that are all introduced for me to keep track of all of them so the depth
of the world building is making it a bit hard and even once I've got to 60% in I still know what's
going on but it's more like oh yeah we've heard of that a couple of times how is that well different
from this well is different from the other well yeah I mean there is a castor character the
front jump so that's probably where you're supposed to go if you forget who people are
I'd have to say I didn't have find that problem but I mean I read it probably read it in a much
more compressed time frame it wasn't just a very quickly say it wasn't just characters though it
was tough like I don't remember the name of the town they're going to ah stuff like that like
like stuff to do with the concrete facts of the world I found that she was not using the names
often enough and it meant they weren't sticking in my head so I will say I thought the witch king
was better than the murder bot novel I like Wells better when she is writing fantasy than science
fiction I was a huge fan of the Rexia series and I really like the murder bots but I never thought
they were like the best of the best things his life bred I thought they were really good by
doing they were amazing I think I do prefer this I only read one murder but novella I quite enjoyed
it I haven't read the rest I read the first one I read the first two I really really like the first
one I thought the second one was kind of a bit too much like the first one this is true of
Alison and all series those again oh 100% I want to say this book may be angry at a bit where he's
talking to the demon who turns out to be the antagonist in part of the novel and they reminded
me of a bit from Amina Al-Sarafi there is a point in Amina Al-Sarafi where Amina maybe
I don't know third of the way through the novel is talking to Salima I think I like I felt so angry
on Amina's behalf because Salima was being so awful and there is a part in this book where
Kai has a conversation with someone and it made me roitously furious and I enjoyed it on both occasions
I very much thought both novels do a good job of portraying injustices in a way that I thought was
intriguing and I enjoyed even if it wasn't like the focal point I want to make it clear that I
I might have been a sounded a little harsh I think this is you know pretty good and I'm gonna
finish it and I don't if I'll read the sequels but that's just because quite often I read the first
book in a series think that's great I don't need to read more of it it will depend but I mean
I'm definitely happy with it being on the Hugo list it probably would not have been on my personal
list but I think it's perfectly fine to be there I feel the fact that I'm struggling to keep going
with this book is not actually a reflection on the book it's it's me I'm sure I will finish it
I'm in the next couple of days and I just said there's lots and lots I like about it and
clearly lots of people do really like this one as well and and because I'm I guess terribly
elitist I actually I have more sympathy for a book that I'm finding slightly hard to read but
that's a lot of people like the book that I think is is too shallow that's a lot of people like so
that's also me so on the subject of books that Alison thinks are too shallow shall we discuss the
scallory segue to I think it's too shallow um that's a fascinating question so stottavillan is
a novel about a john scallory hero his name is Charlie so he's down on his luck he's got no money
and the only thing he's really got in the world is his parents home his parents are now dead which
his step brothers and sister are trying to force him out of and he wakes up one day to discover
that his uncle who was a recruit reclusive multi-billionaire has died and wants him to take over
a I mean you don't discover this quite a way but you discover it quite soon wants him to take
over the family business which soon turns out to be super villainy and he goes off and learns how
you'd be a supervillain and and stuff happens and also there are talking cats so this is a
intended to be a comic novel and indeed there is funny stuff in it and there was one place where I
laughed out loud at a joke that I would say is pretty purer all it is funny in places and
it is way less so last year scallory wast is stuck on this novel knocked off Khaji
preservation society I think Khaji preservation society hung together much more as a coherent
novel than this one does because this one there is not a single page where I didn't go no that's
ridiculous no you are telling me to believe this I do not have disbelief suspenders that are big
enough for this novel or strong enough for this novel this is nonsense you don't get to write
nonsense just because it's a funny novel um or actually you do but you have to be funnier than
this there's a kind of balance here I don't think this book is funny enough to justify the
nonsensical nature of it obviously millions of people on the internet disagree with me because
this is another very popular book and if you like it I'm sorry it's fine Liz any thoughts I mean
I think you could probably take my section on the scaldy novel from last year's shortlist and
just change from the names and stick in here Liz look I know I am not I'm not the target audience
these things I would not have read this unless it was on the Hugo shortlist because I already know
that like with rare exceptions scaldy books tend not to hit for me and it had all the same things
that I didn't really like about last year it's extremely glib it doesn't really make sense if you
think about it for more than like two minutes I didn't particularly like the main character
everyone sounds exactly the same and quippy and makes pop culture references although not as many
as in last year's book the talking cats are slightly amusing and the swari dolphins are slightly
amusing but I think my main thing is like it is so shallow like for a book about basically finding
out your relative was a supervillain and in a there was a sort of secret society of supervillains
or maybe it wasn't a supervillain I don't think it really delves at all into what it means to be
a villain it kind of like goes a little way in there by saying whoa just exploiting the system
and things like that and then kind of tiptoes back from it and then gets a little bit maybe deeper
into it and then tiptoes back but it never really delves into like what his uncle must have been
doing to accumulate trillions and trillions of dollars and for all you can say that he's doing
it by you know opposing the other villains he still managed to accumulate trillions and trillions
of dollars and owns his own volcano island where he treats the staff quite well but he does own his
own volcano island like it doesn't really want to dig into this I think because it's trying to be a
bit more fun than that but it just feels like it skates shallowly over the top yeah so I think
this so this is true and I think it everything Liz said I agree with I liked this in the sort of
I read 75% of it in an hour kind of way like it it's not a long process it's kind of
scallisy in his zany mode which I enjoy far less than scallisy in his thoughtful sci-fi mode I
think I much prefer the science fiction to the zanyness I want to say like so scallisy clearly
is bothered by rich people being bastards because this has been one of the themes of his last two
novels both of which have ended up on the Hugo Ballot but I think both the adventures of
Aminal, Serafy and Saint of Bright Doors and some desperate glory been a very different way
they all also touch on what it means to abuse power the adventures of Amina or
else Raffy especially like Salima is it made me much more angry than any of the billionaires in
this do and obviously Salima is not a billionaire but she has a commensurate amount of wealth for
the time the other thing is I found the description of the billionaires in this much more sanitized
than I found the description of the pirates in Amina because billionaires are bastards like
you don't get that much money if you're not a sociopath and so it is I don't know it feels
like a kids daydream in terms of like the fundamental setting which you know I don't necessarily mind
but I don't necessarily also want to give it a Hugo award I have a lot more I think I have a lot
more time for scallisy than either of you do and I do enjoy his novels when I read them but I agree
with this that I probably wouldn't have got to this had it not been on the ballot because there is
so much else to read at the moment I keep wondering when scallisy is going to do something in the
because I loved the old man's war series I thought it was really good and yeah he hasn't done anything
that made me think that since I guess the last mprox series which I also really liked but yeah
this is not this is not where he sings for me I just feel I could have watched that Simpson's
episode where Homer goes to work for Hank's Scorpio in about 22 minutes and it probably would have
had more left so but that is why I put in the notes that it shares with the Adventures of
Amina out Sarafi a desire not to talk about how criminals make them on it you know that that is
that was my point about the book that you cut me off of then made that I said in chat I want to say
one thing before we move on which is it does account as a reference if you explain it every
single time like every time scallisy makes a reference he explains how clever he is by having
made the reference with one of his other characters and it's like John you're making references that's
fine stop explaining them it's like the guy in the bar who keeps saying that was a quote from this
movie you know and it's like I know and I wish you'd stop it's it's very it's annoying tick I don't
mind putting references in it's the constantly is the constantly lamp shading the fact you're
putting references in that's it's very irritating maybe that's why I prefer the stuff is that isn't
set in modern day earth I'm always saying I like lock in which I guess is earth based and
didn't like the last themprox as much as you lock in's definitely him in sort of thoughtful
science fiction mode more yeah I like that let's have a bit more of that right books I would like
more basically is what I'm saying here which just go to it's pretty generally applicable advice
I'm just wondering if there's anything else I want to say about scallisy I think people who will like
it will like who like his comic novels will like this oh yeah did you say earlier that you thought
the plot was unambitious because I think that's part of my gripe with this that it is it is telling
a very a very dull story where everything falls in ways that are convenient
translation state is a novel that is set in the worlds of ancillary this that and the other
and follows I guess it picks up a thread from that trilogy which is about the Prescott translators
Prescott are aliens who are very much not like humans and their translators are very much
very sort of are the are how the the Meskidism that the Prescott used to talk to people and so
this novel we've said the stories of a of a person who has spent their life up to this point
caring for their dead grandmother and is then thrown out of the home they lived in and told to go
solve a mystery of a missing Prescott translator a Prescott translator who you meet as a juvenile
and then learn about their how they grew up and then another character and these three stories
are told chapter by chapter and they are all entwined and I like this a lot and I the one of the
problems where you get stories where you have three different narrators is that one of the
one of the tales is told in first person the other two or a third person one of the things
with stories with three different narrators is often you find you want to read one of them more
than the others and one of them slightly more interesting than the other two but I actually
enjoyed all three of these strands I enjoyed the way they all came together I enjoyed learning more
about the Prescott translators who were even weirder that I had thought and yeah I like I'm
lucky I feel like she can do no wrong maybe like her books there's a lot here about identity and
autonomy and I like all that stuff which I like novels that talk about it a lot and deal with it
and it does a lot of that I observed that there was a weird running around the maze
a maze section later in the book and I wasn't quite sure what it was for and John said it's
allegorical in it and it obviously is this is a standalone novel it probably helps if you've read
the ancillary trilogy wouldn't have thought so but it might be wrong I mean maybe I forgot most
of it so I have I had forgotten most of it because I forget most of all of books it will at the very
least spoil the ancillary novels if you read this one first then you plan to go back so don't
yes that's true yeah so read a first if you're going to I quite like to translation state I think
all of the characters are interesting in their own ways and the novel had a lot to say about
boundaries which I found really interesting I think it's in some ways this is another novel that
may be very angry with one of the secondary characters who spawns about like she owns the
place and I just want to punch her in the face which is lovely I thought that it was a very
believable portrayal of two people where you can see that they are thinking things that are compatible
but neither of them thinks the other is thinking that I really liked that I think this is probably
actually my favorite of her book so far but I really liked it also the grandmother sounded
awful I did enjoy this book but that's because I bought my copy of this book while I was shopping
in California with John last year hey and therefore it's a nice memory of that and all the advice we
gave to that man who was second handbook shopping at the same time as us yeah and made him buy stuff
other than that yeah I think I think you've got a lot of it I think I like it a bit less than you
because I think it gets not bogged down especially but okay so I really love the preska because they
are so stupendously alien in in some ways I think it's a really I often complain about books where
the aliens are not alien enough and I think the preska do a great job of just like their children
being so unsettling these juveniles and so then you do get this idea of why people are like okay
we can't have preska juveniles you know just running around because they are incredibly dangerous
and don't know what they're doing can I clarify preska translated juveniles yes sorry preska
translated juveniles and I think the problem is that you know from the start how these three people
are going to converge basically you know within like a couple of chapters what's going on and
then it takes a little while to get them all into place and then there's quite a long stretch where
I suspect I just didn't gel with this as much as you did but like we end up with two of the
characters basically going through puberty together hiding under a blanket and there's some interesting
stuff but the voices of them are incredibly teenage and I've found this a bit in other lecke
novels that sometimes I feel like the character voices are very much younger than I think the
characters actually are and this doesn't quite work for me and so once we got to that point I
was kind of like okay I'm enjoying the character building but can we kind of move it forward a bit
please that's fair so I think what I'm saying is I would like this book but I would maybe shrink
it by a third and speed up the bits I didn't enjoy as much as the other bits but the bits I did
enjoy I really enjoy I mean I really love like the first 60 pages I thought this is going to be
amazing and then it didn't quite pull it off so so you so the blanket bits didn't really work for
you and the maze bits didn't really work for me guys guys guess which bits were my favorite bits
Liz Liz has given me a look at Alice it is until he's eloited I really like the maze and part of
this is because I really like that kind of like it reminded me a lot of like cosmic horror in a way
like which is a genre I adore and it kind of like you know what you see is not quite what you see
and there are things happening that you don't really understand because they're happening in
a dimension you can't really perceive and I was like oh I like this bit big good and it was also a
metaphor for the maze of their relationship and I was like oh she's bloody gone and done it
a cosmic horror metaphor oh John is just the happiest man alive now bloody lover cosmic horror
metaphor to talk about relationships and feelings and things but I like this one yeah I mean I do
think that is one of leckeys I'm gonna say strengths but I think it's almost spawned like an entire
I think like subgenre of space opera where we also have feelings yes one like because I don't
think you can have Becky Chambers without translation state not translation state without
ancillary justice like I just don't I don't think you can have a memory when we call
Empire without it either no yeah yeah you know I think ancillary justice was an incredibly
important novel in our field it's one of the ones where everything we're reading now
owes a huge debt to that novel yeah yeah like june harley I think I see it in like alia
deboto stuff and I do genuinely like it I think I just have a slightly lower tolerance for feelings
and so sometimes there's too much feelings I want the right amount of feelings no yeah I get it I
completely get it I can see one of the things and I think we'll come back to this later but one of
things I really like about this short list is that it is six novels all of whom feel quite different
from one another in ways they have like shared themes but like I think this book does what it's
doing really well and I don't think any of the other books on the short list are trying so much
except maybe the test which we might come on to in a bit yeah now I think of the six books this
might be the one that fills its brief best for me oh yeah which is not doesn't mean that it's
going to be top of my list spoilers because I think it's briefest maybe somewhat less exciting
than a couple of the other novels on the list so whichever ones we've got left right
but but I think it's actually you know it feels very very very well put together
in lots of different ways yeah it's very accomplished very I think even and definitely from a novelist
who knows what they are doing and is doing it I agree with that
Saint of Bright Doors is the first novel from Vajra Chanda Sakera is another kind of fancy
novel but maybe not it's basically the main character is Feta who is a child who was raised
essentially to kill his father who is a saint and we sort of follow his fairly meandering journey
around the world interacting with his father and his father's enormous cult he moves to a city
called Luriat where he you know encounters bureaucracy gets involved with the arts I should
also say that Feta can see a whole bunch of invisible devils that no one else can see and is basically
trying to hide his is true nature a lot of the time Luriat is a city where there are the the
bright doors which just kind of appear out of nowhere mysterious portals it kind of follows Feta
through honor as I say sort of slightly meandering maybe not super obvious storyline but which
feels comes to a very like satisfying ending somehow that's not a great description but I find
this one quite hard to describe it's not as simple as xyz things happen this is the ending
it's like it does not do what you expect I think if I was going to describe this book I would say
it's about a man who is grappling with the expectations of his parents and the ways in which he reacts
to those expectations the ways in which they intersect with other people's expectations of him
and the ways in which he feels he has not lived up to those expectations or all lived up to them
I think it's a very personal story where the the real the thing that happens is really all
infectors it's not I don't mean to say it's imaginary but like the arc of the book is very much
in Feta like what's happening around him is is almost secondary to what's happening to him
if that makes any sense at all but I agree it's hard to summarize I really what things I've really
really liked about this level I really like the city I really like the sense that we were
that Feta has this enormous weight when we said he was honed honed to kill his father I think by
his mother I think is not yeah too much of a spoiler you discover this very early in the book
and you know I can I can see why this is like a lot particularly good ex-relationship
but he goes off to a city and the city has other people who are like him in that they are
semi saintly or they have they are touched by the world it's not around us and also lots of
people are particularly ordinary and so whenever Feta has a conversation with one of those people
that touches on any of this they're just kind of assuming that he is talking in metaphors it has
a section where he wanders around amaze for some time unable to get out which is probably a
metaphorical allegory for his mental state which I thought was quite interesting that we have two
books on the shortlist that have that section is it yeah having read it and going oh this is this
is just a book full of full of wonders there are so many wonders packed into this level I do
not know what to think I read reviews as I do and one of them was like this is just a
foundational myth of Buddhism and here is here is how it works and here are all the parallels
and another review that said hey you know you you people who are lapping this book up you think
this city is so amazing but it is just Colombo and I'm like well there are plenty of people who
write novels set in London but nevertheless do not manage to catch what is magical about London I
don't think that's necessarily a problem but so that's one of the things that this this is this
is a myth retelling and some of that tentativeness about Feta's possible destiny is actually matched
in the story that this is this is building on I thought it was all very good except I don't know
if it completely hangs together as well as it might do I found some of the bits a bit weird it's
got a bit of a first novel feeling it to it it feels like it could have had numerous less elements
in it and still been a fully full novel but I really enjoyed it really liked really liked that
it tried to do a lot of stuff I like novels that have too much of them that's probably not a
lot of surprise to anyone just listen to this podcast my opinion of this book is that it is
I liked it a lot I think it is a very very good debut novel I think that as Alison says it has
lots of things in it I don't think they quite all care here this is tricky because I don't think I
need my secondary world fantasy to be I don't need to know all the rules and I don't need them to be
explicitly laid out but I do need the rules that are mentioned to intersect with the plot and I found
the central bright doors kind of I wish there I wish they had either been in it more or less I
think I was like vaguely dissatisfied when I got to the end and I was like oh like that was that one
thing that happened and it's like I understand why but you could have told the exact same story
and did not have the doors in it and I'm like the doors are really cool but they're completely
extraneous to the story and I don't know I think you know his second or third novel he will have
really cool things that weave into the texture of the plot he's telling in a way that I think will
enjoy even more and I'm very much looking forward to that novel and it's a very nitpicky criticism
but I just like I said I got to the end and I just didn't quite feel like it all carehered
in a way that it could have done I also thought the ending was rubbish felt the last two chapters
felt like an entirely different novel to me and not in a good way it felt very passive and
for a novel based so much in the emotional arc of its main character the disinterest in the main
character shown by the novel in the last stages is genuinely baffling to me oh but I really I mean
I really not knowing this is the foundational myth of Buddhism or not realizing it well enough I
really enjoyed the last two chapters as I thought they really put it together because I thought it
was kind of all about how fetters journey kind of is maybe a little bit passive and he's kind of
earned that right to sort of step away from this defined path to you know you are you have
informed as a weapon to kill your father to to basically go away from all that don't he's waving
his arms at me but I don't think he does step away from it I think I think something else happens
that mean he doesn't that means he doesn't take any active he just sort of drifts and the whole
novel is about him drifting in expectation and I thought what he was realizing at the end of the
novel was that he could have his own path and then at the end it it very much feels like the book
doesn't want to explore that and it didn't not explore it in an interesting way to me yeah I
think I would have to go back and read the last two chapters again but I think it is just I was
reading the same thing and interpreting it in different ways oh yeah that's bad which is nice
you're nice buddha's child referred to as rahula as a feta since it was tied to tied him to the
earthly plane and prevented him from achieving enlightenment or could do that's that's that's
that's the link yeah I mean I'm aware of that I'm not sure we need to give people a primer on but
it's mythology indeed because we aren't very much not the people to do that
definitely I would also like to say I think so this is we've called historical fantasy
well we call it the sort of secondary world fantasy of colombo um but it it's not because
this is a city where we have plagues and pandemics and quarantine hotels and he ends up in refugee
camps and giant quarantine camps and so on so it is very much I really like how it kind of straddles
that being a secondary world fantasy but it's like explicitly almost tied into hours I thought
it did a good job of that I don't mean to imply that it's not talking about things that happen in
our world I just meant like it's clearly not set in our world but it does it like you said it does
a very good job of dealing with some of the same stuff that our world has to deal with I did like
that about it yeah I just mean kind of like talked about historical fantasy is one that books on the
shortlist a kind of full secondary world fantasy which as far as I've got does not kind of pull
in anything from our world and this one which is clearly like a mirror of current issues does that
make sense johnson like think he eyes I think it makes sense I don't the reason I think historical
fannet all right this is a genre debate of doom Liz uh strap in oh dear oh dear historical fantasy
is urban fantasy from before the 20th century an urban fantasy is first world fantasy in the 20th
century so historical fantasy is first world fantasy a while back this is secondary world fantasy
because it's not urban fantasy which is but I don't think I've never thought of secondary world
fantasy as not being able to pull whatever it wants from our world but like this this book is
not set in Yorkshire it's set in Luria uh in a world where the land has literally been reshaped
and it's like but I think that's all I mean by that I never thought of secondary world fantasy as
implying a divide in terms of like the themes you could cover or the bits of our world you could
bring in like I would argue Brandon Sanderson's Mistborn is a secondary world despite the fact
like he imports the industrial revolution does that make sense so it yeah that does make sense
and I mean I think things like Adrian Tricoski's like uh was it House of Open Wounds is also
clearly bringing in that industrial revolution a fantasy setting and yet I would still say it was
secondary world fantasy I just think there's something about the Saint-Brite doors that feels
like it is more inflected with our world than a lot of the others are yes I I read this as a
renamed fantasy colombo rather than rather than a city entirely built you know an entirely
secondary world city that shares that has some features in common with colombo yeah I don't know
if there's any real difference between those two things I feel there is because I don't agree with
you but I mean it's like if you have a fantasy city and you have a square that's exactly that's
obviously Trafalgar Square I'd be kind of going oh no this is really just an inflected
it's an urban fantasy that is an inflected London yeah once again having never been to colombo I
think that's something I have to leave for others to debate how closely this is actually related to
it listeners if you have opinions on genre right in you know we're gonna have we're getting so many
letters at this point to John not to me right to John and tell him it's on a metaphor I maintain
that genre is just vibes this I guess I guess this and that actually it's six what Lizzie is saying
is because what I think what Lizz might be saying is that this has first world fantasy vibes yes I
think maybe yeah I think it's got maybe it's got portal fantasy vibes oh yes like someone has
stepped through a portal from our world through some kind of door maybe maybe the doors are a metaphor
well there was one point what I was reading so I was going oh those doors are actually going to be
the our world portal doors but they aren't so you know now that'd be way too obvious for this book I think
and the last book is Some Desperate Glory by Emily Tesh this is a book about a teenage girl who is
very angry at a lot of things and she has been raised in a small space station which is very
focused on fostering a sense of community among its residents in a way that makes the people who
run it happy and the way I've described that listeners it may not surprise you to learn that a
objective reading of what is happening will be slightly less wholesome than I made it sound and
she goes on an adventure then a series of things happen none of which I really expected at any
point now again this is one of my patented very unhelpful things this is future no for future
ochre thoughts we have to stop letting John's summarize novels but it's very funny did you say
it is funny or it isn't funny I said it's but I find it very funny I think we should let John
do it yeah it is a lot of your jokes I don't find funny but this one I do find quite funny
alternatively we could just let John do all the novel summarizations in future one of those
though I think that might get wearing I think for me this book so this book feels to me like a
rejoinder to Old Man's War in a way and I and other books but especially Old Man's War in that it is
a book that makes you really think about the question but what if we're the bad guys and also
makes you think about very difficult questions of like in some ways it's trolley problem the novel
and but it does it in a much more interesting way than that description makes it sound and I
I found it absolutely fascinating and very thought-provoking and I enjoyed the heck out of it especially
how angry it made me because I've mentioned that a couple of the other novels here make me angry
with the way that power is abused but in this novel all it made me cross I like you just you get
I just it was so good it was like electrifying I read the whole thing in a state of some
dismay but it was good dismay and I enjoyed it really really a lot good what did you guys think
did you hate it am I wrong no I agree with you hey super good I think it's better than a memory
called Empire I will say I think because I've memory called Empire I mean I assume I've said
this on the podcast but like if not I think it's a masterpiece but I think this is like this is
one of the best pieces I've read in ages I loved it okay so this novel starts off with a very
a story you will have read a lot of times before which is somebody who is being trained to be a
a genius basefaring weapon blaster and immediately subverts that so it starts off
and then it and then you start to gather the tool is not what it seems and and then it
so the the heroine gets off planet and then you discover it's really not what it seems
and then it takes an immense turn to the left because it does it does quite a lot of things
with structure as well it's just an is an extremely accomplished first novel and I think it's very
good and I liked it a lot but yes it is you dialogue not merely with Old Man's War which in itself
was trying to pick up some of the themes of classic science fiction but with all those novels of
classic science fiction and I think one of the things that's very good about this book is that if
you've never read any of those novel those classic science fiction novels then then you will start
eating this up enjoying it and only gradually will you will you gather that that you are being
fed you're being spelled a lie in the same way that the heroine is and I you know it's very very
good again I'm not 100% certain I it nailed the ending but again first novel what is the more
bi-emily tesh I think we've got a novella we have a novel is it I'll die is it her first
level at all there's an award-winning duology of fantasy novellas bi-emily tesh I believe this
is her first novel yeah there's there's novellas and I think we had them in previous Hugo Pax
when she was up for the astounding and people have been telling me to read tesh for a little while so
sorry guys I had not previously read any Emily tesh it's very good it's a very good book yeah I
don't I don't think either of you've got over kind of just how much ends up being packed into this
novel it is like a yeah this could be five novels yeah I read a lot of mediocre YA novels where like
you can see how this would be chunked up into a trilogy which is you know Kia the main character
spends the first book coming to the realization that maybe like the society of space vera she has
been raised in is not entirely telling the truth but then it turns out that when they said oh yeah
there's like an AI supercomputer which has decided to destroy the earth that's not allowing
there really is an AI supercomputer which is essentially decided the earth must be destroyed
yeah you know it's it's it's not it's not like everything they have told her it's a lie it's that
some of the things they have told her a lies but some of the things they have told her are the
truth and she has to decide how she feels about that and so I think it's got a lot to say using
that to jump off about free will and the choices we make and the choices we are forcing to and
I'm sorry talking about like the first third of the book because there's only 130 000 words so
it's 20 000 words shorter than Amina which is absolutely baffling now I've said out loud and
the end of part two of the novel so the novel split into five parts and at the end of part two
the reveal there could have like in a lot of stories would have been the end of the first book
and then we would have had to wait for book two so the fact that it was like I could I was not
sure where it was going and because I was expecting the story not to do anywhere near as much as it was
it was genuinely exciting to me that it went there so quickly and in that way it felt a bit like
the good place where the good place very often made decisions and resolved them a lot more
quickly than you'd expect from the type of thing it was and it was really refreshing because
you meant you never quite certain what they'd do next because they were subverting your expectations
on like a a level of the underlying structure and this does a similar thing the fact it deals with
similar themes and I think looks at those themes in as much if not more detail is just icing on
the incredible cake because I love like it really wants you to think about how your access to
information and your upbringing affect what it is you think is right and how you act and it does
that through showing you and it's not until the very end that it starts putting those pieces together
in a really masterful way as a debut novel I mean I know she's written two novellas so like it's a
little bit cheating for this to be a debut novel because two novellas could be a novel you just cut
it in half in the middle right but it's so good like it's so good very excited very excited to read
more of her stuff um this is the only novel that appears both on the hugo shortlist and the
Clark shortlist which I thought was interesting so Clark judge is liked it it is all three fair
there's three books on this list I would say clearly fantasy so yep and I was not expecting
the Clark judge just to pick starter villain well I wanted to say is yes more of what John was
saying which is it feels like it is a book like shorter than me and else raffy but managed to do
as much kind of character work as that and cram in a whole load of plot and world building
all into one like it doesn't feel like it takes any time and that's quite it's quite a feat because
your main character that you are dealing with at the start is a terrible person who is going to
have to go through this journey to becoming a less terrible awful person and kind of overcome
the upbringing she's had but it doesn't feel awful to kind of spend this time in her company at the
start which it really easily could have so I think it's also yeah just nicely written in that way
I do like books that paste like novels rather than paste like the first volume of a
n-volume series and I think this novel does that I would not I would certainly not like it as much
if it'd be spun out into three or four books which it as you say it probably could have been
but I don't think it is paste like a novel and that's what works so well about it I think it's
paced so much quicker that's what novels are paced like I think you're occluding what makes this
novel special by saying all novels are like this and I don't think that's because I don't think
this would work anywhere near as well if it was true I am saying something savage about the current
state of the genre in that so much of the stuff is massively padded and this one isn't but I think
books historically are not so padded this novel does do this very well okay as well as that and
that is why I will put it at the top of my list have we got to the end of the six novels now
and that was the old thought podcast no we have to do the rankings listeners
who wants to do their ranking first I think this is a good list I think you know there are
there are a couple of novels that aren't really to our taste but that's not because
they're clearly novels that are to quite a lot of people's taste have John and Liz persuaded me
I think I'm still going to put the same to bright doors top just squeaking out some desperate glory
I think some desperate glory will probably win I think a lot of people think it's very good and
they are probably right to do that but I think I personally enjoyed said to dry doors a bit more
translation staked third witch king fourth adventures of a meaner al-Sarafi fifth and starter villain
sixth Liz what was your list I previously had the saint of bright doors at the top but I think
now we've just discussed some desperate glory again I might have convinced myself to put with
the way around it's close isn't it I mean for me I think the thing is the top two are way ahead of
the others because I didn't like translation state quite as much as you guys did so it's
definitely I think some desperate glory and then saint of bright doors those two may change depends
on my mood next time I fill out my ballot then I mean pending pending how much I like witch king
but I think it's probably going to be translation state I mean as of else a ventures of a meaner
al-Sarafi then witch king then starter villain but basically the top two might flip third fourth
and fifth place is might flip around a bit and sixth place is sixth place here are my picks for
this year so we have some desperate glory in first place and then we have translation state
because I do think translation state sticks the ending better than saint of bright doors I'm afraid
which is why it's in third I'll put the witch king above adventures of a meaner al-Sarafi
above star villain that would be my selection the witch king and adventures of meaner al-Sarafi
those two are the closest together for me and what does that make the consensus ranking
I mean I think some guess what glory comes first right because two of us have put it in the top
place and then I think it's probably saint of bright doors next because that's the next highest
for me in al-Sar and then I think it's translation state in third and then I think it's witch king
and then adventures and then starter villain which I think these none of us have picked the average
octa-thorp listing this time so the first year it was allison the second time it was Liz
this time it's no one one day I will be our fridge listeners but this is not that day and that was
the octa-thorp podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
do we want to do things that should have been on there oh no we've gone on frages let's stop there
I mean let's have a conversation about it when we see the long list oh we'll be able to analyze
the long list on sunday night at Glasgow ready to talk about it on the product one day lunchtime
if we get to have a lunchtime slot I'm not sure I want to yeah I can see the peel but I think I
might want to get the pod done before the hugo is possibly anyway the theme music for this episode
was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in competec.com used under a creative commons
attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]