Let's just go through them. Let's just go through them. Let's just go through them, but skip found artists because they're doing you both staring at me.
Yeah, don't fair enough. I'm 100% Switzerland on the artist.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 93rd episode of Octo the Wop, a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom, which is coming to you on the 28th of September in 2023.
I am John Coxon.
Hi, I'm Alison Scott.
And I am Liz Batty.
And finally, finally, we have the response we've all been waiting for listeners.
"The match will be occurring. Abigail Nussbaum says..."
Apologies for not responding in a more timely fashion to your proposed cage match between myself and Chris Garcia.
Now I know that being O'Koron on the podcast is essential for matters of honor, I will be sure never to make such a mistake again.
As for Chris's challenge, I naturally accept and expect the organizing committee or ever come we both happen to find ourselves at next to spring's action in arranging cage, referee, medical assistance, etc. Best Abigail.
Hoorah! It shall occur.
Let's get this happening people.
"Strongly suspect the next convention with both Abigail and Chris is Glasgow in 2024. That's the gauntlet for you, Esther."
Do we know anyone on the programme team for Glasgow?
So, if this does occur, I would like to be the like Ringmaster.
Is that what it's called in cage fighting?
I want to be the person yelling in the blue corner with several phransines.
You don't want to be the Ringmaster, do you? Because the Ringmaster is like the referee and you're what to be the announcer.
Oh, I don't want to be... Well, I could be the referee as long as both of them are not to country.
I would like to get the number of trists, so you could be the referee, John. I'll be the announcer.
Listeners, write in with suggestions for a neutral referee to referee this Abigail Chris cage match.
You can volunteer yourself if you like.
Please come up with the person in fandom who is exactly the average of Chris Garcia and Abigail Nussbaum.
I'm not sure they even have referees in cage fighting. I have to say, I don't know very much about cage fighting,
but I thought part of the point was that there are lots of rules and they just kind of shove them in the cage and let them get on with it.
Well, you were the one who brought up refereeing. I just want to do the shouting. And I stand by it.
Chris says that he's going to buy me a photographer's vest, Ruby sunglasses and cigarette holder, and from this point forward, I shall be set on the S-Coxon, which...
Mmm. It's very kind of you, Chris. Liz, do you want a... I'm going to have a photographer's vest. I'm looking to get rid of. Do you want one of those?
No, I mean, maybe Allison needs it to take all our golf stuff on flights with low-looking limits.
Hehehehehe.
The really funny thing about this is that Liz wasn't in the chat I did yesterday about the 7 kilogram carry-on limit that I technically have on my trip to Australia
and the fact that my carry-on bag cannot possibly weigh less than 7 kilograms.
It does seem quite harsh.
You know, people pack for a week in a carry-on bag with a 7 kilogram weight limit, and I can't pack for 24 hours on a plane.
Well, that's just how that goes, right?
I mean, fundamentally, the problem is that I do not want to put my laptop into check baggage and I do want to take my iPad on the flight with me in between them.
No, that is, I mean, that is, both of those are entirely fair. I would not want my laptop.
In fact, I'm not sure if you're allowed to have your laptop in check baggage because it's got battery in it, but yeah, foreshadowing.
And then he also notes he's never heard "Espanar Sheriff, future host of the Anger Locust podcast origin story."
So he enjoyed that.
We've got a lot of people saying it was nice serious, "Espanar on the pod." I'm glad everyone liked it.
We'll have to put Stephen on the pod sometime.
Yes, he also notes the Hugo packet is now complete, and this is true, so "Ersatz Culture" noted in 5/7.
I mean, I think I'll try and dig out the link.
But the fanzine and fan writer categories have now gone live after they were made live unofficially, so it feels like that might have been the impetus that the world come needed to get their act together.
But yes, so Chris also reports that Hugo packet is now complete.
And then we got a toot of comment from "Ersatz Culture" who told us we've been name-checked on Chinese social media by Arthur Liu.
And this was very good because I opened the page and obviously most of the posts that Arthur did was in Chinese, but the two phrases that leapt out at me was the word "oxo thought" and the phrase "chengdu" is a shower.
And so we have become a term of art in Chinese fandom, which is very pleasing. And we will discuss why now.
The thing about the explanation that "chengdu" is a shower is that Arthur says, um, by which they mean that "chengdu" is a showy peacock who claims all sorts of wonders for the world come but doesn't deliver.
And that's not quite what the etymology is, but there we go.
I think it's because he's reading it as "chengdu" is a "shower".
Like a show-off?
It basically gets to what it is we're talking about, I think, just from a different route.
Who wants to talk about what happened?
I listened to do ask Arthur what he meant, or are you just doing it from Google Translate?
That's from a machine translation.
Errrr!
But I think so, "Ersatz Culture" in the two did, um, did note that they had emailed Arthur to say that "chengdu" is a shower recur, refers to a shower of "encompetive" and that's not a shower.
But it's just a shower of incompetence rather than someone that shows off.
I think that was a slight misconception.
But only very slightly because I think the fact that "chengdu" doesn't have a lot of substance behind quite a lot of things that it's doing, and that is quite worrying at this stage, which is, you know, we're only kind of a month, four weeks out from the convention now, um, is kind of worrying.
We don't have much time to, we're gonna have to move into "chengdu" was a shower, and that "chengdu" is a roaring success.
I hope they're not, because we'd have to redraw the art.
What the discussion has been referring to is that it looks like "chengdu" have stopped selling, attending memberships. Sorry, attending tickets.
And it is quite close to the con, so you'd expect them to have some kind of cut-off date, but it sounds like there were people who had applied for fan tables, and they didn't know kind of how many people they'd need, and so they were holding off actually, like, getting tickets.
And now they may not be able to get tickets, or they may be able to get tickets, but they'll have to buy date tickets instead, which could be a bit more hassle.
But it seems like they have kind of unexpectedly stopped ticket sales without warning anyone, and you could understand if they may have, you know, stopped ticket sales in advance of the con, but you should probably let people know when you're gonna do that.
Yes, and it seems to have made a lot of people in Chinese fandom quite annoyed. So this isn't us.
This isn't us wondering whether or not we're applying our view of how it should work to a convention which is from a different culture.
This is people in that culture being annoyed by a thing the conventioners doesn't, uh, done and us reporting it, which I think is a, I think is a good distinction to draw.
Well, and also this didn't really annoy people in the West so much because nearly everyone who had any plans to go at all got their membership by voting last year or has made plans in advance, because obviously you'll have had to apply for your visa by now if you're going and things like that.
So, and there's not that many Western fans going, there are some. I hope you all have a lovely, lovely time. But it was just, I found it very nice that I went on a page of Chinese words and I saw Chengdu as a shower and I was like, ah, I've had an impact.
Anything else on Chengdu? There's a nice video of the building, which again I got from a South culture, are Chengdu chorus, Bondon? Yeah, and it looks a lot more finished than I could have done.
Given some of the shots we saw in kind of June, July, doesn't look finished, but it looks on the way. It's quite nice.
Reminds me a bit of the new mall and train station they built near the World Trade Centre with big, swoopy ceilings.
Moving from one worldcon to another, I did a panel for Glasgow in 2024 and it was called "Glasco 2024 presents the media of storytelling, print versus screen".
And I was there with AM Justice and RWW Green and Dan Hanks, and it went quite well I think. It was interesting chat.
And I will put a link in the show notes if you would like to watch me moderating a panel or you would like to watch any of those three people being on a panel.
Hoorah. I want to go into a brief non-sequitur here, which is that I've also done "Pints of Science" quite a lot, which is where people go to a pub and they hear from scientists in the pub about their research specialties and you talk for about, I don't know, 15 minutes on your research.
Maybe, maybe a bit long. And then people can ask questions and it's good. But one of the things that has become very obvious over the course of Pina of Science is that the people you're talking to is people that already like science.
And so although it's very good for them, it doesn't really help like get the word out about science, particularly because you're talking to people who already have what is called in public engagement circles.
Science capital, that is people who are already invested in and know a lot about science. And I do have to wonder whether or not the Glasgow 2024 presents stream is not also talking to people who have what I would say is Worldcon Capital.
Or perhaps just Convention Capital. But I do wonder how far out of our bubble they break.
Well, what do we reckon? Well, I think these started as, and Glasgow was bidding during the pandemic and so they couldn't do bid parties. So they were looking for something that they could do that was not bid parties and they concluded that online events like panels and talks and
discussions and all sorts of things like that were a great alternative to bid parties for a convention that wasn't bidding. And the thing about bid parties that they are also preaching to people who are already familiar with Worldcon.
And I feel like this process has carried on from there, but it's also performing a function to maybe get less well known authors names out there and also to give people practice and things like being on a panel and panel moderation.
And Glasgow is doing quite a lot of good outreach in the Glasgow area. There are a lot of people actively involved in the convention who are not names that are familiar to me from UK fandom or World fandom more generally, but have got involved in fandom through Glasgow.
That's their entry point in to fandom. And I think that's pretty good. So I think that they're doing outreach in that way. I'm not sure that this particular thing is very outreachy.
But the thing about panels on the internet is that they kind of stay there forever. So one of these nearworthers that they, they're getting along now later becomes incredibly famous.
People will go off and find that stuff. So one of the things that I think we probably talked about this because we decided we're going to do it.
This year's EasterCon conversation recorded almost its entire program and we've had a sort of think about what we should do about that.
And the answer is that we are going to place it with two libraries is the attention, one of which is the South friction Foundation and one of which is phallac.org, not to be like put up on the internet, but to be available for academic research and things of that kind.
Yeah, no, that's a good point. That's a very good point. It is definitely true. I don't have a feel because I'm not like this is only the when London in 20 when black when London 2014 started rolling, which must have been like what 2009 ish.
I think I was still relatively new in fandom. So it is not clear to me how much of an impact London had because I didn't really have like a framework for how to compare it to.
Whereas it definitely seems like Glasgow is getting a lot of people into the community, which I think is like really great.
So yeah, that is a good point. And the point about them sticking around forever is also a very good point because it does, I think, it does give you like a loie-bree of things Glasgow has done that makes it clear that Glasgow is doing things, which I think is a good point.
I think it's like a good feeling to have about a world con and might be the diametric opposite of Chengdu in some ways.
I mean, all Chengdu are doing is building an entire new facility. Does that even count? But yeah, I'm not suggesting Glasgow build an entire new facility.
That'd be crazy. Chengdu does always give this feeling of being something that is not really of fandom in the way that science fiction conventions normally are.
So building a giant, a child facility and putting your tickets on ticket roster and things like that are kind of an examples of that.
That it's going to a slightly different crowd. But that's okay. That's that reach of a different sort.
I mean, I think we are clearly Chengdu has led to more interaction between Western SF fans and Chinese ones in all sorts of different places.
And that is absolutely great and probably worth all of the pay just for that really in the long run.
But then I'm not somebody who's trying to organise the trip of a lifetime to China at the moment.
To link it all together in a neat bow, that is something I've noticed like a lot of people coming into Glasgow are glass region people.
So it's quite nice that Glasgow is doing that for Glasgow as well. Everything's great.
It was a good, I did enjoy the panel. So that was also nice.
And my liaison, Pam Livingston, was an absolute star and she looked after me very, very well. So thank you very much, Pam. You were amazing.
I don't know, Pam listens, but if she does, she was amazing. And if she doesn't, she was still amazing.
Just one more loose thread for this. If people want to go to Pints of Science, which sounds like a fantastic thing, can you put something?
Because I think quite a lot of the people who admittedly have science capital but might like that sort of thing are science fiction fans.
Yes, yes, that is fair. I'll put link in the show notes. They tend to be in May.
So I've brought this up at almost the worst possible time being as how it is four months since May and eight months till next May.
It's fine. Our listeners are literally organised people and have calendars and consent reminders and we'll definitely not forget about this.
[Music]
So we should probably start by saying we're not going to talk about novel because we're going to do an entire episode on novel after the voting deadline.
What's your best pick in the Vella? Go.
Oh, we're doing it backwards. I've only read one of them so far.
Which one? Into the Riverlands. Any good?
Really disappointing actually. Boo.
Because the first one in the In The Only Vos series I really liked and picked as a pick and this one just doesn't add anything new.
I've read the first two and they're great but I haven't read the third one yet.
Alison, what are your novela reading?
My novelas are on my cobalt, all six of them ready for my 24 hour play journey. Gotta read them all on the plane.
Yeah, no, I also have not read. I've got a bit honest. My Hugo reading this year has been... I have not slacked but like, I just haven't got as far as I usually do. I'm not sure what.
So I've read any of the novelas or novelats. Have I either read any novelats?
I have read two of the novelats. I don't particularly want to vote for either of them so I hope one of the other four will get to be better.
I've read all the novelats except the space-time painter because it's not translated and I tried Google Translate and I think I'm missing lots.
Yeah, Google Translate's much better for non-fiction, for like, like, fancying content and report ours which is for fiction. I think it's really, really hard for fiction.
Yeah, no, the best one I think is probably the John Chew which I know John likes. I also write, you know, like, Marie Vibbot. Okay, those are two best ones.
Oh great, okay, so I think the John Chew is fine. I've... Whoa, wrong head.
I have a real problem with science fiction books that don't have science fiction content and...
It's got a Superman. When was the last time you met Superman, Alison?
No, no, no, and the Marie Vibbot is a science fiction story that doesn't have science fiction content. The science fiction content is entirely separate from the actual plot and consequences of this thing, which is about... Well, I mean, you know, it's a perfectly good story but it's...
But it's science fiction background is just window dressing for it.
I'm gonna be interested to see if you like the SL Huang which is kind of fiction in the form of a fake nonfiction article which links to lots of footnotes about real AI things in order to discuss AI.
And as a story, it's like, it's not a story and it kind of is like, well, I don't want to read a story which is full of footnotes about things I already know about because it just feels like, why am I reading this article telling me about, like, the heart bleed bug?
Whereas the science fiction. So I'm quite baffled by it's on the shortlist.
Well, you've got to remember, I think, novel and short stories both have, like, really long tales, don't they? So I think it can be that there's, like, 50 stories nominated and one or two nominations can take something up.
Yeah, that's true.
I have read, "If you find yourself speaking to God of Dress God with it, informal you, and I did enjoy it muchly, so, you know, I'll be happy to write for it.
I haven't read the others, but I do intend to read the others." On short story, the only one I've read was "Rabbit Test", which I thought the first half was superlative and the second half sort of just sort of peated out to a close.
Having said that, I haven't read the others. So, like, what do you think? I know Liz loved "Rabbit Test" if I recall.
I do think the first half is very good.
I've read 506 and "Rabbit Test" is the best.
I think "Rabbit Test" is like the gorilla in this category. Everyone thinks it's a shoe in. People think it is an outstanding story of its time.
Oh, it was okay. I'm probably - I'm hard to please. I'm sorry.
Siri, should we say a bit about Siri's? Because I feel a little bit more qualified to version Siri's than I normally have, as I have read books in four of the six things and, yeah, quite like them.
I think I've read the entire four of them and most of a fifth and nothing of a sixth, so it is very unusual for me.
What's getting your series, "Rabbit Jackson Bennett", because it's a Finnish series, so he's got no chance of being nominated for this again, and I really liked it, as mentioned many, many previous times.
I feel like, you know, Agent Tykofsky is bound to be back again with a different series.
I do feel a bit bad about Rivers of London because it's been nominated before, I think, and, you know, there's a gap before the next possible nomination, but it will be there, and the Naomi Novick is also in "Load Style".
I also - I probably think the founders' trilogy is the best one of those, but it's very tight.
So I quite like the Lock Tomb, even though it's not finished. We could always wait until it's finished and then vote for it once it's finished.
I don't think you can.
But next year is our chance to vote for Brits, so I think next year my ballot is going to be absolutely stuffed with British nominations and votes for British finalists because I am a terrible nationalist in this regard.
I don't think you can vote for the Lock Tomb again.
No, I think Liz is right, because I don't think there'll be enough extra words added.
So I think this is probably unless she writes a fifth novel, which I think would be a mistake.
Why can't I vote for the Lock Tomb again?
Because you have to have at least 200,000 words added, so unless the next volume is twice the length of the previous volumes, it won't be eligible next year.
In that case, I'm going to vote for the Lock Tomb, which I like quite a lot, even though, oh god known as a pile of poo, but never mind.
I will vote for the Children of Time, because it's the best one and you're the wrong edge.
Is that helpful?
Insightsive Criticism!
It's very good, it's going to be second on mine, so...
I am also halfway through Fandryside by Robert Jackson Bennett at Liz's Request, so my pick is just saying it does seem to be quite good, seems to be the sort of fantasy I like, and I am really loving it.
And also, after reading Hugo novels, reading something where somebody had put a lot of thought into world building was really a great tonic, and I like that.
Because there's a lot of world building in this novel.
For Shadowing for Next Episode.
Yes.
I will say, so I'm going to say something which sort of foreshadows our novel discussion.
So put it this way, I think Fandryside and I think Children of Time are way better than anything that's in the novel category this year.
Is that unreasonable?
Like, if I was looking, reader, listener, for the best science fiction that is on the Hugo Ballot this year, I think two of the best science fiction are in series, and I think probably none of the best science fictions are in novel.
So, that's like a hot take.
Yeah, okay, that's our hot take.
Series, the good thing about the Hugos.
No!
*laughs* However, not a great year for novel.
And then, graphic story.
I've not read any of the graphic stories in this category, but I'm going to pontificate anyway.
I've read previous installments of Once in Future, Monstrus and Saga, and I do not understand.
Like, they're just not very good, and like, ch-pfft.
This is the category every year that I'm like, I don't understand what the Hugo Electric sees in any of these.
Like, I read quite a lot of comics, but like, these are not my comics.
So, I feel like, to the point where I'm like, maybe I just- maybe this isn't the category I should pay attention to, because like, clearly I am so out of step with what the Hugo Electric thinks about this art form that is not useful for me to try and chime in.
What did you guys think? Either of you read any of these?
I've read one of them.
Was it good?
Which is Once in Future?
I mean, I like it, so yes.
I think it's a bit of a step up from the first three volumes, because it's where things start to come together a bit.
I sort of like a planned five volume sequence. It gets less episodic.
I think like the character relationships, particularly between Duncan and his grandmother are quite well done and quite coming together.
And I like how colourful the art is in a lot of kind of the other world bits with the knights.
I do think if you haven't read One, Two and Three, you're going to be totally baffled by Volume 4, but could be the same for Selma Monstrus.
I have one comment on the graphic novel's shortlist, which is that I look at something called Dune, the official movie graphic novel.
And it strikes me that the amount of weight this is carrying from previous texts is so great.
And the likelihood that this is just pictures of the scenes from the movie rendered in graphic novel form seemed very great to me.
And it seems unlikely that it's going to be a shining example of the genre.
And if I'm wrong about that, I'm very sorry guys.
Right, best related work.
Terry Pratchett One's going to win. Haven't read any of them.
Any further comments on this?
I will read the Terry Pratchett One because I am very interested to read it.
And Blood, Sweating, Chrome. I feel like if any of the others are going to win.
Why is it pending? I don't know.
So I guess I'm discussing all of this as if the main voting block is going to be Western.
But obviously if the main voting block is Chinese, there is a quite significant chance that Chinese science fiction and oral history Volume 1 might take the prize.
Is that book in English?
I don't think it is, but I might be wrong.
Because I'm quite interested in Chinese science fiction and oral history. That would be really interesting to read, wouldn't it?
And also I note that it's published by Chengdu Chimes Press.
So it might have a home-field advantage even beyond just being Chinese.
But what I don't know, looking at the nominations, what I can't tell is whether or not the number of Chinese nominators was higher than the number of Western nominators, but they nominated more widely.
Or whether it's lower.
Because I think you could explain the nominations either way.
And so I'll be fascinated to see how much of an effect it has at the voting.
But yes.
I don't suppose it will win, but I want to have a little nod for Buffalo Leto World Outreach Project.
Because I think the actual model there, where you take something and you try to put it into as many human languages as you possibly can.
It's really quite interesting.
I don't know how many languages it's in a lot.
Many.
It's a nice project.
Should I give it a hugo for having a lot of translations?
I don't know.
I mean I also argue that is noticeable for its, you know, primarily for its fictional texts.
And so you have to be awarding them aspects of it, which are not the fictional text.
And so for the Buffalo Leto Project, all I can, you know, vote for is, you know, well done, you go, it translated.
I cannot tell if any of the translations are high quality translations.
Are they well done?
Did they add something?
Can just say, well done, it's been translated.
Yeah.
That is fair.
I feel, that's the problem, right?
I feel spectacularly unqualified to make a judgement as to how notable it is.
In some ways.
I keep thinking about, there are a lot of countries in which there's essentially no science fiction.
I'm not sure whether this is necessarily the best thing to get translated into those languages, but anything that we can do to get SF to people who literally aren't reading any of it because there is none is a good thing in principle.
Yes, I think, I think I agree with that.
Best dramatic presentation, I would argue that this is another category that has some of the best science fiction on this ballot in it.
And I think those two things are severance and everything everywhere all at once.
And those will be at the top of my ballot, very, very closely followed by turning red and distantly trailed by Black Panther II and Avatar II.
What do you think?
I absolutely agree with that, except go on, severance or everything everywhere all at once.
We discussed this already, I'm very definitely on the severance train, and I think you are on the everything everywhere train.
Dithering a bit, yeah.
It'll be those two, haven't decided yet.
Right.
I would rather, I think I would rather severance win it because everything everywhere got an Oscar.
So I kind of think it's already doing well enough, whereas I'd quite like severance to get more recognition.
And I know that's a daft way of framing it, but that's just how it is in my head.
Shout out to Cora Bula here, who said that she hadn't watched severance because she doesn't really like office dramas.
And Cora, I'm sorry for telling tales out of school, but that is one of the biggest laughs I've had this year, so, you know, it got on the pot.
Liz, where are you on that?
I'm probably with John in that I don't know if everything everywhere all at once needs more awards, and it is really good, but I like severance a lot as well.
I haven't got round to watching Nope, which is the one I hope to get to before the deadline.
I think Nope is very, very good, but it is not as, it is worse.
Jordan Pills films have been going down in quality, which is to say he's been going from like a five out of five to a 4.75 out of five to a four and a half out of five.
So that he's still maintaining an astonishingly high quality, but I will say like if you've seen Get Out, if you'd put Get Out below severance, you can safely put Nope below severance.
And if you've seen, if you haven't seen Get Out, watch Get Out instead of watching Nope Get Out is amazing.
That is the Coxon view.
Yeah, I think it's a tough year.
Like I can see you in which Nope might be the front runner.
Yeah, I mean, I was annoyed. I can't remember what Get Out lost to when it was on the ballot, but I, um, I thought Get Out deserved a Hugo like unequivocally.
I just thought it was an absolute masterpiece.
So, um, and I do think that's why I said like, I think this is one of the categories where the quality in this category is top notch.
And the other one where the quality is super high, I think, is best dramatic presentation short form in which I will be voting for Andor and Andor.
Mmm.
Which way round am I putting the Andors? It's the question I find myself.
I feel very embarrassed about this because I have not yet watched for all mankind and I think it's probably very good indeed because it's got a relatively small audience and nevertheless it's getting, it's finding its way onto the ballot.
But yeah, one way out for me, Rick's Road is definitely below one way out, which is I think, oh, I just thought it was fantastic.
That's fair. Liz, what do you reckon?
I'm just looking at what Get Out lost to.
Wonder Woman.
It lost to what?
Yeah, no, fuck that. Like, I was outraged at the time and I was still outraged.
Get Out is in every way a better movie than Wonder Woman and everyone who voted for Wonder Woman should be ashamed of themselves.
Mike dropped from the job.
Done.
So one way out is the Andor episode where they have the chanting one way out and Rick's Road is the end episode.
They are both fantastic.
I genuinely, it might come down to just how I'm feeling on the day.
And then I think probably, I think, I've not seen Stranger Things for, and I don't think I've gotten up to Stranger in a Strange Land for a Mankind.
So I'll probably put Balanzashi's next.
But I'd be astounded if Andor doesn't win it.
This is another one where if Andor doesn't win it, I will be ashamed of the Hugo Electric.
It'll be another Get Out here for me.
I've seen them all and Andor is the best.
You say for all mankind must be great, but it's pretty good, but with some really annoying things in it.
But it does appeal absolutely directly to, you know, space program nerds.
So that's it.
Okay.
So that's why it's going to go the Hugo Ballad is that space program nerds really like it.
And there's a lot of those.
It's pretty good.
And it has some great episodes, although I don't think they're not one nominated this year.
It's as good as one last year.
But once it's got momentum, it's going to be on there.
I think it's third or fourth best on that list.
I think for mankind is not as good at the expanse.
I don't know how common that opinion is.
Well, we are very bogged down in the expanse.
Yeah, they're different.
We kind of watch an episode and go, "Oh, we really like that."
And then we watch the next one and then we go, "Oh, this episode is in fact,
this episode is entirely political manipulations that are not obviously forwarding the science
fiction of Bitsons plot."
If you feel that way about the expanse, I am now extremely curious how you will feel
about for mankind.
And I love for mankind.
One thing I will say about it, which is why I like it less than the expanse, is that
several of the scenes I have to watch by being in a different room and hearing the TV because
I can't actually watch them because they are too excruciating.
And I find it incredibly difficult to actually watch.
It's a very intense show for me.
For all mankind.
Yes, for all mankind.
You have to watch it from another room.
Wow, okay.
The bit where I can't say it, but there are, in every episode there is usually at least
one sequence where a character does something and I can see how it's going to go and I'm
like, "I can't watch this happen."
What's it, second-hand embarrassment?
I suffer second-hand embarrassment very acutely.
See, I normally do, but for all mankind it's fine.
Yes, fair.
Best editor categories, no one knows what editors do.
Editors are a mystery.
None of us are voting.
Next categories.
Any follow-ups on that, guys.
No, that's fair.
Best professional artist.
I will confess I haven't looked yet, but it is one of the categories I always vote in
because it doesn't take long to look at the pictures and be like, "All right, those pictures
best."
Yes, so I'll say the same that's for fan artists.
What I care about is how well the artist is representing the book and unless I have some
familiarity with the book it can be quite hard to tell.
Semi-pros-ing, I'll be putting uncanny at the bottom because I don't want them to win
another Hugo.
I'll probably be putting a skate pod at the top, not because I have a good example of
their output because I like a skate pod and I think one day it should probably win a Hugo
for best-sowing protein because it has been very consistently good.
So I don't like fiction podcasts.
I don't listen to fiction podcasts either, but they are actually not just podcasts.
Being able to tell whether something is notable is not quite the same as liking the thing it
is notable for doing, if that makes sense.
I'm not going to start listening to fiction podcasts to find out what's good, right?
Listen, it needs to leave you a question.
I'm still using a question, but I'm sorry.
We're going to avoid discussing Francine, FAN-CAST and FAN-ARTIST because obviously various of us
are nominated in each of those three categories.
Nonetheless, obviously all of them are chock full of excellent people and we recommend you
consume all of them thoroughly prior to voting.
Yeah, but do vote.
Do support the Fancart categories.
I think we haven't quite managed to get rid of the minimum votes requirement yet.
I think it gets ratified this year and we'll be gone next year, but meanwhile we still need you to vote guys.
Yes, agreed.
Even if you vote, no award, please vote.
Arthur Looze obviously getting jobs vote because he mentioned Dr Thought.
No, fan writer, Bita Carella, who is the highlight of my social media feeds every time they publish anything.
I love their Elon Musk.
He is the funniest character in all of fiction.
Just, oh my goodness, so good, so good.
And I was introduced to her through the Hugo ballot last year because I hadn't come across her before that, but she is great.
Right, and then load star.
I have read two and a half of these.
Well, I've read one, so go ahead, John.
Erm, okay, so I read A Catwoman, which I thought was...
I thought it was good up until the ending where randomly COVID happens and there's a lockdown.
And it talks all about that.
And then the characters continue having their adventure outside anyway.
And I was like, I don't know what message it is you're trying to send by including this in your book.
Bloodmarked, I'm halfway through.
Very conflicted about bloodmarked because on the one hand it is an attempt to take Arthurian legend and explore what it would be like if it had black women in it.
But on the other hand it...
There's a lot of proper nouns, it's that kind of fantasy.
And I don't hate it, but I'm not sure it does much that interests me.
But the kind of racial components are really, really interesting.
So I was kind of like half, incredibly in my wheelhouse, and half kind of varied by the numbers.
Erm, and I kind of find it hard to disentangle those.
And then I read the Golden Enclave's "Why Naiminovic?" which I thought was good.
At the moment I'd probably put bloodmarked at the top, but I'm not sure I've got enough, like, of a view of the category yet.
So I'm deprioritising this category because I increasingly find that I am now so far away from being a young adult that a lot of young adult fiction really annoys me.
So I'm not sure I'm actually going to get rad to reading any of these before the Verdict deadline.
Last year, "Loadstar" had two of my favourite books on the ballot in it.
Erm, so I do often read "Loadstar" because I do think that sometimes it has some real gold in it.
I'm just not sure I've come across the real gold yet.
Obviously there'd be some amazing young adult books.
I haven't read in "The Serpent's Wake" but I do normally like books by Rachel Hartman.
And then "A Stounding"!
I've read "The Travis Baldry" book and I'm sure I've read the "Everena Maxwell" that got them on the ballot last year,
which I think was the kind of romance novel, which I very much enjoyed.
You're kind of interested in looking at colonialism.
But yes, I'm not sure I've got a very good view of this category, either of you.
Isabel Kim has put a package of her short stories in the Hugo packet and I've now had a couple of reports from people going,
"Oh my god, these are amazing!"
Ooh!
Yeah, Isabel Kim's, er, I nominated one of her short fiction pieces from "Stranger Isons",
which is a much more interesting take on AIR to, I think, than some of the other ones.
Yeah, and I've read "The Everena Maxwell" as well, the first novel, the, you know,
"Fake Dating", "Let's Huddle" for warmth in a cabin one, as I think of it.
Yeah, I think at the moment I vote for Kim first, then maybe Maxwell, but I have to do a bit more research in this category.
Okay, I think that's everything.
Alison, you're going on Juff.
I am, I'm literally Juff.
Yeah, because it's like "Jiff" isn't it? It must be pronounced the same.
Juff.
Erm, so it's "Giff" anyway, and I'll die defending it and also "Guff".
Chris Garcia is going to write in.
Chris Garcia, you're always right, Sid, that was a pretty straightforward prediction, wasn't it?
Yeah, I mean, I'm not saying, you know, I don't bet on things that I'm sure are outcome.
I mean, if you didn't get a letter from Chris, you'd check your spam buckets, right?
I took it still alive.
I messaged him to make sure he was okay, yeah.
But yes, "Guff".
It's all go. Sorry, it's all Joe.
Yeah, so literally getting on a plane before this episode comes out, by the time this episode comes out, I will be in Australia.
I'm taking enormous amount of tech with me. I don't know how that happened. It doesn't seem like me at all.
But I'm taking a number of, I'm taking a 3D camera and I'm taking a 360-degree camera and I'm taking a telephone.
Guess which one's good to get the most use?
There's a camera and I'm taking a microphone so that I can record a couple of issues of Octa thought while I'm in Australia and New Zealand.
So we better do that, guys. We haven't actually sorted out exactly when we're going to do it, but we will.
And yeah, there's just whole box full of tech and I carefully packed it up to make sure it all fitted.
And then I remember that we were recording today, so I had to carefully unpack it and set up to record.
I didn't know that. That's amazing.
I have started thinking about, I'm not administering Guff yet, but I've started thinking about how you can support the fanphones
and one of the ways you can support the fanphones is by getting me to send you a postcard.
And I will send you handwritten postcards from Australia or New Zealand, probably from Australia, for a donation of 5 or more to Guff,
which you send to guffeurope@gmail.com.
By PayPal. If you can't do it that way, then get in touch and we'll find another way you can pay.
And they come in four flavours, which are kind of picture postcards of Australian things, which are at the 5 level.
And the other thing is a 5 level is a photo of me on the Guff trip, but that won't be a handwritten postcard.
That'll be kind of sent from an internet postcard sending service.
And at the 10 level, you can have a special and unique, well, not unique because there's going to be a few of them,
but a special card that's being designed for the Guff trip.
And the other 10 level is special requests like, "Could you send it from New Zealand?"
And "Could you have one with Lego on it?" and things of that sort, they cost 10.
And yeah, please support Guff because this trip's going to be amazing and it's also going to cost a fortune, very sorry guys.
But I will report back, there'll be lots and lots and lots of Guff reports.
How much would it cost to get a postcard made of yet Lego?
You could get them on the Lego store and I think they're about to any quid.
Oh.
And there is an Australia, there's a Sydney one, there's an Australia one.
Could have fun, have lots of fun.
Yes.
And I am meeting lots of fans and this is once again, if you're in a place I'm going and we haven't already agreed to meet up,
then please get in touch and we'll sort that out.
I've reached out to a lot of people at this point, but I'm sure I've missed some people and I'm sure there's people out there that I don't know about.
I do want to hang out.
That was the Auto Podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
[Music]
When I was young, there were movie tie-in novels and very occasionally one of them was good, but most of them were not good at all.
But I suppose 90% of everything is crap, so you know.
I did quite like the movie tie-in novel for solo, which was written by Merlaffte because there is a brilliant scene where Chewbacca and Lando discuss hair conditioning advice and that scene was worth reading the novel.
Like, because it just makes perfect sense, Chewbacca's like, "I've got to get all this out of my hair, who is the person to talk to about personal grooming, that guy?"
Fucking, no notes, 10 out of 10.
And it's definitely not hard, isn't it?
So...
Exactly right.
The theme music for this episode was Surf Shimmy by Kevin MacLeod and Combetech.com used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.