I'm a big fan of skulls.
You can't be a fan of Warhammer 40,000 for too long without acquiring a fondness for skulls.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 145th episode of Octothorpe,
which is finding out that it is the chosen one,
despite the fact that it's of a different ethnicity
to everyone else on the planet,
on the 9th of October 2025.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Tommy Ferguson.
Hello, Tommy.
Hello.
Thank you very much for coming and being Liz for the day.
It's my absolute joy.
I'm new to Octothorpe, but I'm playing catch-up really quickly.
You'd never heard of us before we'd asked you to be on, huh?
My letter of comment elides that.
Yes, indeed.
And we do have some letters of comment.
And let's start with a letter of comment from one Tommy Ferguson.
So this wasn't planned because we asked you to be on after you sent this, but it's quite good.
Talk about a segue.
Indeed.
Thank you, John.
Yeah, the email was around Alan and David's note for Unconfined.
It got me thinking again about Easter cons and their future.
And I should add, I'm on the committee for Unconfined,
so I might have a slight bias there.
What I really like about what they're doing is their ambitions for outreach,
especially other parts of genre fandom and younger people.
I saw this in evidence that we connect and we try to do
with relative levels of success,
but I think it was made a lot easier with our city centre location.
People knew where we were.
People had experience of being there before.
And it was accessible.
and it's the same for Glasgow in 2027.
Though I'm not too sure I'd say about previous conventions
like the Metro Hotel, for example, or indeed Telford,
which were not as accessible to local people
and therefore made it a bit more difficult
to get people to come for the very first time.
Again, and you mentioned pricing as well,
another thing we touched on to try and do the outreach
made it as cheap as possible for people locally to come.
And in fact, we had a £5 Saturday rate
for cosplayers and so that's something i'm really enjoying about on confined and maybe something
you should think about for shoot you restocons no we had um i would say i was working yesterday was
saturday as we record listeners i was working an open day at northumbria which the university i
work at and they had the newcastle anime and gaming con and so campus was sort of half very
nervous 18 year olds with their parents and half people dressed up as anime characters and it was
quite the vibe but i really liked the cosplay presence at um reconnect in belfast i thought
that was really good and i think certainly exposed a lot of people who might not otherwise have come
to our brand of fandom so i thought that worked very well i think your point about telford being
great for eastcon people but not necessarily great for bringing people in is a good one too because
it was a good site but like you said there's not a lot of passing trade as it were yeah and i love
Telford, I thought it was a great convention.
I thought the hotel and the
convention centre combination was really
good, but it was very much
for an established audience,
people who normally go to Easter
Cones. And the same with the Metropole
in Birmingham. I've heard some comments already
about even though the hotel prices
are ridiculously cheap for a Hilton,
fantastically cheap,
it is still a stretch for people coming
for the first time or just wanting to
test their feet in the
water to see what this thing is about.
I think there's an anime
convention at the same time
as the Eastercon so it might be that there's
potential for some sort of
cheap membership for people who are going to be
at the anime con but I don't know if they're thinking about that
but that could be a way of
trying to achieve the same sort of thing
Yes, I mean I think it was wonderful
that this year's Eastercon
was at Belfast
was it this year's Eastercon? My brain is fried
It was
Feels like years ago
It does feel like years ago. Sorry. I think it's wonderful that this year's Eastercon was in Belfast because it's a capital city and it allowed, it meant it has some presence in the local area.
But fundamentally, the thing that's driving where we hold EasterCons is where we can hold EasterCons.
And so I think it's important that when you've got them in sites like Glasgow, where we can, we should be able to attract local attendance.
I mean, historically, of course, Glasgow got huge numbers of local attenders at WorldCons at EasterCons.
But this is a long time ago now.
And that wasn't the case the last time we held it there.
Yeah, we shall come back to that with a little bit of foreshadowing there.
It's been a long time since we've held an Eastercon in Glasgow because the previous one was 2014.
And that was quite small because, well, it was quite large as EasterCons went,
but it was probably smaller than you'd expect a Glasgow convention to be.
I think probably because of LungCon.
Anecdotally, I know lots of friends of mine didn't go to that EastCon
because they were going to WorldCon.
So I'm curious how unconfined numbers will look
and how many people they will get in from Glasgow.
I mean, especially because Glasgow 2024 did such a good job
of bringing Glaswegian fandom in.
I assume that will be a very different mix of people to the 2014 EastCon.
But yeah, we will see.
I am not clairvoyant, so I do not know.
but I've got my fingers crossed it'll work out.
I was also going to highlight something you said
in your lock, Toby,
which was that you were a big fan of the Dread movie.
I am indeed.
Unlike Liz or me.
Well, I'm of a certain age, I should say,
and 2008 was one of my growing up formative experiences
and I loved Judge Dredd as a comic
and I loved the concept.
And then when I heard they were remaking the movie, in effect, we talked briefly about the original Stallone Dread movie.
And when I heard, again, say the remake was happening, I thought, listen guys, don't fuck this up.
It's already had one go, which wasn't well received. Just make sure you don't mess it up again.
And I don't think they did. I think they got, to a certain extent, a lot of the spirit of Judge Dredd.
I think you guys talked about it last time,
where they didn't quite pick up on the satire
and the authoritative nature of the state.
And the idea behind the comic originally
was to show that up and satirise it.
And I think a lot of people now have seen the movie
as an action movie and view it that way
and don't see the kind of subtext.
But having said that, I really enjoyed the first one as well,
the Stallone movie.
And I know it's got a whole bunch of criticism,
but it takes a lot of different aspects of Dread.
It takes a bit of the comic humour.
It takes a bit of the look and style as well.
I really enjoyed.
And apart from Stallone's acting,
there's some really good other actors in it as well.
Yeah, so Paul Weimer and Jonathan Baddeley
both wrote to say that they were surprised
we hadn't mentioned the Stallone movie.
And I freely confess I have not seen it.
And I mentioned this in the pre-recorded topic.
I was like, oh no, it's a lot of fun,
despite, you know, maybe not being the most
true to the comics adaptation it could have been.
I think it's possible that at least one of us should have watched that movie before we did our Dread episode.
I mean, I don't know because I don't want to.
But now Tommy told me it's good.
I might.
Or, well, no, Tommy told me it's fun.
I shouldn't put words in your mouth, Tommy.
I think Tommy may also have said that it's a generational thing.
And you might find that it doesn't necessarily speak to you in that way that old product sometimes doesn't speak to younger people.
The visuals are good. You'll enjoy the visuals. They're fun and entertaining. It's not a great movie. It's a good movie. I don't have the same kind of scale you guys have for waiting movies. My movie tastes at thresholds are quite low. I will enjoy most things.
I think John's movie's threshold tastes are quite low.
Rude. What I hadn't realised is that one of the people in the 1995 Judge Dredd movie is Ian Dury, and that does make me excited to watch it, because I am a big fan of Ian Dury.
Legend.
He's typecast in the movie.
You will see it as an Ian Jury part.
Brilliant.
I don't think Ian Jury was good at playing characters
other than Ian Jury, was he?
He was the Sean Connery of his day.
So yes, please watch it.
It's 90 minutes, even less perhaps.
It's not a huge ordeal.
And you will take some stuff away from it.
Hopefully smiles.
Yay!
I will take some stuff away, yeah.
Because what I took away from Dread 3D was, oh, I don't want to watch that again.
And you guys mentioned The Raid.
Alison, don't watch The Raid.
You will not enjoy it.
No, no.
In fact, both John and Liz told me not to watch The Raid because I would not enjoy it.
We do try and look after you.
So we also heard on Blue Sky from Brian Nisbet, who basically expressed condolences with Alison
for her going back down the Slay the Spire rabbit hole.
How's that going, Alison?
I've reached Ascension 16 with the silent.
I don't know what that means.
I have so little context for that sentence.
I understood all of the individual words.
No clue.
I am confident that people in the audience will understand.
I've taken time off for other obsessions in the meantime.
Oh, well done.
And I was thinking about doing a predictive pick this week
where I talked about the fact that Blueprints is now out for the Mac
and Hades 2 has been released.
But that's clearly just follow up on previous things
that caused me to lose a week or two of my life.
Sorry, spend a week or two of my life
productively engaging with top-tier entertainment experiences.
I should say that that piece of information about Hades 2 being released
will go down very well in our heart at all.
There you go.
Not with my bank balance, but with the house.
yeah no well i spent 323 hours on hades one which i'm gonna say works out quite well as cost per
pound i should also add it's not me playing but it's my eldest daughter we also heard from chris
garcia chris like me is excited about the fact that joe walton is one of the guests of honor for
worldcon in 20 in montreal in 2027 and says she had the best quote about me ever patrick nielsen
Hayden says doesn't Chris have a big ego and Joe said have you ever met him he's all id
and he also says that John lied about having two dinners because it was actually two lunches
I'm not sure that that's a major difference it's a philosophical point for sure you know were they
at midday then are they actually dinners John is from the north you know Chris I'm from the east
you're from the north now aren't you you have your dinner right and then your tea
he does make a point about having known a lot of movie folks there are layers to get to them that
are there for pretty good reasons he knows the folks that directed captain marvel that is a
classic chris garcia name drop and if he wants to send them an email he's got to go through their pr
reps at about two out of three times it's a miss and so that i think goes back to what we were
talking about last time he did mention about the sound design and you guys talked about last uh last
time uh and he highlights that the best sound design he's heard is on the movie the abyss and
i have to absolutely agree with that um because watching that even with your eyes closed it is
terrifying and knowing what's going to happen can come come next uh the sound design just enhances
that so much to you for a bit of chris that's a really good show no the abyss is great i watched
it for the first time relatively recently and it is it is a it is a cracking movie extremely tense
like oh it's so stressful um but yeah i did enjoy it when they joined the rat my nerves get really
anxious uh that's just a creepy yeah i can't believe john you haven't watched that before
you are just ridiculously young it's scary well but also it wasn't easy to it wasn't easy to watch
like it's only just had a re-release on disc and before that you couldn't it wasn't on streaming
and it wasn't out we also heard from scott edelman on blue sky who wonders whether social media is
contributing to the death of conventions no yeah no i agree i don't think it is i think it's additive
not subtractive that's an experience yeah i don't use social media instead of hanging out with my
friends in person i use it as well as and anecdotally i think some people get into cons
because of social media so it might actually have the opposite i don't know how you find out
um i think it'd be very difficult to actually know for sure but my suspicion is that it doesn't
reduce con attendance if i think of um reconnected recent conventions um use of discord in association
with the convention itself has done nothing but enhance it increases access increases capability
it's just a massive addition as you say to uh to the con experience when and like because i did the
discord for the world con the glasgow world con and there were a lot of people i say a lot of
people like maybe even handfuls of people who came up to me and said that they'd found the discord
helpful as new attendees because it had like let them start getting to know people before actually
arriving on site and i do think that if you're very embedded in conventions already they're not
daunting but i think having ways that you can kind of get into the community in advance of arriving
in the room with a thousand people in it can be really useful i think that ties into that as well
like facebook twitter well blue sky now i guess um discord yeah i was going to say the average
national science fiction convention octocon um which is actually happening right now as its podcast
goes out um has a huge online presence before the convention they've won events they've got the
quizzes they've got a huge facebook presence and discord presence and they really actively
enhance their community and they still have a very strong masking policy so they're very aware
of their community needs and but their online social presence is part of the dimension and in
fact the sunday is online only so there is no in person and that that just makes the dimension
welcome for everybody yeah no exactly i think that's a uh a good a good point um and let me
so and actually you are so you are going to be on a panel at octagon tommy you mentioned in your lock
i did i'm on the very first panel hey coincidence or anything um 10 o'clock on a saturday morning
um which is you know quite nice reasonable times uh and the panels are about remakes and as i
mentioned earlier about Dread.
One of the key things I want to bring to
that panel is
every time you hear somebody's remaking or
making something, my first
thought is, please don't mess it up.
When I heard they're making the series
of The Expanse, I thought,
guys, this is my favourite book series
ever. Just don't fuck it
up. And did they?
They did not. They did a really good job
of it. I'm one of those
people who are massively evangelical
about The Expanse books and TV show.
And I kind of, I mean, I thought Battlestar Black,
because it was my favourite TV sci-fi show ever.
Nope, it's now The Expanse.
And the guys that developed that science fiction group
never tire of me talking about it.
That's fair.
So, obviously, I love The Expanse so much
that I'm savouring the television series
and only watching episodes very occasionally.
and in fact
Johnny Baddeley wrote
to express support
for my struggles
with The Expanse
and said
it's taken him eight months
to go through season two
so it's not just me
The show that is that
for me is For All Mankind
where I sort of
basically got so slow
at watching it
that I said to his partner
you could probably watch it
without me at this point
because yeah
we're watching like
one episode every six months
and that's probably not
probably not helpful
about what mankind it's one of those shows where people tell you you know it's a slow burner
you know it came at home give it a few episodes once you get into it you really like it and i
just hate that nonsense i mean show doesn't grab me it's terrible and then i'm a complete hypocrite
when they talk about the expanse because you do need to give it a few episodes to get there
yeah well it's season four we're still waiting for it to get better so you know i have to give up now
frankly it's clearly it's clearly very well made and it's good science fiction and and you'll see
we haven't given up right yeah yeah just that we're just like oh should we watch the expanse or
oh there's another series of slow horses maybe we should watch that instead you should slow slow
horses is great uh i am told i haven't seen it yet it's on my big list of things i want to watch
um it's not so not not genre though unless your genre is grimy things set in london which um
you know after randor i i quite like well and the other thing is like do you remember in the old days
when there wasn't enough science fiction tv that you couldn't you just had to like all of the
science fiction tv right yeah because there was like three of them and that was it i i may remember
the older days back before the dawn of time when in fact i did like doctor who and star trek i still
love star trek doctor who but star trek's great um right
we should do topics and we have some we well we do so um we have tommy here with us today
listeners you may have noticed if you've been paying attention and we're did you introduce
tommy at the beginning did you just say this is tommy or did you say a little bit about tommy or
got to say i'm going to introduce tommy now with us we have tommy ferguson and tommy is known to
some people listening to the podcast but for those who don't know uh tommy has run a couple of
conventions um including core flu crack and reconnect in belfast and he is also running the
forthcoming uh non-con which will be at the same hotel as reconnect uh next year and we're going
talk to him a little bit about all of that um is there anything else you do you think people should
know about you tommy before we get into the before we get into the nitty-gritty alison has something
and tommy is a fanzine fan aren't you tommy i am i see i see like the guy to confess hello my name
is tommy's for a bison amber fanzine fan but you've been clean for a while i think there's i think i've
had zines from tommy in my memory in the 21st century pretty sure yeah yes thank you thank you
john i will link to your website in the show notes tommy are your fanzines on efanzines.com
some of them are um some of them are co-edited and uh we haven't got permissions etc but yeah
most of them are sitting there somewhere most of them are very old ones there's nothing recent
that I hasten to add. And is there anything else you think people should know other than that you're
a fanzine fan? I'm old, so I've been active in fandom. I counted it out 45 years now in various
different ways. And as you said, I seem to be a con runner again. That's kind of how I started off
from fanzines into con running. Yes, primarily in Belfast, as you say. I spent some time in
Toronto in the late 90s. People may remember me from there. But I got into fandom in the very early
1980s, the Irish Science Fiction Association, long gone but much remembered fondly. And then my very
first convention, property convention I should add, was at Glasgow at Albuquerque 3, the much-missed
Central Hotel. That was where I first kind of started my formal life in fandom, as it were.
I went to Toronto on my TAF trip by, I suspect I missed you by a few years, but I did enjoy meeting Toronto fandom.
So let's talk about Corflu. For those who don't know, do you want to explain Corflu to our listeners?
So Corflu is a small convention primarily run by and for fanzine fans.
I'm assuming everybody knows what a fanzine is.
Corfu's been going, it's 43 now, I think, this year.
It's been going forever.
It was the very first convention to have a hybrid element, a Bidou element.
And effectively, it's people who write, produce, edit fanzines,
who come together to discuss the same.
And it's actually a great, fun convention.
I think it's the only convention that didn't miss a year during the pandemic.
That's right. I was a core 350 guest at the College Station 2020.
In fact, that was my first core fleet, which kind of begs belief.
When we were finishing up on the Saturday or Sunday, March 2020, everything was getting shut down.
airlines are getting shut down
our fights were brought forward a day
so Rob Jackson and I
were flying back together
basically panicking
my wife was going mental
to Hallyden in Texas with its open doors
policies, no masking
everybody getting together
we will be free, get home now
so yeah
as Alison says
we've run continuously
for the last 43 years
yeah so the
The 38th core flu was in Bristol, which was in November 2021.
So there was a sort of long gap between the 2020 and 2021 installments,
but it kind of contained most of the lockdowns.
And fancyclopedia notes, this means that core flu might be the only annual convention
whose sequence remained unbroken.
So if anyone can think of any counterexamples, write in.
Sequence of physical conventions.
Because obviously people had online versions, which counters real cons.
Jury's out.
The one thing I was going to pick up on, something that Tommy said,
is the one thing I do think our listeners know about fanzines is that Octothorpe isn't one.
Look, right, we've got to let that go.
One day we have to move on.
It's becoming a distraction.
That's one.
Obviously can't be in the fan awards.
Yes.
So I think I first met you, Tommy, at the Corflou in Bristol, I think.
That makes sense.
It does.
And I thought, this is an up-and-coming sort of chap who's going to run a convention in Belfast.
So what made you want to bring Corflou to Belfast?
It's a long story, as these usually are.
A guy called Mark McCann, he was my co-editor on Goddard-Ambrung,
a fan he used to do back in the 90s in the Good Mate.
So he and the other co-editor, James McKee and my wingman, as they call him, Eugene Doherty, went to the Leeds Corfu back in 1998.
They came back with stories of drink, loose women, drugs, debauchery, and all around a good time.
And I thought, fantastic.
Mark Leather wrote this up in an article, which is published in the Corfu Crack Souvenir Book.
So you can read all about it yourself.
that should be online somewhere.
I thought, yeah, this sounds like right up my street.
I really want to get to one of these things.
And as I said, from 1998 to the next one
that I actually physically got to was Texas in 2020.
Life got in the way.
Things happened, et cetera.
And when I was there in Texas,
I said, I've got to do this.
These guys have paid for me to come out here.
I've got to pay it back somehow.
I said, right, listen,
I will do one of these core flus in Belfast.
and it was Pat Berzi who actually said to me at the bidding session
so when is it going to be, what's the story, tell us more details
and I fondly recall asking, well, when are you all free?
Famous last word.
I basically organised a convention around people's needs
so we couldn't do it the year I wanted to do it
which would be the anniversary of Irish fandom
so we did it the following year
and my reasoning for doing it was
these are all the people in fandom I really like
and respect and love to spend time
with in person. I want to
get them to my city and
basically organise a party and have
a good convention on the side.
It was just an excuse. And as I
said on the bit in session, this is quarterly
crack. Crack meaning to have a good
time in Irish, to have fun, to
get together, to socialise. And that's what I wanted
to do. I don't know what I really
think I could speed up, was to organise a quarterly
crack in Belfast.
And yeah, it happened.
It was fun.
I really enjoyed it.
I'm going to apologise again, as I always do when I talk about corporate crack.
I had some really good organising meetings with the hotel.
We talked with the head chef and the manager.
I had a fantastic vision for what the Sunday lunch was going to be.
Again, the reality on the day was somewhat suboptimal.
Again, that's the only flaw I thought in the whole corporate experience for me.
I think that's what we enjoyed.
But that meal was just terrible.
Again, I'm sorry, people.
It's not even in the top 10 of worst hotel meals I've had.
Worst convention banquets I've had.
And also, I think it goes to something we've been discussing for a while,
which is it's surprising how often the food that is available at a convention
is completely out of the control of anyone involved in the convention.
And that is distressing, but unfortunately true.
Yeah, there's always reasons for that.
The anniversary of fandom is 2022, I assume.
Yes.
If I've done the maths right.
So, and is that fandom like on the island,
Ireland of Ireland,
or is that Northern Irish fandom specifically?
So there's a thing called Irish Fandom Day.
You can look it up.
I guess it's 1947.
So Irish Fandom Day is the day
when James White first met Walt Willis
in a bookshop in Belfast.
I think it was on Wednesday.
And I think it was 75 years from then that I had originally planned to host the quarterly crack.
But as I said, people couldn't make it.
There was other events planned.
I'm not precious about this nonsense.
So I did it the next year.
Surely, John, I mean, we did have a cover from Hyphen last week.
Anyway, I don't know.
I have not heard of Irish Fandom Day.
For some reason, Ogsthorpe cover reading inside coverage did not convey this information to me, Alison.
I don't know why.
No, I just assumed you already knew about Irish fandom.
I'm sure I've mentioned lots of Irish fandom things before.
Okay, right.
But there is a difference between knowing about Irish fandom and knowing about Irish fandom day.
In much the same way that, like, I don't know when bottles were invented, but I have a bottle on my desk right now.
Roman times? Gotta go with Roman times.
So, yes, I'm familiar with Irish fandom. I've even been to some of the conventions.
I want to offer something in my defence, which is I opened the issue of Prolapse,
and Pete Weston also didn't know about Irish Fandom Day when James Bacon emailed the article for Prolapse.
And I feel like if my Spanish history is only up to the standard of Pete Weston, then I'm not doing too badly.
You're fine. You're fine.
But yes, there's a good article in that about it if listeners want to go read.
I'd say you were one of today's 10,000, but I think you might be one of today's one.
I'm going to guess that there's at least one listener to this who has also learned something.
Maybe all of them.
Maybe. But I have learned things.
and so how do you think other than the meal like what did you did you enjoy doing core flu crack
like and did you think it went well i really enjoyed doing it um as i said i think at the end
um i did again tomorrow frankly um it's just it was just a lot of fun um i did you know a bit of
humblebrag mostly organizing myself um hey it's not very hard to organize to be honest you know
people come together and things are fairly
fluid.
Things that really happened to me
at the party was whiskey tasting,
a bit of a feature at Corfu,
gets people in the mood, shall we say,
and then Spike does her wine
tasting the next night, and
again, gets people in the mood.
Objectively, it went really
well. We had large attendance.
We dragged people out of the woodwork
who wouldn't normally come. Linda Grecke,
fantastic, wonderful to see her.
Joseph Nicholas came across, again, he hasn't been to many conventions recently.
A whole host of people turned up who people just did not expect to see.
And yet, it was, objectively people have said it was a fantastic time.
I really enjoyed doing it.
The hotel was great.
I chose hotel specifically because that's where I had my wedding reception many, many years ago.
On the same floor, bar, restaurant, hotel, convention space, all the same area.
And a nice part of Belfast, South Belfast,
people who know Belfast will know that BT9 is the kind of respectable part
just beside the university,
but far enough away from the students to make it okay.
Fair enough.
I genuinely enjoyed going on it.
People think I genuinely enjoyed attending, had a good time.
And yeah, again, I'd do it at the top of that.
Good stuff.
Did you go to Corflucrac, Alison?
Oh, yes.
Tell us about your experiences at Corflucrac.
Well, it was my second time in Belfast because I've been to TitanCon after Dublin 2019.
But my memories of that are rather inchoate due to being exhausted, really, really exhausted.
So Corflucrac was absolutely lovely because it was a good-sized convention.
It was neither too small nor too large.
It had a reasonable number of US travellers.
had a good number of uk fans including fans who are you know young some is z younger than you john
i think not actually i think z is not younger than you i was gonna say younger than john
maybe we're we're about the same age i would have said yeah similar age yeah and um
tommy had planned a whole pile of ice breaking exercises and we wandered into the hotel i guess
before the con officially started to discover everyone was just chatting to everybody else
in a kind of ice breaking not obviously required here way and there were people who'd not been to
Corflou before but but just you know it's a small enough convention that you can just chat to
everybody I I think the hotel food had a lot of food that did not contain vegetables and in general
our experience of Belfast cuisine was that week was that we kept finding we kept being offered food
that didn't have vegetables in it and we had to work quite hard to get food that had vegetables
in it and I you need to know I'm not a very vegetable forward person normally I have no
trouble going for a few days without with minimal vegetables but but a lot of it was deep fried as
well it was kind of the hotel was kind of like we have we have a bunch of tapas bites and they were
like deep fried things um but apart from that um Belfast was lovely the weather was lovely I think
are mostly lovely the beer was lovely the people were lovely the convention was you know core flu
has quite a small program but a carefully formed one um and it was all very good and i had an
absolutely brilliant time and it was the week before the easter con so it just left me slightly
tired for easter con but fortunately not sick um because there was a whole thing about the
transmission of viruses going on so and i think somebody at core flu somebody at core flu had
covid joe scolari unfortunately the night before oh that's sad but was very good at um insulating
he was fantastic yeah i i was sad that i didn't get to go i did not go to uh i i blah i'd been
to belfast once on a sort of i went to armar for a summer school so i kind of went through belfast
but it wasn't until Reconnect that I got to visit properly,
which is a lovely segue into Reconnect.
So how soon after running a core flu did you decide that you wanted to run an Eastcon, Tommy?
Was that something that you'd already decided at the point the core flu was happening,
or was it soon after?
It was well before.
It was 1986, actually.
LAUGHTER
Well, yeah, so quite a long way before.
Fair enough.
Yeah.
And it's Ian Sorensen's fault,
what most things are.
Hey!
Yep.
I think I mentioned at the opening ceremony
to reconnect the story.
So as I said,
my first convention was Glasgow Albecon 3.
I had a fantastic time.
And on a Sunday morning,
slightly hungover, I have to say,
I went to the future conventions type panel,
kind of hostings almost.
And I thought,
I don't know what this convention nonsense is, but I want more of it.
Tell me more.
So I signed up to Ian.
He was obviously getting ready to host the panel.
And I said, listen, this is something he's never going to let me forget, ever.
I said, is it OK if I run one of these things next year in Belfast?
I said, oh, asking Ian Soren for permission to run a convention.
Oh, yeah.
So I haven't let that down.
So he said at the end of the panel, Tommy Ferguson,
he was going to run a convention in Belfast.
Tommy, stand up.
and I went, yes, it's going to happen.
It's going to be this year.
It'll be in Belfast.
It'll be the Students' Union.
And I was just making it up as I met along.
Enthusiasm is half the battle.
But there were conventions in the Students' Union in Belfast, weren't there?
Mecons?
Nikons, which is before Mecons.
So Nikon 86, the very first Northern Ireland Science Space Convention,
happened six months after Albicon 3.
So yes, the enthusiasm took hold of me
and I grabbed Eugene Doherty
and between us, we organized the first convention.
There were four Nikons.
Nikon 1989 was the Unicorns.
Terry Pratchett was our guest of honor.
There was a bit of a hiatus then because we all graduated and we don't.
But you're right, Alison, there was another sequence of conventions
called MeCon, M-E-C-O-N.
And that went for 10 years and had some stunning guests.
It was a really fantastic sequence of conventions,
which I was only tangentially involved in, to be honest.
And then after that, a bit of a hiatus and time cons came along, building on the game of films kind of stuff.
So yes, my very first desire to run an Easter con happened at Albuquerque 1986.
It didn't actually come to life because, well, life as well.
There just isn't a facility, or it just wasn't a facility in Belfast to run anything like a 1,000-person convention
until about 5 or 10 years ago when the International Convention Centre opened adjacent to the hotel.
and once that happened I started to think a bit more about it
and then about five years ago
I heard of a scheme for the local tourist board
that would actually pay you money
to bring people into Northern Ireland
for conferences etc
quite a lot of money as it turned out
and that made the whole thing really financially feasible
and that's when James Bacon got involved
local fans got involved
can we actually do this?
James went we are doing this
not can we it's very much a yoda sense there's no try let's do um yeah and we could go off planning
um started organizing stuff together and lo and behold as you say i was in camp we were 26 months
ago it actually happened lovely stuff how do you spell nikon n-i-c-o-n n-i-c-o-n they've got
fancy they have fancyclopedia pages for both mecon and nikon i found mecon but i was having trouble
with Nikon. No, it was an ironing convention.
And then
the Unicom was called Unicon,
which is a good...
And it looks like both
Nikon and
Mekon ran
until they ran the Unicom
and then never run another one, which
I think is a bit
sad. We went to Unicom in
Winchester, which was the one before,
to bid for the one.
And our slogan was very
carefully crafted it was nikon all we need is you
thank you for the groans brilliant no further uh comment at this time you were selected as the east
con at uh birmingham in 2023 is that right am i remembering that right that's correct yes
Yeah, James and I got up and the fun con was our alternative bid.
And once we saw that happening, a slight bit of nervousness because it was a very well done bid.
Everything's lit my face, I think that was called.
But yeah, we got up, we had a stage, we had a plan.
Most people on the podcast will know of or heard of James Bacon and his enthusiasms.
I was
I was the laurel to his hearty
keeping things sensible
treasurer etc
making sure the money was there
and that was a nice kind of
co-chairs we kind of played off
each other he says let's do this let's do
this stuff and I went no we can't afford to
yeah we can't let this go go go
no no
and we had those conversations with
Keith Smith and you may all recall
we had no plans
or very little plans to be online streaming or anything like that.
Again, complete vendor cost.
And JT was our tech person initially,
and he said, what do you need to do is do something very small
and then build on it.
And as the memberships grew and grew, due to our very low price,
we got the funds available to enable us to do streaming.
And at the end, we decided, God, February of this year,
that in fact we could stream five rooms, the main hall,
those four other rooms.
And I'm happy to say, by the time this podcast goes out,
those replays will all be available.
Those replays will be available for 12 months
at replay.hdeconbelfast.org.
Interesting. Okay.
It'd be great, actually, to watch some of the events,
the convention I co-chaired.
I didn't get to see many.
No, yeah, exactly.
I think it's really good that you can do that, right?
Like if you miss something or if there's a clash, you have that security blanket of I can catch it on catch up.
And you feel like you're you don't feel as much like you're missing out.
At least I don't.
As well as being able to kind of include people who can't get to the convention in person, which is another big boon.
You can hear our live show from East Con Belfast in episode 133, listeners.
It was episode 136 where we did our reflections on East Con Belfast and Reconnect.
And the only thing on the show notes, apart from the link to East Con Belfast in that episode,
is the fact that Rattlebag has won a major award for Best Cocktail Bar,
which tells you something about our East Con experience, which involved a certain amount of cocktails.
But we did also enjoy the convention very much.
So I guess the question is, did you enjoy it and would you do it again?
Yes and yes.
I would do it in a heartbeat.
A bit like Corfee Crack.
I had such a fun time organising it.
The committee we had were all very positive.
There was no egos.
Everybody was trying to do their best.
When we made mistakes, we stood our hands up and said,
sorry, we messed up there.
Let's do it better next time.
The convention itself, I thought objectively,
all the feedback I got, people had a great time.
There were some challenges with access between the two sites,
but that was always going to be an issue we knew about.
But yeah, every time I walked around,
and I did a lot of walking around,
I was like 50,000 steps in one day.
People just come up and said,
what a great time they were having.
And that just made my heart sing.
The fact that we've been able to do this,
put this on in Belfast,
the very first time,
we had 140 people who'd never been to New York City,
we had a whole host of people from Belfast
who'd never even enjoyed any kind of art.
our form of fandom and conventions and and we made a surplus so we can do it again next year
not an Easter cone but another convention yes this is a great segue so you are running
a convention do you want to do you want to tell us more about that well you dropped it in at the
start of the event at the introduction um but yes um because we had such a great time we got some
really good local engagement and from our community the various genres we have a convention next may
8th and 9th of May, back in the Hill, the same hotel, using the exact same spaces.
We have Anna Smith-Spark and Adrian Tchaikovsky as our guests of honour.
And we're really looking forward to getting everything together.
It'll be a small convention, 150, 200 people maybe, something like a Nobicon in size.
And we're really aiming, to be honest, to get that local community involved,
both north of the border as well as the Republic.
and I'll be at OctaCon,
the National Art of Science Fixing Convention,
this weekend, pushing this left, right, and centre.
And you can find out more on our website,
norncon, N-O-R-N-Con.org,
which should be live at the time this goes out.
So I was trying to find the website
to put in the show notes,
and I happened upon a YouTube video
which explains the joke of your fanzine title,
because it's the Norn scene from Wagner's Gotterdammerung.
And now I understand why your fanzine was called Gotterdammerung.
And I was like, oh, that's very good.
I like that very much.
So I'll put a link to that in the show notes, listeners,
if you want some Wagner.
Dee, dee, dee, dee, dee, dee, dee, dee, dee, dee.
Enough of that.
I wanted to just pick up on something you said
about using the exact same spaces.
Presumably you're just going to use the Hilton
rather than the conference centre as well.
Yes, just the same spaces in the Hilton.
The Hilton spaces, because, yeah,
There's plenty of room there for a kind of, you know, what Geese used to refer to as the mythical 200 person fantasy convention in Brighton.
The kind of small convention that you run because you want to, rather than the one that's part of a chain of long running events.
Yes. So one of the things that we probably might have talked about otherwise this weekend is that we understand that Pictcon,
Pictcon, which is the same weekend as Novicon, unfortunately, which is far as attempt to launch
a new convention in Perth is going very well and has sold 100 tickets, something like enough.
Anyway, that's the point is that once you, once you, when you do these things, if you,
if you build it, they will come. So I'm assuming that if you build Noncon, it will be an enormous
success. And is it, does, does the Belfast Council help you with that as well? Or are they like,
oh no, that's just a small local convention, we don't care.
They would help us, absolutely.
The challenge being that we need to bring people out of state,
so that's out of Northern Ireland,
before they will financially help us.
They're going to help us with advertising support
and getting the local media involved as well.
But in terms of money, cold, hard cash,
we need to get people from mainland UK or the Republic of Ireland
to come to Belfast and have hope to get out of stays
before any kind of subvention will kick in.
Having said that, the guys have been fantastic.
We had a lot of radio exposure.
We had media exposure.
They put us on their website, which a lot of the touristships view and see.
So, yeah, there's lots of good support there.
That's good.
I'm glad that you're getting that support.
And I think that's brilliant.
And I'm very excited to see more conventions kind of in the UK.
I think that's great.
and especially in Northern Ireland, which is, I mean, I want to go back to Belfast.
I had a very good time, so maybe not next year, but at some point, for sure.
Yeah, very conscious. This is quickly following Eastercon,
but it's quite deliberate because there's a few other genre events happening throughout Northern Ireland next year,
and we've chosen a time specifically to make sure that we can get some local people coming along.
And indeed, it's great to see, as you say, I mean, regional conventions like PitCon, BristolCon.
indeed Norncon here in Belfast are now starting to pick up and become become more sustainable
yeah yeah so you said um previously that you're working for Unconfined which is the 2027
Eastcon in Glasgow um so what are you going to be doing for them well I should point out first of
all that um I want to pay back all the support and help that we got for Reconnect this year
by helping out future conventions in whatever capacity um I'm not working next year on 2026
because I'm non-con.
Again, I will help out in person at the convention,
but I don't want to get too involved.
But then I'm free the following year.
So I've stepped up for the communications role for Unconfined.
So all the newsletters you see coming out will be by my fair hand.
And then closer to the convention,
I'm sure there'll be some at-con roles I'll be picking up as well.
Genuinely excited, as I say, because of the nature of the outreach.
And in our committee meetings, we've had some friendly rivalry.
Alan, co-chair with David, is very keen to beat our 999 attendance number.
Still annoys me.
Really still annoys me.
No, that's fair.
I can imagine why.
And so how long have you been working on Unconfined?
Have you been on the team the whole time or is that recent?
No, that's fairly recent.
for the last few months and I probably should be remiss as well if I didn't mention the Dublin
2029 committee bid which I'm also helping out on and a non-specific role just basically pushing it
as I'm doing right now it's a great bid and I urge you all to support it yes yes Dublin 2029
will be great yeah I got I got joined to the staff discord for 2029 by mistake and I was like
I don't think I've volunteered yet.
And they were like, I bet you'll do something there.
Yeah, I will, I will.
Yeah, no, very, very supportive of Dublin 2029.
I'm very much looking forward to going back to work on in Dublin
because I did have a fantastic time the last time.
And I guess that begs the question,
will there ever be a Belfast Worldcon bid?
Yes, when are you free?
I think I've got a space in 2039.
I'd love to be a Belfast Worldcon, genuinely would.
But the challenge is we don't have the facilities, unfortunately.
Even for a 4,000, 5,000 convention, we just wouldn't have facilities for it.
Yeah, until they build something like that, unfortunately it's off the cards.
But yeah, a drop of a hat, I'd be there.
That's fair, that is fair.
Tommy, is there a Belfast food specialty that we should have looked out for and made sure that we ate and should make sure that we eat at NogCon?
I'm sure I put it in the Facebook trailers, but there's a thing called a Paddy Pizza, which is effectively a base of Irish soda bread, pizza stuff on top.
Is that Paddy or Patty?
Paddy, P-A-D-D-Y. It's a speciality of a bar in Belfast, but then it's kind of spread out.
that sounds amazing okay i'm going back to melfast i'll send you a bit i'll send a link to that
yeah yeah thank you very much brilliant oh oh i've just seen a picture oh my god
that looks it looks amazing right it does look like the sort of food i like
so vibrant food culture food yes we went to the a the initially started uh restaurant for our
anniversary last week and um the fact that we have a mission start restaurant in belfast is a plus
um but then the rest of the scene just builds off that and yeah no it's a fantastic food culture
here from the the lowly paddy pizza to the the high-end hood casino yeah no i loved the food
uh in belfast um i did not have a bad meal while i was there it was great and you're so what
conventions are you going to like you i know you're going to novacon because i sold you a membership
are you going to Smothcon or not?
I'm not unfortunately
I really would have loved to have gone
but family commitments mean
unfortunately I can't
I'll be at NovaCon, I'll be at Octocon
this weekend
and of course EasyCon next year
Wey!
Alison and I will also be at NovaCon
and we're doing a live Octothorpe
so we'll see you there
and we'll also see you in the bar
we're not just going to blank you until the live episode
we're not we're not quite at that level yet um but yeah i mean you'll need to talk to our people
shall we do picks tommy do you have a pick so my pick is a book um it is and i'm not too sure
it's been picked before but it's from this year from the spring uh it's sleeper beach by nick
Harkaway, which
neatly ties into
the Soul Horses we talked about earlier, because
Nick Harkaway recently interviewed
the author of Soul Horses,
McCarran, and that's a fantastic interview
if you can see it.
It's basically a detective noir
thriller with science fiction
elements, a whole bunch of set of
big films, set in the near future.
It's the second book, the first
book was Titanium Noir,
this one's called Super Beach.
It reminds me a lot of Francis Buford's Chukoka Jazz.
Don't know how I pronounce that properly.
Cahokia, I think. Cahokia Jazz.
Oh, geez, I've mangled that.
Very hard-boiled detective, old Raymond Chandler,
with definite sci-fi twists.
It's got the baddies of our succession and murder-type empires.
It's very complex and very funny as well, very sarcastic.
complex clones pop twists and if you like any of that kind of stuff i've talked about
you will love this book so i know because nick harkaway is john le carrie's son correct um so
obviously john le carrie is is um i have it on my bookshelf downstairs and i have not yet read it but
it is very much on my radar and i am excited to read it just as soon as i've read all the other
books um but yeah uh um so i had not realized there was another one in the series but i am
intrigued. Yeah, once you read Titanium Noir, just send me a WhatsApp to say thank you. That's fine.
All right, I will do that. I will do that. So somebody, I think Liz must have picked
the Titanium Noir then because I think we've had it as a pick and I definitely haven't read it.
So, but clearly Nick Huckaway is someone who's on my radar, but haven't read yet.
So, and I'm currently in a Slow Horses thing. So, you know, I've got all of those to read.
I'm dithering about whether I should read the book first
or watch the show first
but I'm leaning towards watching the show
and then reading that book
and then trying to understand what's going on
You're flighty the books
the books are unperdominable
in quotes
So Liz picked Titanium Noir
in episode 97 listeners
so if you want to go back and listen to that you can
although there's no requirement
how would we even implement a requirement guys um well some people do think that they need to start
at the beginning and i just i think it's important we keep telling them that it's not
that it's entirely up to them very much a fan of listener rights
uh allison do you want to go next yes so i had a slight issue with finding a topic a genre pick
this time so I am picking the podcast Strong Message Here by Helen Lewis and Armando Iannucci
which is a Radio 4 podcast it's been going for over a little over a year and they're fairly
snappy they're about 25 minutes they talk about political language and the way it is used and
abused and it is both very informative so it does get you thinking about the words that
politicians and other public figures use all of the time which do not mean what they
pretend they mean and the ways in which that influences discourse. And it is also very funny
because these are two very funny people. And I'm sure because it's a Radio 4 podcast,
there must be some scripting going on, but it feels very conversational. So it feels like they
go down the sort of conversational rabbit holes that I like in podcasts and often don't find as
much of as I would like in Radio 4 podcasts. But this one is great. It's topical, but nevertheless,
I'm listening to it all the way from the beginning. So they talk about politics,
political language that's been in the news this week, but they also, but they're also talking
about the subject more generally. Absolutely love it. There's been a year of it. So there's quite a
lot of episodes for me to go through. And the reason I've been listening to it is that I have
been making a very large knockoff Lego micro blocks model that I bought in a charity shop.
so that gave me lots of time to listen to podcasts
over the last few days.
I will take that and put that on my list
because as I mentioned I listen to podcasts
when I'm running and that sounds perfect.
Yeah, no, it sounds awesome.
It's a really good podcast.
Not science fictional at all as far as I know.
They mention science fiction occasionally
because science fiction also has quite a lot of invented language.
Oh yes.
And politicians take some of their words
from science fiction as well.
Yeah.
And often not in a good way.
But it's not a genre podcast.
So that's my pick for this week.
i for one am enjoying living in the world of the torment nexus
and and no that that podcast does sound very good so i have a i have a satire shaped hole in my
listening ever since um they made it so the news quiz isn't isn't on podcasts properly anymore so
i shall look that up what why oh i mean this happened ages and ages ago um but they made it
so that all of the BBC podcasts are like on a four-week delay rate and for some podcasts that's
fine but for news satire it doesn't work quite as well it should be said that might be true for this
as well then well as I said I'm listening I've not got up to date yet and I mean so I'm listening to
podcasts for a year ago but in fact I do remember what was in the political discourse a year ago so
it's fine well I also think that a podcast about discourse might need to be less topical than
the news quiz I'm going to pick a game I'm going to pick a game that is genre it's called Spirit
Island and this is a game that is very highly rated on Board Game Geek and I played it in a
board game cafe pre-pandemic and I thought it was a bit crap and then I kind of came back to it later
because it so commonly is at the top of these lists and I thought well maybe I should give it
another go and actually i do wonder whether it benefits quite a lot from not being played
with four players i think maybe the downtime at four player is not very good but sort of two or
three players it kind of hums along quite nicely uh and this is spirit island um and it's a game
where the reason i got back into it is because it came up on a panel we had at the excellent
reconnect east con in belfast um which was about uh depictions of history in board games
And although Spirit Island is not a historical game, and neither is Settlers of Catan,
they both deal with colonization and colonialism.
And so obviously they're kind of germane to the discussion.
And Spirit Island is the explicit kind of new play as the spirits who live on an island that has some native peoples.
And the aim of the game is to repel the invading forces.
The base game comes with Prussia, England and Sweden.
And you can buy extra boxes that add other colonial powers and other spirits and things like this.
And it's just very good fun.
And you sort of build your hand of powers by drafting cards from a deck of cards over the course of the game.
And you play those powers to do various nasty things to the colonists.
And yeah, it's good.
It is currently slightly hard to get hold of because the company that makes it has had some layoffs due to the tariff situation in the US,
but is beginning to come back into print, I think.
And also there is a digital version on iOS and on Steam.
So I think the Steam one is currently quite heavily discounted.
I think it's 60% off.
So yeah, I would recommend people go and have a look at that.
It is good. I enjoy it.
um it's very popular game for solo play as well as for um across the board play to the app store
page and the steam page in the show notes listeners i've been meaning to play spirit island for ages
it's one because because as you say everyone talks about it it's one of the very highly
rated games that i've not yet played thank you very much for joining us tommy it has been very lovely
thank you for having me and thanks so much tommy that was fantastic you're welcome on that bombshell
That was the Octothorpe podcast.
And it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
There's a rat, isn't there?
Yes.
That's a rat.
They killed a rat while they made the Abyss.
And as a result of it, it's been...
Cameron won't cut the scene.
And the BBFC is absolutely implacable that if you kill animals on screen
and you actually kill them, you can't have a rating in the UK.
Yeah.
So I don't know how they've...
Presumably they have resolved that with a CGI rat or something.
But anyway.
No, they haven't.
It's not out in the UK.
So how's it got it?
So, yeah, you can't see it in the UK legally.
So, but the point I'm making is before that even,
where there was a long time where you just couldn't watch it
because the DVD version wasn't up to Cameron's standards
and it hadn't been made into an HD version yet.
So he wouldn't let anyone sell the old version,
but he hadn't made the new version.
So you just couldn't, like, well, I mean, you could
because I torrented it, obviously.
It never came up on, like, Netflix or anything.
But, yeah, no, I believe it's illegal to see it
or to sort of show it or sell it in the UK unless Cameron has capitulated.
No, they didn't even kill the rat.
They'd merely tortured the rat.
It's illegal to torture animals on screen in the UK.
Yeah, yeah.
Not a good thing.
Hmm.
Yeah, but I mean, is it illegal to torture them historically?
You know, does that mean that there's a load of movies from the past we can't see now
because there's all sorts of classics that have scenes that wouldn't be allowed today?
i don't think that's actually all that true i think the point is that a lot of see a lot of
movies did it off screen and suggested and camera was like no we're actually going to
waterboard a rat on camera which i think is something that a sociopath does and i'm not
sure lots of directors did it because you could just have a picture of a rat and then cut away
to reactions of characters and then cut back to a rat and he chooses not to do that i'm feeling like
battle scenes in the past
with horses and things.
Yeah. Westerns and
dances with wolves, I thought,
famously tried to not
hurt the animals, but by accident
and unfortunately did.
But that's why they have, like,
the no animals were harmed
thing, right?
Yeah, no, I mean, basically, James Cameron
was the person who made you put that into
the Code of Conduct.
Yeah.
Every film now says no animals were harmed because
James Cowra was like, no, we're going to use rats.
Five rats, apparently.
And there's a film called Amoris Perros in which there's a dogfighting scene,
but the dogfighting was simulated, so it was allowed to be screened.
So you can show depictions of animal torture if animals were not actually tortured.
It is the act of torturing an animal that makes it illegal.
And I basically think that's okay.
Yes, that.
But the question is when you go back into the past and say,
OK, so if you're looking at a film from 100 years ago,
do films from 100 years ago have to satisfy our current state?
But the thing is, this law was passed in 1937, Alison.
And that was why, because there were other directors injuring other animals.
So I guess I will say that if it's a film from 1936 or earlier,
maybe there is a very narrow argument that it should be allowed.
But The Abyss was made in the 80s.
And so, hmm.
Anyway, this has been a digression.
Welcome to the podcast, Tommy.
We're doing, is this still Chris's loc?
Yes.
Good.
But the Abyss is great.
And despite that scene, I would recommend seeing it.
But yeah, you might have to go to a place called America.
Or the internet.
As we say, look, we're down the back of the internet, super.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod at incompetech.com,
used under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.