Did you know that Britain is 0.14 more democratic than Mauritius?
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 115th episode of Octothorp.
This episode is coming to you on the 1st of August 2024.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
This is a pretty bumper episode because we're going to talk about the business meeting at Glasgow
and about some aspects of the Glasgow Worldcon. There's quite a lot of discussion listeners,
so we're going to do letters of comment at the end if we have time and we suspect we will not
have time and we'll come back to it in episode 118. But please keep writing, we still love you.
So Glasgow, we're going to be at Glasgow listeners and we're going to do some programme.
So Octothorp has a table talk which is at 11.30am on Saturday the 10th of August and we have a
live recording which is at 11.30 in the morning on Monday the 12th of August. And so if you would
like to come to our table talk and just talk to us then please feel free to do so and then if you
want to listen to us do the pod then you can do that as well. Hoorah!
Please definitely come to our table talk if you are the sort of person who would not come
and approach us in the bar. If you're happy approaching us in the bar you can do that pretty much any
time. Whenever we're in the bar I don't know where that will be. Get a ribbon, if you're a listener
we'll all have ribbons I think. Oh yes. So come and find us and say I'm too nervous to talk to you
oh Octothorp people but can I have a ribbon. I'm on two panels, one about Ahsoka from the Star Wars
universe and another about safety tools for tabletop role-playing games. We will be putting
in the show notes the times and details of the panels but we won't be reading them out here
because they'll be very dull listeners. Look at the show notes if you'd like to know when they are
Alison and Liz what do you want at Worldcon? So I particularly want to plug the fan funds
as the Guffin administrator and we're having an auction on Saturday night at 8.30 um do come along
and bid on amazing things and there'll be a catalogue. There's also a reception for the fan
funds that you're all welcome to come to on Thursday afternoon pretty much straight after the opening
ceremony in the fanzine lounge which is being run by John's other half, this mania sheriff with
help from my other half Stephen Kane so that should be a good place during the convention to hang out
in the in in hall 4 which is kind of the big social hall at the convention. I am also on Thursday
running a maker fanzine workshop for a Glasgow 2024 fanzine and then I am on some panels one on
how to generate and increase your podcast. How do you keep your podcast exciting and
build an audience and I mean obviously this is a spoiler but our answer to this is have a
wuss for business meeting agenda with 50 items on it that we can talk about. I'm on a panel about
history Scottish fanzines and I am on a panel about fanzine covers. I'd obviously love to see
any of you at all of them. I'm not doing anything at Worldcon apart from the tabletop
tabletop and the live podcast recording so if you want to see me at Worldcon that's where you can
find me. Listeners I am in charge of making sure people on the Glasgow discord talk enough.
This is a bit like having a czar in charge of water being wet in that I was quite worried about
it before we opened the discord then the discord opened and I was like oh people are quite happy
quite happy to talk on the discord as it turns out but I am running a couple of activities to
encourage people into the discord. I'm running a play along of if we ran the zoo con which will be
on on the discord as a choose your own adventure style thing with discord polls and I'm also running
a scavenger hunt which by the time this episode drops both of those will be in full flow and
for anyone who remembers our episode on if I run the zuc on I'm doing all different scenarios you
will see different parts of the game please come and join. Yeah it's busy just go on innit.
I want to give some credit the discord strongly encouraged people to post something about themselves
in the members directory and they called it members directory to make it clear that you can
go and look people up and see who they are if you're chatting to them about a thing.
This is a really good idea or all phallish discord should do this I love it and it has led to a
lot of people so you discover that people do all sorts of things and are coming from all
different parts of the world in a very exciting way so it's good.
Glasgow 2024 have removed 377 votes from the hugos because they believe that it was a coordinated
act of vote stuffing by not real people a lot of people had obviously made up names when they
purchased their wuss was membership and they have removed those votes and re tallied the
category they have not they were all voting for a particular finalist they did not have
evidence that that finalist was involved in the attempt to stuff the ballot so they have
not removed them there's a full statement about this which you can see on will put a link to
the statement on their website and it seems to have got to have fairly well as a statement of
well this is clearly transparent and we're glad that you took this action and have told us that
you've done it um we'll probably never know what exactly went down but people have been trying to
work it out for from data that they have available to them all over the internet so if you're interested
that you can follow the trail of tea leaves yes indeed we condemn the attempt to stuff the ballot
and we applaud Glasgow's robust transparent and decisive action in this matter yeah and they did
a great thing as well which is that they started off by talking to the finalist concert to let them
know that they were invalidating these votes and then they whole held a meeting with all of the
hugo finalists has said you need to know about this before we release the press release which was
i thought thoughtful unkind and it other that meeting had not just all of the wussfus division
it but also um the chair and the promotions head and so on so it clearly took it very serious yes
yes and exactly when like you know when you and when you announce this there is going to be a lot
of speculation about who the person is or well who the finalist concerned is and you know that might
spill over to other completely uninvolved finalists and so it's nice to give them a heads up to say
look this is coming we want you to be aware before you read the press release along with everyone
else in the world so thank you Glasgow who are generally being very nice to finalist yes
at Glasgow there will be a series of incomprehensible meetings listeners if you
have attended a world-con business meeting before you know what i'm talking about but if you are new
to world cons or business meetings or science fiction family generally then we will never to
explain no but people often believe if they're not into world cons that there is an elite shadow
eacoball that controls the hugos and there is it's true and let us tell you all about it for two hours
every day at the world con there is a meeting which lasts usually about three hours but this year
will last five hours which basically does an awful lot of talking about how world cons should work
and they use parliamentary rules to do this to make it as weird as it possibly can be and no
i'm not exaggerating as much as you think if you've never been to one any any advances on that
listen Alison i think it's worth saying look the business meeting lasts for quite long time
but you are not obligated to go to all of it you are perfectly allowed as long as you can kind of
sneak in and out quite relatively quietly to drop in and out of the business meeting when you happen
to be free like don't feel it is only for people who can commit to attending you know 100% of the
time it is okay to just pop in and out you might miss stuff you probably won't be able to time it
so that if you want to see a particular thing be discussed you'll be there for it but it is okay
to kind of you know participate in parts of it and not the full thing so if you want a gentle
introduction you know you can go along one day and you don't have to stay for the whole five hours
yeah and i think it's also important to note that you don't have to go at all if you don't want to
like it is fine i'm not judging i will probably go to at least some of it because i care too much
about some of this stuff more than it's healthy but yeah i'm not going to judge if other people
quite reasonably decide they'd rather just have a nice convention it would be it would be interesting
if some octa thought member turned out to be a stalwart of business meeting fandom a couple of
years down the line octa thought listener i mean i'm sure there are some listeners who go to a lot
of business meeting stuff and but i don't think there's many who are going to challenge us on it
being kind of very difficult to know what's going on world con have published the business
meeting agenda you want to hear what christopher j garsia's thoughts were on this i've put a link
to his deep dive into his opinions on each of their um agenda items um and if anyone knows of
any other deep dives along those lines please let me know and i will amend the show notes to include
them on a previous episode which was probably either episode 95 or 96 but the show notes are
inadequate nor he passed john we discussed the chengdu business meeting and uh day from karti's
last minute surprise uh to invalidate online uh or to invalidate any attempt to take the business
meeting online in future world cons um there are resolutions that are a direct result of him
doing that and those resolutions are c1 c3 c4 and you're already having fun listeners yeah i mean
there's just going to be an hour of this now so by all means we'll see you in Glasgow
come to our table talk if you're currently not enjoying this it won't get better
that the auger thought guarantee and at our table talk we promise not to talk about the
weswesfus business meeting we do not promise not to talk about the weswesfus meeting guys
c1 basically says you can try and post the pwn emotion indefinitely at the main business
meeting the first time it's brought and that would change it from it only being possible at
the preliminary business meeting um so it's basically another opportunity to get things off
the agenda if you don't think they should be on the agenda c3 restricts a business that can be
submitted by surprise effectively it would mean you can't do it without unanimous consent and c4
which i think is the one i want to discuss most is the amendment to the standing rules that would
basically remove standing rule 7.9 and i think we all know that that is the rule on proxy and
remote voting and so it would explicitly strike that and would allow proxy voting again and thus
move in the direction of remote participation which i as anyone who's listened to an episode of
what i thought before and god if this is your first one i'm so sorry but i enthusiastically
support this motion go back and listen to the last episode it was better or the next one that
will be better with my slight parliamentary hat on i'm going to point out that these are
divided into two categories ones which are about not letting this sort of thing happen again
and the one which is about repealing the thing that got done last year
yeah it shouldn't have happened nothing a change is big as they shouldn't have happened without
ratification um we've talked about it before and so i'm very much in favor of um the repeal one and
i don't care what was it what what was just us to sort it out i'm less excited by the by the
nuts and bolts of making business meetings work than the others are yeah i'm in favor of these let's
repeal things so we can at least try a virtual business meeting if it turns out to be terrible
then we can have another opinion on it but i think at this point we've got at least try to you know
reach the 20th century yep oh 21st century probably i don't think they were doing remote
business meetings in like 1901 and c4 segues into a number of motions which are targeted at
changing the way the business meeting works so d9 would set up a study group to review the rules
over participation in the business meeting it would assess alternatives to rules of order
it would assess remote participation and it would assess whether or not it's possible to schedule
the business meeting separately from the world con and then f14 and 15 would bring in popular
ratification so instead of things being ratified by the next business meeting they would be ratified
by popular votes so the next work on would run a popular virtual then we put the same way that the
movie one is doing are we going to talk about the movie yeah we talked about in this one at least
90 days before the first preliminary business meeting um so so yes in the run up and then f15
basically sets up secondary business meetings and they would be online business meetings that would
happen as well as the primary business meeting which would be the business meeting we currently
have so what do we think about these i mean i think first i think they're not going to get
debated this year because there is too much debate in the business meetings i think we should know
that the business meeting timings have changed from being the usual 10 to 1 p.m to being 10 a.m to 3 p.m
a Glasgow so that is like 20 hours of business meeting or i guess more importantly if you want
to be there and taking part that is like your entire days basically spent in the business meeting
it is i think too much and something has to change i quite like popular ratification but i'm i'd be
interested to see how this kind of test vote at Glasgow works first um if you are not a Glasgow
member or haven't done this yet they're basically holding a sort of popular vote on where you can
vote yes or no to ratification of one particular bit of business passed on from Chengdu which is
the independent film categories in the hugos and then they will report back did people vote in it
did they vote yes did they vote no i think that will give us an indication of how like a popular
ratification vote might work and so then we can use that to decide how we feel about popular
ratification more generally which i think i'm kind of in favor of it brings in the whole membership
rather than a few but i can also see problems with it people are very worried about popular
ratification for all the reasons that people worry generally about referendum and popular
democracies i'm actually i've taught quite a lot of people including quite a lot of people who
are not bussifers nerds about the indie film vote and i'm quite encouraged by what i'm hearing
because people are reading the statements and and drawing conclusions i think are reasonable about
them so i'm hoping that will be reflected in the vote yeah i think in general i'm pro popular
application and i'm deeply against f15 which is the um secondary business meeting idea because
i think the reason to have the business meeting online is so that it can eventually take the
business meeting away from the world con and have it separately so that people don't have to take
time out of their world con to do it and i think this would explicitly mean that the world con one
was was given primacy over any online participation and i have a severe philosophical objection to that
and i like d9 because d9 basically says why don't we go away and try and form consensus and come back
with a single care and proposal and i like that more of that yeah i don't believe we can ever form
consensus on this issue but i think a study group is probably the only sensible way forward here
i think all of the proposals on this agenda that essentially offer a solution
queueing out of cloth by one faction oh i i i'll never gonna be the way and we need to do a little
bit better do we want to go from here to independent film if you are a wussfus member Glasgow has
written to you to invite you to vote in a consultative vote on the two independent film new hugo
categories that were got their first pass last year in chen do and are up for ratification this
year the deadline for voting will have gone by the time you listen to the podcast but we did want to
talk about it briefly both because it represents the way forward for as i said a trial run for the
popular ratification proposal but also because we as have mentioned before we have
thinks about these hugos which is that while we're not averse to independent film is some way
being recognized these are not the right models because they're very very confusing when you go
and vote you've got a little statement in favor from the proposals of the hugos and a statement
against which was written by olav rocke and amanda wackarock friends of the podcast and
which i thought was very good but it missed my favorite argument against
these categories which is that they do not partition the hugos and we try where possible
to make sure you can one thing that you do is only ever eligible for one hugo we don't always
manage it but normally normally the hugos are pretty good about that and these did not do that
i very much want these hugos not to get ratified so this is my big hope for the business meeting
which i have to say i'll probably not be at any of though i was hoping to be at this bit of it so
we'll see do you have anything to say on this i agree with alison i think i'm not necessarily
against rewarding short cinema at the hugos and i think like a best dramatic presentation very short
form would be fun like i'm not saying i think best dramatic presentation is perfect as is i just
think this is deeply imperfect in a way that i don't think fixes any of my problems with the
category and i think in practice most of the interesting cinema i would like to reward is short
film so you could very easily achieve this by having a time-based definition that would do
something very similar for short indie movies but yeah so i i am broadly against this one yeah i think
what i would need to be positively in favor of this is a list over the past few years of things they
think that would have been good nominees and finalists and then i can see whether it would
have been at all feasible for me to see any of them because that's a problem you're trying to reward
these these indie films which really don't get a lot of distribution and then it's like well if
no one can actually watch them then it's going to be very hard for people to to nominate them
so there's that i think i could also go with a very short film category but you've got to be
careful to kind of have a big kind of a gap so that very short films go in there but it doesn't
include like 22 minute episodes of animated shows if that's what you want to keep into short form
so it's hard to kind of have a thing that gets the best of like indie sf short films but doesn't
just get token over by like six episodes of lower decks or something yeah the other thing i think
you could do is simply have a category which explicitly rules out episodes of television
because i think it's relatively easy to define a television series in a rigorous way and that
would be the other way of doing it yeah but i i feel like you'd be at risk from worldcon related
youtube videos and things of that sort as well so you know i have two other things which are
basically i don't know how easy it would be for Hugo voters to actually watch any independent
short films because none of the film festivals really allow remote participation including sci-fi
london which is the one written by one of the people that suggested this double category
and was online during the pandemic and has gone back to not being online which is frustrating
and the other thing is i'm not sure how aware the Hugo electorate are of independent cinema in a way
that i i don't know whether it makes sense for our opinions like are we going to actually
award any good stuff or is it going to be a category which has limited participation so i think the
thing i would want to see is if we want to reward short independent films i would want the people
who are advocating for that to work on educating the worldcon membership about those before trying
to get it on the Hugo awards and doing it the other way around smacks of self-interest to me
it feels like unfortunately this would be a great fit for an award where you had a jewellery
nomination stage and then a popular vote final stage and that's not possible in the Hugo
system at the moment we can change anything in the wistford's constitution if we try harder
than maybe the episode i agree with everything that you've both said but i'd also like to add
that one thing that the worldcons could be doing to promote short film is getting more of it on
the program having a short film program having more stuff that's about short film and getting
you know the world calls it a great place to find some great short films and and present them as a
as a freebie for the members in advance and say we've chosen 10 excellent short films made in
the city that we're in here go and look at them guys yeah there's nothing stopping a worldcon from
having a kind of short film competition as part of what it does and i'd love to see that shall
we move from here on to extended eligibility yeah and so speaking of independent cinema the
wistford's constitution basically allows for what is called extended eligibility items that receive
extremely limited distribution in the year of first publication or presentation the eligibility
may be extended for next year by a two-thirds vote of the business meeting and so every year there are
some resolutions for extending the eligibility usually of these kind of small and independent
films which have had like a few showings at film festivals or maybe a limited release overseas
and giving them an extra year and i am basically favor this i think in general maybe we should just
say anything which only been released at film festivals you're getting extra year by default
um but this year there's a couple that i think are really pushing the definition of limited
availability and those are proposals to extend the eligibility of the boy in the heron and godzilla
minus one both films which came out kind of at the end of 20 23 and my problem is this is that
when they say did not receive wide theatrical release until late in 2023 this is true but the
boy in the heron came out on december 8th and made 35 million dollars in the us and godzilla
minus one came out on december the first and made 45 million dollars in the us by the end of 2023
according to numbers that i fished out of box office mojo so that to me is not limited availability
and also i think we should remember that we are not actually nominating on december 31st people
can still be watching these films in january and february and nominating them and i think the
really strong counter argument against this one is that poor things which is a finalist was you know
also released in december in the us and made less money than either the boy in the heron or godzilla
minus one and still made it onto the ballot so i argue that they were available enough that people
could have nominated it and i think kind of this is stretching it quite a bit and we just end up
with an eligibility extension where anything released in december in the us um on thousands of
cinema screens could then be eligible for next year which i'm not sure it needs and it's the same
because i really love godzilla minus one but i think it has burned its eligibility which let's
be clear most smaller movies are released in december it's the normal time to release your
awards darlings and then anyone who's seriously into film can see those on cinema screens in january
and february in good time to nominate as liz says i think we'll look at we also get a fine for
both the boy in the heron and godzilla minus one that people did nominate those movies in quite
large numbers just not insufficient numbers to get on the ballot and really it's just saying
can we have two bites of cherry for anything we like please and i
can see the minus one was very good it would have been on my ballot if i'd seen it in 2023 but you
know if they wanted me to see it in 2023 they could have released it in july i think the other
thing liz said was i don't think it would be a bad idea so allison i think said this earlier in the
episode which is she would like see the business meeting basically discuss far more as much as you
can away from the business meeting that doesn't really need to be discussed at the business meeting
and i think going through individual films being like was it only shown at a film festival it can
be eligible in this year then like just make that put it in the constitution because as allison is
remarked elsewhere that's how the oscars do it so why not the huco awards so some films get a very
limited distribution in theaters specific in december like not two thousand screens like ten
screens specifically so they will be eligible for the oscars in in that year um the the streaming
first movies do this and the notion that we should be doing something totally different for
for world cons is a bit weird also when we're talking about things that you could do
by not by popular ratification this seems like an excellent example of something you could do
by popular vote well in advance for the world con i just not have it trouble the world so there
have been a bevy of um things brought to the business meeting about the huco awards as one
might expect from what happened and last year d 10 would establish a huco process study committee
which would think about the huco awards very hard and come back with some recommendations
one of the things it would think very hard about is third party administration of the huco awards
f5 basically says if you disqualify or move anything under the relevant section you would have to
publish and explain that with the statistics f6 would basically make a huge number of amendments
to introduce a body called wsa which i don't know what it actually stands for because i don't
think they define the acronym no they don't but they they basically say this would be some
independent body which would replace the mark protection committee and would administer the
huco awards f7 would mean that you can't remove things it would add a new thing which means you
can't remove a work for a reason not in the constitution unless required in local law
and if it was required if it was done for that reason there would be a retrohugo five years
afterwards f8 would is just terrible we'll go into why but it's a really really poor amendment
and should die in a fire jon jon tell us what you really think f9 would let you disqualify
huco administrators which i originally put in the show notes under the don't do that
dave resolutions but moved later but it is basically a don't do that dave resolution as well and then
f11 would establish a elected subcommittee which would do auditing of the site selection and huco
award processes and report back to whether or not they were done properly or not any any
disagreements with the way i've summed that up i just want to say that this section contains some
of the my all-time least favorite was for business meeting agenda items and and there is no amount
of pointy fire that is sufficient for some of them yeah so let's go so any of us any of us against
having a committee i mean the whole point of committees is that why would you be against it so
i'm pro committee i guess okay so committees are slow and people want blood now that's the argument
against a committee it could take a few years for the committee to get to some sensible point
look how long the load start up but now we do have the load start so you know it's okay but
yeah no obviously we want to committee we're in favor of doing less action aren't we guys
i was certainly don't like any of these other ones so yeah now i am in favor of a committee i
just worry that committees are where things go to die and i think this year we might have potentially
this committee a committee on like reforming the business meeting and a potentially a committee on
the center resolutions and that might be just a lot of committees and not enough people to actually
run them and do a lot of work in a year and report back and i fear this is dragging on and it might
be like 2027 before we get anything but in general i think this is a good one to take to committee
if only for the fact that there are like five different amendments submitted that all do slightly
different things in slightly different ways and maybe we should pick one yeah so one of the things
that i said i think it was me who said it but i think was said was said on the podcast anyway
after Chengdu was like i want to see sort of widespread consultation in whatever the solutions
are to these problems and then one of the problems i think is that there have been groups of people
who have tried to talk to other people but they haven't had the breadth of scope to be able to
talk to everyone and i think the advantage with the committee that's actually a part of the business
meeting is that they could do things like ask the seated world con to distribute a consultation
survey and so i think this is an imperfect way of getting what i want but i can't see a better way
of getting what i want so i think i do support it while agreeing with Liz that i have worries about
committees being where things go to die so yeah i think that's well well said Liz
i do slightly worry about our ability to run good committees in this space that there's a there's
not that many people who are that good at this stuff and they are already working pretty hard on
on the business meeting stuff we've already got that's my only caveat though because i think
this has to be a committee it's going to take a couple of years we just have to get it right
and some of the other ones i'm also kind of looking at them with the angle of all right if this was
in place last year what would it have done and i guess the illegal exclusions one would say
we can run some retros in 2028 for certain categories in 2023 which i don't think would be great to be
honest i don't really like the using of the retro hugos which were established to like fill gaps
as a way to kind of make good on things we have subsequently messed up on if only because i think
if you do that in 2028 so you rerun the 2023 you know astounding award in 2028 i think definitely
the person who was excluded in 2023 is going to win weren't i'd also it is i think you would need
to pass f8 to make f7 make any sense and that's basically the one where if you if you if you if
you remove anyone from the ballot then the entire category is not run and it just it seems like
an absolute mess and this is exactly why i'd like a committee to go away and think about it properly
because i don't think this actually helps so i am against f7 and f8 on that basis yeah i think
the risk of f8 is you disqualify someone without citing a clause the constitution or something or
say you do disqualify someone and you made a mistake but you then basically say to the other
finalists tough no order here and that seems a bit heavy-handed because it's not the other finalists
fault i i i think it would create even more bad feeling towards the hugo awards from creators
who are already pretty pissed off with us we skipped over f5 and f6 f5 is the one that stipulates
that you have to publish your disqualifications but it says that you have to publish them with the
statistics published as required in section 312-3 and i don't like that because i like the way
Glasgow did it and in general i think the business meeting should hue to the way world cons are
choosing to solve problems rather than trying to solve them in a different way and force the
world con to change i think there should be a thing saying you have to publish any moves or
disqualifications and you have to explain why you did it i i would just like it to have a little
bit more flexibility as to when the world con actually announces that and i think there's probably
that that that might be able to be ironed out in the meeting when they discuss this hard degree on
this what what Glasgow has done in terms of hugo transparency is it seems to be just about perfect
to me and and should be a model for future world cons yeah i think you could say must be published
like at the latest with the statistics but you can choose to publish earlier and that would be a
small change to the wording and would be fine agreed f6 i don't like because it makes up a new body it
doesn't actually say what the body is it replaces the mark protection committee but it doesn't seem
to replace the duties of the mark protection committee or basically it's just a mess it's a
badly badly written mess this is one of the reasons why i think we need a committee uh i
would vote against just i think it's i i respect what it's trying to do i just think it does what
it's trying to do extremely badly would our marks be unprotected if this best look right mark plumber
is a guest of honor and is this how we repay him by ceasing his protection for shame listeners
for shame any other thoughts on f6 other than boo it's very long oh it's it's just
i mean it's just terrible i i mean one of the things that worries because because of having done
a job that involved a lot of government drafting not not legal drafting but but you know writing
things that are clearer say what you mean them to say i don't think it's a skill we're that great
at in fandom and i don't know how we get the people who are good at it onto the committees that they
need to be on to make this stuff good but this is not good there are two types of people in the world
there are people who do not mind appearing less intelligent than they are because they explain
things in a way that is understandable and there are people who are very keen that you understand
exactly how clever they are and they word things in ways which are incomprehensible to reinforce
their status and fandom is very full of the latter in ways that make it difficult because
a lot of these discussions revolve around people showing how big they're basically showing how big
them business meeting penises surely you mean business meeting brain john no no i definitely
think i mean penis i think i think the problem is that it turns out the mark protection committee
is like you basically have to go through and find everywhere you mentioned the mark protection
committee and replace it and so some of it is just minor changes there but it's quite complicated
and then you have to do things like okay well if the wall con committee has these powers which
we're now going to delegate to wussf which epigems will science fiction awards or something
then it just gets complicated but yeah i worry that this is not the way to set up a committee
which they also say potentially has paid staff they say they will be supported by mark licensing
fees paid by will con and they give like percentage of membership fees i went and figured out and for
Glasgow i think it means they would have got a budget of about 18 000 pounds i'm not sure if
that's actually enough to do anything with paid staff by the other hand it would be a lot of money
to not use in a sensible way if it turns out we haven't set this committee up correctly
so i think this really does need a lot of intensive study i've just had a comment thought on that
18 000 pounds which is that it's it's not it's not merely not enough it's not enough by at least one
and possibly two orders of magnitude i don't think they have any idea how much it would cost to retain
professionals in this area well it doesn't specify what you'd have the professionals doing it might
be enough to get like you know like the legal advice on the trademarks or whatever it's not
enough for natural paid staff but it might do a round of auditing on a very simple thing or
something like that or just like someone professional looking at the accounts that should be within it
but i mean that's supposedly five percent of every wussfers membership so i think if you
upped it much people would start to get a bit like really f9 disqualifies Hugo administrators
who are romans in favor i'm in favor but i also just keep thinking okay so what if
hypothetically we had another world con in two years time which decided to appoint
Dave McCarty as Hugo administrator at this point we then basically get to okay so you've declared
just that that declares themselves to be an incompetent world con but they know that's going
to happen so kind of what what are the sanctions basically and i think it's very tricky like what
would happen if another con did decide to go rogue what could we realistically do about that
and i think the problem is we don't really have sanctions for that because it's not something
we generally thought would occur i don't like this partly because of the lack of sanctions and
partly because you just redefine the role so that he was in a slightly different role but nevertheless
had the power and also i worry about banning people from working on world cons when it's
you know getting good people to work on world cons is a problem even though obviously i don't
personally think Dave McCarty should be Hugo administrator again i think having a process that
doesn't exclude the bad actors will make it harder to get good people to work on world cons and not
easier i understand the sentiments but i think if you have a organization which is riddled with
corruption it is hard to get people interested in working for that organization who do not want
to be associated with corruption and so i think the answer to that is making sure you don't have
the corruption i think this acts in the direction of more good people i do agree with Liz there's no
way of sanctioning realistically there's no teeth to the constitution but that's true anyway so i
don't know i don't know i think you ought to wear with what you can i will also say i think that
the idea of the world's constitution is to set up what we want the world come to look like and i
think even if a committee did basically say well you can be the Hugo administrator but Dave's going
to tell you what to do on the secret and if you tell anyone we'll shout your kneecaps like i think
that's impossible to avoid but i think making it clear that we don't want that to be how it is
is valuable because it sends a message i think we've probably recapitulated the business
mutual discussion at least in part on that topic and i think i will be interested to see where this
one ends up this is one of the amendments that i thought was quite interesting but it might just
get dumped into a committee with the rest of the committee things so i've got thoughts against it but
if it passes i won't be upset i just think it probably won't do a lot but maybe it's fine to have
that symbol in the constitution anyway and then f11 f11 yes which is the last one
oh we sort of set up an extra committee more committees yeah we set up a sort of monitoring
committee of people independent from the next two world cons who form a committee and report back
on anything they observed in Hugo and site selection voting or presumably if they are not allowed to
see any of the figures then their report back that this will come didn't let's see anything
i think i'm kind of in favor of this although it seems like a lot of committees still but i think
having like imagined that 2026 and 2027 have a an observation committee formed of three previous
Hugo administrators or something because if we're letting these people then probably presumably
the people who have been good Hugo administrators will be first in line yeah it could be quite good
i was just thinking about probably Hugo administrators and considering the fact that that might end up
with ferrets in a sack but it's possible that that one of the ferrets wouldn't be invited to be one
of the three people yeah i suspect that if the business meeting is voting on who gets to be on
this subcommittee you know we won't like vote for our own destruction probably i just have this
image when liz was like Hugo administrators and it could be good i just had this image of liz like
patting Hugo administrators on my head going who's a good Hugo administrator who's a good Hugo administrator
oh yeah now i have a new art prompt because yeah so we broadly speaking in favor of f/11
i think so unless by passing this we make the job of whatever committee that comes up in d9
more complicated i i think this should be limited to the committee that's the the committee of the d9
as one of the things that they're looking at i will say i think it's evidence in favor of having
committees to look at this stuff the various motions that have been proposed by the mark
protection committee are fairly sane and well considered and i would hope that that would
extend to other committees as well i i think i'm sort of broadly in favor of f/11 but might want
it to be committee motions d11 to d14 concern the shenanigans at chengdu more directly um two of them
are um redacted from the agenda i'll come on to that in a second one is an apology
um which we will discuss the meaning of that and then one basically explicitly means that the
works removed will be designated finalists despite not appearing on the ballot the reason the two that
are redacted are redacted is because scottish defamation law effectively means that if you can show
damage to reputation then you are guilty of defamation unless you can prove the same as you made it true
and Glasgow have sought legal advice and decided that they would be best not to publish this text
themselves text is available online um one of them's on par 770 and the other i think is in the
business meeting discord i will endeavor to put links to both of them in the show notes and it will be
discussed at the meeting but it won't be kind of officially published by the worldcom there's been
quite a lot of hand-wringing over this from some people i basically think it's a very unfortunate
situation that has been handled as transparently as humanly possible which stands in stark contrast
to the actions of some previous people in which things were handled with much less transparency
in ways that made me cross so that is my thoughts there Alison and Liz what are your thoughts
i mean on the resolutions or on the you know on any of it on on the like you know not publishing
the full content of these resolutions and discussing them like in a i think unfilmed and
unstreamed bit of the business meeting yeah i mean it seems fair enough i'm not legal expert but i
do remember that worldcom 76 spent an awful lot of money to resolve a defamation case and i suspects
all the other world cons have looked at that and gone boy we really do not want to be in that
situation where we spent several years and tens if not hundreds of thousands of dollars on this and
have taken legal advice and gone for the absolute safe route and i can't really blame for it i
agree with that i am sad to see that this part of the business meeting will not be streamed because
as as you know bob i'm very much into the business meeting in general becoming as online as it
possibly can and the free streaming of business meetings well i can't actually attend the world
con is one of the things i particularly like about modern world cons because i generally attend all
of the business meeting in the years i'm not at the world but this worldcom made the decision to
not require wis
but i am in favor of passing a resolution one of these resolutions to basically say
look what happened last year is not something the business meeting grieves of and approves of
and we apologize to those people who are affected i think i'd also be okay with adding those people
to the official finalist list as a you know a gesture which cannot make up for being excluded
from the actual finalist list but i go back and forth on that one i think it's a shame we've got
like four resolutions and not maybe one resolution but that's just how things have gone this year we
have a lot of kind of competing and slightly overlapping resolutions and amendments i mean
yes that's not uncommon for wis just business meeting agendas and and the way that the the way
that the organization works almost compels that if you've got different views or things you're
going to get competing amendments i would like to see a motion of censure past in sub form i want
to say that clearly me too if you had to pick one of these which one would it be
i mean i don't have 11 and 12 to hand because they're not in the agenda i'd have to go and get
them back off of file 17 17 but i am perfectly happy with d 13 which i think kind of overlaps
quite a bit with d 14 despite having the same proposal in one case well i think d 14 is designed
to d 14 is designed to make sure that those things are listed as finalists even if d 13 does not pass
i suspect the intention is to let people go along with the finalists bit even if they don't
want the apology bit but i think i want the apology bit so like yeah i think i'd just split
them have an apology and then have the finalist bit rather than having a both and then a half of
it but anyway happy to pass both of those i don't like the wording of d 13 which i think is
a flowery in that kind of roberts fools parliamentarian way that winds me up quite often
so but i would like a simpler apology apologies are best the short when they're nice and short
whereas i agree with allison and whereas i think that was a good point
um be it resolved that octa thought considers d 13 to be good but bit flowery yes um all those in
favor say aye aye aye no i'm trying to push this to a serpentine vote here
what serpentine vote great on radio one two three hey there we go okay it was unanimous listeners
who wants to introduce wispous memberships and stuff so there's f1 and f2 the first one is
about what you do if people accidentally purchase duplicate wispous memberships and the second one
is basically saying instead of saying wispous membership and attending supplement we go back
to supporting membership and attending membership and i'm not super i'm not super concerned by either
although i do like how f2 just says you know if we pass this go and change it back to the old
terminology throughout the constitution rather than listing every single place in the constitution
where we have to change it yeah i mean i don't think this actually changes the new thing where
you have the wispous membership and the attending supplement on top and you can't ever sell that
wispous membership unless voting has not opened i mean i was in favor of them all being more
transferable anyway but i understand it's apparently awkward to deal with i just feel sorry for all
the people who bought wilcom memberships and are now selling them at glass you know selling
their Glasgow memberships at the last minute and can't sell the wispous bit i don't know i think both
of these are probably like things that we should talk about but maybe not this year so i oppose
considering them but if they get considered i'd probably in favor of f2 in Nicholas White's
early commentary on the agenda which we're linking to he says about some other items
some of this stuff matters but it's not for this year this year needs to concentrate on
cleaning up from last year and i absolutely agree with that and this is an example of something
that can wait yeah i mean i'll say that Chengdu passed on an unusually high number of items to be
ratified before we even start on the new business and new resolutions so it was going to be
quite a lot anyway and i think we just have to postpone anything that's not completely vital in
order that we at the business meeting actually gets everything done in time i say we i'm not
going to go to the whole business meeting i might go to parts of it but i'm not spending 20 hours
thinking about Robertsville de Vore. The mark protection committee have submitted f3 and f4
so f3 provides explicit licensing of the wiswers marks and this comes up as a result of Kevin
Sandley's comments last year about wiswers marks and how they run enforceable and some very uh
enlightened people pointing out that that means that they can't be trademarks then because that's
not how trademarks work and this is a attempt to bring the wiswers constitution in line with
u.s trademark law and therefore i support it i think it probably is important enough to be in
the mix this year and then the other one is they would quite like to be able to let mark protection
member mark protection committee members force meetings of the mark protection committee and
they would also like a mechanism for removing members of the mark protection committee and that's
a direct result of the many shenanigans that had to go through for the mark protection committee to
be able to do anything with the four people they sent showed earlier in the year and i think this
is probably also something that we need to do so yeah broadly speaking in favor of f3 and 4
how are you guys yeah it seems like we basically had a committee that sort of ticked along and
norm was particularly concerned about it and then when it did become a big thing we realized that
there were lots of handy mechanisms that should really be in place for any committee which were
not and so this is an effort to tidy them up which is good and i do not know enough about the um
i i mean i know a little about u.s trademark law but not enough to really comment here so i'm
going to say if the mark protection committee think these changes are necessary then i think i'd
agree with that so we have f10 which makes another committee and it is a committee basically
that makes a Hugo oversight committee and a Hugo software advisory committee and so the first one
is about more oversight of the Hugo's and the second one is about oversight of the Hugo's software
i think the Hugo's software one is probably not necessary it just seems to add extra
extra levels in and i'm not convinced we need them the Hugo oversight committee is basically another
version of the Hugo committee we discussed earlier except instead of having members elected by the
business meeting it will be elected by the association of science fiction and fancy artists the science
fiction of fantasy rights association and the european s science fiction society which i mean
have we taught them do they care like if you're going to say to software by the way you now
appoint a member of the Hugo oversight committee meaning that your designated representative will be
responsible for oversight of the Hugo's i don't know what they would think about that so we should
probably check in with them on that i also worry that if we do this we i think we do need to make
sure that for at world cons that take place in non-anglophone locations we are able to select
enough people to be on those oversight committees who can really provide oversight yeah i mean it
should at very least be two amendments and i think we've just got too many competing Hugo oversight
amendments i will say i do definitely support having like sensible software to tabulate the Hugo's
and it not just being as we discovered a big random SQL query that devant gati runs but i'm not
sure having a software advisory committee is going to help because the number of people
qualified to be on that is probably small and maybe they're already writing the Hugo software so
kill this one pitch it back to the big committee see what the big committee say yep site selection
changes so f12 basically acts to disenfranchise anyone who might want to join our community so
you probably tell my opinion on that from the way i've described it
and f13 f13 attempts to make sure that countries that hold the world con are countries that are a
good fit for the world con and it does that through looking at the reporters without borders global
score the freedom house freedom in the world data set and the economist intelligent units
democracy index and like i see i see the point but i think this is exactly the sort thing that i
would quite like to be discussed in committee rather than trying to hash out the details
at the business meeting at the world con because i think this is one of those things where
where you draw those lines probably needs quite a lot of discussion and i yeah i don't know i
mean i feel like if i wouldn't want the world con going to a country whose um
whose president was on record at saying they were playing to ban elections in the next four years
so you know that's a start so i assume that i don't know how the democracy index is calculated
but i assume that if if um the elections in the united states went away the united states would
go down in its democracy index score but yeah chris has done some quite good analysis on this
actually and said look at what the countries that they don't like having covered i think we can't
escape it in that we're you know if you look at these three i think they've chosen three different
indexes you know because you only have to pass one of these indexes to be you know a place which
is eligible to bid for a world con and what you can't escape is that on those three indexes it is
the kind of the same countries which are coming up poorly in all of them and they are mostly not
ones which have traditionally held world cons and they are mostly lower middle income countries
you know especially in africa and parts of asian so i don't think you can really like we can't on
you can't disentangle these things i think is the tricky one like it is just a fact that there are
more kind of authoritarian regimes in those places but i don't know whether there are other
indexes we could be looking at or if these three are really the best and that's exactly why i'd
like to see this be in committee it also doesn't cover the issue where you've got a country that
is a federation of states say where human rights varies and democracy varies quite a lot between
the states and that could that could become an issue i mean just say america we know you know you
mean the USA i don't think it necessarily just means america if if the EU ever managed to get to the
state it wants to be then then or the united Arab Emirates yeah but i don't think any of the
you know uae constituent states would pass right i think we've digressed anyway we had a bid
we had a bid that was Saudi Arabia and like it did not win do we want to rely on
bids in countries that are very bad for human rights just being defeated at the ballot box
or do we want to have some rules i don't know whether 60 60 and 6 are the right levels and i
don't know whether these are the right indices but i'm not inherently against the idea of trying
to make sure that there is some safeguard but what i would say is that if you're only passing on one
metric if things get reevaluated the next year it could be tricky so two things i want to say i
think one of these is because after the change in will come a lot people came along and said you know
why was china even allowed to bid for a world con and lots of people said well that's just how
it works anyone can bid for will come and this is a way of saying no look we have minimum standards
you cannot bid for will cons in places that don't meet these standards to kind of you know pass off
that argument and the second thing is that the timing is very unfortunate because if this gets
ratified so if this gets this gets passed this year and then ratified next year it would take
effect in 2026 which is exactly the year in which the first place to be disqualified under these
scores would be bidding because it's the year that Uganda would be bidding for 2028 so basically the
first effect of it would be to disqualify bid in its first year that it was there and it also means
that the Uganda bid are going to be basically waiting for a year to see if 2025 ratifies this
to know if they'll even be allowed to continue the bid so i don't think there's a way around that but
it's just going to be really unfortunate for them they will have to basically wait a year to decide
if they can continue bidding or maybe they'll just drop out early because of the uncertainty but yeah
i think like the first i think this coming into effect and the first thing it does is saying to
the first african will come bid um bye bye is a really unfortunate side side effect and then there's
when we censure you we mean it which basically means you can't put censured people on
bids or let them administer world cons or you can't write in for them on site selection ballots
etc but basically trying to take people that have been censured by the business meeting out of
world con running which i think we've already discussed but um but yeah and then there's
ratification and then we're done yes so Chengdu passed a bunch of stuff which has gone for
ratification i have a suspicion that if the Chengdu business meeting had been bigger possibly fewer
things would have been passed on for ratification if for example online voting had been an option
so that people could come in and bus us members from around the world can participate remotely
e5 seems pretty unobjectionable it basically means if you are bidding for site selection you have to
have a postal address and an email address because these were passed last year there's no kind of
little explanation for why they should be on the ballot seems fair enough you have to have a
postal address is this so people can send you letters of complaint i don't know seems good let's
rify it e6 is the one where when you file your site selection ballot you have to include your
postal address email address and you may include a phone number and if you don't have your name your
signature or your postal address then your ballot is only counters no preference and this i think is
a reaction to all those Chengdu ballots that didn't have a postal address on by basically clarifying
the word address in the constitution to be postal and email when presumably it was when it was written
as just a dress didn't mean email address i don't think you really need someone's postal address to
know they're a person who exists and i don't know what you're going to do with postal addresses
anyway because what if i just write like john's house on my thing are you going to cross check it
with what i put in my membership form what if i moved house it just seems like an extra requirement
that we won't actually do anything with and is designed to close what people perceived of as a
loophole which probably wasn't loophole yes both both signature and postal address are very western
constructs so i mean i don't mind this probably is something that needs to go off to the big hugre
committee i don't mind having some requirement that means it is reasonably straightforward to
acetate that this is an individual you were being i don't know what that would be but it's not this
yeah you can't even say like a unique email address because people share email addresses within
families and so on i think i agree with allison like i i don't inherently oppose there being
more checks on whether people are natural persons especially given the news this year that there
wasn't attempted to stuff the ballot by non natural persons but i don't know whether this is it and
i would quite like it to be something that was thought through in a way that i felt better about
so then i think the next one that's interesting is the fancast not paying compensation so this would
mean that if a fancast paid its contributors or staff monetarily it would not qualify as a fancast
and i don't know what that means what is being paid is a patreon being paid yeah i don't think
this is probably being thought through do we do we know i think a patreon is being
paid i think i would argue it is but i'm worried that you could argue it isn't and i'm worried that
what i'm going to argue that it definitely isn't until the amount you get from the patreon exceeds
the costs of running the podcast that's the thing isn't it like if you take in an amount of money that
means you can't pay your contributors or staff is that does that mean that this doesn't qualify
and i don't know if that's clear from this i think that would be something that individual
administrators would have to rule on and so i think this makes it fuzzier not less fuzzy so i think
i'm against but i'm not sure i mean this has come from fanzine right like the wording in fanzine is
that you can't pay your contributors and stuff other than in copies of the magazine so i think it's
kind of lifted that language and i don't know of any fanzines that have patreons so i don't know if
that's a problem i mean i can see they're trying to do stuff like okay if we say we had a patreon
which got us enough money to pay an editor to professionally edit the podcast i can see that
would be like a disqualifying thing but if we got a patreon that just paid like we got 20 a month
that covered our hosting costs that seems like it shouldn't fundamentally disqualify us from
being a fan cast yeah i think i agree with that i think i would agree with a resolution that said
that my worry is that that is not this no but i think it's a case of there are some very clear
lines but then there's going to be cases which are much closer to the edge like maybe you have a
patreon that brings in 1,000 a year so that's more than you need for hosting or you know come to
be more than you need for say hosting and podcast expenses does that count but not like
money that you are living off should that count i would like to see a solution here that is
consistent across fan artist fan writer fanzine and fan cast thank you maybe we need a committee
for that as well e10 language requirement would change it so that at the moment if a work appeared
in a language that wasn't english then it's also eligible in the year in which it first was published
in english and if it work was published outside the united states it is eligible in the year in
which it is published in the united states and it changes that so that it's the languages of the
administering and prior world cons and it is the countries of the administering and prior world con
and this sounds very good but i wish it was as well as the united states and as well as english
because this year the world con is in scotland and last year it was in china and what this resolution
would do is mean that anything which hasn't yet had a uk release date but was published in the us
this year if this had taken effect that would not be eligible this year and then because there
won't be another british world con for ten years it would also mean it wasn't eligible next year
when it goes to seattle because it would already have been published in the us and so it would have
fallen out of the eligibility window in one direction for the uk and fallen out in the other
direction for the us and it would just never be eligible and i think that is a problem because i
think this is very well intentioned because it reduces the implicit assumption that most world
cons are held in the us but it does not address the problem which is most world cons are held in
the us which is still true even if you ignore it really hard and most welcome members come
from the world us even when the world con is not in the us and most dr thought listeners come from
the us really oh my god we know this we went we went through it on a previous episode in the
after show yeah i just think this will mean that interesting works that are not from the us have
a harder chance of being recognized and i think that will have the exact opposite effect to the
thing it is trying to do and i worry i'm meant to sit down and do like a grid of okay what if we have
world cons in say China followed by the uk followed by the us and all the different
publications and when they would be eligible but i didn't do it because it would be a very
boring spreadsheet but i am worried about edge cases that i haven't considered while being
thinking this is generally a good thing yeah so i think i might be against ratification until
someone can demonstrate to me that it doesn't end up disenfranchising things that would otherwise
have a chance effectively i would be entirely in favor of this amendment if it didn't have any
strike throughs and just had the word and a few more times yeah but this is now for ratification
so it can't be changed yeah that's the problem isn't it if only i had been able to participate
in last year's business meeting uh right and then it's as thick Liz you're our asian correspondent
yeah yes so this is the idea that we should have an asian science fiction convention i just haven't
quite i don't quite understand where like the pushes for this unless there are basically i would
want to see fandoms from a whole bunch of asian countries who really wanted this and even then
i'm not sure it makes sense to have it under the world con umbrella but i also think we should
abolish the nazvik anyway so i think i'm not in favor of this i am in favor of more conventions
and potentially will come supporting things like an asian science fiction convention either through
people assisting or by financial support and seed funding and so on but i don't think i'm in
favor of adding an extra thing that the will come is for some reason administrating in basically
every year because asian wilcons are pretty few and far between lizz is completely right i just
don't want a bunch of white people to go to asia and start running conventions there thinking
they're helping oh do you think this is what this was about i think this is about having a one i
think it's about pushing back against the fact that the constitution for some reason has the nazvik
and no equivalent in other places which is a historical anomaly we should correct and i think
this is about correcting it and also possibly about having a like wisface affiliated convention
in china more often if you had asphyx every couple of years and then a kz would bid for a world con
based on that that could be a success
picks next time we're going to do picks so we're going to do very quick picks or not do pick i think
we can not do picks to be honest it's going to be so long i think we can just say look come and see
us in clasco and in then we've got some picks you can do live in person picks by asking me and john
and allison in the bar what we like and what we've been reading and doing recently or at the table
talk or a table talk please sign up for a table talk or we'll feel silly also all of them are just
going to pick a generic thing anyway which was not science fiction related so there's no evidence
that the lake district isn't a spaceship that's been buried in the north of england-liss
yep first time for everything ah that was the old thought podcast and it's goodbye from me it's
goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
oh there's a big bee in my room no it's a wasp a giant wasp um we might need to pause for a minute
while i uh watch the wasp carefully liz liz looks quite worried about this it's really big
you've got a webcam liz show us the wasp show us the wasp show us the wasp
or don't make any sudden movements i thought they show you the wasp
ah the wasp is gone the wasp has gone back out the window we're good all right hey good wasp
so oh no the wasp the wasp is back okay it really is quite big um i'm just gonna run away
bye liz
hello sorry has has it been resolved yes it flew out the window and i have closed all the windows
uh cunning like a good like you know three or four centimeters long
anyway yeah and i don't come across wasp very often so i hope you enjoyed my wasp panic um
i'm gonna cut the episode now sorry i was trying i was trying not to enjoy it but i did enjoy it yeah
because i realized i didn't turn the camera off did i just disappeared and through the laptop to
one side yeah yeah sorry john was going to do the censure resolutions before we had a wasp um
intervention i've only just noticed the tobs cosigned one of these hi tobs yes i've never seen
your name in the wasp was business meeting agenda before this is a lovely surprise
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud and competec.com
used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
Thank you.