Liz: I do definitely need the water because I'm just gonna briefly send you a photo of the temperature sensor on the front of my fan.
John: *laughs*
My cold open joke got me a free book.
Thank you very much to listener Bridget, who I had said I'd pay postage for three Tade Thompson novels,
and she very kindly waived it because it was a good joke.
Liz: *laughs*
John: So thank you Bridget!
*music*
John: Hello everyone and welcome to the very 105th episode of Octothorpe.
This episode is coming to you on the 14th of March 2024.
I'm John Coxon.
Alison: I'm Alison Scott.
Liz: And I'm Liz Batty.
John: We heard from some people.
Alison: Ang wrote us a long interesting letter about the Hugo controversy,
which we're going to cover later when we talk about the Hugo controversy.
And meanwhile, she says she liked my Gregg Wallace reference so there.
John: It was a good Gregg Wallace reference once you had explained it to me and Liz,
both of whom had no idea about Gregg Wallace.
Alison:But who have now been sending me Gregg Wallace memes for four weeks, so you know.
John: Oh yeah, now we know about Gregg Wallace.
Like, now we're clued in.
Alison: I just, this is maybe the only time I understand the popular culture meme before either of you two do,
so I'm milking it.
Liz: We also got a letter from Andy Openshaw saying,
"Why is no one talking about *A Murder at the End of the World*?
I thought that was canny good and deserves to be in contention."
I did think about *A Murder at the End of the World*, but the ending is rubbish.
I mean, I think it is science fiction, but it's not at all interesting for its science
fictional elements.
It could be, but I think it kind of has too many flaws to really be interesting.
John: An example of this, I think, is the, there was a show called *The Resort* in 2022,
which was great and had genre elements, but kind of ended on a damp squib.
And I think, I think that was a similar thing where I would have loved to
nominate it, but ultimately I just felt like it didn't quite stick the landing in a way that made
it feel fulfilling.
And so like this, this can be a problem with limited SF shows.
So yeah, it's sad when it happens.
Liz: Yeah, I mean, I should say it's all about kind of, you know, the end of the world they're in is kind of
a tech billionaire's Icelandic hideout against climate change.
And it's got that kind of it is, you know, 10 seconds in the future thing going on,
but then in the end, I don't think it says anything super interesting about it.
And I had figured out the murder too early.
It's all right though.
Alison: But I had never even heard of it. So thanks for the recommendation.
John: And I, and Andy also messaged me on Saturday when we were both doing our Hugo nominations.
He messaged me asking why some things are listed in the long form tab of the Hugo Spreadsheet
of Doom and some things are listed in the short form.
And he was like, why? Why does that happen?
And I basically told him that it's whatever people reckoned they wanted to put on whichever tab.
There's no unified mind behind it.
And so it kind of gives you a clue as to where people are thinking of nominating things.
But yeah, there's not much more order than that.
John: When did you do your Hugo nominations peeps?
Liz: Couple of weeks ago.
Alison: So I did get up yesterday morning.
This was Saturday, thinking, oh, I should probably nominate for the Hugos today.
Let me check where the deadline is.
And then I got involved in many other things.
And then I remembered again.
And at that point it was 12 minutes past three.
The deadline was four o'clock and I was like, whoops, I hope the website doesn't go down.
But in fact, the website seemed very resilient and was having no problems with people who
left it to the last minute.
No doubt because there weren't very many of us and everyone else had done it in good time.
But I did it at three-fifteen and I was not the only one on, on our Discord server who had done it at three-
fifteen. So there we go.
And Steven didn't do it till three-forty-five and was then like, who should I nominate?
Do you have any ideas?
We were like, we made a list in the last Octothorpe, go look at that.
John: So Chris also speaks about the same mysterious thing that Ang spoke of.
So we will talk about that later.
But he also says Paul Doerr isn't Zodiac.
My dad would have known Doerr and it's quite possible I met him in my very young years.
Neither of us were murdered.
So it can't be him.
Thanks for writing in Chris.
What I love is Chris can drop names in any situation.
You need a name drop.
Chris Garcia is your guy.
Spacecraft: Chris Garcia, serial killer: Chris Garcia, anyone else in the world: Chris Garcia.
Alison: Old computers.
John: Old computers: Chris Garcia.
He also apparently does a podcast about Zodiac called *Zodiac Speaking*
and we will link in the show notes.
Alison: What, Chris does?
Because of course he does.
John: Of course he does.
Chris Garcia Renaissance man.
Alison: Chris does everything.
If Zodiac does turn out to be Paul Doerr Chris, that podcast is technically eligible.
for Fancast.
Ersatz Culture and Raj had a chat in our Mastodon mentions in which they note that
**The City of Last Chances** was published in the US in December 2022 as a simultaneous ebook release.
So it is not in fact eligible.
We regret the error.
Alison: Oh s*** I've nominated it.
Should have nominated the second one.
John: Ersatz Culture wrote to say **Children of Memory** is actually eligible because it only became
available in the States in January 2023.
So yes thank you.
That was too late for us to include it before nominations shut.
Hopefully no one got themselves in a knot with that information.
Alison: Martin Easterbrook writes to say for scholars of the constitution.
Do we have any scholars of the constitution in the house?
Alison and John: na na na na na na na na na na na na na na na na BatLiz!
Alison: at what point does someone officially become a Hugo winner? This is like at what point somebody
is officially... this is like at what point does somebody become king? and the use of kings
to impart messages over vast distance because they have the divine right of kings once
they're kings? So if you keep a supply of kings and kill one on the home planet then you can
impart a message by because the person or the the heir on the far planet is now is now king
and so has the divine has the divine right of kings and so can do king things and so thereby
you know that something that something has happened but anyway at what point does somebody
officially become Hugo winner and I assume it is at the point where their name is read
out on stage?  John: I'm gonna say I think this is the sort of question that arises from hanging
out in the WSFS business meeting Discord I think it's when they win a Hugo. Alison: When their
name is read out on stage because he's got the name he's got the word officially in his
thing. John: What's what's the counter argument to it being that?  What are the options? Liz: We know
that **La La Land's** name was read out on stage and did not win Best Picture Oscar because
they gave him the wrong envelope so what if we gave someone the wrong envelope? Alison: Yes but
the Hugos would never make a mistake like that Liz: Would we then just have to declare that
was the winner because that seems like a maybe not great system Alison: Okay I'll amend this, at the
point at which the correct winner is read out on stage, will that do? John: On the subject of
another thing Martin Easterbrook wrote, he asked in a previous episode you know whether or
not basically he argued that this had happened before at western Worldcons sorry he happened
the thing that happened that Chengdu with it being slowly taken over by a group outside
of fandom had happened before at western Worldcons and like no one was really talking about
that and España Sheriff sent in a link to a discussion of the 1987 World Science Fiction
Convention in which the Scientologists tried to steal the Worldcon and if you read this
article I think it becomes very clear that people did have extremely strong opinions
about this and those extremely extremely strong opinions were no no no! So I think I think
when this happened in the UK people were also hopping mad. Alison: oh yeah they were apoplectic and
I was there at the time and if you read the article that España links to it was more
it wasn't quite they were trying to take over the Worldcon; they were trying to get undue
influence through sponsorship.  This is more close to the Raytheon thing and because the Worldcon
was very short of money and this is a problem with with the way that Worldcons
are sometimes very short of money, they made some decisions that they absolutely should
not have made but it didn't they didn't realize how bad it was going to be until it had happened
and you know there were other things about about that Worldcon. It was my first Worldcon,
I was so excited. I spent the entire time being in an advanced state of excitement.
Liz: We also heard from Tammy Coxon who we well we kind of called out last episode for saying
that Worldcon is dying and I thought she left us a very reasonable comment saying you know
fair enough for calling it out which is if nothing else it's a very nice way of doing
the discourse in which we don't get annoyed with each other we just have a conversation
and she just say yes she thinks she's seeing a lot of enthusiasm maybe coming out of Europe
and maybe less out of other places and yet that it is just really really hard to run
a Worldcon right now and she has chaired a Worldcon and can't imagine, sorry she used
to want to chair a Worldcon she has chaired a NASFiC, and can't imagine doing it again. I
mean I can't imagine charing a Worldcon but fortunately we seem to have enough people
who do want to do that that it's working at the moment and I do hope that maybe the
current Hugo thing will lead to some productive changes that will help motivate more people
to want to run Worldcon, so thank you Tammy. Alison: I'd agree with that. JohN: yeah thank you very much
for leaving a comment Tammy and and being very gracious about us. I want to say one thing
I want to pick up one thing from the comment which is I'm not she says I'm not a business
meeting fan and I'd love to figure out a way for us to run the organization more fairly
in a way that makes running Worldcon something more people want to do. I think there are a
lot of people who try to intersect with running the Worldcon at a high level and they intersect
with the business meeting and they're like oh no I cannot do this. I think there is a conversation
we need to have about the fact that the business meeting massively enforces the group of people
who work on the Worldcon and massively puts off the people who currently don't and so
if we're going to have this conversation we need to have a serious conversation about
what the business meeting does to people who might want to get involved because I think
it puts a lot of people off. Alison: I have thinks here and the main one is that the vast majority
of people who work on Worldcons, including working on Worldcons at high level, aren't
really very involved in the business meeting. They'll kind of go along to present their
bid and to accept if they win, but only a very small proportion of Worldcon runners have
anything to do with the business meeting. John: Yes. Alison: And the vast majority of people who work
on Worldcons think the business meeting is just as mad as everybody else does. The only
people who don't think the business meeting is mad is the set of people who like the business
meeting, which is quite a small set of people. John: Yes.I completely agree with everything you've
just said, but I think if you want to get involved with running the Worldcon, naively a lot of
people who don't really know how it works go to the business meeting because they're
like this is where the decisions are made and I think that belies the fact that most
of the decisions are actually made in committee but I don't think that's transparent to new
members at all and so I think you have this core of people who would quite like to be
involved in the Worldcon at quite a high level and the business meeting is basically
this giant distracting put off. Alison: Agreed. If you want to get involved in running Worldcons,
including getting involved at a high level, so what you do is you email volunteers@glasgow2024.org
and they'll give you a little job to do and then you'll find that
people resign above you as things as things go terribly wrong and then suddenly you'll
be working on the Worldcon at a high level, that's how it works. John: Ah, would that it were not
so. Alison: but honestly if you want to get involved in the world calls at a high level that is
my top tip. It will work, sorry Esther. Liz: I've got nothing to say about business meetings
because I think we've really covered that ground before and we shouldn't do it again
unless we have something new to discuss. John: Fair. Alison: We definitely will sometime but maybe not
today.  Sandra Bond wrote to us – we did get a lot of letters this week – and said Liz: It's
because we haven't recorded for a month. Alison: We should record every two weeks, shouldn't we? Except
when we don't. "I finally caught up with you once again while driving around after Corflu
and nearly swerved off the road into a New Mexico canyon when I heard you once again
plug me for a Hugo nomination." Okay so we have a kind of listeners advice here which
is if the contents of the audio you're listening to while driving might make you swerve don't
listen to it while driving. Listen to stuff that won't make you swerve seriously. John: Well this
is this is partly my fault because I do the trigger warnings in the show notes and it didn't
occur to me to put this as a trigger but it probably is one so we will endeavour to be
better about it in future Sandra but no and not only did we plug Sandra I nominated Sandra
on Saturday boom. Other things on Sandra's letter. Perhaps you could find
a few seconds to plug my first collection of verse, Poetry Slum due out at Eastercon
I did my Kipling pistiche about Dave McCarty won't be in it so you'll have to wait for
her second collection of poetry if you want to read that and she has sent us the covers
which we'll put in as the chapter art, chapter art? John: Yes we will link it somewhere Alison: and I was
wondering whether I might, to whet everybody's appetite, read out the poem from the back from
the blurb that gave her the title for this. If you want to score sestinas or a baggy
of blank verse, you can buy them on the dark net then again you could do worse than slip
down to the sleazy spot where the versifiers come and speak to the suppliers down in the
Poetry Slum. John: I do like Sandra. Alison: I like Sandra and I like Sandra's poetry a whole lot, a lot of
her poetry is really good. John: finally bring us home Liz. Liz: Actually we got two more cos I missed
one. We heard from Murphy's lawyer on Bluesky.  We're on Bluesky I'm trying to be actually
doing stuff on Bluesky by the way. Alison: that's Harry Payne. Liz: Harry Payne who has been sideloading
our podcasts on to their e-reader so you there's a picture of like Octothorpe with the logo
in black and white on a Kobo. I didn't even know you can do that but it's quite impressive
it might be easier just to like put em on your phone if anyone knows out there listening listening
to Octothorpe on a fridge or a toaster or you know 1983 Unix workstation please please drop
us a line. Alison: I was gonna say if you're listening to Octothorpe on a pregnancy test please let
us know. Liz: Nicholas Jackson Jackson also sent some messages on Bluesky say the discussion of
Hugo Popes, Cardinals, etc reminded him of a costume from the masquerade at eastercon 1999
which is Andrew Patterson as St Hugo of fandom and he sent a picture of Saint Hugo of fandom
so we'll put that in the show notes for you all. Thank you very much Nicholas. John: Anyway that
was letters letters letters of comment. Boom, commented. Now let's look at the BSFA Award
shortlist. We have questions. I've not discussed this with my fellow co-hosts but I feel confident
that we have questions do you guys have questions? Alison: oh about the BSFA shortlist? John: yes so the so one
thing we should say is I believe from the long list best translated short fiction did not
get a lot of submissions and they have transitioned it to being a juried award. I don't know whether
this is permanent or whether this is just this year or what exactly the deal is but it has
definitely happened. Liz: When it says this award is selected by an appointed BSFA jury does
that mean the short lists are selected by a jury or the voting like the whole thing is
done by jury because a jury shortlist with a public vote sounds pretty good. John: I don't know.
Alison: If I click on the voting form in my email from the BSFA I can see if I can vote for it
or not right? John: Yes you have to bear in mind that neither me nor Liz got that voting form.
Alison: because you're not BSFA members? John: yes indeed. Alison: Right. No I am not being given an option to
vote on it so it is a juried award. John: wahey. Thank you for finding that out, Alison. Liz: I will, I will
note that Best Short Fiction is now things which are shorter than Best Shorter Fiction
I don't know I find I still find that a little bit confusing. Alison: so shorter fiction's like novellas
and novellas? John: yeah and then short fiction is shorter fiction than shorter fiction, it's
shorterer. Liz: Yeah. John: And then you have best nonfiction short and best nonfiction long because they've
changed it! I noticed when I first looked at this this page they were not templated similarly
and I was a bit like come on guys but they've changed it so they are so that's good, good
BSFA. Shall we stop talking about our annoyances about quibberly little pedantic things and
talk about the actual works well I mean the reason I'm talking about this is because I
actually am not familiar with most of the works right so one of the things that was
noticed when this went up which is the under Best Short Fiction which is for fiction that's
longer than short fiction The Book of Gaheris was listed by Kari Sperring as one of the
nominees but that has been replaced with Knotted Thorn which is one of the stories from The
Book of Gaheris which is good because Knotted Thorn is eligible and as far as I understood
it the full book was not but I think that was probably just an error by the BSFA. It does
look like they have they've gone through and fixed some of the mistakes which is really
nice because the first version of this shortlist they had not and it is good that they have
Yeah I mean I'm gonna call out that I actually haven't read any of the novels unusually but
in Best Nonfiction Long we do have the collections of essays by Neil Harrison All These Worlds
and A Traveller in Time: the critical practice of Maureen Kincaid Speller which we suggested
for the Hugo nominations a few weeks ago and there's also quite a lot of interesting stuff
in the best nonfiction short category like there's a interesting looking set of essays
there with everything from Fiona Moore's Project Management lessons from Rogue One but also
there's one about the burden of writing from the margins, there's one about dominant themes
in Afrocentric Fiction by Eugene Bacon it looks like a really strong shortlist although
I have not read all of them yet and it's nice that the BSFA has continued to kind of recognise
that because I know there was a while where the BSFA Best Nonfiction I think there were
a few years where it wasn't awarded or then it became jureed and so on but it does seem
like now there's enough people reading and nominating things to justify having two categories
for this which is pretty nice. Yeah, no, it looks like a vibrant shortlist and you can
vote on the shortlist if you are a member of the BSFA or a member of Eastercon, Levitation
it actually says attendees of the Convention Levitation 2024 but I assume it actually means
anyone who's got a membership in levitation not many people who turn up on site so historically
it was paper ballots at the Eastercon but I assume they'll have a mechanism for people
to vote online because otherwise that would be a bit mad wouldn't it I'm pretty sure you
couldn't even paper ballot last time I did it I just had to log in and do it on my phone
at Eastercon. I hope so because if I'm thinking about a virtual membership to levitation partly
so I can also vote in the BSFA awards so if I don't get a vote then it takes away a
little bit of the value of my virtual membership and also seems a bit weird that I don't get
a vote because I am geographically too far away and cannot make the Eastercon.
Eastercon!
Yes!
We're excited about Eastercon!
Levitation.
I am excited about Eastercon which is Levitation in Telford it is not too late for you to join
and also if you don't fancy getting to Telford there's a virtual membership and a full virtual
convention I'm going to say much like we had last year but I think they're using a slightly
different system for that. Social events will be happening on a Discord and there's going
to be I don't think they've announced them yet but I think I'm going to say so that people
are excited about it that there are going to be some social events in advance on Discord
so that you can hang out with people and if you haven't been to an Eastercon see what
it's like and talk to people about it and make plans for Telford and so on They'll
be happening in the week before Easter but just in case because I think if there is
another episode of Octothorpe so the next episode of Octothorpe. will be on Maundy Thursday
so it'll be before then so I'm mentioning them now even though they're not announced
yet but they'll be happening the week before Easter so that you can get used to Discord
make sure you're logged into Discord before the convention so that we don't have to sort
it all out on Maundy Thursday and by we I don't really mean me I mean Andrew Emily and other people
like that and maybe me a bit and then John, are you doing anything at Eastercon? I'm running
the newsletter I'm excited about Eastercon I'm also a bit sad because I will not be at
Eastercon I will be watching from afar but on the other hand that means I also won't be
on a rail replacement bus to Telford so I have made some good choices in life yes oh
yes enjoy listening to Octothorpe on Maundy Thursday while you are on the rail replacement
bus everyone. yes so there's there's been some sort of landslide between Shrewsbury
and Telford. I think they call it a landslip because that sounds less alarming. There's
been a there's been a geophysical buggery in between Telford and other places. The report
I saw from National Rail basically said they are trying to clear it up before the 31st
which does firstly mean that it might get done before but also means it might not so
yes if you're planning to travel by train be aware. There are trains to Telford they're just
doing rail replacement at the weekends there probably will be a rail replacement on Good
Friday and Easter Monday I think they had already announced they weren't going to be
trains those days I think you might be alright on Maundy Thursday I don't want to guarantee
it though. Alison will stake her reputation on it there was a report on this that confused
two things which was that there was rail replacement services over the weekend because it was a
weekend but also the landslip which has affected the trains but not to the point that they're
not running. I will say that last time there was a landslip and it was affecting the trains
I went to the station and they said oh yeah, it'll be fine it'll go a bit slower through
the land slip bit, but you should be fine. I got all my money back for that train journey and
the conductor even gave us free crisps because we were stuck for so long. so yeah. I
now do have an ordered list of games which I will buy if I ever get delay repay for anything
The Coxon technique. It's probably my best achievement which given I have like a PhD thesis
bit bit conflicting.
Shall we discuss the Hugos? Yes. Now I know we don't really talk about the Hugos very much
on this podcast. In fact I think we talk about them so much I've made that joke before
haven't I? So we pre-recorded the last episode because we knew we needed to do it and get
it out before the Hugo nomination deadline which meant we have not commented on several
new aspects of the 2023 Hugo ever-evolving big clusterf*ck thing.  The main thing that was
reported was a big report from Chris Barkley and Jason Sanford which I'm gonna say is
a pretty long report and covers quite a lot of stuff but the main thing in it is they managed
to get some emails which were released by Diane Lacey who was on the Hugo administration
team for Chengdu which essentially show exactly what was going on during some bits of the
Hugo process.  So they released these emails and these emails basically show a couple of
things.  One, they show Dave McCarty emailing his team and saying when you are reviewing
the nominees don't just review them for technical eligibility please highlight anything of a
sensitive political nature that being defined as work focusing on China, Taiwan, Tibet or other
topics that may be an issue in China. Which is basically a very broad slate isn't it? And
then there's a few more emails that basically discuss exactly what they were finding in some
of the the Hugo finalists. I think dossiers. There are dossiers. So the two things so there
are these emails from Diane Lacey which are basically they were going through trying to
like say what might be issues with some of the potential finalists and they released
for instance the big one about like Fan Writer which has a lot of really random things like
'Alastiar Stuart wants to go to a Batman hotel in Taiwan'. Blog reviews that mention China
you know shares a bunch of news about it. The thing that really pulled this up is it's
just basically like doing some googling but doing some googling incompetently. For instance
they said that Paul Weimer who was removed from the final ballot traveled to Tibet and
tweeted pictures and talked about food.  But he hadn't been to Tibet. And yet they also
missed other finalists who have been to Tibet. And the other thing that came out of this
is there's a a nomination spreadsheet it's called validation and it basically is where
they were doing these validation things and writing you know known issues possible issues
minor issues or whatever but what it also shows is that this is presumably the raw
output of the first run of E pluribus Hugo and there's a bunch of items on there which
were not on the final ballot. And if you look at the emails that were sent between Dave
as well it also says and I'm gonna just find this and quote. "Tomorrow I have a four hour
meeting with my Chinese counterpart to look at ballot detail and determine if any ballots
are to be voided which happens with frequency so it's not really that controversial if we
determine we need to do it." mmm yeah. So it's also clear that they voided a bunch of ballots
basically saying that there was some kind of slate voting going on which appears to just
be have been people voting for the same things off a nomination list although it's quite
complicated it may not be exactly that, but that's what we have to assume and then they
rerun EPH and got a new set of finalists and if you look at this you know spreadsheet
called validation I think it's clear there are like a couple of different runs of EPH
on it some after they had pulled out a bunch of ballots and then a few extra things get
on and then there's also this mysterious thing called the invitation list which appears to
be things they were going to check because they thought they might end up on the final
list, but they're not under the first run of EPH so I assume most of you have seen
this at this point but basically what we can say is they did extremely incompetent weird
vetting to try and find political issues and then seem to start iranably remove people
who had said something about something that might be controversial but also that they just
basically threw out a bunch of ballots. And that's a large bunch of ballots to be clear,
maybe most of them. I wanted to just mention a couple of other things that are just old
history now but probably in case our listeners don't know.
Kat Jones, who had previously told me that she was involved only at a very early stage
with the Hugo eligibility process, but was at the time the Hugo administrator for Glasgow
turned out to be one of the people who compiled these sets of sets of information about possible
candidates and she has now resigned from her post at Glasgow as has everybody else who
has had anything to do with this and Glasgow has a whole new Hugo team.
Good.
Under Nicholas Whyte who has also written a blog post which we'll link to saying actually
I really didn't have anything to do with this and I did try to volunteer for China but
was but never heard anything back seemed to have dodged a bullet there.
I may be paraphrasing there but goes on to say a little bit about his philosophy in running
Hugos which won't be which will not be a surprise to anyone who's worked with Nicholas
on anything to do with this.
So I think that's a good post that's useful from Nicholas and hopefully everything is
fine for this year's Hugo administration and Glasgow has been very careful to make it
straightforward for Chinese nominators to nominate in this year's Hugos which of course
they can do as members of Chengdu.
I speculated many moons ago that the reason that we hadn't seen the Fan Writer or Fanzine
part of the Hugo packet was because there was some snafu with it at a Chinese censorship
level and it this very much supports that theory.
So there were people at the time who were not convinced that that was a fair take but
it turns out that it was.
We all wanted to be optimistic about the Chengdu Worldcom but there was evidence that it was
going weird quite early on that I think no one really wanted to believe was true and
has tragically turned out to be very true which is frustrating.
I can't believe that Kat Jones didn't immediately disclaim all of this as soon as the discourse
started like I don't understand how she didn't expect it to come out like I would have
just been like yes.
Because if you had apologized if you had come clean and apologized at the point the
stats dropped you'd still be the Hugo administrator.
Or at the very least you wouldn't be persona non grata forever but at this point if Kat
Jones is ever on a Worldcom committee again or like a Worldcom team again I will be extremely
angry and I think there was a way to manage that that would have made me much less angry.
I'm not sure if that's fair because it's clear that what she did was do the work and
then have second thoughts and you know people make mistakes.
She made a couple of mistakes actually so doing the work was a mistake but then also
when it started to come to light she was kind of how dare Diane releases emails rather
than Diane Lacey let's be clear here was completely correct to release these emails.
It was absolutely the right thing to do.
It's never too late to start making good decisions.
And it's hard to sort of say oh but they're private email should I release them?
No you definitely should.
Definitely definitely should.
There's also a thing here which so Dave McCarty was the Hugo administrator for at least one
of the puppy years and apparently quite happy to throw out slates by Chinese voters but
not happy to throw out slates by fascists.
I don't know what to do with that information at all.
Makes me very stressed out.
I think the I want to be slightly careful about what I say here but some American fans
including some fascists are very litigious so it's not impossible that Dave felt that
if he had thrown out ballots from puppies, puppies would have sued, and that that would
be a worse outcome than not throwing out the ballots.
I don't think he thought that random Chinese voters would be suing.
I think I would prefer that interpretation to many others.
But also always look for interpretations that don't require people to be actively evil.
I don't think very many people are actively evil.
I think they just make bad decisions and they compound in a way that gets you into situations
that are difficult to get out of.
That gets complicated when you talk about stuff like dog whistles and how I think there is
a group of actors in every community that is very good at exploiting that inclination.
And that's the problem when it comes to that.
Liz, have you got anything on any of those scorching hot two-week-old?
No, more than two-week-old takes.
Scorching hot month-old takes?
Yeah.
Hey.
So yeah, I mean I think I would fall on.
You don't throw out slate ballots.
We came up with a way to basically make a fairer nomination system given the existence of slate
ballots.
And I think we use that.
And if you basically use your ways of down-ranking stuff that's on slate and they're still
at the top, then they're still at the top.
So I'd say a couple of things.
Yeah.
So one is...
One take I've seen is that this was Western fandom in the form of Dave McCarty, Kat Jones
and Diane Lacey doing this.
It was all coming from the Western Fandom's house and we were doing it to China.
I think if you read these emails, which are all being sent when Dave is actually in China
meeting with a lot of the team, it's clearly not just one side of the Hugo administration
team.
It is with his Chinese counterpart.
They say they're going to have a discussion with his Chinese counterpart and so on.
I think you can say that it was the Hugo administration f*cking over all the voters,
both Chinese and non-Chinese.
But I don't think you can say it was entirely like Western fandom doing this of their own
accord.
We just don't have those emails or those emails don't exist.
Yeah, no, absolutely.
I think the emails make it as clear as clear can be.
The emails make it very clear.
Yeah.
I mean, I'm also, I will also say that I am...
I don't know, weirdly slightly offended that it appears that whoever's vetting the podcast
didn't bother to listen to any of the podcasts, because they're all down as no issues.
We've been criticising China.
Why were we on the ballot?
Boo.
But I don't think we were the only podcast to bring up issues around China and the Chengdu
Worldcon.
Kat and Diane did not get down to podcasts.
What happened was that Kat in her...
What?
Yes, they did.
Yeah, they did.
Because it says no issues in Kat's column on the spreadsheet.
Oh.
Yep.
Yeah.
How dare you say there are no issues with our podcast?
There are many issues.
Mostly harmless.
If we're going to say, if we're talking about people not reading the emails, then I am going
to have to ding you for not reading the spreadsheet.
We have no issues, guys.
I certainly have no issues.
Do you have no issues?
I know.
I don't think any of us have been to Tibet or Taiwan either.
But, you know...
No, no.
I'd love to.
Yeah, I'd love to go to Tibet.
I would very much like to go to Taiwan.
Also to make it clear, free Tibet, Taiwan is an independent country.
Solidarity with Hong Kong.
Anyway, so...
But Ada Palmer's thing about self-censorship is relevant here because they did a much more
thorough job than was probably required by their Chinese paymasters, right?
Yes, I think...
I mean, I don't know because as Liz says, we don't...
get an insight into the Chinese side of the committee anywhere near as good as the one we have into
the western side of the committee.
But I would be astounded if this was like coming from the Chinese government.
I suspect it's coming from the people in the Chinese half of the subcommittee who are
aware of the sorts of things they need to be doing to make sure that they don't get in
trouble.
So I think it's exactly what ADA Palmer says in that article about, you know, you get good
at...
Self-censorship.
Yeah, I mean, I mean, they're also presuming at this point thinking, these are all the people
we are going to invite on an, you know, expenses-paid trip and potentially give them a big microphone
if we give them an award to stand at the front and say whatever they like.
And so they probably were thinking we want to exclude anyone who might use that microphone
to say something extremely controversial.
For instance, the Octothorpe podcast, how dare they...
I'm making it perhaps a little bit too much about us, so we should move on from that.
There have been some great takes about this on the Internet since we last recorded.
I do want to specifically flag up James Bacon wrote in Journey Planet a scorching article
about all of this, which is extremely angry in an extremely good way.
And I will put a link to that issue of Journey Planet in the show notes.
And I know that him and Chris have invited Paul Weimer to collaborate on an issue examining
kind of where we go from here, which is very interesting.
I've heard of multiple people who are working on various proposals for where we go from here.
If you have any thoughts, you're happy for us to broadcast and discuss on a future episode.
Please do let us know.
I got one more thing to say about the Hugos.
And we're getting into a very dry side of things now.
Like we weren't before.
But we talked before about how the Worldcon Intellectual Property Corporation is the thing
that basically controls the Hugo trademarks.
And they had various meetings from which we know about the censures for Dave McCarty,
Ben Yalow and Chen Shi.
And also the resignation of Dave McCarty, and also the resignation of Kevin Standlee as chair
and who went back down to being a regular board member.
But they did release the minutes of these meetings, which don't tell you very much,
except they do tell you the number of people who voted in favour and against the censures.
Oh, I did not see that.
Well analysed, Liz.
So I mean, I'm a bit confused because I was trying to count how many people were at the
meeting.
And I think some members of the board must have abstained or not voted in these votes.
But it's not listed because it just lists in favor and against.
So you don't know if people have abstained.
But anyway, they voted by 10 to 3 to censure Dave McCarty and then 8 to 5 to censure Dave
McCarty, Ben Yalow and Chen Shi.
And 8 to 6 to recommend Kevin Standlee, which is interesting.
So if you want to try and figure out who the 10 to 3, 8 to 5 and 8 to 6 were, well, have
fun.
I mean, I think, and I think one of the things that comes out of all of this is that it wasn't
just Dave.
Like until the Lacey emails came out, there was this narrative that maybe Dave had done it
all.
And it turns out everyone on that subcommittee is culpable probably.
And Ben Yalow was on that subcommittee.
And I've had this image of Ben as a generally all right, nice bloke who sometimes a bit
vague and now I've got a very different image of him in my head.
And as we said earlier, Nicholas Whyte has become the Hugo Han Solo.
Well, I mean, when I think of definite rule following, constitution abiding role models
from science fiction, I don't think Han Solo.
But I mean, I haven't read any of the extended universe novels, so I could be completely
misrepresenting him.
I would recommend not doing.
Ang wrote to us, Ang Rosin wrote to us with quote, a bit of a rant, which we are cutting a little
bit, about the Hugos.
She says she's seen the story develop and right up to the report by Jason Sanford and
Chris Barkley. Quite a lot of stuff has happened since then.
But indeed, we haven't been here.
So she said she has two questions for Chris and Jason.
Who is your intended audience for the report and who asked you to write it?
And she thinks she's answered it herself.
Quote one, we wrote it for people like us and two, if you were people like us, you would
know.
And I think that's actually quite a fair criticism of this report that it's quite hard to parse
if you're not already in the bubble.
I don't know how successful we are at this, but my aim with all of this discussion is
to bring it to people who are not following it closely.
Because I think that is why we all wanted style to thought in part was to let people
who are not in the bubble into the bubble.
Just wanted to do a podcast.
I just wanted to make John do all the work.
Yeah.
We could have a podcast about board games, guys.
It'd be way less stressful.
Oh, there's a thought.
Where would we get listeners from?
I think we've become like the Octothorpe podcast network.
John, if you want to start up a little board game podcast of your own.
The thing is there is there is one other podcast in the world called Octothorpe, and it is
a board game podcast.
Yeah, if we want to do a board gaming podcast, we need to pick a different punctuation mark.
When we're trying to open the bubble up so that people can see what's inside, we are
also, I think, trying to do it in a relatively measured way.
I mean, I do.
We do know we disagree quite a lot.
I disagree with that.
I saw a YouTube video, which we haven't linked to.
I don't think a couple of YouTube videos about this, which essentially take Abigail
Nussbaum's very considered report and make it hysterical because that's how you get views
on YouTube. It's like going, Oh, look, this is a shock and a scandal.
And of course, this is a shock and a scandal, but I think it makes a lot of sense to try
to talk about it in a measured way rather than actually I'm over here sharpening my pitchfork
way.
So so an Ang mentions that in her email using some spicy language.
But yes, I want to sharpen my pitchfork, but I want to do it slowly and menacingly rather
than quickly and frantically.
Is that good?
No, but I think I agree with Ang here, which is that the report is important investigative
journalism presented in a very odd way.
I don't know.
I found the report itself very hard to read.
It's kind of a mix of report and editorial in one and I admit I was more into the reporting
bit than the editorial, but yeah, no, I like the detail.
I like the detail stats.
Ang's take on the report is that it's rambling self-indulgent one-sided and agenda-ridden,
which I would not necessarily have used those exact words, but like I think it's difficult
to criticise it as a take.
I might say rambly.
Yeah.
So Liz, Camestros Felapton released a very, very, very long set of stats of data
that was like the one that you were talking about doing but didn't do presumably because
they had done.
No, I didn't do it because I was too lazy.
So thank you to Camestros Felapton and Heather Rose Jones for doing the thing
I started, but they actually finished it.
And because it is 48 pages long, I'm very glad I didn't do it.
My only reservation about this is I just don't know how much of those figures in the Hugo
stats are now basically made up.
So it could be we've put a lot of time and effort into deep diving into something which
is just built on a house of cards, but I'm glad it exists.
And if anyone really wants a deep dive into how you can look at the Hugos and say, "Look,
this is why these stats look funky."
If you read it all, you definitely will understand EPH by the end of it as well.
So give it a go.
Wahey.
Given that human lifespans are short.
Do we really all need to understand EPH?
And I don't have a pick either.
Sorry.
I forgot.
Liz, you're going first with your pick.
Pick something.
Well hang on, let me look at Goodreads and see what I read.
I've got a pick.
I could go first.
But...
Why are you making me go first then?
You go first then let me look at what box I've read.
Okay.
We went to see a indie Australian science fiction film called Monolith.
That sounds good.
It was good.
It stars Lily Sullivan as a journalist who has been embroiled in a scandal of some description.
The exact nature of the scandal is not really important.
And she has resorted to podcasting to shore up her struggling career, which is very funny.
And she starts looking at a story.
So the podcast she's doing is this conspiracy theory podcast.
So it is like very much a kind of a cuckus podcast, if you will.
And she gets an email from someone and she starts looking into the subject of their email.
And it's all her on screen and then other people on the other end of phone lines.
But the entire kind of thing is her in one set.
I don't think it's perfect.
I think there are some things it does which it could do better.
But certainly it was really worth watching.
Really interesting.
Very creepy.
Very much gets the vibe it's going for.
And I thought the ending really enjoyed how the ending kind of lampshades
the futility of existence?
Go watch it.
If you can find it, I have no idea where you can watch it.
I think you can rent it on places where you can rent movies.
But I don't think it's streaming for free anywhere.
Blockbuster?
We, it got a theatrical release for a single week in the States.
And so we went to see it in the cinema.
But I don't think it's had a cinema release in the UK at all.
I think it has stopped playing in the States.
So yeah, I think it's a rent it at home jobby.
I'm forced to conclude.
I'm going to have to start renting some movies to get the ones I want.
Because a lot of them just never turn up on streaming and they are available for a little.
And also with the amount that we watch movies at home, which is that we go to cinema quite
a lot.
So this might not apply to every listener.
But there's I do sometimes wonder whether it would be cheaper for us just to rent movies
where we want to rent them than it would be to try and hop around all the streaming
services.
Because rentals are usually about three quid.
And subscribing to a streaming service for a month is more than that.
So yeah, I'm beginning to wonder whether just yeah, renting them when I want to watch
them is the way forward.
Bring back Blockbuster.
That's what I say.
I have a pick, which is that I had arranged to have lunch with a friend in London on a
Thursday when I was also going to the pub on Thursday evening.
And that left me with four hours in the middle of the day.
And I said friends, what should I do with the four hours in the middle of the day?
And one of the things that Alex Holden said, I think Alex is a listener, was why not go
to Tom Hanks' Moonwalkers at the Lightroom Gallery in Kings Cross.
So Lightroom is a new gallery that is in something called Lewis Cubitt Square, which is kind of
way north of Kings Cross in that bit that used to be a dingy industrial site and is now
what Steven calls Googletown, a place where rich people hang out.
And this, the gallery is a featureless box onto which things are projected onto the floor
and walls.
And this is a whole set of information about Apollo, which is not really going to be very
new to most of the listeners of this podcast.
And indeed, most of, I knew most of the stuff that was contained in this already.
And I'd see most of the pictures before, they're not all of them because apparently there are
10,000 pictures and they've all been remastered for this.
And they used a very good camera, which you might not have realized because a lot of them
were, a lot of the photographs were reproduced, reproduced in not a very good way in the '60s
and '70s, but they are in fact very good photos even before they got remastered.
This is kind of an answer to the question of, well, what happens when you want to do planetarium
shows, but the old planetarium projector is now completely obsolete.
So you project things onto your planetariums instead, but planetariums are expensive because
they're domed shapes.
So why not just project things onto a cube?
And there are a lot of exhibitions like this.
We all really liked it.
There were four of us and we were all very moved and thought it was kind of delightful
and thrilling.
But I have some caveats, which is the full ticket price is £25, which is absolutely outrageous,
holy goodness gracious.
We have a art pass, so it was £12.50, which felt fine.
And there are codes hanging around on the internet that will get it for £19, which is
only ludicrously extortionate.
£25 is too much for a one-room video projection.
And I was like, that's the same cost as Titanic Belfast.
If you happen to be in Belfast next Easter for some reason, that's also £25, but has
like multiple rooms of this sort and also many other things going on and an entire ship
for you to look at, not the Titanic, and costs £25.
So if you're in the mood for some ludicrously overpriced Apollo nostalgia, I thought it
was pretty good.
Tom Hanks turns out to be a giant space nerd and part of the narration is his story of what
it was like to be obsessed with Apollo as a child.
So, as certainly the four of us were obsessed with Apollo as children and probably quite
a lot of you listeners were as well.
So for that sort of person, I think it probably hits the mark pretty well.
Don't go at busy times because reviews say it is oversold at busy times and people have
to sit on the floor, which is no fun if you're the sort of age for people.
For people who were obsessed with Apollo as small children.
I realise I have a lovely little anecdote, which is I want to tell you a story about
my husband, which is he was an obsessed, an Apollo assessed child and he had the prized
possession of an Apollo 11 patch, which was like a really phenomenal souvenir if you lived
in North Wales in 1969.
And he got his mother to sew it onto his anorak so that he could wear it to school.
And so he had an anorak with an Apollo 11 patch on and he hung it up in the cloakroom
and when he went back at break time he discovered he had an anorak with a circle cut out.
It's a sad story.
I said they have Apollo 11 patches if you'd like to buy one and he said it would just make
me sad.
That is, I'm so sorry, that's awful.
It's one of these conflicting emotions anecdotes, yes.
But what it was like to be a 10 year old in 1969, imagine what it was like to be a 10
year old in 1969, so that's part of what I liked about the show is it gives you some
of that feeling.
I might have to look at it going, it sounds intriguing.
Liz, do you have a pick?
I mean I don't have a pick, so...
Liz?
I don't want to pick something substandard.
Sorry, I didn't think about it.
We'll pick your friendship with me.
Listeners, you did not see the look on Liz's face when I suggested that.
Look, for picks we like to pick things that listeners can at least experience and I
mean our listeners can be your friend, but they cannot experience the particular bond
John and I have.
A bond which, you know, we test on a frequent basis and becomes stronger.
And that was the Octothorpe podcast.
And it's goodbye for me.
It would be goodbye for me if I wasn't laughing quite so hard.
Sorry, is that another cultural reference you guys don't get?
I got it.
I was busy texting my wife.
OK, so John wasn't listening and Liz got the reference, OK?
Yes.
Yes, do I need like a hand signal to show I've got your references or something?
You could laugh.
I don't know.
Maybe they're not funny.
See, now it's really awkward, isn't it?
Moving swiftly on.
The theme music for this episode was "Fanfare for Space" by Kevin MacLeod at incompetech.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.
[ Silence ]