And the winner for Best Fancast is
Octa Thor by John Coxson, Alison Stark and Liz Batty.
So I'm always the first on the Zoom call.
LAUGHTER
And Alison's usually the last.
Yes.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very first
Octa Thorpe Award acceptance speech.
I'm John Coxson.
CHEERING
Oh my God.
LAUGHTER
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
CHEERING
I'd like to thank everyone who nominated and voted
for us and everyone who nominated and voted
in the fan categories generally.
I'd like to thank my wife, it's Banyah Sherif.
I'd like to thank my mom, dad and my family.
I'd like to thank Claire Breyerley.
Claire Breyerley.
I've said it right more times than I've said it wrong now, Claire.
So that debt is settled.
I'd like to thank Mark Plummer, Chris Garcia, Tobe Svalwell, Max Hargdon,
the Hugo Girl podcast and Third Row fandom in general
for encouraging my fan act and keeping me
enthused about the community.
Thank you so much, I am so honored.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
I'd also like to thank my family, Stephen, Marianne and Jonathan
Kane, for being endlessly long suffering.
For all of the plot collective that Steve Davis, Julia de
Cesaré, Mike Scott, Flick, Sumason and the previously
mentioned Keynes, for modelling collaborative fan act
and for the whole of fandom, for keeping coming up with
interesting things for us to talk about.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
So 19 years ago, I attended my very first WorldCon
and I sat somewhere way out in the back over there.
So to win in Glasgow is really special for me.
I want to thank my family.
I want to thank John, who came up with the idea for a podcast.
I want to thank Alison, who does the art for our podcast
every time.
And I want to thank all those friends that I made in Glasgow,
many of whom are still here with me and to thank everyone
who couldn't be here today.
And finally, I really do want to thank our listeners
without them, they wouldn't be here tonight.
Thank you.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
John wants this one carried down because he's going to drop it.
MUSIC
Welcome to the very 116th episode of OctaThorp,
which is coming to you on the 15th of August 2024,
live from Glasgow, the WorldCon for our futures.
I'm John Coxen.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
I've just been handed a telegram by noted member of the audience, Ian.
A telegram.
Congratulations, OctaThrop, on your huge award.
Claire Broily and Mark Plumer of Croydon.
CHEERING AND APPLAUSE
That's very, very good.
Thank you for that most excellent letter of comment.
We are not worthy.
So yes, thank you.
Thank you, everyone.
And meaning that we have our huge awards.
We have a shiny.
We now have a trophy each.
Several people have asked whether we get a trophy each.
So yes, we get a trophy each.
They're very heavy.
They're very beautiful.
And I love it very much.
Mine is in Liz's room.
Liz is in the Armadillo and Alison is here.
LAUGHTER
So Liz is on its way being shipped back to Thailand.
Yes, I did not fancy carrying a large pointy metal object
through several sets of airport security, basically.
Shall we have a...
OK, I want to do a quick show of hands.
Who is a regular or occasional OctaThrop listener before today?
Oh, that is most people.
Has anyone just turned up because this was a room with seats in
and it's Monday morning?
Hey!
You're very welcome.
Has anyone never listened to our podcast?
Oh, wow.
Oh, wow, right.
So, hello.
I'm really sorry.
LAUGHTER
So we do a podcast is usually slightly more structured than this will be.
We talk about science fiction and science fiction fandom
and conventions and picks and wasps and whether or not it's dark where Liz is
in that order.
And it's quite good.
And we hope you like it.
Cricket sometimes.
And there are many episodes.
Please don't feel you have to start episode one.
Please don't feel you have to listen to any of them.
But if you would like to, we would be filled to have you.
But if you're going backwards, do not listen to the immediate prior episode.
No, whatever you do, don't start there.
You start wherever you like, but don't start with episode one, one, five
because it's 70 minutes about the business meeting and...
Ooh.
It was heavy.
Oh, I was going to make the same joke I made at the fan...
Who was at the fan fund auction?
A few of you.
Right.
So I was going to say, yeah, no.
Hello, everybody.
And welcome to the overflow Wuss for Christmas meetings.
LAUGHTER
And normally at conventions when we do "Opt thought live", we pride ourselves on having more
messages in our Discord stream than any other item at the convention.
So, last time I checked, there have been 1,180 messages in the business meeting
stream since the last time I did it.
So, guys, that's your target if you are watching this on this board.
That is free a second.
That is going to be a challenge.
Three a second, says Duncan, from the audience, which is a challenge.
And I would like it to be a challenge that we do not rise to.
I think we could reasonably go for, if we divide the number of messages in the business meeting
by the number of...
Oh, God, it's happening.
For those who are not in the room, the Discord has now got a lot of gifts in.
Are they locust?
LAUGHTER
So...
Anyway, this is one of the...
No.
And guys, as you know, guys, this is great radio.
This is great radio.
It's all thing about it.
Giggling.
Top quality, top quality audio.
All right, no, no, no, no, no, great, great, great, great.
Stop.
LAUGHTER
Please stop.
So, I think it would be reasonable to say that if we get more than the business meeting chat
divided by the number of hours of business meeting, we can consider that a normalised success.
That would only be eight messages.
Eight?
Yeah.
Yeah, so we've got more than eight.
Jobs are good.
Right.
Accomplished.
Because there have been many...
I just want some of the people who would like to be in this podcast and this live podcast are not here
because they are at the business meeting, which continues on into infinity.
Yes.
Liz, what do you think?
LAUGHTER
Yeah, we didn't really do show notes.
Shall we talk about the hugos a bit?
Because they were pretty good?
Yeah, they were pretty good.
Yeah.
I...
Do you want to start?
LAUGHTER
I was taught because I've had slightly more sleep.
And slightly less ADHD.
You have had approximately one hour, twenty minutes more sleep than we have.
We did not have a lot of sleep.
So, yes, the...
When we do convention podcasts, we've got into the habit of doing them on a Monday morning
and I thought, "Okay, that's only going to be great and we'll be super excited, or we really
depress and then we can all be really depressed with you."
But...
Which would be great.
It went pretty well.
Yeah, we went a hugo.
I wasn't expecting it, even though several people said, "I think you're going to win a hugo."
We won it by a pretty narrow margin.
So, thank you everyone who voted because if there's...
It was by seven votes.
So, if the people in this room did not vote, did we?
We would not have won.
And we all voted for ourselves, so that means it was really four.
LAUGHTER
I feel like you've forgotten Stephen and just Spaniel and Marianne.
We won by, we won by, like, minus six, and that's all.
LAUGHTER
We won by this podcast and their families.
And I'm not absolutely sure I voted, I'm still...
I think Nicholas says he thinks I did vote this time.
Commiserations to the people that we just squeaked past, which is world building for massacres.
I met them this weekend, I think, for the first time, and they are absolutely lovely.
So, you know...
Yes.
So...
I wasn't listening, but I agree.
You weren't listening.
Oh, God, John.
I was reading the discourse.
LAUGHTER
Is there a voice of discord in the room who's going to keep us updated with what's in the room?
Is it?
Yeah, everyone.
Very...
I'm very sorry, voice of discord.
LAUGHTER
Emily points out that people who came second probably have families too, and Beth points
out that their family is very fraught with thought.
LAUGHTER
I would like to also say thank you very much to the other finalists, all of whom make cracking
vancasts and are well worth your time.
It is a strong and vibrant category, and I am...
I actually think it's one of the stronger categories on the ballot, because there's a lot of stuff,
a lot of different stuff.
It's highlighting a lot of good fan activity, and I'm very proud to have been recognised
in it, because...
Yeah.
I think I'd agree with that.
I mean, we've met most...
You'd agree with, because...
Yeah.
Because most of the fan casts are here, I think.
Mmm.
So it's been great to hang out.
There was a podcast meetup that was just enormous.
One of the things about...
Has anyone been to a meetup this weekend?
Did your meetup, yeah?
Did your meetup fit onto the eight person meetup table that was assigned to it?
LAUGHTER
Because I went to like a 70 person meetup, which was the podcast world, and I went to another
70 person meetup, which wasn't even on the programme, which was the cuspus world.
Was that just the bar?
Oh, no.
No, it was like...
Well, we...
They have planned to hold it in...
The disused bar on the first floor of the Armadillo behind a sign saying, "Beware of the Armadillo."
LAUGHTER
But when they went there, they found a lot of security guards crawling around, so...
Because it was the one nice day we've had this weekend, we all sat out on the grass, and...
It was quite good because I got some fresh air.
Oh!
It's not bad.
Despite the fact, I'm not in this hotel, so I'm not in the crab closet, so I had some fresh air walking to
and from my hotel, but otherwise I've kind of been in the fetid environment of halls four and five for most of the weekend.
And that's how the hoo-hoo's went.
Oh, no.
Right, I'm thinking.
[LAUGHTER]
The hoo-hoo's...
I can hear his body, I forget the back.
Hi.
It's my name, my wife, that's her life.
So, I feel like that I'm going to give some credit to this convention for supplying what they described on the
invitation as "heavy or derve".
Heavy or derve?
Which we thought was going to be haggis pakora.
Yeah, it was.
I was quite... I was so glad.
It was just...
It was dinner.
It was just a buffet.
It was actual food.
Yeah.
It was like...
Hot food and vegetables.
And they had the most Scottish of drinks, biramaretti, which, when I think Scotland, I think, biramaretti.
And then I also want to thank Seattle for doing a really nice after party.
And they gave us a lovely little gift.
And it happened to me...
So good.
I'm so happy.
If you'd said to me, I didn't bring it on Fred.
If you'd said to me, "What gift will Seattle welcome gift to the Hugo Funnelies?"
I'd have gone, "I don't know."
And then I got it and it was an espresso cup and I was like, "Oh!"
With a tiny sashay, you have sofied themed coffee.
And I got so excited.
And I took two, one for me and one for España.
And then I realized that I was supposed to queue up and let them rewrite my name down.
And I had not done that bit.
So, you're the third one.
No, I've only got two.
I'm not.
I didn't steal anything.
I could have got one for Steven.
I kind of started in on this, "Oh, I've been on the finalist from two different categories.
Can I have two espresso cups so that me and my husband can have espresso cups?"
And then we remember we do not use espresso cups.
We just got rid of eight.
We looked at my parents beautiful China espresso cups and said, "So, these are for when you serve coffee."
None of these have Seattle World Con branding as well.
When are we going to drink tiny coffee and tiny cups after dinner?
What you do is...
No, when you watch the...
Right, so if you ever watch the Ant Man films, have an espresso, you can feel like you're
a giant man drinking a tiny coffee.
It's great.
Every time we watch the Ant Man movies, we have espresso.
Thematic.
Or a sports direct mug.
It works in either direction.
So anyway, so...
The Hugo.
Yeah.
I mean, I thought it was a really good ceremony.
I'm quite glad it started late because I sent my family stream and I think if it hadn't been
late, they would have missed it.
So, I forgot to tell them what time it started.
So that was good.
It's really weird because I'm very glad that we are early in the ceremony because I don't
think I really want...
You're getting a little bit nervous, a little bit nervous, a little bit more nervous.
And then you kind of like...
It gets your moment and you have like the maximum nervousness.
And then, you know, in previous years, like, "Oh, we didn't win.
Okay, I can now enjoy the ceremony."
But I'm very glad we're first.
Oh, it did mean I sort of sat there hugging a Hugo for two hours.
It was...
I want to say about the ceremony, John Scalzi's speech was amazing.
It was really, really good.
And I just...
I think he really nailed that.
Obviously, "T" Kingfisher's speech was brilliant.
Like, I always like when she wins when they win because firstly, they're very good.
And secondly, the speech is so good.
And then Emily Tesh's speech, which she wrote in the audience of the ceremony.
And if that's true, she is annoyingly talented.
But it was so good.
It was so powerful and I liked it a great deal.
And then we did a speech which had a funny bit at the beginning, which Liz asked when we were on our way over.
"John, do we have to do the funny bit at the beginning?"
And I was like, "You Liz? Yes, we do."
I thought we might do it wrong and then it would fall very flat and then everyone would just be staring at us.
But...
Actually, the lights are so bright you can't really see anyone in the audience.
So, I think that is helpful to me.
I feel like enough people in the audience got magic.
Yeah, well, because we won and that means at least like seven people listen.
The other thing about the Seattle after party is that they served us more beer, which was good.
So there was actually plenty of alcohol at both the pre...
There wasn't plenty afterwards, but that was only because we'd have...
It doesn't matter how much they had provided.
We would...
The Hugo Finalist would continue drinking until all the alcohol was gone even...
But there was a reasonable amount of alcohol I applied to.
I didn't feel short-changed and that is the first time that's happened at a Hugo Finalist party I've been at.
But at the end, the room was emptying out and all the alcohol was gone.
And then there was this huge, almost untouched sandwich buffet.
Yeah, yeah, because they'd served us dinner before and then there were sandwiches after.
Which was very lovely, but I didn't need a lot of sandwiches on account of how I just had dinner.
John, is it possible that many Hugo Finalists are a bit nervous and don't want to fill their boots at the buffet?
Oh yeah, well, you'd think, but if it was nearly untouched after, maybe, I don't know.
No, no, no. I don't think it was untouched. I think it was just enormous.
So I think if they served a third as much sandwiches and used the extra money to buy beer...
I think they should have used the extra money to buy a wider variety of soft drinks.
Because one of the things that got mentioned in the Hugo Finalist Discord afterwards was that a couple of people who don't drink and they were like,
"Well, I had water until the water ran out."
And that is awkward because why did they not have iron brew?
Like, literally why?
Somebody did say...
Somebody did actually, maybe it was a Spaniard.
I feel like somebody essentially told the conference centre that not serving water was a kind of fundamental violation.
They should get their act together.
And they did it.
I mean, I don't know if it was, she's not saying yes.
So I think...
She said no.
She said it, but she didn't say it to the convention centre because she was a coward.
She's so not a coward.
Well, I'm reporting her words.
I didn't make those words up.
So this is from the least cowardly person I've ever met in my entire life.
I mean, yep.
It is fair to say that there are a preponderance of opinionated women in my life.
And that might not be an accident.
Hello, John.
Hello, Liz.
Hello, Alison.
So yeah, the actual ceremony, it's very nerve-wracking when you're listening to the thing.
And then they said the thing and then sort of everything goes weird.
It does.
And the three, the experiences I think it's most similar to are my PhD driver and when I got
married.
The experience of wandering around a hotel bemucidly, clutching a thing, while everyone
takes photos of you, congratulates you and distracts you from getting anything to eat,
is very much like the experience of being in a wedding reception when you've just been
married.
And it was very lovely.
And I took photos with lots of people.
I believe there is a photo of Emily Inkpen doing something ill-advised with my Hugo.
And I'm really hoping I get a copy of that photo because it may be a lot.
What's she looking at?
I have no further comments at this time.
I went to John's wedding reception and by the end of it he'd taken his tie off and it
was tied around his head.
So I think maybe a wedding reception was slightly, slightly higher in the category.
Emily's fortune in the chat has said there was so much buffet, you could see it from
the massive, behind the massive barrier that separated the Hugo finalist reception from
the hyperloin in the main hall.
Which in a smuggled you all sandwiches.
Nula says in the chat, "I met Octo Thorpe at a charity do once.
They were surprisingly down to earth and very funny."
[laughter]
I had tickles me, I don't know.
I'm just like that.
Yeah, and we have ribbons.
If you want a ribbon come and get a ribbon.
Yeah, we should have said earlier, if you don't aren't already wearing an Octo Thorpe
ribbon and you would like one we have ribbons, I think we've probably got enough for all
of you who don't already have one.
We don't have enough Hugo's to go round unfortunately.
So, so, so, Pat Montgomery texted me, and he said, "Congratulations," and I said, "Thank
you," and he said, "This is your second, isn't it?"
And I don't expect...
Sorry, I know the joke, but this is very good.
And I don't expect people to know how many Hugo's I thought, "Oh, you know, I expect
me to remember, but I have one, three, yes."
But the thing that's interesting about this is that the second Hugo I won at LACom and
the person who was my designated acceptor was Pat Montgomery.
Yes.
That's why it's funny Pat can't remember your run to do because he accepted one.
So of all the people in the world who aren't you, he should know.
Other things about the Hugo's, they had a few glitches in the ceremony and it was quite
funny.
I think it is a testament to how good a job the Glasgow team have done, but especially
Meg Mcdonald, the Division Head of Promotions, that the amount of warmth and goodwill in the
room while that was happening, people were laughing, they were cheering, they were clapping.
That was a very happy room, celebrating a thing that everyone was there to have a nice time
to celebrate this convention, which has been wonderful, and everyone was just behind the
convention in that moment.
And I was like, "This is lovely."
And then an astronaut fixed it, which is the exact skill set.
Like astronauts are hired to be able to take things going wrong and very quickly identify
how to fix them and then do it.
And it is not a surprise that the person who did that in the room was the astronaut,
because that is what you, that is what they are selected for.
My favourite line of the whole ceremony was, "And the winner is Octa Thorpe."
No, my second thing.
My second thing.
Sorry, I like that one.
Sorry, the case is a really massive thing.
I'm sorry, I'm collapsing.
My second favourite line of the whole ceremony was, "Oh, I tell you the winner, but I don't
have an envelope."
And everyone thought, "I'll read it off the hugo."
Yes, that was so good.
She was just like, "How do we...
That's the thing."
Quickly identifying problems and solutions.
Because obviously, if you do it at the hugo ceremony, you just cover over a small period
of embarrassment.
And if you do it in space, you're not dead.
And you don't.
I did think that they got the tone right for the hugos, because they had this really
horrible thing of like, "How do I acknowledge what happened last year that's probably going
to come up in some speeches?
How do we kind of deal with all this?"
And so I thought, one, getting John Scalzi to explain the hugos to everyone, it's great.
There's lots of first world comp people here who are like, "Why are they called the hugos?
Why are they so pointy?
Why are they so complicated?
Who gets to vote?
How do we decide?"
Yes, and so I thought they did that really well with Scalzi.
And also I thought the nominies, the finalists and winners who had been effect in the previous
year, who mentioned it in their speeches, I thought struck a really good tone of, "We
want to celebrate this year, but also acknowledge what happened last year."
I think they realised that Glasgow, Glasgow are trying their hardest to make it all work.
And so I thought that was good.
Because it could have been a ceremony where there were some real downers.
Like if someone got up and was basically like, "Yeah, this is the hugo eye."
It could be like feeling like this is the one I deserved because last year took it away
from me.
But I thought it was just nice.
It's even very nice in the audience, but also I was sitting directly behind Naomi Gritza,
so she was having a good time.
She had a good night.
Roshi Chen, who won for Best Editor, and that should have been included.
Emily Tesh was going to win for Best Novel, but I did not put it together until Emily
Tesh won for Best Novel.
And then I was like, "Yes!"
So if you are listening, if you are watching on replay, if you can hear someone shout, "Yeah!"
as she goes up, "That is me, I was very excited."
You were very excited.
Well I was very worried it wouldn't be her.
And I'm very glad it was her, because I think her book was the best book.
As discussed on previous episodes.
And I thought it was the second best book, but the book I thought was the second.
It came fifth.
So, you know.
I think it's a very good thing for the genre that St.
Abright Doors has won an Nebula, and some Desperate Glory has won a Hugo, because if
those are the two books that Science Fiction Community have decided are the two books to
recognise this year, that's pretty damn good for the state of the genre.
Those are two incredibly accomplished books.
What on the clock?
In Ascension by Marge McInnes, which I picked on OctoThorpe some months ago.
Liz is the tastemaker, but not the taskmaster.
I'm sorry for people who misread the episode title and thought we were going to do a task
master episode.
No.
We're not funny enough for that.
Alex Horn's very good, and we're fine.
Who else won?
Strange Horizons.
Bloody brilliant.
About fucking time.
They, yes, very happy with that as well.
And also, yeah, I was talking to some of them, and one of them basically came to their first
world con on one of Hugo, and I was like, it doesn't, it's not always like this.
Yeah.
Because my first world con I presented at Hugo, and then the last, and then the time after
that I was on stage was yesterday.
So that's like in a 13 year gap.
Yeah, but it was very good.
And I got to say Claire Pirely's name right.
On stage.
About time.
Of course.
A lie, you've let a roof comment.
Please wait for the microphone to reach you before making it.
We do have a roving mic, that's good.
We do.
And when should we open it to questions?
Do we have anything else we want to say?
I think, do we want to say other things about the convention as well as about the hugas?
It bloody good, wouldn't it?
This is the best world con I've been to.
I think it's probably a very good world con, and I'm looking forward to attending it over
the next four months on replay.
I will say, I don't know if we're going to do picks, but my pick is a panel.
Sorry.
And it's a panel that's not on replay, so I'm really sorry.
So I spent the weekend mostly, I've been doing the fanfans, and I've been doing a lot of
work for it, and fanfans is not great work, and I've been very tired, and every time I
get, ah, this is so, this is so hard, ah, I'm so fed up doing fanfans, and then I go,
they gave you a five week trip to Australia and New Zealand, and you can stop complaining
now, girls.
So, you know, so I'm going to be doing fanfans for a while.
They gave me a wife.
Oh, yeah.
Oh, I feel, I feel hard done by it, because I could do with a wife, because I have this
in this.
Oh, I don't know.
I think any spouse could handle that.
The opinion of the author podcast is that any spouse could deal with this issue.
It's the only room I can blame.
Or might not, I don't know.
I mean, is it that you want a wife or just that you want an extra person to clean your
house?
Have you considered hiring a cleaner?
It's complicated.
I have a complicated relationship with professional staff in my house.
I mean, I was going to say, have you considered polyamory?
There are always two solutions to every question.
One is capitalism, and the other is polyamory.
My husband's...
I don't think my husband's in the room.
Stephen?
Yes.
But I do think my ex-husband's in that room.
Wow.
That, that.
Well, wow.
Wow.
So, so...
Oh.
We were talking yesterday on one of the... maybe in the podcast meetup about how much of your
personal life you expose on the podcast, but I'm kind of like polyamory being there
done that.
Got the ex-husband.
Oh.
Shall we talk about the interview?
We were interviewed by someone, and I don't know who they were.
Go radio.
There were apparently a local Glasgow radio station, and they did videos and bits that
might put on their socials and stuff.
Yeah, it was kind of social video.
And Meg pulled us... we were just being taken off stage at the end of the thing after the
winner's photo, and Meg was like, you'll be great for these guys.
Stand there, do whatever they say.
They asked Ken Maclellan to move out of the way, because he was in the video, and I was
a bit like, oh no.
So, that was kind of...
Sorry, sorry Ken, if you're listening.
Back to the video blog, which we were talking about.
So they got us up, and they asked us some questions, which were kind of the sort of questions
you'd expect.
And then they asked what we really liked about Glasgow, and I was like, oh, I know what I'm
going to say here.
And John said...
I've really enjoyed the food, and I think Glasgow has a very vibrant food culture.
Yay!
And then Alison said, you swine, you were swine.
You snuck to me, because I was going to say how much I liked Glasgow's vibrant food culture.
I mean, I have had some great food.
I mean, I've also eaten in the Crown Plaza, but I've eaten some great food.
I haven't got off-site very much, because fanfums is fine.
I had some fabulous meals in Australia.
We had dinner with the eminent Claire Briarley and the eminent Mark Plummer on A Night, I
forget which.
And they said, I was having a rest of the day, and I'm assuming you're very busy and too
busy to have dinner with the likes of us.
But if you are not, we would love to get dinner with you.
And then they said, oh, we'd love to have dinner.
I've been prioritising seeing people and spending time with people who I do not see all the time.
So I love Claire Briarley and I love Mark Plummer, but I do, in fact, see them.
No, I know you're very lucky, but I've been having breakfast with Liz a lot, because she
lives in Thailand, which is ages away.
And I was glad to see Mark and Claire, because they live in Croydon, which is ages away.
You have to like, you get to King's Cross and you're not there yet.
It's very strange.
Um, but yes.
Um...
So that was you, guys.
So that's everything about the Hugo's in a consolce and structured way.
But we're talking about the convention.
Great.
Oh, we did the fanfons auction.
How many people have donated something to the fanfons this weekend?
Right.
How many people haven't donated something to the fanfons weekend?
You've still got about four hours.
We'll take the clothes off your pants.
Get down to the tables or, you know, just come and push cash on me.
Um, fanfons are great.
We did a live auction and we raised £4,400.
£4,420 and £20, that last £20 being the Battlestar Galactica calendar that Caroline
had lovingly kept since 1987, which, which Justin's tore up.
So we...
So that's some kind of...
I came in to, for the...
There were a set of Piercon dice, which were incredibly useful.
And I came in and the first bid was 50 quid and I was like, nope.
I don't need more dice, but I especially don't need dice that eventually go for triple digits.
I have said to multiple dice makers, oh, you know, there's something about dice in
conventional auctions.
If you give us unique dice, people paid too much.
We had three Glasgow 2024 dice from a limited edition of six and they went for £45, £55 and £60.
My Glasgow in 2024 was bought for me by one, Esther McCallum Stewart, because she bid me
up.
I think it was the East Confan Fund auction and she bid up the James Shields donated some
dice.
She bid against me until the price was like £150 quid and then she was like, I'll send
them to your job, what's your address?
She is a lovely person.
So, yeah, no, this...
Oh, that's one of my highlights.
No, I'm not too young to know who Taggot is.
Sorry.
That's why one of the prizes in the scavenger hunt you had to find a murder because of Taggot.
They were all Scotland references, some more obscure than others.
Oh, I'm sorry for putting toy money in, but come on.
So the scavenger hunt came out and I'm not easily distractable.
As evidenced by the fact that despite the fact that I had many other things to do, from
the moment I worked out where the scavenger hunt was, which did take me some time because
it was hidden in John's entry in the members' directory.
I went back and edited my introduction post, yeah.
Honestly, though, if you search for scavenger hunt, it appeared.
And Alison was like, I don't know where it is, where is it?
Where's the scavenger hunt?
I'm like...
I refused to give anyone too many hints because I was like, once you get it, it's very obvious.
I didn't...
I didn't feel...
It took me about two hours and I felt very stupid for about what I don't...
For about two more hours.
How's the scavenger hunt?
So I then spent about the next 36 hours doing the scavenger hunt and not really doing anything
else.
So I discovered the fabulous Easter egg at the scavenger hunt, which was the Tifbunch you
got everything you had 20, 24 points.
Yeah.
I'm not an idiot.
I mean, I am, but not with numbers.
Well, I mean, I am.
So, and I made an armadillo with a traffic cone on its head out of Fimo for the scavenger hunt.
And then I was like, oh, this came out quite well.
So I baked it into the...
But when I made it, it had little armadillo markings all along the side, but it only had
them on the front because I knew I was only using it for a folks' bit.
So once I decided to keep it, I had to turn it round and put the markings on the back as
well before I found it.
So I wasted a little more time.
And...
And also, a lot of people came up to me through the con and said it had really helped them
like feel good about meeting other people and stuff.
And that was kind of what we were going for.
So yeah, I'm really happy.
Well, John did two games.
And the one game was the scavenger hunt.
The other game John did was if I ran the zoo, if I ran the con, and which is the NESF
for con running game, which we did as a former episode of Octthorp.
And he wasn't at all sure how it would go.
How did it go, John?
So I have a sticker on my badge, which says, "Secret Masters of Random, hashtag Fran was
right."
And I found these stickers outside the Argyle Suite, and I nearly cried.
And part of that was because I'd been spending some time with Joe Playford, and if you know
you know, and part of that was because it was just very touching to know that I'd run
this game and it evolved like little culture and people were having very detailed discussions
about con running, but they were thinking they were playing a game.
And also like, and there was a character called Fran in the game, and the person, I need to
send a message to the person who wrote that scenario.
But I think giving you a person.
A lot of the scenarios are written very, there's no characters, but I think the fact that everyone
latched on to Fran is a sign that if they ever do a fifth edition, I think putting some
more named fans in other scenarios might help people get into it.
But yeah, like we had 100 odd people voting in the polls and arguing about whether or
not we should tell the hotel about our ton of ice.
So it was fun.
And also, yeah, a friend of mine was like, "Well, do you know what these stickers are
about?
Because I'm confused."
And I was like, "Yes, I do."
And they were like, "Why?"
And I was like, "Because I ran a game."
And they were like, "Oh."
And yeah.
So the stickers were based on the ricks.
I've been doing some virtual rippons, but not as many as I would like because...
I guess you've been busy.
Yeah, because I've been busy.
I did say I probably wasn't going to do quite a minute because I can only do the stickers
on the laptop and I pranked my legs so I can't carry the laptop.
So that, but you know.
Liz, what do you think?
I mean, I think I have more thoughts on the Discord when I've had more than five and a
half hours sleep.
But I think that was definitely a case of the Discord.
The Discord for this convention is massive.
I mean, I think like the number of program items exceeds the number of threads we're
allowed to have or something ridiculous like that.
Yeah, we are.
We are pushing up against some technical limitations annoyingly.
And so it was definitely people finding like a little corner where they could find their
tribe and I'm so happy that they found their little corner and made in jokes and stickers
and everything because otherwise you could look at the Discord and be like, nope, 5,000
channels, I'm off out.
And so I think that worked really, really well.
Probably better than when we did it as a podcast, to be honest.
Yeah, maybe.
Dokes for funnier.
And we're going to make Esther play it so that she can see whether she gets a better
score than the accumulated wisdom of the guys who are all gone.
When are you making Esther play it?
I don't know.
She's been quite busy and we haven't had time to sit down and compare diaries.
So one of my other convention highlights was that I met Esther's mum who has been at
the conventional weekend.
So we were kind of like, oh, we are not worthy again because Esther seems to have come out
quite well as a person.
So that was very nice.
So I think it's quite nice bringing your mum to the con.
Yeah.
So, so Adri's parents were in the audience to see him.
Yeah, my dad found out I wanted Hugo at, hang on, I've got a timestamp, 1110 today.
Because I'm good at communicating.
Your dad's having a good Monday then.
Yeah.
He's retired.
All Mondays are good Mondays for him.
Yeah.
I just, I have actually met John's parents.
So, yeah.
Yeah.
Mm.
Why?
On holiday, John.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
Liz was on holiday in the same place.
We were on holiday and so we hung out for a bit and it was great.
Hmm.
Sorry.
That was an interesting anecdote.
It was just a nice time.
This is an eye-hat.
And but Alison's going to go to LA con and we can show Alison Galaxy's edge.
She's promised.
She looked in the, dead in the eyes of John, I promise I'm coming to LA con.
I'm pretty sure I didn't say that.
So one of the things about this is that we might go to see, Stephen wants to go, might
go to Seattle as, see it.
Oh, it's complicated.
Anyway, last after ChaiCon, Liz and John went to Disney to Orlando, yeah?
Yeah, it was before, but yeah.
But anyway, so I didn't do that and then they sent a lot of photos of them at Galaxy's
edge and I was like, got a bit of foam over here.
Just a little bit and, you know, could have done that maybe.
And so after, and John was like, well, there'll be another LA con quite soon when there is.
You can come to Orlando and we'll show you.
No, well, there's also a Galaxy's edge in California.
Yeah.
Come to Anaheim, we'll show you Galaxy's edge and I'm very looking forward to that.
So that's a plan.
And then they announced when they announced LA con yesterday morning.
Yes, the guests of honor are great.
Yeah.
I'll probably talk about the guests of honor, but I'm only going to talk about one right
now, which is that the fan guest of honor is Jerry Sullivan, who had just got COVID
at the point.
So she wasn't in the room for them to say and we like to introduce Jerry Sullivan, but
there was apparently a very big cheer in the business meeting when Jerry's name was announced,
which is quite nice.
They are all their guests are good.
Do you want to read the map properly, John?
Come on.
I was going to talk about the LA con guests.
I mean, I'm not going to, they're so, I have three.
Three, I think they're very exciting.
They have Ronald D. Moore of Bathstyle Electica for All Mankind, Deep Space Nine.
Like that is really like what you can do, I guess, when you're in LA.
So I think that's really cool.
They have Stan Sakai of U Sanji, your jimbo.
And they have Tim Kirk.
And I was a little bit confused because I think there's also a Tim Kirk in UK fandom.
There are two of them.
I thought it was like, which Tim Kirk is it?
There are two in UK fandom.
Yeah.
And it's under those.
It's not to be a Tim Kirk who has previously won Hugo's for art, but is also a Disney
Imagineer who made Tokyo Disney seat.
So I am personally very excited about all these people.
Barbara Hambley, Colleen Duran, Anita, Sen Gupta are the three we haven't mentioned and
the Toastmaster will be a Syla Benin, which is also a very good pick.
Especially because it means she's going to get to more.
Man, it's just going to be different sea creatures like for every category, isn't it?
I mean, I met Sue Mason in 1984, one of my oldest and dearest friends and approximately
two minutes after we met, she said Colleen Duran is the best illustrator working in the
world.
She is my favourite illustrator.
So I am delighted that only 40 some odd years later she's getting to be a guest of
an honor at a world con.
It's like, I feel like she's quite a niche interest.
And we were talking, we were talking, I can't remember if we, I sometimes get confused
between conversations I've had on the podcasting, just conversations I've had.
So like apologies, I don't remember if this was an episode.
We were discussing when Gerry Anderson was a guest of honor at a world con.
And we're going through the list of guests of honor and there really aren't many that
have worked in media, which obviously reflects the interest of the world con.
I think it's great.
But like I do think, you know, especially now the quality of science fiction in movies
and TV over the last decade has just, I mean, it's insane.
Like, you, for mankind is absolutely amazing.
And the fact that like it's up there with like severance and and or another great science
fiction that's on the screen.
And I do think Ronald D. Moore is exactly the sort of person where it's like, he's done
thoughtful science fiction.
He's done a lot of it.
He will be fascinating to see on panels.
And obviously it ties in with Hollywood and the fact that we're not sandalies.
But I just I really like that they have him as a as a guest.
I think it's really good as well as people from the more literary tradition of the world
con.
I think it's a great roster.
I'm very excited about LA.
I mean, my sister in Nolibs is Santa Monica.
So we will definitely be going because because it's good excuse to hang out with her as well.
I missed Spanish yesterday as we usually do Spanish at half five on a Saturday, but yeah,
I was busy yesterday or Sunday.
Oh shit.
Well, OK, I've lost a day.
That's awkward, isn't it?
Well, oh well, sorry, Ashley.
But yeah, good, good guests.
All right, I'm going to do a pick.
So long time listeners will know that I quite like Agent Tchaikovsky.
And I'm also quite a big fan of Keering Gillan.
And so when I saw that Keering Gillan was running a live action role playing game or
no, sorry, he's running a role playing game live on a panel for Agent Tchaikovsky, Emma
Vicelli and Amal Mocta.
I was like, I have to go to that.
I got there half an hour early.
The room was full.
They turned away quite a few people and and Keering ran a game for the other three in
which they were playing panelists at a world con who were doing a panel about a game that
they had made.
So the panel made their characters and then left the room re-entered as the fake character
they just made and then those people made characters to play the game in the game.
Right?
Now, this was quite confusing.
I went with Andy and Joe.
It was Joe's birthday, happy birthday, Joe.
And that was the first panel she's ever been to at a world con.
So it was quite the introduction.
And it was phenomenal.
It was so good because they took questions from the audience like it was a real panel.
So you've got the person who's like, this is really more of a comment than a question
which got a big round of applause from the audience, which doesn't usually happen.
And just Keering, prancing around, he's like, oh yes, no, the floor opens up and there are
demons down there and the Tolkien fans that are squabbling over the Silmarillion.
And it was just, it was so good.
And I'm really sorry it wasn't on replay, but it was probably the best program item
I've ever seen at World con and I'm so sorry Alison.
And I got kicked out because it was full.
So thank you, John, for telling me in Masti, tell what.
Yeah, no, I'm sorry.
But I, that's, yeah.
But I said to, and then I met Keering Gillan at the post Hugo reception and I was like
squeezing to him.
And then I told him the question I asked when he came, I was like, I was one of that question.
He was like, brilliant.
When I talk about that question, how it really showed the people getting the panel and I
was like, oh, so anyway, so yeah, I like Keering Gillan, then he's good.
And then Emma, and then I met other people and I had a lovely time.
Thank you.
So I thought the idea of picks was to highlight things that other people do.
Well, you can go and play die the role playing game.
And if you're ever at a convention where Keering, because sometimes Keering runs 36 person games
where he plays evil Keering Gillan and he's like the god for six different groups flitting
between them.
And that also sounds amazing, but he, this is not the only time he will run this.
I, I feel like, I feel like this is a point of the future that going to see Keering Gillan
do his thing and not being so busy at conventions that you can't see any program.
I got to one program item that I wasn't involved in.
So that is my pick.
And two of the guests of honor at this convention are Claire Braley and Mark Plummer, the eminent
Mark Plummer who said to third telegram earlier this episode.
And they are Britain's greatest living fan writers and they, oh, that is, that is in
Jupiter.
And I've got a present for them.
You know what this is.
Do I?
Oh, good.
I know what it is.
I just have to find it.
I don't know what it is.
John Cox and brought a load of pins over to the fan funds table.
I did.
And I immediately brought one, but one which I thought would be a fine pin to give to
Claire and Mark because it is a real society for the protection of birds, shag.
And one of the things about Mark and Claire's guest of honor speech, which is my pick, and
they basically do their, they are very serious fan writers.
Yes, they are very serious.
And they have a, an obvious resentment of tradition.
And they are also extremely interested in fan history.
So what they did was a really extremely serious canter through fan history, through the medium
of extremely silly photos of all of their friends.
Yes.
And it was hilarious.
And if you are one of their friends, you should watch it.
And if you aren't one of their friends, you should watch it anyway because you will
probably laugh quite a lot.
It is a very funny speech.
And one of the things that was not in it was any mention of their no shagging disclaimer,
which I thought was quite interesting.
We have five minutes.
Have you done your pick list?
No, my pick is, well comes, like well comes.
I mean, I did see lots of panels and like the name, the titles of them all have basically
left my brain because my brain is going, oh, there's a Hugo there.
So we'll get into those on a future episode.
But I mean, well come, well come.
James, so James Shields has just put a picture of Karen Gillan on the, on the discord and
said, I've just realised this is not who John was talking about.
And it is probably a sign of my flavour of nerd that I was more excited about Karen Gillan
than I would be about Karen Gillan, which is quite a statement.
So from Mark's, they have never seen them in the same room.
So, yes, a shag.
Bridget also has a shag.
I'm glad you've got a shag, Bridget.
Of course.
I mean, I hope you're all enjoying the flavour.
What it is like to record a podcast with John and Alison and admiring the edit job John does
every week.
We'll talk.
Yes.
And people came and I only knew two of them, which was genuinely baffling to me.
And one of them said, I love how you don't talk over each other and don't interrupt.
And I was like, this table talk might be awkward because you listen to an edited podcast and
it ain't always like that.
So we had to explain that we record separate streams.
And so John removes all the times when I talk over John Liz and John talks over me and
Liz and Liz does not ever talk over anybody except sometimes there's a zoom glitch.
Other than that.
I do sometimes when I'm like, Alison, shall we get back on topic?
No.
But yes, does anyone else have any?
Does anyone have any questions now before we wrap up?
I hear muttering about comments in the audience.
I don't believe we have no questions.
Bridget comments the shag is available on eBay.
I didn't know that you could get them there, but apparently...
I didn't know.
Yeah, no, I didn't know you could get a shag on eBay.
Interesting.
Lea Neel asked on the Discord what the question I asked in the Dye panel was and it would
take so much explaining, but I won't explain it on the podcast.
But if you want to know, I will be in a bar at some point.
So do come and find me and I will talk to you enthusiastically about it at length.
Closing remarks?
I'm the moderator now.
I would like to thank the tech team in the room.
I want to thank them for all of the work they've been doing over the last few years.
JT always makes recording the podcast incredibly easy.
It's easier to do a live podcast at a convention than it is to wrangle the Zoom.
So JT, thank you very much.
And to the rest of the tech also, thank you very much.
I met JT yesterday.
I'm just going to say...
I'm not met JT, but...
No, no, no.
And he was explaining that because of doing opt forbs, they could now set up this...
They knew how to set up this room for every podcast in the world, because they have recorded
opt forb, and after that nothing is ever as bad ever again.
We were talking, so Kevin and Laurie Anderson from Hugo Girl were a Spaniard in my plus
ones for the reception and the afterparty.
And they were talking about recording an episode of Hugo's There with Seth, and they
said they were very impressed by the podcast room.
There's a podcast room at the convention, so if you want to record a podcast, you can
go and there's multiple microphones and you get a stick at the end with the different
tracks and they were like, "It's so good!"
And I was like, "Yeah, they asked us, they asked us, like, you know, what would you want?"
And we said, "We would want this."
I gave Meg the acceptable minimum what you actually really want if you're going to go
the mile.
And yeah, I know they were like genuinely like, they're really good.
So...
We're going to get cut off in like one minute.
So if you want to do...
They were very happy.
Thanks and stuff.
I would also like to thank Esther, Meg and Marguerite for running a fantastic Worldcon
and being very kind to put us on the programme.
And a round of applause for JT and Tech as well, because like we got distracted by
an ago.
I would also very much like to thank my lovely co-hosts, Alison and Liz, who have been very
good. We've recorded 116 episodes now, which is quite a lot.
And yeah, couldn't do it without you guys.
Love you both.
Love you too, John.
Right then.
And on that disgustingly sweet ending.
It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
[Applause]
[Music]
This podcast will end at the beep.
Brilliant.