Please continue while I retrieve my Allen keys and fix this sagging microphone stand.
Fair enough.
That was the wrong size Allen key and it's now dropped down a bit more.
So I'll be back in one minute with a bigger Allen key.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 137th episode of Octothorpe, a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom,
which is arriving in the club to a susurrus as people note its return and will be coming to you on the 19th of June 2025.
I am John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
John, can you play a bit of the and or club mix under that intro or will we get done for copyright?
Let me consult the lawyers.
The lawyers say they don't exist and we'll definitely lose to Disney.
Hmm. Fair, fair.
Yeah, yeah. Don't mess with the mouse.
We will put in the club mix or the hour of more mothma dancing because it is a certified banger.
And just imagine that's playing or play it yourself through your headphones while you listen.
Yes, that is our recommendation for this episode.
It will lead to this feeling much more high octane than usual.
And we have some layers of comment, listeners.
We heard from Jake Sellabrookins who sent us a lovely little mp3 with some ruminations on the pronunciation of wussfuss.
And, well, I'll let Casella take it away.
John, Alison, Liz, hello.
This is Casella from A Meal of Thorns and the Ancillary Review.
I've been enjoying all eight of your thorps lately.
I thought I knew how to pronounce the acronym for the World Science Fiction Society.
But after saying it a few dozen times, I'm less and less sure.
There are regional vowel dialect choices warring invisibly within me.
Wissfuss.
I think Wissfuss.
Yeah, Wiss...
Wiss...
No, Wissfuss.
Mm.
And then we also heard from Ange who gave us the Scouse version.
Here's your Scouse pronunciation.
Wissfuss.
And what I want to know is where were all the rest of you?
But well done to those two for writing in.
We appreciate it.
It's actually quite nice to hear the voices of the listeners.
Yes.
I don't think I want you to send us MP3s all the time.
Otherwise, well, I mean, maybe we should get everyone to send us MP3s.
And one week we'll just put together an episode which is listen to MP3s.
And we won't have to do anything.
But it is nice to hear from people occasionally.
We also had Neil Harrison record Andy Openshaw saying Wissfuss.
And I will insert that recording here.
Wissfuss.
But Andy messaged me the day after.
So Andy hadn't listened to the podcast at this point.
So he thought Neil was just being very extra.
And that was very funny to watch.
But also Andy writes, please note, I'm from County Durham and I'm not a Geordie.
We regret the error.
Oh.
I just I have a very I have a very favourite folk singer who's called Jeslow, who is from
County Durham and actually talks about himself as a Geordie all of the time and is kind of.
Does he live in London?
Very much not.
Where does he live?
Well, in a bus.
He's a or in a van.
He's a working folk musician.
He's a folk singer.
He's not earning the big bucks, John.
Oh, no.
I mean, he lives.
I don't know where he lives exactly.
But you should look out for him because he's amazing.
I mean, he's really, really, really good.
I wonder.
I guess the reason I asked was because I wonder whether there's a thing where if you don't
live in Newcastle and you're from County Durham, you might call yourself a Geordie.
But if you live in Newcastle or you're from County Durham, you might draw the line differently.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So I think that might be.
I think he may be a Geordie on stage.
He's certainly a professional Geordie, right?
Brilliant episode title.
I will put a link to the music of Jez Lowe because I love it.
All right.
I have also seen Jez Lowe, weirdly, where mine and Alison's musical taste have overlapped and
he is extremely.
I would have said he was extremely Geordie, but now I don't want to get into the whole minefield.
I think I've recommended that John go and see Jez Lowe before because, I mean, I'm sure
he does gigs in your area quite a lot.
And he's so good.
But yeah, we saw him at the Chroma Folk on the Pier Festival that we went to with his band.
We're going to start with some letters of comment on almond croissants and we're going
to let Alison loose on the relevant Facebook thread.
Alison, do you want to pick some things out?
I think, in case you make clear, we're starting with some comments on almond croissants.
And we'll start with Nola, who said, I'd like Alison to know that I did laugh at her almond
croissant fantasy hero joke, despite only hearing it.
Goodo.
And also on almond croissants, David Bamford wrote to say, they listened to the episode on
a drive down to Androsen that if there are no almond croissants to be found when we get
there, we will be most upset.
I lived quite close to Androsen for four years.
And when I lived there, which was from 1974 to 1978, I think I can state with almost absolute
certainty that there was no almond croissant to be found for a considerable radius.
I mean, probably could have got one in Glasgow.
Andreas de Vaux wrote to say, two Mastodon posts saying they became hungry and now crave an
episode about banoffee pie in the same detail and engagement.
If we ever have Stephen on the podcast as a stunt Alison, you should ask him about banoffee
pie.
Yes.
And also said, I did in the process find a recipe for apple pie with frangipan, which seems
to be the fancy French word for a tasty nutty paste.
Yes, it is.
And almond croissants have to have frangipan in the middle of them, which is part of what I
talked about on the episode.
So yes, if you are one of today's 10,000 on frangipan, Andreas, I salute you.
Various people bought almond croissants or lamented the fact that they could not eat at
almond croissants on Facebook.
Sheila last said the best almond croissant she's had is from Pret at Waverly Station.
And I'm here to say that there is a world of wonder out there for you because although
Pret's almond croissants are, I think, pretty good for chain coffee shops croissants, and
I will definitely have one if I am in a Pret, there are a lot better almond croissants out
there to be found.
So off you go.
I think that is that everything on almond croissants?
Maybe not quite.
There's one thing on almond croissants which is not in the show notes, but Andy Openshaw messaged
me to point out that Pink Lane Bakery, which didn't used to have a location that had seating,
has now opened a location with seating in Jesmond.
So yeah.
Thank you very much, Andy.
Oh, isn't Pink Lane the one we went to by the station in Newcastle?
No, that's Pink Lane Coffee.
Oh.
Pink Lane Coffee and Pink Lane Bakery are a coffee shop and a bakery on Pink Lane.
Ah!
They are geographically coincident.
They are not, like, corporately coincident.
No.
Ah, they are not a brand.
Okay, so we went to Pink Lane Coffee, which does have seating, and as I recall, did a perfectly
adequate almond croissant.
But I was too, we were travelling by train along with Claire and Mark, so obviously Claire
had that, I must be, I must be on the train good and early.
I took Liz to Pink Lane Coffee and she departed for her train 15 minutes early and exited the
coffee shop, saw the station across the road and thought, and said to me, I may have left
too much time for my train, John.
And I was like, well, no judging, no judging.
That's the sort of thing we'd have done.
I was being picked up at the other end and so I did not want to disrupt things by getting
on the wrong train.
Yes.
No, it was very fair.
Also, I was jet-lagged.
It is where I usually recommend people go if they are about to get a train from Newcastle
on account of how it's extremely close.
We did also get some letters of comment that were not from, not based around almond croissants.
I will pick out one from Blue Sky to get us rolling.
Ed Morland writes in to say, on the subject of Magic Maze, which I mentioned last episode,
the red dobber of passive aggression may be the single greatest board game component in
the history of board game.
Yeah, no, I think that is a defensible statement.
I did watch two people trade the dobber back and forth angrily in complete silence once and
it was delightful.
You may need to explain how the dobber works in Magic Maze because I think I worked it out
from context.
Or not, if it's funnier.
Basically, if someone needs to do a thing and they haven't noticed they need to do a thing,
you put a red thing in front of them to tell them that they're fucking up and then they
have to work out what it is you mean by that.
Shit, I need that for Hannaby.
And then if two people, if two people are just trading it back and forth, it just gets
incredibly funny as they both get more and more frustrated.
And I have seen this and it is great.
Magic Maze is on my list of things I'm hoping to pick up in a charity shop at some point.
I think we should play Magic Maze.
I mean, it'd be a terrible podcast, but it'd be very funny.
Is it one of those silent ones?
Yeah.
Well, next time we're in the same place, we could just record a video and stick it on YouTube.
So we have podcasts with no video and then we have video with no sound.
So there probably would be some sound, I think.
Yes.
Right.
But yes, thank you very much for writing in, Ed.
Should I talk about Hinkley?
Yes.
So last episode, I think we were talking about most remote Eastercon venues we'd had recently.
And we mentioned the Hinkley Eastercons, which were in the Hinkley Island Hotel, which is no
longer the Hinkley Island Hotel.
It's a jury's in or something.
But anyway, and Rosanna Pendleby wrote to us to say, very weird to hear Hinkley mentioned.
I wasn't expecting it on Octop.
Ah, well, you should because it's stuck in everyone's memory because of the weirdness of
the Hinkley Island Hotel.
Did have a little sort of, a little like row of shops inside the hotel.
I once saw a stand-up comic do a set and he described Hinkley as the sort of place where
people still point their aeroplanes.
Ooh.
Yeah.
Never been.
I'm sure it's lovely.
We also got some comments this week on Facebook.
We heard from Tammy Coxon, who says the 2008 site selection vote is used as a cautionary tale
because apparently there were more than 12 people on the Chicago Bid Committee who failed
to vote, which I did not know and makes it even more ouch, basically.
Yes.
That was great.
Tammy also leaves some comments about the evolution of the fan art and pro art Hugo categories and
links to her piece on File 770 on it.
We will link to that and I note that there may be more discussion of the art Hugos later
in the episode foreshadowing.
Yeah.
I think the point that she made is that some professional artists are grumpy about being
relegated to the fan artist category because the sort of way they make money from art isn't
the sort of way that the professional artist Hugo reflects because it is very focused on
art for publication.
And there are lots of other ways to make art these days and make money with it.
And I think that's a good point that I hadn't considered properly.
I still don't think it makes up for saying that all that fan artists have to only work in
an amateur basis, which obviously rules out many of the previous fan artist Hugos.
Presumably the thing we said last time about 25% of your income coming from your art would
fix this.
But Mike Scott also wrote on Facebook to point out that the early fan artist Hugos were often
won by pro artists for fan art they were doing in their spare time.
But obviously that's happened in fan writer as well.
So I assume that you could word the thing to be like if you're not getting 25% of your
income from the art you win for, which would probably work, but you'd need to workshop it
a little bit.
I think it would be better than this tack anyway.
I mean, I think there must be something around saying that fan art is open to people who've
done a body of unpaid work for fan art purposes.
Yeah.
But I don't know.
People have been arguing about this for a very long time.
Mm hmm.
And we're going to continue arguing about it.
Yeah.
Yes.
Yes, we are.
We also heard on Facebook from Farrah who pointed out that our discussion of food last
week about food at Reconnect, the Eastercon, did talk about sandwiches a lot, which does
exclude people who are going to have dietary restrictions, which restrict them from eating
anything with gluten, which is very true.
I think this is partly because I really like sandwiches and I don't eat a lot of sandwiches
right now.
And so my brain automatically goes to sandwiches.
And also because it's what my brain thinks of as easy to move, portable food.
And I feel that the hotel was quite good at food you could sit down and eat, but maybe not
that stuff you could grab and go.
So we do need to have options that you can grab and go that are not based around bread.
Yeah.
I think I will say like I assume gluten free bread sandwiches would be OK for people with
celiac.
But there are not that many portable forms of food that are not wrapped in something that
you would have to make gluten free.
I think.
You could have like sushi rolls or something.
Yeah.
Sushi.
Great example.
Yes.
True.
That is.
I think there are counter examples.
I guess my point being there are not lots.
No, there are not.
But I think I would like to see more like gluten free sausage rolls, gluten free sandwiches, gluten
free tortilla wraps.
All of these things I fully think should be gluten free.
100%.
I guess what I mean is when I say there should be a wide variety of sandwiches, I mean there
should be a wide variety of sandwiches that can be eaten by people with a range of dietary
preferences, not just by people who are not celiac.
Does that make sense?
But I don't think I said that last time.
So it's fair cop.
It does make sense.
But as someone who does not regularly eat the gluten free options, I have no idea if hotels
always provide really terrible gluten free sandwiches and therefore you prefer them to do something
that wasn't a sandwich.
So I guess I guess the question I would ask, I think would be really useful to ask.
is what conventions have done this well?
And what did they do?
Because that was a point I tried to make last time, which is I'm not sure whether Belfast
was uniquely bad or whether conventions are just very bad at this.
So please tell us about the conventions that did food requirements well.
And please tell us what it was that they did.
Like, what is the actual answer?
Because I'd be fascinated to know as someone who does not have any of these dietary requirements.
As somebody who's worked on quite a lot of conventions, I think the answer may be
that it's not so much anything the convention does.
It's the thing the venue does.
So that no matter how much you tell and work with the venue in advance, they can still mess
it up on the day quite substantially.
I think Inominate had an excellent range of food that catered to almost everybody by having
indoor food court, an indoor food court system.
And we went back to the same hotel not that long later, and they just couldn't do it for
us.
I have no idea.
So Inominate was the 2017 Eastcon in Birmingham.
Birmingham also has the advantage that it has the food trucks outside.
But I think we discussed last time, Belfast probably couldn't have done either a food court
or food trucks.
Well, the food court was just the hotel's internal catering putting stalls in a conference room.
Yeah, it was great.
So any hotel could do that if they wanted to.
They made a packet because obviously lots of people bought food and liked it.
The hotel sold a lot of food profitably.
That's what hotels should want to do.
You would think.
I think I would also still peg 2017 as being the recent high watermark of confit.
It was really good.
And it was varied.
And it wasn't just, you know, a jacket potato with beans.
I think I had like a goat curry.
It was super spicy.
It was really good.
Goat curry was...
It wasn't even that spicy.
I mean, this also...
Also in 2017, this was more important because they hadn't built that giant resort world thing.
So you couldn't easily pop out to Nando's or whatever.
No, they had.
Yeah, we had resort world.
We just didn't realise we had resort world until we got there because the previous time we hadn't.
Because I had a really good meal in 2017 and I wanted to go back to the restaurant, which is no longer there.
All right.
Well, we just hadn't realised it was there then.
Or maybe it didn't have as much stuff.
That's probably right.
I think it's very new.
Shall we leave that for the listeners and move on?
Yes.
Raj wrote in.
He kept looking for us in the bar at Reconnect and it was his own fault for not checking which bar we meant.
Sorry, Raj.
I think this is brought to you by the fact that we were all in Rattlebag for a lot of the time.
And...
Raj wasn't in Rattlebag.
And we missed you, Raj.
But we couldn't actually have had the entire convention at Rattlebag.
We did meet Raj at the Octothop meetup.
We did.
I don't know.
To be fair, we met Raj at least once when he was coming back from a bar somewhere else.
So...
I did watch several EastCon catch-up items and the BSFA lecture on DEI and Tolkien was his favourite.
He didn't love the zoom UI on phone though.
And he said he would like it to...
So, he discovered that Firefox would continue to play when the screen was off so he could listen like a podcast.
And he would love for just the audio to be extracted to listen like a podcast.
I do wonder whether...
I thought this for punctuation and actually because I had all of the files, I was able to do it just for me.
And it was really good because it meant I could just listen to them like a podcast.
Which I think is the way to listen to panels because the video very rarely adds much context, I find.
So, yes.
I don't know.
I think...
But I think I want to applaud Belfast for their excellent approach to the online components.
And I think I'm happy that EastCon's are trying to get this bit of the catch-up right before branching out.
I will say, in the UK, it is EDI.
And I am getting progressively more frustrated with the fact that everyone's calling it DEI because the US version's been in the news a lot.
So, yes.
EDI.
It's a very small rant.
But it is a rant.
So, we thought we would alert you to a couple of online events which are happening this weekend.
Assuming you are listening to the podcast right after it comes out.
And I assume you all do listen to the podcast right after it comes out.
The British Fantasy Society are holding basically a one-day showcase for the World Fantasy Con, which will be happening in the UK later this year.
And so, they have, I think, a free one-day online...
Oh, it's free for BFS members and a fiver if you are a non-member.
And you can sign up and attend online.
And they've got panels and readings and discussions with their guests.
And it will give you an idea of what you're going to get at World Fantasy Con.
So, that is happening on Saturday, the 21st of June.
And on Sunday, the 22nd of June, the BSFA and the Science Fiction Foundation are holding their joint online AGM as they usually do.
And that is on the 22nd of June.
I don't have all the details about that.
But I think if you're a BSFA or SFF member, you will have been emailed or will be about to be emailed details of how you join that.
Thank you very much, Liz.
Are you going to go to either of those things?
No.
On account of time zones.
The Read Our Latest News page, yes.
So, we'll put a link...
I'll put a link in the show notes to the Science Fiction Foundation one, which does give you an idea of the timings and what's going on.
But again, I think you have to be remembered to be linked.
I've got all the information in my BSFA newsletter.
Ah.
Yeah, so there's lots of interesting things going on.
Would you like to tell us about any of them, Alison?
Yeah, I mean, I thought you'd said that there was a link and it had everything.
So, Paul March Russell in conversation with EJ Swift.
A Fish and Five panel.
Writers from the forthcoming Fish and Five anthology discuss their work with Eugene Bacon.
The SFF AGM.
The BSFA Applied Science Fiction panel.
Alan Stroud, Anna Sun, Christina Carley, Fiona Moore and Stephen Oram discussing about how science fiction can be used in different fields.
Reflections on the 2025 Clark shortlist.
I don't know who is responsible for that because no name is mentioned.
And then the BSFA AGM.
And then perhaps a bonus final feature.
Oh.
So that's quite a full day, actually.
That's the 22nd of June.
It's not impossible.
So that's quite clever that they're on two adjacent days.
So you can have an entire virtual weekend doing science fiction conventions if you want.
Yes.
Do we think it was on purpose?
I guess.
Actually, I suppose it probably was.
You would like to think so.
And it actually might have been.
Nice.
So yeah.
I probably won't be going to either of those.
But they do look cool.
And the British Fantasy Society's event has some interesting people present.
And sort of the program looks pretty cool.
It's got readings by various people, including Russell Smith, who is good.
And yeah.
Just some interesting looking panels as well.
So hurrah.
At the time of recording, there are 29 non-member tickets for the online convention.
And there are 34 BFS member tickets left.
I assume that this is due to Zoom number caps.
But I don't know.
So hopefully there are tickets by the time we drop the episode, listeners.
Our apologies if there are not.
Casella over at Ancillary Review of Books, who sent us a audio snippet earlier this very episode,
has written a very sort of detailed and very well thought out article arguing that there should be a Hugo Award for best translated work.
And effectively, we will link in the show notes, listeners.
And I recommend everyone go and read it because I'm sure that there will be nuances in that article that we elide.
Elide on the pod.
But effectively argues that a best translated work is necessary to recognize global speculative fiction.
And that's something we should do if we want to put the world into WorldCom.
And in general, I think it is very well argued.
I would love to see WorldCom recognize more works in translation.
I think that's very good.
I think I would want to see the translator and the author win whatever the award was,
because I think you'd want to make sure that you are recognizing the skill in the translation as well as the skill in the original text.
Casella does say basically he can see one pitfall, which is that because Hugo rules say that work can only show up in one category.
So he can imagine, for instance, translated novels only winning the best translated award.
And sort of people thinking, oh, well, you know, they won that because it's best translated, but they wouldn't have won if they were in novel.
Or the reverse, kind of a translated book being put into novel instead of into best translated work and then losing in novel where it might have won in best translated
work.
I think the obvious solution here is to make it more in the vein of the Lodestar, where it is an award that is awarded sort of coincident with the Hugos, but is not a Hugo.
And because that means that all of those books are still eligible in the Hugo categories.
I don't think the presence of the Lodestar indicates that Waspurs cares less about young adult fiction in much the same way that I don't think the fact that the
Astounding is the Astounding indicates that Waspurs cares less about upcoming authors.
I think it's just a recognition that these things seek to award on a slightly different set of criteria than the Hugos, which is very much kind of hard number based
definitions of things, mostly ish.
What do we think about this idea, peeps?
So I think you've covered the main issue, which is that we tend to try not to award Hugos for the same thing in two categories.
And you're going to have an uneasy split whichever way you do it.
So yes, it could be an extra award.
I think the other thing is whether we think there are enough Hugo voters who read sufficient fiction in translation to do a good short list.
I am not 100% convinced of that one.
I think just because you can list quite a lot of potential contenders in translation doesn't necessarily mean any of them will have enough critical mass or readership
to get on there.
I think basically this is just where Casella is more optimistic than I am about what the readership is reading.
I mean, I think one issue is that we know translations can get on the Hugo ballots and have got on the Hugo ballots and won.
So if these novels are not currently getting on the Hugo short list or long list at all, does that indicate that there's just not quite enough there that the readership
are reading to get on?
I mean, the solution here would be to run it as a like a trial balloon category, like best poetry and best game for a year or two years and see what you get.
I think my other objection, which is not really specific about best translation is more philosophical, is that we are never getting rid of any Hugos and we're just
getting more and more.
And I don't believe we will ever get rid of Hugo because I think as soon as anyone proposes to get rid of a Hugo, there will be enough people who really care about it that
they will show up and vote to not get rid of it.
So I think it is becoming an issue of how many awards we have and how long the award ceremonies are and how much overhead this is for conventions to manage.
And I just don't see us ever going down.
But that's not really specific to any of the actual proposed Hugos.
It's just my feeling that we've got a lot and I don't know what we do about that.
Maybe we just have lots and it's fine.
Yeah, I think you've basically covered all of my points between you.
It's really the overlap and how many Hugos do we need anyway.
Are there other ways that we could recognise translated fiction that aren't having a special Hugo?
Do you mean as Worldcon or as the field in general?
As the field in general, I think.
And partly some of this is about having publishers looking out for the best books in other languages.
And it doesn't even need to be other languages.
There are plenty of great books written in English in countries other than the US and the UK that don't actually ever make it to US and UK publishers.
Though that is better than it used to be.
And I think just looking more widely for your science fiction is a good thing.
I agree.
I think so.
I think Casella is making a specific argument about translation.
I think because there are lots of books written outside Anglophone countries.
I'm reluctant to say just the US and the UK because I am reminded, for instance, that Canada also has quite a big impact on Anglophone fiction.
And I'm sure that Ireland, Australia and New Zealand would also want to have a vote.
I think the thing is that if you seek to recognise books written in English outside Anglophone countries, are you encouraging the sort of dynamics of that global
hegemony in the same way the Worldcon already does?
And might Casella be suggesting this because he thinks actually disrupting that dynamic might be a good thing?
And so I do take the point.
I don't think I want to see an award for best science fiction from outside an Anglophone country.
But I do think having an award for translated work would be cool.
I am curious and I have not done the research.
But I would be very curious to see how many translated works make it onto the short lists or not the short lists or the long lists for the Hugo Awards.
Like Casella gives the the numbers of non-English works that have made it to finalists for their three for best novel, two for novella, three for novelette, one for
short story, one for related work.
And so like, you know, clearly that says there's not a critical mass to get them into the traditional Hugo categories.
But do people like are people reading these enough that they make it onto the long lists?
Because if they are, then this award could work.
But if they're not, I think that the constituency might be so uneducated in this sector that it ends up not being viable at all.
And I think I'd be interested to see whether.
Yeah, I'd be just interested to see what that data says, basically.
But I think Liz's point about trial balloon is also very good.
Like run it for a year and see what the numbers are and see what happens.
You don't necessarily have to run it as a Hugo.
I don't know whether any Worldcon can obviously award a special award.
But I guess running it as a Hugo would make the point better than running it as not a Hugo.
Even if you thought in the long run running it as a Hugo was not the right way to do it.
That was a very convoluted point.
But hopefully it made sense, listeners.
Okay, so I know I should have made this point earlier.
And in my defence, I'm tired.
But something triggered something in my brain.
And I was reminded that the BSFA has introduced an award for best translated short work.
And they have done it as a juried award rather than as a public award.
And so there's nothing stopping the Worldcon having a juried award for best translated work.
And a juried award is probably a much better way to do it because...
Yeah, so how much work are juried awards, John?
Ah, they're fine.
You just read books.
It's great.
I think I would also say that there was a science fiction and fantasy translation award,
which I believe was juried.
It only lasted a few years.
And I'm not sure what led it to close.
But maybe that would be something that could be revived.
The problem...
The problem with the juried...
So, in order to submit a book to the Arthur C. Clarke Award,
you have to pay £250 to submit your book.
And that makes a lot of sense because the Arthur C. Clarke Award
firstly has a cash prize of the number of pounds equals to year.
And also the Arthur C. Clarke Award has been around long enough
that it has a cultural cachet that means you want to win one.
The problem with spinning up a new juried award
is how do you get the books to your jury?
And do you make them all by them themselves?
Which disenfranchises anyone on the jury who cannot afford to do that.
Do you give it some endowment?
And if you do, where does that come from?
Does it come from the Worldcon?
Can you persuade...
You might be able to persuade one Worldcon committee to do that.
Can you persuade enough that you get the critical mass
to have a juried award go forward for a long enough time?
You might be able to persuade our authors to submit for free.
Like, give us free books, we might give you an award.
That could work.
Might be the best option.
But there are considerations with a juried award
which the Hugos don't really have to think about
because the Hugos don't...
Firstly, the Hugos have the cachet already.
But secondly, the Hugos rely on people reading
sort of nominating books they've already read.
So you don't need to try and give everyone all of the books.
The Clarke...
Yeah, like I say,
you have to pay £250 and also give
seven hard copies of your book to the award.
And there will be...
For a new award, there will be lots of people who think,
I'm not going to do that.
And that might impact how viable it is.
I wonder whether it would.
I'd be interested in hearing about other sort of newer,
more junior juried awards,
how they do submissions and stuff.
Because I don't have a good view of that.
So if any listeners know, please write in.
A couple of other things to add is,
I did go back for the past few years
and do what John suggests and look in the long list
to see what is there in translation.
Love you, Les.
But basically everything since about 2021 is skewed
because of the 2023 Worldcon in China.
There are non-English language stories
and translated stories on those lists,
but they're almost,
I think they're all exclusively Chinese
or Chinese translations.
And the other thing is,
I had a quick look at the World Fantasy Award,
which has this kind of hybrid
voted by attendees of the World Fantasy Award
and also judges who can add extra nominees
before they vote,
has occasionally nominated and awarded
translated novels.
In particular, in 2006,
they gave it to Murakami for Kafka on the Shore.
They've also nominated,
I think, Perfume
and The Memory Police
are both in translation.
So they are occasionally picking out translations,
although I think those are all
kind of very popular translations
that a lot of people will have heard of.
I'd be really interested to know
if they came from the voters
or from the jury.
And I don't think there's any way
you ever find out
which ones kind of are jury editions
and which ones are voted ones.
But that would be really interesting.
So they do occasionally award that.
I had a quick look at the Nebulas
and I think there was like one
that I spotted.
This is not a very systematic,
I've not done a very systematic survey though.
So there's probably more that I don't know.
And sometimes in,
I was looking at Wikipedia
and they don't always credit the translators.
It's hard to know if there are translations,
but I think they,
yeah, they have nominated like Calvino way back.
Although that is in 1975
when apparently the best novel shortlist
was about 20 novels.
So do not remember
or know what was going on there.
But yeah,
I just did also want to add
that the Science Fiction
and Fantasy Translation Awards,
I think had some sponsorship
from various foundations and things.
They closed them
because they didn't have the time and energy
for all the people involved to run them.
So it wasn't financial.
Okay, interesting.
That's good to know.
So I'm just looking through,
I have just read a lot of books
for the Clark Award.
Far more, you know,
far more books from the wider genre
than I would usually read.
And as part of that,
I have read three books in translation,
which were Nomadland by Francesco Verso,
Jump Noughts by Hao Jing Fang,
and The Mark by Frieda Eisberg,
which was my pick last episode
or the episode before,
can't remember.
And so I have not read enough
works in translation
to fill my Hugo nomination ballot
this year.
and I am a Clark Award judge.
So I suspect I'm towards
one end of the bell curve
on how well read I am.
And so if I don't have enough
to put a bunch in
to other people,
I would say probably not.
And so I don't think this works
as a Hugo Award
that isn't juried
because I don't think people
have the breadth of reading.
But I think to test this,
we would need to do a trial balloon
because it might be that I'm wrong.
I would like,
I would,
and to be clear,
I would very much like to be wrong.
I would very much like it
if Wasfus generally
was reading lots of works
in translation.
And I think that would be great.
But for much the same reason
that when the first time,
what was the year
they first run the game,
Hugo?
It was LA Con 4, right?
Yeah, 2006.
And it didn't go.
Yeah.
And so like in 2006,
the Hugo Award
was awarded for?
They didn't award one in 2006
for best game.
Or did they try it
and it didn't work?
They trialed it.
I'm pretty sure they trialed it
and there weren't enough nominations.
Okay.
And like I was,
as everyone who listens to this knows,
I was a big booster
of the best game Hugo.
I was part of the team
that wrote
the best game Hugo proposal,
a relatively minor part,
but I did help.
I voted enthusiastically for it
every time I could vote
and I have nominated for it.
I mean,
obviously I've mostly nominated
board games,
which have made it
nowhere near the ballot,
but I've nominated,
damn it.
And so I'm a big fan
of that,
Hugo.
But in 2006,
it wasn't ready
because we hadn't done
the work of the intervening
15 to 20 years
of building up
the Worldcon's awareness
of games.
And Era,
who did that work,
spent years on it,
years and years,
building up that literacy
in the community
and also games developed
in parallel,
which helped a lot.
And so I think this is
a really good idea,
but I think it's the sort
of thing where I would
imagine it might end up
an award,
I would say the earliest
this is going to end up
being an actual award
is 2035,
because I don't think
it's cooked yet.
And I might be wrong.
I'd love to be wrong.
But if I'm not wrong,
the next step is to build
the capacity to support
the award.
And that's going to take
a very long time
and be very,
very arduous.
But I think it's work
worth doing.
Yeah.
I think that's,
yeah,
there might be a slightly
pessimistic take.
It's a long term optimism.
What do we reckon?
I will just say that
having looked up the 2006 stats,
it was also a very different era
in terms of the number of people
who were nominating
for the Hugos,
because it is much smaller
than it is even now
after we've had a bit of a drop off
in the past few years.
And so that could also be one reason.
There just wasn't the population
of people there
who were nominating in the Hugos
who were playing enough games.
Oh, you weren't saying anything.
Okay.
I will also say that I do think
that when we talk about novels
in translation,
there's kind of almost
two different things
we are talking about sometimes
because looking at the debate
around Casella's post,
it was kind of about
the very sort of literary side
of translation,
that they're coming from
small literary presses
and the things that were mentioned
were books from
small literary presses.
But I think we're also overlooking
that there is like
huge readership
for some of the sort of
translated,
like recent Chinese
and Japanese novels.
And I'm pretty sure
like if you'd run this
in the past few years,
it would have been
like a lot of the
translated Chinese web novels,
like probably
Grandmaster of Demonic Cultivation
that everyone was reading
during COVID times.
So you might get
a very unexpected shortlist.
I don't think there's a way
you could change this.
If you have a juried award
for translated works,
I assume you're doing works
that have been translated
into English.
Hmm.
I think that's the way
you'd have to do it.
If someone reads the
Ukrainian translation
of Lord of the Rings,
which is a new translation,
and like,
what is that?
Does that count?
Probably not.
But like...
Well, also,
we had the new translation
of Beowulf
on the Hugo Ballot
in Best Related Work
a few years ago,
which won.
I mean, it was amazing.
It's a fantastic translation.
But that is a translation
from Old English
into English.
I wonder if Casella
included that
in his stats
about translations
reaching the finalists.
Yes.
Did he?
Excellent.
And yeah,
the proposal is
specifically for
translated English.
That makes sense.
I think that's the only way
you can do it.
Like, it just occurred
to me as a thing.
Yes.
I think...
I don't think we have
a fully educated
body of voters,
but then that's probably
true for some Hugos
we've already got.
So, you know.
Certainly Best Editor.
I still don't know
what editors do.
I do know they edit,
but I do still think
the best way to do it
would be to give
the editor on all
of the fiction awards
a Hugo as well
as the author
and recognise
the editors that way
because I think
it would be so much easier.
Yeah, anyway.
That's kind of why
I don't want to have
a Hugo for Best Translator.
Well, I mean,
that's...
We do have a lot of things
to say about translation
because that actually
reflects the fact
that science fiction
translation is a
specialised job
for something
which is already
a specialised job.
And there was...
There's been...
In regular translations,
there's definitely
examples where
a particular translator
from a language
has been so good
at rendering books
into English
that the novels
of that country
have become
much more prominent
for a while
because the translator
was doing
all the translations.
I don't think
we've had
a translator
of that quality
working in science fiction
ever.
And I think
it would be very interesting
if we got one.
Who are you thinking of
as the sort of
almost celebrity translators?
The two examples
are the people who...
The couple
whose names I forget
who translate
great Russian novels
and William Weaver
who translated
Umberto Eco
and Italo Calvino.
But there are more.
I think magical realism
was probably
significantly improved
by translation.
Do you not think
Ken Liu is an example?
I think he certainly is
in the science fiction
field.
He's probably the closest
that we have got
in the science fiction
field, yes.
The names that come to mind
are him and Anton Herr.
So if you want to end
on a quick plug,
Anton Herr's translation
of Bora Chung's
Red Sword
is a good book.
OK, readers,
you may know some examples
right in.
I mean listeners,
obviously.
You know.
But our listeners
are also readers.
Listening and reading
can be the same.
If you read an audiobook
you're listening.
We're nearly an audiobook.
Do you read an audiobook
or do you listen
to an audiobook?
I have heard people
say they read them.
I think that's
a response to the
audiobooks aren't real
book...
Listening to audiobooks
isn't real reading
brigade,
which I have no truck
with but that is
why people say
they are reading
their audiobooks.
Well it's also like
if someone says
what are you reading
now,
they don't...
They're not making
a value judgment
on the mode in which
the words are entering
your brain, right?
You'd think!
I think that's
the other thing.
We don't want to have
two words for
ingesting book.
This segues
very neatly
into a discussion
of if we think
that the Hugo Wars
do not currently
recognise
the sort of
beating heart
of the genre
and that there
are obvious holes.
Do we think
best translated work
is the biggest hole?
That is to say
I would argue
before the best game
Hugo,
games were the
biggest part
of the genre
that the Hugos
were ignoring.
Is it true
that the next
biggest hole
is translated work
or do we think
there are others?
For example,
audiobooks?
Well, I was
looking at
the proposal
for an audiobook
Hugo for which
there is not
a lot of support.
I'm interested
in audio formats
in general
because I think
they're underrepresented
in the Hugos
but again,
I take the point
that we have
quite a lot of
Hugos already.
At the time
the argument
was, well,
actually you've
got a real
overlap problem
with best novel
here and if
the thing that
you're awarding
is best audio
performance,
then actually
you've already
got space
in the dramatic
presentation categories
for the performance.
I mean,
there is an implicit
problem there,
isn't there,
that audio
performances
almost never,
if not never,
get nominated
in best dramatic.
Yes,
and so there
is an argument
that it would
be quite good
to have something
for best audio
and although
audiobooks were
one of the things
that triggered
the discussion
but I'm really
interested in the,
there's an awful
lot of audio
fiction out there.
some of it
is turning up
in editor
awards for
best short
form for
things that
are in fact
edited for
podcasts but
professional ones.
Fan casts have
a space in
fan casts but
a lot of these
things are not
fan casts but
you know,
there's a lot
of fiction being
produced in audio
form in our
genre that is
very interesting
and it's just
not being picked
up anywhere.
It's a great
example of,
you know,
there doesn't
have to be a
Hugo for
everything and
indeed there are
lots of gaps
where there isn't
a Hugo for
things.
I don't
listen to any
audiobooks or
really any
audio drama so
I have no
interest in
extra Hugos for
those things
specifically.
I think it's
going to be
tricky for
audiobooks like
you say because
you're specifically
rewarding the
audio recording
otherwise it would
be in best novel
or something.
So that also
runs into the
double Hugo
thing.
so in the show
notes listeners
we've also
written down
best music
and best
poem as
examples of
things that
have kind of
been discussed.
I think of
poetry, music,
audiobooks and
translated works
the one I'm
most likely to
read is
translated works
but given my
earlier comments
about how little
of my reading
is translation
I don't know
whether that
recommends it.
I don't know
but like if
this would act
to open people's
eyes to a great
world of SF
that is out there
that would be
cool.
So I'm not
inherently opposed
I'm just trying to
give my
just trying to
discuss it in a
good way.
Yeah I think the
issue is that
that argument is
there for basically
every small niche
that we don't
currently cover.
I mean I read
more novels in
translation actually
than I read
poems but that's
not necessarily
an I would say
we should have
translated work and
we shouldn't have
poems.
We have got
best related work
I think it would
be nice to have
something for best
fabulous thing of
the year that
doesn't fit into
any other category
and I'm sure that
there was some
award set that
has this.
I can't remember
which one it was
though.
Yeah there's one
award where it's
just the best
thing isn't it?
The Diana Jones
award is for the
best thing in
gaming.
I mean it's for
excellence in
gaming and so the
last winner was
the Union of
Workers at
Paizo.
The one before
that was the
Coyote and
Crow role
playing game.
The one before
that was an
activist called
Agit George and
the one before
that was a
publisher called
Nibcard.
So it has gone
to a publisher,
a person, a
game and a
union in the
last four years
and it is an
award for best
thing.
It's usually a
short list of
three to seven
nominees and then
it gets released
at Gen Con.
And usually it
attracts like
interesting commentary.
I think it is
quite a cool
award because I
think it's
interesting to look
out what it
has rewarded.
Maybe we
should have an
Octothorpe award
for best thing.
Only if we can
also have an
Octothorpe award
for best stuff.
Fine, we can
have two.
We can have
two.
Distinction
between things and
stuff will be
highly contested.
It's very clear to
me it will be in
the style guide.
shall we do
picks?
Yes.
I am going to
go first.
pick a book,
listeners.
Now you may have
noticed that since
the Clark Award
short list came out
I've been picking
lots of books and
this will continue.
I'm going to pick
A Letter to the
Luminous Deep by
Sylvie Control.
A very excellent
novel with a title
that I continually
get wrong.
It's a book
the title of
which confounds
me because I
keep wanting to
call it Letters
from the Luminous
Deep on account
of how the book
contains more than
one letter.
And I think this
is, you know,
annoying.
But the letters
in the book are
very good.
It's an epistolary
novel and I
bloody love an
epistolary novel
listeners.
And it is the
siblings of two
people who have
gone missing in
mysterious
circumstances and
they are trying to
piece together
their last
moments and
kind of get to
some closure.
And the novel is
letters between them
and then letters
they have found
from the two
missing persons
that have been
written to one
another.
And it's
secondary world
science fiction
in that it's
not in our
world but I
don't think it's
at all fantasy.
I think everything
is technology
even if it's
different technology
to our world.
So Abigail
Nussbaum in
Discord said that
she didn't think
it was cosy.
I do think it's
cosy in that
in that sense
of it feels
very intimate.
It feels like
you're reading
something very
private and
very intimate
and very loving
and it feels
like exactly the
sort of book I
might take to a
log cabin and
read by a fire.
And it's just
really beautiful.
I know that
España also
really enjoyed it
and I would
commend it to
listeners.
And I believe
my two learned
co-hosts have
already purchased
it.
so when we
complain about
things that are
called a
blank a novel
I was slightly
put off by this
novel because
its title on
Amazon is
A Letter to the
Luminous Deep
The Perfect
Cosy Magical
Academia Read.
I don't like this
in the same way
that I don't like
games that
say on their
front cover the
greatest card
game of all
time.
I don't know if
it's a perfect
cosy magical
academia read.
I don't mind
magical and
academia things but
I'm not fond of
cosy things as we
all know.
It may not be as
cosy as all that.
So what I am
going to say is
that if you go
on the website of
a proper bookshop
like Blackwell's
it doesn't say
this.
So I think the
problem here is
Amazon.
Might be.
Oh this is
this is I mean
just just picking
some books that I
have recently
looked at and
may were thinking
of purchasing on
Amazon.
The masterfully
woven and
breathtaking epic
adult fantasy of
cutthroat
competition and
imperial deceit.
The gripping
biopunk murder
mystery sequel to
The Tainted Cup.
It's all over the
place basically.
The sweeping
magical solo
debut by the
best-selling co-author
of This Is How
You Lose The Time
War.
Like if I did
think of having a
moratorium on ever
purchasing any of
these books that
have these subtitles
but I can't because
I cut myself off from
basically all books.
1984 the new
edition of the
20th century's
dystopian masterpiece.
Even the old ones
aren't immune.
At the same time I
was about to say but
John broke in.
The Lord of the
Rings the classic
fantasy masterpiece.
Yep.
So yes it's
Amazon.
Sorry publishers it
wasn't you after
all.
Well it's because
Amazon's always been
terrible at search
metadata and so
people have started
doing yes due to
technical limitations
like the one thing
with online shopping
is we've still not
gotten great at
serendipitous discovery
online and that is
what they're trying to
drive.
Desperately trying to
drive it with any
tools they're allowed
to have.
Bless them.
I've started to pay
a lot of attention
to what my
friends like.
Yeah.
So my pals
recommend things and
I put them on
lists and when
enough pals have
recommended things or
they've recommended
them enthusiastically
enough I go yeah
I'll have a go at
that.
I put a lot of
things on I get a
lot of things out of
the library because
because pals
recommend them.
Some of them I
even get around to
reading but not this
one.
But yeah no it
is it is academia.
So it's tricky
because I think
Sylvie could throw
on her website or
maybe in the yes
on her website she
describes herself as
a romantic fantasy
author but I would
have said that the
book that she has
written like so she
has written two
books both of which
are in this series.
I would say they
are not fantasy
because they do not
have magic in.
They have technology
in a different world
to ours.
And so it is
interesting because
there is clearly
like a blurring of
genres happening
there where
secondary world
science fiction is
sufficiently rare
nowadays that it's
being it's being
lumped into fantasy.
And that's
interesting to me.
I mean you know
Anne McCaffrey was
always sold as
fantasy right but
it's clearly science
fiction.
But also wasn't the
first one quite
fantasy and then it
was retrofitted
later.
I don't know even
I'm not old enough
to remember that.
They're all very
but I mean they all
feel very much like
fantasy until they
properly retrofit it.
I don't think it's
unreasonable to say
this book which is
full of dragons in a
sort of oldie worldie
fantasy setting but
is secretly science
fiction is probably
going to appeal to
readers of fantasy.
So she says she's a
romantic fantasy author.
Does that mean it's
got smut in it?
No.
Oh boo.
Quite like a bit of
smut.
I mean it's got some
pretty breathless
descriptions of
libraries.
so my pick despite the
fact that I haven't
actually seen it yet
is Sci-Fi London
2025 which is taking
place from the 19th to
22nd of June 2025
which is I think
today as you read
this at the Picture
House in Finnsbury
Park.
Amazing science fiction
and socialising.
The Picture House at
Finnsbury Park fun fact
was our closest decent
cinema for quite a long
time until our new one
opened.
So I am very excited
about this and I
haven't yet decided
exactly what we are
going to do and what
I mean is I have to
I have to negotiate
with my husband but I
have never actually got
to Sci-Fi London
though I did watch the
short films when they
were available online a
few years ago in the
pandemic.
So this is this is kind
of a thing for me.
So hopefully I'll see a
few of you there.
I know that there are
other Sci-Fi London
fans who listen to the
podcast.
The no so they did
Sci-Fi London did
online shorts last
year as well but they
it has been on and
off I would say.
So I did it last year
but it looks like this
year they're not doing
it.
I would be interested
to know what is
driving that like
whether it's just very
technically difficult
whether they keep
trying but some years
it doesn't come
together or whether
you know I don't
know whether they're
just kind of finding
that there's not the
demand.
I don't know.
It is I would like to
get down there one
day.
I don't think it
will be this year.
What are you doing
next weekend John?
We can pick you up.
The one thing I will
say is and I missed
it this year which I'm
annoyed by is that the
Sunderland Short Film
Festival when we were
watching the Sci-Fi
London track a number
of the films we'd
already seen at the
Sunderland Festival so
what I might just
start doing is paying
a lot more attention
to the Sunderland one
because they had a
sci-fi track and you
know it's not as
full featured but you
do get some there
was some good science
fiction in that too
there's just not that
many there's not that
many science fiction
films out there right?
Well it's clearly sort
of 25 to 30 and that
is more than than
Sunderland showed but
but yes I mean
presumably it is a
limited number and
that's one of the
reasons why that I
mean we didn't even
mention short film
when we were
discussing extra Hugo
categories right?
So yeah there's 10
feature films and a lot
of shorts so I mean
basically I need to see
if Stephen wants to do
this because I guess I'm
suspecting the answer is
going to be no.
You could always go on
your own but yes.
And I might.
It's not impossible.
Have you ever been to
Sci-Fi London Liz?
Yeah.
Was it good?
Yes.
Day!
You heard it here first
listeners.
I mean I haven't been
probably since 2014 maybe?
No there's a name I
haven't heard in a long
time.
It was great.
A man used to shoot
underpants into the
audience of a t-shirt
canon.
That does sound
great.
Okay well I will look
out for that.
If you get any
underpants from a t-shirt
canon Alison can I have
them?
Yes.
Day!
Great.
Okay.
And the reason I'm
picking something that
I haven't actually done
is because I've spent
all of my spare time
for the last ever since
we last recorded playing
through Blueprints
which was Liz's pick a
little while ago and
no don't start don't
start don't don't even
go there because you
know it's your life you
only have one life do
you want to spend it
all on this game?
When you get to room
46 which is the
ostensible objective
when you buy this while
you buy the game you
realize that that is
really just the
tutorial.
Intriguing.
Sorry Alison.
I picked up again but
now I've stopped because
I got annoyed with the
puzzles so yeah.
I mean I've
practically filled a
notebook so I
started with a
notebook but I think
really what you want
is one of those
leather-bound jobbies
where you write in it
with a lovely fountain
pen.
if you've been
keeping a beautiful
notebook then
Blueprints would be a
great reason to start
using it but I have
filled a very large
notebook pretty well
with notes and I'm
getting through it.
I'm still making quite
that sort of thing
yeah.
Have you reached room
46?
Oh yeah yeah yeah
long I was explaining
that you reached room
46 and you suddenly
discover you have now
finished the tutorial.
How many sanctum keys
have you done?
All of them?
Four but I think we
probably shouldn't be
talking about that
on the podcast.
That's fine okay you
can bring it I don't
think that's really a
spoiler if we've already
said look there is more
stuff after you get to
what you think is going
to be the nominal end
of the game and that is
naming one thing you
could do out of like
77.
There's a lot more
stuff.
I have a list of about
35 things I'm trying to
progress and then like
yesterday I happened to
look with the magnifying
gloss it's something I'd
seen on like my second
run through and
discovered there was a
useful message in it
that I did not
previously know and I'm
like what?
What did you look at?
Was it the note that
tells you how to pay
billions?
Oh the thing in the
security things.
Oh yeah yeah yeah
okay.
My pick is a book and
it is a book published
in 2015 because despite
all the Hugo nominated
stuff I should be
reading I've apparently
gone back to reading
all the things.
It is Wilding Hall by
Elizabeth Hand which is
I think it's a novel not
a novella but it's quite a
short novel and it's in
this incredibly atmospheric
novel about basically
members of a British folk
rock band in the 1970s who
go to record an album at a
very remote country house
and it's but it's told in
that way of kind of an oral
history so it's all the band
members and associated
hangers-on later on telling
the story of what was
happening that summer when
they record an album and
things happened under
mysterious circumstances
and it's all kind of tied
in with like folk music
and British folklore and
how much of kind of folk
songs are about historical
folklore and tales of
different folk legends.
It's just really well done.
I mean I am a sucker for
this kind of like oral
history stuff.
I really liked reading like
Daisy Jones and the Six
which is basically Fleetwood
Mack in a fictional way and
this is another thing from
kind of the same era but I
like the kind of distance you
get with everyone telling
the story they remember and
saying oh no no this thing
that this person is sure
happened we never saw that
happen and and all this kind
of stuff.
I mean I guess one thing is
it doesn't really tell you
what's going on at the end
but it's kind of such an
atmospheric feeling of what's
going on of this kind of
like glorious summer young
people just on the verge of
like massive creative success
and what they do that summer
and how much of this comes from
the atmosphere they were doing
in all stuck in this country
house together.
It works really well.
Anyway I enjoyed it.
It sounds good.
I have not read it.
I've been told about this
book before and went I must
read that.
For some reason I have not in
fact read that but obviously
it is very much in my
wheelhouse.
I am very interested in
English folk and the way that
it uses traditional music and
also doesn't use traditional
music.
So some of the most famous
bits of pieces of English
folk music or modern English
folk music have no connection
to the tradition whatsoever
and other things keep popping
up and then there are some
some ballads that have been
massively reworked multiple
times and others that nobody
ever sings for often for very
good reason and and all the
stuff about what was collected
and what was not collected which
we're sort of beginning to
remedy now.
Fascinating stuff.
I want to read this book
novel anyway.
Yay!
Yes I think it's absolutely up
your alley and unlike
Blue Prince it will take you an
afternoon.
Oh I could just borrow it.
I could just borrow it.
Look.
That was the Octothorpe
Podcast and it's goodbye from
me.
It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
I really need to write a style
guide.
Do you need to write a style
guide because I just keep
dumping stuff into the show notes
in a random way then you have to
reformat it.
Oh no that's not it because I
don't think having a style guide
would help with that so much.
No.
It's that I have to go to look at
last episode's show notes to work
out how I do the show notes and
that is suboptimal.
I was just going to say you still
have to go and open the style guide
and look at it or you could just
look at last episode show notes.
Yeah.
Hmm.
Style guides are better.
Let's not have a discussion on
style guides shall we?
The theme music for this episode was
Fanfare for Space by Kevin
McLeod and Competech.com used under
a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.