I just bashed my microphone with my cup of coffee.
Hello everyone and welcome to a very special episode of Octa Thorpe.
So it's a very special episode of Octa Thorpe on which we are going to play if I ran the
con, the smoth con 3 game.
So back story to this, in the mid 80s at smoth con 3, the idea came up to have a game which
would simulate con running and so they wrote a little con running simulation game which
I think has been played at quite a few smoth cons since then and certainly I played it at
some point in the run up to the London Worldcon.
I think Alison's played it as well but since either of us have played it, it's been through
multiple editions but in 2015 when Sasquan had a guest of honour, Lesi Cherich who helped
out in a row at least some of the original game, I think the first edition, basically
they then expanded and updated fourth edition which I think is so only needed because certainly
the version I played which was basically the first edition having gone through some corrections
and so on, hadn't really been updated to take into account things like the internet.
What kind of databases desktop publishing?
Yeah, it felt very dated and it felt very, I thought it felt very American, I think actually
it's not that it's very American, maybe it's just that it's very Worldcon and Worldcons
were and still are quite American, you know, that's dropping but I mean at the time when
I, we did the London Worldcon, you know, you're having maybe two every ten years that were
not in the USA.
So, so it's basically a game about playing, running a convention.
I am going to be the secret master of fandom.
We've known this for a while.
John and Alison are going to be my committee.
In theory you have multiple committees but we're going to play it through with one and
see how many points they get and then you listeners can play at home and see if you
can get more points than John and Alison in running a convention.
We should tell people that this is available to buy and they can go and buy it at a link
that will be in the show note and you can buy a paper coffee or you can do what we all
did which was to buy the PDF which is I think five dollars, it's not very much.
Yeah, it's very reasonable.
It's very nice and yeah, it comes with everything you need to play it, all the instructions,
everything and you can even print out cards to select the scenarios if you like.
So in theory we have two or more teams.
I did play it I think in, must be 2011 or 2012 with quite a lot of different teams.
I can't remember that we scored very highly.
I think we got very, we scored very well for giving everyone beer I think and running lots
of parties.
Hey!
Yes, the idea is that the committees play and each committee will alternate someone being
the chair.
So you're going to make decisions as a committee but the chair has final say if you disagree.
We never disagree.
Oh no.
We have three phases, the bidding phase, the planning phase and the at-com phase and in
each of those phases we have a set of scenarios.
You will select a scenario and I will start by reading you the kind of setup in that scenario.
You will make decisions for yourself.
Sometimes the decisions will be randomized by D6 and then we'll keep moving through that
scenario where you know the decisions you make early on will have consequences.
And in fact some of the decisions you make in scenarios in the bidding and planning phase
will have at-com consequences.
So what will happen is we will do each scenario and at the start of each phase you will get
a set of resources and these resources are people points, financial points and goodwill
points.
And usually to take an action it may require people points or financial points.
If you have them, if you do not have people or financial points and the action you would
like to take requires them you can't take that action.
And what you're aiming to get is mainly goodwill points.
You really want goodwill points not to have negative financial points but also you will
lose points if you have too much money because you actually don't want your convention to
make too much money you want to spend it all.
And really you want your people points to be positive because that means you had lots
of helpers and they all had fun.
Yeah.
In reality there would be someone keeping score.
In fact I'm going to be the secret master of fandom who also keeps score.
Let's see how we get on.
So I think we start with a bidding phase scenario.
There are and we're going to probably do at least one bidding phase scenario maybe one
or two planning phase scenarios and hopefully one or two at con phase scenarios depending
on how long it takes.
There isn't an official time limit but basically if I think you guys are taking too long to
make a decision I'm going to start singing the countdown tune.
Hey.
I think this will instill the appropriate sense of urgency in you.
This is very much an experiment.
Listeners we have not tried this before.
I as I said have played this game once and we didn't do a very good job of it and this
is a new edition that none of us have played.
So let's see how far we get and I will tell you who wrote each scenario is also has credit
authors so I'll tell you who wrote each scenario as we get to it.
The bidding phase I think we're probably going to play one scenario out of 12.
Would you like to give me a randomly chosen number between one and twelve?
Hey Siri give me a randomly chosen number between one and twelve.
A random number between one and twelve is eight.
Eight.
I heard that.
We are doing scenario starting at number 3401 pre-supporting memberships.
We are doing pre-supporting memberships in our notes.
Pre-supporting memberships.
Because this is a well-con.
I mean I would say that this is we are never running a well-con.
So do we need to find three so oh yeah.
No no no you should not find 3401 because it will tell you what's going to happen.
Okay fine.
You're just going to tell us everything we need to know.
Yes.
It's not like a smoth.
What do you do about pre-supporting memberships?
You can choose not to have them.
Charge $10, charge $20 or charge $40.
Erm.
I assume you're a modern world-con here and so it's like more than world-con prices.
Or rather 2015 anyway.
Yeah we're going to charge $20.
$20?
Yeah $20 seems good.
$40 seems too much and $10 seems too little so.
Can't we have like a couple of friends tears and like supporters tears and things as well?
Just $20.
No you can only.
I think what Alison is asking is can we make running the world-con slightly more complicated
please.
In return for a load of startup care.
Er no.
No okay right $20 we're going with $20.
Alright we are charging $20.
So $20.
I'm just going to by the way this is a society I'm noting down kind of the route we take
through this scenario.
We are charging $20 so I go to that one.
You gain income and committed supporters.
We're charging three financial points and one goodwill point.
Okay so we are on six and three now right?
Because you said three and one.
No gain three financial points and one goodwill point John.
Oh so we're on five financial.
But you're keeping a spreadsheet in the show notes so we don't need to individually do
this because Liz is doing it for us.
Well I'll do it or John can do it.
I could do the points I'm happy.
It'll keep me focused.
I also realise that the art for this episode is going to be the branding for the convention
which we can't call Octicon.
Puctuation the world con.
Alright so well done we have gained some finance and goodwill.
Sorry you have gained some finance and goodwill.
I obviously am neutral and do not care whether you do well or badly.
So keeping track.
You'll care where we're running the world con Liz.
Keeping track of the pre-supportors cost you effort.
Lose one people point.
Are you going to give your pre-supportors a discount on the convention rates?
No.
Oh yes.
They should have bought a friend membership shouldn't they?
That we haven't sold them.
Yeah no we are because otherwise we're going to lose a ton of goodwill.
True.
Fair enough.
Yeah probably.
Is it just this is just a yes or no at the moment.
Yes you can say yes or you can say no.
We're going to go with yes because it could be quite a small discount.
Let's go yes and hope that we get the option for it to be a small discount.
Remember when you decided to give your pre-supportors a discount on the convention rates lose three
finance points.
Oh what do we do that immediately or you remember it?
We do that immediately.
Oh man.
Well you gained three and now you've lost three.
Okay now roll a dice and give me the number between one and six please.
I've rolled a two goblin.
Everything works smoothly.
Gain one goodwill point.
Hey.
And that is the end of the scenario.
Have we time to do one more bidding one because that was pretty simple.
I think we can do another bidding scenario because that was pretty short yeah and not
the most interesting.
We are going to do a scenario called Kill the Wabbit which is by Priscilla Olsen, John
Pomeran, Sergio Turic and Mark Olsen.
A newspaper article captures your attention.
A rabbit breeders convention has just decided to hold its national convention aka Bunnycon
in your locale.
You happen to notice that the prospective convention date overlaps your own.
Will the bunny birthers be a bitch?
Sure enough your hotel rep calls you to tell you that the bunny birthers are very interested
in using them as their major convention facility.
In fact they have made an excellent upfront money offer of 20k to reserve space and the
hotel wants you to match it within the week.
If not they will give the hotel to the bunnies.
Or in shock you thought you had an agreement but then your stun mind begins to function.
Do you agree to match the payment?
In which case you will lose two financial points or ask the hotel for a meeting to discuss
this.
Oh god.
Well we think we've got a contract so like can we do you think the best plan is to try
and get them to discuss it and then try and get them to stick to the original contract?
Yeah let's have a meeting to discuss it.
Let's have a meeting.
A bit worried about this.
Alison has a worried face now.
I say now.
Yeah because the meeting could go in a number of difficult ways.
Anyway let's have the meeting.
Alright roll to see the next answer.
I get a 3.
That doesn't seem good.
Nope that's fine.
Sure they are willing to talk to you.
If you're older one or two they just wouldn't talk to you and say no we want 20,000 so yeah.
Jesus.
When you meet with the hotel you make a strong pitch that your convention will be much better
for the hotels and the bunnies.
Just think of the cleaning bill.
Roll to find out the hotel's answer.
Five that doesn't sound good.
Sorry the hotel likes you but it's a business decision.
They want the money.
No.
So the hotel is holding firm and requiring a 20k payment to hold the space.
Do you?
Fold up the bid.
Brackets.
This will have dire consequences.
Find a new site.
Pay up if you have at least two financial points and you would lose those two financial
points which you do but that would leave you with not much money.
Decide not-
But it's the end of the bidding stage.
We're not going to do another scenario after this right?
It's not.
We're not going to do another scenario.
We're going to move on to the convention phase.
You could decide not to pay and see how it goes or look around for alternative facilities.
The thing is that going into the convention phase with no financial points also seems
like a bad thing.
We're going to get some new ones.
Do they?
I assume they.
I assume anything that we have carries over though so um equally.
Yeah I assume you get extra so you'll get another two but also you also get extras for
kind of- you basically will get the set amount it gives you in the beginning of the thing
which is you'll get another two financial points for planning on one for Atcom.
But then if you have- oh it's just three down here is that wrong?
Oh sorry I was doing the wrong thing.
No it's three I'm reading one for three committees and then basically if you have lots of goodwill
you'll get more people and more money at different points.
Probably changing the site this late is going to lose us goodwill.
And money.
It could easily cost more than 20k to switch sites.
Yeah we probably just need to-
I think we are just going to suck it up at this point probably.
Yeah.
As we can.
So you're going to suck up and pay up and lose two financial points?
Yeah fucking rabbit.
Of course the news gets out to the finish room and Mill that you're having hotel problems.
It doesn't matter that everything settled now.
People here that your hotel didn't trust you and held you up for a big payment.
Lose two goodwill points.
Hey he he he.
Oh no.
So you lost two financial points and then you lose two goodwill points anyway.
Oh I know why we've given it.
I know why I've given up con running.
Yeah you pay up and you're screwed anyway.
That's hard.
I don't know what you do with that.
Yeah.
This is what con running is like with sites.
That's why you run virtual cons.
That's probably a better path through.
I mean there are better paths through which is you know you can if you try and find a
new site sometimes it goes very badly and sometimes it goes better.
If you keep going sometimes the the bunnies decide to go somewhere else and then you
can switch back to your hotel unless you burned all your goodwill with the hotel and
then you know if you've already got a new hotel do you go back to that hotel?
It all just gets very tricky.
There is there is a good path through it but again there's a lot of luck involved.
So this was the bidding phase.
You almost had your hotel swipe from under you and you did pre-supporting memberships
but then gave them all the discount on the actual con.
And so you've got some goodwill but not much finance.
We're now entering the planning phase.
So do our people and goodwill add to the numbers that are there?
I'm pretty sure you get now basically the next line added up.
So it's seven people, three finance and four goodwill.
Yep and then you get an extra people point for every three goodwill points you have at
the time rounding up so I think you get another two people points.
Excellent.
That should make up for not having any money.
Yeah.
So you've got nine people points and not much money.
Yay.
We just have to basically throw people at the problems rather than money in the next session.
Sorry for the million.
So we're going to enter the planning phase and in the planning phase there are 26 possible
scenarios.
We are going to do scenario 22, 01, the relationship.
And relationship is in quotes.
Their relationship.
All right.
Oh no.
The head of the art show is pushing for a policy which would charge a percentage commission
instead of a fixed panel fee.
This is very unpopular with the rest of the committee.
In spite of this opposition at the division head of exhibits inexplicably insists upon
supporting the unpopular policy proposed by his area head to the extent there is repeated
heated debate on the subject.
Do you tell the division head that committee consensus must be followed?
Do nothing now and hope that things settle down a few weeks or support the division head
and allow the policy to be instituted.
Percentage policy, right?
That's what we're doing Britain.
I don't know what we're doing Britain.
Art shows 10%.
Let's go with that one.
All right.
What could possibly go wrong?
Yeah.
What do you think, John?
I think that's fine.
I can't see it being.
I really think this is just been blown out of proportion and we should just like simmer
down.
But also how do UK World cons do this?
Do they go with a panel fee or a percentage fee?
Because British conventions are always percentage fees.
Yeah.
That's interesting.
I don't know.
I had no idea.
This is something I didn't know about.
I didn't know about this either.
I'm now looking up World con Art Show applications for 2024.
I can't see what's going on.
We're going to go with percentage on the ground so that's how it's done in Britain
and I'm sure the art show head is right and it's got nothing to do with some secret relationship
they're having with the exhibits head.
Anyway, so we're going to support the division head and allow this policy to be instituted.
Please, is that okay, John?
Yeah.
I think that makes sense to me.
Alright.
Roll to find out how the committee reacts.
Okay.
D six is another three.
A rumour surface is that division head and his art show area head have been enjoying a
clandestine relationship.
The shit hits the fan.
Brackets the division head.
The rest of the committee becomes convinced that the exhibits division head is merely the
puppet of the art show head.
The exhibits division head loses most of his effectiveness and credibility.
It's one people point.
Oh no.
Oh, we've got loads of those though, so that's fine.
Do you?
Yup.
Fire both the exhibits division head and the art show head, in which case you will lose
a further people point.
Fire the art show head, do nothing or talk to both individuals and ask them to cool things
down until after the problem has blown over.
Oh, I don't know.
What do you think?
I think I probably want to fire someone because like it's not.
I feel like if it's not a problem that they're dating with, they're not telling everyone
that they're like dating and it's affecting the convention, that's going to be a problem
down the road.
What do you think, Galasan?
Sometimes you move one of them, but if you've got a division head who's not performing,
moving them to another division probably isn't the solution and that's not really one of
the options we're given is to move one and not the other so they're no longer in a line
of control.
Yeah.
We're not giving the option to fire the exhibits division head only and keep the art show head.
Oh, so we can either fire the art show head or both.
Yes, which I think is a bit of an error.
You should be able to fire the division head.
Because you should never fire the junior, should you?
You should always.
Yeah.
I'm just thinking back to like real life World Cons.
I know I've been on conventions where there's been a, you know, no couples on the committee
policy, but not a no couples on the in the division policy, which is trickier.
No, well, like the problem is like I said, I've been the problem is that there's a couple
of the problem is that it's like a couple that are not being forthcoming with the fact
that that's affecting if the, if the exhibits division head is going back for someone and
not disclosing that there's like a conflict of interest there.
That is when it starts getting into like trust issues with that division head.
Yeah.
Because you don't know whether they're doing the right thing or whether they're just going
to do things for reasons you can't see.
So if it's a choice between if we can't move that person, if we can't move the division
head and we can't fire just the division head, I guess I favor firing both.
But I was going to say I'm coming around to the idea that we just far both of them because
we have a ton of people points.
Actually they're a problem and it's possible that they can come back later, but we've
already said we've already lost the credibility of the division head already.
So I feel like we might as well just far them both.
But with an asterisk that that might not be my choice to try to help being given better
options.
We're dissatisfied with the options given to us in this role playing scenario game.
Yeah.
Always, always true in all games of this kind and indeed real life.
Well, to be honest, I think that so if we choose that one, you lose one people point
and I think the response is possibly what would have happened if you just fired the
exhibits division head anyway, which is rumours spread about committee instability.
Lose one goodwill point.
No.
Yeah.
I think that's not a bad outcome.
Even the amount of stuff that could happen.
Okay, we're going to have another planning phase.
We are going to have another planning phase scenario.
Oh no.
For our second planning scenario, we are playing the BNF by Priscilla Olsen, Fred I6 and Lizzie
Turret.
Hey.
A big name fan, BNF in your area, recently turned pro, wants to run the Hugo Awards ceremony
right.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
He is known to be a loud mouth, rubs people the wrong way.
So far he's given out lots of advice but never attended a work session or taken on even
minor responsibility.
You have reeled out about his competence.
On the other hand, he's a major figure in local fandom and is assuming that he has his
pick of jobs for the cop.
Do you?
No.
Explain that this job must go to someone with more experience.
Wait and see whether he starts showing more interest in the con as a whole.
Bouch the inevitable and offer him the job, plan to keep a close eye on him or ask him
what he has in mind.
Erm, it's got to be either, I feel like it for me, it's wait and see you'll ask him.
It's definitely not.
Ask him seems too nice.
Wishing and seeing.
Oh, waiting and seeing is just hiding for disaster.
I would ask in a kind of, oh, we hear you're interested in this.
Can you send us a position paper by datex saying what your plans are?
And then when that doesn't come, you can give the job somebody else, which is kind of
what asking what his plans are.
Erm, so that's the last option, right?
Yeah, okay, let's do that.
I'm up for that.
Alright, so you ask him what he has in mind.
Please roll.
Six.
That's six.
He has reasonably good ideas, but there's one hitch.
He really wants to invite his colleague and good friend, Dick Heller, to be the Hugo
ceremony MC.
This gentleman has never been seen going on stage sober and is known to be even more
obnoxious drunk than he is sober.
Now what?
Pass.
Agree and accept both your BNF and Heller.
Turn down this dynamic duo or try to get the BNF to select someone else.
Erm, the third option.
I'd go ssssssssss, yes see.
Try and get this BNF to select someone else.
Okay, please roll.
Okay...
FIVE!
The BNF won't give up the plan to use Heller.
What's worse, he already told Heller that he's on the consideration for the job and has invited Heller to participate.
Now what?
We're all quinching 'cause this sounds painfully familiar, doesn't it?
Yup!
(laughs)
Two options- okay.
You grit your teeth and tell him that he had no authority to make such an appointment,
and insist to explain to Heller that it's all a mistake.
Now there's no way you will appoint him to the position.
Or you figure that now your stock will try to make the best of it.
Maybe you can get him to invite a better speaker to serve as the MP,
MC, and relegate Heller just to the actual UQG award presentations.
No, it's gonna be the first of those.
'Cause otherwise we know what's gonna happen because we've sat there while it happened.
Yeah, I'm just- I'm- I'm um...
So this came out in 2015, which was before
like a lot of the code of conduct revolutions we've had in the scene.
And yeah, no, not a chance in hell I'm gonna let an obnoxious drunk guy
be involved on stage at the UQGos.
Uh, so that's a hard pass.
Alright, so explain he had no authority to make that appointment,
and you will no way have him in the position.
He's got a big fan base, oh god!
(laughs)
And- and then I hide under the table because it's very awkward and I don't like it.
Heller is offended.
Lose one goodwill point.
(gasps)
Well, just straight off, blind me.
And we're not finished yet,
'cause that was- it leads to a further section.
You now have to find someone else to run the UQG awards ceremony.
Lose two people points.
Okay, that's fine.
Got people for days, mate.
Hmm, not the way we're going.
What is worse, you now have a well-known fan in touch with your committee
who is not on your side.
Every time there is a glimmer of a problem within the committee,
he's on his phone to his favourite news-in-editor,
telling all.
Lose one goodwill point.
Oof.
Yeah, no, the mightglies special.
(laughs)
That's quite a good one.
There's a lot- there's a lot of different ways this could go.
But if we had him,
that'd be like little time bomb waiting for the convention.
Yup.
So, uh, do you want to do one more planning phase one?
Yeah, okay.
Some of them have to be good, right?
No.
(snorts)
I wonder if you might have had a-
(laughs)
a good thing.
Again, this does feel very realistic.
It does, actually.
I think it always did feel quite realistic,
and that's a good way.
In a kind of-
everyone should play this game a couple of times before deciding to run a world card.
All right, let's play scenario we're in the money,
which was definitely written in 2015.
This is written by Glenn Glazer and Lazy Chiric,
and I think Glenn Glazer was the chair or involved in Sasquam.
A political group has started paying serious attention to a voted award you give,
the prestigious Cithers Award.
They've rallied their followers,
and in response, people of opposite politics rallied their followers in opposition.
Besides headaches for your election administrators and social media teams,
this situation has also buried registration under an unprecedented deluge of what you call
voting memberships.
These entitle the member to vote, but not to attend the con,
and unless they specifically ask otherwise,
they receive electronic publications and not print ones.
This in turn means an unprecedented amount of money to budget with.
So you're in the money.
Gain six financial points from all of these unexpected memberships.
Woohoo!
Wait, nothing can go wrong.
I wasn't paying attention in 2015, guys.
It's not the worst problem to have.
Sugarplums dancing the dreams of your division heads
as your finance team wants about overspending even the surplus you have.
Oh, that is the worst problem to have.
Do you?
You've got four options here.
Go conservative by keeping to the original budget
and just enhancing a few line items.
Do the traditional thing cons do with last-minute income
spend it on food and beverage?
Allow exhibits to rent the entire prop and wardrobe set
from the popular TV show Game of Privy's as they want to.
Or do you allow events to stage a live concert
featuring S.F. author Peter Peacock and his heavy metal band Pigeon Wind.
I went to the last of these in 1987 when that was how old were you then, John?
Minus one.
But I went to see Peter Peacock, Peter Peacock and his heavy metal band Pigeon Wind.
Though in fact, it's Pigeon Lords when Peter Peacock plays with them.
I mean of those I'd probably go for option B, but...
Yeah, as I'd like option B please.
Yeah.
I mean you know what we're like guys, right?
Alright, so we're spending it on food and beverage.
That's right.
Though I mean having said that I did run an easter con
where the entire purpose of running the easter con was to bring a band I like to play.
So the facilities people provide menus and their
dreams of lobster and caviar in the staff den.
You figure you can spend about half your windfall on food.
Do you?
Do you want to do?
Modously increase food and drink items across the board.
Put it into the con suite or ramp up private events like staff den
and the scissors award ceremony pre-reception.
And you're going to do one in this case.
Across the board, I would.
What would you do, Alison?
I think I'm going to do it across the board.
Yeah.
Alright, please remember modest food.
But modest increased food.
Yeah, yes modest increased food.
But please remember you did that because it will come back at con.
Oh no, modest food.
Just this could be more.
There was something else we had to remember on a food on it.
So, you know.
I don't think we have to because we...
And have we spent our three finance points?
Or is that something that's coming back at the con?
Which finance points?
It said you could spend half your windfall.
Oh no, you haven't, you haven't spent that yet.
Alright, so do you want to spend more of your windfall money?
Choose one you haven't chosen before.
And your two options are basically renting all the props and
wardrobe from Game of Privy's or having the live concert.
I'm going to guess that either of those can increase goodwill,
but they could also go wrong.
I mean, if I was doing it in real life,
I'd probably go for the Game of Privy stuff on the basis
that we might attract some people to the convention
who wouldn't normally come and we might grow the community a bit.
And I think the gig won't really move the needle on much,
but I might be wrong.
I mean, I think the Hawk Wind gig really,
you know, it was something that people talked about
four years afterwards.
It wasn't, you know, it did kind of do its job,
but I'm not sure how many people it brought into the convention,
whereas having a lot of stuff from Game of Privy's.
I remember at 2014 when the committee,
the board were kind of like,
"Oh, I don't know if we want to get the throne because,
because everyone's seen it before a lot of times."
The Privy, I mean, ever...
And I'm not sure about having a big Privy in the middle of the van village,
you know, but in fact, the giant Privy was extremely popular
with lots of fans, including lots of kind of,
actually, smuffy fans.
It wasn't just that the random members of the convention,
it was everybody.
So I'm going to get the props and costumes from the Game of Privy's.
That sounds good.
But not more than three finance points worth of them.
I am not sure we're going to get to pick, but yeah, I agree with that.
Let's have a giant Privy in the van village.
That sounds good.
People could queue up to use it.
Right, so we spent modestly on food,
which by the way, we have not spent yet, but we'll spend that calm.
And then you're going to let exhibits rent all the proper wardrobe sets from Game of Privy's.
Yep.
Now I'm a spin back to the Game of Privy's bit.
Everyone in exhibits is super excited and gets to work immediately.
Roll.
Five.
The studio is cautiously interested.
They name a prize for the rental and shipping of the artifacts of the show.
It's a big number representing most of your windfall income.
Do you say yes and sign the contract, in which case you lose four financial
points or get cold feet and consider other options instead?
Four financial points seems like that seems good to me.
Yeah, let's go with the four financial points.
You've got loads of money.
What could go wrong?
Why not?
All right, roll.
So we've lost four financials.
So we're down to five financial points.
And I'm rolling a four.
A four.
All right, things go smoothly.
Hey, please remember, Privy's props.
Okay, the art for this episode is now going to be a job Privy in the fan village.
Can you paint me and John on the Privy in the manner of, I think, what is still my
Facebook profile photo where I think John is sitting on me on the Privy?
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
[laughs]
It might have to be all three of us on the job Privy though, I think.
That is fair.
That's all right, you could have one of you poking around there.
We'll find a way to do it.
But we're not finished with Game of Privy yet.
Someone at the studio is a fan.
They love your card and want to help.
Not only can you get the props, you can get most of the cast as well.
There will be a slight extra cost though.
You can either, we've struck entertainment gold,
lose one financial point and say yes or politely decline.
Yeah, no, we're going to shake it.
Yeah.
We are going to be overrun with 10,000 Game of Privy's fans, but we'll cope.
It's all right because they will offset the sad puppies in the scissors voting or whatever
the award's called.
They will and also, I have been to parties run by the Game of Privy's fan club and they are awesome.
All right, we say yes to the cast, Liz.
To them, please also remember as well as Privy's props.
Remember, Privy's cast.
Did we have to take a point off for...
You have to take a point off, yeah.
So we're actually down to four.
And now you have another choice if you want.
Do you want to have your live concert?
Right, no, we are not going to have the live concert.
This was a hopefully, hopefully Peter Peepcock won't get too upset with us.
I absolutely love, by the way, that Michael Moorcock's Facebook told him he couldn't call
himself Jerry Cornelius.
So he changed his dayboard Facebook to Buggyly Otherly, which is another Moorcock character.
It's quite good.
I'm just checking, I'm playing this correctly because obviously there will be a sort of point
where we come back.
So you now have basically a suspended @com scenario, which I can resume at any point in the @com phase.
Okay.
You're going to resume it at the most inconvenient point, aren't you?
Well, Murphy is allowed to resume it, which I think means I am allowed to resume it at the most
inconvenient point.
And I may have some information about how much money you've spent.
Anyway...
Shall we move on to the convention?
I think we should.
Yes.
So we're going to add the five and the four and the one to our @com.
So you're at @com money and also there is a special note, which is for every three good
will points, you add one financial point.
We do not have... does it round up or down Liz?
It rounds up.
Oh, so we get one financial point.
Nice.
So you're low on goodwill, but you're quite high on people and money, so that's good.
We can throw some cash at this one.
Let's try this one, which I think will be quite short and funny.
We're going to play The Lady and the Snake by Mark Alton and Lesi Turic.
I think that's quite an old one.
That's one from the original one.
Do you remember the scenario or do you just remember the actual situation?
No, no, no, not enough.
Okay.
The lady in the snake, a lady wearing a snake, is reported in the hotel lobby.
The hotel is concerned, do you?
Tell the hotel to go ahead and remove them, send out ops looking for them, or ignore the situation.
Well, the hotel can piss off, right?
Because they charge us an extra 20 grand, so they should be nice to us.
So I'm not letting the hotel do nothing.
So what are the last two?
Yeah, okay.
So now a day, I mean, so we definitely say there's a code of conduct issue, and if we send...
'Cause...
Well, only if she's only wearing a snake.
No, I mean, I think it's a live animal at the convention, and we're definitely not having pets
attack her. But it could be, but it could be a service snake.
No, it could not be a service snake, they're wild.
They're not trainable, not bloody service snake, come on.
Well, it's possible someone would argue with you about that, but anyway, that is not an option.
You can either, if you're not sending the hotel, you can send out ops to look for them or ignore it.
We're going to send ops to look for them.
Or we could ignore it, we could just ignore it.
What'd you think, John?
He's too busy googling service snakes.
I'd probably...
Yep, it turns out that snakes can be official emotional support animals,
so it is entirely possible that it is one.
Have found that out.
Did not know, but did suspect.
Yeah, I knew you'd...
You had that "I am googling" now, look on your face.
Yeah, well, I was curious.
I think, like, it depends, right?
'Cause if someone's setting a python on attendees, we need to be aware of that.
So we should probably send ops just to have like a little quick look to make sure that's not the case.
But if it's just a lady with world-behaved snake...
Not, I don't know.
But I think we need to be aware either way.
Right, yeah, no, we're going to check, so we're going to send out ops to have a look.
All right, you have...
Could not go possibly wrong, right?
Sent ops looking for them.
This could not go possibly wrong, right?
And they get eaten.
Instructions to the searches were unclear.
Nobody planned what to do when the snake was found.
So the lady and snake wind up being brought to ops.
[Laughter]
Yup, no, that would happen.
That would definitely happen.
[Laughter]
Entirely legitimate.
All right, please roll to find out what happens to the snake.
One.
Someone from program happens to be in ops and offers to put the lady and the snake
into a herpetology discussion group.
Do you accept the offer with release or relief or turn down the offer?
100% accept.
Yeah, like that's just a win for us.
I'm not sure it is because I have vague feelings about some of the ways in which this one goes wrong.
Have you even seen the film snakes at a con?
[Laughter]
So you're accepting the offer of a herpetology discussion group?
Yup.
I mean, hang on, now, before I do that, what is a herpetology and why do we discuss it?
Reptile science.
Yeah.
Yeah, that seems good.
All right.
That had considered a scenario where John has not heard the word herpetology before, but you know,
you'll want to taste 10,000.
It's an educational game.
All right, you gain two good will points for a fascinating program item.
Hey, see?
We were only on two before, now we're on four.
Ooh.
And then roll to find out what happens next because the snake is still here.
[Laughter]
All right, watch me roll a one, guys.
I've rolled a four, Liz, by the way.
You've got four.
All right.
Some...
He eats everyone.
Sometime later, the snake is found curled up on a sofa in the sufferer suite.
[Laughter]
Do you call the hotel to take care of it,
send ops to do something about it, or ignore it?
After all, it doesn't seem to be bothering the fans.
Uh, what, where is the option for locate the lady whose snake is?
[Laughter]
I'm going to send ops to do something about it.
You can't locate people at the world, God.
Yeah, that seems like very much an ops thing that ops should do.
We sent ops to take care of it.
It's just not going to go well.
Uh, roll to find out if ops succeed.
[Laughter]
Six.
They don't.
Snake gets away.
Roll to find out what happens next.
I think you can possibly get an infinite snake loop here,
so let's see if we can break out.
Okay, so it's my roll.
What happens next?
Three.
Three happens next.
Uh, snake is found wrapped around real two of Star Wars.
Do you call the hotel, send ops, or ignore it?
Send ops.
We're going to send ops.
We'll keep sending ops until they fix it.
All right, let's send ops again.
All right, one more roll, please.
That's a four.
You're old for it.
The snake gets away.
Roll to find out what happens next.
Oh, technically we should have been in an extra roll here,
and I realize I've missed out.
Uh, one.
One.
Okay, roll again.
Is that Alison's turn now?
Six.
Sometime later, the snake is found receiving a whole costume award.
Again, do you call the hotel, send ops, or ignore it?
Send ops.
Eventually they've got to be able to do something.
Send ops, is there anything ops ever does about this?
Yeah, if you don't roll terribly, they're not,
you know, do opsy things.
I've rolled a six, but we know what happens with a six.
So should I roll again?
Um, roll one more time, yeah.
Four.
Yeah, it's the same one.
All right, should we have the other option from ops?
You roll the one.
Ops succeeding, capturing the snake to the cheers
of the assembled multitudes.
The snake has moved to ops.
Aah!
And efforts are made to contact the owner.
Lose one people point.
As it ends a person.
And in theory, you can go, you can go round around again with the snake,
just endlessly calling ops to try and capture the snake
and then escape the game again.
But let's assume the lady retrieves the snake from ops
and is never heard from again.
Hurrah!
Okay, that was just a good time for everyone.
I'm just for interest.
What happens if you get the hotel to kick them out of the first place?
Uh, if you get the hotel to do it.
Hang on spoilers.
I want to, I want to spoil it for next time I do this, uh, game.
Because we might play, we, there is some merit in just playing this again,
every time we need a...
Yeah, but we won't do the same scenario again,
there would we?
We won't do the same smoth either.
And eventually you can get, you can basically get stuck in a big loop.
We could be a committee as the three of us,
we get a, get Esther to be a smoth.
Okay, we're going to do another at-con thing.
We are going to go and see what happened with all of those decisions you made precon
about your spending money.
So, you have modest food.
So remember when you decided to spend some of your windfall income
to modestly increase food and drink items across the board?
People seem mostly happy.
There are some rumours of secret concom stashes,
but no one really takes them seriously.
Lose three financial points.
Okay, that makes sense.
That's what it said it was asked.
Yeah, that's what we wanted to do.
That is performing us advertised.
We're down to four financial points listeners,
but it should be fine.
How could we possibly need more money than that?
Game of Privies.
Remember when you paid to bring in the props of Game of Privies?
Roll.
Oh, I think it's Alice and Turn.
Full.
It was worth the expense.
Everyone ooze and ooze of the gorgeous costumes and realistic props.
And of course, everyone wants their chance to have their picture taken on the full size,
replica porcelain throne.
Game two good world points.
Hey.
And remember...
We're up to six.
Remember when you paid to bring in the cast of Game of Privies?
Yup.
How does that go?
Roll.
Five.
Many of your attendees are thrilled,
but others are appalled that you have turned the world con into a media convention.
Lose one good world point.
Oh for fuck's sake.
Fuck 'em.
Everything that's wrong with our community encapsulated in a sentence.
Yeah, because people get into science fiction by watching shows like Game of Privies.
Disappointed by how real life is not like Westeros.
Alright, so that was a pretty good outcome I think for your extra cash.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
We're now, we're now sitting pretty actually.
Because I'd say four on finance would be a defendable outcome.
So shall we do one more at Con Scenario to see if I can make you lose all your money?
Yay.
Let's spend a little bit more money, get some goodwill.
What about the dungeon master?
That sounds like a good one for us.
Yes, I'm down.
Ah, we're going to do Scenario 1101, The Dungeon Master by Joe Rico.
It is Saturday morning and you and your cohorts are pouring caffeine into yourselves
in an effort to convince the rest of the convention that you're not dead.
All Friday nights you have been hearing reports
that four strange mundane looking types had registered at the door.
This foursome had then spent most of their time showing a picture of some kid to various
fan in the games room.
Someone mentions that a couple had tried to play some D&D,
but had proven to be rank novices.
Now the foursome is in the hotel coffee shop and their leader is coming up to you.
My name is Club, Cow Club.
I'm a PI.
I and my associates are looking for Dennis Dork, a 12 year old genius who has last seen in his
MIT dorm room two months ago.
We have reason to believe that Dork, a D&D fanatic, is attending your sci-fi convention.
Your convention is responsible for Dork in local parentis wise.
We expect your full cooperation or criminal and civil remedies may be applied.
You have two questions to answer.
Is Club right? Are you or your convention responsible for a runaway child at your convention?
And what are you going to do about finding Dork, if anything?
Is Dork a member of the convention?
Do you agree with Club that you are liable for his presence?
Disagree with Club or want more information on the penalties by consulting a member of your
committee who is a lawyer, in which case you meet him at noon and you lose one people point?
Ah, less lawyer.
Definitely lawyer.
Oh my god.
We lawyer up.
Okay, lose a people point.
Deal.
Alright, we're all six.
We were on seven.
Attorney Rick Lates can be found in the pool where he is in charge of the jacuzzi track of program.
He listens as you tell of your meeting with Club.
He considers your problem carefully and then renders his opinion.
Simple answer, Club is full of hot air.
In local parentis is a principle that is not half as meaningful today as in the past.
As far as the con goes, we never assume responsibility for any attendee is other than
kids in babysitting.
However, you and I know that miners come to our con without supervision and we would never want
any type of litigation.
My advice, is how Club you don't consider yourself liable in the least, but as concerned citizens,
you would be happy to aid in any attempts to find this lost child.
Yep, let's do that.
Thanking him, you give a two litre bottle of Pepsi to the half submerged counselor and
do you decide to help him anyway or refuse to help him?
Saying you don't think you're liable anyway.
I'm going to take the lawyers advice.
I am not a lawyer.
That was a lawyer that's on a advice.
We spend some people points on this.
Let's go with that.
Your lawyer is currently drinking Pepsi in the jacuzzi though.
I would know that one.
It's okay, still a lawyer.
Even if submerged.
Yeah, this one is clearly going for like the sort of feeling to the scenario.
Quite like it.
You're going to say you're not liable and help him anyway.
Is that okay, John?
Yeah.
You have a following options to find him.
It costs one people point apart from option F, which costs two.
You know from club that doc realizes people are searching for him and that
doc cat doesn't have much money.
Choose which options you will take.
And I think you can have as many, I think you can have as many here as you want.
So you can look at your registration records.
Look at the hotel register for the room block.
Post a poster with his description.
Alert the hotel to the situation.
Show Doc's picture at staff headquarters and let all convention personnel.
Or assign a person to club to help him search, which costs you two people points.
I don't think we should put a poster up.
I think that's kind of excessive.
Yeah.
I think we should check our registration data under the hotel data to see if he's in the thing.
And I think we should tell our staff.
Do I assign a person to club?
Is that a bit much?
Oh no.
Did we have an option for going to look in the con suite?
No you do not.
He's probably not got a hotel room.
He's got no money.
So let's not bother with the hotel room.
Just is he a member and is he a member and tell our staff to keep an eye out for him?
Yeah, that's two.
All right.
That cost you two people points.
Roll a D6 twice and add the results.
Oh, I'll do one.
You do one?
Yeah.
Six.
I get four.
So that's 10 in total.
Brilliant.
And your modifier would have been two.
Because you chose two effective options.
Just to say that the hotel register,
your correct has no effect because he's not using his own name.
They can't afford a hotel.
And the posters lower your score because it tips him off that you're looking for.
Mm.
Anyway, you rolled a seven or more.
So your effort succeed and Dork is found.
Gain one goodwill point and one financial point because there was a reward.
Oh, one goodwill and one financial.
Going up on that goodwill track, we're at six now.
And you gain another one goodwill point because Club will write a book on this case,
which attracted national attention and he will praise your efforts.
Wow.
Okay.
So we get up to seven goodwill points.
Six, five, seven.
Wow.
Okay.
Because we basically we narc and that's what you should do, kids.
Well, I mean, we're not going to, it's under 13.
I mean, I feel like, yeah, there's no way.
No, don't.
It's fair.
You know, if it was like a 17 year old, then I think we'd have a big ethical issue.
But for a 12 year old, I think we have to, you have to try and get them back.
Yeah.
So I think that is the end of our scenarios for today.
I'm just, so I just tell you because they're quite,
quite good ones.
What happens if you don't do things?
Basically, if you don't consult your lawyer and you admit liability,
that goes badly.
It was right the following out a thousand times.
I will never ever admit liability in any circumstances.
You can either do that on your own, lose one people point or pay me one financial
point as a retainer and I will do it for you.
If you're, if you're wrong, he's angry.
If you're correct, but you don't consult him, he's like, yeah, you, you have to do
the ego.
And if you, um, in some scenarios, the police arrive and then hotel security,
check all your rooms because the kid was sleeping and registered on someone's floor.
You can lose a lot of points on that one.
So basically we took a very good path through that and we're also a bit lucky.
You took a very good path one, but you were a little bit lucky.
Yeah.
So I think that's the end.
So we should add up your total score.
So presumably giving helping club would have helped.
Would it's giving assigning somebody to club to serve?
Yeah.
You get basically, you spend two people points on it and get two extra points.
Hmm.
Okay.
That makes sense.
Um, that one actually helps, but you're way over there anyway.
You only need seven and you're rolling two de six.
So you'd be quite glad to do it if you don't do anything.
So to get your final score, start with the number of goodwill points.
Seven.
Yes.
And what your finance, and your financial points are five.
Yeah, we can't make him money.
Yeah.
Divide the, if your financial points are greater than four, divide the excess by two,
rounding down and subtract that from the score.
So it's not good to make too much money.
So the excess is one divided by two is half rounded down to zero.
So still seven.
Yeah.
Okay.
So we, we made, so my theory that four was probably about the amount you were okay to make.
Of course, in fact, exactly right.
And that was not a memory from the eighties.
That was just kind of feeling about conventional finance.
We can pass that extra along.
It's not a problem.
And then people points, our people points are positive.
So divide them by three, rounding up and add them to the score.
Oh, so that is two, because we had six people points.
Yeah.
Your helpers all had fun.
So you get a total of nine points.
Hey, that's good, right?
I mean, we're not competing with anybody, but that was a good con.
Everyone enjoyed the, the work on that John and I ran.
I know it was a freedom con.
Yeah.
You brought as a giant toilet.
You didn't lose any children.
You didn't cause ruckions by over filling the con suite with food.
And I've got an art prompt.
So I could do that.
Yeah, I think that was quite successful.
Just going to be punctuation con the world con.
A badder saying that with like a, a giant privy with three of us on it somewhere.
Nine points.
Okay.
So listeners, I guess how do you play through?
Hmm.
I guess we just have to tell them like what pages to go to.
And then they play through and then listen.
If they want to try and beat our score, because if they listen,
they'll know what the right answers are.
So they should play before.
Yeah, but you also need a, you need a GM really because it's hard to do it without
kind of seeing what the next step is.
But no, no, people who've played this game, write in and tell us your experiences.
And what was particularly funny about when you played?
I mean, I'm going to say, I do think this 2015 update is a fast improvement for me
on the previous versions, because yeah, it's a lot more up to date.
Yeah, there was a lot of stuff that was very old fashioned.
There is still quite a bunch of stuff.
I mean, we didn't do it this time, but there is a scenario about like how much effort
you should you put into like your software and ask for sweets, which is very American centric,
because in the UK, you're going to put much less effort into those, for instance.
And there's also, I think, a lot where it's about unionized workforces,
which have basically, there's like different implications for having a fully unionized
facility in the US and there are in the UK.
I spent a lot of time flirting with the leader of the bunch of people who were setting up
the exhibits hall at Chicon, and that all of that time was very well worth it.
I'm not proud.
But basically, he was kind of like, you didn't move a sofa, did you?
And we were like, oh, oh, I'm so terribly sorry.
And, you know, and oh, you guys are lovely.
And oh, I really, I can only really move so fast if I have a hefty,
a couple of hefty chaps to help.
And he kind of went away going, just remember that we'll always come and help you lift
sofas rather than, oh, no, let me put this on the list of things that this convention is doing,
whether or not supposed to.
And I think there's, yeah, I'd not, I'd not be to a convention in a
strongly unionized convention center before it was a shot.
Yeah.
Yes, that's it.
But it's just that there are things to consider in the US when you're in a unionized
facility that I've not come across in the UK one, like, you know, is there been a problem,
you know, moving furniture and plugging stuff in in such a strict way.
But that's just the different systems.
But that's why it's such a shock to me to see like conventions,
advertise that they have a non-union facility.
And I'm like, try that.
That's a negative thing, which, I mean, think it is.
And indeed, union is good.
We approve of unionized facilities, but we understand that it can be quite difficult for
some aspects of conorally.
Yeah, basically for your building up your exhibits, all and so on.
That was quite fun.
We'll put a link for you to buy it in the show notes.
And thank you to everyone who has written scenarios or contributed scenarios to this
across its four editions.
Yes, thank you to everyone who has been responsible for the events that caused
the scenarios to be written, having carefully pliled off serial numbers.
Yes, that is all so fair.
Yeah, I think your goal, your goal is to never be the inspiration for an if-I-run-the-con scenario.
Yeah, that does seem reasonable.
Oh yeah, if you're listening here and you've actually been the person in a scenario,
to let us know, were you the 12-year-old in the games room?
Were you the lady with the snake?
So that has been a very special episode of What to Thorpe, and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
[Music]
I'm Liz Batty.
What do you think?
I'm John Coxon.
And I'm Alison Scott.
Yay, okay, we managed.
I've uprooted the natural order of things.
I'm sorry.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod in Competec.com,
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.
(silence)