Right, let's give it go otherwise I might have to go and get the Alan Key.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 114th episode of Octa Thorpe podcast for Science Fiction
and Science Fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 18th of July 2024. I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty. We have some letters of comment and Liz is going to take the
first one. We have a letter of comment from Christopher J Garcia so he confirms that he will
be watching Godzilla in release order adding an important non-canon pieces like Bambi vs Godzilla
and SNL skits which is a level of dedication I had not expected. Yep he also thinks Saint
of Bright Doors will be second for the Hugo right we're gonna make a note to come back to that in
after what? He thinks it will come second for the Hugo behind something Chris tell us what will
win the Hugo in fact if you'd like send us your Hugo predictions for everything then we will check
back in on them on like whenever our post will con episode is. Yep. And also he was in LA during
the 1984 Olympics and he got to hold the torch. Fucking love you Chris. I mean how how did you get
to hold the torch? I didn't get to hold an Olympic torch but I got to hold a Paralympic torch because
that's one of the photo opportunities that they give you at the Olympics. Oh I got to stand near
the torch. I mean it's not there was not only one torch in 2012 and I don't suppose there was only
one torch in Los Angeles either and they have a lot of torches. Olympic secrets. We all know this
because of Doctor Who. I know lots of stuff about the 2012 Olympics because fun fact it was sufficiently
close to my house that I could hear the fireworks through my window as they come on the tally a
little bit later and it was quite quite wild. Nice. I didn't know what was that Doctor Who episode.
I guess it was during my phase of not watching Doctor Who. Well you remember when Russell T. Davis
was in charge and it was all a bit nonsense. Yeah I was still watching that. Was the Olympic torch in
it? Yeah David Tennant's Doctor did the like the like the brazier I think in what episode?
I don't think I've dreamed this. Listeners right in. No but I think I've blanked out of my
memory for like safety. I can only keep so many things in there now. I'm trying to get rid of
some of them and if I got rid of that one I'm quite pleased. You say nonsense. I do. Going back in
time and then making history work the way it's supposed to is a something that Doctor Who has
been doing since its earliest days. Yeah but the bit where a paving slab gives a amount of blow job
that was pre-nonsense though. Yeah okay. So I talked about collecting convention badges by accident
last week and we had a couple of walks. Collect wrote to say that she and Alan made all of the
badges for Discworld Con and Bristol Con and would I like them? And the answer is yes but
and I sent you an email about when. For a Mendelssohn wrote to say I'm sure the Sartre's
fiction foundation collection in Liverpool would love the convention badge collection.
I will write to them at some point and say would you like a box full of moldy badges
and see what they say. I put a pickup in last episode about Tor recusing themselves
from the Locust Award and I said it was a classy move and Edward Morland wrote to say
that he thinks if you've won 37 times in a row then it might be a bit late to call recusing
yourself a classy move and all I can advise Tor to do is try not to win any awards on the way
back to the parking lot. Yes so after we discussed the Locust Awards last time and Don does a little
drop-in on this we actually looked at what was said about the Best Publish Award in Locust.
Debbie Pillai in her speech accepting Best Publisha has withdrawn Tor and also Tor.com
from consideration for a few years to allow others to shine which I think is I think it's
still a classy act because it may be the 37th they've won but you know there's been a different
string of managing editors for Tor and Tor.com so it's not like this is one person winning
and so I think it's quite nice that when Debbie Pillai obviously had the power to do this
she decided it was time to take a back seat and for someone else's whip so we look forward to
seeing who is on the list next year. Recusing yourself has become more popular in recent years
so that they may have thought it was time and I don't think Tor.com has won anything like 37 times
so you know I think recusing them as well they are separate publishers although they have
the part of the same publishing group but then a lot of things are the part of the same publishing
group publishing is a bit like that. It's also a bit tricky because you know Tor and Tor.com
I wonder if there are people who read Tor stuff and Tor.com stuff and just think it's all Tor.
No I'm sure there are lots of people who think that but it's definitely not.
I think Tor UK is still totally separate and therefore would still be eligible.
I may be wrong. I feel like it's separate in the same way which is just a separate publisher
managed by the same overall massive publishing conglomerate but you know if you're part of a
massive publishing conglomerate please write it and explain your corporate structure to us.
The thing is there's like a massive publishing conglomerate right like there's Halt's Brink which
is a massive publishing conglomerate of which Magmillan is a sub bit of which Tor is a sub bit
of that and what I don't know is whether Tor UK and Tor US sit under the same sub bit called Tor
Publishing. It's very complicated. All right whoever knows this write in and tell us.
Somebody who's listening to the podcast knows this I am 99% sure.
I know it. Tor UK isn't in the Tor Publishing group because if you go to Tor Publishing Group.com
they have a list of the things that are in it and Tor UK is not on the list.
Research. It's Tor Bramble, Forge Nightfire, Torteen Starscape and Tor.com.
So it's kind of slightly further removed but it is still all part of I guess McMillan?
Yes which is all part of Halt's Brink. I do think it is fair to say that if Tor had
recused themselves and then Tor.com had won 25 times we might plausibly have argued that that
was not quite what we meant when we asked them to recuse so I think in general this is probably
the right way to do it if you're going to. So next year everyone vote Tor UK in the locus
publishing award because I think that would be very very funny. Oh Edward does also say
if there's nothing else on locus expecting individuals or individual organisations to
recuse themselves in order to fix the awarding organisation or the voting base is complete lack
of interest in the breadth of the field. Feels like putting a sticking plaster over a gaping wound.
It's tricky in it. I don't think I want the Hugo to forcibly recuse people
and I don't think it's unreasonable that people tend to vote for the things they know
and that most people don't have a massive breadth of field which they can call on especially when
it comes to stuff like Publisher. But yeah I don't know. What do you guys think about that?
It's tricky because when would you recuse someone because you know you win a few times in a row
all right and then at some point you're like oh maybe I should recuse but then you know we've
talked about recusing before like there's a point in which it is kind of awkward you're sort of
recusing yourself because you're saying well uh you know everyone else who wins after us is only
winning because we recused ourselves. So I think it's a tricky balance. I don't think I think it's
working okay in that people are recusing themselves after multiple wins and that's probably how it
should work. Maybe up to thought pointing it out helped because we are so influential. Yeah I'm
an influencer. If anyone from Tor is listening right in yeah I think the thing is right that like
obviously if you codified it in the so phrases if you do it with the Hugo you need to codify it in
the Wussfuss constitution and that would make it very awkward because we all know it when we see
it I mean it's much easier if people recuse when it becomes taking the piss and that's what
annoys me so much when people don't recuse when it's taking the piss because I don't think it's
easy to codify it's much easier to do it if you're the one that won but maybe I'm wrong I don't know
what other people think listeners right in. When we were discussing it last episode we weren't
necessarily saying Tor should recuse themselves we were also saying to voters if you have voted for
Tor 12 times in a row is this because you genuinely have read lots of different books and you think
Tor put out all the best ones or is it because you're still remembering oh Tor put out some good
stuff I've already for them last time I'll put them at the top again and just like be aware of
what you are reading. We also heard from Mike Scott who says yes I did indeed find the cerebus
reviews that I was talking about but he also notes that Andrew Willstone did a very insightful
review of the entire run a few years ago which he did and we will link to that in the show notes
this is quite a lot of thoughtful discussion of cerebus I don't know what triggered all this kind
of reevaluation of it but it does seem if you want to read it then there is a lot of discussion of
basically whether you should start and when you should stop. I nearly I was reading Andrew Willstone's
review and I realized that I had not said something about cerebus last time which is that it's it's
hard to overstate how influential it was and how important it was until it went completely off
the rails it's and I think it's the first example of my lifetime of the victor a lot of Victorian
novels that we think of as great were serialized and I think cerebus gives the sense of what it
must have been like as those were coming in because you know it was just people were talking about
at the time and it was wildly influential and it just became weirder and weirder and weirder and
it is quite a lot like um real dimensions just from Shandy in his review and I I think it is quite
like just Shandy in that way of course cerebus does go off on and tangents quite a lot like all
of the time and I have not read all of it Raj wrote in on mastodon and said when we talked about
Rebecca's World on a previous episode quite a long time ago now he had loved it as a kid much like
I did and has set a price alert for it I guess on eBay and has now bought a reasonably priced copy
and so thanks us for getting him to reread it so you are welcome Raj I saw that you gave it four
out five on Goodreads so I'm glad it held up so hurrah and if you're interested in that listeners
and you haven't been listening since the beginning the episode I was on of alleybaker brooks' podcast
fantasy book swap I picked Rebecca's World and we discussed it so if you're interested in my
thoughts you can go and listen to that I'll put a link in the show notes and Alison was also
all fantasy book swaps well put that in as well why not I picked Marianne Dreams by Catherine
Store the book I named my daughter after and a lovely segue is that Ali left us a comment on
Facebook Ali is our occasional children's and young adult literature correspondent
saying that the sequel to this rather delightful quest novel should be eligible for award nominations
and it's called Vivi Conway and the Sword of Legend by Lizzie Huxley Jones thank you very
much Ali Duncan McGregor says he went for a walk good on you Duncan Bridget Badger says that super
art referring to our episode art last time which is quite super if you haven't seen it because it's
very small in the show notes you can click through to octothorp.podbean.com and see the full size one
and it is a good one last time I said to Alison Alison Alison please can you draw like Godzilla
smashing the octa-thop logo and she has drawn Godzilla smashing the octa-thop logo and now I'll
be demanding ever more elaborate show art. We're going to talk about the things that we're picking
for the Hugo Awards that are not best novel because we went through our best novel picks in episode
111 and we also will be skipping over best game or interactive work and if you want to hear our
thoughts on that you can listen to episodes 104 we talked about chance of sinaa 109 we talked about
dredge 112 we talked about Baldur's Gate 3 113 we talked about Alan Wake 2 and I will be picking
Jedi survivor later this episode. I'm talking about Zelda and you'll have to listen to the other
episodes to find out why we'll start with novella yes novella who wants to introduce novella I have
read five of the six novellas I should say it's it's gonna look like I've read an extremely
haphazard selection of stuff and this is basically because I loaded all the stuff up on my kindle into
a very random order so it's because you've read an incredibly haphazard selection of stuff listen
I'm wondering about whether I should recuse myself for the rest of this episode because of how little
of the Hugo stuff I've read I will ask clever questions about it maybe it's fine it'll just be
an episode with lots of me so I have read five of the six I have not read life does not allow us to
meet by hee-hee but I have read all the rest they're all pretty good I don't think there's any
duff ones I just think there's kind of five novellas that I all think are not quite
amazing don't want to be read I have read all six Liz oh hey my main
thought is that I don't like Alex Woodens translations and I don't know whether the underlying stories
would have been better translated by someone else for me but certainly life does not allow us
to meet I detested see to Mercury I thought was a really interesting conceit but I thought it was
clumsily written and I assume that is in the translation and not in the original Chinese but
I might be wrong I loved Rose House by Arcadimartin which is probably not a surprise because I love
everything Arcadimartin right but I thought it was really creepy in a really nice way
Malath's the gates was pretty good Thornhead's Ditto and the mimicking of known successes
I remember enjoying but can't remember anything about what was that one about does anyone remember
I read this category first yeah so that's the one where basically humanity has left
earth to do climate change and gone to live on these sort of orbital platforms and there's a
detective investigating the death of a man who appears to have just stepped off one of the platforms
oh I do remember that yes yeah you meant that one yet it's because the title has nothing at all to
do with the story it does though it does yes no I did enjoy that but in a very it was all very
competently done but there was nothing completely outstanding in any of the books on this I think
the only one that kind of thrilled me was Rose House so I think I probably agree with you basically
yeah so it's I think one thing that's interesting is all the Chinese nominees that were previously
untranslated have been translated by Alex Woodend so I've not seen it mentioned anymore but my
assumption is that Glasgow arranged some translations it could be totally wrong on that so yeah it's
very hard for me to say whether I am put off because of the translation or because of the underlying
story we have no particular expertise here I also quite enjoyed seeds of mercury but there were
certain things that just didn't quite make sense like the main character essentially inherits
after his aunt dies she had like this groundbreaking idea essentially for new life and the main narrator
ends up inheriting that and I couldn't quite work out why that was necessary it's one of those
things where if you take that out and just had that aunt there running out of money and then
trying to get the funding for it the story would have worked I think just as well would that have
required a female protagonist oh yes it would but why wasn't it an uncle I mean you know no that
but that is true it basically has this kind of pioneering female scientist who is entirely like
offstage because she dies at the start of the develop but I did enjoy that I enjoyed them all
I thought mamas at the gate and Thorn hedge so mamas at gate buying Nivo and Thorn hedge by
Tking Fisher both suffered a bit because they are very much in the mode of what I know Nivo and
Tking Fisher right which is that Thorn hedge is like a sort of fairy tale retelling of Sleeping Beauty
and mamas at the gates is another in the long-running series of singing hills novellas that's one
and so they're both good installments in that but didn't give me anything new the mimicking of
known successes I really like the setting and found it an extremely slow mystery and Rose House I
just I don't think I quite gelled I really like the idea and everything it just didn't come together
so it's going to be a very tricky category for me to vote in because I really don't know which
one to put first as of listening to this I will have two days to do that so I've hopefully thought
about it a bit by then when Liz says she enjoyed all of them it's vital that we reiterate she didn't
read like it does not allow us to meet yes sorry I did not which it's a gender not like and so John
is now like he's like if you like that we're not friends anymore twisting the knife I was not the
only one who really detested this novella at the moment how would you rank them Liz if I forced
you to if you forced me to it's probably mammoth at the gate Thorn hedge Rose House mimicking of
known successes seeds of mercury but then as I get further through that I'm like am I really
going to put that on fifth it's hard that's tricky isn't it because I think my list Rose
house goes at the top I think for me mimicking of known successes goes at the bottom because
although I really enjoyed it I don't think it's it's just it's a nice detective story and then
probably Thorn hedge above mammoths of the gate and I really don't know where seeds of mercury
is going because I did not like the writing but I thought some of the ideas were interesting
and I don't know how to slot it in amongst the others it's definitely not going first but I could
see on the day me putting it second or fourth so there's quite a lot of variance there
novelette I've read one of the novelets I read three okay which ones of you read Liz
I'm really sorry I read introduction to 21 81 over to your second edition by Gucci translated
by Emily Jin one man's treasure by Sarah Pinska and the year without sunshine by Naomi Quitson
hey I read I am I was it I am I am AI or is that the trick well it's I am yeah it's about a woman
I am assuming it's pronounced I is it it could be a I'm so sorry I don't know but basically it's
about a woman called I who runs a company called I am AI what did you think of the ones you read
so it's actually well since I read two of these because I read them pre-nomination because they
were ones that were highly rated and so I was reading them to see if I wanted to nominate them
so finally I did not nominate either of them because they're quite good but they're just maybe
not my type of thing woman's treasure by Sarah Pinska is basically about garbage men and finding
magical objects and it's pretty good but it didn't kind of stick with me and the year without
sunshine by Naomi Quitson I think I talked about last week it's the one about kind of
communities banding together in a post-apocalyptic well not really post-apocalyptic but
something has occurred and communities are banding together and it's about neighbors and I think
a fairly reasonable story about how they they might come together it just didn't have a lot
else for me an introduction to 2181 over to your second edition is very interesting I enjoyed
this one so it's about kind of essentially a world in which we have figured out cryo sleep
and it reminded me a little bit of almost Ted Chiang who does you know he does like
wrote "Liking What You See" which is like what if we have this technology let's explore loads of
aspects of it and it's a little bit similar to that I just found that the key thing in 2181
over to is kind of it's supposed to be the introduction to a book there's kind of lots of
characters who are talked about in this and that you're supposed to kind of find how it all comes
together at the end and I think I had not got strong enough impression of the different people
and how it all fit together at the end but there is a lot of interesting stuff about what would
happen if you could actually put yourself into cryo sleep and wake up in the future yeah I think
at the moment that's probably top of my ballot but I do have another three to read and I have
heard good stuff about I am I. I have just realized I have indeed I have actually read Warman's Treasure
by Sarah Pinsker and I did quite enjoy it it was before I cancelled my uncanny subscription
and I thought I at the time really enjoyed it I am I I thought was good I don't know I obviously
I've not read any others except for Warman's Treasure at the moment it's going below Warman's Treasure
for me yeah so I will just say here that I have realized that I read Give Me English by I.J.ang
because it was on my Kindle from the Vote Packet and I thought it was a best short story not many
but it's not it's just in there for the Astounding Award eligibility I think but that was also quite
interesting interesting I sure that is obviously I'm going to read I'm going to read that at some
point I haven't got to eat it it's one of those ways like it's got a science fictional premise I
don't think the world building quite works but the premise is interesting enough that I didn't care
how many short stories have we read four I've read all of them I think tasting the future delicacy
three time is the one which actually has some it leaves some things untranslated and puts it in
a footnote which I like when if there's not an obvious translation and so you can either go for
something that doesn't quite fit or you can leave it untranslated and put a footnote in to say here
is the concept that you need to know and I've left it untranslated because you can't put a single
word in I prefer that way I think than to doing it as a straightforward not quite accurate translation
even if it does break up the flow a bit because you have to read an extra footnote so I think it's
a balance you don't want to do it in every sentence because you're going to spend your whole life
reading footnotes but I kind of like it as an occasional look I cannot translate this perfectly
you should know that this is the word that was used and that it has all these different meanings
for people who can read it in their original language yeah I did enjoy the tasting the future
delicacy three time story so hurrah it's translated by jwetting si nie the author talks about the
translation choices made at the start of the story which is really interesting the part of the reason
I think what I'm bouncing off is Alex Wooden's translation and not the underlying text is that
the you're I'm going to read the author's note verbatim in Chinese I purposely used the title
insert string of Chinese here to express manifold meanings such as taste delicacies three times
three kinds of delicacies and three sections of an article about delicacies it is extremely
difficult to keep the manifold meanings in translation the English translation of the story
translated the title is three gourmet delicacies different from the previous offered translation
so the version in the pack has a different title to the title on the best short story roster
because the version of the pack is titled three gourmet delicacies that I really think underlines
how much control you have over the English you use when you're translating Chinese and the fact
that this translation I found much more compelling than the wooden translations I think is also
telling so that's a brief digression at the beginning on on the Chinese translations in the
packet it makes me really wish I read Chinese I feel I want to say at this point if you're Alex
Woodend write in Alex is a very well respected translator of Chinese science fiction and
I mean I know this is hard but I do I do feel everything you're saying about overly literal
and therefore clunky translations really often getting in the way of stories quite a lot
especially for Chinese science fiction but actually other science fiction in translation it's not
you other other SF authors have been bedeviled by having translators who did not let the story
sing as much as it might have done I know this is an incredibly hard topic though I'm just going
to put into the show notes because we recognize this is a topic that you know we are pretty badly
equipped to discuss there's like an essay by Ken Liu about translation and also a piece by
someone who reads Chinese and English looking at some of their translations and discussing how
they feel about them and will pop those in the show notes for further reading which which other
ones did I read I read better living through algorithms which I mentioned briefly last week
that's the Naomi Quitsa story which is very much in the vein of the other Naomi Quitsa stories
I read How to Raise a Crockling in Your Bathtub by P. Jelly Club which I liked enough to put it on
my ballot and I read The Sound of Children Screening by Rachel K. Jones and what was the fourth
old future delicacy? And future delicacy three times yeah so what do you think of them Liz?
I'm trying to think what's so about them if you have something to say then you should you should
go ahead and do it and I'll just argue with you that's more fun. Hey better living through
algorithms is I really liked it I like Naomi Quitsa any way I thought it was fascinating
as a concept and it reminded me a lot of the stuff she's done in her catnet YA novels which
have been in the load style category previously it kind of feels to me like she wanted to look
at the same basic concept but in an adult short story rather than in a YA novel so I like that
a lot. How to raise a crackling in your bathtub I thought was great I really enjoyed it
I thought it was just I liked the ending a lot and The Mausoleum's Children I thought was okay
and The Sound of Children Screening I liked a lot and tasting the future delicacy three times
maybe really laugh at the end. I very much liked how that came together. An Anselis journey
I thought was fine I'm not sure I thought the concept was up to much so I'm not sure whether
I would have liked it more with a different translator or not because eh but yeah Liz promised
to argue with me. I did but there's not a lot to argue with. Am I just very sensible and right
about everything? Everything no but possibly a short story. I can agree with you yeah um I think
I probably like tasting the future delicacy three times a bit more than you did because I think
that might actually be top of my ballot. But I also like The Sound of Children Screening I think it's
it's essentially kind of fantasy horror fiction that plays with the idea of Portal fantasy
while also writing about school shootings which is a very tricky thing to do and I think it does
a really good job. I also think it landed the ending I liked the ending I thought it ended where
it needed to and the ending made sense which is not always true in that kind of short story.
I think yeah Sound of Children Screening is probably top of my ballot and then probably
Kraken and then probably algorithms and then probably tasting the future delicacy and then
probably Moseleym's children and then probably Anselis journey that would be probably my ranking.
I've used the word probably about 15 times there probably you probably have Liz taste maker
Batty do you want us take us through the best series finalists? Yes so there are six finalists
the final architecture by Adrian Tchaikovsky Imperial Radge by Anne Lecky the last binding by
frame ask the laundry files by Charles Doss October day by Sean and Maguire and the universe of Zuyar
by Aliette de Baudat and I have read some or all of five of those. Is the one you haven't read any
of the last binding by frame ask? No. Oh which one is it October day? I know it's been nominated
for series like four times and I've still never got around to meeting any of them. So I have I have
read this is basically there are three things here where I've read either all or part of one novel
and decided that the series is not really for me. There is one that everyone says is excellent
and I'm saving it for sometime when I need something fantastic to write and read it. There's one that
I've read all of I think is very good indeed and one that I've never actually heard of.
And weirdly the one you've not heard of is The Laundry Files by Charlie Stross.
It is not The Laundry Files by Charlie Stross but the laundry files by Charlie Stross is probably
not the series for me and neither is October day and neither is the universe of Zuyar and I have not
read the final architecture because honestly there's so much Adrian Tchaikovsky I mean I don't think
I've read the final architecture which series is this? This is the big space opera one with the
kind of race of crab alien crime lords. Tell me which the books are. No Google fine.
Shards of Earth yes shards of earth haven't read it.
I think it's going at the top of my ballot. I'm about to say something that might upset people
but The Laundry Files would have gone at the top of my ballot in the days when there were only five
books in that series but more recent books I'm like no it does not. I liked it when it was still
it and it doesn't feel like it anymore to me. Maybe that's unfair but that is my opinion.
It feels a bit diminishing returnsy like I loved the first few but the first few are the ones that
we gave Hugo's two in like 2005 or something and it has not kept me entertained for 20 years.
Yeah I think I would agree with that.
So I think the Anlecchi is fabulous under the I can't imagine why it hasn't won best series
before but presumably because the first three books were before we did invented best series
and it's certainly going to win and it's going to be top of my ballot.
I hope it doesn't win because it has already won Hugo Awards and Adrian Jiekowski has not
so I hope he wins. But I haven't actually read the here Adrian Jiekowski so I would feel
slightly bad about saying it's top of my ballot when I haven't actually read it.
And I haven't heard of the frame mask but this has read some so could you tell us a bit about
the last bundle by frame mask?
I have read the first one which is a marvelous light which I actually read I think when it was
in a previous Hugo packet. I was just going trying to work out when I was discussing it.
It's the first one which is rather like is definitely sort of romance with magic.
So it's about a young man who thinks he's got a little posting government and it turns out he
is like liaison to Secret Magical Society and he gets thrown together with someone from the
Magical Society and they have a romance. It had quite a lot of sex scenes.
I was looking up what I wrote about it and one of the things I wrote was I had to stop reading
this on the train because I was worried someone would look over my shoulder and see I was reading
a big sex scene. It's a teeny bit Harry pottery because there's a Secret Magical Society and I
know Harry pottery is not actually set in Edwardian England but it feels like the Magical Society is
100 years behind or whatever so you get that feel a little bit. I quite enjoyed it. I have not yet
read the other two which are in the voter back so I will be getting round to them but you know I
thought first one was pretty good. Not going to be top of my ballot because I'm pretty sure that is
Adrian Charkoski. But it might be third. Is it romanticy? Yes. But I think of romanticy as being
more sort of like fantasy that is not set in our world which has romance in. But I guess you probably
I don't know that's just maybe my definition of romancy which is not everyone else's definition
of romancy. I say you could pick this one. I think the romance aspect is stronger than the
fantasy aspect if that makes sense. Like I've read fancy novels where there is some romance
I would just ask this as a romance novel where there is some fantasy. One reason I'm not putting
the end lecky top is because as we previously discussed I did not like the fourth Imperial
Raj book as much as you two did and I feel like the first ones have already been pretty well
rewarded. So that is not a rational way to look at it. I'm not you know thinking of them as a series.
As a series I think it's very close to Tchaikovsky and possibly ahead but I also think it has had
awards love elsewhere and I think final architecture needs more awards love.
Yeah I think I agree with that. It's worth noting that translation state is the fifth novel
in the Imperial Raj universe. There was also provenance which I remember nothing about
and which I thought I think seemed to remember thinking was fine at the time but I was not blown
away by. Could I completely forgotten that was in the same universe but again I have read it and
completely forgotten about it but it's very that one is much more like lightly connected
than the latest one I think. So the reason I would say I'm not going to put an lecky at the top of
this category is because I think she is better at writing standalone novels than she is series
by which I mean I think and celery justice and translation state are both very very good.
I mean the other three books in this series are okay whereas I think if you read the Tchaikovsky
trilogy I think I mean I've only read the first two but certainly unless he massively fluffs the
ending and unless he's been very untchaikovsky like and had a wibbling quality the thing I think
Tchaikovsky is very good at is delivering consistent high quality works without fail and lecky seems
much more bumpy and I think a series should not be as bumpy as lecky's writing is.
You're making it sound like I should get the Tchaikovsky read before the deadline so that I can vote for it.
I think you should read it all about the deadline. Yeah I might manage one.
I mean there's just like three 800 page books it's not much.
Well but I know it's just like three 800 page books but I'm gonna say I prefer this to somebody who
writes like 17 novels in a series because I find it very hard to believe that 17 novels series are
gonna hold the quality and also actually be doing different exciting things with every book.
Yeah so I think one of the things I like about the final architecture is it is three enormous scale
galactic space operas that are very heavily serialised and yet when I reach the end of it
the main to the main character Idris Telemia Telemia basically has a kind of really sort of slightly
sad and tragic story which manages to pass the wall three and I think ends really well.
So one of the things I like is when you are having this galactic scale like clash at the end you
also have this very human story going on that I found really satisfying. I may have had a little cry.
Hey. And how many space opera books make you do that?
That is a fair point. I think yeah I think for me I suspect the reason I am such a massive
Tragofsky fan is that he is that he is one of the authors that manages to bridge the massive
ideas and world building with stories about people and not every author manages to do both of those
at once. I think one of the massive problems I have with Summer Lecky's books is that they fall
too far to one end of that spectrum. I actually think Lecky kind of goes both ways and her best
is in the middle but she doesn't always land in the middle. I just want to pick up you kind of
like saying Adrian Kuchakoski does the massive ideas in the world building. I love that stuff.
The stuff I don't like is is space adventure where I go. Oh no this is a big old story just
just with spaceships instead of biplanes. And I don't think I've never seen Adrian Kuchakoski do
that. I mean you know you might do for all I know but not in the things I've read at all.
So I think I probably am going to like it quite a lot but like just sit down and get on with it.
You're going to mean him eventually. Just go for it.
What's your ranking going to be? Alison and Liz. So I will try to get some of it read.
And then otherwise yes I'll be voting for the Lecky. I don't know what I'll do with the rest.
Haven't read the mask but really then probably I'll be an order. Bode,
Stros, Maguire. My order will be Tchaikovsky, Lecky, Stros, Devodar, Maguire.
I don't know where mask is going because I haven't read that one yet. What about you Liz?
Hi, order is Tchaikovsky, Lecky, Mask, Stros, Devodar, I think.
That's actually the same as my order except you've read Mask and not read Maguire. So maybe I will
agree with you or mask and we will have the same order. All right I'm useless at the next two categories.
So I've read, I've read 4.5 Best Graphics Story. So Beowulf, I've not read.
None of my libraries have copies. The version in the Hugo Packet was not the full version
and I'm reluctant to spend 25 quid on a physical book just to see what it's like. So I've not read
that one. I have read the others with the exception of the three body problem part one where I read
the first three pages and thought no and put it down again. Shabek Lebeek, which I probably
massively mispronunciating and sorry to everyone, which was published as your wish is my command
and that is the version I'm reading. Kindly lent to me by Neil Harrison is amazing so far. I'm like
a third of the way through but unless something really weird happens it's going top. Sargave
of all the 11 is the first Sargave comic I've read. It's pretty good. I liked it a lot. That will
be going second. It makes me want to go back and read other Sargave comics. Wonder Woman Historia made
me very angry in a good way. Zeus was a prick and I knew that but it really makes you feel it
and I like that great deal and at the moment I think that's going above Sargave actually and
then the witches of World War II had an uphill struggle with me because I'm very tired of World
War II and I'm very tired of British exceptionalism in World War II and also I didn't really like the
art style or the coloring or the characters so I didn't like it very much. Sorry Paul. Sounds like
that one is not for John. I like like vivid more impressionistic abstract comic art which Wonder
Woman does fantastically and which is World War II is very literal, very subdued, very mostly
beige art and I think that's because it's trying to look like World War II and you know that's fair
but it's not my cup of tea. Anyone else read any comics? Would it just be noted comics expert
John Coxon? Best related work? I will be voting for all these worlds reviews and essays by Neil
Harrison. I have also read a city on Mars which is very good but we'll be going below Neil on my
ballot and I have not yet got to a traveler in time. The critical practice of Maureen Kincaid
speller but I want to without you peeps. I am partway through a traveling time. I have read all these
worlds reviews and essays which we'd be going top of my ballot. I haven't read the rest. I mean one
of them is a podcast right or something similar to a podcast. That's a great question. I I'm just
double checking so I don't think the culture the drawings was in the packet. It's not and I'm not
going to seek a copy out so it's probable that I'm not going to read that.
Indeed. The city of Mars was also not in the packet but I had read it already and I don't know
about the two. I can't see the two other finalists discover X and Chinese science fiction and oral
history. I assume Chinese science fiction and oral history is an oral thing but...
So the Discover X interview I think is a sort of interview talk show which appears to be related
to the Chengdu Wilkon. Oh yeah now I remember. It's a professional podcast that is a short feature on
the Chengdu Wilkon. This is going below no award on my ballot guys because I hate it when a Wilkon
eats itself on the Hugo ballot. That's really interesting because if this is a digression but
where's the line for you? Like if if Meg did a bunch of audio interviews at Glasgow with people
working on Glasgow and then edited them into a project like as an independent and released it
and it was a fantastic fan historical resource and it got nominated I would think that was completely
legit and so I'm not saying I think this Chengdu project is completely like worthy of a vote
but I can definitely imagine situations in which you could get a very similar project that I would
think was amazing. Also Meg I'm not suggesting you do this. Stop planning to do this. Say no to this
idea Meg. Put the audio recorder down Meg. You are correct that it would be possible to do something
that was heavily Wilkon focused that I would nevertheless think was the right sort of thing to be seeing
on the ballot but that is not what has traditionally happened when things that are world-conner
indeed convention focused have happened so no it is theoretically possible but but I don't think
this is one I think this is a little promo video. No yeah I mean don't get me wrong I'm with you
on this particular case. I have read quite a lot of the essays in a traveller in time the critical
practice of Maury Kincaid speller because I've been reading her work for a long time. My vote is
nevertheless going to all these worlds reviews and essays by Neil Harrison. I am quite excited
by a city on Mars but I haven't read the whole thing yet I've got a bit and I do like its premise
very much and John Pickett has previous. I did and I haven't been able to read the culture the drawings
I it would be a bit sad if it won. Yes I think that's fair. I feel it would be people voting for
something which it is not. Yes. Which is they love Ian and they'd love to give him a hugo. The project
on the oral history of Chinese science fiction I believe is in the packet and is a text document
but is not in English and so I have not read it. I think the tables of contents are in English
but none of the text is and it looks absolutely fascinating but I cannot in any way really evaluate
it but it is exactly the sort of thing I think should happen it looks like a detailed fan historical
work and it is yeah. Oh I wish they translated this but I mean this is where I go oh I wish
you translated this or because I will call it stop for the translation of this. Yeah but how long is
it? Yeah I mean there's no way that Worldcon has this is about 800 pages of combined text
and so no I think it would have been lovely if it had been translated but it would have been
monetarily and temporally quite un-undertaking. Phanact.org let's let's do some crowd
funded to get this translated. I have no idea what the going rate is for that for translations
but I suspect translating a 750 word document is a lot of money. Maybe translate the first chapter
and let's see also a good option and that would be a good option for the hugo pack too now that I
think of it. I think it will be interesting to see whether that the fact that all these worlds of
using essays by Neil Harrison is in the voter pack in its entirety and a traveling time by Maureen
Kingcanspeller is not. I will be interested to see if that seems to have any effect on the voting
because only the first part of Maureen's book is there and it's I think it's quite a short
excerpt. It doesn't feel like you really fully get into it unless I've dealt a long file or
something but I think it's just an excerpt isn't it? No I yeah well it says "except" in the
file name so yes I think you are probably right it has the first... no sorry the forward the
introduction and the first three essays one of which is a screed about Sherlock. It's a start of the
book and it feels like maybe it would have been more interesting in this case to have part of
the middle of the book and not have the introduction in there. Certainly if there are only three essays
by Maureen and one of them is about Sherlock it's difficult to form a view of that as opposed to 450
words of the purest Harrison Gold. Can I make that the title of the episode or would nearly
himself? I think you might have to run that one. Past him. I could always make the title would nearly
himself. I think you might have to run that one past him. Right best dramatic presentation long form
who wants to go through this? Alison you've seen some of these. I have I have not seen
haven't seen all of them though. God what am I like? Neither have I for reasons to become apparent.
I haven't seen Barbie which I mean I definitely will see Barbie before the voting deadline.
What have you been doing? I saved it for when Marianne came round and then we didn't watch it so
you know that's what happened. What I mean is I don't get round to a lot of things. I probably
should have gone to see Barbie in the cinema I'm not quite sure why I did. Oh I do remember I was
expecting it to be on my various aeroplays last year and it wasn't I was very pissed off.
No of the ones I see poor things will probably get my vote. What about you guys?
But now I've seen and now I know that I've got Netflix after all. I can probably see
Nimono which I believe is on Netflix. Yes. Liz how many of these have you seen? Four.
Which ones? Barbie Dungeons and Dragons, Nimono and Spiderman. I'm gonna say you should see poor
things way more than I should see Barbie. I will watch poor things. Yes. Recall that poor things.
I mean I think I will now it's on Disney Plus but I think I will say that poor things did not get
like a massive cinema release here and it was months later than yours. So there is a countries
now I haven't seen it. Yeah there is. I also watch Barbie on a plane. Sorry Alison.
I mean I think I did watch poor things the very first day it was on Disney Plus so sometimes I
live in the moment. Where are you putting your various things Liz? So they're all pretty good
too very good actually. I think my current ranking is Spiderman, Barbie, Nimono Dungeons
and Dragons. I think I'd agree with that. I think I'd probably put poor things above Spiderman although
it is very close. I might watch poor things and then re-watch Spiderman. I have just seen her of
somebody. A friend out friend of the podcast says that the Wandering Earth 2 is basically a
remake a better remake of the Wandering Earth in many respects and I thought that was interesting.
I've not watched the Wandering Earth 2 because the Wandering Earth 1 I thought was extremely bad
and the Wandering Earth 2 is three hours long and I would have to pay to watch it and I am
unpersuaded that it will be worth the time or the money. If it lands on free streaming anywhere
I might watch the first half an hour to see if it's any better but yeah.
Best dramatic presentation short form and it's a return to the old days with multiple doctor who
finalists. And multiple strange new worlds finalists. It's not really the old days for that though is
it? I mean that is new. No but multiple finalists from the same TV show. We can only have two now right?
Isn't there a rule? Do the Wispus Constitution? I just type Wispus and it auto-complete to my
menu bar now. While this is looking at the Constitution I will say I have watched none of these
and I will not be watching any of them before the voting deadline because they're not the things
that I'm going at and going oh I should really make sure to watch this before the voting deadline.
I think Strangely World is probably better than Doctor Who but I only know that from what my
friends say about it rather than from any actual intelligent. Yeah my ballot is going to be
those old scientists and then some space where I have Rhapsody and then Gloria's Purpose and then
the Two Doctor Who's which I can't remember which episodes they are purely from the titles
but yeah. Wild Blue Yonder is the one with... It's one with a really long corridors right?
Yes yes it is. And then the Giggle. I would put Wild Blue Yonder above the Giggle.
I watched the first of the specials and then it wasn't terrible but you know the series is not
the science fiction series for me. If there are more than two works in the same category there are
episodes the same dramatic presentation series only the two works in each category that have the
most nominations that appear on the final ballot but we already know they didn't disqualify
anything from this category right? Because they announced the disqualifications. Yes I assume
that if anything had fallen foul of that it would have been announced as a disqualification or there
would have been some thing at the announcement so presumably that means it did not happen.
Yeah because I was wondering if the other eligible Doctor Who special would have been on there
apart from for that rule right? One sec. All right so I've watched five of these. I haven't watched
Loki because I haven't watched Loki season two yet so it could be amazing. I don't know what I'm
gonna put top it's either those old scientists or long long time from the last of us might be
long long time. Those old scientists just for Jack quade's war cliz he deserves the Oscar.
Okay so those old scientists is great in a very sort of referential way. Long long time was like
genuinely the most I've cried at any television show this year. But you hate crying so clearly
that makes it bad. I don't know I think there's a cathartic thing to having a good crud jump.
No I was mostly taking the bass sorry. It's very hard to compare one thing which is basically
super fun and super referential and one thing which is kind of the standout episode that stands
low enough a series I liked but not that much. So those are at my top somewhere and then I think
it's subspace rhapsody the Giggle and Wild Blue Yonder but kind of under duress because I don't
like subspace rhapsody that much. Okay and other other episodes should have been above subspace
rhapsody. Tomorrow and tomorrow and tomorrow I agree I would have put that above subspace
rhapsody. It does not surprise me that the two meme episode to the ones that ended up on the
ballot though. They're great meme episodes but they're definitely meme episodes. All right shall we
jump straight to fan categories? We shan't talk about fan cast on account of how we have a
conflict of interest because we're in it. And we love all the fan cast. We love all of the fan casts
you should listen to all of them and vote for the one you thought was the best. And I mean
I recuse myself from saying anything about fan artist. I feel like fan artists we also have issues
fanzine and I'm now feeling slightly fretful because I am not sure whether Black Nerd,
what Black Nerd problems put into the Hugo package because I went to their website and found it
quite hard to read the content on the website because of the website design. I mean Black Nerd
problems is laid out as what it is which is a magazine so it's not like there's an issue I can
download. So I think I basically had, I think I ignored the stuff in the voter pack and kind of
went back and scrawled back to stuff from 2023 and kind of read the selection of it. It's pretty fun.
Nice. I like the full lid where Alistair Stuart covers a huge range of stuff that interests him I
guess but it does seem very kind of all sorts of things in a reviews fanzine.
A bit like this podcast. Maybe this episode maybe. I think Journey Planet did very strong work last
year and good issues on a very on a wide range of subjects so and it is also a fanzine in actual
issues and I like that because I'm old but my and and I have a conflict of interest for idea
because I am in it but but my vote will probably go to idea despite that because I liked everything
else in it quite a lot as well. Cool. Yeah I think it's a very solid list I feel I should mention that
nerds of a feather do some great reviewing and unofficial Hugo book club, vlog do some great posts
as well. I think we probably said that last year but I mean I think from this list I would be happy
with any of those winning. I think I will say I recommended a website on various discords a few
weeks ago called Rascal. Rascal is doing a pledge drive and when you like look at the little snippet
that comes up on discord it says that they are "voicy" which is an adjective which basically means the
the voice of the journalist comes through very strongly and I think black nerd problems I enjoy
because I think it is a voicey. Reading the articles like I really feel like an idea for what it would
be like to talk to that author sort of in the pub or in the bar and I really like that. I particularly
liked the spider verse. That is a good adjective and voicey is one of the things I am looking for in
fanzines in general that I think fanzines are a good place for it that professional magazines are
much less likely to have that feature and one of the things you the point about doing community
content is that it is off the community and and your verse is very important. Yeah I think we are
kind of reinventing new journalism or whatever it is that became new games journalism which became
the idea that you can kind of use more kind of personal anecdotes and so on so I think this
is not a new idea. I really hate the adjective "voicy" for some reason. That's fair. I think I just to
say Rascal started with the TTRPG new games manifesto so I think they are explicitly aiming for that
in their output. Yeah and it's all over the place right lots of journalism which like you know how
much should you have of the personal and how much should you have of the journalistic and what is
your balance and fanzines a good example of that but maybe that's a discussion for another time.
"Fan-reya, I'm gonna vote for Bit of Corella because I still love midnight belts." God I laughed
such a kind of like cynical laugh at today's midnight pals, midnight society. I'm not sure I've
read today's. Although what about "Posey Parker?" Yeah the punchline of that one is just like
it's funny but painful. Yeah I do not disagree. Also it's got the word "beevagina" as in
my totally normal party of beevagina women which yeah it's quite funny. Ah she's so good. Yeah I'm
gonna put her at the top of my ballot. They're all good fan writers Brent. I find this category
very difficult to decide on. I like aspects of what all of these writers do. I don't really know how
I'm gonna rank them yet. I know. I do work from bottom but I do basically do the top half of the
ballot before the bottom half so these are the ones that I've done less reading on so far. We do
have another three weeks as we know over three weeks as we record before the deadline listeners
which is why we have not all finished the reading but we are not going to have another chance to
record if we want to get this out to you the listener. You do not have over three weeks John you have
13 days. Boo. Just saying. Shh. Let's shh. Load star understanding. Yeah I've not I've read one of
the load stars. I liked it a great deal but I've not read the others. I've read two. Which ones?
Guess which one I liked most John. And "Reveler" by Francis Hardink. Correct. What I was gonna say
what author do I like nearly as much as Adrian Tchaikovsky and it is obviously Francis Hardink.
Fair enough. And "Reveler" is pretty good. I don't think it's like her top book but you know
second best Francis Hardink so pretty good. I did enjoy Liberty's daughter but not as much
and I will probably read one or two of the others or at least I will try. I really liked to
shape a dragon's breath because it made me so angry about Indigenous peoples and the way they
are treated in a way that I thoroughly enjoyed and also I read it because it crosses off
north of the astounding and north of the load star in one book. Life hack. Smart. Yeah I've
also nothing to say on the sound links I haven't read enough yet. I'm trying. I have read all of
them except for M.X. Liu. Mm hmm. Well done. I will say the Sunidin did not gel.
I put the Sunidin down halfway through with a plan to come back to it after the deadline
but I was finding it very slow going. I, Jang, I've read I Am I and I've read the short story that
was in on Cami and although it was pretty good. Hannah Kaina I'm reading God Killer and God Killer
was a blessed relief because it was just solid and I really needed a book that wasn't like incredibly
incredibly anger inducing or incredibly slow. Like I just I'm reading it the pages go quick.
I like it a lot. It's very good. Not going to put her at the top but I would happily read more by
that author and Jiren Jade Zhao. I remember liking Iron Widow a great deal. It has been a while since
I read it but I do remember thinking it was cool. At the moment I'm probably putting
Monaco Black Goose at the top because I really liked to shape a dragon's breath.
But I need to read the rest. I need to finish the Kaina and I need to read and I need to read
something by MX Lou before I can vote competently. But I'm almost there. I've just need to read another
one, two, three, four, five, six books. Making the to heat the
brierly voting competence threshold. In that that's to hit that in both loads that are
understanding and to vote in most of the others. Anything else on the Hugo Awards?
No that was a lot.
[Music]
So we're going to do picks because you've not heard enough of our opinions about science fiction
this episode and I'm going to pick Star Wars Jedi Survivor, the adventures of a good boy and his
owner. The good boy is called BD1 and he runs around and he slots into things and he goes
"brom" and he's great and there's also a ginger guy and the ginger guy is pretty okay and has a
lightsaber and there's also "do you play as the droid? Do you play as the droid?"
You play as them and they are a team but more you play as as Cal. It's good. It's basically
they looked at the first game and they went "how do we improve every single aspect of this game in
the second game?" and then they did and that is the sort of sequel I like. It is bigger, it has more
open world bits which feel better, it has a more compelling story, it has better villains,
it's just real good. One of the best Star Wars but I never picked Jedi Fallen Order and I will say
it's also a blessed relief because before these games there hadn't been a single player Star Wars
game that was worth playing for at least a decade and that depends how you define the Star Wars game
force unleashed which I thought was pretty bad so it's just nice to have good Star Wars video
games again for what I would argue is the first time in a very long time and that is lovely.
"What's your ranking of the best game category John?"
Chance of Sinard, Alan Wake 2, Star Wars Jedi Survivor, Dredge, Baldur's Gate 3. I have got to
the bit of Baldur's Gate 3 where there's a game that's fun though so that's nice.
"So yes one of the problems I have with Baldur's Gate 3 is that every so often I would be in combat
and I would go "God I remember so much of this sort of thing from a very long time ago both in
tabletop role playing and in video games and I didn't like it then and I don't."
"Liz how are you ranking the video games?"
"Chance of Sinard and then Dredge."
"There's a much shorter list than mine."
"I mean the thing is that I have not played the Zelda game yet and I cannot play Alan Wake 2,
Baldur's Gate 3 or Star Wars Jedi Survivor because I have not bought a PlayStation 5."
"Ah that is true, that is fair."
"So that is a bit of an issue. I would like to play Baldur's Gate 3 and Alan Wake sounds good and I
played a bit of Star Wars Jedi for an order and it was quite fun but none of them are quite the
thing that makes me get a PlayStation 5." "Baldur's Gate 3 plays on your Mac?"
"Yeah it's my work Mac. I'm not installing Baldur's Gate 3 on it. I also don't want to play it on a
Mac where it's shit. I want to play it on a PlayStation where it actually runs. I don't want to play it
at five frames per second."
"That might also be a problem I'm having with it."
"I will also say that although I initially thought that Alice in Complaint about loading screens
was a Mac specific one, fuck me the loading screens take a long time on a PlayStation 5.
What is going on? The SSD is designed to be like lightning and I'm waiting like over a minute
for the neck and I'm like what is happening? Like I was and it's really annoying. I would
make more sense to me if I was loading a game and it wasn't in memory but when I'm reloading the
same combat again why is that not cached? Like why does that take a long time? It is baffling.
I don't want to sound it. At someone with ADHD it's very annoying."
"Things I don't care about in games as a rule extensive texture scenery voice acting."
"But like Horizon Zero Dawn didn't have this level of loading screen."
"The voice acting in video games is great."
"I click through most of it so I read what's at the bottom of the screen and I go right well
I could wait 20 minutes while I have this conversation or I could click onto the next thing.
My life is too short. I read books guys.
Not if I'm an architect or you don't apparently. I read some books."
"I don't think the voice acting is what makes the loading take a long time."
"I think there's just a lot of stuff right?"
"There's definitely a lot of stuff."
"It loads a huge area and you could go anywhere and there are like 97 different things you could
do and it loads them all in while you're waiting rather than micro loading it as you're playing the
game. I do not understand this but you know somebody in our audience will understand why
why we have these long loading screens."
"Do either of you want to do pics?"
"No I'm good. I want to have my dinner."
"I've played a lot more animal well and and I've also played Quite a bit of Cinka Pouse
which I think I've probably also previously picked but if not I can't really pick three video games
at a row can I?"
"There's no lore against it."
"I can pick Cinka Pouse if you like."
"What is Cinka Pouse?"
Cinka Pouse is probably well in my view but not everybody's view the best of the roguelikes by
Michael Bro who is an independent game designer who game designers love but lots of other people
find a bit strange and it is a game in which you are a sorcerer and you have five ones and you
are on a five by five grid with five monsters and you do not know what any of the ones do and
you find out what the ones do by firing them at things and noting down what happens or other
game notes are down for you and to make it better. At the time when he designed it Bro was living
in Portugal and he was learning Portuguese so the entire game text is in Portuguese
and people got very angry about this but of course you know deciphering what the game text is telling
you is part of the puzzle you could perfectly well work it out without knowing any Portuguese
and after some years of this game existing and people whining about the fact that it was only
in Portuguese asking for translation he did in fact translate the entire game into German
so it's now available in Portuguese German and it is fabulous it is so good.
So you play through five screens with your five unknown ones and then you finish that game
and you start a new game holding the points you've got from that game so that you can play
multiple games in a row and there is so much depth to this and so much interest in it but it is
just another extremely nerdy roguelike of the salt that I like so you know you can get it on
IOS and some other things but I play it on IOS. Fabulous game one of the people I play it with
us by daughter so we come round and we put the turn it over to the news to the big screen and then
we sit there arguing about what we should do next and what is the most likely thing to avoid us
being killed by a frog again. Way! Essentially if you like extremely technical nerdy roguelikes
you should definitely play this game but you probably already have. Turns out I already own
Cinco Paus because I bought the bundle for Rachel, Justice and Equality on itch and it was in that
bundle. This often happens in the games good. That was the Ulta. podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me.
[Music]
I'm just going for my Alan Keys. The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin
MacLeod in Competec.com used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.