Close parenthesis.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very
119th episode of Octothorpe, a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 26th of September
2024. I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty
We have a I would argue a plethora of letters of comment this episode
And we're gonna start with Alison not the Alison wrote in but Alison
You know Neil Harrison wrote in and said I don't think Alison ever closes the
Paranthetical that she opens when she mentions the Cambridge fantasy society
She says open parenthesis and never says closed parenthesis
So all of the rest of the episode is within an enclosed left parenthesis
I would appreciate it if the next episode starts with Alison saying closed parenthesis
And I believe I have provided an appropriate close parenthesis. Yep
I kind of drop open loops in conversation and writing all of the time and
Because I'm not a computer programmer. I don't worry too much about this or a copy editor. Sorry Claire
Yes, I respect Neil's attention to detail
Yeah, cuz I was like what parenthesis where when and I listened to the episode in theory twice
So we're gonna group our letters of comment by theme this episode listeners
So we've just had the parenthesis theme and now we're gonna talk about Hugo's
More specifically our winning one and Liz will introduce that yes
So we're still very excited about that, but we also got a lot of letters about that
So I'm gonna start with a letter from Christopher J Garcia
Who wrote his disjointed thoughts from the Trader Joe's parking lot? Thank you Chris
And he says octa-thop wins
Thank You Chris and that it sounds like an incredible convention
He also says it's highly possible that Alison could win Hugo's for best fanzining Glasgow in LA and then best fancast in Glasgow in LA
Which would be quite exciting. Hmm. Yeah, yes
Sentence not sound at all enthused by this
This prospect I wouldn't like that to be a reason why anyone nominated us. I think that's my point
I don't think I don't think if we end up on the LA ballot
Which we may or may not and it would be an honor if we were I don't think that would be the primary reason
I'm not worried
I've seen a lot of Hugo ballot or a lot of Hugo
Long lists and I believe that people nominate things for Hugo's for all sorts of daft reasons
And this would not surprise me the slutter on the subject of winning a Hugo and the open shore wrote to us on
Mastodon and said regarding Liz and the photograph his recollection is that Liz insisted that he hold the Hugo award
Despite him saying that it really should be her holding it. So yes, it's lovely photo
But the optics are misleading so Liz you've been called out
And then he goes on to say on the subject of the award themselves
I saw John for the first time since Worldcon last week at the Newcastle first Thursday listeners and asked him
How long did it take you to stop touching it every day in what I now recognize as typical Cox and humor?
He replied I think it's getting on 22 years now Andy. I did say that. Gosh you are young aren't you?
I am young. Yes, and also he agrees with Liz about the parties
I think I think Alison also thought this which was that the party atmosphere was not
Good due to the size of the venue, but that is not Hugo related
But thank you very much for hanging Andy. I can't remember all if I made Andy hold the Hugo
It's possible I had begun to become bored of carrying it around with me
I can mention was like no you hold it for bit, you know like it to baby or something
They're heavy also like babies. They're probably not quite actually I don't know if they're heavier than babies
listeners right in does anyone have a baby and a Hugo so we had a letter from Peri-Ann Laurie
She also said congratulations, and we're not gonna say everyone said congratulations
So we probably shouldn't mention it every time I couldn't congratulate you in person because I was at the bus was
Business meeting during the live podcast. I'm so sorry Peri-Ann
I have been going to parent business meeting for over 30 years initially it was entertaining
but now I fear I'm just a masochist and
She says we can't have people
Spending 20 hours in the business meeting during the world gone and if we have members who attend virtually
But have no say in the governance
How can we call them members and it is clear to me that we now have an 18th century governance system for a 21st century?
Organization some of us have been batting around ideas on the disc on a discourse server
Is this the same as the existing bus for this school server?
Is this a different one many of which have been referred to a new committee co-chaired by far and Colin?
So perhaps we'll have some solutions for next year's meeting to discuss
Yes, so is this the same discord server or different different school server? I get confused. I don't know
We hope hopefully
Peri-Ann will write in and tell us I assume is the same one, but I'm not sure I went to a whole 45 minutes of business meeting
But due to technical hitches, there was no actual business going on. So I just tried to jump. Yes, that did happen
What what particularly were you going to see?
Oh, just you know see if it was interesting
Well, I had the hope they might get to something I was interested in in the first like hour
But as it is we didn't get anywhere. So I in fact it was a full-on hope
We wouldn't have gotten you on to any business in the first hour anyway. It was in my hotel. I drank coffee
Yes, exactly right. It was like round the corner from breakfast
So it wasn't hard to drop in on the way to the convention. Okay. Do you want to do Renee Liz?
So we Renee wrote as an email about recusal and we said
Police send us your your loud opinions on that and she did send us our loud opinions and I'm gonna paraphrase him as best I can
But really opinion is there is a place for considered permanent recusal from an award or category for professionals
But they're not sold on it for fan categories for fans who have not professionals
Essentially because it's reviewing and critiquing work in s of fandom that isn't being done elsewhere and being done from a fan only
Perspective and to a permanent recusal kind of remove your voice from that conversation and she worries that if more and more
Non-professionals permanently recuse themselves then we end up in a place where like these voices are absent from the category rather than being a space
Where old and new voices can mingle? Yeah, I think that is a pretty interesting opinion
Actually that there's kind of a difference between professionals who are often getting recognition in lots of places and fans
And this may be the place where non-professionals in the fan categories. This is one of the few places they get visibility
I mean, I do like that nerds of a feather kind of previously one recuse themselves
And other people won for a few years and then nerds of a feather came back and went again
I thought quite like that so I think that's maybe the model I would be aiming for take a year off
Don't get that kind of bounce of name recognition in the next year or the next couple years
But then when you feel like it you can put yourself back into the back into the ring if you want to we didn't say last time
But it does sound from what John was saying about it would be an honor to be on the ballot in
Los Angeles that we are planning to recuse for a year rather than longer. Don't know who quite decided I did say if I
Think that is reasonable. I think this leads
nicely on to a letter from Meg MacDonald who says long-time this in the first time writer and then notes texts to John
Don't count which you know is gutting to hear Meg
writes very
eloquently
This is tricky right because it's bad form to write read out good reviews on the podcast. So hmm
She says she thinks some of the work we've done so far in 2024 in discussing incredibly fraught issues
And the passion nuance and kindness and integrity with which we have dealt with them deserve to be recognized on the ballot and heard by far more people
She then goes on to say I feel like you've I did not eat that from a collective conversation
When it all rolls back for next year and that feels like a shame in a waste
so I think that kind of echoes the sentiment that
It's all about a conversation and taking those voices away can be a negative as well as a positive
She then wrapped up with ps Liz needs far more airtime
Which yes fair enough we we are aware. Sorry Liz. I want to pick up a little on this
I think one of the things we want to do is
surface a lot of the other good podcasts over the next year that are doing things if not exactly like us because
Obviously, there's nothing that's exactly like us but are actually in this vanished space and
Contributing things to the community and I think this is something that that I feel pretty strongly about that one of the great advantages of producing
Is so that you can highlight other people who are doing really good work?
We're still in the conversation Meg
You can still listen to us even if we're not the Hugo nominated podcast doctor thought next year
And I mean that's it I would hope that the visibility that we get we're getting that visibility anyway from having one Hugo win
And I'm not sure a second would add a huge amount because everyone knows that the Hugo win is life-changing
I mean if anyone comes and breaks into a house. We've got something to bludgeon them to death with now
No, that's a bit over the top. I mean we can't keep that in. Oh, that's going in Liz. There's no doubt in my mind
That's that that not only is it going in is the episode title. It's a bit violent. Go on
There are three of us at this house. We have three bludgeoning tools
It does occur to me that therefore you do need to want to count how you got two hands dual wheeled hugoes
But what only one of them is my bludgeoning hand
So if you've ever bludgeoned any one with your offhand please write it open brackets not you Chris
I am very torn because this is gonna be like exhibit a
If my like forthcoming trial
So full disclosure when we won I was like we should just recuse forever and like we've got you I've got a Hugo
Frog to Thorpe it'll always be my Hugo Frog to Thorpe
very honored and I've been I feel very valued and recognized and and all of those things and I'm like do I
Need to be someone who has all of these feelings again. I thought that bubbles to the surface after
Reading Megs letter is that I had not quite thought about the reverse and and this is an
Sentiment there was echoed in the Facebook comments, which was people like seeing us when they you go
and I hadn't really figured any of that part of the
Process into my thinking on the matter
And I think I need to think about that some more and so I I would I thank Meg for hanging because it made me think quite hard about
my own
Motivations for like what I wanted from everything and that was really useful. So yeah, thank you Meg
And then we have put links so we have put links in the show notes to the Facebook comments on the episodes where people
congratulated us on winning Hugo. I will put everyone who congratulated us. I will try and put their name in the show notes
Apologies and advance for the people I miss out who I will definitely miss out. So Sandra Bond wrote us a little poem
I shall recite there's a wulk on the held up in Glasgow where the you go isn't such things are done
And I listen Scott and Liz Batty and John Chox and we're chuffed because they won. Thank you Sandra
Hey
It was very lovely. That's very sweet. Thank you. Thank you, Sandra
Oct thought poetry corner. Oh, yes at that poem is at least three lines
So I want to put out such as his Hugo eligible in 2025 for shadowing alright
So that's enough about he goes for a while
We'll probably remind you about he'll go in again and again until you're totally fed up
We also got lots of other things in the last episode or the one before we talked about
Worldcon
Information
Basically, we talked about the info desk about the lack of maps about not having a paper newsletter and so on
And it turns out people have strong opinions on these and they rolled into us
We did get a letter from Alan Fleming who was the area head for the info team at the Glasgow will come
So thank you Alan for writing in and be very nice
He says another member of staff said to me that every contest turns into an info desk
And I think that is actually true
Basically, if you have some people who look like they might know something or are semi-official
Then yeah, you basically turn into an info desk whether you like it or not
So that's probably true
But yeah, possibly we need like a big sort of a great big red arrow saying info here or something
And he did say that they needed more signage
But the cost of hanging banners in a conference center is high
Yes
He basically limited to like little mini mini signs or things on stands or whatever
I wonder if we could have taken the big display board near the escalators and turned that into giant arrow and put an info desk
Like right there. I want to pick coming on info desk location because as people may remember
I ran info desk at intersection in
1995 done, and I don't remember that so
That's why I said it
One of the things about Alan's thoughts on info desk is that they are not at all dissimilar from my thoughts having done it in 1995
But we did stick it in the concourse roughly
Where the registration desk was this year with a big sign on it saying info desk as a result
We took most of the information. We also set it up
24 hours earlier than we were expected to set it up because it was obvious that all of the other convention spaces
Were unable to do any jobs because they were overrun with people asking for simple information
so on a related note about fans asking for help on anything and everything from anyone who have to be sitting behind a desk
That's what Peter Sullivan says. He had the online equivalent of this in the online team had an email help list for online queries
Which kind of had to be emailed because if you can't figure out how to get onto the discord or any other
kind of world-con space then you probably need to be by email and
They got a few people who clearly thought it was just a general convention help desk email
And they had to pass them on to the right division
He says I do remember one email asking where the courtesy bus from their hotel to the convention site was leaving from and
Yeah, that's probably an email where you want to say yes
I will pass you on to facilities for that one so that facilities can say hmm. What courtesy bus?
Yep, the convention never said anything about courtesy bosses, right?
I think there was like one little van that ran around the the SEC site
But I think generally if the con haven't said anything about bosses
There's no buses guys stop buses. I think that SEC had a bus
But yeah, I'm not sure
When I've done social media for a convention, I've discovered that the social media
channels also get treated as a general help desk
Information channel and I found that about half of the queries I was getting were kind of instantly answerable with
Lines that we already had and the other this is not Glasgow. This is different conventions and the other half were
All of the form I need now to write a message to the person who job this is to say
Please get your finger out and make some progress on this topic because we are getting queries about it
And a lot of those ones were of the form I have written to X at ycom.com
Six times and had no response and I understand you're all volunteers, but it's been however many weeks
I've also been on the other end of that transaction. I shouldn't say I'm I'm kind of some paragon of con running or anything like that
But I think anything that's got any sort of generalness about it is going to get a load of queries and then Doug talks about
maps and
He says many more physical maps posted but he were here would have been appropriate and
The online program should have had hyped links for the description of where the item was with perhaps another link to a map
Maybe even with the location marked we did talk about
Andrew January's map project last episode
But I think that is the sort of thing that Andrew would quite like to be able to do
I'm terribly worried. I'm putting lots of words in Andrew's mouth
So Andrew if you disagree with anything I've said here, please do write in and and set the record straight
But I believe that is that is one of the goals
He has wouldn't it be great if you clicked on the link and it popped up a little map on your phone with a little blob mark
You were here using your GPS and then a little like thing that rooted you to the program room like a Disney
Hi, Andrew GPS GPS not great in conference. I just put in principle. That's that's not impossible
So they do do this at Disney and it is great. So like it is hard, but I have seen it done like
Obviously Disney is mostly outdoors. So I don't know it's also chock full of
Long-range receivers because they were gonna do more stuff with their magic band things
So there's gonna be a lot more kind of stuff that happened when it detected you in locations
But I think they basically didn't end implementing a lot
But as part of that project they blanketed the whole thing in Wi-Fi and put in a lot of receivers
So that might be helping them with that. I don't know it could do that actually
I never use that functionality. I used it to get to Oga's cantina
Liz on the first day and then I knew the way to Oga's cantina and I did not need the math anymore because I am
predictable we also got some comments pertaining to
our discussion of communications and that kind of thing last episode
First one I'll read is from Duncan or Master Dom
Who talked about the discord and he says he thinks engagement during program items was lower than Duncan is used to at Easter cons
And he he didn't feel like it was quite the roundy back channel
He has grown used to and that's interesting because the discord was very active
But did you guys find that it was less active for program than you've become accustomed to I?
Was surprised for my program items how little
Interaction engagement there was on discord. There were a lot of people attending the convention
Online and I was expecting that to be reflected in quite a lot of commentary on the items
But but there was very little apart from one item where I think there was quite a lot of comment on
Discord, but we may be a trained alistairist to do that now
Yeah, no fair
Liz you made a face
Well, I was only on octa thought and up to the pad a lot of comments on discord
So I don't know what it was like for anyone else's items
Maybe people were just being present and in the moment
I'm also going to guess that there was quite a high ratio of people there in person to people watching
Online and of course that every room is screamed
It would be interesting to know if rooms that were streamed did actually get more comments than rooms that were not streamed
Oh, yeah
I wonder if we have any listeners who could pull out that kind of data
Oh, it is just pull out the number of the number of comments for each item and then I will do the other bit Andrew
I mean, I mean whoever it might be I love that
I have a large data project that I'm going to work with somebody who's not on the pod to do and
They're definitely up for this. This sounds like the sort of thing that could progress in the new vancom.dev server
So Chris Garcia says he doesn't like discord, but that's because he's a ramen lovely Chris
But he also is yeah, we get a few of I've had a few comments like that from in various places from people who don't like discord
It's how you're it's how you're configuring it guys
Especially the people who like oh, I used to love you's letter the 80s, but I can't get the hang of discord
It's so much better
I think we should allow that there are people who don't like discord because not because they're not configuring it correctly
But possibly because the way we are setting up our servers and so on leaves a conversation happening in a way that doesn't work for them
I would say to Chris have you tried opening 17 different discord windows and reading them all at once because that might work for you
on that topic
Alison did try to listen to the podcast while simultaneously listening to the cricket
But concluded that she is not Garcia enough to be able to pull it off and had to listen to one at a time like a normal person
Can't edit it. I mean I did more or less managed to listen to the podcast while watching the cricket
I'm getting better Chris. I may need training. Yeah, but quick. It's pretty slow
There's not really a lot happening so you can probably listen to a big chunk of podcasts before anything happens
Yeah, that's why cricket is great. Yeah, no
I think I think it is tricky right because I'm sure there are I think there are probably people who would like discord if discord
Less manic and I think there are things we can do to set up servers and that's one of the things I mentioned last
Episode, but I think there are also probably people who just don't like discord
So you know it's a broad church. No one's really a wrong man
I love you all listeners except for you. You know who you are
Chris also commented on paper
He says paper is a good thing if you've got a period where there is boredom
Which seems on the face of it to rule out Glasgow because it was many things but boring was not one of them
He went to a conference where there were no newsletters in con areas, but in the cafe
They had them on every table
So that is interesting
But then he goes on to say the funny thing is we've lost a huge amount of online data printed things are not as likely to go missing long term
Paper is significantly more stable and I thought I was really interesting because Chris for those who don't know is a curator of
Things and yeah, we hadn't really talked about the preservation aspect and the historical aspect very much
And I thought it was a good point. Thank you Chris
I mean this is this is one of the
benefits of things in in kind of lumpy form like
PDFs and podcasts that they do kind of sit around for for future archivists
You know, I mean if we go offline
I think the chances that one of our listeners has carefully downloaded every episode and stored them somewhere a very high
Weird weird though. This is to imagine. I don't think I have a full copy of any
Podcast I listen to listeners right in and also phalact.org if you if you want to if you want to plot an octave
Did I say blocked right didn't mean blocked if you want an octave archive let us know I really rarely deleted stuff from my phone
So I've probably got them all somewhere, but I know John also has them all so I don't need a copy people on Facebook commented
Saying so Costanza Hoffman said that her impression is less was it all too serious?
Which fair enough in order to get humor arises from having a bunch of people
Who bounce off each other and generate humor if you're trying to do something on a shoestring
Staff at the last minute. That's one of the things it's harder to set up and make happen
I think let let this format develop also
There's there's a sorts of humor that's that are gonna work in a paper newsletter
But if you kind of shove them on screen as an item on a rotating slideshow might not work or might
Shock somebody out of context or so you'd have to you would have to think quite hard about how you did it
It's not trivial to see how you would make it funny memes or memes
Yes memes
Oh memes. I mean memes
Convention related memes are good overheard at the convention things out of you know out quotes out of context that that they'd almost certainly work really well
Jan Van Tint wrote in and said all newsletters. Yeah, I'm a fan of paper to the point out of helping out with the printing
Jan won the Doc Wear award in no small part because of his huge services to printed newsletters over a
number of years
But he says having pick up points for paper news
Preferably spiked with a plot to like humor helps those who know about it
He notes that the newsletter Glasgow was on the website on the discord
Which for him worked better than putting it on screens?
I think I think I think I agree with both of those comments
Tammy Coxon wrote in to say about death of emails the role was originated by Ben
Yellow and he did it for most of the conventions where it's happened
I was unaware of this because when I worked on lonkon 3 it was flick
but
I think that is an aberration and it has mostly been bent and it must be an enormous amount of work
So we were talking last episode about you know
Recruiting for that role, but I do wonder whether that would have actually been quite
Difficult, so yes, thank you very much for writing in Tammy because I've been I'd been unaware of that
I think having a lot of emails is less oppressive if you don't have to do anything with them
I think it is it is a great role for someone who
Really really wants to know everything about the world come because bear in mind that you will see everything
So if you are the sort of person who lives for knowing exactly how the sausage is made you will see
Every single ground up, you know who should do it Liz
Alison you have just described Alison
Yeah, if you if you like to every single tiny bit of the behind the scenes of the world con
But without the obligation to do things about most of the emails then it is a great role now
That is the person I am I mean I read not quite but nearly every messenger on the Glasgow server without really causing me any
Stress or grief no, I mean I'm being slightly I'm being slightly jockey
But I actually do think this might very much be Alison's skill set and so I'm just dropping Alison in it live on the pod for anyone listening from Seattle
Really is that that's that's fine because my actual going forward major action plan in my life is to take things like that
Put them on a list called who died and made you someone in honor of death lies there
I might have mentioned this on the podcast before and I can put on that right in live time
volunteer to take on the death of
Emails role there we go and it could just sit on that list until one day I go
Oh, yes, this is the year when I have 2000
Unallocated hours to give to this but yeah, no, I am very very I mean one of my skill sets is
Processing a lot of information very very quickly and identifying which people need to do which thing
So let's move on to discussing the letters we got about the wuss first business meeting
So we haven't discussed the wuss first business meeting yet listeners, but we'll discuss people's discussion of it
So we heard from various people about the wuss first business meeting so june young wrote in and said congratulations for a
He go in thank you very much to june
She also mentions to Alison that she met Alison when Alison was in Wellington this year
June was at the Wellington ferry luggage collection with a sign that had her name on it. Yes, sorry June June June very
Graciously
Yeah, she's Simon Littons partner and she helped me a huge about in all sorts of ways
And I might have given her a terrible infection and I'm very sorry June mentions that she is listening from
Episode 1
So she started listening casually and then she went back right to the beginning and she's up to episode 34
Hope you're enjoying those June
I think if you're going to listen from episode 1 doing it after having listened to a couple of the modern ones is the way forward
But yes, it's great for when she's doing dishwashing or housework. Yes, that is that is the glory of podcast
She said she had to listen to the episode where you went over the Glasgow wuss first business meeting items twice
Thanks for covering this I am in awe of anyone who listened to that twice
That is 140 minutes of us talking about the business meeting that is dare de-occation
I mean or if anyone who listened to it wants frankly
Yeah, but June also mentioned she was one of the 30 people who turned up physically to the wuss first
Business meeting in conzeland to defer all of the agenda items to the next year
Wuss first really needs to make allowances in the event of health and safety reasons preventing an onsite meeting from occurring
Thank you very much for being in top top letter not just because I agreed with it. We also heard from
Christopher J. Garcia
We have from Chris we've heard from Chris several times and basically he's gonna keep popping up through this episode
He says I do wish we had virtual meetings throughout the year and the door was slightly open for it
I think now we may get to this in a later episode
But the door was slightly open to it by someone's a beating a proposal to have lots of virtual meetings throughout the year
And I think it did not pass
Probably because it's added extremely complicated Chris also said he would love to see more advisory votes
Though I fear that end up like the one this year or a sizable chunk voting in favor of the indie film Hugo was ignored by the business meeting
Go figure
That's tricky, right because lots of people in the advisory votes said they would be in favor of an indie film Hugo
But then the people who are at the business meeting were like no, we all think this is terrible
And so I mean I think it's good to have the advisory votes
but what is the mechanism we are suggesting for bringing into the business meeting?
I mean, this is a advisory vote and
The problem is that the people who are actually in the build this business meeting is still gonna make their own minds up
And obviously if one in the business meeting was pretty strongly against it
So I mean I think it does speak to that proposal that no one has that the business meeting to vote it to speak in favor of it
So why'd also I will just know it did lose the advisory vote. It was a vote that was lost and
I sympathize with the fact that if you're on the losing side it must suck as someone who voted remain but
It
That's how votes work
It's true the way we're if it won the advisory vote in a slam dunk or something and then the business meeting like nope
Yeah, I would have been weirder
But also I think the problem with the one Glasgow chose to to make the example of was that I'm not
I think I probably am against an indie film Hugo as a as a sort of concept
But I'm definitely against it as it was written in the vote that would have taken it into the Constitution
Even if it was an idea I was passionately in favor of the one that was actually passed for ratification was was bad in
TDS ways that would have made it difficult to actually implement. So I am glad it was struck down
So it is a bit of an odd one from that perspective
I guess I feel bad because in any other year that wasn't Chengdu that amendment would have been basically gently passed back for some more
Revisions before being brought for ratification and pretty sure yeah, you know
It was very unfortunate that it it got rat if it got put through in the first year and there were a few things that
Probably shouldn't have been Nicholas White has made a long post about the 2024 consultative vote and a report on
As as in his role as Hugo administrator with pointy ears
And about about how they felt it went and what they've
What they've learned from it and I will put a link I'll put a link in the show notes if anyone is interested
Chris also says I am pretty sure John sounds like Martin Freeman looked circa 2001. Thanks Chris
I think I'm just gonna put a picture of Martin Freeman from 2001 into our show notes and leave it there
No sense at all. I mean done
What doesn't make sense about it other opinions on what John sounds like a welcome please write it
Yeah, it could have said that he sounds like what Martin Freeman looks like now
I a 50 year old man
So I think it's probably more flattering to John that he suggests that maybe where Martin Freeman was 30 he
Looks like John sounds although I've got to say Martin Freeman looks pretty good now anyway true
Raj says on Mastodon that lizz is the one that doesn't sound like she looks but he didn't verify in which way
I
Think it's like just be getting weird now. Yeah. Yeah. No, I mean I don't disagree
DC on the subject of
The business meeting said thank you for the inoculation against any sense that they should go to the business meeting
We restored them to sanity Duncan and Raj. I think
Basically concurred. So yes, we we were thanked for our service in business meeting methadone
And this is a shame because I I do quite want people to go to the business meeting
I went to much for the business meeting at Shicon. It didn't unduly
Disturb my enjoyment of the rest of the convention and it was all pretty interesting
It's only that there was 20 hours this year
Yeah, I don't I don't want to discourage people from going to the business meeting if they're interested in that sort of thing
No, but I don't think we were um, I don't think we were very negative about business being
I think we gave it a pretty good sort of relatively righ
Shake and if listeners felt it sounded awful
I would also say if it sounds awful
I recommend not going because I don't want it to spoil people's enjoyment of a world con out of a sense of duty
I do think it's a shame this year that it was in a different
Location to the rest of com. I understand why but it means it's very hard to drop in for an hour without missing a load of other stuff
Whereas I think if people could drop in for an hour
Then that's the best way to know if you will enjoy something like the business meeting but being a 10 minute walk away
May that more difficult? I am going to slightly push back on that and say that there were half hour
gaps between program items
So you could basically attend the business meeting for a program slot and not miss a huge amount of the rest was gone
Just one program slot
Which you could then pick up on catch up. I speak as someone who went to the business meeting for a program slot in order to vote against something
But but I will say again
I don't blame anyone who chose not to and this is mostly why I want it to happen separately from the world con
So I very sincerely do not think that
People prioritizing their enjoyment of the event they have spent usually for for digits sums of money to attend is a bad thing
You know if it was on zoom and you had a free weekend it would be a different conversation
But Glasgow cost me an excess of a thousand pounds and I wasn't spending a single minute of that convention doing anything
I did not want to do and I think that is the right call go in peace listeners
Gareth Kavanagh listened to that episode and said that he was a BM nerd and it was a good episode
Thank you Gareth and I even sinner wrote in to say it was something that appealed to him as a civil servant and trade union rep
Which yeah, I can see that
Indeed so we did hear from a couple more people about the business meeting
so we hit from Ed Moreland on blue sky and
Ed's heated that two people they know have now listened to their first full episode of octoth up after the Hugo win
And the good news is only one of them decided to start with the full breakdown of the business meeting agenda again
We are sorry
The person Laurie Laurie Burchall who was the listener they have replied and they have now listened to other episodes and are enjoying our game
Recommendation, so thank you very much for that. We're sorry about the business meeting, but we hope you enjoyed it
We did hear about stats membership attendance stats does anyone want to go into that?
There's just two master bombs. Yes, because I can call you wrong, right?
We touched briefly on the subject of
Worldcon attendance numbers
and whether Glasgow was bigger than some other world cons or not and I believe it was John
Who said that they thought the Helsinki figures might be
Invlated because they had not
De-duplicated the day memberships and we heard from Tero on
Mastodon who has it on good authority that they were de-duplicated
So we're pretty sure that those Helsinki numbers are
Accurate. Thank you very much. Terrell all right, then then I'll go for it. We also
Discussed the number of first world con attendees. We thought they were and we heard from
our analyt on
Mastodon who thinks that the number of first world con goers was probably
Underestimated on account of how that rate was more expensive than the Scottish resident rate
So if you were a first-time attendee from Scotland
You would probably pick the Scottish resident rate and not be counting those stats and that might also be why they ran out of first world
Con ribbons because if they bought like based on first world con numbers plus a bit more
And then it turns out there are a ton of Scottish first world con members that they hadn't counted that might explain why they ran out
So thank you very much for that. Yeah, no, that was interesting. I hadn't thought of that, but it makes a lot of sense
So Raj wrote in on a lock prepsode one one four
Which was when we were talking about the Hugo finalists
John he says he agrees with me about Alex Woodens translations. He struggled much more with theirs than with the others
Which yes fair enough. Thank you Raj. I'm glad it wasn't just me
Disagrees with Liz about the definition of romantic see I think fantasy romance is set on our world can definitely be part of the genre
and
noted of best series the Tricovsky is the only one I've not read anything off and I don't mind too much because being Tricovsky
There'll be another trilogy due a week on Tuesday. So yeah, I'm reading some proper full-on romantic
Listeners look forward for my opinions in a later episode Adrian Shikovsky apparently writes books faster than I read books, which is a
problem
I have read another agent. I cost key. I mean I don't know where to pick it just because I've picked on many other agent
Ticosky
Previously look right. You know my opinion on this Liz pick early pick often
Oh, you were my opinion is there's no such thing as too much Adrian Shikovsky
Right to say he's done Hugo reading for the first time in a decade and doing it even semi-controncibly is exhausting
How do you keep up with it every year?
And my answer is a sense of guilt and anxiety Raj. I just do some of it
I mean I did the novels and some of the shorts, but not all of them
But I mean now that we do the novels on the podcast that gives me some incentive to actually read them. I
Read fast and I like free stuff
That second bit is definitely true we also heard again from our on master don
Saying the cute entertainment people deserve so much credit
And that we should watch the cute data extravaganza on replay as it's not just very amusing for people like that
And I am a person who likes that. They also actually include some insight into queuing etc
Okay, I do like my stats with the side of insight
So I will have to go and prioritize that one
Do you want to plug back to the back to our futures here?
So this is probably a great time to remind people that John and I along with
Klebrile Emily and Andrew January and Meg Donald are running a small online convention for people who were members of
Glasgow
2024 that is attending members or online members whether or not you actually attended where you can watch the catch up and hang out with us
all weekend which sounds like a fun thing to do and
We'll put a link in the show notes for how you can express interest and it is a chance on the first third of November to
Catch up with that catch up that you've been forgetting to catch up with even though catch up will be available
Till the end of the year is that enough plagues for catch up John?
Hey guys, we heard you like to catch up it will be good
We will be there and there will be program and if you like either of those things it will be a good time
We also heard from a lot of people lots of whom gave us congratulations many of whom gave us interesting
comments and food for thought we
Unfortunately can't read and react to all of them
But I have put a list of them all in the show notes and we thank all of them and if I have missed you out
I'm very sorry, but please let me know and I will add you in really we should have a scrolling YouTube
Thread with sombre music for our black Christ, okay?
Okay, sorry, maybe that was another magic. I will stop
So this is a sad and potentially
triggering discussion listeners, so there's a content warning for sexual assault in this part of the podcast but
The news that Neil Gaiman has credible allegations of sexual assault against him came out
Shortly before we didn't have a chance to record a bunch of normal episodes
So we haven't really discussed it obviously
I'm very sad about this because I'm a huge fan of his art
but apparently not the man himself and
We have put links in the show notes to various bits and bobs on this if you'd like to eat more
But yeah, I don't have much to add to all of the reporting that's already happened
So do go and do go and read that yes, and what's come up very recently is
That they have canceled a couple of potential adaptations and also they've put a pause on
Filming of the third season of good omens
So it's now kind of not clear when that will continue or who will be in charge
Yeah, and I think I just hope that these revelations coming out about Neil Gaiman one
There are a lot of people who were big fans of his and he has always been a person who I think people have
Quite intense parasocial relationships with he's not someone I've ever met or interacted with but I know you know
I know there are people I know who are friends of his and I know there are people
I know who have always kind of admired him as a greater and for how how much he puts himself out there and supports different causes
Online and seems to be very friendly with his fans and obviously that's now taken on a darker tone
And I hope anyone who was a big fan of his is dealing okay with the news and that anyone whose
Lively hoods are also tied to him. There are a lot of people who work on
TV and film adaptations are a lot of people who are working on good omens whose jobs have presumably now been put on pause and we hope this all
Resolve successfully. I will note that Gaiman is also basically deploying to make any public comment at all since July
I'm not entirely sure if there's any way in which this could resolve successfully
I mean it will resolve at some point
I know a lot of people have close personal friends of Gaiman and I know and a lot of people who are outraged by this story and some of those
People are the same people, you know, and I don't know any more than the reporting
I mean and I know that I guess it's my job to comment on podcasts
But some of these stories absolutely horrified me out
You know and and they had a degree of plausibility about them as well that I think and there's a lot of them
Future world cons
There are gonna be some more world con listeners one of them is gonna be in Seattle and
Allison foreshadowed a thing that they're doing I did
Seattle is having a poetry Hugo a well off poetry Hugo some people are like well
There should be a pur to hugo all the time, but I think that's it's got the same problem that some of the other suggestions have
Which is that the field is is large and and the Hugo voters aren't necessarily paying attention to it
But we will see how it goes next year the poem has to be at least three lines long so
if you write a haiku and you can you can be eligible for the
poetry Hugo
That seems like quite a low bar for for winning a hugo so it would better be a very very good
Hiku readers right in and we will have the octa for
Hugo eligible haiku corner next episode. Oh, that's some point in the future
As you see Sandra wrote a sub home that is eligible. There are many many other really solid science fiction poems
For example, not for this what year but in the past Harry Josephine Giles is Deep Wheel Ocadia, which won
The arthsea clock award would be the sort of thing that you would expect mate might turn up on
a best poetry ballot so I am looking forward to seeing what people come up with and
If you're thinking if you read a lot of science fiction poetry and you are thinking of nominating in this category
Please write in and tell us what good science fiction poetry we should be reading and also they are going to have a
Judged film festival, which is something I think we have mentioned on the pod as a good idea
But I think this is a great idea
I really do think that it is
Something that I think I'd love to see more world cons do I do appreciate it must be a hell of a lot of work
And I'm not saying I think every world cons should do it
I do also wonder slightly about the fact that they're doing it
Given the LA is the next one because I assume LA might want to do things with a film as well, but I think this is really good
I'm curious to see how much of it is available for people who are not there on site or for catch up
But it will be good
Yeah, no, I think this is a spectacular idea and we definitely did plug it
So hopefully they got the idea from us, but if it was a separate idea that seems good too
Now I'm looking I'm excited about both of those
But I may be as I may be an online member of Seattle. I may not be there in person so
Because it's expensive to go to Seattle and I want to know that I'm gonna have good time
I think the poetry Hugo is interesting because what I've mostly seen
Being discussed after they announced this is people going where do I find good science fiction poetry then?
So there might be a chance to bring a lot of venues to people's attention
And I do hope we get some kind of slightly more
substantial in in length and content than haiku
nominees for it, but I'm not a regular reader of poetry. So I really have very
little to suggest for this one. It's gonna be interesting
Film festivals, I think it's been a while since we had a a film
Program at a world con and doing it as a full kind of judge film festival where you can submit your films and everything
It sounds like a really neat idea and I hope it goes well for them
Yeah, me too
But it'd be interesting to know if there are actually a substantial number of people attending world cons who want to spend their time
Watching films, which unless they are sort of short films probably requires like a substantial investment of time
And I know when I go to world cons generally there's other stuff I want to be doing more than watching a film
I might be able to watch at some other point. So that's kind of my
You know argument against why you might want to do that, but we will we will see how it goes
I support them like doing things that other world cons have not done for a while and trying some new stuff
That's how we discover what works and what doesn't. Yeah
I think that in the past we used to have a lot of films at conventions
Historically and we did it because you couldn't just go and get films right they they weren't available
And and so having rare science fiction films at conventions was always quite a big draw for people
What the case is now is that there's a lot of independent films that don't have distribution
And it is actually very hard to see those films and getting them into a film festival that's connected to the world con
Is a way for film fans to see them and everyone at a world con has
Choices to make about how they're going to spend their time. So some people like to sit in the business meeting all weekend
I understand but some people will want definitely already at world cons a film
Will want to go to this film festival because we will need sharks to see films that they aren't likely to be able to see elsewhere
There are many many science fiction short films that are
Almost impossible for most people to watch so so I think yeah having those available
Especially like because it's definitely true that most of the blockbusters are
Relatively easily watched because even if they don't get official releases in your territory that often available through other means
But john remember how hard it was to watch gods in the minus one
Yep
And it's a testament to its quality that it's almost got onto the hugo ballot despite it being almost impossible to watch
Yeah, I I guess the thing is whether does sticking this onto a world con mean that a lot of world con go is go
Oh, I can see some films. I'll do it mean you end it with sort of a short film festival which exists inside the world con
Almost exclusively viewed by people who have chosen to come for the kind of film festival nature
I think this is a case in which I don't mind either of those happening
But also like most other things it will be somewhere in the middle. I for example
I don't normally play games very much at conventions because I think well I could play those games at other times
But lots of people like to play games
As part of what they do at the convention as some people like to play games is all of what they do at convention
And I think i'd fill kiss another thing where people do it
Some of the time or all of the time and I think that's fine
both those sorts of
Fans are very welcome at the world con and and some of them will
And film fans will do that come in those two types
I'm sure and I could definitely see that there'll be films where people go
Well, I'm not generally going to see a film festival at this convention
But I'm very excited to see that particular film and I will go and see that one
Because one film seems not unreasonable for five days of the world con
But yeah, I think this is great. Um on the subject of
LA LA con five looks good
It was seated at the Glasgow world con and received 450 out of the 530 votes cast
And so yeah, well done to LA. We discussed it. I think a little bit of the live episode
I think I went gosh. Well, look at their guests aren't they good because they are and you need lots of other stuff to be a good
Well, con but you know, they're guests are good
Also, it's in Anaheim and I have other interests maybe in Anaheim
Um, so Tel Aviv in 2027
We speculated on a previous episode that we weren't sure whether that was still a going concern
But they had a table at Glasgow. So um, so I guess it is
And if anyone would like to go to a 2027 world con in Tel Aviv
More power to you
Seems very strange to me, but you know takes all kinds
I think it'll have a lot of americans at it
I mean, I I think there were you know, there was a lot of discussion about having an a world con in israel
Even before
Essentially the entirety of israel was a place where the government advises you not to travel to it
Yeah
I have two things to say about the Brisbane in 2028 bid
One is that they have changed their dates in order to align with an eclipse
Well to slightly offset an eclipse
Well, they're not going to be in uh late august anymore. They are going to be in july
So that you can go and visit the solar eclipse and then go to the world con
Which yeah, I mean it seems like a
Good strategy except it might backfire if it turns out it's incredibly expensive to go to Brisbane at that time
Because of the eclipse. I'm actually looked up the path of the solar eclipse in 2028. I'm just doing that. I mean australia's
australia's a big place and this this is the zone of totality goes along a lot of place a lot of australia here
Yes, but no like
No offense to australians, but it goes across the zone of you know
The zone of totality does go across a big chunk of australia where not a lot of people live
And I think this one is only in visible from australia, New Zealand
Which is another thing right? It's not like that this one is visible from you know
The u.s and the uk and australia this one is one that you can only see from australia and New Zealand
immediately it goes through sindy not through britsman
But I think it's going to be interesting to know if this makes it incredibly expensive to fly there considering most people would probably want to fly into
Sydney
Because I suspect there's a lot more flights to sydney than there are to britsman
You may need to sort your dates because most people will go for a longer trip if they're going to australia
I would recommend going to australia for a longer trip
So you you might need to tweak your travel times a little bit. It may make some things more expensive
I think if you avoid the eclipse your
Trip will probably not be a great deal more expensive
But if you do not avoid the eclipse obviously there's a kind of eclipse premium on
On anywhere to stay anywhere in an eclipse zone of totality
I also say that they have pre-support at the levels of lobster and pineapple. Whoa, can I get both?
Well, as we've established
Alison is susceptible to cool rewards and fun names for pre-support
So basically everyone should be calling their pre-support moves or something so you can sell one exclusively to it exclusively to alison
I recommend setting it around maybe 250 dollars
You can also be
What is often known as a friend of the bid but in Brisbane you can be a mate or a young mate or a great mate
If you want to give them even more money, which is
Pretty good
Yeah, those are great. Those are great names. I love it
amazing
Mate of the bid is fun and it's 250 dollars
so
Yeah, 250 australian dollars, which is like
Less than an American dollar like two
It's like twice the American dollar here. It's just peanuts to space. Look
So yeah, good stuff
And then just before we do picks
We should mention that there is a
Phanak history zoom on the secret history of plotter which will star Steve Davis zoom asan
Alison Scott and mike scott and
If one of them is familiar it is because it is Alison and it will have happened just before this episode drops due to a slight
Cock up on the announcing on the plugging things we're doing front
But you can see it on the phanak.org youtube channel
which we will put in the show notes and
And a reminder that the fan act.org youtube channel is
eligible for best fan cast and I think they do
fabulous work in surfacing
People who've got some understanding of bits of fan history and and learning about it by
Basically asking them what actually went down and the people going oh, I don't really remember because i'm 89
So I this is why plotter is trying to do this before we get too old to remember
Sensible there were nine
Nine entities in the plot to capal and so far the only one of them who has died was the cat
So, you know, that's a good time to be doing these things rather than when you go when you start going
Oh, it would be nice to hear from from so-and-so, but they're dead now
Oh
Kido key so picks we must be nearly there now picks picks picks. Does do you have a pick? Uh, yeah, I do a pick
I was just deciding
I'm gonna pick control
Which is a video game from 2019 because I am up to date with the state of modern video games and so on
Um, it's like an actually adventure game. I believe it is connected to the allen weight games
Which I haven't played well, basically it's a sort of action adventure where you
Go into the federal bureau of control, which is what seems like a regular if dated office building and turns out to contain
Multitudes because the federal bureau of control is the one that looks after basically all the supernatural happenings in the world
And there's a whole plot going on but mostly you play as someone with supernatural powers and
a gun with
Mostly infinite ammo
And you go around battling the mysterious creatures who've been taken over by a supernatural entity called the hiss
So you spend a lot of time
You know shooting enemies, but you can also throw things at them lift them up throw them around
Mind to draw them and so on so you get to combine like having supernatural powers and having a gun
and
All the time you are kind of picking up little like found letters and so on
That are like case reports and notes and memos between people and files that kind of fill in all the backstory of this supernatural world
And occasionally you have to do things like oh to get to this place
You have to go through the motel and you flick a light switch
And you end up in a mysterious motel and have to figure out how to find your way through this motel puzzle in order to open up
The next bit of the world and it's just it's pretty nicely done
The graphics are pretty good some of the kind of like surface textures
I mean i'm not someone who normally goes oh surface textures
But there's some bits of sort of like where you're supposed to be walking over like marble surfaces, which are pretty cool
You get to speak to these supernatural entities
Who used your world words a lot in a kind of cool way
And like you go around corners and there's always like mysterious whispering and things like that and then like a big
Monster will come out that you have to kill before it explodes in your face and it's pretty good
Nice
It is yes, it is in the same universe as allan week i think um but but yeah
I've heard of it. I have not played it. I kind of on my list ever since enjoying
allan week two so um so yeah interesting pick
Frank's Liz
So my pick is chaos, which is a tv show on netflix, which is currently my um
most valuable streaming service given all the games as well
um
I don't this seems very strange to me because I've I've not net generally been a big netflix person, but here we go um chaos is a
human accommodate drama
where the
gods the greek gods are
Running the world and the world is kind of slightly like contemporary world
But probably is a little bit more like a 90s world
Because in particular there are no mobile phones that being made more straightforward to make the plot work
It stars jeff goldbloom as Zeus and he has been very jeff goldbloomish and that that's kind of gives you a sense of the
flavor and there are
All sorts of interesting people as many of the gods and other characters from greek mythology their stories are
Slightly changed they're changed enough so that you never quite know what is going on
But if you're familiar with greek myths, you will be familiar with a lot of the things going on here
And I we are finding it very funny and I haven't quite finished it and I suspect when I do finish it
I'll be like oh well
Some of the big reveal stuff is not quite as exciting as it might have been but the actual
The journey has been jolly entertaining and very amusing
There is a very amusing underworld
Um, which is all shown in black and white
Um, so that you know when you're in the underworld billy piper is casandra
um
And nobody believes so which is probably a a shame because she's generally right that being casandra
And it's just generally a great and enjoyable show that will not trouble you too much
I understand that the more you know about greek myths the more you're getting out of this
So people who are have been paying attention all the way along
Like it even more and people who just kind of vaguely remember reading a couple of books on myths in school
um kind of
Like it but but it's it's got a lot of deep cut jokes for the for the real fans
Um, and it's very funny really liking it
And a lot of people are talking about it. So I'm sorry
I'm just kind of joining a crowd of a lot of people who are talking about it. No, it's good
Finger on the pulse
It's eight episodes
I'm gonna pick alien rombulous
It's an imperfect film. I don't think like you know, it's not a stone cold classic
But it is it is okay
And god knows I think
Having the first alien movie that's okay that has been released in my lifetime is worthy of celebration
So alien and aliens are obviously very great and they came out in 1979 1986 and then in 2024
We finally have a alien movie that will not make you
Want to throw it in the sea after you've seen it, which is lovely
So I will say I think one of the things the movie does really well is it has characters in it who make terrible decisions
But it shows you enough of their trauma for it to be very obvious while they're why they're making the terrible decisions
And so although characters do make objectively the wrong decision in several points
You never doubt that that person would have made that decision in that context, which I think is a very good
um
Piece of character work. I will say I enjoyed it much more than a spanya
Who thought it was okay until the ending which I think it's fair to say she detested
So, um, I think it's a great movie. I think a lot of people in it are are pretty good
But I think david johnson who plays the android is
Absolutely superlative. Um, I hope he is in many more things
He has been in other things previously that I am not familiar with
Um, but I'm hoping he goes on to to many other things because um
I really liked him. It's very good. It's also got Ian home in it, which is a bit strange
So you know how you make me feel old sometimes
I'm not intending to read
So fun fact I snuck into alien which was an r-rated movie a couple of days before my 14th birthday
And I think it might be the traumatic experience that put me off or up for life
But I have seen alien and alien since I would agree that they were very good
But have not not felt a strong urge to see other films in the series
I mean pre-theuses unmittigated wank
Also
Not in the cinema because this is I don't want if I have to go and shut the movie off or go and hide behind the sofa for half
An hour or whatever
I don't want to do that in a cinema or I want to do it in the comfort of my own home entirely firm
And I think I also like movies like this sort of smaller screen where they're less scary
Oh, it is very it was very scary. Okay. I wouldn't I would not say it was that scary
I think there are horror films which are way scarier because they are
Going for it. This is just like occasionally an alien is going to pop up, but you know an alien is going to pop up
So yeah, I enjoyed it. I can't I can't quantify like how much did I enjoy it because it's an alien film
And I think that does add a few bits, but actually I think if it was just a
We have taken a bunch of young people and they are on a spaceship with some mysterious enemies
and there's a
Oh an android of dubious loyalties and so on
I probably still quite enjoy it and you could also cut off the last 50 minutes, which are nonsense
But otherwise, yeah, I really enjoyed it
That was the OptiThought podcast and it's goodbye for me. It's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me
*Music*
Do you want to read one of them and then I'll do another one? I could do can I?
Well, I was taught a lot and we don't want to give people too much lids because it might be more than they can handle
Well, that's the aftershoes. That's good
The theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud and competec.com
Used under a creative Collins attribution 4.0 license
This podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]