There's no good word for a video podcast, that is vlog.
Just take video, just take video, let's just take video.
Anyway, I think you might find something that's fun in all of that.
*snort*
Baby, figures crossed.
Alternative episode title.
Hello everyone and welcome to the 26th episode of the Octa Thought podcast.
This episode will be going out on the 4th of March 2021 and I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
And we have some letters of comment for you all this week.
So firstly, I'm going to start with a letter of comment from Roman Ozanski who
thought we did not particularly fairly treat the NK jemisin novel,
the city we became, because we said things about it but none of us have read it.
So I've got two reactions to this which is firstly, all I was doing was reporting that my wife
didn't think it was great and that does affect my opinions on whether or not I'm probably going
to read a book. If other people do not take opinions from their loved ones then that's fine.
But I do. Secondly, I have started reading the book and although I am enjoying it,
there have been multiple times so far when I've been reading it and I've read a sentence and I've
been like, "Oh, that's not what I was imagining. I've clearly missed a bit."
And I've gone back several pages to be like, "Where did she establish this thing that's happening?"
And she just hasn't. And so it is, I'm finding it incredibly jarring in a way that I haven't found
any of her previous works. I'm wondering whether that's something other people encountered when
they read it. But yeah, like so there's a pipe where someone at a bike shop starts talking to the
main character but at no point has it been established that he's standing near a bike shop.
And so it's just like the bike attendant starts talking, it's like, "What bike attendant? Where did
they come from? Why are they there? Where are their bikes?" And you just weren't any before and
so you weren't imagining any bikes and there's nothing there are bikes and you have to readjust
the scene in your head. And I am finding that very odd. But since last time I also read,
Piranese, which is excellent, but feels more like a long novella than a short novel, I would say.
And I've also read the third murder bot novella in preparation for reading the murder bot novel,
which I believe is eligible this year. And I also thoroughly enjoyed that.
"Didn't you also read another book?"
I read "Space Between Worlds" by Mackiah Johnson. I can't remember if I said I had read that last
time because time is an illusion and reading time w so. But no, the space between worlds is amazing.
I thoroughly enjoyed it. I liked it better than Piranese, I think. It and the vanished birds are
definitely the two best books I've read so far that have been published in 2020. I will be
enthusiastically nominating both. And if the jemmison stays at the same quality as it has done so far,
I suspect I will like it less than those two. But it might be that it picks up later in the
book because I'm only about a quarter of the way throughout the moment.
I think I am more sympathetic to Roman's point than you are, partly because I am not
bothered about what your wife thinks about books. But also because I tried to think, well,
what if I was listening to Roman on a podcast about a book? Are you really, really liked? And he
hadn't read and he didn't really say anything that I spanned it. So he, I think he has a point
there, but we also said a bit more. I think we also sort of segued into a discussion of
fix-ups and our general not-in-termment of fix-up novels without really being clear about
fix-ups or the fact that we've gone on to a kind of more general topic.
Claire Braley of Croydon, right? I'd rather people thought I drink too much than that I have poor
taste in reading. And I'm sure nobody would think either of those two things, Claire.
I know for a fact that Claire has liked books that other people didn't like on occasion. So,
how do you respond to these accusations? Claire, please write in with your next letter of
comment and tell us about the subjectivity of art. I actually sent us a very long letter,
so thank you very much, but we're not going to read out all of it because we have many topics
to cover today. But she did also write us some poetry for Liz. I think Liz has to read out the
poetry. Claire says, "I'm surprised that Flanders and Swan didn't conclude geckos in their best
jury. I'm slightly worried at this point. This is me not Claire, that I'm now going to have to explain
to John who Flanders and Swan were." "It is a poem especially for me."
Octa-thorpe Poetry Corner. "I'm sliding down the wall and not liking it at all. When did you get
that anti-gecko spray? I'm just here in your abode to catch the latest episode of the Octa-thorpe
podcast, as we say. Back in the skirting board till you're ready to record, I've been hoping you
might mention me on air. I've been a long-term fan and I don't deserve this ban, so I'm writing
in to say that it's not fair. I only made a chirp when I was startled by that burp and you've had
much bigger problems with the sound. But if I develop fur and then try to learn to purr, is there any
chance you'll let me stick around?" "Oh." "Thank you, Claire. I will also say that my anti-gecko spray
is apparently a nasty smell that they don't like and so they won't go near it. The idea is it stops
from coming in because you put a kind of smell they don't like you don't like. It doesn't actually
make them slide down the wall like anti-climb pain to anything, although that would be very funny."
"While I was distinct to that poem, I realised I have to do an art for this podcast, which is
basically some geckos on a wall that says this wall has been treated with anti-gecko spray."
"Good poem, thank you, Claire." "Yes, thank you, Claire. I enjoyed the return of poetry con."
"Yay." "Other people can also join in by sending us poetry." "Yes, we want Chris Garcia to send us a poem.
On the subject of Chris Garcia, he writes that he is in fact a multitasker. It's rare that he doesn't
have two films running in the selection process, a podcast and a conversation with a child."
"Hang on, yeah this is for this episode, yeah cool. Time is blurring together."
"Because unlike Chris, John is not a multitasker."
"I mean I'm not even a single tasker, so there's the hat."
"Right now he's listening to Eltathorp watching wrestling and listening to John Paul
retail the plot from the regeneration to the fifth doctor. He's not seen the episode and thus he's
fairly certain he's getting the details slightly wrong about how the poor patrol intervened.
Although I do thoroughly look forward to the doctor who poor patrol crossover."
"Yeah, I mean that sounds good."
"Yeah, I don't have any, I'd love to have some witty follow-up but I literally
I know nothing about poor patrol."
"That's fair, he spells Alison name wrong. He's going to be an easier con, which is a great alternate
name for EasterCon, which I love and he's eaten chicken mole pancakes. So you know I'm going to
have to give that a try at some point."
"I think I mean chicken mole pancakes don't you?"
"Yes, true. And finally, so and Rosin says that when Alison last episode mentioned that she had
Stephen and Jonathan wandering around and suspects that neither Stephen nor Jonathan sleeps on Alison's
desk. Alison, can you confirm or deny?" "Um, cannot confirm or deny that."
"Okay, weird. And and does not log any books, films, TV series, cats crochet or podcasts.
But she did then follow that up with a tweet to us in which she showed us her big old traditional
notebook of reading, which has is basically just a list of handwritten agatha-christianophils."
"Hah, isn't that a log?"
"I mean, yes, this is what she says in her tweet. She says, 'I made a fallacious claim. I do log
books, but only series and mainly tried to stop myself buying electronic duplicates,
which doesn't always work.' And I replied and said, 'That is also the main reason I log
books and movies to stop myself buying duplicates and also it doesn't always work.'
"I'm trying to be in trial at this site for Andrew's secret code. I presume which is like
P for Poirot maybe?" "Yeah, that would make sense. Yeah, murder on the Orient and express
as a P so that that seems consistent." "Okay, and then the ends might be
Marple." "Octothorp, the podcast of codebreaking." "Oh yeah, because I see there's a P that's
labelled 'Hercu Poirot' as Christmas, so yeah. But then there's lots of Ks and As, so
Andrew, please send us a follow-up tweet to explain your secret code of Agatha-Christies."
So my favourite line from Andrew's log is the following line. N or M?
"T and T K." "I leave it as an exercise for the listener to work out which part is the book title,
which part is the tag and which part is the andg notation." "I write my journal in whole
sentences by and large with very few abbreviations of any kind and I still go back in years later
and go, 'What on earth was this about?' 'I don't think I'd do very well with
vigorous abbreviations. I've just been completely lost.' And I also, one of the nice things about
middle age is that it doesn't really matter whether you forget that you've already read
things and read them again because you can enjoy them just as much the second time
whilst your memory is completely shot. Yay! And also mentions that she has volunteered for
EasterCon and this is a sort of segue you see. I've never really used them before but I'm
told they can be particularly effective. So EasterCon peeps. It has been three weeks since the last
EasterCon weekly video. But there's only one, all right, like there's only been one video so far,
right? So it's not really a weekly video. No, no, there were two videos. There is a video that says
we will be releasing weekly videos full of content telling you what's going on with convention
and then within a week of that they released a video with zero content saying everything was
under control. So, yes, they said they were going to do a podcast and we are still eagerly waiting
for episode two. They said they were going to do a podcast but when they think about a podcast is
that there are audio's not videos, I'm like tilting up with Mills here. Possibly. I think...
Well, I mean the other alternative is we call it a vodcast and no one wants that.
Yes, that's true. What I think we're trying to say is that some of us want to plan for our Easter
weekend and in particular some of us are in a position where we've been asked to do tasks by
the EasterCon and like for example, I'm a deal... I'm planning to sell stuff at EasterCon and
in order to trade I want to know how the dealer's room is going to work and what we get so far is
kind of note saying the dealer's room is going to be amazing but we won't tell you what's happening
yet or what you need to do or how you need to prepare and that is becoming difficult because we
don't have very long left and I've also been asked to do a job by the EasterCon and I've kind of gone
well yes in principle but until I know how your platform is working I really don't know what the
job you're asking me to do is going to look like in the context of a virtual convention. It's a job
that we do it though, we've done it regular conventions but it's obviously going to be different
at a virtual convention so that's all quite... we get into the stage where resolving that sort of
stuff along with everything else in our lives, not that there is anything else in our lives but
you know there we go. Within the amount of time we have left before Easter is becoming worrying
and difficult and if you say agree to do something you kind of would prefer to have the time and
space to do it really well and that's the thing that's worrying me at the moment.
In more positive news I've had my £20 refund from EasterCon for the difference between my attending
and my virtual membership and I immediately spent it on a board game so hurrah as promised
the coxing guarantee. It's the circulating economy. What board game did you spend it on John?
I spent it on a game called Star crossed so Star crossed is a game that is played with a
Jenga tower or an off-brand Jenga tower other brands are available mine is from John Lewis and
you play a couple who are engaging in some sort of conversation or some sort of scene and every
time you make an emotional bid you pull a block from the Jenga tower and when the Jenga tower falls
you must act on your emotions wherever your emotions have gotten to by that point in the game
and it sounds fascinating and I am excited to play it. Is this a two-player game? It is a two-player
game. Yeah so that's quite nice. Okay so I have a massive fondness for games that use the equipment
from other games. This is with my buy nothing hat. Games that assume that you will have things
like counters and dice and monopoly money and Jenga towers around your house. I specifically bought
a Jenga tower to play this and another game called Dread and I have no intent of ever using it to
actually play Jenga. Oh dear. Well Jenga's quite a good game. Oh I was gonna say have you played
fog of love. Fog of love. Yes I have played fog of love. This very much sounds like the Jenga.
This sounds like the love child of a game called Dread which is a horror RPG in which whenever you
take an action you pull a block from the tower and when the tower falls one of the players die
which is a very effective mechanic for running horror RPGs and there is a game called Fog of
Love which is another two-player game which revolves around relationships and exploring them
and that's based around a kind of card based almost legacy based mechanic and Starcross does
seem like the kind of interjection of the Venn diagram of those two games but I have played both
and they are both very good so I'm excited about Starcross. Yes I thought when you said it I was like
oh if John likes the sound of that he would love fog of love and you did love fog of love so it's
all good and I've said love about 17 times now. So and we have now done our obligatory gaming content.
Highmark. I do have something else to say about EasterCon which is that they announced in
that the dealers they are charging dealers 20 pounds to be a dealer but if you're a member
that's included so it's like a dealers table is included in membership but if you want
just be a dealer they are selling dealers only tickets which is oh that's interesting.
Kind of strange and it does make me worry that they that they do want me to spend eight hours a day
in in some kind of virtual space which is the thing that Canzeland tried to do and then roll
back on when they realized it wasn't a very sensible idea because it doesn't really work because you
want to be in other places at the same time but you can be in some other places at the same time
so it might work. They've also said dealers are going to get some stuff on program and they can do
literally anything they like with their program space except a reading which made me think two
things. The first was what if what if you're selling tarot cards? Are you allowed to do a reading then?
That's not that sort of reading but yeah so the first thing it made me think was well if I have
some program space to do anything I like in I'm good through a party because that's what I do
so there will be a Stoshurts party at the EasterCon and it will be an officially sanctioned bit of
program though they don't know it yet. Also it may be think oh I want to have a reading so there will
be a Stoshurts party and there will be a reading at it because we're explicitly not allowed to
so if you're an author and you'd like to read something at my Stoshurts party it should be
probably quite short like about ten minutes or you could do poetry poetry would be great so if
somebody if one of our listeners would like to write an EasterCon related poem that I can read
out at the Stoshurts party that would be fantastic. That does imply that EasterCon have a platform
of sufficient granularity that you can easily kind of confine the activity the dealers are able to do
to only their dealers room and program room and presumably not not the rest of the convention
otherwise everyone would be buying a 20-quid dealers membership. Possibly yeah. I mean I don't
I think you could trust science fiction fans by large to do the right thing. I think you can
but I think if someone says well the dealers are paying 20-quid to be dealers and they get
access to everything that I get access to except that I pay 50 quid then. Well I don't think they do
do though they they get access they get to be on a single program item in the same way that I think
they've announced that BSFA nominees will be able to attend the awards ceremony but they don't
generally have access to the convention. I think as this is point right like that that employs a
platform like we wouldn't have been able to do that up on graduation because as soon as a dealer
was in the bit where they could plug their wares they would have been able to access everything
else as well. You'd almost think that we would have an honest system and that science fiction
fans are by a large honourable. I think you could run a science fiction convention virtually with
the honest system. I think there's absolutely no requirement to have a physical paywall because
our members just they'll do what they know they should and a couple might not and and then we'll
just kind of ignore them or shame them as we do. But my mind so I think my point here is that
what I'm saying is either they have a either they have something which gates you off or basically
they're saying you can pay us 20 quid and they get exactly the same as you do for 50 quid
if you say if you're a dealer right. So basically they're giving dealers a reduced cost to incentivize
them to deal but then you're kind of like well what is the kind of value I get for the 30 quid.
Did sort of see what I'm getting at we know nothing about their platform but then I'm starting to
infer things based on how they are obviously setting up and running their convention which
makes me intrigued into how they have presumably solved this problem which I think most of the
conventions have not tried to do of having different classes of members with access to different things.
On the subject of Alison's poetry readings next episode will be the anniversary episode of
Octa Thorpe and I am announcing without having conferred with either of my co-hosts that we will
be publishing a poetry anthology as a zine so if you want to write poems for the anthology please
send them to the usual address. I'll lay out you don't have to do any work.
That's a smashing idea. That's why I announced it without discussing it with you.
I mean if I had something that would have to do any work then that's fine.
Remember clear hues and limericks guys if you don't think you're necessarily a natural poet.
Yep. There's still there's plenty of forms that have your name on it.
Since last time there has been a thing that happened in that Disc on 3 disinvited a guest of honour
and we have linked in our show notes to John Scalzi and his vague and official pronouncement
about a thing and the reason we have linked to that is because we may or may not have thoughts
about this but we are probably not going to go into detail about those thoughts due to the
potential forness of the said thoughts on the part of various of the co-hosts and so
we know it happened. We you know there are also people discussing it.
File 770 has had some excellent roundups. Go and engage with the rest of the fandom.
I did actually write something about this on my facebook which we can also put a link to
if for people who are my facebook friends and if you're not my facebook friend then you know
you could always friend me and say you listen to what to thought.
But what I was trying to do when I wrote my thing on facebook was essentially
do what Scalzi did but obviously I am much less of a good writer than he is and so I didn't
do this good job of it and so I fermented a row and one of the facebook does not let you turn
comments off and Scalzi very cleverly turned comments off on his pronouncement and his explanation for
why he turned comments off was because I probably want to use this again another time which I thought
was quite right to. I mean I think the point here is that presumably Scalzi had within a minute of
the announcement a bunch of people asking him on twitter when you're going to write something
about this and what's your opinion whereas I think we should say that no one has asked for our
opinion. It just feels a bit weird to be to be saying oh we're linking to Scalzi saying and we
feel the same way but we have not actually had a clamor of people asking for our opinions which
is what what you'd expect. You know it just it just feels slightly odd to me. It's just me.
[Music]
Pico-com. Oh Pico-com was great! I hit people with fish! I did not get their informed
consent first I just went to slap them with fish. So Pico-com happened last weekend as we record
which was the 21st of February and Pico-com was quite good. It was a discord and crowdcast I/O
convention. They had some panels which I went to a couple of and a pub quiz which was good but they
also had my personal highlights of the convention which was fish slapping. You could donate money
in order to receive Pico coins and you could spend your Pico coins on fish and then you could slap
people with a fish and there was also scavenger hunt which ate my day. It ate my entire Saturday
and it ate a Spaniard's entire Saturday too. We were on different teams for the Scam Phan.
It was very good. And it ate my entire Saturday and I learned how to sing barbershop by myself
on zoom a lot and then make videos of it and put it on youtube and they're all unlisted for
which I think the world can be very grateful and I learned a lot of other things. I was struck by
the number of items you needed for the scavenger hunt which were available within easy reach of my
computer downstairs which does slightly worrying me about it. I'm worried about the amount of
clutter I have in the house I think. Do we need to, will our audience understand why Pico
Con had fish slapping or do we need to explain the fish slapping? Liz give us the history lesson
because you weren't at this Pico Con but you've been to other Pico cons. I will say that Pico Con,
it must have been the first science fiction convention I ever went to. I think in 2003.
Wow and for as long as I've been going for some reason there is always an item on the program
which is labeled, what is it labeled now? Harmless fun. For as long as I've been going there's always
been an item on the program labeled Harmless fun and what Harmless fun turns out to be is
some representatives of ICSF and I think other university science fiction societies
basically hitting each other with fish. I don't know why. Never dared ask why but basically
you go out to the quad at some point and some people hit each other with fish. In January of
February in the UK which means it's probably not the most fun activity for the people who are
getting slapped with fish I would understand. I was going to say I listened to do it before
it became the fish slapper but presumably Pico Con started after you were a student and so you
never took part in the actual fish slapping. Okay so here's the really astonishing thing about Pico
Con which is this was Pico Con 38 automata which means that Pico Con actually started before I was
a student or just as I was a student but certainly before I was traveling to other science fiction
societies to a slapfish. It is certainly the sort of thing I might have done as a student and
thereafter. I think Paul Treadaway they weren't fish slapping at the very beginning I don't think.
Paul Treadaway thinks he was one of the very first fish slappers and he was obviously slapping for
cusses so yeah so I mean this is fan history we're actually doing fan history now so I know that a
lot of our listeners are into fan history but I think really Rob Hanson or Mark Plummer could
maybe do an exhaustive study of fish mutilation at British conventions. I went to Pico Con in 2007
which I believe is where I met Liz for the first time and I believe was my second or third convention
and it was a lot of fun and the fish slapping was very confusing and the scavenger hunt was good and
there was beer. There's also and they didn't make this virtual and I thought it was a bit of a shame
they'd also traditionally have the destruction of dodgy merchandise and I feel like that is something
we could take virtual. And also I've never really been because I understand it's funny but also it
always just seems a little bit wasteful but maybe that's just me being a stuck in the mud,
stick in the mud. Listeners write in and tell me whether I should have used a you or an I, sorry Liz.
It does raise quite a lot of money for charity though. They raised a thousand pounds for charity
pretty much entirely through selling electronic fish. A whale cost 100 Pico coins which meant you
had to donate 100 pounds to charity. At least three people bought whales which were horrifically
imbalanced. They only put the whale in as a joke. None of the other fish cost more than a couple of
quid. They were not expecting anybody to buy whales. So the fact they sold multiple whales is brilliant
and there was also a leaderboard for who had lost the most hit points because you go into
negative hit points so by the end someone had minus two thousand hit points. I like in particular
that they sold whales to whale. Yeah I was going to say that is particularly well named isn't it?
You can't we get the most money from? But other than that tell me more about pico coins. It was
discord and crowdcast. Crowdcast is a private you register and then you get a private link
so it can be paid or unpaid and you have a stream with with associated chat. It's fine. It seemed okay.
It had like the advantage over punctuation was that it all came off the same crowdcast link which
you got emailed so it meant that you weren't constantly having to find new YouTube links.
I think the disadvantage from punctuation was that I'm not sure crowdcast has like a TV app
that says widespread as YouTube's so if you wanted to watch it on your TV it would have been
very slightly harder but in general I think it was a slightly different set of trade-offs to
what we did with punctuation and but I think it went fine. I think it was a very similar model of
convention. I think their discord usage was probably better than punctuation. I think if we
have a run on another punctuation my inclination would be that we would want to talk to them about
perhaps poaching some of their people because they did have a lot of really cool stuff happening
on their discord in terms of like interactivity which I thought was really good. It felt exactly
like pico corn. It really did like it was the closest. I thought that was amazing and I don't
think anyone's quite managed that trick. It really I had just the same sense that I do
with a pico corn. There were author talks for me to ignore though in fact I did listen to one
and a half of them and then remember why I don't normally go to the author talks at pico and they
had the author panel and it just they just did the whole convention in that way and it was lovely.
Really had a fantastic time and I went to get my vaccination in the middle of it which you then
used in the scavenger hunt. So yeah I then used the vaccination as good news for the scavenger hunt
and then I think I might have been very dopey at the pub quiz. In fact I know I was very
dope. Apologies to all my team members. We came second in the pub quiz because I was I was super
dopey because I just had a vaccination. How did they run the pub quiz? They did it. You had a
table on discord and you were in voice chat on discord and then you had the quiz was happening
through a stream on Crowdcast. So it's like basically having it split across two different platforms
which I think worked really well and it's a good use for discord tables so when you said oh we
might not use discord tables for punctuation next time I was actually thinking well we might use
them for something just like that. Yes and that really neatly segues into our write up of punctuation
that we published over the last couple of days as we record and there will be links in the show
notes. So we've published two blog posts on the punctuation website. We published a financial
report and we published a feedback report and yeah there is there is three graphs split across
these two blog posts so graph fans like fill your boots. Yeah so to summarise the financial
report and feedback report it went pretty well. We had a lot of fun. We made quite a bit of money
for charity though if we thought about selling virtual quails we maybe have made some more
and we'll probably do it again sometime or not and we are holding some of the money in case we do
it again and if we don't do it again we'll give that money to charity in the same proportions as we
did before. So it's going to slightly more detail we took £985 and 20 Australian dollars so pretty
much £1000. We spent about 300 of that on holding the convention and we have about 700 pounds left
over which we're splitting as Alison described so our £5 member was plenty to cover any costs
that we incurred and in terms of what people thought of the convention most things were rated on average
are for or higher. There are a few things that weren't which I kind of go into more detail on
in the post that's linked in the show notes. Three other things that jump out are firstly people
didn't find the set a new table feature useful as Alison describes but it might be that if we had
a more targeted use for that that would change. People didn't like I think people thought the
virtual combatges were kind of neat but Jim really didn't think they were amazing and I think
we need to think about the effort to pay off ratio at future conventions and people didn't
think it was easy enough to or sorry people didn't like that we split the chat during panels between
YouTube and Discord and a lot of people said you just need to pick one but obviously when we talk
to people about which one was you pick they all disagreed so yes there is that and I go into
kind of some thinking about that in the post as well but yeah in general people rated us very
very strongly across most categories which was very gratifying and we're glad people enjoyed the
convention. I think the thing I took away from this is that running a virtual convention is really
extremely cheap a lot cheaper than I thought it would be actually I thought we might need more
zoom licenses and more little costs that we didn't have. I mean if you took out using poll
everywhere which as we say cost is quite a chunk of money and we only use for a few program items
you could probably run most of the convention for about 120 quid so if anyone is thinking of doing
a small virtual convention and you're thinking about what money you need to charge to do that
you can think about the fact if you're prepared to kind of put some money up front you might be able
to do it basically based off the tip chart or nothing at all. So that's what you fancy but there
were obviously you know depending on the size of the convention when there probably were places
we could have spent more money like we could have had guest savannah in which case we would then
want to reward them in some way that would cost us money. I mean we charge people to fire just
because less than a fire it doesn't really seem like a reasonable amount of money to even bother
collecting and I think then you just lose most of it in like processing charges and fees but it was
definitely more way more than we need to actually run a single convention on this model. No it's
it's worth pointing out that we spent with the exception of Paul Everworth we spent 120 pounds
on like the zoom and stream yard and wordpress site but we also spent 120 pounds on like payment
processing so like depending on how you do your payments you might be able to make that cheaper
but that was by far our biggest expense as it turns out but in terms of like if you can get like a
bunch of people just like pay power use some money and you can ignore the specter of payment
processing yeah 120 pounds is like you can do it for that with about 200 people which is pretty good
and discord cost us eight pounds and that was because we thought we might want more emoji than
we actually did so that was quite cheap so if you're wondering why does every convention use discord
is because it's so cheap like you don't understand how cheap it is to run a convention on discord
so cheap let's um let's do another con sometime yes washing my thought was hope etc yeah this
episode is episode 26 and next episode is the anniversary of octorp and so we thought we'd
wrap up this episode by doing a sort of year retrospective of what we've been doing to stay sane
in the apocalypse this might be very gloomy i'm not entirely sure i've stayed sane i think i may have
reassessed my sense of what sanity consists of and we we're kind of like this oh we might be
getting towards the end of all this now although we might not and they might be
de-restricting everything in the summer except that maybe it still won't be safe to do some of the
things you like to do and it's all um i've kind of got very used to living in a house and never going
out and doing things on computers i never seeing anyone and i kind of go how did i ever find time
to say spend a couple of hours traveling to a place in order to do a thing and then spend a
couple of hours traveling home again why would anyone do that so that's going to take some
readjustment i think i'm gonna be um one of those annoying pricks now uh so what have i been doing
to stay sane in the apocalypse well um i've learned spanish um so i've been doing spanish lessons
with my sister-in-law every week and i've been doing my duolingo i do not have the streak that
claire brianley has uh because no one does she's got a massive streak claire brianley is an amazing
streaker it's true she is an amazing streaker um how big is this streak because i'm i'm not 1,200
days oh it's quite big yep mine is two because i lost it to the day um it was about 100 one of the
things i've learned to lockdown is the time terrible at streaking um i was actually voted person most
likely in my year to streak through university campus when i was in sixth form true fact so um i
find your lingo streaks a bit tricky because like they come and they go and you can repair them and
there are little things you can get that protect them so i don't treat them anywhere near as seriously
as i treat the streaks that go away when you lose them and so i find that my duolingo streak is much
less good than my um exercise streak on my appwatch which is currently about a thousand and 20 days
so in lockdown i've also been i've also been exercising every day which is something i hadn't
been doing prior so i run three domes a week and i lift weights twice a week and i do apple fitness
plus so i do yoga or core strength or high intensity interval training uh and i do those in various
quantities through the week um so i am currently thinner than i have been since i left home um which
is quite good and i've never been fitter um i uh i've um i've learned how to write ios apps i've
been doing the hundred days of swift course uh by paul hudson i've been doing that every day and i'm
currently on a 56 day streak with that uh and so i've written some apps i wrote a duck with louis
calculator and i've written a alcohol intake tracker um which is quite fun and i've been doing
various things and it's and i've really enjoyed um learning kind of proper software development
um uh people who listen may know i'm a physicist by trade and i write python um mostly in my day job
but that's kind of more um uh procedural programming and so doing ui based programming has been a
really interesting uh shift um i've also been upping my reading um and i've been journaling both of
which i found very um restful and so yeah um i i really like the apocalypse and i know that makes
me an annoying prick but um i am i am flourishing uh i'm not sure if i'm sane but i'm not sure i was
sane before so yeah i don't know but sorry to everyone listening who wants to punch me now uh
when we're back in person feel free yeah that was quite annoying so each other i mean i can't
yeah that's one of the reasons why i've been less vocal about the stakes saying in the apocalypse
segments on the podcast because i'm like what i'm basically doing is doing enough things that i
don't have to think about how awful the world is and that is probably an unhealthy coping mechanism
but it manifests as an annoying prick yeah probably is yeah um have you considered writing a meta streak
app such that you can then log all your streaks on your meta streak app and get a streak of streaks
so yes liz i do indeed have that oh god i will post a link to it oh you've already got one oh geez
okay i'm sorry i'm so sorry um but this is why when fitness and stuff came up on the third row
uh discord i was like have you considered streaks and um i think uh i got the impression they don't
work for everyone but they very much work for me as it turns out yeah they didn't work for me at all
which is why i had to mute that discussion because it's all like have you tried streaks it's like
yes i have tried streaks they didn't work um i also know that you run your life by reminders
you can you don't need to put this on the podcast i know you run your life by reminders because
basically every week you say oh we can play al Capora this time next week then and i go i don't
know yet john and then you say are we gonna podcast this time next week and i say i don't know yet john
um we do the same time so if listeners can can be aware of this at 6 p.m on sundays i have a
reminder that says check calendar and so if you ever schedule anything for me during a week you
will receive a message from me at roughly 6 to 8 p.m on a sunday saying we still on because um i
have a reminder that tells me to do that and so i do it because i'm that person i i am not as good
with reminders and streaks and things of that kind as john but i have done my fair share of
annoying prick type things like i too am exercising every day um mostly in my house mostly using
um a VR headset and i have a very long list of exciting VR fitness games now i'm i wouldn't say
i've tried all of them but i have tried an enormous number of them and i am getting better at drawing
i think i realized that at the point where i was like i am going to paint vegetables every week that
my sana my grip on sanity might not be as good as it could be like it's the things i'm choosing to
do like like the other day i wrote a little nature notes post about how caroline and i had seen a tree
with mistletoe and um and and and a little bit about how mistletoe works which is very interesting
you see we have a conception of what our self is like we have a sense of self and we believe
that we carry on being the same person from day to day but i can kind of look at
allison a year ago or a bit more in a year ago and if you've said to me well in a year's time
nothing will be much worse about your life despite the fact that we will be in the middle of an
apocalypse but you will be interested in the mechanism by which mistletoe attract attaches
to its host tree i'll be like you know you're a crack dude and that's it so i feel like i
i feel like philosophically i may have changed personality very directly in in ways that unless
it's not necessarily good but yeah i can draw much better than i could a year ago no and i think i
think like to justify my annoying prickness these are all things that i've been intending to do
and have never got round two and i was like well if i don't do them now i'm never gonna and so there
was a kind of sense of um vague malaise and guilt that kind of nagged me into it um but it is also
it's just good to have my anxiety i have always found it easier to deal with my anxiety when i
keep myself busy and so um yeah well i mean i think learning to draw was definitely the
category of things i was hoping to get around to but my drawing is much better than it was
the i mean it's just much better than it was a year ago and the fitness stuff is good um i i'd
love to say i've lost a lot of weight but i haven't um roughly the same weight that i was at the start
but liz you have a disadvantage here in that you've been keeping sane in the apocalypse by living
in a place that is not really all that apocalyptic yeah i do have a strong advantage in that the it
turns out the apocalypse is not evenly distributed i was looking at uh it's a john bern murdock the
financial times journalist who does lots of nice data visualizations have it has like a visualization
of the whole pandemic with you know chunks for different parts of the world and basically it is
exactly the inversion of what i thought we were going to see a year ago in that all the majority
of cases have been in lino north america and then europe and then south american then you have these
little tiny bits for comparatively for you know africa and and east and south east asia um and if
you'd ask me a year ago i'm pretty sure that is exactly the opposite of who i thought would be most
prepared to uh whether a pandemic so that's quite interesting um but yeah it turns out i have been
doing okay by living in a place which is still having a pandemic but just controlling it very
well and for the most part with a few exceptions life has continued pretty much as normal as long
as you never want to leave the country uh the the main problem is that at some point i would
like leave the country uh and the the longer i'm here the the more i recognize that um you know
there are people i haven't seen for a long long time and at some point i think vaccination status is
going to be a big deal in whether people can move around freely and um i am not likely to be vaccinated
anytime soon so that's kind of my background is the apocalypse coming but otherwise yeah i
haven't really had to take on any special mechanisms for staying staying in the apocalypse because we
haven't really had one because if if i was still able to go outside and see my friends i would have
a lot less time in the evenings for all of the things i've described and i would probably be
in general happier um so i think i miss my friends a great deal and whenever i see photographs of
san francisco i tear up so like i'm clearly not thriving in every dimension um like i miss my
friends and i miss i miss i miss going to san francisco and like seeing friends there and i miss restaurants
and i miss sport yeah and i'm hopeful that will come back at some point but um but if i spend enough
time learning spanish and learning programming every day i don't think about it and then i don't get
sad this is a coping mechanism known as avoidance but for something that's essentially temporary um
it's actually okay to develop coping mechanisms that involve not thinking about the temporary
state of the first well now and this is the thing right i i can't do much to control this other
than staying in my house i'm wearing a mask when i have to go outside both of which i'm doing and
so spending too much time being sad about the fact that there are things that i don't like about how
my life is at the moment doesn't seem like a good use of my energy um so yeah i think i'm not
i'm not worried the way i'm coping i'm aware that i have got this coping mechanism which is basically
stavie'sy enough that you don't think about what's happening um so you know i'm just sort of like
and a meta level conscious that that is a thing at the moment i've also been doing a podcast with
two lovely people oh yeah so there is all the stuff like we we did a podcast and we ran a
science fiction convention and stuff like that and we forgot we'd run the science fiction convention
when we did a review of our fanak in 2020 which was very funny um so when you were sort of talking
about journaling i've been journaling a lot um sorry Claire um because because glares go to
to read my journals when i'm dead and go what on earth was this about is that a threat
is that i don't know how to pass that it's a close gonna read all your journals after your
dead Claire may read all my journals before then Claire wants to do an anthology of my fan writing
and i'm like but my fan writing is largely in co-it bits and pieces because i should do a fancy
scene um anyway um that that brings some of the incur bits and pieces but i've been doing a lot
of journaling and i've been doing a lot of self-reflecting and again these are things like i
feel like i may be although i go well i'm exactly the same person i was a year ago i'm clearly not
the same person i was a year ago because the person i was a year ago was not very self-reflective so
it's kind of weird and then having said oh yes i've been doing lots of this stuff it happens that
for the last week i haven't for the last week i've been taking a particular video game and going
oh it's got this set of incredibly hard achievements maybe i could get all of them which is i know
in a moment of self-reflection perhaps not the best use of my time um but something's going on
there and i think it may have something to do with the anniversary of this and thinking oh yes
all of this is a year since we started um reordering our life so there will be an apocalypse for those
of us who did i i think it's also like john says about about copy mechanisms like there's probably
part of your brain that's gone well i'm gonna do all this stuff and things bad but it's all temporary
and then you're like oh it's a year doesn't seem very temporary new so the other thing i found is
that so for instance my parents didn't open their christmas presents because they were like we'll
save the freestyle and we can have family christmas and something i have been doing in the apocalypse
is that i've not just been in a holding pattern waiting for my life to restart i've been making
the most of what i can do in the apocalypse i think a lot of the people i've been talking to
seem to be coping better have been trying to make the most of it instead of kind of waiting for it
to stop and so i did i should eventually say to my parents like you should open your christmas
presents like like you know i mean i'm hopeful i get to see you but you can't just you can't take
every joyful experience out of your life until the world's fixed and then have them all at once that
that doesn't seem like a good tack i appreciate that's difficult because i am um privileged in
that i have had the energy to follow that advice and i appreciate there will be people for whom
that is not true and they don't have the spoons or the batteries um to kind of try and make try
and make the best of the situation because it is a hugely stressful and um draining situation to be
in um so i know that there will be some people listening who are like well yeah but i didn't have
the the the the batteries and i completely sympathize um i don't have any useful advice well
all once again refer people to the cgp grave video spaceship u in which he talks about what to do
if you have no batteries and where to start so that is us staying sane in the apocalypse next week
we will be uh reading out the poems we have received for our anthology for the anniversary of the
otterthorpe podcast and we will be discussing all of the exciting news that has come out of
easter con about what it is they're doing and how and we will be talking about our plants for easter
con and what we're going to do which we'll know about because we will know a lot more about how
easter con is going to work by then yeah and that is a good thing to look forward to and liz where
are you going that means you can't record next sunday is it exciting i might go to the beach
tell us about the beach liz what is it like is it outside is there air
is outside it is a few a few hours uh from bankok hey that's good that was the 26th episode of the
oxithorpe podcast and it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
that was an entire year of podcasting
i'm not going to a particularly no speech because i'm going to all witches close and also there are
quite a few places so in this like we're in a the like british tears except they're done by
collars instead and so i'm currently in an orange zone and i'm going to travel to yellow but some
of them won't let people travel from orange zones yet without 14 days of quarantine are these
like tears they are very like tears except that they're color coded and so there are five of them
and also but also provinces can have their own adventure restrictions anyway the point is that
i can't travel everywhere because not everywhere wants to accept visitors from uh orange-tiered
places when they are green or yellow-tiered places but what orange tier means is i mean i think we've
had like a handful of cases on some days in the past two weeks right so by orange tier we mean
that we are coming down from what the british would consider to be extremely well controlled to
almost zero so it's only context really when you when when allison said oh are there five
five levels because they're color coded does that imply allison only thinks there are five colors
because there are more than five colors i was thinking it was like the mousy mousy of
pandemic control so instead of having a die you would have like a die with colors on
a for for people who can't manage numbers oh she she's off again making cultural references i don't
get Liz yeah don't get this one either massy massy i mean he's calling us off a gamer he must
have played massy massy must i is that a game that cats play much played i mean it's not a game
that virtualizes well but it is much played amongst um actual people at like games conventions
and things in corners because you play it with an anvil which the originals does not contain an
anvil why do you take a heavy weight so when you when you slam down the cup to catch the mice also
what are you talking about i found a link on game.co.uk to a game called mousy mousy it's got a solo cup
and an illustration of two mice but it doesn't have any pictures of it in play so i can't look
right all i'm saying is you need to put a link in the show notes okay so okay so after the apocalypse
i will play mousy mousy with you oh hello lison being proposition again it's a sound vaguely threatening
it's a game for people who have not yet learned to count so therefore games with dice where you have
to do something that involves the numbers on a dice are too hard for them so so you you use a die
with um with colors on it instead this is probably off topic um the theme music for this episode was
fanfare for space by kevin mccloud at ncompetech.com used under a creative commons attribution 3.0 license
this podcast will end at the beep beep