Let's not get sidetracked into a discussion of lamination.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 118th episode of Octothorpe, a podcast for Science Fiction
and Science Fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 12th of September 2024. I'm John Coxon,
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty. We don't have letters of comments today, listeners,
we are going to do a bumper mailbag next episode and we will be going through about two months of
letters. So if you have things you would like to tell us please write in, we promise we will
have read them before the next episode. And we'll include as many as we can. So just to start
discussing our second Glasgow episode, there's a lot of Glasgow. We forgot to mention last time
there is a Worldcon photos album on Flickr, there will be a link in the show notes and this is
photographs by a team of people. So there are photos by Paul Weemer, Olav Rockne, Simon Bubb
and Dan Other and those are just the ones I know about. I think there's also some photos from Michael
Ben-Viniste in there. Amanda Wacka-Raku is not actually behind the camera but was actually doing a ton
of the support for Olav as well. Yes, true true true. And so yes, we will link in the show notes but
if you want photos of the Worldcon, there are some there. I've been very much like how basically
older photographers at the Hugo seem to be Hugo nominees and thank you very much to Olav and Amanda
for giving up some of their time when they could be wandering around drinking wine to take nice photos
everyone on a very phototopable backdrop. We will put some art in the show notes. Andrew Hogg noted
fan artist inventor of the comic strip, fanboys has done some reorganizations of the photographs
with various backgrounds and I will try and put together an online album of them and put them in
the show notes because they are quite wonderful listeners. When I saw the photos I was like oh
other people went and got lovely photos taken with Plus One and I should really have done that.
Sorry Stephen. I also did not do that. I felt like that was a mistake. There's a very good picture on
friend of the podcast Andy's Blue Sky where it's the three of us and Andy and Andy's holding my
Hugo and so it looks like I am the hanger on next to a Hugo Award winning podcast which I did enjoy.
Oh that was in the bar wasn't it? Yes. Yeah yeah I'll put it in show notes.
We discussed a variety of things about Worldcon last episode. We discussed registration and the
hugos and a little bit of the business meeting and the program and today we're going to be focusing
on Hall 4 to start off and we're going to start with meetups. Hall 4 is big. Very big.
You might think it's a long way from the Crown Plaza to the business meeting but that's just
peanuts to Hall 4. Look I guess we should say this is actually we're talking about Hall 4 and 5 I
guess because we'll talk about the dealers as well. Hall 4 was sort of exhibits, fan tables,
the fanzine lounge and bits like that and I also had the food tracks and also had the parties in it
and then Hall 5 was dealers and the art show. This is the AD&D division of the convention.
Yes. Did you guys ever have to go to the stationary supply office? Consupplies. What's that Glasgow?
Yeah. No I wish I had but I didn't please tell us. So I went hunting for something for
program ops on Thursday morning and I was looking for like consupplies office and I went and asked
Phil Dyson and Phil was like oh okay wait I'll show you and he basically had to lead me to it by
the hand because you went all the way back to the back of Hall 4 to an unmarked door that looked
like a staff only one and then through another set of doors and there was like a little office
that was full of like stationary and things and but yeah it was basically so far away from everything.
I'm now sad I missed out on what sounds like the best program I am that was available at the
convention which is just a room full of stationary. It was but it was it was mostly empty by the
time I got there and also like 2,000 steps in search of a thing. I will also say I just want to make
it very clear that that is a reflection of how much I love stationary and not a reflection on the
quality of the Glasgow 2024 program which was excellent. There were no laminators John.
Ah what I've got a laminator in my house what shit pastry covered but but good really because
you know laminating things for six days and then throwing them away is not the best. No no I know
I know. What else was in Hall 4 other than a very well hidden stationery office? Meetups Liz,
meetups and we went to the podcast to meet up and I was like hello I'm a podcaster and then Tammy
came and I was like I know who Tammy is and Laurie and Kevin were there so it was fine but I was
very shy. How did you all enjoy the podcast meetup? There were a lot of podcasters and the thing
about the meetups in general is that Glasgow had I think quite optimistically put three
backwitting tables for three meetups in the various lots that have meetups and I think the podcast
meetup had about 60 or 70 podcasters. I think that was kind of normal for meetups meetups were
quite big at this event a lot of the meetups were quite big at this convention and and one table
of 10 people was not quite going to do they split us very arbitrarily into fiction and non-fiction
podcasts which is probably the right way to go for us because most of our podcasting friends are
doing non-fiction podcasts I think I'm just hoping I haven't distanced anybody terribly there.
I didn't even notice who we divided oh it's just wandering around. Yeah no they divided us into
fiction and non-fiction podcasts and we were in a group with other people who were doing non-fiction
podcasts of podcasts about science fiction and related things rather than podcasts that are
actually generating fiction either by reading it out as some podcasts do or by doing like dramatic
bits and bobs but not in a best dramatic presentation way. The only fiction podcaster I think I know
is Emily and Capen. Obviously there are many but that's their only escape pod. Oh well yeah okay
but like the only person I'd feel that like able to like say hi to a convention I guess.
I know the escape pod people I think you know. Oh well no that's true I know Alistair and
Marguerite and yeah who were kindly hosting the podcast meetup which yes yes they were.
It was a very you know nice thing to do. In my head Alistair is a fan writer and fans enerter
and I always forget that he does a semi-prosy. When also in my head is skate pod is a semi-prosy
not a fan cast so like he he brackets fan cast from both directions like a pincer movement.
Yeah so so podcast the podcast meetup had had podcasts that were dramatic presentations and
podcasts that were semi-prosy and and fan casts and all sorts of things because categories are
nonsense just one you go for everything. Oh oh it could be a very big big Hugo.
Best thing this this idea comes from Ian Snell his idea for a Hugo Award for Best Thing
which would neatly sidestep all eligibility considerations and be reliably won each year
by an episode of Doctor Who. Doctor who didn't even win it's best. Now I know I don't let facts
get in the way jokes Alison. Good strategy good strategy I had numerous conversations over the
weekend and since with people who think who told me that X thing should be a Hugo category and
in all of those cases I'm kind of like really do you think do you think there are enough things
for people to nominate them consistently every year and then you know not everything has to be a
Hugo. So this is a digression you wanted to say things about meetups. I wanted to say things about
meetups which is that I went to the podcasting meetup which was a kind of official meetup that
was on the program and I also went to the fan funds delicate reception which was a meetup that was
not called that but was a program item that was on the program and had enormous numbers of people
at it which Joseph Dichliss said in a hushed tone surely these people cards will be fan funds
delegates and I was like well the vast majority of them are in fact because it's quite a big party now
and with a photo of that one and then I went to a couple of meetups that were not on the program
but people just have meetups like the TWP meetup and the customs meetup which was amazing because
we had sorry I should say the Cambridge University Science Future Society meetup and which in
open brackets now incorporating Yumsborg which was the Cambridge University Fantasy Society
which had I mean and probably about as many people as the podcast as meetup just vast numbers of
people of all ages and that was quite excited. Cambridge full of weird nerd shocker
Cambridge full of weird nerd shocker indeed and one of my personal delights was discovering that
Rosanna Pendelbury who's one of the nerds for feather people who I met at the weekend is also a
cuss was chair being like me but about kind of 35 years difference so this was all quite cool
and in general meetups were hugely delightful and I think there were just lots of meetups
happening along lots of different axes over the weekend and it gave me a chance to meet people
I looked back before people I hadn't had that before people who I really wanted to see at this
World Cup but only actually saw at the relevant meetup and it was great and I hope everybody else
also had fun of that kind. On the subject of meetups to be personally introspective it's very weird
because at this calm I was probably first and foremost a podcaster and I don't really think of
myself as much of a podcaster. Hugo award winning podcaster Liz Batty in "Don't really think of
myself as a podcaster scandal" yeah but like the only program items I did were related to
Octothor basically so it was clear that like I was a podcaster this time and it's a bit strange
you were podcaster here wouldn't you? yes but I didn't do any of the actual podcaster program
because I didn't think I was qualified to be on any of them very well there were the good people
so yeah that that's what we call self exclusion and imposter syndrome they generally were like
great people for all of them and I didn't think they'd do a great job like if you could have put
me on a thing about oh how to make your podcaster the answer would be get John to do all the work
and that's or you know get your brother to give you a very nice microphone thank you brother.
It used to be when I was on panels I introduced myself as a fanzine editor and I might mention
my day job and now when I'm on panels I start with that I do Octothor because that is like the
thing for which I am most notable arguably in total but definitely in fandom and that is kind of odd
it's kind of gratifying because I think it's neat that like we had an idea and that idea has
become a thing we are known for which is really nice but it is I do tell your spoilers like when
I'm like it's weird isn't it yeah well because on the panel on andro I was like I'm a podcaster
my podcaster Octothorpe is a Hugo finalist and like it's like it's all true but it feels weird to
mention but that is also undoubtedly why there are panels where I think I have the expertise of a
fan and the eloquence of a eloquent fan and the thing that is pushing me over the edge into being
the person that's asked is that I have done 116 episodes of a popular podcast.
Semi popular. Semi what the fuck is that?
I do think I was listening to the three black halflings and one of the people I met this
weekend was their producer who is very lovely I was listening to them and the way they
kick off each other and speak and thinking oh well one of the things about podcasters is that you
would think that after you've done a certain number of podcasts your ability to sound okay on
items is quite is enhanced by that experience and I'm not sure it's invariably true I think my
performance on panels is better than it was though though sorry to people who saw me over the weekend
at Glasgow. I didn't mention this in the program or when we were talking about replay but I was
quite proud of how the Ahsoka panel went because there was me and Dan Morin who is a podcaster in
the Apple Blogosphere and we were the first two to speak and we kind of set up a running
joke with the other panelists picked up and went with and we kept coming back to and like it is
that sort of thing where you start getting better at picking up people's balls and I'm not sure I'm
I'm still not sure I'm great at it but I'm definitely a lot better at it than I was before we'd thought
thought. At the podcast meetup one of the people was one of the podcasters I'd been on a panel
with earlier in the weekend and I I introduced him to a wider group saying and and his podcast is
great because of Exford Wild he just beamed from ear to ear and I thought oh it maybe I am learning
some management training after all only 40 years too late. What are they so the cuspous meetup
and the podcaster meetup and TWP which is the women's periodical which is an appa filled with
women yeah an appa for women based mostly British women if you're interested in that get in touch
and I'll get in touch with you and tell you how to join we should probably explain what an appa is
but basically people write things and staple them together and mail them to each other and a staple
is a tiny bit of metal that you can put into paper to make them stick together yeah if you're a worse
real fans don't use staples and mark plumber will testify he will testify against but he will
testify did you go to any meetups Liz other than podcasting no I was just a podcaster you know
John that's mine identity now we mentioned appas and another example of an appa is WUF
which was collated at the fanzine lounge and allesim will tell us all about it so WUF is the
world con order of fanads which is an appa that is collated at WILCON you can either send a pdf in
or you can come along with a load of copies and and the instant fanzine went into it which was
very gratifying because i've been involved in that and the and Christina Lake put it together
because she has not had Liz Batty's how to say no to allesim trading
Christina i'm available i am very grateful for everyone who has not had that training
so the fanzine lounge the fanzine lounge was pretty good it was run by my wife is fanny sheriff
with some help from my husband yeah no it's good good place to hang out did some sort of editing
there there were like neat things chris gossia's t-shirt was there um so for those who have seen
chris gossia on stage when he won a hugo he was wearing his flint stones shirt that shirt has
been retired and so he got everyone to sign it and i signed it chris's nickname for me is john the
rock coxon it's a long story it's been his nickname for me for a very long time and i signed it that
way because i knew he would appreciate it and then i won a hugo and he was like now you're
john the rockit coxon so i had to go back and add et onto the end of rock but i did and it was fine
and that was really lovely and there was dragon racing and we've discovered the way to get young
fans into fanzines which is you have the dragon you have the fanzine lounge in view of the children's
activities part of the fan area and then you do dragon racing and children come and they're like
we want to race the dragons too please which was as fanny was very happy with so one of the
other things that fell off by to-do list was that i wanted to make to have a kind of structural
thing for making mini fanzines where you have a sheet of instructions showing how you make mini
fanzines and you have blank mini fanzines and then you have craft items which there were in the kids
area and then fanzines happen more or less organically if you do that and i didn't have time so boo
another time but that was also deliberately designed to end up with children making fanzines
ispania my wife exhibited in the art show and she sold prince and her fans and she sold
most of her fans and all of her prince which is really great some of the art was amazing in the
art show this year i did not get time to look at all of it which was to my great sorrow but i
really thought there were a lot of great art on on display and world con art shows are one of my
favorite parts of the convention i also thought it greatly benefited from not being in a completely
different building a significant walk away from the rest of the convention unlike some previous
european world cons yeah so having it in the middle of the dealers room was lovely for the artist it
was not so lovely for the dealers who were tucked around the back um but i think all of the dealers
did quite well it was a generally a color there were a lot of people who saved up a lot of money
to come to world con and then wanted to spend some of it in the leaders room and that was quite good
our fan funds tables got moved from fan tables into dealers room where we said we cannot secure
these tables for all of the hours in which hall four is open um because we got we had a lot of
quite valuable stuff knocking around the fan funds tables and people kept donating stuff and so on
and they moved us into the dealers room thank you thank you Glasgow that was very very kind of
the overall amount raised for the fan funds was a shade over 6,700 pounds which is a lot of money
and we are very grateful to everybody who donated things and all the people who helped out i have a
list of 36 people who materially physically helped with the the business of doing the work the fan
funds at the world con which quite a lot it was good i bought a anthology of fan writing by Randy
Byers who who i miss very much it's going to be really weird to have us here at World con where
Randy isn't there and that moves us on to the in memoriam section of hall four which was right
in the very middle the the little bit that the fan lounge was in was in the sort of calm middle area
of the of hall four um with kind of exhibits and food and all of the other stuff around it and um
right in the very middle was a tree and a memorial garden and the kind of memorial scroll i there's a
there's a link to that on the internet which we should link to and i'd go and look at it kind of
quietly and peacefully not in the memorial garden but in my hotel room at some point because i
knew i would have a little gripe which i did and it's quite nice doing that in my hotel room rather
than say at a ceremony where i feel blobby especially not in the middle of the hugos imagine if that
had been kind of immediately before or immediately after we had won a hugo that would be really
weird i'd have to go up go up and get the hugo or puffy faced so i quite liked having it dotted the
hugos thank you i'm torn did they did they put it in the opening ceremony which i didn't go to
they did right at the end apparently okay i confess i had to leave the opening ceremony early on account
of how it went long and i had to be in a different place so i missed it but i heard reports that it
was and i haven't checked was that our place was that the fanfans yes it was the reception yeah i
think it's nice to have like a big public thing where we show the memorial scroll but yeah i agree
that it works for most people in the hugos but maybe not the people who might after then be
composing up on stage shortly after also i find it harder every year and i don't think i'm alone in
that that it's gone from oh there would be one or two names where i'm like oh this is hard to to
oh goodness it's not clear to me if that's an age thing or a network thing because like obviously
as you know more the longer i go to conventions the more people i know and then the more people
there are who might go but i remember my very first immemorium had someone that i'd met on my
taftrip who was younger than me on it so it never gets easy and actually writing my taff report 10
years late was quite hard in places because when you're writing about like oh i went to this place
with these two people and they are both no longer with this is like oh okay like stu shiftman and vj
bowin and and a lot of Seattle fans i met yeah no indeed right sorry but then capitalism happened
and that made everything better let's talk about dealers there was places that sold games and that
was great and also i got to know a couple of the dealers quite well because i ran the scavenger hunt
on discord which we'll talk about later but a few dealers submitted prizes to that which we were
very grateful for um so thank you to everyone who did two of the stalls i was particularly attracted
to were mati makes and beyond cataclysm and beyond cataclysm were also at east con but at this
convention every time i had groats i went to spend them at the beyond cataclysm table and i got some
good swag and if you are on instagram i will put a link to my swag in the show notes i like the
dealers room i didn't buy a lot i will say i find it increasingly tricky in the dealers room when
there are a lot of like self-published authors who have a table because then i feel a bit bad about
just wandering past and like ignoring their efforts to get me to talk to them because i
generally am not going to buy any i'm probably only going to buy books in the dealers room because
i've already heard about them i'm probably not going to be persuaded to buy your book just from
talking to you so i just liked it more when there were more like general booksellers but i did like
boner books who are published and had big tentacles for their book i got a ribbon that said experts
in edging i also got this a ribbon this was the only corporate ribbon i think from illumicrate.com
and they sell books with beautiful painted edges and i saw the ribbon and i was like i must have that
on my ribbon beard and then i did all of the ribbons i had with ones that convention gave me
or ones that my mates gave me um and even at that i had to stop because i'd have fallen over and
tripped over on my ribbon and that would have been terrible but but that was the one that i made
an exception for because i thought it was so funny my favorite ribbon is okai sci-fi which
makes me smile every time i look at it i can see it from my chair i did not get that one ah great
ribbon i did get the vibrant food culture ribbon yes i got more than a hero a union man which is my
favorite uh sartre quote i got vibrant food culture and i put it next to the haggis pakora ribbon haggis
pakora yeah yes are you familiar with the hoo song boris the spider no yes so you can see haggis pakora
and it scans the same so i had haggis pakora but um um in my head for like a lot of the convention
and i had haggis pakora and they were good i did not have haggis pakora and i had had an
intention to have haggis pakora but the food trucks in hall four did put me off fried food for life
i would have been very unhappy at this convention except that about i think sometime on friday
somebody told me that you could get a perfectly nice baguette with food in it from the deli on the
concourse and i ate those for lunch for the rest of the weekend weekend and it was all right because
they felt like food to me whereas the most of the stuff in hall four triggered my there are too many
carbohydrates and not enough other macronutrients in this food so they were like that like the geros
which is normally a very safe thing for me was like um meat and bread and salad which is something
i eat a lot of and also chips but why would you do that because the only food they were doing
the things you get out of a big frozen bag and deep fry i had a lot of good food in nearby
our guile street which is very lovely including on the monday night we found a place we found at
satellite again and i had lovely scottish beers and lovely lovely burger and it was yummy so so
actually next next world come we're all that can make a plan to go out to the together i know
we did in chicago but we didn't this time that was a mistake i mean i didn't go out for dinner very
much at all though because i mean our guile street was great but it was like you know you are out of
the con for two or three hours i could only get there by cab and i couldn't and there weren't
there weren't enough cabs so yeah yeah and i was a bit disappointed that having looked up on google
the menu for the the clide built restaurant in the concourse which looked pretty good when i went
check the actual restaurant it was smaller and totally different and a lot more fried and shut
at seven p.m or something that there there weren't there wasn't food on most of the times we looked
we found a very nice indian that is only a few minutes walk from the scc called india key and
it's probably not as good as indians on our guile street because lasko has some of the best
indian food in the country but it was fantastic for somebody who come and walk very far so it was
absolutely lovely and then we actually went out with lillian one night well props to lillian for
arranging being the one person who arranged dinner with me in advance and that was great that was to
belgid restaurant called brel where i had um in complete defiance of this theory that i like um
that i wanted something healthy i had mac and cheese and it was fantastic i do want it on the record
that i did post about dinner we were going to and you were like i'm in the bar and didn't come so like
it wasn't entirely that there was no option but yeah but it would have been like three quarters
and half for me to get to wherever you were i think the problem is with this is that as i think
again taste but i'd much rather go off site what i've tried to do more and more at world cons is
consider people who i would like to see and actually have proper experiences with and then
make the time to do that because i think it's very easy for me at a convention owing to i mean
owing to fadav ADHD and there's a lot happening to just ping pong around everyone and be like oh
i'll catch up with you later it was great to see you and then never actually do the catching up later
and so what i was trying to do was go off site with people where i would like to spend two or three
hours just with them and to be to live in that and not to get foam mode that there were other
people i could be having more fun with so like we went out with mark claire on one of the nights
and it was just the four of us obviously like mark and claire great and then like i got with
going out for beers and pizzas on like the when's the old thursday night i can't remember
was really good but then obviously there are times when it's just like now i just got to get
something at the camp last because i really don't have two hours to spare but and it's hard because
like i say there's a lot happening at worldcon should we talk about parties there were some
i had whiskey and japanese gin the japanese party was really good they had japanese alcohols and
they were all very nice and like you know you weren't getting huge servings but it was just lovely to
sort of sample different things and i remember one of my favorite memories in my first east
com was there was a party for anticipation which was the montreal 2009 worldcom i remember very
fondly they had maple rum and i that is my favorite one of my nicest memories of that convention is
like drinking maple rum at their party and i love sampling weird alcohols from around the world
so yeah i know it was it was cool there was like a good mix of different bids there
sort of advertising and chatting and stuff what did you guys think of the parties
this is one of the so some of my worldcon experience was mediated through a
i am not going to do anything where i'm not going to be able sure i'm going to be able to sit
out and i thought that i would probably because if i went to the bar i could hang out in the bar
with people and if i went to the parties i thought that there was quite a high risk i would be
unable to sit down with people i wanted to talk to and in fact there were a few times in the bar
when i found it difficult to sit down with people i want to talk to but in general the
cramplars a bar was much better than it has been at previous not the the fan bar was fine but the
main cramplars a bar was much better than it has been at previous clasco worldcons and was quite a
good place to sit down and hang out liz what do you think of parties i didn't enjoy the party much
basically because the newsletter at least for first few days there was no way of knowing what
parties were on any one day like there wasn't a big board that told you what parties were on
it wasn't in the newsletter so what it was was like some kind of indoor tents which were generally
surrounded by an awful lot of people very close together and so it's like oh do i kind of elbow
my way through this group of people to try and work out what the party is for and most of the time
i didn't and it was also far enough from the fan bar and the cramplars a bar they're like you
couldn't kind of flip from one to the other so i would mostly go into the bar so i felt it was a
bit of a missed opportunity i think also they didn't really advertise they didn't seem to
advertise the parties very much i'm not sure if people who are new to world can't even
knew that they were kind of these parties going on because i want the news let's say
look lots of open access parties i think that segues quite nicely into communications
where i think there were certain things this convention did not have a newsletter it had
powerpoint slides which were put on screens and it was not there were a screen behind the
volunteer desk and there was a screen in the business meeting when the business meeting wasn't
happening and i don't think i saw a screen with the newsletter on it at any other point during the
convention there were screens in many program rooms but it'll be sec program rooms because of the
whole streaming thing that you know there wasn't there weren't screens in the
cramplars a program rooms i don't think yes there were and they had the newsletter on
so the screen where there were screens in program rooms they had the newsletter on between items i
thought that bit of it worked pretty well moving to this new process it happened quite
late it happened in a fairly scrappy fashion i think steve was working with a terribly small team
um i think you could do a lot more with it if we have a printed newsletter then people
due to world calls often don't see that either so so that is a whole issue with
well communications generally the bigger this is quite a big world call the bigger the world
call the harder is to get your messages out to members at the convention yeah no i agree with that
and i think did i just not get to program early enough to see any of this i think you must have just
yeah i you didn't get there early enough or like there were probably rooms in the cramplars that
didn't have it i can only remember seeing it in one of the our guile rooms probably one or two
but maybe not three and and maybe maybe it depended if there was someone there to turn it on because
not every room was manned for every item and and i feel like this is the first go at a new model for
how you do this and it ought to you know there's a lot more we could do with this model because i
don't think we're going to be doing paper newsletters forever i think it is a you know i think we've
known it's due for a little while and i think it's doomed but it's not that i miss paper newsletters
it's that i miss knowing i can go somewhere two or three times a day to get a concise set of
information that is useful to me and there will be some humor in it and i didn't get that from this
newsletter yes that that no no neither did i and that's the thing right if the only the only place i
knew i could go to get the information was the volunteer room because i'm not going to go to a
program item just to see the newsletter and then leave again because that would be the actions of
a lunatic and also the thing is it's the same thing you get you know when you go in a restaurant
that has electronic menus and the menu switches away from the menu item you want to order and you've
got to wait a minute for the menu item you want to order to come back so you can look at what it
costs and what the options are it was that where it's like oh there's a bit always gone and then
because it's like eight slides or whatever it takes ages for it to come back round it's like
c-fax for the 21st century yeah it's like i kind of feel and maybe i am wrong but there is a reason
that paper newspapers have survived and c-fax has not and i think it is because paper news is a
better solution than c-fax to delivering information and so i think if i was going to pick one i would
have picked paper newsletters and i'm relatively tech forward i love that you're on i love that
you're on that side of the argument today but i i a person who has been arguing this point for many
many years at this point and on the other side i mean i kind of agree we are having paper newsletter
reconnect i believe we we are we have made arrangements to ship our little printers over there and
because i'm not doing anything else for reconnect i think i'm going to be working on it so that
should up the humor value hashtag dot even a bit arrogant i have always been pro having
information in as many places as you can possibly have it and wanting there to be paper newsletters
entirely i have always been a fan of paper newsletters because i think the answer is both i think the
answer is usually both when you're trying to communicate things or even not both but as many
as you can and this gets to something that i think was a problem i think this is a problem with this
convention that dates back to mid 2019 where this convention had a publication under promotions
division and i was arguing as far back as luncon that that model was not fit for purpose because
the primary function of both of those divisions is to disseminate information to people and it used
to work very well because the way they did that was very different and i think the way they they do
it is getting more and more similar over time and so at this convention you have promotions
which did a very very good job and was very good you had publications which we will get to but i
think if you were going to pick the division that did the worst job at Glasgow it would probably be
that one no offense to anyone who worked on it but i'm really sorry yeah and then you had online
services which was technically not its own division it was under the it division which is the tail
wagging the dog but basically i worked with and andrew and emily on discord and that was one of the
other big ways the convention had of communicating information to members and it is notable that
what that means is you have three you have the two code dh's of promotions you have the publications
dh and you have paul taylor who is the dh of online and alan bond who is an area head the area head in
charge of the entire online convention which should be its own division and this speak who then caught
covid the day before the convention no it was later because he had british andrew and emily
on like friday morning the point being even if he hadn't caught covid he should have been committee
level there's no way you want that person to be an area head that that doesn't make any sense
and this speaks to a problem with how we i think this speaks to something with how the world
con was constituted which probably made a lot more sense pre pandemic than it did post pandemic
but also meant that the world con had a very fractured idea of how it was going to disseminate
information and i think there are aspects where that became very clear i was on the discord trying
to disseminate information but because we weren't in promotions i couldn't like directly interface
with the social media team i was having to like send emails and like that got very complicated
and i just think there were barriers there that didn't need to be there and that is one of the
one of the more frustrating things i found about this convention from the perspective of working
on it i mean i think there's a couple things that i think one is that like your workflow cannot
just be the work flow can't be paper newsletter or thing in program rooms or whatever your workflow
needs to be okay this is the information this is how we set up our workflow so it becomes a thing
we can't explain the program rooms and a thing which you know gets posted to a discord channel
at a certain time and a thing which becomes like a thing which is easy to read on the web not
a pdf or slides and we don't have that workflow i think the other thing is that cross-divisional
communication within world constructors can be tricky because you have to give people the autonomy
to go and do stuff themselves but also make sure they don't go off and promise a bunch of stuff
and then their division head says no actually we're not doing that so i think that's a general
it's always difficult right and so one thing is also the more divisions you create sometimes
the more of that you end up with in fact one of the things that happened this time was that messages
from the convention were included in all of the newsletter messaging and that was a problem because
those messages were extremely dull and very repetitive and that's that's an issue that that
you need to have somebody quite senior and in fact all of megg and ester and margarit could have done
this but it what happened was people who were immediately below that level who were not capable
of seeing that if you are going to message people it needs to be amusing it always you can have the
odd message that is that is dull but necessary but the vast majority of your messaging needs to be
light-hearted or people will not read it they will not pay attention and they will turn off from
those things and we know that for a long time you know people at the World Cup have fun they don't
want they don't want the bad news yes i think that's true i don't think you need a mix of messaging
so you need you need like a light-hearted vehicle so the print newsletter is often quite like jokey
and light-hearted but like the messages are on discord so for instance levitation the message on
discord tend to be a little bit less light-hearted and more informational because you're conveying
that information differently and what you want there is brevity so that someone can quickly
grasp what it is they've just seen in announcements and then go and read a different part of the
discord but like the other thing is that you've just got to put as much of your information out in
as many ways as possible because there will be people who only read the facebook there will be
people who only read blue sky there will be people who only read discord there will be people who
only read email there will be people who read none of those but might see something if it's like
thrust in front of them in paper form there will be people who will see it if it's like on a screen
in a program i am what you get to is a thing where you are like liz says you are coming up with
information you want to disseminate and you want to disseminate it through every organ you have
and if those organs are separated on different sides of divisional divides that gets harder for
no reason and this isn't something i should say this isn't something your world con is uniquely
bad at every organization has trouble getting information from silo to silo like from i mean god
knows i work in academia and like getting information from different academic departments or research
groups to each other that is also a problem just because you talk less to people who are further
away from you and that means it is harder to communicate with them and so i'm not trying to
diss world con i'm not trying to diss the world con for not being good enough at going cross division
but what i am trying to do is say you need to think very carefully about where you put the walls
because it is difficult to cross them and so the less the fewer walls you have in between parts of
the convention that we'll need to talk to each other the better so for instance and god knows
mega mat didn't need more work but i think there is a strong argument that online convention should
probably be have been under promotions not under it because i think that would have made more sense
in a conveying information direction but then that's not really promotions division anymore because
it's doing a lot more than just promotions but then the promotion division does a lot more than
promotions now anyway it's not just because you're doing all of your at con communication with
members through social media and that's not really promotions at that point that's member services
and so i just which is a different division so this is this is kind of what i mean i think
and i don't think this is Glasgow specific either but i think world con generally needs to take a step
back and work out how the last five years have changed how these structures need to be so so
will con felt this organization have felt quite bureaucratic to work within even by the standards
of world con and i think this is speaking to what you're saying but what it meant was
often very long layers as you said some very major parts of the convention which were
at area head level some very long chains of of responsibilities so you'd find yourself
side of five levels down in the organization you know 100 000 personal organizations
try not to have more than five levels of bureaucracy and i'm not sure we need that for con
running and i think we need to look at having simpler flatter structures generally and i don't
know i don't know how you do that other than by saying oh yeah no alfjara world con which i
absolutely will not do i'm very glad for people who run world courts me too and i i think because
a lot of recon stuff that like area heads and below we're doing kind of went up to division heads for
approval i think we then got to a situation on the ground where there are a lot of area heads
running important stuff who did not have autonomy to just make decisions and so they were paralyzed
because they need to go and find their decision head division head to make decision and then you
have only maybe 12 or 15 people who are in charge of an awful lot so i think we need to kind of do
that you need people have a bit more autonomy pre-con then by the time they get to the con they can
just go ahead with stuff and they're not waiting for someone else to tell them this is okay because
that's a recipe for a small number of people who are massively overworked i mean you get that
anyway but you know a smaller amount of people who are paralyzing everything else because they
cannot be in six place at once this is not this is also compounded and i think it's very important
we recognize so for those who aren't familiar with world con the way world con works there is a
committee role called death of emails and the role of that person is to be on every single email list
and tell people who are having parallel discussions where they haven't looped each other in that
those discussions need to be combined so basically the role of that person is effectively to keep an
eye on these walls and to make the walls more porous and that is a very good thing that i have
not seen other organizations do and i think that is something world con does better than a lot of
organizations the problem in this particular case is that the death of emails committee role was a
man called ben yellow and long time listeners will know that he was disinvited from clasco and
that role was never re recruited and so glasco was at a bit of a disadvantage here on account of
the whole Chengdu kerfuffle because if that role had been someone else i think a lot of these problems
would have been better and i think the fact he was taken off staff exacerbated some of this
and that isn't that isn't glasco's fault really i don't think because i do think i would not have
wanted ben to continue beyond program program on committee so yeah you can't do that because
the other thing about death of emails is that you can see everything apart from maybe stuff that
goes only to the chair so they have to be someone who is quite high level but that you can trust
with everything i think the i mean it is a problem that glasco if they did not re-recruit someone to
replace ben like you know he left because of tingdu issues but he could have left for any reason
and i think the other thing is that now you know when i did longcon in 2014 it was basically
nearly everything was done through email and a few kind of group chats for little mini things
now it is email and discord and a mix of discord channels open to everyone and discord channels open
only to your own division and then at con it's a mix of discord and the email and what's up
because people are getting too many pings on discord so they have to be on what's up instead
and we've just fragmented everything a bit too much so i don't i mean i don't solution to that
because i think the fragmentation is probably useful in some ways but um yeah you've got to have
you've got to try and be aware of all these cross-communications that are happening and the
solution is probably not to have everything open to more people because i know you get 10 people
sticking there or in about how you know tech division should make this decision which they
already made six months ago and you don't know all the information so you've got to kind of
stop the natural tendency of fans to give advice on everything but also making things a bit more
open that's very tricky needle to thread look Liz let's not cast too many stones at fans who like
giving advice on everything on our podcast where we're telling them how they should do their jobs
right yeah but we're not actually personally going to run a world called just check just say i also
absolutely did that on the world con discord i would like go in and think i was being helpful
and probably not be helpful and this is because my brain is like oh but you have done this before
you must have helpful information it's like no you actually haven't done it for like a long time
me too but i cut i cut back once i noticed i mean i noticed other people being worse and i was like
oh can we talk about publications please yeah i for one enjoyed going to land of Scots
if you were only going to print one thing would it be the thing that people are going to read
afterwards when they get home or would it be the thing that they need this weekend in order
to work out what's going on oh hang on oh i i disagree with your framing here but fair enough
continue so i don't i do not think this should have been a printed document at all i do think the
convention program guide should have been prevented printed in sufficient numbers that anybody who
wanted one should should have a been given one and then being taken out to the back and quietly shot
and showed how modern smartphones work but there we go all right so i am simultaneously i am
simultaneously disagreeing from i'm disagreeing with you from two different directions here
i'm a big fan of printing the pretty thing that can be the souvenir rather than the ephemeral thing
that will go in the bin when i have my like agent track off ski hardbacks i buy the hardbacks with
the very pretty covers because i want them as objects of art and i don't mind having world
con souvenir books because they are a souvenir key word here is by why am i paying so that people
who like bits of dead tree can have no i mean and and i agree i don't i wouldn't mind if it was a
fiber extra i do think it needs to be pre-com because so it gets tricky right because what you
don't want to do is for someone not to notice that they need to buy it in advance and then not have
one for them the other thing you don't want to do is print them all afterwards and send them
through the post because that is much worse for the environment and so like i actually do think
having a table of them where you have some guesses to how many you're going to need print that many
and have them at the convention is probably the right model i would be interested to know how
many they had left and i hope what world cons are doing are discussing what percentage of them go
like and printing a number that makes sense in that context i hope there aren't thousands of
unclaimed ones left over i would be interested to know how many go in the bin i would be interested
to know how many i'll never looked at again i was like why haven't we got a pdf yet and i have
you told the answers because they're going to correct it which does make some sense which
leads me on to my next blood about the souvenir book the question i have is why are we not printing
the paper program guide is it because it's too expensive in which case i think we do need to
reevaluate you know what we're including in a membership cost and what we're not the number one
question i think that i got a program participant check-in was do you have a paper copy of the program
and the answer was no we don't try the accessibility desk i think they did have some i think they end
up with quite a few but that was like an enormous question so if the answer is we're not printing
them to try and push people to smartphones i think we should we just have to accept that not
everyone wants to use their smartphone yet and we need to have more copies than we had and there
are still problems with people who find it hard to read their smartphones on the go or
had technical problems with the con guide and things like that so i think we need to decide why
we are doing it i was like i did not see any physical copies of the program change street
sheets at this comp normally there are some pink change sheets which you will find like
with the newsletter and stuff i don't know how you would have done that because they didn't give
the newsletter any printing exactly so i i think they were printed i mean you said you don't normally
print them but you normally distribute them in the same places because then you train people to go
and pick up bits of paper yeah well when i've done when i've done newsletters they've made us print
the pink sheets okay newsletter never printed the pink sheets when i did program but your online
program guide doesn't tell you what has changed and it also is no good if you have a paper copy of
the program and also the paper copy of the program was a very strange format not made for printing
well it was made for printing in a particular very tall and narrow format which i don't mind
but it's not made for printing on like a four paper or anything so if you want to print your
own version before you come to com also had mistakes that was another problem i would like to say
something and before i say i would i would like to encourage anyone who is likely to be upset by
savage criticism of this world gone to cover their ears for the next 10 seconds i think you need to
spell your guests of honor's name right in your fucking souvenir book the attention to detail in
this book was a fucking disgrace anything else you can get wrong that one you cannot you just cannot
to be honest when someone says to me what did you think of the Glasgow souvenir book at the moment
i go oh is that the one that took place in Scotland with two teas i don't go oh yeah that was full of
great articles and artwork i think about the really awkward cringe worthy errors and they're very small
things so it it really lets down what is otherwise quite a nice publication that you know can stand on
would be able to go on the shelf with pride along with your vast collection of world called
souvenir books which i do have actually you know i have i have kept one from every world god i've
gone to i've got not that i mean speaking of how many we think there's going to be left over from
2024 if you did want a 2005 Glasgow souvenir book you could have picked one up on the freebies table
this year oh do we still have 1980 the 1987 one the hardback one because though there were thousands
of those knocking around for decades but i think they're all gone i didn't check it's just i know
the 2005 one has that very nice cover so i recognize it from a distance when i did so for those who
don't know because i don't know i never know what people know and it's probably better to tell
people twice than tell people zero times i i was the dth for publications at lungcon 3 in 2014
working with case van tawne who was my dh and i did all of the progress reports for London i
my i just did them me and me and and then i sent them to jhanis gill who proofread them and made
try hadn't made stupid mistakes and then they got published and they were very good and i got to
use uh brine tailber artwork on all of them and i was extremely proud of them and i still have
copies of them in my house definitely used alison scott art work on at least one of them just saying
yes on the progress report minus one the cover was uh the hit truck is going to the galaxy i think
was the hit track collector london by one alison scott i still have it on my fan art page i was
quite pleased with that one and john commissioned it long long time ago it's a good it's a good piece
um so the and at that point we still we were mandated by the wussfus constitution to send out
physical pr's and we broke the rules because pr4 we didn't send out physically we're just like
we're not going to uh because we don't want to we think it's a waste of money we think it's a waste
of paper it's just a lot of effort and we're not gonna and so i do have a lot of sympathy for
publications and for paper and things and i just wanted to note that because i've been working towards
using less paper in this realm for a long time but i also don't think the answer is zero paper i'm
kind of in the middle of this yeah but no it's not good enough you you need to proofread
your publications and if you don't have time to proofread your publication you need to give it
a little bit more time and proofread it and this i believe that it went out in draft quite a lot
of people all of whom were very busy and none of whom thought it was their responsibility to make
sure it didn't have errors in it so making sure that you have somebody on the con who absolutely
knows that it's their responsibility to deliver something as error-free as possible i think is
critical because there's got to be some errors you know if if the error on the cover or the error on
the guest of ottopage had been the only error in the entire book people would have gone oh well
that was a bit stupid but in fact the things riddled with errors errors got into it between when i
sent stuff in and when it got printed you know which is what normally happens with documents
that's why you have to proofread proofread is very important and we love them
anyway this was the bit that and right okay so i just i want to make very clear
given that this is the thing i'm most disappointed in the convention for that tells you how good the
convention was because there are conventions where i've had significantly bigger criticisms than this
one and it is it does suck to be negative and i am yeah it was a little bit unfortunate in time
because what happens is you register for convention you get a little stuff and they give you a
program book and you go what yep yep yep yep unless you don't realize you're supposed to pick it up
and you forget and go and get one on Saturday morning i think the the nice person on registration
told me to get a program but i'd save a book but not to me but i mean i guess it was like busy and
it was staff registration and i wanted off anyway so we're not going to talk in detail about covid
you can see a lot of past episodes where we've talked a lot about cover policies and and so on
and i don't think we have much new to say about Glasgow's but i will say you know a bunch of people
got covid at the calm and Glasgow had a covid policy where they recommended wearing masks and testing
and i think a lot of people just hadn't read it or weren't aware of it and didn't kind of have
that little mental reminder that you are going to a giant event maybe you should bring some masks
and covid tests just in case and then you have a lot of people trying to find covid tests the
con cannot afford to provide you know five covid tests per participant it's going to be
always a limited number people scrambling to find them in like local pharmacies i think
they just probably needed to stick that somewhere in an email to say you know please remember to bring
whatever precautions you are bringing and bring some tests just in case and that might have helped
us a bit when you know the covid cases were kicking off on Sunday and Monday so we talk about discord
i like discord oh i like discord i did like the con discord but it was also a lot of con discord
and i'm kind of in two minds i think it's good to have a big con discord and it's nice to have
lots of activity but there was also stuff like hello i'm going to go into con discord and ask
a question which has already been answered seven times on facebook and three times on this discord
did you know that sometimes in Scotland you get different money out of cash machines because i
know that now toy money god yeah because i heard that a lot and did you know that most
place in Glasgow will take cards because i heard that a lot for you and then i end up getting some
Scottish money out to pay the one vendor who didn't take cards but yeah did you know Liz that the
tap water in Scotland is drinkable and the lose in certain Glasgow stations cost a coin to use
because that was another one that came up bewilderingly often tap wall one is interesting though actually
because i default to assuming the tap water is safe to drink pretty much everywhere and then
have to mentally remind myself nope and then i know a lot of people who come from place where
the tap water is not drinkable who have who basically will assume that you can't drink it
unless someone tells them otherwise so it's worth saying once and it's also worth noting that it's
not fizzy water so it doesn't have bubbles i helped with the discord but most of it was
Andrew and Emily January who do lots of good things i helped with the social bit so i ran a
scavenger hunt and i ran if i ran the zuc on we covered those in the live episode i think
i'm going to criticize the discord i think i underestimated how busy it would be when we were
when i was advising Emily and Andrew on on things and i think we should have more aggressively
gated a lot more channels so that it was much more possible to out of the box just get channels
that gave you information and not gave you discussion so that's something i would take for next time
i will also say in hindsight i wonder whether the staff discord and the con discord should have
been kept separate because i'm very used to aggressively muting channels on discord but i think
people who are less used to discord are less used to muting channels and having a completely separate
discord for staff chat might have helped people not need to go to whatsapp i think switching the
channel over the discord server over at the last minute was a massive mistake yeah i'm not sure
i mean i don't know if i think it was massive well i think if they've done it three weeks if
they don't three weeks in advance or a month in advance it would be fine i think doing it at the
very last minute meant that people then had to try and find their staff stuff in this sea of
convention discord and couldn't cope because the great benefit of having most of your
communication on discord is that you get a built-in death of emails because all the committee can
see everything like and so it's actually quite nice and it was very useful for a discord perspective
because he as emily andrew were in charge of this court they could see discussions happening
everywhere and they could be like oh this division is having this conversation and they are about
to ask us to do a thing and we start thinking about that early thank you for the kind words
about the discord peeps it was mostly emily and andrew i basically just sort of said vaguely helpful
things occasionally and made a spreadsheet is there anything else you want to talk about on
cons we need more maps and also we need some way to identify which building rooms are in and
unfortunately the system of the islands or whatever it was or in this one and the locks are in a
different one only works if you know about scollet geography and even that i mean i didn't know what
alsh ash one and two because yes i guess lok alsh is a lok but that's not how people think of lok al
at all they think of color look alsh and there is a discord server which has spun off called um
fancon.dev which is basically people who are interested in developing software solutions for
conventions and friend of the show andrew january is prototyping a new way of doing convention maps
in his copious spare time and so i am interested to see where that goes because yeah one of the things
we got very frustrated about was the quality of the maps we had available i'm saying we a lot
it was mostly andrew because of the most go on the portal
i'm going to pick the acolyte which is denny plus show it's a star wars show it was imperfect
but it was a hell of a lot more interesting than some of the other star wars shows looking at you
asoka and the reason i'm picking it is twofold firstly manage a sinto's massive arms yeah
uh as um recommended by noted science fiction critic abigail nusbaum who is fully in favor of
managers and toes arms if you like good arms this is a show for you congratulations go to your
book out abigail it has been cancelled because dizney make decisions out of fear rather than out of
any desire to make good things this is most evident in lucas film which makes me very sad
and there is a petition to bring it back and i'm going to put it in the show notes and it probably
won't do anything but christa loyev i just want them to make more interesting star wars that isn't
just more bloody day for loney live action crap that's my pick you say they do it out of fear
rather than desire to make good things but don't don't they do it out of desire to make more money
there was an attempt to break down number of hours of content watched on dizney plus by different
shows and i did think it was interesting that andrew came out pretty low but obviously kind of
got the critical acclaim and so on and so there is going to be a season two it seems like the acolyte
suffered from not having as many viewers as something with baby odourine and then maybe also
not getting the critical acclaim i think i'm watching it but i understand like there's some
stuff that happens midway through maybe involving manager sinto and his lovely arms
and that maybe means you need to give it a few more episodes to get going and that may have hurt it
it's imperfect but i think the main problem was there was a giant brigade of hateful
sawa's fans who was like hang on a minute this has this has people of colour in it and um yeah
i am fed up with capitulating to those people i thought i will i will see two movies this week
i am bound to be able to pick one and i am managing it but this is a bit of a retro pick
in that i am picking nimona and i understand i am late to the party have either of you picked nimona
i don't remember i mean they might pick the comic liz taste maker batty strikes again
web comic was to web comic first yeah boy um and stevenson so it is it is a movie it is a fairly
cute animated movie with lots and lots of good things in it it is about a chap who despite being
top of his classes face doesn't fit in a kind of weird futuristic medieval world and so therefore
gets framed for a crime and becomes an app cast and he makes friends with a girl who turns out to be
a bit tantier shape shifting and together they fight crime they do not fight crime but they attempt
to clear his name and it kind of goes in many of the directions you think it might go but it's
quite entertaining while it does it and the animation is very good and riz armored who plays the chap
is extremely good in the voice acting the voice acting is generally pretty good but he is
outstanding i think and i enjoyed it quite a lot and it's definitely worth one hour and 42 minutes
of your netflix time which is how i watched it and it was a hugo finalist i think last year yes
we discussed it in our hugo episode and you guys said it was good and i was like i'll definitely
get around to watching that and now i have it's quite good isn't it so there we go it's quite good
and i'm picking it i want riz amed to be the first asian james bond oh he'd be good just massive
non sequitur but like i know not everyone agrees with that i just think he would be elos good in a
suit he's great actor like come on guys let's do this what about dev patello he looks good in a suit
good actor i like i don't see why we can't actually have a pair of crime fighting spy dudes in a in
a double act here this would be good too i also kind of think anyway i let's not have a huge
aggression right now about how they should do james bond films but i've thought about that as
well i mean i think if you're going to have a duo it's not james bond it's like the man from
uncle or something that's fine yeah that'd be good you but but why can't it be james bond gold and
i had double o six and admittedly he turned out to be the baddie exactly but there's like probably
eight other double o's let's have some more of them in the films can you imagine can you imagine
a james bond film where it was dev patello learning to be the new double o seven from riz amed
that'd be fucking great imagine we just remade golden eye with riz amed and dev patello
yes do it do it cowards do it amazon get on it liz do you have a pick i am going to pick the case
the gold nidal oh it is a puzzle game i don't think alison has picked it have you played it though
um i've played it i don't think i picked it so much picked it no i don't think i don't think you have
and i don't think either of us either of me or liz picked nimono so i think it is three new picks
this time what what platform did you play on liz i played it on Netflix games or or on my mobile
telephone which is not great actually you probably want to play it on something with a slightly bigger
screen because it will test your eyesight for certain puzzles so basically case gold nidal is a kind of
detective puzzle game where you click through there's various cases and you basically click through
sort of in a point and clicky way on little pixel art of what's going on in the story of the golden
idol which is a mysterious relic which has some supernatural powers and as you go through you are
basically it gives you kind of a an outline of what's going on with lots of missing names and verbs
and nouns and that kind of thing and you have to fill them all in and piece the narrative together
from the clues you can put together by clicking through the different screens and it's very fun
there's a main game of about nine episodes i think and then two dlc's i'm currently in the middle of
the second dlc trying to figure out what on earth is going on and it's very good i think it's
pictured about the right level like most of the puzzles are doable but you have to think and then
occasionally i've come across somewhere you can do it but i sort of brute-forced a couple of them
because i didn't really figure out what's going on and then there's somewhere i've just been like
yeah i don't know what's going on here i'm gonna get a hint i will say there is a slight bug at least
in the android version of the netflix games one where it will accidentally think you have finished
the last episode before you have filled in all the blanks and then give you kind of what happened
which is unfortunate but i was most the way to figuring that out anyway okay so you should definitely
play it but maybe not on an android phone on netflix until they have updated that but i think it'd be
great on an ipad or something yeah i've got netflix at the moment so i will play it on my ipad yes i
think that bug where you learn too much in the final puzzle is is there an ipad as well i think
that's happened to me that was the old thought podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me
and it's goodbye from me
next time you're running podcast programming can i suggest an item on how to get your
co-hosts shut up so you can get a word in eduase oh it's true it would just be me
and you too and you won't be able to see anything i don't think that's true i don't think that's
true i think there are other podcasts that have this issue liz you are there is a podcast i love
called three being salad and uh the liz on that podcast is mike wozniak uh because he is the one
that struggles to get a word in so like it is not just you you are not alone i feel like that on
my mike wozniak that's my parasocial thing oh bloody love mike wozniak the theme music for this
episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud and competec.com used under a creative commons
attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]