Why would you even say that?
I mean, what happens in your own dreams that you don't draw is your own business, Alison.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 163rd episode of Octothorpe.
Which is refusing steadfastly ever to let its son leave the island.
On the 2nd of July 2026, I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
Swim Headphone Corner.
Trish, who was the person who asked for swim headphone chat in the first place, said thanks so much for answering.
I don't think I can afford the recommended shocks model, but I appreciated the link and I was ridiculously happy when John included the previously deleted three-minute discussion about them.
Yes indeed.
I think that didn't you actually include a brand new discussion about them, John, rather than the previous deleted one?
We recorded a whole new discussion just for you.
That was even longer.
And and for other listeners, it turns out that other listeners are also interested in swim headphone chat.
Yes.
Also in swim headphone chat.
Neil Harrison said, I very much enjoyed the swim headphones segment.
My running headphones are the shocks bone conducting headphones as well.
I use them to listen to this episode.
And the discussion caused me to put my fingers in the ears to get empirical conf confirmation that they work only by bow conduction and the podcast actually got significantly louder, which was weird.
I think if you're thinking about buying running headphones and you ever go swimming, you might want to buy the shock swim headphones rather than the run headphones because the swim headphones work fine for running, but the other reverse is not true
Yes.
And and on them being unaffordable, I did mention last time I'd bought about four sets of swim headphones.
Um and these are the first ones that have ever worked.
I I guess it's like Vibes Boots
Put a pound in a bucket every time you go swimming and then eventually you'll have enough of your swim efforts.
I had been eyeing up a pair of Shock's Open Swim Pro Bone Conduction Headphones for quite a while.
And I got paid and I have taken the plunge.
That was a pun, listeners.
Ooh.
Oh ho.
And now I also have a pair of Shox OpenSwim Pro headphones, completing the trifecta.
Ah, but
Important question John.
Did you get the black ones or the orange ones?
Orange ones, obviously, I'm not an animal.
I also got the orange ones.
Um it was my
Personal tribute to John.
Either that or I thought they'd be much more noticeable if you dropped them somewhere in a swoop pool.
One of those two.
Which ones have you got, Liz?
I've got the orange ones, but they were ten pounds cheaper, so Oh I went to a place called John Lewis.
and purchased them.
And they were not cheaper, they were the same price.
But that's right.
Yeah, but I went to a place called the Internet, so Yeah, I could have done that.
And actually if I'd bought them direct from the website, because of Black not Black Friday, Amazon Prime Day, I could have got a free gift bag.
But I don't think I really want a free gift bag, so that that's fine.
No.
And it comes the I was pleased that the headphones come with a little pair of swim earplugs.
That was nice.
But also, I was slightly irritated, you can't delete audio from them without plugging them into your computer, but you're not supposed to plug them into your computer when they're still might be a bit wet.
Which means that I have to like set a reminder every time I finish swimming to delete the episode I've just listened to.
And that is suboptimal.
That would be good if they fixed that.
But I actually found the process of putting the audio on the headphones very easy, so that was alright.
In
Non shall we move on, 'cause in in non-Swim headphone news, we heard from Ali Baker, who says, uh the Francis Harding Symposium, the keynote speaker sounds familiar
Ellie Bleaker, Alex Barker, Ali Baker, something like that.
So yes, we did not mention that friend of the podcast and podcaster in her own right, Ali Baker, is doing the keynote at the Francis Harding Symposium.
So another reason for you to buy your tickets and go along.
Yes.
And tickets are no longer available if you want the lunch, but if you don't mind about the lunch, you can still go and get tickets.
And I will put the link back in the show notes, listeners.
Um and that is being organized by Farah Mendelssohn and Virginia Preston.
We heard from
Tammy Coxson.
We heard from Tammy Coxson in a variety of guises with a variety of hats.
But I will read Tammy's thoughts about Nuremberg.
So Tammy says.
Had Brisbane been performing in December the way that they've been performing sort of in the last couple of months?
then she would have warned Nuremberg away from bidding, but she thought Brisbane looked quite weak and the Nuremberg bid looked like a promising alternative, which is why she jumped on board at the time.
Uh but she says she thinks Colin and her and other people they spoke to at SmothCon was very clear about what running WorldCons entails and also very clear on the timeline.
She thought, and still thinks, that it's theoretically possible that a sprint bid could get all the pieces in place in time, but
Basically they couldn't sprint fast enough, so um they didn't feel like moving forward to the vote was a good idea.
She says she does feel bad about the impact of this on both the LA and Brisbane Brisbane finances.
I mean I will say like I don't think Nuremberg should feel bad about that.
It is a negative thing about the way things have gone, but I don't think like ultimately you shouldn't bid a Worldcon if you're not confident you can deliver the Worldcon.
And I and I think
I think bidding a Worldcon to aid the coffers of the conventions around you, that that is a level of self-sacrifice that is uh that is this unwarranted, I think.
I think I think this was the right decision
She says she's gonna become a friend of the bid for Brisbane and vote so that she doesn't have to worry about her membership in the future.
And I do want to say
Generally speaking, so LA has been struggling for money a little bit because their memberships have been trending very low.
So I will say, and and I think this is true of all worldcons, is that the earlier a worldcon has money, the better able they are to spend it
So if you are confident that you're going to go to a Worldcon, it is worth supporting them at a level that will mean you can do that as early as you can.
So I am about to
Friend Dublin and um friend of the show Meg MacDonald has offered to do filk with a traffic cone on her head if you
uh by your Dublin um pre-support or friend at a sufficient level.
Um I can't remember the exact things, but I'll link them in the show notes.
And and so I'm gonna do that and make her write me filk.
That was filk, right?
Filk.
Yeah.
I thought that was a one weekend only offer, John, so I will let you check with Meg whether you're making a filk fur
a longer period now.
Uh good point.
I mean I did I did think seriously about okay how much money do I have?
How much would I need to be a super friend and make make wear a traffic horn hat.
I have been tempted to be a super friend
It is quite expensive, but I will definitely be at Dublin and I do want Dublin to be good, so I'm a bit like maybe I should put my money where my mouth is for
home and nearby conventions.
Meg hasn't offered to don a mermaid costume.
I don't know what level you have to back at to achieve that.
Meg, write in.
Yes.
I was gonna say something quite rude and I will not.
Liz.
I'm too scared of Meg.
That is fair.
I don't think Meg would make a lovely mermaid.
Oh yeah, no, I uh completely agree.
Ming wrote to us num numerous times on our
Facebook thread and was one of the people who woke up at Swancon to learn about Nuremberg uh at the Nuremberg announcement and therefore that Brisbane should win the
um site selection race.
Um he's now working on the Brisbane bid, which is good and is very excited by the idea of a Worldcon that is only
Four hours away.
I mean and I it is fundamentally your fault for moving to New Zealand though, Ming, so you know.
Um he also attended satellite virtually
Um, because they had an item called Ming's Minging Morsels.
He had brought two jars of jobby nut butter from Malaysia to Glasgow, which does sound like a minging morsel
And other people said that that was quite a good programme item.
Indeed at the time I did not go to it.
He also says, can we tell
him more about the tradition that if you give someone twenty units of local currency, they have to run a Worldcon.
Just asking out of mere idle curiosity.
So if you're anywhere near Ming in Wellington, please press twenty New Zealand dollars on him pronto.
I think it was um so very sadly recently John Dowd has passed.
Um and I think it was John Dowd who there was a convention committee and it might have been New Zealand 2020
that was offering pre-supports if you gave them twenty units of any currency, and so John took them rupees.
Which 20 rupees does not equal much money
He did also say I'd be happy to pay you 20 of a currency that makes more sense for your finances, but uh he was very proud of himself for uh for for doing the hack.
I mean I I think the winner there would be to give someone uh twenty Vietnamese dong, which is uh five thousandths of a penny.
But I don't think you can because you can't get a twenty denomination and do it.
So yeah.
That is that is yeah, there is a there is a limit to the to the joke.
The joke is limited by the production of currency.
I I would like to say that I don't think uh he said Ming's Minging morsels, but I will say that I have just finished that the chocolate Ming brought me from New Zealand when he visited.
and it was proper good.
So thank you Ming.
But was it Jobby Nut chocolate?
Mm no.
It was very nice Whitaker's brand chocolate.
Excellent.
Raj wrote to us to ask, have we ever been to FantasyCon?
He's wondering if it's more of an industry networking event for writers or ones for fans.
I've never been to FantasyCon.
Have you guys been to FantasyCon?
Nope.
Lots of my friends go.
Um I think that yeah, it is more it is more for people who write, but it is not exclusively for people who write.
I wouldn't want to
Suggest you shouldn't do it.
Uh yeah, think could be pretty good.
Might be might be worth a day trip to see it since St.
Glasgow Raj
Yeah, if if there was a if there was a fantasy con in Newcastle, I would go.
Yeah.
Y Yes, the the the FantasyCon was gonna run in Holloway, which is about
ten minutes down the road on by the train for me and I was gonna go to that as a day tripper.
Um in fact I was going to take a table as a day tripper and and sell badges to the plain people of FantasyCon.
But that was a Covid plan and it disappeared
Raj also says Ottoman Coffee House is great.
Is there a link to the top 100 that John used to find it?
There is.
We should place it in the show notes
I will say I have been to only one of the world's top hundred coffee shops, according to this person, and I didn't think it was that good, and there are much better ones.
But probably Ottoman is great.
Ottoman was great.
I will say so um according to this list, the best British
So actually, according to this list, the only two of the best coffee shops I think are both in Scotland.
Uh there are none in Northern Ireland, Wales, or England.
So the same people have done like
country specific top hundreds which don't seem to have a website.
I have looked.
Um but one of the coffee shops in Newcastle has the branding in their thing being in the top hundred.
I think the coffee shop in Newcastle is better than Ottoman Coffee House in Glasgow
So I would agree with Liz, there is definitely some fuzziness here.
But Ottoman was lovely, so I would highly recommend.
The best coffee shop in the world is Onyx Coffee Lab, which is located in
Arkansas in a city called Rogers.
So I I'm never going to go to that.
I when I see things like I we are one of the world's hundred best coffee shops.
I am reminded of the fact that I whenever I go to a fish and chip shop, it is always the world's best fish and chips, or one of Britain's best fish and chips, or in the top
Five fish and chips or has a gold fish and chips award.
And I concluded that there had to be quite a lot of fish and chips awards, and I suspect it's the same for coffee shops.
Yeah, I think the interesting thing about this is that um like they per like it's like a combination of it's a combination of public vote and like an expert jury.
Um and you can apply to be on it.
And what's also weird is that the top 100 European coffee shops, so the 50th placed on the top 100 worldwide
is in the Isle of Sky and there's nothing in London on the top 100 worldwide but that Isle of Sky one is fifteenth on the European and there's a London one which is twelfth and I'm like, well if it if it's better in Europe, why isn't it better in the world?
And I don't know
But what I really want to do is just find wanky third wave coffee places and it's a very good tool to help me do that.
So hurrah.
There's also a great app called the European Coffee Trip.
um which also can help you find uh wanky uh third wave coffee places near to you and has rather more locations on it.
So
um and and recommends the one I really like in Newcastle and another one I really like in Newcastle.
So I will put a link to that in the show notes as well.
It seems extraordinary that that John has more rarefied tastes in coffee shops than I do, but there we go.
Oh I have I have had
I've had the coffee at your house, and so I am not surprised.
Oh, that was me.
Oh.
I'm doing something different with the coffee than you are, probably.
That is true.
I don't have I don't I what I really care about is the taste of the coffee.
I'm not the ancillaries are not important to me.
I think you are much more I I'm happy to have coffee in a hole, like in a well
And you could lower the coffee down to me in a bucket.
I'd be like, oh coffee.
Um whereas you like things like sofas and nice pastries.
I do.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
But also I if I if I drink coffee with
C thrilling abandon, then I Vibrate into another dimension.
Now can't sleep for a week and get jitters, so you know
I'm I'm in the process of discovering I was discovering the Thriller Vice Matcha the other day, which is not a thing I'd have thought I'd have ever said.
We had some commentary about the eclipse.
Um Paul Weimer and Mike Scott need to have an arm wrestle at the next convention they both appear at.
Okay, so that's something I wouldn't pay to see.
You wouldn't pay to see?
Yeah, exactly so.
Who would you pay to see Arm Wrestle?
Oh, redacted.
Paul Weimer writes in to say you can see eclipses in cities just fine in fact and sent us a picture of
an eclipse and weirdly in the sky above the eclipse there are the words copyright Paul Weemer twenty twenty four um which is quite the I've not seen that in my astronomical data before Paul.
You'll have to tell me uh how that manifested in the sky
Mike Scott confidently asserts that it doesn't get properly dark in cities.
I have been to the countryside, Mike, so I am familiar with uh light pollution.
And Tammy Coxson sent in some commentary.
Firstly, she corrected me on clouds and then realised I'd correct myself later.
But thank you very much for writing in Tammy.
And she also sent some lovely eclipse photos on Blue Sky.
Um I will say I am seeing the eclipse in Gijon, which is a tiny uh Spanish city uh in the north.
Uh I don't even think it's a city.
It's where Ian Watson lived, which I did not know until he passed.
But uh is not a large town and uh I do not expect there to be much light pollution.
We heard from Jake Sella Brookens.
uh who enjoyed the Clark discussion and is looking forward to more and ooh there has been lots of Clark discussion online.
I'm enjoying it.
Um
And he also says that a little bit ago he for ARB, ancillary review of books, he wrote up some findings on the Hugo's overlap with other awards, which we will link to.
But he also put together a little spreadsheet gadget to compare SFF Awards list to other SFF Awards.
And I have looked at this gadget and I deem it to be a very cool gadget.
Yes.
And those things that I did not know you could do
in like a Google spreadsheet.
So yeah, it's very nifty.
What I will suggest is if you want to play with this in detail, make a copy of it and put it in your own Google Drive, because if two people use it at the same time it can get confusing.
So Casella has made a copy.
Um but also you can just clone it into your own little area and play with it.
But yeah, it's really cool.
Uh this also means that to to do this blog post, um Gasella has put together like a great big list of lots of information on lots of
Science fiction awards which is linked from his blog post on ARB but also I am now going to steal it because it's a lovely day to set.
Thank you, Cassella
Scott Edelman wrote to say that all I talk about um Glasgow reminded him of his wonderful memories to Tantrum uh visits to Tantrum Donuts and the Broken Clock Patisserie.
when he was in Glasgow.
Did I mention Tantrum Donuts on the podcast?
Uh I don't think you did.
Yeah, I did.
Well so I I went to Tantrum Donuts having spotted it.
earlier in the weekend and going, Haha, we must go back to Tantrum Donuts for coffee and donuts on the last morning which we did and they were very, very good so that's a shout out.
I don't know the broken broken clocked patisserie, do either of you?
Um, I've googled it, but that doesn't probably count.
It is on a website called bestrestaurantsingglasgow.
com.
Fantastic.
And it has an Instagram.
I'm trying to work out what the best
It's got on Instagram and a Facebook, I'll link them in the show notes listeners.
And looking at the pictures, they look quite tasty.
So yeah.
He has also bought his membership to Eastercon 2027.
So apparently we we addicted him to Easter Cons which is good and he's looking forward to going back to Glasgow and eating more Glas Region Donuts
So that sounds fantastic to me.
Good.
There is also there is also a place I went when I was at Satellite, which is Pasteis Lisboa, which do amazing pasteldanata.
I don't know how to pronounce it the Portuguese word pastis uh but that is how it's done in Portuguese.
Pastel de nata
There we go, nailed it.
Vibrant food culture.
Still haven't had a pizza crunch, but they are opening a branch of
a Scottish fish and chip chain I forget the name of in Newcastle and they do do deep-fried Mars bars, deep-fried haggas and pizza crunch.
So that's my lunches for the next year sorted and then I'll die of a heart attack.
Yes!
Yeah.
Alison is less excited by this than me.
Uh Al Alison got a hypertension notification from her watch the other day.
Oh no.
But I mean it's like it was like a hundred and three degrees or something at the time, so That's fair.
But apparently cardiac arrests have been up forty percent in London this week.
Yep, the number of excess deaths in Paris was fifteen hundred this week from the heat, and in London it was five hundred, something like that.
Okay, so apparently a lot of lads went to the test match and drank their normal amounts of beer and then got taken to hospital and some of them are still there.
So honestly guys, don't do that.
Can can we drag back to topic and do another letter?
We heard from Christopher J.
Garcia who says Olstalk transitioned into a swimhope phone podcast so gradually he barely noticed
It now competes with his newest podcast, Moist EarTunes.
Thank you very much, Chris.
Oh no.
Well and he's going to start work on the best games Hugo issue of the drink tank to promote board games.
Yes
Board games.
Excellent.
Yeah.
Still doing a board game every day.
Frederick Coulter wrote to say if you rely on Google search f
AI for information and I think I can say firmly that no none of the three of us were doing that.
And then we heard from Kate McDonald, who writes in
She basically says, what is SWOFCON and SPOFCon?
We referred to it several times in the satellite and world con sections, but maybe I misheard.
So
There's two things here, so SmothCon, S-M-O-F-C-O-N, uh is a convention of people who run conventions.
So people who run commissions are affectionately known in some circles as secret masters of fandom because they're not masters and it's not a secret, so it's a sort of ironic phrase.
Um some people have moved away from that in recent times because it got it's people started taking it too seriously on both sides of the divide, I think.
But that's basically a convention that runs every December for people who are interested in running conventions to go to.
And then SwanCon is an Australian convention, which Alison mentioned.
Um it's it's the Perth Convention, Perth is in Western Australia, the s River Swan
is the river that runs through Perth and a lot of Perth things have swan logos and things.
Nice.
So hopefully that answers your questions.
Kate.
But please keep writing in with other questions and obviously if other people listening have questions write in with those.
Or you can send us more eclipse pics.
Or pictures of your cats.
Whatever.
Pictures of your swimming.
Picture your swim headphones.
Mm.
Pictures of your black cat in an eclipse?
Yep.
And then we got a question from Neil Ottenstein.
Neil says, now that the Elicon 5 business meeting agenda is available, are we going to get a preview episode with the highlights on what sessions slash discussions would be most important to attend?
Shall I segue?
Yes.
So yes, the LACON business meeting agenda is out.
The business meetings start on
Friday, July 17th, in the morning Pacific Daylight Time, which is gonna be like mid-afternoon UK and very late on Friday for me, I think.
Uh and there are uh subsequent three online meetings and then the site selection business meeting in person at the convention.
And yes, we do intend to go through the business meeting agenda
Maybe not in exhaustive detail, but there are definitely some motions that we will be discussing.
But we will have another episode before they before the business meeting starts.
And so
Hopefully we'll if we don't get to it today, we'll get to it in two weeks' time.
But yeah, basically the first business meeting will be elections to committees and the business which has been passed on to LACOM
And then the second business meeting will be doing the new constitutional changes, so new business.
And then the third business meeting
is going to be a special one in executives session reporting on the stuff about Chengdu that was started last year.
So basically if you
Have something passed on from last year that you are really uh keen to vote for or against.
You need to go to the first business meeting.
Um if you want to look at the new business which is starting this year, you need to definitely be at the second one
on the first of August.
And if you want to see the executive session, then you need to make sure you go to one on August the ninth
I'll put a link to the page with the details and I've listed the dates in the show notes, listeners.
Thank you, John.
And then there will be an in-person site selection business meeting on thirtieth of August.
Yes.
Although as previously we discussed, not a lot of tension in it now.
It's
Probably gonna be Brisbane unless some people get very very very organised very very quickly and very very convincingly.
So it's gonna be Brisbane.
Well I think yes.
The deadline for filing has passed, but you could technically still have a write-in, I suppose, but it it's extremely unlikely.
Yes, it's extremely unlikely, but I I don't want to say definitely, I'm being like cautious.
And I will of course be submitting my right-in for Mike Scott's house.
We suggest all listeners do the same.
But will it be dark enough to see the eclipse?
Yes.
But it will be the wrong side of the planet to see the eclipse.
So it's tricky.
Hmm.
Pros and cons really, yeah.
Pros and cons.
Ha ha
It'll be dark enough to watch the tele showing the eclipse.
Mmm.
I've now been to Mark's TV room and can confirm that there is enough room for three people to watch television in comfort.
Simultaneously.
Excellent.
That's good for program, right?
Yeah.
No, no, for for watching television.
For the eclipse.
But also for the WorldCom program, y you know, because all of the program's gonna have to be in that room as well, right?
Uh oh no, I think the program can be in the main living dining area which will probably take twelve to fifteen people in comfort.
Look, we'll just put Marquee on the lawn.
We know this is how it works now
The Lord, that's a massive slope.
Oh my god.
So um twelve to fifteen people is enough for just under
to Hugo finalists if the new uh amendment to the Wispwas constitution passes that we will talk about next time.
I thought you were going to say that it was enough for a quarant Whisper's business meeting.
It is enough for a core West business meeting, that is true.
Twelve people.
Oh, I assume the business meetings would still be online.
As we've established that that is corrant.
So there you go.
Uh true.
Good point.
Thank you for keeping our nonsense accurate nonsense, Liz.
He's got to be constitutionally accurate nonsense, John.
Come on.
As we have plugged several times on the pot previously, Alison and John
were on Scott Edelman's podcast Eating the Fast Fantastic, uh, which I listened to.
So I wanted to see if they'd said anything rude about me.
And they didn't say anything rude about me.
It's very nice.
Um but I did I did think it was an interesting podcast.
Um and I'm gonna say what I thought was interesting is I think you could see that there is
Podcast John and not Podcast John.
And on Eating the Fantastic, I think you're a bit more not Podcast John.
And so that was interesting.
Like you get to see what is behind the curtain a little bit.
Whereas I think Alison has more integration between her podcast and not podcast.
personas.
Interesting.
Ooh.
I thought I was being quite podcasty.
I thought you'd be a bit well I thought you were being a bit less podcasty, but
No, that's fair.
You probably pop po podcasting in bits and then I'm just having fun eating chicken in bits and I'm sure that that's what Scott is trying to achieve, or part of what Scott is trying to achieve with his podcast.
Yes, I mean I think that's partly because you were eating chicken, is you were a bit more you know, a bit more relaxed because you're eating chicken and you know, this is a good a good idea from Scott's part to have everyone kind of
eating together and therefore maybe a bit more chill and a bit more relaxed than you might otherwise be.
Yeah.
It's almost like he's thought about the format.
And planned things.
And it's good at it.
Yeah.
Yeah, I I mean he's done a lot of episodes as well, hasn't he?
Quite a lot.
How how how what what number episode were we of Eating the Fantastic?
You were two hundred and eighty four.
So he yes, yes.
quite a lot more experience than us.
I did think it was interesting when you were talking about how many podcasts make it to episode one and never get any further.
No, it I mean, yeah, he's right about that.
And yes, somehow we have
We have made it this far.
And yeah.
So I I thought it was interesting.
So anyone who is interesting in the inner workings of the pod should go and have a listen.
And if you're not interested in the inner workings of the pod, then probably go and listen to someone else's eating the fantastic, uh which might be more interesting.
Yes, I think that is probably fair.
Uh I will say that we did have some listener feedback to us from people who had listened to Eating the Fantastic and thought that it might be better aimed at us.
For instance
Tammy Cotson wrote in uh to tell us that TJI Fridays is an American chain and Alison couldn't be more wrong, which yeah, it's probably better uh sent to us than to Scott.
Yes, founded in New York City
Apparently.
Yeah, no, I was completely wrong.
But yes, if you want the complete story, I recommend clicking through to Tammy's comment because it's very interesting.
Yes.
Do do not take this on a reflection of ha how often you think we are wrong about things that you that no one of our listeners have intimate knowledge about to write in to correct us.
Don't consider that.
I I I refer us back to
Um our we are just like mates chatting in the pub mission statement, which means that obviously we'll be about as wrong as people who are chatting in the pub, which is quite often really.
I don't know what to say to that, but
Maybe that's just me.
I think if we're in the pub I might say Alison, you were talking absolute bull nonsense more.
It's interesting cause the other thing is well no because if we if Alison had said that on here, I would have googled it and told her she was wrong on the pot.
But because we were walking to Nando's and then eating Nando's, I couldn't check.
So I was just like, oh.
And I didn't I didn't go back to it.
So it's yeah, it's interesting.
I hope everyone enjoyed the episode.
Thanks to everyone who wrote uh about it.
Um we have had feedback from other people as well as Tammy and uh the reception seems to have been broadly positive.
Hurrah Uh right, shall we discuss Eurocons?
So yes, Eurocon is next week.
By the time you get this, I will be at Eurocon and it will be in full swing.
Um This is the thing where I'd normally say I have here are all the things I'm going to be doing at Eurocon and I have not
signed up for programme and I am not any part of the organizing committee.
Thank you very much for organizing the Eurocon and I am not sitting on any tables particularly though I might help out with a couple for an hour or two.
And I have no commitments whatsoever.
I think this may be a first time for a very, very, very long time.
That's been the case to convention for me
So what you gonna do?
Drink German beer?
Drink German beer, tourist a bit in Germany, Tammy's sorting out a cocktail trip, you know, that sort of thing.
The usual.
Well, yes, except without all of the commitment.
So um what that means is if you're coming to Metropolitan going, Oh, I really hope I can see Allison because I'm a huge octhorphthyl and I like
to tell us so you will need to find me in a bar which should not be too difficult or message me.
And it sounds like if you want to avoid Alison you should go to the programme.
Ha ha True.
That's always true.
No, I do I do go to program.
Sometimes I might go to the program.
It's a possibility.
I haven't actually looked at the program yet, but I assume there is one.
So very exciting.
Yes, and then uh
In future Eurocon news, the Eurocon for 2027, we already know is going to be in Lisbon
And there was some discussion this week because the British Fantasy Convention is this year uh in twenty twenty-seven I should say, is also going to be taking over some of the duties of the World FantasyCon.
Oh, so it it's actually going to be World Fantasy card as well, is it?
So it sounds like and I must have amissed some discussion about this, that basically
The World FancyCon board, who are uh kind of I think they do the site selection, usually people sort of bid to do things, but the board is one who chooses, not like a member vote or something.
Wanted to try and run
Tw the twenty seventy-seven COM outside the United States.
So this year it's going to be in uh California.
Last year it was in uh the US as well.
And so they wanted to do one outside the US, but there wasn't a viable bid.
And so essentially the British FantasyCon in twenty twenty seven will include the World Fantasy Awards and some other World Fantasy Con features, but it will not be like a full World Fantasy Con.
I assume this is basically
People who would normally go to World FantasyCon, who don't want to go to the US, who would like somewhere to gather, will probably go to the British Fantasy Society event
and there will be the giving of the world fantasy awards.
The awkward thing is that they're gonna now be on the same date as the Eurocom.
Which I think is I mean my opinion this is not like a huge clash.
It is quite unfortunate, especially given that they've taken on these extra
well fancy con aspects and therefore be kind of a bigger con than they otherwise would be.
Um and it's probably too late, you know, it's too late to change the dates.
um because they've already scheduled 2027.
But it is awkward, especially because the team who are chairing the FancyCon 2027 are part of the team
uh bidding for the 2030 Eurocom, which will be voted on in 2028, and that means if you're at another convention then you're presumably not going to be at the 2027 Eurocom
And if they were a large team, they could obviously have people from the team at the twenty twenty seven Eurocon representing them.
Yeah, I think we don't know.
I mean it this is a while off, right?
This is eighteen months away
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
We don't know really who is involved, but it just ends up being a really unfortunate like thing that at the point that you say we would like to run a Eurocon, one of the first things that comes up is
And we're also running another con on the same day as the twenty twenty seven one.
Yeah, so that's the that's the thing, right?
If if I think there is a
If you are bidding to run a Eurocon, I sort of expect you to be going to Eurocons and talking to the people who run Eurocons.
This is something that, for instance, when China started trying to run a Worldcon, Chinese people came to WorldCons to meet Worldcon community and talk to them and be a bit more integrated with the Worldcon community.
And I think in general, if you want to run a Eurocon, you should probably be going to Eurocons, uh, and if you want to run an Eastercon, you should probably go into Eastercons.
And you probably shouldn't be scheduling conventions that directly clash with
the convention you're going to run because that makes it very much look like you're not part of that community and you're doing it for reasons that are less community-minded.
Yeah, I mean I think if somebody wanted to run the Eastercon and was running a convention at Easter, I think the Eastercon committee would take a n r remarkably dim view of that.
And I
Yes.
Imagine that the Eurocon commun there is an issue with hearts and minds in the Eurocon community as well and and it's not that the this isn't a new thing, because it's not that the
The fact that it's now also World Fallacycon has caused the clash.
It was already clashing.
So there was a proof previous decision made to run World Fat to run FallacyCon on the same weekend as the Eurocon.
It's true, but the Eurocon I mean, I would just say I think for Eastercon it's different because I can tell you what the date is of Eastercon going quite far into the future.
I can't tell you the dates of Eurocon's far into the future.
It is a bit trickier 'cause about forty years ago
Jerry Sullivan got a chart from John Dolman with the dates of Easter for many years into the future written on it.
And she pinned it up by her desk.
And it's been very useful to her ever since and it has just run out.
So thank you, John, for doing that.
And if you're listening, we need another one now.
I'll just ask her Google AI, that'll tell me all the dates, right
Yeah.
Sorry, it's not clear to me when the dates for FantasyCon 2027 were originally announced.
Yeah, I think I think if they were both 2027 cons, they may have
you know, these two cons may have been planning in parallel and announced at pretty much the same time at which point, you know.
But I think if I was doing it I wouldn't want to
If I was the World Fantasy Convention board, I'd probably have thought, oh, maybe we could expand our reach with Eurocon rather than going to the UK.
Which is quite an Anglocentric choice.
Like you could have the World Fantasy Convention Convention Awards at Eurocon.
That's true.
You could have them in the Montreal Worldcon, also not in the USA.
Um so like, you know, you've got options there that don't involve clashing with the Eurocon.
But also I think if I was the 2027 FantasyCon team
I would have avoided I would have avoided taking it on because of the optics of competing with the Eurocon.
So I think I think I don't yeah.
The the logic on both sides is opaque to me
And I don't quite understand it.
No, that's an interesting thought.
I mean I don't think you'd want to take the fancy World Fancy Awards to uh a WorldCom because you'd kind of
clash with the Hugos, right?
You don't want to announce the Fantasy Awards and the Hugos on successive nights 'cause I think you're both gonna trample on each other's um you know, publicity and press releases and so on.
As far as I can tell, FantasyCon twenty twenty seven dates were announced.
In June 2026.
So as far as I can tell, they were well aware of where the Eurocon was and they have scheduled this to clash.
If anyone has a source for an earlier announcement, please write in.
But I cannot find one
Anywhere online.
Yeah.
Every news source has it in June twenty sixth.
But you know, we you know, dates can sometimes be tricky and there may not have been a f you know, full selection of dates available, but I do think it's less of a thing if you're like
an essentially, you know, domestic UK com.
Yeah.
But yeah, so it's just a bit unfortunate.
But also if you wanna go to the World Fancy Awards, you now don't have to go very far in twenty twenty seven for most of our listeners, so
Yes, although I will be at Eurocon.
Cause yeah.
Oh, are you gonna be going to Eurocon in twenty twenty seven?
That is currently the plan.
'Cause you wanna go and have past dinata.
Yup.
Yeah.
I mean I I I'm whereas I'm kinda like, Oh, I'm going to smofcon in Lisbon, do I need to go back to Lisbon so soon?
Yeah, Eurocons are wildly different every time though.
So I mean that's you know, that is one of the delights of them.
They are they are less alike than other travelling conventions, in my view.
Indeed.
Uh the Eurocon has announced uh a person attending the Eurocon is Adrian Tchaikovsky.
Uh so that's good.
Oh, which which one?
2027?
Yeah.
Ooh.
I don't know if Adrian's a guest.
He's just confirmed.
So I don't know.
I don't maybe they don't really have a concept of guests.
There's no guest listing
Maybe they're gonna be a bit like um some comics ones do where you sort of have confirmed you know, a confirmed list of people appearing and you add to it over time.
Which is quite a neat way of doing it.
In the show notes, did you want to list the twenty twenty eight bid?
Future Eurocon bids, so at MetropolCon in Berlin, there will be a
uh bid for Croatia in 2028, which would be um Sfera S-F-E-R-A, and I think I've been to um Zubrovnik.
But I've not been to the mainland Croatia.
I'd love to go to Croatia.
Dubrovnik was great, so I assume the rest of Croatia is also great.
So that would be good.
Um there doesn't seem to be any news about that other than a uh listing on the Metropolitan website for the fan table that the Croatian fans will have.
Can't find a link uh better than that, listeners.
If you find one, please get in touch.
And then in 2029, there is a bid for Poland.
Liz, do you want to tell us about Poland?
Uh it will be in Warsaw
Uh and it's it's a fans association from Warsaw who have run multiple Polish conventions before uh and w would like to run one in twenty twenty-nine.
Sounds good.
Yes.
Alison, do you want to tell us about the 2030 bit?
Whi which one?
Are there two?
Yeah.
Well there's a there are two announced ones, yeah.
So as
as I think we know because we've discussed it previously, there is a bid to hold the twenty thirty Eurocon in Birmingham, um, along with the to be combined with the Eastercon and all under the auspices of the BSFA.
We've talked about that quite a bit already, and I'm sure that'll come out.
over the next little while.
And there is also now uh apparently a bid for Copenhagen.
Um and I think this is just literally a placeholder bid at the moment, but they have a um they have a blue s
um page and and a Facebook page and an Instagram page and I haven't I don't think any of them have actual content on them beyond we're thinking of doing a Oh no, they do have a couple of things.
Just here we are and
Come and say hello.
Why don't you go and say hello to them at Metropolcom?
I will 100% say what would you like to say on the world's
Premier podcast about science fiction science fiction phantom and swim headphones next week while I'm in Berlin.
Yes, take your microphone.
Yeah uh oh no, oh god.
See, you've gone you've gone too far now, John.
You've gone you've gone too far there.
You've suggested a level of professionalism that we don't have.
I didn't mean to engender existential dread.
But I will try and say hello to them at um I'll try to say hello to a lot of people at Metropolcomp.
That sounds like uh something that is not too hard for me to commit to.
Yep.
And that's the other thing that's weird about scheduling convention that competes with Eurocon, because if they were unopposed for 2030 Eurocon, you might think, oh well, you know, they'll probably get it because it's unopposed even if they do ruffle some feathers
But when it is opposed, uh that takes on a rather different um kettle of fish.
The person who is opposing or one of the people involved with the Copenhagen bid
is Sanabo Claumark, uh, who was at SmothCon and seemed very lovely and uh full of excitement and vim and vigour.
And she has been enthusiastically networking with Smoths in Europe and building community and other things like that
And they say Copenhagen would be a fantastic city to hold a Eurocon in and I that that does sound right.
Yep.
I mean I'm not not that I would ever dis um Birmingham and in particular the Eddie Sea area, which is obviously one of um Europeans cultural and architectural highlights.
Um, but Copenhagen.
Hoo-hoo.
Yeah, I would generally rather I've not been to Denmark, so I'd rather probably go to Denmark, but we will see.
Uh i uh well you could also go to Legoland.
What had it even occurred to me?
That is interesting.
I mean presume you could go to to Birmingham and then go to Legoland.
Windsor, right?
That is also true.
But Legoland in Denmark is more Lego than Lego anywhere else.
I d I mean I don't know for sure that the Legoland in Denmark is better than the Legoland in England, but I sort of assume it is
I don't think it is, I think it's just more Danish.
But it's also it demarks where Lego's from.
It's it's spiritually like from the home of Lego rather than being, you know, in a random place.
See it's got that going.
Um, I have been to Denmark and Copenhagen in particular and I did like it, but you should start saving up now.
Yeah, I've I've um I've visited Scandinavian countries, Liz, so that is good advice
Pff oof.
Mm.
Yeah, it's a Scandinavian country, guys.
It it's more it's gonna be more expensive than your swim headphones, let's put it that way
But now because Legoland Windsor is operated by all of the Legolands are operated by Merlin Entertainment and not by Lego, but now Merlin Entertainment is owned by the same massive conglomerate that also owns Lego.
So yay?
Question mark?
Uh venture capital.
Uh yeah.
I mean you never go to theme parks run by massive conglomerates, do you, John?
Well, the thing is, right, is that Disney is still owned by Disney.
Yes, that's true.
Anything else on Eurocons?
I should I'd like to go to another one at some point.
I'm gonna have to pick one.
Yeah
Have you considered have you considered a Bangkok Eurocon?
Uh I think there's a fundamental thing about Europe.
You are misunderstanding, John.
We're not running Eurovision rules.
Yeah, we learned that Canada's about to join Eurovision, so I think we're good.
Do you want to talk about Eddie Clark?
A thing I thought was neat, part one of a possible occasional list.
Eddie Clark has been running a series of
blog posts where they try and bring some attention to um overlooked queer SFF
of the past few years because the Galactic Spectrum Award has not been running since twenty nineteen and so there's a gap where this specific award has not been awarded.
And so there's now kind of spanning that interim period between twenty nineteen and now, a set of lists of just interesting queer SF to read.
I thought it was interesting.
There's like some I have read, some I haven't read, but I've heard of them, and a few that like I've never come across at all.
And so it has kind of expanded my
reading this quite a lot and of the ones that I have read I've enjoyed them all so I think they could be a really neat reading project.
I might see if I can
fill in a few of the gaps in my reading.
'Cause I think sometimes I am here and I'm reading too many like Hugo Award things and it's all stuff from twenty twenty five and it would be nice to go back and fill a few of the gaps from twenty twenty two to twenty twenty five, maybe that I have not.
filled and in some cases do own and just haven't read yet.
No that I think that is very fair.
That's very sensible.
So yes, hurrah
It does seem to me to be slightly strange that there isn't a set of queer SF awards.
I mean there's obviously queer in the sense of rum.
There's lots.
Come on, John.
But queer in the sense of of LGBTQ.
Um yeah, no, it does seem strange.
Uh so so this so this is this is part of uh the point Eddie is making is that the Galactic Spectrum Awards ran until twenty nineteen
And when the convention that they were held at went on hand hiatus for the pandemic, uh the con was returned but without the awards.
And so this is one way of trying to fill that gap
Um there is also the Lambda Awards have a spec fiction category and there's um the otherwise award often awards things in this space, but is not explicitly for queer SSF.
So I think it's a nice gap to fill.
See what happens in the future.
Yeah, absolutely.
Uh shall we do picks?
Yes.
Wait.
I will go first, and my pick continuing a recent theme of I play lots of Hugo nominated uh
Video games is that I played Clare Obscure Expedition 33.
Anyway, I should say I got a code for this
From the Hugo packet and as I've said, thank you very much for them for basically especially finding me uh an Asian region PlayStation code.
So I played it on my PlayStation.
Oh, that's very kind.
It was very nice, yes.
Uh so they sent me that and I installed it and checked it worked and then kept playing for another like sixty hours.
It's an RPG.
It's a turn based RPG, which is not one I have played uh genre I have played that much.
So basically it's a it's a turn based RPG with like
immediate quick time elements like you have to parry and jump and things when you are fighting enemies.
But I don't think listeners are going to be super interested in the game mechanics
And honestly I enjoy the game mechanics, but they're kind of a means to an end of getting through the game.
Because the game is it's pretty great.
It is extremely French.
It's extremely melancholy.
The setting is that you're in this sort of, you know, pseudo uh fantasy Paris analogue where every year a giant woman called the Painteress paints a lower number on a monolith many miles away.
and everyone of a certain age above that number dies.
Oh no.
So every year, like the population is becoming younger by one year.
And every year an expedition sets out to try and
take down the painteress and stop this happening.
And you so you go off, you know, you you go off on the expedition Expedition Thirty Three
And you are basically unfolding the story of what is going on in this fantasy world, what is going on with this giant woman called the Painteress.
And I I won't go too much into the plot because it's uncovering it is part of the fun.
And is the number currently thirty-four?
Is the number painted on the thing currently thirty-four and it's going to be thirty-three and It becomes uh thirty-three at the start of the
game.
It is basically unimportant, but it is.
Well just worry I I We are all over thirty-three listeners.
Marianne'll soon be over thirty-three.
Uh yeah, but ba basically it's a story all about it ends up being all of a story about sort of grief and mourning and how you cope with
uh grief and how you get through it and do you get through it and what do you do and do you end up losing yourself in that.
So it's all kind of got this very melancholy air
It is also, as I said, quite French in that the the music has lots of French singing.
There's one bit where there's only one bit I think where text is ever displayed in the world
And it was interesting because as the characters said what they were writing, it then turns up in French in world.
I was like I was like, what's going on there?
Oh, French.
Um so possibly I should have played it with the French voice actors for like maximum immersion.
But I think the voice acting is very, very good and
The motion capture that goes with the voices is also pretty good, even though I think in some cases like they're different people.
It's not always the mo cap and voice being done by the same person.
There were two performance capture artists on Claire Obscure that did all of the performance capture.
And so it is quite m you know, melancholy and mournful, but it's also
extremely weirdly whimsical.
And some of this is is kind of explained when you figure out what is going on a bit more.
But it's just nice that you kind of are, you know, going around trying to save save your
town, everyone over the age of thirty-three has died and you meet a sort of giant sort of stuffed character
uh named SQA, who is how you get around the landscape.
And when you go swimming he'll shout things like, Let's go for a swim swim Yeah.
So so the the tone is kind of off beat and
fun and it's uh not to give anything away but the end you get to pick from one of two endings and you know neither it's not that there is a good ending and a bad ending, I would argue that neither ending is particularly great, but
They illustrate different things and I picked my ending and was very sad and then went back and immediately watched the other ending and that was also very sad.
French.
But I think I picked the better one.
Argue with me in the letters.
Well, how do we know which one you picked for the letters
Ah, okay.
I can say that I picked the ending where the title that comes up is A Life to Love.
And if you've played the endings you will know which one that is, and if you've not, hopefully you are intrigued.
So, I mean it's not a perfect game.
I think the the tuning of the difficulty I think is a bit off.
There's only three difficulty settings and the easy one is a bit too easy and they turned it up to normal and kept dying a lot.
and I was not interested in dying that many times, so I turn it back down.
It was kind of not really enough of a challenge.
It is basically very linear
There's some areas of the game where you you go in and there's not a lot there and it feels like maybe they didn't have time to flesh out everything they would want to flesh out.
But I think it's I really enjoyed it and I think it is kind of a good achievement from a very small game studio and
is a totally original setting and world and not franchised and I was like I enjoyed getting to know that.
Mm-mm
Sounds good.
Alright, fair enough.
I haven't started Claire Obscure Expedition 33 yet because I've started Blueprints and I don't know what's going on.
Oh, did you not previously play Blueprints?
No.
Okay, I have not quite.
I'd been finishing um Oh god, what'd I been playing?
Uh the a different game that I've forgotten.
It was good, I can't remember what it was.
I have almost finished Hades 2.
I mean probably I mean I've almost finished it for me in that I have unlocked the the la the
last bit of plot where you learn something exciting and you go, oh, I did not realise that.
And um that was a surprise to me.
And um then there's a bunch more.
you know, points to get, but I'm probably not gonna get those.
That's fair.
So I've I've done mo There's a trophy for getting to room forty-six on day one.
Yes.
I don't think I'm ever gonna get that.
I have not done that one.
I've I mean I've seen there's like uh playthroughs on YouTube to do that and it does seem to be it it's
Like it's very look-based as you'd expect.
So you'd have to basically just play a lot until you get the right set of conditions.
No, and that's that's the kind of trophy that's the kind of trophy I don't really love, because it's like I don't want to have to just
Play the game over and over again until luck means I get the achievement.
That's not actually an achievement.
though Jonathan got it and and of course there's a whole bunch of stuff about y once you know how to play the game to a high degree of efficiency, you are much more likely to do the things you need to do.
for the day one trophy.
Yeah, and you'll probably get it if you play enough, then you will kind of recognise the conditions and you will be doing something else and then go, Oh, actually I could do this, let's go and do it.
Does that make sense?
No, because you only start from day one on day two trying to get the day one trophy.
Yeah.
Oh, sorry, I've got it.
Yeah, I know what you mean.
You've got to start a new game.
Yeah.
Yeah, I don't know.
I don't know if I can be asked to get the platinum.
Not sure I can be asked to get the platinum on dispatch either, but we'll see.
Oh, I've never been asked to get the platinum on any game ever, so
Oh actually that's how I can work out what game I played last.
I can look at what platinums I've got.
We won't.
I think if you try and get like platinum on Claire Obscure I think it will take
Ages.
Yes, I I feel like reports of Claire Obscure mean I might not like it very much, but I would very like to much like to have a go at it before.
You go voting deadline.
I am going to pick Port Marion, which is where I was on holiday last time and sent you a picture postcard from as the cover.
Um Port Marion is an Italian village in North Wales, which is the most extraordinary thing to find randomly on the North Wales coast, because it's not like anything else in
the UK, it's not really like anything else anywhere, but it what is sort of trying to be like is an Italian village, maybe one on the Amalfi coast that is built onto an estuary.
or mountain area.
Um it was the brainchild of architect Clough Williams Ellis who basically spent his life building
building bits of it, bringing f what he says fallen buildings from out other bits of the UK.
It is celebrating its centenary this year.
Um it is probably best known to
uh genre fans as the setting for the nineteen sixties television show The Prisoner, um, which was filmed in and around Port Marion and um so a lot of things that people thought were
extraordinary film sets are in fact just bits of what that village is like.
Um it still has many of the things that it had in the sixties.
It also has some other things.
Um
And we went as well as being a place that you could go for a day visit, which I had done several times before, it is also a place that you can stay and I have friends who stay there very often.
Um and they said why don't
um why don't we all go and stay there for a uh holiday?
Um which we did a couple of weeks ago and we had nice weather.
Though it
We did not have the scorchingly hot weather, we just kind of had ordinary English weather, or Welsh weather in this case, um, so kind of dull and a bit rainy.
Um, and I spent a lot of time swimming in the outdoor pool, round and round and round in ellipses, because it's an elliptical pool.
And um in general enjoying the space.
The the the great thing you get by actually staying in one of the cottages uh in this um
village is that you get to enjoy the village before everyone has arrived for the day and after everyone leaves at night and it's a bit like
Imagine if you went to Positado but had it to yourself.
So whenever whenever you see these amazing tourist resorts and um the fact that they're extremely full
This is an opportunity to go to something that is just as beautiful as that but not extremely full.
And I think it's amazing, the most marvellous place.
That's it really, that was my pick.
Um obviously it's a holiday, so it's not cheap, but it's also no more expensive than other sorts of holidays, really.
So
I you said elliptical pool and I was like, I think I know what that looks like, but I'm gonna Google.
And I did Google.
Uh, and it was what I thought it looked like.
But then I also found out that someone's made an elliptical pool table for the sport of pool where wherever you shoot on the table you score.
Yeah, no that's not that useful, is it?
I dunno.
It's fascinating.
So no I did spend a little time.
The the elliptical pool is fifty feet long.
So I spent a little bit of time swimming round and round.
Um
contemplating because normally I kind of contemplate how many lengths I've done, but in this case I was contemplating if if the elliptical pool is fifty foot long and maybe thirty foot wide then how
how much am I swimming if I go around the outside of it.
But I never really worked that out.
I did listen to Octhorpe, the the you know, the doing the edit lists.
So if I made no comments on the edit that was because
I was swimming around and round an elliptical pool at the time.
You were in a swimming pool.
Right, and then it's my pick.
My pick is
Uh Widow's Bay, which is a television show on Apple TV, and it stars Matthew Reese, who was in The Americans, among other things.
uh and Kate O'Flynn and a variety of other people and Stephen Root who is great and the basic conceit
Is that you we follow we follow a mayor, who is Mayor Tom Loftis, as he tries to revive the island by bringing tourism onto the island.
But there is a slight snag in that most of the people who live on the island are fairly convinced that it is cursed.
And as the show goes through, you see him trying to build the tourism on this island in a kind of
kind of parks and wreck style uh department of m misfits and relatively incompetent people as other members of the island are like, stop bringing the people here, you're gonna get them all killed.
Haven't you noticed the fog?
And over the ten episodes things develop in various ways.
So I'm gonna say firstly the names of the episodes are great.
uh and the little descriptions on the Apple TV inter um interface are also great.
And then the acting's great and the story's great and it kind of
It reminds me a little bit of a cross between Parks and Wreck and The Wicker Man.
Uh and it's good.
High recommend.
Might watch it again.
I've got one episode to go.
I am enjoying it a lot.
Yes.
It's going to be on my ballot next year.
Yeah.
I think it does a very it's a very effective way of like it is funny, but also kind of swaps very well from like
funny moments to much less funny moments.
Yep.
And I think like uh Matthew Reese I think does a great job of that.
Like there's times when he has to sort of flip from one emotion to another
quickly to make things land and he does.
He is amazing.
He's really, really good.
I find him very sympathetic even when
I think he's making the wrong decision.
He he plays it very understandably.
Yeah.
And you can kind of absolutely you can see what he's trying to do even as you're like, no, no, no, no, don't do that, Tom.
Yelp.
And actually the finale I oh yeah, we should talk about Arthur finale, Liz, because I was it was a banger.
Mm-hmm.
And for those who have seen, so there is a tweet, hang on.
So there was back in the old days, there used to be a website called Twitter.
There was a person on Twitter called Katie Dippold.
Uh and she tweeted a picture of her as a ha as the Babaduke at a Halloween party where everyone else had basically just turned up in normal clothes and was drinking wine.
But anyway, the person who is making this show is the person who went to that party as the Babadook.
So if you're familiar with this viral tweet.
Um you may already be familiar with the showrunner.
I did already I mean I already knew this anyway, I think.
But also um the showrunner Katie DePold was on a podcast uh where she was introduced as um
The person famous from the viral Mabaduke tweet.
Uh yeah, it was good.
Um but it's just really good.
I'm looking forward to season two.
Uh impatiently.
I want it now, but it's not coming out now, so I've got to wait
Yeah, absolute crack in.
High recommend.
And Hugh GogoGo released a podcast about it and we will link to that in the show notes too.
And hopefully it will not do that Apple TV thing of
Not having another series for like two and a half years.
Ah, fingers crossed, yeah.
That was the Octothorpe Podcast.
And it's goodbye for me.
It's goodbye from me.
So we're done in forty six minutes, so I think we probably
Have time for what is in the agenda, so the Eurocon stuff and then picks and then I might mention a couple of cool things.
And we can save the business meeting agenda for next episode.
Yeah, I think that was the plan.
I think that is a good cromulent plan.
And then it will be all business meetings until August.
Surely not.
Summer of Fun
Isn't that like the exact opposite of the summer of fun?
Summer of exciting discussions about transferable voting systems.
Oh yeah.
Just to prepare yourselves, listeners.
Yup
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod in Compatech.
com used under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.