Right, well, I have fun editing that into something that's not too
defamatory, but still makes sense. And if you need me to do a drop in of any
and all bits of that later, I can do it.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 41st episode of Octa Thorpe, the podcast for
science fiction and science fiction fandom, which is coming to you on the 30th of
September. I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott and I'm Elizabethie.
So we are recording at an unusual time because John's busy. It is now at a perfectly
reasonable time for John and for me, but very late at night for Liz. And when I, when we
recorded a bad time for me, I have nine cups of coffee in order to feign
a wakefulness. And I have suggested this approach to Liz and she's like, now,
no, that seems like a terrible idea. And I have to question her commitment to the
podcast at this point. Liz. Yeah, but if it's, I think if we're
recording a podcast at 10 a.m. and Alison never asked to drink six cups of coffee,
that is a little different than if you're recording a podcast at 10 p.m.
And I've got work tomorrow. And we're just accommodating John for having a life.
Yeah, how dare you, John? Yep. Sorry. So we had some letters of comment. We had a
letter comment from Chris Garcia, who has cracked his knuckles and loosened his neck.
And he says, okay, let's do this. The five best high school films are Heather's
Scream election, 10 things I hate about you and the breakfast club. I think I've seen two of those.
I think I have seen all five of those. It's a long time since I've seen Scream, but I think we're
slightly stretching high school movie to include films with people of high school age who all get
killed. Sorry, that's probably a spoiler for Scream, isn't it? I'm pretty sure the blonde girl
gets away at the end of the movie. Now that's a spoiler. I don't know because I haven't seen Scream.
I am, I am extrapolating from other movies that I have seen. One of my favorite high school movies
is Final Destination 3 by the same logic, Kraken movie. Frandau has also posted about high school
movies in the OctaThought Facebook group. If you're on Facebook, you might like to join the OctaThought
Facebook group where you get prime content like this. She says, if, which is a good, good call,
I'd say, back to the future, which is definitively a high school movie, Ghost World, The History Boys,
Kooties, um, Subtrinians, which we did actually mention. Frandau said, had John heard of Centriniens?
Yep, I have. I thought T'Lula Riley was very good in that movie. I assume that's the remake of
Centriniens, of which we shall not speak. War Games, the prom, which has Ariana to boast in it,
so I'm going to check that out. Was there an original Centriniens? No, put in my leg. We're not
falling for that one. School That Forever. Oh, and Clueless, which nobody has previously mentioned,
but Ang Rossin mentioned. School of Rock. School of Rock is a good choice, yes?
Did anyone mention School of Rock? Because that's definitely the best high school movie.
Have you seen If? Have you heard of If? Um, I thought you'd mispronounced it. Uh, no, don't know
if I've seen If. No, well, I mean, you'd have to go away. Will we be setting John Ho'Work from the
past. If is definitely worth watching. There are many films called if. So this is my
have to tell me which year if dot dot dot. Now there's really anyone. Ah from 1968.
Starring Malcolm McDowell. Yep I am not aware of that one either. That is before my time.
Sorry. Oh god. Oh god young people are young. I think Heather's probably has some things
in common with if. My brother Dave messaged me saying as a layer of
comment what the fuck is Heather's I've never heard of it and I was like fair
enough. It turns out the people who have similar
upgree rings have similar cultural references. Who knew? Yep. He also says he
loves the instruction of the pick feature so that's good. I've been I've
forgotten we had a Facebook group to be honest so there's a whole discussion
about high school movie so I was completely unaware of. It's quite good. What I
like about that though is that because Alison has also forgotten that we had a
Facebook group because the last time she posted it was to plug episode 31. Yes I
do need to remember to plug Octa Thorpe in the Facebook group every single time.
I will get better but join our Facebook group. We'll put a link in the comments
not that Facebook links work very well but there we go. I also forget to tweet it
but I think Jordan usually sorts me out. Basically you might be getting the
impression that the bulk of the work on this podcast is done by John. Thank you
John. The thing is I don't use Facebook very often and so and this may explain
why our listenership is not quite as great as it might be but we have a very
engaged listenership as a proportion of the total listenership which is I think
all of them. This is your cuter writer to say no no no long time listener first
time correspondent here. Having discussed high school movies in some depth we
should move on to topics. Oh hang on what's the discord mention from Emily
after Eliz? Well it's about high school movies. Hey seamlessly we've gotten. She
says Heather's is great but the musical is even better and I was like I'd also
the musical brought Heather's to a new generation and I'm now going to do a
John here and go well there was a musical so I'm gonna have to look that up. It had
quite a short West End run apparently. I mean to say with Beetlejuice isn't it
that they made a musical of Beetlejuice 30 years after the fact that it's quite
popular with a whole different generation. Beetlejuice best high school movie.
Finally just on something that isn't high school movies. Bug Bredshaw tweeted
others to say that you can totally have a microphone in a mask if it stands
proud from the face like the masks with clear plastic panels. It puts the mic in
the same good position as a headset mic. One way they sanitize those mics is
20 minutes each side in an ultra-vio that box.
Hello everyone it's John here just a quick pick up before we get into the rest of
the episode. The next episode will be our episode 42 and so if you have any
reminiscences or stories or other things you would like to share with us that
are connected to the Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy or to Douglas Adams please
do email them in because we will be doing a segment next episode all about
Douglas Adams and the Hitchhiker's Guide. Thank you very much I hope you enjoy the
rest of the episode.
We have some stuff to say about Novocon. Novocon has announced a COVID policy
which they posted on their Facebook page and there will be a link in the
show notes. So they've basically worked with the hotel they have some
limitations because the hotel's requirements for its own staff aren't as
rigorous as Novocon wanted to put in place but it is still not bad. They're
going to try and have spacing where possible. There will be separate entrances
and exits in the dealer's room at art show. They'll be sanitizing. All the hotel
staff will be double vaccinated. All the program rooms apart from the main
program have windows that can be open for airflow. The main program room has
high ceilings and far escape doors that they will open and they're going to
require masks in the main program unless you're on the panel. Masks while moving
around the hotel, not masks in the bar areas, they ask you to be back sedated.
Where possible? They ask you to take a lateral flow test prior to attending
the convention. They don't say that they're mandating any of that but we
could ask them. They say please do not host or attend room parties which is
probably pretty sensible. Please don't attend if you think you have COVID.
Pretty sensible. So I think it's pretty good. It looks good. That'd be the
basically thought through and made reasonable judgments which is all we
ask. This all looks very sensible. I think, you know, I have a few kind of
queries and questions about how some of this will be done but like in general
this is exactly the sort of thing that I think convention should be doing and
it's all very good and this means that I will feel pretty comfortable attending
Novocon and having a good old time which is something that I
am quite looking forward to achieving. Yep, yes I too am very much looking
forward to going to Novocon. It'll be good. So Corflou, I think we're still
waiting for yours. Who else is happening in person is that it?
Well at the time of recording we are a couple of days before fantasy con.
Yes they're the first in-person convention this weekend.
Mm-hmm or last weekend as you're listening to this.
Yeah we talked about fantasy cons rather bare bones.
Bare bones is a good word for a basic over policy.
Last time I think. So I'm having a quick look at
fantasy cons list of activities which will all have happened
by the time you listen to this podcast but haven't at time of recording.
So we don't know how fantasy con was but if you were at fantasy con
do write and tell us what you thought and then we'll talk about next time.
Oh yes yes please do do that. Because none of us going.
And obviously there's nothing listed. There's no parties listed, there's no
book launches, there's no kind of events or activities listed that would involve
any sort of mingling like that. It's basically all panels and readings
are the only kind of programmed items. I think that is interesting because
obviously even if you can go back to being in person there might be things
that you're not doing. You're not having kind of a big disco.
You're not having like book launches with wine. You're not having
big parties, bid parties, room parties. Basically none of those things can happen.
And so then you kind of but you do need to provide
something so maybe you start filling up those late night hours with more
panels and readings and so on than you might otherwise put in.
Or you try and encourage people to socialise in more covid friendly ways
like outdoors or in smaller groups or more spaced out.
But maybe not in the way that we're kind of used to doing
in the evening at conventions where you basically all cram in the bar
and shout to the physics hours. Vauxhall!
I think maybe there is an argument here and I'm not expecting Ramthas. He gone to be
the ones to do it because I think it's early. But I think there is an argument
here that we need to think a little bit about how we
port social experiences into a world where we want to prioritize ventilation and
kind of covid safety in physical spaces because I
understand why they're probably showing away from those sorts of events. But it
strikes me that like if the hotel has a beer card and
it would not be impossible to put those events on and just have them outside.
Patio heaters. Patio heaters exactly that kind of thing.
Stocking patio heaters for this winter I would say. Dry robes.
We had an entirely outside pub crawl a few weeks ago
by just taking huge advantage of beer gardens and I appreciate burning them.
Probably has fewer beer gardens. Is that right? I don't think it's north but still.
No, everywhere has beer gardens now. I've got to say I've actually just looked at
a slightly different page because there is a Google Doc linked elsewhere on the
fancy con website which appears to include a lot more items than
we're on the page I was looking at and actually there are a whole load of
book launches and indeed apparently Friday evening karaoke.
So you can just ignore everything I said about not being able to do those items
they will be doing those items.
Fantasy cons program is in a superposition between
happening and not happening depending on which pages of the internet you look at
and at the time of recording it is impossible to
collapse it into a single wave function. If you went around to the on please tell
us what the wave function looked like after it was observed we would love to know.
Yeah we might have to do a drop in on Monday morning.
This is the sort of thing that it strikes me that a book launch could be done with
kind of cocktail style seating and kind of more you know I mean table
service might be slightly the wrong word but like you could have drinks on tables
and encourage people to sit around the table and have that kind of experience in a way
much less mingly than it would be normally but which was potentially
better than nothing. So I'll be interested to see how fantasy con has done this
and as I say if you attended please do let us know.
And it does also say that the look launches are in a big room so possibly
they have a sufficiently large room that you can actually have quite a lot of people
say it's sitting at tables. I don't see where do they have their
I'm on fantasy con.org but it seems to be about oh hang on do I have to click 2021
I see and then I can go. It's fantasy con.org I've loaded it.
Yeah so you have to click on 2021 because somewhere is it 2022
and even then you don't end up at the actual main website
which is somewhere else. Oh yes that's really weird
because their website seems to be for the 2022 one
and I don't see and I see the 2021 page but I don't see a link to the
program at all so I'm not sure. Yeah no because that's because I'm a totally
different page. Okay I mean it's not entirely different website.
Oh fantasy con website is quite strange because the main fantasy con website
is the website for next year's convention. This is a problem that
Eastercons could have because Eastercons are independent in the same way
but in practice don't tend to. I had not seen this website
interesting and it looks like they are trying to run as much of
a kind of just fully standard convention as possible
but it looks like they do have a lot of book launches
but they're putting them in their biggest function room so presumably they
could be as spaced out as possible and being fancy con they do have the
fancy con banquet and the British Fantasy Award and they also have a karaoke
session on Friday night so I mean it's interesting to me
that I would say you could make panels a little more
covid safe you can have everyone master part from possibly the panelists but
it's probably more difficult to make things covid safe if
everyone is moving and mingling and eating and drinking and potentially
making a lot of aerosols by doing karaoke. Yeah karaoke well-known covid
safe activity. So it's interesting that they're kind of going fully
back in to kind of not even the new normal the new normal is
the old normal I think so I'll be very interested here if anyone is there
at how it went although possibly you do karaoke by having the entire karaoke
audience at the back of the room and the one person doing karaoke at the front
which could be quite funny or you could have the person seeing the karaoke
face away from the audience you could have the person doing karaoke
in a box there's a microphone sanitizing issue too
call back to the letters of comment now listeners if you don't mind sanitizing
your karaoke microphone for 20 minutes in an ultraviolet box
you can have very safe karaoke from a microphone sanitization standpoint
so you just need enough microphones that you have
you can always have a microphone out of the box at any given time in an
elaborate system of different colored tape on each microphone. Yeah that's not
how karaoke works ever is it? No it may not be. You could potentially have karaoke
with no microphones and then it becomes a competition of who has the best
operatic projection but i'm not sure you want to be encouraging maximum aerosols
right now so i but i guess this means it's feasible for panels you would need
essentially twice as many sets of microphones as you had
panels and then you could have an hour in between each panel to put the
microphones in a little sanitizing box i assume you could buy little sanitizing
boxes i assume so too and if you buy a lot of
sanitizing boxes you can use some of them as UV lights for the rave aspect
i don't know whether fantasy con is famous for its raves
if you buy enough UV boxes you could probably use them as little mini gel
docs and do on the spot PCR testing
okay you can't i see us all giving liz a cladding from the audience today at this point
we are looking forward to octagon when i will not have a cold because my
immune system is now functioning properly and will not be
severely depleted by random viruses octagon i don't think it's having
um kind of explicit guests of honor but they are highlighting
kind of regular octagon attendees on their website so that's quite good kind
of just bits and bobs about kind of people who come to octagon and be
well they're excited to see um at the convention um there's some cool
people on that list previous guests of honor and just
interesting bobs um and they've got their uh program
um kind of online so they've got some talks and some workshops which are
happening um on zoom um and the social fabric of the
convention is happening through discord um and anyone who went to a
concentration will be relatively comfortable with this
kind of thing um one that leaves out to me that i won't be able to go to
ooh i'll be back from holiday then i might be able to go to it
is paul carol is doing a workshop on how to write
comic scripts um which is potentially something that would be quite
interesting and there's also going to be some role-playing games
um which you know all good including the alien rpg
system which i think is the new one which is
potentially quite interesting and there's an adorable picture of an octopus
octopus with 2d 20s and antlers and the staff
oh they're a little octopier so cute yeah no octagon has the best graphic
design game of any convention and i will probably go to the workshop of
making your own crocheted octo because i'm going to be doing some in front of
the convention anyway so i'm going to make an octo
that sounds like quite good actually i'm not sure i can crochet well enough for
it do i need to have got do i need a hook i probably have a hook
uh they say you need about 25 grams of yarn
uh decay if possible and a crochet hook between about three or five
millimeters or one to match the way of the answer
basically go and like scound around and i'm sure you can find yeah i'm sure i
have both these things you know a small bit of yarn
and i definitely have loads of stuff what i love about this
is that when you said 25 grams of yarn my immediate thought was
like i didn't know they measured yarn in grams and it makes me think of cocaine
and having met people who have yarn as a like yarn addictions one might say
that actually seems like a very apt comparison because i know several
people who who buy yarn who basically their houses are 70
percent yarn at this point well i mean i think usually so what
is that i think the thing is with cocaine you don't normally just like
stash loads of it for later just in case um i'm not sure that's how that works
no true my understanding is it's quite moreish
i mean generally i think it's if i look at patterns they usually
have it in meters or yards but if i just have some scrap wool
lying around i don't know how much that is in
yards but i can wait it until he how much is in grams
so it's quite practical we may have gone off topic
into yarn fandom i mean yeah yarn is pretty
genre adjacent
i was going to go to firecon last weekend but i didn't it was online
um but i caught what i believe is a disease known as a common cold
um and i have multiple lateral flow tests
negative lateral flow tests to support this and i have all
i am waiting for the result of a PCR test
it turns out that my body used to have an immune system
but it kind of went oh i haven't used this for a year and it
doesn't spark joy so i'm going to get rid of that
and um as a result i had a cold like nobody's ever had a cold before it was
like manon flu or something like that and i was very very poorly
um for a cold but i'm better now um
mostly better now a bit i'm a bit husky but i'm okay otherwise
so that was why i didn't go to firecon because instead of going to firecon
i spent two days in bed watching youtube videos
and sleeping a lot so and then a third day when i managed to get up
just a bit so yeah quite poorly but as you had a membership
right you can catch up at a later date yes but we all know i'm not going to do
that but yeah i've got a couple of weeks right to
catch things on youtube and people keep telling me that there's marvelous
stuff so i could but you know you want to know what your
strengths and weaknesses are and i think one of my weaknesses is that i don't
do that sort of thing very much i think you have much longer
potentially oh good that'd be good yeah yes
everything i heard about firecon is that it was fantastic and i did enjoy
the fringe as it was last year and fully intended to go again
this year and forgot but i also wouldn't have been able to tend any of it live
because of time zones and so on so oh but they had they had the bonfire
they did although they did have the bonfire which would have been in my
time zone however it is i think not recorded
and i was actually out doing things during the day last weekend
anyway so for last for last year's con they
kept the archives for a year so you'll have to see
what happens this year so you have a year in which you can feel guilty you
haven't watched them yet and we can regularly remind
Alison had she watched any firecon or does she just feel guilty
every every episode listeners we will do a new feature called did Alison
watch the firecon program yet and it will just be Alison saying
no every time and because i know i'm the same like i have the best intentions
and then i never catch up with the program
yeah but i am i'm a person who doesn't even have the best intentions at this
point i'm not i know exactly how overcommitted i am
i'm sure your intentions are very lovely one thing that did happen at firecon
was the uh ignite awards which were announced
and Liz you said things about the ignite awards before you're recorded
so do you want to speak a little bit about these
so they also announced the winners of the 2021 ignite awards which are the
firecon annual awards and they have multiple categories best
novel of adult you know adult middle grade um i've got to say i haven't
actually read any of the winners unfortunately but i have read some of
the nominees that i really quite liked i think we've discussed before the city
we became by nk jemisin was on there and also vagabonds by how jing fang was
a nominee for best adult novel um in the best ya novel i read elatzo
a by darcy little badger which i thoroughly enjoyed and i think
john europeic fan of ray bearer ray bearer is really good i enjoyed it i
probably don't i don't know whether i like it more than lats away i've been
going back and forth on that um the one that won legend born i've also read i
thought it was by far weaker than both of the others which i find
interesting i haven't read so i've read the winner of best novel which black
son by rebecca roanhorse which i thought was good
and probably better than the jemisin but i haven't read the other three
um and i've read riot baby which i thought was really good
and i've read the inaccessibility of heaven by eliette de baudard
uh which i also thought was really good um and i've read the parable of the
sohor comic which won for best comics team i'm not sure what
i guess that means you can nominate a creative team regardless of like
exactly when the trade paperbacks came out like it's understood that you're
nominating the team behind a work rather than like a
specific trade paperback but um but yeah um but i i enjoyed that as well
um generally speaking the ones that i have read of the winners
seem good except for legend born which i didn't really
didn't really care for uh but which clearly other people liked
yeah i guess the drive dominating best comics team is you don't end up with
weird situations where you know an ongoing comic which is divided into
arcs gets nominated in multiple parts or you know versus a comic which is
ongoing but it also would allow you to do things like
comics which are divided into arcs which are drawn by different
artists but have the same right difference and i guess you could nominate
them as a as a team in whatever form that you wanted
i think it's a pretty good way of doing it yeah yeah and also one thing i will
say is that it's interesting to me um that the
short lists like the the nominated works for the
categories that have a Hugo Award equivalent art generally
kind of there is some overlap there um in every category except for best
short story which is um five completely different stories
which i guess goes to show like how much breadth there is in the genre
in short stories at the moment um novelette uh the only one that crosses
over is the winner at the in the inaccessibility of heaven
uh the other the other four are also uh different in the
ignite short list than they are in the best short story Hugo Award
finalists so i thought that was quite interesting uh and probably says
something about just how much shorter fiction there is
kind of available in the genre um at the moment
golden age etc etc if you look at the short story nominations
in the hugos and you look at how long the tale is of stories with a handful of
nominations in short story versus novelette and novella
is them much much longer tale and especially i think
the novella market um in some ways is expanded because um
tor.com published an awful lot of novellas but i think um maybe we've lost
some of the other venues that might you know magazines that might publish
novellas so i think there's a much smaller pool
but there are also some really good novellas coming out
so i don't think it's it's not that the pool is so small you can't have a
really cracking short list it's just that the number of short stories is
immense yeah all right for the genre yeah yeah
to segue seamlessly from the breadth of short fiction into picks
i have recently been reading issue one of
constellatheon magazine um which i have been thoroughly
enjoying uh for those who don't know um that was a magazine which is bilingual
in english and spanish uh and it has english stories that are translated
in spanish and spanish stories that are translated into english
and so if you if you um get an issue it will have both
versions of each story in um it was on kickstarter a while ago
i kickstied the first issue and yeah i've been really enjoying it i will put a
link in the show notes to where you can go and read it online
um i really enjoyed the bowels kurtador and older stories
um so far uh i would think about halfway through
issue one um but it's really good and it has convinced me to back it on patreon
um so yeah that is very good uh and i have been very much enjoying
reading that and especially like getting a glimpse into spanish language
sf um although i am not sufficiently fluent in spanish
to be able to read the stories in the spanish without having to look a lot of
words up on the way i refuse to select anything
for my picks that i have not completely consumed at
which is a bit of a problem because i have been dipping in and out to multiple
tv shows and also reading a very long space opera book which is very good so
far but i've got to read the other 200 pages to tell you if it it finishes well
um so i'm going to have a non genre pick um because the one thing i have watched
in fall and the past ten days is the later series of nailed it
the baking show on netflix um where essentially people try and make really
elaborate cakes and always fail to make the really elaborate cakes
and you know allison was asking is this not kind of really mean but i think the
thing is at least by the point of series six
everyone who goes on this show knows they will completely fail to make the cakes
they do not get enough time there is no way they have enough time to make them
but it's about kind of who can do the best job
and the the co-hosts have such a kind of lovely chemistry and kind of gentle
mockery of each other and the rest of the crew
um and it's also clear now that people are coming on the show because they really
want to meet the people who host the show and have them say something nice about
their cakes and also i get that it's probably very
difficult to bake under pressure when you're being you know filmed in a tv
studio and you're very excited but if one more person
takes their cake out of the oven and puts them straight in the chiller and
doesn't realize that this means that they will
all the oil will you know chill and the cakes will then be stuck to the tin
then i think any of the contestants really need to watch the previous six
series in order to not do that also there is an episode in which they do
blind baking of pies where you put the beans in to
uh so the pastry bakes without bubbles and this is a bit of a spoiler
but more than one contested leaves the beans in
that fair enough that's quite funny it's got Adrian Pimento on it from Brooklyn
Nine-Nine who also played Derek in the good place
Derek and that is something that has tempted me to watch it in the past
should we all three say Derek at the same time Derek
they do in fact call Jason Manzukas on the later series because
presuming he was off filming somewhere and couldn't come and be a judge
so they just basically call him for absolutely no reason other than it's
quite nice to call up Jason Manzukas and he might say something funny
they have excellent guest judges as well that's awesome i might have to
load that up so so i have three picks
um i have a thing which is which you can go and watch i'm going to talk
about it very quickly which is kind of genre adjacent
which is that on i-player at the moment there is a 1975 adaptation of three men
in a boat where the three men are Tim Curry who
is genre adjacent Michael Palin who is pretty genre
adjacent i would say and Steven Moore who is genre adjacent
Marvin the paranoid android indeed and the adaptation was done by
Tom Stoppard and the entire thing is directed by Steven Fries and it's not
actually as good as you might expect given that but it's still pretty good
it's only an hour ago watch it um that's obviously three men in a boat
being a historical account of a boating trip
through Oxford and in Varroons is not very genre but there you go
and then i have a thing which is genre having mentioned Wuber a last time and
for my guff report i read Blast Off at Wubera by Hugh Walters and i enjoyed
it more than i expected to um so it's quite a
volicking story about the daring do of boys in the in 1957 which is when i mean
i don't know if it's actually set in 1957 it was published in 1957 and it's
kind of tells of the machinations of the um
English governmental class at that time um as written in a book for young boys i
don't think Hugh Walters necessarily realized that
he was writing for girls as well until girls started to write to him and tell
him how much they liked his books after which he put more girls in
so that's that's quite a good sign for the times
but this one doesn't really have any it has some perfectly adequate women
characters in it but it doesn't have any girls in it the
main character is a boy um and it's actually much better that i
remembered so i mean it's not much better than i remember because obviously i
remember thinking these books were amazing
um but then in retrospect i thought oh no they can't have been very good but
in fact it's not bad if you like adventure stories
from the 50s um and then i have a third pick which is that
while i was sick i watched um some youtube streams of
a person who's famous for being for doing sidoku on the internet
instead playing through a video game called the witness and it reminded me
how much i liked the witness and in fact it reminded me enough that i'm
playing it again and the thing about the witnesses it tells it's a social
story without using any words there are that's not
quite true because there's some kind of archive
recordings and videos of real people saying things real people said
um but there isn't actually any words in the plot
of the game so i think that's quite interesting
and also it's one of the best puzzle games ever made so
if you have any interest at all in puzzle games you've probably already
played it um so yeah that's those nice picks those
were quite quick though weren't they it's three okay if they're quick and i don't
draw breath so it's hard to wear it out no so so i think and i and i have not
played the witness but having heard you talk about it i might have to look it up
and infinitum for a week well because it's by the chap who did braid
which i quite liked it is by the chap who did braid he
basically made a load of money so imagine you had made 40 million quid on braid
or something like that would you then spend it all
making your next game add a bit more of a size or would you go no no i need
some money for my for my pension and things like that
i mean you know it's art in it i mean i think the witnesses
wash its face i think it did very well i'm about a quarter of the way through
the witness and it's not that quick if you're rubbish at puzzle games
so oh sorry it it was a quick description not a quick game it's quite a slow game
unless you're simon from cracking the cryptic in which case
he goes through he goes through these puzzles at a rate of knots go click click
and everyone's like he's like oh i'm sorry i'm really slow i'm not good at
this at all i don't really see i'm really stuck on this one i'm really really
very stuck and meanwhile marks they're going and here's ten dollars from
Bertie in in michigan going you're not stuck at all
so i bet you're doing really well and by then he's solved it and people are like
he's complaining it's slow because he's taken in five minutes and it took me
three hours to solve this puzzle that's fair i can um i can get it
on my mac for 35 pounds or on my ipad for nine
it's i'd get it on the ipad because the entire game is about drawing
lines with your finger ah you know i might get it
yeah so it's lovely on the ipad it looks very pretty
the graphics aren't quite as nice but but the actual how to play it
is much better on the ipad okay one ground okay interesting
see i have it on the playstation which is why my phone also contains for an
example this oh yes you will need to take notes
that's fair oh no but i take notes on my ipad
i have to buy a new ipad yeah this is the problem okay so i take screenshots and
then i open up a window with good notes and then i scribble on my good notes
thing ah that's just that's just good sense that is that um
i am i am going to put i'll send you a typical a typical screenshot
for to put in the chapter as the chapter art for this
thank you thank you so i will do that and apparently
the witness won best iOS game of the year 2017
so yeah high praise probably do we have anything else on picks
out of three which i think is enough did you have a picture on what's your pick
constellatheon magazine oh yeah constellatheon yes
do you read them in spanish no because i am insufficiently good at
spanish now i know people are going to write in and i'm
very sorry people uh but i am reading the first harry potter book in spanish
the reason i am doing this is not because i love transphobia
i just want to get that out of the way in advance
but it's basically because i am familiar enough with the harry potter story
having it having been one of the formative stories of my childhood
um and it is a series of novels which has been widely translated
and so i was able to procure it in spanish and then i can read it
and i know the story well enough that like i can
mmm it's kind of like a safety blanket like i can understand most of the words
and like if i trust myself i do understand the gist of most of what's
being said although when pronouns get involved it always gets complicated
uh i think this is true in any language but certainly it's the bit of spanish
where i find the hardest um but it is it is really cool to be
able to read in spanish and kind of just pick out the words i don't know and add
them to my anki uh deck and it's it's proving
quite a good way of kind of building up my confidence with
interpreting written spanish um but obviously it is written at a lower level
than the stories in consolatheon are because the ones in consolatheon are
designed for adults and harry potter is written for 11 year olds
and in spanish i am 11 i mean mentally i'm 11 as well as anyone who's
witnessed me tell jokes will know but yeah in terms of reading comprehension
i think harry potter is probably about my speed in spanish
so so harry potter is not a bad choice for language learning generally
because it's it's translated into every every language on earth practically
yeah if anyone has any recommendations for um
british kind of children's books that british children might have read who are
my age that have been translated into spanish that do not give jk rolling
money when i buy them please do write in i would be very interested
or read something that was originally written in spanish
but is mostly read in translation in english
oh good point so yes if anyone has any recommendations for things like that
please also write in turned out most of my witness screenshots
were deeply spoilery which i should probably have worked at if i thought
about it right i think we should this is not going to be on the podcast
so let's finish the podcast and then you can chat
yeah let's just go like i'm really tired okay so anything else is going to be on
the podcast is there anything we're looking forward to in the next
two weeks and four days uh i'm hopefully going to finish a book
hey what on this that was the 41st episode of the octa thought podcast
and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
i haven't done any of my hugo reading and oh god i like that you're using your
sexy deep voice at the moment uh reminds me of is it friends episode where
phoebe has a cold and does the sexy singing this is my husky voice
woof woof woof woof oh bloody hell i have to keep it in
hell i think we can probably cut most of that
it's not a joke worth keeping what the husky joke
woof woof woof woof woof the theme music for this
episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in
comfatec.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0
license this podcast will end at the beep beep