Thank you to everyone at Ch icon who came up and said kind words about the podcast, especially
the ones who I had never met before and especially the person on the day before the convention
started who overheard me and Liz and Ispania talking on the way back from breakfast and
said, "Oh, you're from OctaThorp, I recognise your voice."
That was very good.
That has never happened to me before.
Hello, person who listens to OctaThorp, it would lovely to meet you.
I hope you had a lovely Ch icon right in and tell us all about it, please.
Hello, everyone and welcome to the very 67th episode of OctaThorp, a podcast for Science
Fiction and Science Fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 29th of September 2022.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And this is the first time we have been sitting in our places with our microphones in a few
weeks.
So, hello Alison and Liz.
Last time I saw you, Liz was perimidilbus and the time before that I was a computer.
So how are you both doing?
Well, we did spend a week eating in enormous breakfast together and generally hanging out.
That's true.
Was that you guys?
Interesting.
Yeah, the last time I saw John, I was sneaking out of our hotel room trying not to wake him
up at 5 in the morning.
I don't remember seeing you.
So I imagine it worked well.
So I succeeded.
Hooray, okay.
Yes.
I'm sure that didn't read to come out quite the way it did.
Who knows.
It came out exactly how it was intended.
I was sneaking out of John's hotel room early in the morning.
But yes, we have some letters of comments and we have a variety of letters of comment
on quite old episodes of OctaThorp.
So we travel back in time to the 20th of August where a man called Christopher J. Garcia sent
us a lock about OctaThorp, episode 64, and said that the transition from 32-bit OctaThorp
to OctaThorp 64 will lead to confusion, but ultimately you'll adjust.
So I'm glad the listenership that Chris has confidence in you and let us know how that
transition has been going.
He also proposes an alternative to the Broily Competence theory and his alternative is the
Garcia rule of voting thing.
It doesn't matter why you vote for a thing.
It's concise.
It doesn't have a lot of provisos.
There's relatively few subsections.
Yeah, it's a very Garcia approach.
It is although he does then go on to tell us a little bit about some of his Hugo votes
and why he's voting for them.
So he is undermining his own voting rule.
And he does note there are exceptions and notes the dirt bag incursion of 2014-2016,
which is fair.
It's good exception.
We also got some comments on the fact that Alison referred to Star Wars Lower Decks.
I was going to make that the episode title, but relented in the face of Alison looking
sad when I said I was going to do that.
But I did leave it in.
And so everyone wrote in to say that Alison had done that.
And yes, it was very funny.
We didn't notice at the time we didn't correct her.
We're bad people.
Sorry, Alison.
I didn't want to have Star Wars Lower Decks as the episode title because I had done us
as Star Wars characters the previous episode.
And I've just realized, oh shit, I could have just done a commemorative plate with the picture
from the previous episode as the middle of the plate.
And that would have saved me about $10,000 at Oh God.
And then the nature of time saving hacks, I do expect every piece of episode artwork from
now on to be a commemorative plate of some kind or other.
Yeah, because I could do a commemorative plate really quickly now because the way I did the
commemorative plate cover was to generate a commemorative plate making macro for Photoshop.
So we got some letters of comment on episode 65 action castle two.
But unfortunately, I didn't understand any of them because you all used the wrong verbs.
It's fair to say that some of our listeners did not particularly like the action castle
episode and at least once said that it gave them info com flashbacks.
So sorry about that if that's you.
Remember to keep the junk mail.
You'll need it later.
We got some comments on episode 66 on Facebook.
I haven't had any emails yet, but I'm sure we will.
But we got Facebook comments and a lot of people liked the picture of the three of us at the
Hugo's listener Liz Batty said that my hair was very annoying.
Sorry about that, Liz.
And Laurie Anderson from Hugo Girl posted to say, how did we fail to record even one
second of friendship audio?
And that is that is a good point.
We did not record any Hugo Girl friendship audio.
It's very sad, but there are some photos of us and Hugo Girl people hanging out, which
was very good.
But there will be in the future maybe at some point when we come to Dragoncon next year,
we're all going to Dragoncon.
You heard it here first, including Alison and Liz who didn't know.
Liz continues to knit and Alison is a gape.
I'm more likely to go to Dragoncon than Chengdu next year, but I'm probably more likely to
go to Winnipeg than either.
Where is Winnipeg?
Can you like Winnipeg and Dragoncon on consecutive weekends and die?
Permacon is the 20th to the 5th of July and Dragoncon is Labor Day weekend, so you couldn't.
So that's not happening then.
I'm not going to any of these conventions.
It would be lovely, but it's not going to happen.
I'm going to Australia and New Zealand.
Oh.
For my guff trip.
Now I have looked it up.
What I could do is go to Winnipeg and then the weekend after go to Gencon.
Interesting.
Oh, that sounds like an amazing thing to do.
I thought you had no more money ever.
Well, I might have some more money by then, I might be able to save up.
Yeah, we know you're going to spend it on them.
Oh, Chicago was expensive.
It was great.
It was not cheap.
Yeah, let's talk about Chicago.
Chicago is great.
It's very tall.
Alison, how did you find it?
It was proportionately more taller than it was for me or Liz, for you.
It's tall, but it's also quite kind of big.
It's got a lot of space.
It has a river and it also has a lake, but the lake is quite big, so it feels like a
sea.
I think the lake is as big as the Netherlands.
So that's quite big.
Can you put that in terms of double decker buses or whales?
I think you could fit a lot of...
Oh, no, the lake is probably bigger than whales because it's about as big as the Netherlands.
It's big.
It's really big.
You may think it's a long way, just going out into shops, but that's just peanuts compared
to Lake Michigan.
Indeed.
Chicago is pretty big and pretty tall.
It's got a lot of skyscrapers.
Some of them are very interesting.
And I discovered that I love the work of Bertrand Goldberg, and wish there were more of it, in
Chicago.
He has two skyscrapers, one pair and one extra on the tour, and they're the best things
on the entire tour.
You may have to explain what tour...
Yes, what tour are you referring to here, Alison?
Yeah, we went on an architectural boat trip of Chicago, where our person giving us the
guide was a real tour.
So she kept explaining whether the building was rental or office or condominiums or whatever,
and also she talked to an enormous amount about corner offices.
So that was a bit weird, but otherwise it was very interesting to her.
So to explain the tour in a more general level, rather than a very specific grope with the
tour before he played what the tour was, it was a boat tour, and we went up and down the
river in Chicago, and a very nice lady pointed out buildings and told us about the buildings,
and it was good.
And she explained who had done the buildings, and then also got quite into the weeds in some
aspects.
But it was very interesting, and I was glad to have done it at the start, because it meant
when I was later walking around Chicago, and I saw these buildings from the bottom of the
buildings, I was like, "Whoa, that's a tall building!"
And there was also other art in Chicago.
There was the Art Institute, I saw Night Hawks, which was amazing, and I also did not see the
Tiffany Dome, but that was fine, because I'd been to the Tiffany Museum.
Weirdly, the Tiffany Museum is in Winter Park near Orlando in Florida, given that a lot of
Tiffany's work was Chicago-based.
There is surprisingly little of it in Chicago, and if you want to see it, you need to go to
Florida for some reason.
I also had, I did not, I had a fine hot dog, I didn't have a great hot dog, I had a fine
hot dog.
I had a couple of pretty good hot dogs, I don't know whether I had kind of the canonical
Chicago hot dog.
Liz, what were your cultural highlights of Chicago?
Well, I don't eat hot dogs, but I did have a couple of deep pumpitas, that was pretty
good.
Yeah, I just loved Chicago as a city, the weather when we were there, just before the
con was perfect in that it was sunny and bright and warm, but not too hot.
So I got one of the Chicago municipal e-bikes and biked it along the lake shore, up to
the zoo, which is very nice, and e-bikes really sort out any pesky hills on the way.
Not really hills, but inclines.
Yeah, it's just a really lovely place to go and hang around, it has nice parks, it has
these really impressive skyscrapers, you know, a bit about the skyscrapers, because
ladies told you about how much of the architecture appears to depend on either having too many
corner offices or not having enough corner offices, it seems to be a very big influence
on how the architecture was done.
Yeah, I mean I have no idea what it's like to actually live in Chicago, because I only
really sort of went around the central bits, but it is a really nice place to spend a week
full of exciting cultural opportunities and good food.
I hung out quite a bit with Nigel Rowe, who lives quite close to the centre of Chicago,
and he was extremely enthusiastic about living in Chicago, he thinks it's a fantastic place
to live, which is why he lives there, given that he's from New Zealand.
We also went down to the museum quarter and we went to the older Planetarium, which is
the oldest planetarium in North America.
In common with most planetarium has had its planetarium mechanism removed, because they're
completely obsolete.
We also looked at a lot of gardens, we went to the beach, we did not go swimming because
there were massive signs saying no swimming everywhere, which I now understand are just
kind of performative signs, and you're actually fine to swim, you just, they really should
say do not swim and then try to sue the city about it.
As Liz said, the weather in Chicago is often very difficult, both in summer and in winter,
but when we were there it was extremely lovely the whole time pretty well, except when we
were breakfast.
We did get very soaked one day and I was wearing my Glasgow t-shirt ready for the 10 o'clock
site selection announcement that Glasgow had won the Worldcon, and by the time I returned
to the hotel I woke up about five minutes from the restaurant, I could no longer wear
that t-shirt for two days while it dried out.
But one of the other big advantages of Chicago was that there was a Worldcon there.
Was pretty good.
Yeah, went to a Worldcon.
So this is, Alison, this is your first American Worldcon since.
It is my first US Worldcon since 1993, though we did go to anticipation in 2009.
Liz, this was your first American convention since Tracon 7?
Nope, I went to Mid-American in 2016.
Oh, of course you did, you went with Anna.
Yes.
Taffter, look at Anna Raftry also went to Mid-American, and this was my first American
Worldcon since San Jose in 2018.
Conferencesco was the first convention that Ispani went to when she was new, and that
was the 1993 Worldcon.
It's the only time the Worldcon will ever be in downtown San Francisco, and so I really
regret I wasn't old enough to go, but yes, it sounds like it would have been an amazing
convention.
I don't think I quite understood properly how to do Worldcons in 1993 when I was younger
than any of the OctaThought team are now.
But I mean, I was filming a lot in those days.
Disgusting.
If you were a filker, then your experience of Worldcon is very different from, if you
are, a drinker.
Alison was running the Fanzine Lounge, Liz was doing pro gops, and Ori wasn't doing anything.
Often, Liz was doing spreadsheets, I think.
There was some spread-cheating, but basically, because I had done program work, and they
run up to the con, I already had a login for the program database and the ability to work
the program database.
So there was some people email you say, "Oh, I can't do this panel.
You make changes.
You edit things.
You make sure it ends up in the online schedule."
And since there was not really a printed schedule, everyone was using the online one,
which could be updated a couple of times a day.
That was good.
Yeah, fundamentally, it was one of those job where you basically sit and type in a window
in this room for a couple of hours.
So, it's not like an actual job.
We probably should say, if you were going to criticize, well, things that I liked a lot
about Chicon, several of my friends have been calling it Chicon, which has started to
worry me.
It's definitely Chicon, right?
I had the target with Steven Silver in Reno in 2011, and successfully wound him right up.
What you called it Chicon?
Why is Chicago?
So it must be Chicon.
All right, fair enough.
The Hyatt Regency is a single massive hotel in two parts, but it means that the entire
convention is all on one site, and it is in, it is banging in the centre of town.
It's more in the bit of Chicago you want to be in if you're on holiday.
So it's very compact as these things go.
It's exactly the right size for a Worldcon, and I think that's a big benefit of the convention.
Unfortunately, it doesn't have terribly good Wi-Fi or internet access.
Those of us who were roaming from America were in a good state because if you're on
roaming, then your phone automatically grabs the best signal as a result of which we did
mostly get signal throughout.
But lots of people who've been told you could only use the online program, then didn't
have any internet access all weekend.
So that was kind of a comedy moment.
I mean, I could only roll them to certain networks because of the way my phone is set.
I had no problems with either Wi-Fi or the 3G.
The Wi-Fi in the deals room and the exhibits hall was the conference Wi-Fi you had to pay
for instead of the free Wi-Fi, which was vaguely annoying, but I had mobile signal down there
so I wasn't really bothered because Ch icon went quite hard on not having a lot of paper
around, which I really applaud.
And I think they thought they were going to have free Wi-Fi down in the conference bit
of the convention.
Oh, they definitely did.
And then the higher did not provide that.
And I think that was a sticking point for anyone who is less technologically minded than
the three of us.
And I think I can see that being a problem.
But equally like, hopefully it's something that next time, next time there is a convention
in Chicago, which presumably will be 2032, the convention committee will be like, last
time you did this and next time you absolutely cannot do this and hopefully it will get sort
of shaken out then.
It did feel like a very nickel and diming thing for this hotel, which must have made
an absolute honest to goodness fortune that weekend.
I mean, you'd say that, but I think the problem is that, you know, right now is an incredibly
bad time for anyone from the UK to be paying the things in dollars because when I looked
at the hotel rates, I thought, oh, the hotel rates are on the high side.
I'll see if anywhere else in Chicago has a better hotel rate.
And the answer was no, unless I wanted a bed in a six-dorm hostel room.
Like, I'm sure they were making money, but compared to the cost of literally anywhere
else in the city, it was a reasonably good deal.
Yes, it was probably quite an expensive.
The dollar is doing quite well at the moment, so the powders do quite badly at the moment,
and everything felt quite expensive.
Yeah, so a lot of it was a shock to basically be thinking, well, this is basically one-to-one.
But I think the prices seem reasonable for what you get, which is a big fancy hotel in
the middle of a made city, although it is sorely in need of renovating.
And I think they compare favorably with things like the cost of hotel rooms near, say, the
Dublin or Helsinki Wilcons.
Oh, I mean, certainly I feel less poor than I did after Helsinki.
Jesus, and Dublin, oh my goodness.
Like, no, I mean, we're talking relatively, but European World Cons.
And actually not, Lunkon so much.
Lunkon had like quite a good range of relatively reasonable housing nearby, but Dublin, especially
Yowza.
And that wasn't Dublin 2019's fault, like I have friends who live in Dublin, and they're
like, no, the housing situation here is just mad, and there's nothing you could do about
it.
But like, I looked at taking a fellowship in Dublin, and one of the things that maybe
think maybe I'll stay in England was trying to look at like where I would live.
And I was like, I don't know, I don't understand.
But moving away from how expensive Chicago is.
One of the things I really liked about Chicon is that I have met an enormous number of people
online at conventions and a hybrid, virtual and hybrid conventions, and through the internet
over the last two and a half years.
And I met a lot of those people for the first time at Chicon in person, and that was incredibly
nice.
And I think it gave me some sense of what some of the feeling of the earlier science fiction
conventions must have been like that.
That some people were just getting a chance to meet somebody who they'd met and corresponded
with for years, but had never actually got to beat.
And Chicon really gave me a lot of that feeling.
And I really, really enjoyed that.
We were all on programme items.
I was on a few programme items.
I was on a couple of kind of more fanishly minded programme items about kind of running
conventions and podcasts and stuff.
But I was on a panel starring Paulina Barron and Eric Choi and Bill Higgins and Mary Robinet
Coel as the moderator on living in space, which was really good.
Mary Robinet's moderation style is amazing.
I don't think I've ever been on a panel as well moderated as that panel.
She did a very good job of explaining to us all how she was going to do it, and then
it worked really well.
And she does the thing where at the start of the panel she asks people for the questions
they have, and then she guides the discussion of the panel to answer all the questions the
audience came to have answered.
And that probably works better if you're a Hugo Award winning novelist and your panels
are busy to the point where you get enough questions that you can structure a panel off
of them.
But it was a very good way of doing it and it meant we covered a wide range of topics.
And people asked questions and some of them I had professional expertise in, which was
interesting and always makes me feel weird.
And the other panelists were fascinating.
Bill Higgins works at Fermilab and so does radiation shielding.
But as he noted on the panel, I've probably got more of a relevant view of that because
obviously at Fermilab their approach to radiation shielding is just put it underground, it'll
be fine.
And that is harder to do in space because there's no ground.
I did point out on the moon, you can use the ground again so maybe the solution is definitely
moon bases.
But yes, it was really good.
And I was on a different panel about Star Wars, I like Star Wars, but we'll come to that
later listeners foreshadowing.
I wasn't on any virtual panels, they were all in person.
I don't know if any of them were streamed.
The mirror when it was was because they were taking questions from the stream.
So that must be on the internet somewhere for people to watch back.
So then you can watch the panel items back now, but I don't know how long for.
Yeah, you've got a month and I'm assuming that's a month from the end of the convention,
but it might be a month from the beginning of the convention, in which case you have about
two days after this episode drops to watch anything you missed from Shikon.
What were you on, Alison and Liz?
I was on two air meat panels and the first one I allowed myself about 45 minutes to get
set up on air meat in my hotel room at the Hyatt.
And it took me about 54 minutes to get set up.
So I was late for my panel because air meat was quite difficult to configure in a hotel
room in a different country.
It turned out.
And it was fine.
I mean, I think there were some issues with, so air meat has some huge advantages, which
is why they use it.
It's a single, it's a kind of one key system.
You basically let people in and then they're in and you gate them once and then it's sorted.
And it has another huge advantage, which is that you, as soon as the panel's over, it's
automatically the recordings there and you can go and look at it and all of that continues
to work.
I think that made up for quite a lot of disadvantages for this convention that was short of people
points, particularly short of people on the virtual side because although people who cannot
attend the convention quite like to attend virtually, we're not seeing yet the community
of people who are prepared to put in a lot of work before the convention for a con they're
not going to be at.
So I think that's something that we need to think about while we're taking virtual conventions
for hybrid conventions forward.
And so I was on two virtual conventions.
One of them was, so how to enjoy your first walk on.
Of course, because I knew nothing about air meat.
Quite a lot of that was actually about how to enjoy it on air meat, which wasn't something
I knew anything about.
And then my other air meat was with Christopher J Garcia, but also with Newt Schutlkotter,
who I don't know, and wasn't actually physically at the convention, but that was a very good,
that was somebody who was good to meet.
And they had some very interesting things to say about podcasting and community, some
building community.
So I really enjoyed being on that panel with Chris and Newt.
And in both the cases, would you say it was good to air meat them?
I mean, I like, I guess people know now, I do like hybrid and virtual quite a lot.
What?
I also hung out a little bit in the fan spaces on air meat.
Not as much as I would have liked, because it turned out I was quite busy hanging out
in the fan spaces at the physical convention.
So if I saw you in air meat, that was great.
And I'm sorry, I didn't get to see more of you, but there'll be other virtual or hybrid
conventions that I am at in the future, I'm sure.
Yeah.
So I mean, I did a panel on con running in the age of COVID-19, which was, in fact, like
broadcast on air meat as one of the sort of live panels broadcast into the air meat.
But I didn't actually do anything solely on air meat.
And I wonder if there are a lot of people who said, oh yeah, I'm fine to do, you know,
virtual panels, I'll be at the con in person.
And then we're like, oh, actually, this is quite a lot more work to set up.
And it would have been a lot easier if I was at home, and maybe that was a mistake.
And you need a bit more kind of like, if you are doing a virtual panel from the con, you
need to know that you kind of need to have the equipment to do it to yourself.
This is not like a hybrid panel where, you know, we'll have some people a virtual and
some people in a room.
It is your effectively, completely virtual.
I learned on the Saturday before the convention that I would need to take my laptop with me
if I wanted to do this.
And we had a bit of a kind of flutter while we went.
Can we possibly take my laptop with me?
And we did eventually conventions.
If you're having virtual participation or hyper participation, you need to let people
know more than a few days before the convention, what tools they need to access your virtual
spaces.
I feel like I've got this giant clockwork key in my back and I can just round me up again.
Right.
You're right.
They're the big advantage of AirMeet.
I think is that it could probably run with kind of fewer volunteers because roll is actually
you could just do it on like zooms and discords.
If you have 15 simultaneous zoom feeds running for a convention, that is a lot to manage.
And the fact that AirMeet could kind of have this and it would automatically, you know,
bring in rooms and things.
Just having enough people to kind of know what's supposed to be going on in what room
at what time is is a lot.
So I think sometimes we forget that things that scale to like three streams do not scale
to a world-con-sized thing.
Especially they were trying to have a full thing of virtual readings and virtual table
talks and everything.
Yeah, I think maybe I need to be clear about, I think also they suffered from a lack of
people really being setting up AirMeet in advance.
And I know there was a guide on how to get on to AirMeet, but I mean, I wasn't planning
to use it for any panels, so I didn't really look at it in detail.
I just basically knew I wasn't going to be able to do that because I'm a convention person.
I did watch a few panels on AirMeet and it was totally fine.
I didn't have any problems with it, but I think that's just me.
Other people had more problems.
We watched the opening ceremony in our room while drinking beers and eating cold pizza.
Yeah, but that wasn't actually on.
AirMeet because what they did was they had a stream of that direct to YouTube.
So I put the YouTube stream on the TV.
Well, I went down and it was extremely busy and hadn't started yet.
So I retreated and came back up to the room and found that it had started and my room
was quite a lot less busy and had my wife in it.
So, um, hara, that was quite good.
Sadly, it also had me in, um, to ruin the moment.
I didn't ruin the moment.
Liz was good.
She was good roommate.
I mean, basically, listeners, I spent quite a long time with Liz in the States.
Well, again, we'll come on to that later for shadowing.
I have one more thought about my in-person events.
I was on about half a dozen, mostly fan and fan related.
And the kind of fan con, fanzine and fan history and fan content stuff was all pretty well
attended, actually.
These were in rooms that would seat about 50 to 100 people and they were, you know, they
weren't full, but they weren't empty either.
It was fine.
Um, I was on one con running panel about organizing a good fan lounge and that was very badly attended
and I heard several other people on con running panels saying that con running panels were
terribly attended and I wonder whether the world con should be putting a little bit less
effort into con running panels because none of the con runners have any time at a world
con to go to programs.
Yeah, I did two con running fannish panel.
One was con running, one was about what I learned from fandom and the con running one
was not particularly well attended despite having what I thought would be reasonably well
known panelists on, I mean, not me, but the other ones.
I thought they were bigger draws.
I was on, I was on building fandom events, myths versus reality.
It was me, Vince Daugherty, Michael Wallace, who was the moderator, Kathy Green and Brenda
Noiseau.
We were initially knocked outnumbered by the audience and that did change by the end with
some late comers.
But Vince said that one of the con running panels he'd been on earlier in the weekend,
there was literally one person in the audience.
The thing is, if you're a con runner and you're at world con, you're probably, especially
because this panel was opposite the business meeting.
And so there's an element here that a lot of the con runners who are going to world con
might either be running fan tables in the dealers room for the conventions they're running
or be at the business meeting trying to affect how the conventions they run will be run in
the future.
And so may not be at the con running panels.
It also might be the case that a lot of the con running panels at world con seemed like
quite con running 101.
They weren't really going into like, they all seemed quite surface level topics.
I don't know if that's fair, but like, I do wonder whether the con runners at a world
con probably don't need that 101 tack and the people coming to a world con who have never
run a convention before might not be going to those panels.
And I don't know, and it might just be that it was bad at Chicago, but it will be great
when a pegging chain do like, because it might just be a quirk of who was there.
It's hard.
It's really hard.
But yeah, they, I don't get the impression it was well attended as a sort of concept,
the con running material.
I thought there was some quite interesting, I mean, just to push back.
So I thought there was some quite interesting con running panels, you know, there's one
about mental health and con running, which I think is a good thing to be discussing about
how you take care of your con runners.
There was one about how we, you know, support a convention in Hindi from across the globe
and running conventions in, in, you know, places where maybe they don't have great access
for virtual conferences and things like that.
So I think there were a few and then there were also some like more 101 panels.
Yeah, it's really hard to tell who's going to actually attend a panel.
The other thing that very surprised me about the programme coming from an Easter Connie
type background is that those rooms that seat 50 to 100 people, they were mostly not miked.
So I was in most of my items were in unmiked rooms and there's it's been ages.
It's been a decade since we did this in, in Britain for the East Kong and even smaller
conventions that I've run with Mike to all of our programme spaces.
I think we get a lot of criticism if we asked panels to run in unmiked rooms, even quite
small rooms these days.
So I don't know if British fans are Deaf-a-on-average than US fans or if this is just a cultural thing
that just hasn't quite got there yet.
This is, this also leads to fewer programme streams because obviously you're then constrained
by the number of, the number of rooms you can put a, a tech setup into.
I mean, I have no inside information on this, but I mean, I suspect it could have just been
budget issues.
You don't quite have the budget to do something and everything.
But you also for this con wanted to run lots of programme streams because you did not really
want overflowing programme rooms.
You ideally wanted people to have a bit more space to spread out.
I think people do not want to cram themselves back into programme rooms yet.
So they had the kind of extra dilemma there of, you know, fewer attendees and you would
expect for a Chicago world con, but not wanting to put them into kind of a smaller space.
And that is a big issue.
On the one hand, I know that by all reports, Ch icon had troubles with their budget, which
must have been very difficult.
But I do think that stuff like making sure programme rooms are mic'd.
And also stuff like even the big programme rooms didn't have a mic per programme participants.
A lot of the time we were sort of sitting quite closely to each other so we could both
use the same mic.
And I don't know how much it costs to mic up a room for disclosure, no idea.
Although I appreciate there are many reasons why it might have been difficult.
I do wish it had been better done, especially because we're wearing masks.
And so the inability to hear people is worse as anyone who's listened to the last episode
of OctoThob will have heard the masks muffle you slightly, which is, you know, problematic.
Also, you can't lipread if people are wearing masks, which even people with full hearing
do lipread all of the time, if they can.
There were parties every night, Glasgow ran a party.
I think every night, except the first night was technically a Dublin party with Glasgow
input and they didn't run one on like the third night maybe, but they run one every
other night.
Yeah, they didn't run one on the site selection night.
And there was like other parties, there was a party with fantastic margaritas.
There was the Manticorns who were running parties.
There were just lots of parties.
I liked the parties.
I should shout out the Fanak and Duff 50th Anniversary Party, which was a jolly good party, which
did not have wild big drinks, but did have quite nice beer and also a lot of very civilised
people sitting around and chatting.
I quite liked the parties.
I don't like the parties when they're crowded and noisy and you can't sit down and the conversations
are essentially very superficial.
So I much prefer what I'd like is the situation that we once had in the UK where you sit in
the bar in the earlier part of the evening and then you have room parties in the later
part of the evening.
I've found the early part of the parties to be rather tarsome, but once they start to
thin out, they are pretty good.
But then you've discovered that it's the same.
It turns out that the set of drunken reprobates in room parties at two o'clock in the morning
is there's a big overlap every time, right?
So you get to know all these people if you do enough of it.
And some of them are the same ones who would be around the bar very late at night at the
UK convention.
Unsurprisingly.
Yeah, I think I just don't like the WorldCom party make up as much as definitely John
doesn't possibly be Alison.
You know, if the parties are great, it's great.
The Glasgow parties and the Dublin Thank You party were great.
But a lot of the time it's sort of you wandering into a hotel room with a few people and you
know, they've done their best to put some decorations up and they'll give you a thimble
full of drink or maybe even a margarita.
Oh, I didn't get the margarita gone to bed and you have some more conversations.
Then you go to kind of another hotel room with some decorations up, have a small drink.
You know, it just I'd much rather have like a kind of bar culture where you have like
one main social space where you can float about and chat to different people.
And yeah, that appeals me much more than kind of going to lots of random rooms.
And so I just kind of just kept going back to the Dublin party and the Glasgow parties
because I had two people in there that I wanted to talk to.
Like I would if they were in the bar.
So the thing I don't like about the Eastercon bar culture is that everyone sits down and
then that is it for the night.
If you want to have a varied night, you have to move around the bar and at the parties
because they're all parties, people move and so you have different groups of people at
different points of the night.
So it actually feels varied.
Whereas like at an Eastercon, like often I'll be at midnight and I'd be like, I could
stay here for the next two hours talking to these people and it would be more of the same
or I can go to bed.
And that is I never have that thought at a world con ever or not an American world con.
So I do quite like that aspect of the social scene.
I know a Spaniard very much values that aspect is one of the things she finds.
She misses most about the US scene is not having that sense of like movement.
Chacon might have been a little bit.
So there was at least one party that I was invited to that only got started at midnight
and I didn't know about because I wasn't reading the relevant person's Facebook page
during the convention and there may be more of that.
So there may be more parties because there weren't that many parties compare.
I mean the parties, the parties that anticipation were quite good.
There were less parties than there were at Chacon 7.
There's a pandemic heart now, I said.
This is probably a significant disincentive to partying for most people.
Yes, that's the other thing is that the way I have fun at parties also turns out to not
probably be very Covid safe.
So that's that.
Yeah, I think it sounds like I move around Eastacomba a lot more and I feel like a lot
more I see a lot more of the convention there throughout the day and the evening.
Whereas I felt there were a huge numbers of people at Chacon that I didn't see because
they weren't at the parties and then I don't know where they are.
And yeah, I think just I feel more uncomfortable, kind of randomly wandering around hotel rooms,
seeing what drinks they've got and awkwardly shuffling out when I don't know anyone.
Yeah, so I had to walk quickly, shuffle out from one party that I was expected to be quite
a good party because I was on my own at that point and I was like, I'm perfectly happy
to meet people on my own.
But in fact, it turned out to be a room full of people that I had almost zero interest
in conversing with.
So, you know, probably wouldn't be better at a kind of group of three or four, which
was for some of the types.
Well, I think you have to be, I definitely find that if I'm in a party, I'm not enjoying
it.
I'm like, I'm a go.
I don't think that's a problem.
But I do think you have to be willing to be like, Oh, no, this is terrible.
I'm going to go and leave now and not worry about the optics very much because no one's
going to remember you.
Oh, yeah, you could definitely do that.
I mean, I don't think anyone cares.
Yeah, they don't particularly want people in their party, not having a good time.
So that's okay.
Yeah, that could have been in a nice bar for all this time.
I spent wandering around trying to find the good party.
My primary motivator with the parties is that it feels different every night and it
feels like there are different spaces which I enjoy.
I don't.
And like, especially on the first night where there was like the random party being thrown
by the two chaps that had the throbbing box in their room with the margaritas.
That was a great party because that was my favorite party of the weekend.
It was a really interesting group of people.
So several of whom I didn't know and many of whom I then met over again over the weekend
because they were people who, they were the sort of people who were drinking margaritas
at the time at two o'clock in the morning, you know.
So I did meet some of them again and they made margaritas with a beer in them, which
was kind of weird, but it was good.
But it was very nice.
I was thinking we get the margarita and you tip beer and tough it.
No, they were making, the beer was part of like the margarita mix.
It was like a sour beer and they were using it.
It was part of the basis of the margarita.
The margaritas were probably...
And they tasted like margaritas.
They tasted like good margaritas, but they were like a beer-based recipe.
It was impressive.
And then there was the Hugo's.
Yes, we went to Hugo's.
Oh yes.
Speaking of amazing parties.
The Hugo Awards ceremony was on Sunday.
There was a pre-award reception where we all went and we had our photos taken and we had
a drink and we could have paid $9 for extra drink, but we decided not to.
And then we went into the Hugo Award ceremony itself.
And then afterwards there was another reception.
Yeah.
With cake.
Um, and my mother told me that if I can't say anything nice, I shouldn't say anything
at all.
So let's talk about the pre-award reception and the awards themselves.
So the pre-award reception was good.
There's photos of us.
Hopefully they come out some point.
I haven't seen any of the photos from that bit come out.
Yeah.
I've seen lots of photos of people having taken photos of people having their photo taken.
But I haven't seen any of the photos that were taken.
Yeah.
We haven't seen any of the official photos.
But I wanted to do a shout out to Castor who Cathy Bond wrote into being Hugo Award
finalist liaison and had never actually been to a Worldcon before.
And they were great the entire beforehand and through the weekend and is now on the Hugo
finalist discourse going, "I am going to track down those photos for you guys."
So hopefully they will track down the photos for us.
I enjoyed the Hugo's.
It was good.
I remit Brendan Nwazow who I was on a panel with.
But because we were both wearing our glad rags and had our hair done, neither of us
recognized the other until we exchanged details.
And she was like, "I already fully wore Twitter."
And I was like, "I wonder why that is."
And it turned out it was because we'd be all paneled together.
Why bother, John?
You hadn't added your hair, did your hair just kind of miraculously fell into awesomeness
somehow?
I put hairspray in it, Liz.
All right.
Did you?
Yeah.
It's so warm.
It does.
I put the hairband in and I leave it there for two minutes so my hair goes sticky up and
then I take the hairband out and I hairspray it so it stays and then I'm done.
Sarah Felix made me a tiara that took my Hugo pin as part of the decoration like tiara
and matched the coloring and style of my dress and also my necklace and was absolutely amazing.
Thank you, Sarah.
It's unbelievable.
I'm so thrilled.
I bought a necklace for Hugo's in the art show basically on the morning of the Hugo's and
it just felt very kind of serendipitous that Vanessa had a necklace in the art show which
was perfect match for my dress.
So thank you very much, Vanessa, for making such lovely art.
So I would like to give a shout out to Tammy Coxen who had the thankless task of trying
to wrangle each Hugo category, get all the finalists into one place so you can take a
photo of all of them which is basically almost impossible because it's hard to wrangle a
bunch of people at the better times and not when they're extremely nervous and trying
to drink their $1, $9 beer and not disrupt their mask.
And networking with people who might be important for their professional career or just that
they've always wanted to meet furiously.
I failed to meet the people that I always wanted to meet because I was too busy eating.
And that is living your best life, Liz.
The people I'd always wanted to meet turned out to be dumplings.
They were bowel.
There were people I wanted to meet and by the time I realised that I'd had a nice time
like chatting and eating dumplings for an hour, I had not left myself any time to actually
meet them, especially when I went to Lou and got back and discovered that we were now all
standing around for some reason so we got good seats in the already reserved seating area.
And in the old days at Helsinki and San Jose and Dublin, the time you met the people you
had always wanted to meet was at the party after the Hugos.
But the problem was that the party after the Hugos was put on by the very lovely Cheng
Dubid and it consisted of the food that hadn't been eaten at the pre-awards ceremony plus
some bad cake and a single flute of extremely sweet, fizzy white wine.
And so I ate some cake and had my fizzy white wine and decided hmm and then went straight
up to the Glasgow party which was far better in every single respect.
There was about a flute of fizzy white wine per third or finalists as well.
Yes.
So there weren't enough glasses of wine for anything like everyone who was there.
It took us a while to realise that what we should have done was all brought a straw and
drunk the fizzy white wine, three of us with a straw each and take the photo as is the
octaloped tradition.
Unfortunately we had one each like reprobates.
It basically did not encourage people to stick around after the ceremony and hang out.
And that was a very great shame because one of the very good things about the parties
at 2017, 18 and 19 was that everyone was hanging out afterwards as you had time to
get drunk enough to go up to defeat digs and be like you're really good.
Which I'm sure was less fun for defeat digs than it was for everyone else.
But like you know.
I think I did that at Helsinki and I just did it in the bar.
Oh yeah, that also works.
I mean I think you've been spoiled by going to three losers parties that had a large budget
then because the loser party was pretty much the same as like the official Helsinki run
losers party in 2016 which is you know with the best will in the world they could not
compare with someone hiring an offsite venue and putting a lot of money into it.
And I mean what I've said is the downside of there being the fancy offsite losers party
is it meant that anyone who didn't get nominated for Hugo could not hang out with anyone who
was nominated for Hugo.
Yeah.
Because basically for those years the people who won and the losers would all kind of go
off to that party and you didn't really see them.
So it was really nice to be able to go up to Glasgow party and then just hang out with
you know a bunch of people who were just at the come.
No I mean that is fair but I had done that for the previous three nights so there is an
element where I was like oh you know nice party would have been good.
I went to better budgeted Hugo losers parties in 2005 and in 2014 and they still weren't
the George RR Martin huge budget kind but they were they were significantly better budgeted
than this one was.
Do you mean the one in 2014 or the one run by 2014?
The one in 2014 which was the Spokane one which we did think was pretty bad at the time
but it did go on quite a lot longer than this one did.
Yeah but you were my all the way.
Yeah because the Chengdu one I think even the people like us who are on the kind of low
end of the Hugo prestige scale had left after half an hour.
I remember being at the one in Reno in 2011 and that one went for like an hour and a half
two hours because you I mean like there was a bar and you got a couple of free drinks
afterwards and so people did stick around and it and so like obviously the ones run by
George RR Martin were fantastic and there was a lot of money spent but I do think that
there is a like the Chengdu one didn't have a bar.
Yeah.
What like have someone selling drinks?
I'm not saying it has to be a million pound party thrown by a millionaire for all his mates
that's like in the ritziest place in the city but I do think it needs to be more than some
sad cake.
I mean I think you also have to take into account that there are probably twice as many people
invited to the Hugo Luther party than there were in 2014 or 2005.
Oh maybe but you also have to take into account the Chengdu have an awful lot of US dollars
that they cannot spend and so realistically speaking.
It's true they could have spent all the US dollars.
They could have had a few beers yes.
Glasgow did a consistently better job every night.
Yeah I was going to say they rather less good party than the 50th anniversary of Duff and
Falak party okay.
Yeah fair enough.
I mean yeah they should probably like there's got to be an in between where you know we
can't have you know really super fancy parties but just something with a bit more gets a bit
more socialization going rather than I'm going to drink my own glass of wine and then run away.
Yeah you do need to put drink into your Hugo finalists after the ceremony because they're
going to need sorry we're all starting like alcoholics here.
Can I skip back to the Hugo rehearsal now because I forgot to mention it.
Yeah go on.
So the first is that it was our one chance to hold a Hugo we should have made a bit more
of that and taken some photos then we got some photos with the.
Well also two of us didn't told you goes.
I held a Hugo at the Glasgow party after the Hugo's.
I did I and I've got photos because the June Hugo was passed around to everyone who wanted
to touch it.
I have photos of John with the June Hugo which are available for a very low price.
This is not the cover up to this episode.
No no you can cut that if that is too much but you know.
Nope I take solace and joy from that.
So I sat down next to a man and started making at the rehearsal and started making kind of
a pleasant conversation as you do and he was wearing a basket.
I was wearing a basket.
It wasn't the brightest room and after some time I realized it was Charlie Stross who I
have known for 30 years.
Yes I did see that and I was like I recognized it was Charlie Stross.
Yeah I recognized him from behind as being Charlie Stross.
I probably would have recognized him from behind right.
Yeah well because and I don't know if you know this Alison Charlie Stross looks a lot
like Charlie Stross like a lot like Charlie Stross even with a mask on.
I might have been a bit struck out but also he didn't recognize me and again we have known
each other you know we we've been to each other's houses we know each other fairly well.
He had a good reason to be struck out he was up he was up for a Hugo and his Hugo's matter
for his publication and like agents and our Hugo was just a little bit of a laugh.
Although he might he had a good chance of winning a Hugo.
How long do you go?
Congratulations to Anna Lee and Charlie Jane for winning Best Fancast.
Congratulations to Cora Bueller for winning Best Fan Writer and congratulations to Sean
and McGuire and Lee Moyer for winning the other two fan categories.
I was glad to see how well represented fandom was across the fan categories I think it's
really great and tribute to the Hugo's.
For anyone who has not looked at the the detailed results which we did approximately one second
after the detailed results were made available.
Which was approximately ten minutes after they ought to have been.
There is a general there is a general thing people saying or maybe the statistics should
not be available immediately because I think some people read them then then you know our
souls to finalists about what is contained in them.
But I think if the results had come out any later Alison would literally have exploded.
One of the very few cast-on memories I have of my first Worldcon which was 1987 and I'm
also really doing any fan act apart from Go to Parties then was leaving the Hugo Awards
which I've found a bit kind of dull and then somebody handing me the sheet of paper with
the long list on and I going oh but this is good.
So it is one of the things that is very caught by a sense of who I am as a fan and what I
value about fandom is that piece of paper or now electronic link.
Though I did manage to get one of the ten pieces of paper that Nicholas had wickedly
run off so there would be some printed copies.
I would say I think I would be fine with it coming out the next morning in general.
But yes I do like it.
And it's because it's kind of when I was a baby fan it was kind of the fact that the
long list comes out instantly was imprinted on my hand brain and I now follow it around
like a baby duck.
Yep you often strike me as a baby duck because you're quite a lot smaller than me and you've
got a very pronounced bill.
[Barking]
Right shall we do pics?
No because I'm still going to tell people where we came in the Hugos.
Oh yeah tell people where we came in the Hugos Liz.
The whole point of being that up was to say have you analysed the stats Liz you're going
to do a statistical research and charts maybe.
No because every time you say you're going to do a chart I'm less likely to make a chart.
[Laughter]
Because I listen was like you're going to make a chart right like 10 minutes after the Hugos
and so now every time I listen to Ryan's me I'm like well I'm that ping-poo gift off
well now I'm not doing it.
But we came fifth.
So thank you very much everyone who voted for us.
Yes we managed to come fifth by one single vote which is quite exciting.
Because otherwise we'd have been dead flat last.
And we did also get 46 nominations so even though we voted to ratify and keep EPH we
actually didn't hear this year to get on the ballot.
So that was very nice to see.
Yes.
Thank everyone I will do more Hugo.
I will do more Hugo stats and error in the future at some point.
I would also like to say thank you to everyone who voted in the fan categories because they
were all awarded and that was great.
And congratulations to Hugo Girl our bestest friends now who were third.
Yes.
Because we're basically like well we can't win maybe Hugo Girl will win.
That seems a bit grateful now because neither of us did but yes.
Yes so it was good.
[Laughter]
Did we mention how much fun we had hanging out with the Hugo Girl people?
It was very good.
Especially I hung out with Hailey on her last night all the way till four o'clock.
Or 30th of the morning when she had to go and catch her plane.
That was really good.
There are not photographs.
That was at the Glasgow party.
See that's what you should have done on your last night instead of sneaking out of John's
room at five o'clock in the morning list.
You should have ported until five o'clock in the morning.
We went for ice cream.
You know you're complaining Hailey's last night and Liz's last night were different last
night so Liz.
There were no parties on that night apart from I guess I could have tried to sneak into
old farts party at 4am.
No.
I should have gone to the old farts actually if that was that night.
I was asleep.
I was asleep as well because I was about to spend 32 hours returning home and so I thought
maybe you know six hours sleep would help.
I was asleep because I was going to get on a plane from Chicago to Orlando and go straight
back to Star Wars which is an excellent segue into pics.
[Laughter]
I'll go to where Star Wars after you two so do you want to do your pics first?
Is this a pic or is this like a special three hour explanation of why John loves Galaxy
set?
Oh no I mean I did.
I've written it all up Liz and that will be available to anyone who stays still too long
at Eastacom.
My pic this episode is Robert Jackson Bennett's Founders Trilogy which I finished on the plane
home from Chicago and left me in the embarrassing situation of having a little cry on a plane
because it was that good.
So it is a fancy trilogy.
I really like Robert Jackson Bennett's previous fancy trilogy which was nominated for a Hugo
for Best Series in 2018.
This is his follow up.
It's essentially about it's a city state which runs on a kind of magic called scribing
which essentially you can, the magic system is you write commands onto physical objects
and it alters the way they interact with reality.
So the first novel is essentially sort of a series of heists to try and steal a very powerful
artifact from a thief who can look at scribed objects and know what's going on and it all
interacts with these merchant houses and they end up stealing this prize artifact but it's
things like you know you can essentially fly by making yourself a scribe gravity rig which
thinks temporarily that gravity is going in the opposite direction and things like this.
So there's a huge amount of very fun ideas in there and that's just the first book but
then in the second one they get more deeply into okay so you can basically tell objects
to rewrite the laws of reality.
What else can you do by rewriting the laws of reality and it gets really deep into what
if you could rewrite the laws of reality surrounding people and what if you can get really deeply
into kind of you know rewriting reality itself.
I'm not really doing it justice because it is like an entire fantasy trilogy about this.
It sounds very interesting.
It's kind of a really great idea that doesn't just like do three books using this great idea
but then kind of each book it's building on it's like well what if I took this and then
kind of showed you what my imagination thinks we could do with this.
Plus it's also got great characters in there a lot of them get really character arcs and
a really good send off or pay off at the end you know by the end of it I'm basically crying
over a magical artifact so yeah I will definitely be nominating it for best series I may put
the last volume lock lands on my best novel ballot and I think it's I can recommend everyone
read it now because it's finished and it's six landing.
And I read Bennett's previous trilogy which was the Divine Cities because it was nominated
for best series in 2018 and at the time I thought it was an incredibly good example of
the sort thing I think should be nominated in that category.
I remember thinking it was amazing it lost out to Lois McMaster Boozjold.
I had not realized that that trilogy had wrapped up but now I do know it has wrapped
up I may have to read that in my pre Hugo nomination reading next year so thank you Liz.
The previous trilogy was amazing I really really really enjoyed it.
Yeah I would say this is as good and it's kind of recognizably the same but also very
different and maybe interested in some different ideas.
So as well as go to the Worldcon John and Liz also went to Orlando to do Disney things
you might hear a bit more about those in a minute and I have massive massive FOMO because
I had checked my bank account before booking my Chicago holiday and I knew that I could
not possibly have added an extra week in Orlando or indeed anything else to the holiday.
So I thought oh this is and then they kept going well you don't you know interactive
things are amazing and immersives are amazing and you should do more of the malice and I
was like oh oh I should.
So what we did was we booked a trip for the family to a place called Phantom Peak which
is an immersive at Canada Water where for the princely sum of 34 pounds you can run around
for an evening in what the one-star reviews say is an overpriced theme bar and the five-star
reviews say is a fantastic cross between a escape room and a bar and a theme park and
a lop and I had a fantastic time.
One of the other reviews said we did some of the trails but then we sat in the bar for
the rest of the evening while our children ran around and did a load of water trails
and that sounded like quite a good way to experience it because I think they have about
16 trails in total which are all of the form such and such a weird thing has happened.
Go and find this person to talk to who will tell you the next stage of your fetch quest
and you do this for a bit and you end up with very sore feet.
I hit by rings.
If you go in a weekday it's 34 pounds and the beer is pretty good and they also have
got trails and we had a splendid time so if you're anywhere near Docklands that's a
jolly good night out I would say and we were put on to it by Fiona Moore and Caroline
Mersey and Russell Smith who had all been and you don't have to dress up but we did
dress up just the tiniest bit and I think that helps as well and it was a lot of fun.
It is a sort of steampunk Westworld themed town organized around one of the old docks
so it uses Docklands in quite an interesting way and there's kind of there's a hooker
platypus game and a really weird boat ride where Marianne got absolutely soaking wet
because they had calculated that three adults could go on this boat ride but they did not
think they would weigh as much as three of us so it was quite wobbly, wobbly that they
thought we got a lot of water in.
There's a whole backstory it is so it's fictional because there has been a blimp crash and there
is some weird stuff going on in the town and you kind of learn about this through the
setup trails but as well as the setup trails there's quite a lot of meta story as well
that's not in any of the trails which is kind of weird so now I want to go back and do a
bit more of it and strongly recommended if you're in the area.
I'm very excited at some point to do it probably not this month.
I assume it's going to be around for a while I assume it's not a limited time thing.
Well, except for insofar as any business is a limited time thing.
But they might go bust because I don't see how they're going to sell only tickets in
the winter.
Why wouldn't they sell tickets in the winter?
Because it's outdoors.
I mean it's under cover but it's in a dock so you're kind of running around the dock.
I think I am less worried about being outside of the winter than you.
Yeah, he said you got very wet right?
People won't do that in the winter.
You were not supposed to get wet.
Our anger wet on the boat ride because we overbalanced the boat because they should
have put two of us on one boat and two of us on the other.
But there's no log flumes because when you said that I was imagining a log flume but
I'm now not imagining a log flume.
No, it's not like a theme park.
It's not like a theme park.
It's much closer to being a lop than it is to being a theme park.
Although there's some kind of infrastructure, mostly what you're doing is talking to the
inhabitants of the town about their lives and why they're there and what they're doing
there and why they came there and where they're going and so on.
But I was going to say I think 35 pounds for something with a lot of actors that is quite
cheap.
That is quite cheap.
It's just starting at 34 pounds but I don't understand what that means.
Yeah, it's 34 pounds on a weekday and I think it's about 49 at the weekend and they do
two, you're there for five hours so they do two sitting daytime one which will be full
of children I'll tell you and then an evening one which probably won't be.
It's only 39 pounds at the weekend.
They should charge more for this.
And do they sell you a lot of beer?
Yeah, no, and they saw me two beers but the beers were six pounds a pint which I would
say for four pure, it's perfectly good brand.
I would say six pounds a pint for beer.
A) I'd just be in a Chicago.
And B) if you go to a bar in that area of London you will be paying five pounds fifty
a pint so it didn't seem ludicrously expensive at all.
Yeah, so they're not making pocket loads on their drinks either.
They originally had a rather poor food offering that was expensive but they've improved the
food offering and although we didn't actually eat there we ate at a, there's a food caught
outside Canada water station and we had some food off of Van there because we'd been warned.
But so we didn't actually taste the food inside but we just have hacked into Lato.
I have an adorable picture of their sample codes which have tiny crocheted platypuses
at the rather than ice cream.
No, I want to go.
I would want to dress up because it is a steampunk world and the worst thing about that kind
of thing is when you've got a lot of people wearing like band t-shirts and jeans and
you're like this does not feel very steampunky so I would definitely want to at least make
the effort to match the aesthetic.
I think a lot of these things you get out what you put in so like I'd be very up for
doing that.
I've never been tempted to go to like a lop like empire or anything like that but I think
with this kind of thing where it's like you pay money and do it more as a theatre production
tempts me a lot more because I think I would have to put less in to get more out than of
a traditional art.
Yeah, I think 100%.
Okay, do you pick John?
My pick.
What is your pick John?
So I would see Liz for a week and Liz is great and my pick is Liz.
Hey.
So in 2020 me and my family were going to go to Orlando to go to Walt Disney World, partly
to visit Galaxy's Edge and do other things and obviously Covid got in the way and our
Virgin Atlantic ticket was made into an open ticket that we had to spend by mid 2022 and
then we got nominated for a Hugo Award.
And so long story short, I went on a family holiday to Orlando and then flew from that
family holiday to Worldcon to kill two birds with one stone and Liz was there as well because
Liz had some time before Worldcon where she was like, well, I could do a thing in America
and I said, I'll go to Orlando and Liz went, I like Disney and so Liz was in Orlando also.
And so I've got a life hack for jet lag, which is if you get off the plane in Orlando and
immediately go and hang out for three hours at a water park with Liz eating Mickey Mouse
ice creams, that gets you over jet lag instantly.
So if you're ever flying to the States, just contact Liz, ask her to meet you at a water
park in America somewhere and feed you ice cream and you'll be right as Wayne.
And so we went to Star Wars Galaxy's Edge the next day and it was pretty great.
I've very much enjoyed it.
Those of who have been listening to the podcast for a while may know that I quite like Star
Wars on the plane to America.
I read the Galaxy's Edge novel, so I was like prepared for Galaxy's Edge when I arrived
and then we went on the first day, we went to Oga's cantina, which is a Star Wars cantina
in Galaxy's Edgeland and it was so cool and they have like Star Wars drinks and they
have beer flights and they have Tiki mugs and it was amazing.
And then they also have kind of they're basically the entire places like being in Star Wars
and they use sound effects very cleverly.
So there's like sounds of starships going overhead as you're walking around.
And I went with a friend after Chicago by coincidence, my friend from uni Fred was on holiday.
In Orlando at that point, so we went to Galaxy together and his partner remarked saying,
"I've only just properly twigged that when I hear starships going overhead, they're not
actually starships, they're sound effects because it is so immersive that you just don't
really notice that it's not real.
It was very good.
There is an app which you could download which has an augmented reality game you can play
throughout the park.
I didn't really do that as much on the first day but I did a lot of it on previous things.
There are two rides both of which designed to be relatively accessible even to people
who don't really like rides.
This band is not a huge fan of roller coasters but enjoyed both a lot.
It was really, really good.
And yeah.
Did you dress up?
No, I didn't.
I haven't got a Star Wars cosplay at the moment.
Don't you think that dressing up and having there not be lots of people walking around
in jeans and t-shirts is just as important in a Star Wars immersive as it is in Steampunk?
I'm just wondering.
Yes, but I have a question for you.
In the London Docklands in mid September, was it 40 degrees?
No.
There is an element here of you're going to be very warm in August in Orlando as it turns
out.
But there are places, I've seen Star Wars.
There are places in the Star Wars universe that are 40 degrees.
There must be appropriate clothing in those places.
Well, mostly if you live in that kind of place all the time you get used to the heat, right?
I mean, the appropriate clothing for wearing to a theme park in Orlando in August is basically
as little as possible and incredibly sturdy shoes.
Yeah.
It doesn't really feel like it destroys the immersion somehow.
I mean, also bear in mind that Star Wars Galaxy's Edge is only one small part of a
much larger theme park as well.
So most people are not spending their entire day most in Galaxy's Edge.
They're going there for a couple of hours and then going off to ride the Slinky Dog World
Acosta.
I spent a large amount of my day in Galaxy's Edge and then I spent a further five days
in Galaxy's Edge going back and doing all the things because there is a game and I did
the game.
I haven't quite finished the game so I'm going to have to go back.
This is very sad.
But yeah, so there's two, there's a ride where you can ride the Millennium Falcon and
you get to fly or be the gunner or be the mechanic on a smuggling run to Corellia and
that's very cool.
I got to fly the Vulcan on my own because I went on the single rider queue and I got
to the front and there was literally no one else because I think they just had a breakdown
and they just reopened and they were like, do you just want to do it on your own?
And I was like, yes.
And so I did all my own and it was brilliant.
And then there's Rise of Resistance, which I don't want to talk too much about but is
amazing.
I wish I'd been able to go with my friend but unfortunately I had to fly back to London
because the day I went with him was the day we were flying home.
But I said, what was your face like when you got off the shuttle in Rise and he sent
me a photo of him being like this?
And I was like, yes, that is a correct face.
It does sound amazing.
It does sound like, and Disney generally does sound like it would be amazingly good.
I don't want to suggest it would be.
It is quite fun.
And Rise of Resistance isn't broken, which unfortunately is a lot.
It is technologically incredible.
There are things where I can only vaguely work out how they are doing those effects.
And it is really good.
I was saying you would love it because there's so many visual illusions and things like that.
You would be like, oh, how are they doing this hologram?
Yeah, I'm saving up my pennies.
I'm going to do it.
But you know, and also I love all of that.
I also love like, I love stuff that was state of the art in 1872 as well.
So even if I don't get to go until it's quite old hat, I'll still like it.
And then I went to get, I went to do the lightsaber, which is kind of a ride you can't
do unless you spend a lot of money on a lightsaber.
Liz, so you get a plus one?
Well, aren't all of these rides you can't do unless you spend a lot of money going to
a theme park?
Well, yeah, but the most of them aren't extra money when you get in.
It's not the rollercoaster tycoon model of charge them when they enter and then charge
them again when they ride.
Yeah, but could you now eBay your lightsaber?
Oh, yeah, but I don't want to.
Yeah.
But yeah, and so it's like a kind of like a little miniature theatrical thing with like
actors and like the speeches perfectly lined up with these sound cues and the lighting.
I don't know what to spoil it to, actually, but it was pretty freaking amazing.
And Espaa was my plus one.
And Liz was my little brother's plus one because my little brother's wife was like,
you do you.
So the lightsaber was very good.
And very sad I just had a whale of a time.
I kind of have this question of, oh, but what wasn't it that everybody else buying a lightsaber
was a seven year old, but I'm sure that's not actually true.
No, I think I don't think and I think there were a couple of kids, but it was definitely
majority.
It's like collectors Lego.
Yeah, it is.
Yeah, I mean, if your kid just wants a lightsaber, you can buy them a $25 plastic lightsaber.
That's the other thing.
Because like if you've got a child who wants a lightsaber, buy them a metal one that comes
with the 36 inch long light bulb on the end is like, yeah.
I could go to Disney when I was 14 to Disney World and it was very good then.
But I feel like they might have a couple of new rides and new attractions.
That was 1979 and Star Wars, Star Wars was an enormous thing, but they didn't have a
thing.
It wasn't owned by Disney.
When did Star Tours open?
Late 80s.
87, yeah.
Yeah, it's possible that they have a few more rides and stuff than they had in 1979
hours and had Space Mountain.
Still have Space Mountain.
And also they hadn't really, I think they've got a lot better at managing queues.
So one of the things about Phantom Peak is of course no queues really.
There was a very sad bit where somebody was waiting to talk to the guy.
We were getting to the end of a quest and getting our pay off for the end of the quest,
which is playing cards that you can keep.
And there were some people waiting to talk to him and they were clearly at the very beginning
of the same quest.
So that was not great.
Yeah, that is tricky.
One of my abiding memories about Disney was that even then they were better at managing
queues than any other theme parker.
I went to quite a lot of theme parks.
But there were a lot of queues.
I remember, I mean, we must have spent more than half our time at Disney World in queues.
Then you need to get up earlier in solution.
No, no, we got into the park at the first moment that you could get into the park.
I mean, this was 1979.
They didn't have all of the fast pass and...
Oh, they don't have fast pass anymore.
They're at anymore.
You've got to pay.
And the Port Marion thing, which we got to do this year, which is that if you're a privileged
person at Port Marion, you get to hang out in the village after everyone's left.
And I think Disney do that right.
Before everyone arises, after everyone leaves.
Yep.
Only if you're Liz.
Which I did.
Because Liz is very special.
John joined me one morning and, you know, we were there half an hour before the scheduled
opening, which was the early opening.
And it was already open.
You basically just like, if you arrived at the time, they say the theme park opens.
You were late.
So that's the way to do it.
I don't think we...
I don't know about you, John, but I did not spend a lot of time in queues.
I mean, I queued for half an hour for Rises since that first day, but that's about it.
The only time I queued for a long time was when I queued for Rises resistance and it broke
down while I was queuing.
That was a long queue.
But especially because if you go to theme parks, I just single ride on most things.
And those, like, you go from, like, some queue to basically zero.
Going as a single rider is so much quicker.
We went on and I think all but one Disney ride, which have a single rider queue, John.
They don't have them.
Oh, no.
That was the Octa Thought podcast.
And it's goodbye for me.
It's goodbye for me.
The
theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod in Competec.com, used
under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
[BLANK_AUDIO]