I have to tell Jerry that we've recorded this now so that she needs to get a finger out and get idea finished.
Hello everyone and welcome to a very special bonus episode of Octothorpe, a podcast for
Crassong and other pastries. I'm John Coxon, I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
Wait, so quite some today?
Yes, so when I decided to start writing my guff report, I decided that most of the
articles were going to be about kind of topics rather than, you know, I went here and I
ate this and I ate that and I ate the other and so also when we had Sandra Bond on doing a very
funny and excellent portion of her Taff report, I thought I know I could do a portion of my
guff report live on Octothorpe, well not live, but on Octothorpe and that would be good and it
would make sense to be the one about Quaslon because obviously I eat a lot of almond quaslon
and I eat a lot of almond quaslon on Octothorpe but not today because today we're recording on a
Saturday rather than a Sunday so I ate at McDonald's instead but hey that's probably off topic already.
So this might get a better title for the printed report but at the moment it is called
Quaslon Engineering, shall I just get going? You guys should interrupt or laugh or whatever
because otherwise I'm going to be very worried by the end of my...
It's going to be like, you know, have your tumbleweed react ready. I'm really not a very picky person.
Was that an intentional joke because it was very funny. Yes! Oh good!
Except as it happens in the matter of coffee shop, I have to have nice coffee obviously and
somewhere comfortable sit down. Ideally that spot should be at a table, big enough to set a tablet
and keyboard on and reasonably close to a pass socket and definitely not a barstools. I'm not
great with barstools on account of having to climb up them. I'm not at all fussy about the
internet access that my coffee shop either free Wi-Fi or fast mobile collection will do and they
need of course to serve a banging almond quassel. So it's a curious thing the almond quassel. What
other peak of human achievement is best made from leftovers? Okay, bubble and squeak. But
almond quassels were developed as a way to use up yesterday's quassel no longer saleable in their
own right. At this point I have to draw a veil over my much-missed local Greg's Outlet Store,
which sold dale croissants in their own right, but they were fine. Take a bunch of dale
croissants, fill them with franger pan, you cover them with icing sugar and almond flakes,
heat them up and nobody will ever know. And yet somehow this has been extrapolated to a work of art,
the sugar and the heat provide just the right degree of caramelisation. There are so many moving
parts, there must be a thousand different ways to make one. In my case I'm after something that
is anxiously perfect in all respects with just the right balance of franger pan,
quassel and sugar and almond. And by right, of course, I mean to my taste, because what
other right could there possibly be? And of course in the manner of the connoisseur,
CXKCD915, I am almost invariably disappointed. This one is too dry, that one is too soggy,
that one has come from the supermarket and no they're never really good, not even the premium ones.
They can be a dale, but not packed with nitrogen and stuffed with preservatives. This one is
vegan, sorry vegans, but the texture of vegan quassels is too crispy for me. These ones have
been made with a single bacon, not a double one, this one doesn't have enough franger pan,
this one has too much and this other one has incorrectly distributed it so one end is
unctuous and the other end is empty. Despite this trail of continuous disappointment,
I order quite a few other quassels as such for the perfect one, I am hampered in this endeavour.
By all insisting on always pronouncing the thing, as I have been doing throughout this
segment, Armand Quasse, who is coincidentally also the hero of my epic fantasy novel.
That's a kind of written joke that will work better in the written version of the article.
This does seem to be entirely the correct way to say it, but in many coffee shops I also have to
put the object of my desire or change what I say to include all the letters I normally a bit,
if I want to actually get an almond quassel, which I always do, Almond Quasselt.
Armandquassels are not known for their health-giving properties and might even be considered a
sometimes food, but the French eatquassels every day and universally the picture of elegance,
they must be doing something right, even if that's just strong black coffee, unfiltered cigarettes
and red wine. I realised this was billed as a chapter of my guff report and you might be wondering
what any of this has to do with Australia. While I was oddly searching for interesting things to
do in Melbourne, one of the things that came up was eat one of the world's best Armandquassel.
Loon is a croissantery set up by a former Formula One racing car engineer.
In one of those great origin stories Kate Reed was working at her dream job but finding it not
all she'd hoped, so was baking a great many pastries to cheer herself up. Eventually she realised that
what she needed was a pivot. I planned a pilgrimage. But Loon has several branches and we fortuitously
passed one while touring the Central Business District with Jaddis Gellb on a cold rainy day.
That allowed us to read a regular quest on but the Armandquassels had all gone for the day.
At peak hours, i.e. before the Armandquassels run out, people queue around the block at Loon.
It was then I learnt that Erwin Hirsch has a branch of Loon at the bottom of his block of flats.
Erwin and Wendy had left their large family home for a new bill flat the previous year and were
promised that that retail unit would have a cafe in it. Anticipating agreeable light lunches,
they were non-plussed to discover it only solved coffee and up market quassels and such as soon
as the latter sold out. Nevertheless, I pressed them to acquire quassels and we went round to see them.
They were brought extra to take to the barbecue that Julian Warner and Lucy Sussex have put on
our honor but also serve for us. And I finally got to try this world-class confection. It was
exceptionally beautiful and as promised, very carefully engineered. The flaked arm and stuck
up vertically like the swords of the iron throne. Most traditionally made Armandquassels a squished
flat but this one retains its classic shape and it tasted very precise. It did balance the flavours
very nicely and the French Japan was evenly spread throughout the croissant and not that sweet.
Each bite was just as you would expect and act exactly as I'd say in principle that I desired.
It looked perfect and it was delicious. You know that if you got another loon quassel it would be
almost identical and just as nice. And I realised that my perfect Armandquassel would just be the
tiniest bit soggier than the loon one and also just very slightly more random.
I know what the title of this episode is now. What's the title of this episode John?
Liz, do you know? No. Very slightly soggier.
Okay. Also maybe the title of the article.
We want you to make 12 identical pastries as they say on the Great British Bake Off
but you could have too much identicalness. I want my Armandquassel distribution to have slightly more
jiggle. No matter how many quassels I eat from Loon, they'll all everyone be in the uncanny
valley of Armandquassel perfection. I have something to show you, declared Damien woman,
after we returned from Womara to the House in Adelaide the following week.
Thought you were about to show us something. But you're about to do like visual aids. No.
No, I don't have anything to show you. No, there will be visual aids for this. I'll have a cover
illustration for it and then maybe also a photograph of a loon Armandquassel. I have something to show
you, declared Damien woman, after we returned from Womara to the House in Adelaide the following week.
It turned out to be a fan scene, an art scene, not an SF scene, all about Armandquasselons.
I was very excited about this because I thought I had found another connoisseur.
I picked it up eagerly to learn about the author's take on the best faces to flying croissant,
her identification of the characteristics of perfect croissant, and her experiences of eating
them. But no, she merely likes Armandquassels and wants you to know that they're good.
I should probably have been tipped off by the staples. It is true that I am almost as
didactic about staples as I am about croissant, but I'd like to think that most people would
struggle with these ones. They were stapled through the centrefold fanzine, a little way from the
left margin. I'm so leaving a fold. Longarm staplers are not exactly rocket science, and I tell you,
this method of fanzine production is shocked me. There we go. In general, Australian coffee is
excellent, and don't they know it? And their coffee shops are generally pretty good, and their pastries
are fine even when they're not a loon Armandquassel. People were very quick to tell me that I would
find it hard to cope in New Zealand, where, according to Australians, the coffee bean is completely
unknown. So as I travelled to New Zealand, I was excited to explore that country's take on my
favourite pastry. But in practice, all thoughts of Armandquassel flew from my mind as I discovered
that every coffee shop in the country, no matter how humble, serves cheese scones, mostly homemade.
Luckily, I was not there long enough to establish a detailed ranking. I loved them all.
So, staples. How do you feel about unstapled fanzines, Alison?
I think they should. Well, I mean, I have no problem with unstapled fanzines
when they are made out of a single sheet of paper.
Oh dear, you're not of like to my fanzine.
Oh, fine. I'm sure I don't like your fanzine. I just might have stapled it before reading it.
That was what Mark used to do.
Yeah, you know.
He sent a lock.
I have a long Armstapler, and I know how to use it.
Did you find in general that the Almond-Crasants were better or worse than the UK?
Like about the same, really. I'm in the same kind of range of really good ones to not like great ones.
I mean, I didn't eat any supermarket ones, whereas in the UK, I do occasionally eat supermarket ones.
I maybe shouldn't say it was that on the podcast, because the answer is
"At the home of my friends when they serve us breakfast."
My favourite Armstapler, of all, and this hasn't quite made it into the article are
other ones from a pastry shop around the chocolateine, which was one of the things we didn't manage to last weekend,
was go and get breakfast from chocolateine, because there were too many places to go and get breakfast from.
You were too busy going to get beer?
Yeah, no, we also had beer and breakfast on Sunday.
Yeah, we went to a brewery called Blondys, and they open at 9am, and they have like a coffee bar,
and they had pastries, and they had an almond croissant, which I actually thought
I didn't like the filling very much, but they also had a cinnamon bun, which was very, very
wonderful. And then they had beer and also curried goat. It was a good couple of hours.
I could detect that the Armstapler, I probably would have had the Armstapler,
which I don't know what principle of somebody hadn't ordered it first, but I could detect from a
distance that it was going to disappoint me. I mean, Stephen's like this with Bonoffee Pies.
You know, he always orders Bonoffee Pies whenever it's an option, and he's
disappointed 99% of the time.
Yeah, I think this is like me in Tiramisu. If I'm at Italian restaurant, I will almost always
order the Tiramisu, and quite often be a little bit disappointed.
Yeah, we had the Tiramisu at a pizza place in Newcastle, and it was like, it was a bit watery,
and I was a bit like, oh, this is disappointing. It's got to be... yeah.
The guy who invented Tiramisu died recently.
Oh, that's sad. So, Julie... when we had Blockta, Julie used to make...
so, Julie is Italian for people who don't know. Julie de Chasare, this is.
She used to make Tiramisu at a giant turkey roasting tin for us, and she used to make
an extra special one for Michael at the time didn't drink, so therefore didn't like the alcoholic
content of Tiramisu. So, but in a smaller roasting tin. So, there was just this vast
quantity of Tiramisu. You can't eat them vastly more than six adults, two children and a dog...
a dog. Six adults, two children, a cat could possibly have eaten, and nevertheless,
somehow we managed it every time, because it doesn't keep.
There's a... if you ever visit Newcastle, which I will, there is a place called the Pink Lane
Bakery, and they do my favorite Newcastle almond croissant, but they are not a coffee shop.
What is your opinion on... ooh... places that are not a coffee shops? That's a very broad question,
isn't it? Because it... oh yeah, that's quite complicated. So, I mean, are you saying places that
serve almond croissant, but... and they're very, very good, but do not serve coffee, so you have to...
they do serve coffee, and they do serve almond croissants. I've never had the coffee, so it might
be terrible, and they also have nowhere to sit. Here's a counter. So, you take your almond croissant,
and you sit somewhere... else? You maybe sit somewhere else, like,
serves coffee, but then they might get the hump about you bringing food from other places.
It's probably a summer activity, John. Obviously, what you need is a park. Yes, you need a park,
which is near both the bakery which sells almond croissants, and maybe a little stall that sells
good coffee. And on the 30 days a year when Newcastle's warm enough to use a park, I'm sure
that's great. It's warm enough to use a park now, and it's March. I bet it is actually, it's lovely
here this weekend. Yeah. I mean, global warming has its downsides, but the warmth in Newcastle is
not one of them. Until the Gulf Stream goes away and it all goes horribly wrong. Oh yeah, then the
coldness in Newcastle will be one of them. I've never tried making croissants because it seems
like there are too many steps. Maybe one day. Massive, massive amount of work. Yeah. And then
if you want an almond croissant, obviously, you have to make your croissants and then wait a day
and then do all the French-Spanish almonds. Hmm, I think you could French-Spanish-Spanish
almond them on day one. Yes, I don't know though. I think because Loon definitely keeps his,
it bakes a load of croissants, and then it, and as it's selling more almond croissants than regular
ones, it keeps a load of them for a day to make the almond croissants out of. But no, I've never
made some, I've made laminated pastry a couple of times, but I generally speaking, I think there's
a reason we haven't experts for this. Go find an expert, buy it from them. Oh yes. I think that's
wise. In general, experts are good. That is the view of this podcast. Well, certainly for things
like pastry chefs and plumbers. You're a plumber. If you're a plumber, write in. And that was the
Octothorpe podcast, and it's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me. And it's goodbye from me.
Hang on, did I actually press the stop recording button? I did not. I should do that.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod in Competec.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license. This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.
Thank you.