I want the left half to shout and cheer.
Okay, that was pathetic. I now want the right half to shout and cheer a lot louder than that.
Okay, left half. Can you beat the right half off you go?
Okay, that integrity. I like that.
[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome to Octa Thor the podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom.
I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott. Liz is we've got a placard for Liz but she's not here.
Oh, we're revealed. So we have an item of business. We have an item of business. It's long and pointy.
Oh, yes, so, yeah. So do you want to bring it up and get your cameras at the ready because this
is a photo opportunity. We need to also arrange you for reasons that we'll see. It's Nicholas,
come around this way. Nicholas, come around this side. This is an on stage, off stage.
So for listeners at home it is April Fool's Day on the day we record and the chapter art for this
episode is a wonderful not a Hugo which is not being presented to us which we are not accepting.
And it is not being presented to us by our stunt Liz Nicholas-Lite.
Oh, oh no, it really is a real hug. It is not a real Hugo.
That is fantastic. It is absolutely remarkable. It's a marvelous art. So for people on the radio,
you can have a look if you see it but I'm going to say a little, oh yeah no, all the way so it
not allowed to hold it. So one of the jokes I didn't get to the newsletter was there is no polite way
to polish a Hugo. So we are very excited to be one of the first people to touch Glasgow 2024's
Hugo based design. I think you've announced that Estelle McCallum Stewart is in the front row of
this podcast and she is now making faces like she's hiding under the table. There is a Glasgow
chair under the table. If found please return to us. By Hugo based designer Sarah Felix.
Can I talk to the object? And also by Vincent Viefmanka. So I'm going to give you a description
of this for the radio but so they have taken an act which I think is an actual Peter Western style.
It has been, it has been, it has been, it's like they talk about this Hugo. They've taken a real
Peter Western style Hugo and they have rocket because it's obviously not a Hugo. I need to say
that. So Esther is that it is a what? A tartan rocket. A tartan rocket and they have dipped it.
Like they've wrapped it like when you get one of those taxis that advertises just eats.
Yes and I think the question on the question on everyone's mind is which local businesses will
be being advertised on the real heroes. So obviously they've said she's under the table again listeners.
We've sent her under the table again. We're not nice people. And so they've dipped it in the
landing zone tartan which is the actual official tartan as mentioned in the authority of tartans
and the tartan, I don't know the tartan times or whatever it's called on that. So yes Nicholas do
you want to talk a little bit as our guest about how this came to be? So the basis by
Villefranke who designed the San Jose and it is exceptionally beautiful. It has three armadillos
on it and some books. Yes and we now need to let our guest Nicholas get a word in.
So you will have observed, you have observed that there are three lovely well read armadillos
here. Two of them in homage to the Duke of Wellington or rather to his statue in Glasgow
are wearing traffic cones and the third is simply piloting the starship as one does and on the sides
you will see two haguses. Yes. One in dormant state and one in full flying state with its
ceremonial toupee. Curled around the back are an acorn.
So what is the significance of the acorn? The acorn and the two cats are personal to the designers.
Oh so the acorn is a Villefranke thing. It's a Villefranke thing. And the cat is for
for Sarah. I believe that's a sign. Sarah could have been here but couldn't quite make it so
it's a shame. Texas is quite far but yeah. On the the plaque on the front says very clearly
Glasgow 2024 happy April Fool's Day, first of April 2024 because this is not a Hugo and we're
not presenting it to anybody and underneath inscribed oof in the base is the ceremonial inscription
there can be only one. And this is the only one that there will ever be and this is as you said
quite correctly Alison, this is a thing of total beauty. It is absolutely magnificent.
I would say that I've seen a lot of real Hugo designs and this is actually better than several
of them. I would agree with that. More stylish, more in keeping with the sanctity of the Hugo brand.
So the actual Hugo base for Glasgow will be quite different but will be also very very good.
The listeners can't see the immense look of pleasure on Nicholas's face when he says that but
this is a happy happy man. So yes Liz Liz Batty who I think has written to us a couple of times in the
past points out the Vincent Villefranke also designed the 2013 Hugo base as well as collaborating
with Sarah on the 2018 base. There will be pictures as I say in the show notes but it is extremely
beautiful and I assume it will be on display in Glasgow. I believe that's the guess because it
would be a great shame if people didn't get to see it. But yes, but yes Nicholas hello welcome.
Hey John, hey Alison, thank you for having me. Thank you for coming on the podcast. We are
absolutely delighted. You have been on our list of possible stunt visits for some time. Yes,
for once I'm in the right place at the right time or am I. So what do you want me to say?
Just tell us how marvellous our podcast is for a bit.
Well as you know I'm kind of constrained on that one. Yes yes.
So the... That's right. Yes obviously. He cannot comment. I just wonder if you've got any news about
the podcast that you'd like to share with listeners before I say something about their stuff.
We are coming to you from Eastacon, Levitation and the Hugo finalists were announced immediately
after the opening ceremony and amongst very worthy finalists we are one of them and this is very
exciting. We would like to thank everyone who nominated us. It is a thrill to be sure.
Oh JT for people who are listening on the podcast later. JT has worked out he could
live stream the discord chat to the big screen in the room. What could possibly go wrong?
I think we probably should say a little bit about our stunt list. So we're absolutely delighted
that our stunt list this week because Liz is in Thailand is Nicholas White but he is also the
division head for Wussfuss for the 2024 Wollcon and I think probably we have to say the disclaimer
now that actually other podcasts are available. Yes absolutely. And then we'll also the administrator
the Hugo Awards. And it's also the administrator of the Hugo Awards. It's coming together in perfect
harmony. So yes and the Hugo finalist announcement went without a hitch. It was all very smooth
and unstressful. It seemed very good. There is a...
The glass go wollcon is now making a health chair fort. Yes. So Nicholas how has...
So this is a swam thing though. I'm going to say from my vantage point in the audience
it looked to me like the Hugo announcement went off incredibly well. Yes. I had in fact was what I
was showing up. I had in fact been told by a number of people in the bar the previous night
that things might not be quite as perfectly, perfectly smooth as they appeared. I'm not
I appreciate that. Of course what you see is the swans are readingly gliding along the surface of
the water and you do not see the little feet paddling subsurface and because it's the Hugo's it's a
swan with three legs not with two. And also also all of the swans in Glasgow for Glasgow 2024 will
have been dipped in the tartan. Yes it's not a white swan but a tartan swan.
Are glass weagen swans owned by the king? I'm a Belgian so I cannot answer that question.
Oh I will say this is off topic but fortunately we've been very on topic.
But I knew Nicholas has... Nicholas has excellent ribbons which have a joke about Belgium on them
and I could tell people who had bumped into Nicholas by observing the ribbons. It was like
all you've seen Nicholas because he knew he had a ribbon. It says on it that's a bit
undramatic isn't it? So the reason that the ribbon says that's a bit undramatic isn't it?
This is a doctor who quote those of you who know me may know that I have watched one or two
Doctor Who episodes in my life and in the episode Time Crash in which Peter Davison encounters David
Tennant the fifth and tenth doctors meet each other. Peter Davison complains that the collision of the
two tortoises could blow a hole in the space time continuum the exact size of Belgium and then he
goes on to say that's a bit undramatic isn't it? So I printed these up for Gallifrey one where
indeed you and I met each other most recently John and it's a little silhouette of the map of
Belgium with the slogan that's a bit undramatic isn't it? So I have many more back in my room I've
only got one left in my hand but you can come and talk to me afterwards. We had dinner and Nicholas
knew that well Nicholas was aware of the nominations and kept a straight face and it was very frustrating
because we were watching him like a hawk fence and there were none. At that point that was mid-February
so we still had some way to go in voting but I could see the way things were going but it was good.
But yeah I'll have more to say about the dinner when we get to picks actually.
Okay very enough. But to say a bit more about the Hugo process the video was just beautifully done
so absolutely props to JT for his and Meg who Meg McDonald who were really at the coalface of
putting it together. We had frustrations we had one very late withdrawal which meant that those
slides had to be rewritten and re-recorded. I was told he pulled out just in time.
You're referring...
I was told the Bigelest Nicholas pulled out just in time.
I have been told that by multiple people who've been opting.
It is true that Bigelest Nicholas pulled out but was not perhaps the last to do so but...
I had not actually had heard that. I'm pretending that I had not heard that because it is better or
it was good that way. But we had the the the great assistance of Sophia Shui in Shanghai who recorded
half of the categories and the withdrawals category. She is of course a native Mandarin speaker but is
as you will have heard from the video fluent in English and because we had so many Chinese names
in the categories I felt it was possibly better to get a native Mandarin speaker to do it rather
than have to be mangling their names in probably saying something quite offensive without necessarily
intending to which is rather easy to do in some languages. So that that's went very well. We had
great participation from Glasgow's team and from the special guests. I hope you all particularly
enjoyed the three black halflings. That was a very good... Yes indeed that was great.
And the presenter who I think probably very few people were expecting to see was Jeffrey Gernsback,
the great handsome... Yes that was a delight. Tell me who Jeffrey Gernsback is. So Jeffrey Gernsback
lives quite close to Chicago and he contacted me in advance of the Chicon Worldcon to say that
he'd hoped he could make it but unfortunate it wasn't going to be possible. So when I heard this I
said you know how much money would that take? What can we do? How can we get you there?
It wasn't possible logistically in the end but we stayed in touch. He sent me that lovely photograph.
He was born about eight months before his great grandfather died. So there's a lovely family
photograph which you'll see in the video of a very aged Hugo Gernsback, his son Jeff's grandfather,
his grandson Jeff's father and Jeff's aunt is in the picture as well. So that was just very very
nice. He was absolutely keen to do it and so we're staying in touch as to how we can get the Gernsback
family perhaps a bit more recognised in the Hugo process than has been the case. I don't think
there'd really been much connection in the years since Hugo Gernsback died which I think was 1967.
Oh it was very cool. And yeah it's like seven seconds of participation but it's seven seconds
more than we've had in 50 something years. We have it. So one of the
the Fancast category was introduced by Tami Coxen and she posted to say that she had chosen
Fancast because she was hoping that she would get to read our nomination out. So hello Tari,
that was very sweet. Thank you very much indeed. And she did it behind her cocktail bar and presented
the Glasgow Gimlet as part of the introduction which was great. But there are a lot of lovely
little flourishes and I thought like I'm not trying to be facetious like from the outside it seemed
like everything went off without a hitch. And obviously like you say the three legs of the
mutant swan frantically paddling. We mentioned Bigelas Dicklas for listeners who don't know
and we'll get on to the people who accepted their finalist slots later but there were five
people who declined. Martha Wells for System Collapse which is I believe the latest murder bot novel
Haya for the far north. Bigelas Dicklas, Natasha Bardon invested in long form and
Camestros flapped on in Best Fan Writer and I just want to say Bigelas Dicklas is a good egg
because I think that was the right call. There have been people who accepted for things that I
would rather have not been on the finalist slate and I'm thinking of you Chris. You know who you are
but I think it's very classy to decline because it's a funny joke but yeah it was quite difficult
to track Bigelas Dicklas down. Tell us about how you looked for Bigelas Dicklas.
It was actually I mean I don't think this needed to be a secret it was it was Amal El-Mortar
one of the authors of this. Oh okay that's. Who made the connection but I think I think
Bigelas Dicklas being a bit outside the community sent me a rather curious message saying
are you the Nicholas White who Amal El-Mortar tells me I need to contact and is this about the Hugo
Awards because if so I don't want to be in it. If however you're contacting me for some other
reason please accept my apologies for the tone of that first paragraph. So I mean that is classy
I agree. I think that is classy. And it's important to communicate during. I mean I think so we you had
five five withdrawals at the end and I think three people that decline three people that um
three three that we had to disqualify although one of those had had been nominated separately in
a different category for which they were eligible. So to to talk about those quickly the three that
were disqualified were all Chinese. One of them was a novel where the copyright date was December
2023 but my intense research in the Chinese science fiction community made it pretty clear that it
wasn't in the shops or available and that even the author had not had a copy until 2024 which means
that under the Hugo Rules it is not eligible and then we had two successful nominees in the
fan cast category but and it made me research the professional criteria because a fan cast
must be a fan cast and not professional and these were both in fact professional productions and
they they accepted that when I explained the rules to them. I will um I will look forward to getting
the Hugo Longlist which I think I'm getting I'm getting at the party this year right which has
last got intended um I'll look forward to seeing which of those ones would have knocked us off the
ballot. No comment. Yes that is entirely fair and I think there was worry there was there was
there was commentary when when Glasgow announced the tack they were going to take with um declaring
who had declined and who was ineligible. I think they was worried it would over shit um over shit.
That will probably be lovely. It would shit all over the other finalists but I don't think they
felt shut on at all. What's your opinion Nicholas? The feedback has been positive as all I would say
but I mean it's it's a fair point a couple of those who declined kind of said why do you need to even
make it public that we were involved with the ballot in in any way um to which the answer is that
people people voted for you and they need to know what happened to those votes and unfortunately
from that perspective the Hugo's belonged to the voters they don't actually belong to the finalists
and I think that's a really important principle that um you know there's a limit to how far voters
wishes should be ignored or not reported and I'm very committed to making sure that voters know
what has happened and can see what's been done with their votes. That's fantastic actually thank you
and I think so we always used we've done this we've had this transparency for a very long time we
we we're just going to draw a a gentle veil over the 2023 Hugo's for the purpose of this book
but we've had this very long standing tradition of releasing this data after the after the ceremony
but I think bringing it forward is quite a bold move from Glasgow and I think you probably did
have to do that as a result of what happened last year. The the secret that not many people have
noticed is we actually did this my first year administering the Hugo's in 2017 in Finland and we
actually published that year we published withdrawals and disqualifications. Yeah but you did it in
Finnish so nobody noticed it. That's fair that's fair and I remember I remember recording the thing
Helsinki airportions yeah I think no one's going to remember this and indeed you didn't so
Hey guys man we have a we do have a terrible memory I mean I speak myself. We weren't doing the
podcast I will say since we started the podcast our memories have been absolutely
invaluable yes no I mean if you say oh you mentioned this on episode 23 we will definitely
remember that isn't that right John. There is there was a there was hilarious statement made there is a
there is a discord for fans of the Wussfuss business meeting and I am in it as a sort of
person who would like the business meeting to go away so what was that a bad actor in that discord
but um but there was someone who said Alison said this on this episode and I said no I have
never said that in my life it was definitely Liz and then I checked the transcripts and it was
Alison and she said it verbatim how they transcribed it and I was like no Alison you did say that
it was only two episodes ago as well it wasn't like ever so you know um so yes so Nicholas you
you are someone has posted in the chat saying you know almost as much about the Hugo's as Liz
so that is high praise it is high praise she's probably more upstate with her recent research than
I am I actually want before we move off the topic of the Hugo nominations I wanted to say something
more about them which is that there are quite a lot of to my mind good ones I know that Nicholas
can't comment apart from say all Hugo he loves all his finalists equally deeply and does not pick
favorites but I was delighted to see some of the people on the um list do and were you yeah most
people were delighted to see there was one person in fan art is 12 I was like I don't know
really sorry a spanya it's okay it's okay she was not hilarious is a spaniel was distracted at
that boat so she's gonna have to listen to the episode to find out the burn um but no so so for
those who don't know Alison uh Alison my learned co-host and ispania my lovely wife were both
nominated in fan artist and obviously a big big booster of that and and ispania and Anna in the
chat have both said they're all good finalists Brent and that is the official key there's that's
the official Glasgow line I think and you might also be the official octal line we'll probably have a
we'll have to think about it over the next two weeks and think about the things that we are
tragically sad we're not nominated and talk about sorry we the things that we are tragically
sad were not finalists um I will say that there were three categories where there was like one
vote in it at the end yeah whether the the next but one candidate would have been on with one
three two years ago two years ago three years ago three years ago twenty four years ago do I hear
five years twenty twenty one I was I was asked to do some work for disco three by dickolas
and um and I said you know this might be really difficult if if octal thought was nominated we
were very new podcast at the time and he said well you haven't been but you know you should make sure
that you all three of you and all three of you partners nominated because yeah you wrote me a
week by one we had a we had a frank discussion because obviously self-promotion is gosh
but um there was a conversation where we're like Alison was like well obviously I didn't
nominate us and I was like if we don't nominate us with how can we expect anyone else to nominate
us and I'm like I'm British and you don't vote for yourself and I have been persuaded actually by um
by John who said if you don't buy two things really one is John who said if if you don't self-promote
then then people from other countries who shall be nameless who were brought up to self-promote
from an early age will get all the war awards and British people who would rather die in a
ditch than say that their own stuff is good will never get any of the awards and then two more things
three things sorry the second thing was the secret zoom am I allowed to talk about the secret zoom
well we yes no but we should introduce it we should do that as the last thing and we should
segue oh the second thing or the third thing because the second thing
Emily ink pen um I'm going to credit for the person who alerted me to this idea suggested in
the bsfa discord you if you're a member of the bsfa should be in that discord it's now quite good
um but she suggested that British people should find a buddy who really really like you like their
stuff and they really really like your stuff um hello ispania and and you should and you should
go and big up their stuff and they should big up your stuff and then it won't feel so bad and on
that topic everyone should rank first in best related work uh all these worlds reviews and essays
by Neil Harrison Neil has joined Esther Neil is under the table Esther is in front of him they are
both um so what we're saying here is Esther and Neil are under the table together
Neil's quite tall so whereas it was quite easy for Esther to hide under the table
Neil's quite tall but Esther isn't i'm not like yet but so easy for Esther to hide under
that now there's so much chapter off this episode now i think i think i think i think
Emily's idea in the bsfaity squad is very good and i think the thing i will say is you don't
necessarily have self-promote but i have started trying to boost other British people who don't
self-promote because i do think if if no one promotes anyone in Britain that is a shame because
there are some good things here can you give me an example of something you've been promoting
Alison Scott for fan artists you should also rank her high at the top of your wallet
Alison is now under the table
well you are that's not that uncomfortable he's to call actually um but the other thing that
happened Nicholas Nicholas is someone who cares i think quite a lot about the Hugo Awards
i think it's uncontroversial to say and one of the things that Glasgow has done is they actually
had a zoom call that all the finalists were invited to that had sort of people talking about
basically what it's like to be nominated how you might want self-promote there were talks
for various people mary robinette kowel came to talk to everyone and it was really nice
um so yeah Nicholas what brought that about like i think it's a great idea but it was an evolution
i i had hoped that we would have a public town hall about the whole Hugo process
and then there were certain personnel changes in our team which meant that the work was
the work was shared a bit more intensely between those of us who who were who remained on it
and we just into the bandwidth to do an open public town hall before the
nomination before voting closed um that still meant that when we brought on um our ace crack
Hugo fineless liaison head roundy shepherd passed this idea onto him former will conchair roundy
shepherd yeah a former world conchair roundy shepherd and the first thing he said was well
let's let's just do this for the Hugo fineless at this point time was rather
was getting very very tight and the invitations went out went out with less than 48 hours notice
which is tighter than i would have liked it to be but you deal with the circumstance you have
and in the event i thought i'm glad you thought it went well i have the sense it was going well as
well we thought it was delicious we we spent an entire hour in discord with a list of the
participants in that zoom chat working out who must have been nominated for what you go
yes we we we started with there was one participant on the zoom whose name on zoom was gong
wandering earth producer and we thought maybe that meant wandering earth two might have been
nominated so we started with that and then i got a DM on the zoom from jerry salivar at which
point i completely lost it because i am unlike unlike lichlus i do not have to be partisan
i am absolutely thrilled that jerry has been nom uh is a finalist for idea which is
not only is it a proper real fancy that is like you can actually get a print copy of
but also i'm in it i want to ask i want to ask nicholas question from the audience
is it a greater honor in your opinion to be the hugo administrator or the stunt liz
feel free not to answer if it will cause an international incident i mean i i think this the
sixth time i've been involved with the hugos but it's probably the one and only time in my life
that i will be a stunt liz so it's just impossible to compare the two experiences
excellent and it was it was steward steward thank you steward for that thank you steward for that
not all the questions somebody in the chat was taking was laying bets on who the stunt liz would
be and i'm just going to say one of the people he suggested was somebody was being stunt liz before
and that's not going to happen and the other person he suggested was the number one
person who will never ever be stunt liz because he keeps turning us down so you know just just
to finish on the the finalists zoom we will also do the public town hall model has not gone away
and we hope that we will do public town halls on all three of the areas of the westfors division
for glasco which is to say the not just the hugos but also site selection and the business meeting
so that's really and that that public i'm really looking forward to public town halls on the
business meeting that that's me because that that will go really that will go really smoothly and
there won't be any controversy versus all sounds will it be okay for me to turn up to the town halls
on the business meeting wearing a robe and having a bell and just shouting "shame"
i mean i'm not in charge of code of conduct questions but
we're has been pointed out in the chat that we said all bsfa members should join the bsfa discord
but in fact it is open to all so everyone should join the bsfa discord and it's good yeah i'd
also everyone should join the bsfa because you know it's the bsfa because it's good too yes it's
also good but the bsfa awards have this charming thing going back to something you mentioned earlier
where you're not actually allowed to vote for yourself and i think that's really cute i think
it's i think it's a bit silly as well but it's very cute the other thing i was going to say about
the um yes but we're british so obviously one of the things about brit let's see you don't vote
for yourself proud belgian here traditionally so one of the things about the zoom was it in that
zoom i think this is a lot of things i'm allowed to talk about that they had kevin lampi talking
to us who is a very high powered PR and he talked to us about how the we should say
in every sentence did i mention that i was a hugo finalist i mean i am not in any way exaggerating
he was on a zoom for hugo finalist and i should say at this point that i am a hugo finalist and
he said in every sentence you say to anybody you should say that you are a hugo finalist and i've
been trying to do though i couldn't do that but i can't i mean it was quite hard just doing it
for the length of that comment my students are going to get really fed up in my lectures
so it was by british standards i think i found that presentation a bit much i think people who have
been outside the system and are for whom it's genuinely a new experience just like a bit of guidance
that they're not jumping and it's something i have heard from first-time finalists previously
that they would have liked a bit more advice as to how to handle it and to tell people well
there's two there's two things here which is firstly we're old hands now but secondly none of us have
any real skin in the game it's purely ego boo for us whereas like if you are an author there's like
actual career considerations involved and so yeah i think having that kind of guidance i mean for
us we were like well you know we might tell people we're a hugo finalist and then we might never
mention it again and it's fine but i can see it for nominated for professional things yes for
someone who's at the very very start of their career and i was about to say who are professionally
nominated but i don't think that's a career i don't i hope that nobody was yes exactly so so
bob shaw um who i really quite adored um had to kind of wrestle his publishers to the ground to
stop them putting hugo winner on his books when he had won the hugo for best fanzine and best
fan writer and and i'm like oh oh and but he but i think times have changed and i actually know at
least one author who has who has won in a fan category and then pushed on their books now and i think
probably that's something that people do more now yeah that's where we admire the modesty of
peter capaldi who is in fact a winner of an Oscar but not as an actor is he what was he what did he
win for he won best animated film quite already in his career he did an animation film about
france kafka oh i i wrote this is slightly off topic but the it's called google it for her job
google it for me it's funny but i went to the the name of the film soaf says in discord if you or
anyone you know has been affected by a hugo award nomination there is support available
and i thought that was very good fair hello so dc says it's france kafka's it's a wonderful
life that's thron yep thank you dc they there was a um the guardian had a profile of peter
capaldi you can take all that other stuff out jolly the lightly edit um the guardian had a
profile of france kafka where of god the guardian had a profile of peter capaldi in which this is
going to tell us what was in it or indeed alice so i would have been alice in this
show which is not this the guardian had a profile of peter capaldi when it mentioned his short film
france kafka's it's a wonderful life but it put the link and the quotes around it's a wonderful life
and not around france kafka's it's a wonderful life so so i wrote to the guardian's corrections
editor as i do every about twice a week and said you have made this trivial error but it made me
laugh which once like that do because they they apparently doesn't make you laugh those things
so there are occasional times when alice says things on the podcast and there is
silence and this is but you're not laughing i mean it's like what so i'm not i'm not saying
i self-promote but i think i may be funnier in my head than i actually
yeah um that was better inside my head before it came out yeah so what we thought of the easter
con what did we think about the easter con yay i thought it was good yep and that was the easter
con time for pics no come on so so i this was my easter con where i wasn't going to do anything
i was just going to have a really relaxing weekend i said i'd do a newsletter shift and i'd do a bit
of work on the fanfums and at four fifteen yesterday afternoon i sat down with karry and
karry sparing and alia de verdard and had a and realized that for the next 38 minutes i had nowhere
to go nothing to do nothing i felt i should have done but happened and then and then normal
reality kicked in since i've been back to the too many things through a lot of life i
have you been busy i i had a lot of fun um as has been mentioned we did the
Hugo announcement on friday immediately after the opening ceremony and i'd been we had decided we
were going to do it on that day three years ago so it was the culmination of a three-year plan
to which many many people contributed um so that was big um and i'm afraid i spent
saturday kind of decompressing um but uh i've been to i've been on a couple of panels i've been to a
bunch more i've had huge fun in the jitters room expensively but there we are um also one thing i
think i've spoken to more new people who have not been to an easter con before here than has been the
case previously and i don't know whether it's because there genuinely are more new people or maybe
it's such i just look more friendly since i grew a beard i wonder because for those those who don't
know this is a smaller easter con than usual which is which is often the case in a year with the
uk world con because world cons are expensive easter cons are expensive a lot of people will choose
the world con over the easter con but i wonder at conventions where there are fewer fans it's easier
to meet the new fans because you can just see more people as a percentage of the convention because
i have met more people this year than i have since the pandemic i think and it's been really fun i had
lots of lovely conversations with people i've not really talked to before and they were all great
and i did not mention to any of them that i had a podcast or that it was on the Hugo Ballot
because that is how i roll sorry you're supposed i understand from kevin lampy is that i'm supposed
to put it in every sentence did you not do that um no i did not what do we think of the venue i now
i'm quite shocked about this because um i was very skeptical i quite like it okay so actually i'm
going to classify this i quite i think the Telford International Center is lovely it's a very good
sized for an easter con we could grow quite a bit and still use it because there's another program
space exactly the same size as this one so you although you'd have a little bit of walking between
the two you could definitely you could put a huge easter con into the space and this is lovely and
if it were anywhere other than Telford i do love nandos so i quite like Telford because there is a
nandos there are yeah i was going to say as long as as long as your idea of a nice place to eat
at an easter con is a low to mid-range chain restaurant that will serve you quickly like say
nandos i feel like Telford is actually pretty good for that there's basically a dozen of them
within about two minutes walk of the convention center and that's been quite nice
if you actually want a proper meal i understand that taxi cabs are available
and there's some very good places to go to in them i've been i've been to two of them i'll
recommend to them the ugly duckling which is a pub on the far side of Telford and the 1840 restaurant
which is a converted Methodist church about halfway to the ugly duckling fair enough so i would have
thought if i were so if i had a if if everyone who has said to me this weekend that they're thinking
about voting bidding for an easter con and they've got some really good ideas and if they did the
easter con they would do it in a particular way that is is not the way that i have done it or that
this year's done it or anything but they've got they've got strong ideas and they want to be an
easter con chair if every single one of those people bids an easter con we will never be short
of bids ever again we do have a question you mentioned that there are taxi cabs available
and david bamford in the discord has asked can you eat taxi cabs though emily emily january says
if you're not a coward and meggwitt doddle says are they deep fried so there are these are the
questions we need answering so this is a Glasgow thing so is there deep fried food available in
Glasgow no there's none fish and chips never made it to Scotland no no meggas promised to take me
for deep fried pizza when i'm in Glasgow meggas never had it you did you promised steward says pizza
crunch and i say pizza crunch we all say pizza crunch so um but no i'm very looking forward to
Glasgow there's lots of great food in Glasgow i'm going to buy a food culture
a few so so obviously we don't have the audience mic so i mean we do have the audience mic but i
am just going to repeat for the benefit of the audience what ester just said which is that Glasgow
has a vibrant food culture and i can confirm that because i i have now eaten a deep fried
bar that's fair so i haven't actually i we split it between four of us which was plenty
and there's still still too much ester came came to shout at us and ispania said she can be
lured out so these are strategies and british it notes that mukvitties do do a chocolate bar called
taxi so hurrah i just provided a photo that's a fair point i want to i want to quickly give my
thoughts on the venue which is i like it um we're going to talk more about this in the next episode
uh because we always do a deeper dive into the easter come when we're not being um drunk drunk
tired and excitable um but what i would say and i've said this to a couple of people i've seen in
the convention up to now is if you are someone who has mobility issues i would love you to write
as a letter of comment before we discuss this easter con sort of very much to like to hear
your thoughts on the access because there was a big conversation about that beforehand and i would
like to know how people found it who attended the con so far i've heard nothing but good things
but i would be interested to know whether that is accurate or representative before i shoot my
mouth out on the radio i just want to say in the discord brityard branch or suggested that people
are coming to talk to me because they think there may be crumbs and snacks hidden in my beard and
i mean you're welcome to all come and have a good look afterwards
well some of you are i i have been told by a secret informant who is my ex-husband
that the venue has planning permission for a second lift and it just needs to find
the penny stored down it's it's um you know the back of it's so far so if we bring the easter con
here they might again they might find it again i'd be happy to come i think this this venue has
been great really and i don't think telford's telford wasn't you know they say they're in within
three hours travel of 90 percent of the uk population um and that's basically true as long as you're
not trying to travel on monday thursday or by train
picks so nicholas as our guest would you like to have a pick yeah my picks are both dr who relations
excellent inevitably it does sound like you're on brand um it's i know it's utterly uncharacteristic
one of them is just a general sequence of books about dr who stories called the black archive and
what they do is every month they take a different story either from old who or from you who and
they've also done screen of the chalca and the tv movie with them with with paul mcgane which
can fall between them and they have somebody just doing an in-depth dive in a scholarly way usually
in the space of 80 to 120 pages just looking at how the story came to be what it really means
what what how it ties into wider cultural issues wider historical issues um i've i've read the first
60 of the 80 or so that have been published so far and of those 16 maybe three or four have been
done and that's quite a good strike rate for any series of any series of books the other one also
dr who related um john you'll recall we had dinner in los angines um a month or so ago with yourself
and espania and with simon garyer um a doctor who fiction writer and writer of many other things as
well he's just published a biography of david twitter who was the first script editor of doctor
who back in the early 1960s and wrote several of the classic stories of the heart and the
and trot and eras including the two trot and dalek stories um very interesting character
who managed to um pass through his career without leaving much of an imprint in people who knew him
they're they're kind of uh people are asked about meetings that he was clearly asked because he's in
the he's in the minutes and they can't remember that he was there a bit like the bob shaw character
who's a human neutrino and uh nobody remembers who he was and you know poor david wittaker died in
1980 at the age of 51 if he'd lived another five years he would have become one the celebrities of
the burgeoning doctor who fan culture that appeared around about that time but he didn't
poor guy and i got the sense that um he'd had an internal career at the bbc decided to go freelance
and discovered that nobody knew who he was which is an awful shame so it's uh it's it's quite a
thick book but i found it very interesting because he goes um simon goes into the um wider tv culture
and theatrical culture and general um issues with how british society functions at the time
so i strongly recommend that i have discovered recently that i bloody love history books
especially very specific nerdy history books so that sounds very good this is this is pretty
specific and pretty nerdy yeah yeah it sounds very very good i might have to look that up like that
one on the space program yeah that was great and it was very helpful in my uh panel on saturday
which feared much more into the geopolitics of space than i think i was expecting it to so i was
very glad i had interesting things to say about that so dc makes the abstit of the accurate point that
david which was omitted from the drama documentary and adventure in space and time his role was actually
merged with several other characters so yeah abstit absolutely fair point allison do you have a pick
um i was wondering if you wanted to go first actually i do have a pick i'm going to pick something
on the bleeding edge of culture which is a six episode television series from 2004 and it is
garth meringue's dark place oh tell us about your cosplay john so yes um on on saturday uh
ispania and i cosplayed characters from garth meringue's dark place i was uh dr rick daggles md
um ispania was maddling wool uh who plays liz asher in the show so this is a um tv show where the
conceit is quite dr who e in the the conceit is it was so horrific at the time it was made that it was
banned on british television and it wasn't shown anywhere in the world except for prue
and um they found it in a cupboard and decided to rebroadcast it on channel four with talking heads
and like historical commentary from the cast but it's actually a pistiche and it's um it's
matt wholeness it's rich die oardie it's matt berry and allislow and it also has like other luminaries of
the british comedy scene from the time so it's got like the mighty bush in it it's got several people
who who went on to do much bigger things later and yeah it's just great so it's on i believe it's
on catch up on the channel for website it will take you maybe three hours to watch the whole thing
it is absolutely hilarious and i would highly commend it to anyone uh who likes comedy horror
or slow motion i'm very much hoping that someone who took a picture of jon and ispania on saturday
can drop it into the discord chat now so that so that jt can stick it up on the big screen so
you can see how lovely their costumes were my pick so very unusually for me i'm going to pick
something i haven't actually watched yet which is the easter con 2024 catch up program
yeah so so i am planning to spend the next week or so um attending the convention virtually in a
way that i couldn't this week on account of how i was in the newsletter room and all the fanfans
table and and working and also in the bar frankly there's a certain amount of drinking went on
it's hard to mention i know um but i believe that there are many many many good things and what
you need you to all to do is is message me or in fact put in the discord your picks for what
things i should prioritize whilst whilst picking up catch up over the next week i thought i might
spend the whole of next weekend just attending the easter con because i never actually have time to
go to it i mean i did go to some program items this weekend but i was on them i attended a very
good program item i would recommend for catch up which was uh stew hotson gave a talk on Saturday
night about um whiteness in gaming and about how we can try and make gaming uh more accessible and
less repellent is a really strong word but less off-putting for people who are not white and i found
it absolutely fascinating and i would i would extremely highly commend it to anyone who is looking
for an interesting talk and the other one i recommend is esta mccollum stewart who gave a great
talk on the history of games and its intersection with dr hoo and it had lots of pictures of chutie
gatwa in it and he's very pretty yes esta is waving from behind her for chair fort are we going to take
any questions from the audience do we have time jt you've got 30 so all right first person to have
a hand up gets to ask a question there kev don't kill yourself jt we need you just following on the
discussion i wonder if we should rename glasco 2020 for a deep fried world con oh esta will
esta will stab you and now we're running away but i think i think that was a comment not a question
kev quite funny though esta says that there is a vibrant food culture i mean i think i'm prepared
to say without shadow of a doubt that glasco will have better food best to tell but no glasco when i
went to we went to um satellite the last satellite convention and uh the food was the highlight of
the convention for me so i'm very much looking forward to going to Glasgow and having lots of
extremely good food i mean glasco is actually a world quality city in many respects i mean
can i just can i have a show of hands how many people i i did this exact same joke last night
in the fanfans auction so i'm sorry guys how many people are intending to attend glasco 2024
weeee
it is noted from the audience that esta did not put her hand up how many people in the audience are
not intending to attend glasco 2024 okay right esta nail hunt them down
she emerges have you got your membership documentation ready this is very good but seriously guys i mean
not not so much now but you're probably for the people who are listening to this on the pod i
mean i think it's going to be a brilliant worldcon i think if you like eastercons and you like
wilcons when they're kind of doing it right and you like glasco which has a vibrant food culture i
understand but glasco is a brilliant world city and and eastercons in glasco are great and
wilcon in glasco is going to be great it will be amazing we will be having an octave meetup of some
description i think i think it's fair to say we have asked glasco if we could have an octave
thought live session at one o'clock on the monday i mean we will have we will definitely i think
unless glasco secretly hate us which we can't rule out i think i think there will be a live
episode of octave octave act glasco but um but yes it will hopefully be good would be good if it was
one o'clock on monday so that we can so that we can talk about the con sorry if we didn't as far
a gun away because we didn't talk about the con very much i mean i and i really had a good time i've
had a lovely time i had a fantastic time yes it was great fun and we need to say what we always say
which is that jt is a wonder and a marvel and
and thank you very much to and john will remember to edit this back in thank you so much to nicholas
for being asked on this thank you it's been a pleasure and that was the octave thought podcast
and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
[Music]
oh yes dramatic readings um poetry corner retracing prince pools axiomatical friends yet unmet
follow live its decrees measuring distance intergalactical by observation from planets like these
by duck bunny that's very good thank you duck bunny the theme music for this episode was
fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in com protect dot com used under a creative commons
attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]