Oh, Alison's gone.
I'll carry her going and assume she'll come back.
- Yeah, why not?
(upbeat music)
- Hello, everyone, and welcome to Octa Thorpe,
a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom.
This episode is a special episode,
and we don't know when it's coming to you.
- Oh, I'm John Coxon.
- I'm Alison Scott.
- And I'm Liz Batty.
- And today, Liz has made us read a book.
- Yes, I mean, this is the first of probably three episodes
in which we all read a book.
One of us chooses a book and we make the other two read it,
and then we're going to discuss it for you.
And the book, which is at first, happens to be my choice.
So I should start with why I like it
and why I made these two read it.
So my book choice is a face-like glass by Francis Harding,
which is a 2012 book.
It's about an underground city called Kverna,
which is full of skilled craftsmen who toyle away
to make kind of magical delicacies.
And we start in the cheese mongas.
So there is a cheese monger who makes kind of magical cheeses.
And one day he finds a child in his cheese store,
whose name is Neverfell, and he adopts Neverfell
as his own apprentice, but Neverfell never leaves
the cheese factory, and she comes to believe
there is something hideously wrong with it
because she always is forced to wear a velvet mask.
But there is naturally, it's not anything wrong
with Neverfell, it's the fact is that Neverfell
is the only person in a world where people do not wear
their emotions on their face who will naturally
kind of have a face that changes with her emotions.
So that is the face-like glass.
You can see everything going on in Neverfell's face.
And she goes into this very strange city
where there are delicacies that can change your memories,
give you premonitions, bring back hidden past memories,
but where no one can ever show emotions on their face
unless they have a face that they were
trained by a face myth to show that particular emotion.
And so Neverfell kind of cannonballs into this world
as a kind of agent of chaos.
She eventually leaves the cheese shop,
falls in with some of the other artisans of Coverna,
ends up meeting the leader of Coverna,
and generally discovering kind of the rot which sits
at the heart of this underground world
where the rich feast on precious delicacies
and it's the underclass who keeps everything running.
And everything is very kind of rigid and constrained,
as you might imagine from a world where you can show
only the set of emotions that you have been taught to display.
And Neverfell essentially upends the whole thing.
So why do I like it?
I think it's one of the first Francis Harding books I've read.
I've read nearly all of her books apart from the new one,
and I felt John Allison had not read enough of her books
to be made to read more.
I just find that I find it hugely, hugely imaginative.
There's a whole load of different things going on,
possibly almost too much stuffed into this book.
But you know, there's whole sections about the cheeses
and the names of the different cheeses
and the more of this cheese will, you know,
show you your greatest fear or greatest power.
You know, there are wines that can erase memories.
At one point, Neverfell meets a man named Maxim Childerson,
and you can just tell from his name
that he is not going to be a good guy.
Boilers, Liz.
Nomineeative determinism.
Boilers, if you don't pick that up
within the first few minutes, well,
I mean, maybe we'll get into that later,
whether it is a little bit too obvious.
But I just kind of find that it's very,
just kind of filled with delightful things at every turn.
I love reading kind of every page of it
and reading about the different things.
While it also has a, you know, a fairly,
some fairly serious messaging
and some fairly serious things going on in it.
I just love every page of it.
And I love Neverfell.
I like a lot of Francis Hardings, heroes and heroines
who are generally children or young adults.
And I just love the way she gets plunged into this.
And it essentially ends up winning out
by being completely unpredictable,
because no one really knows what she's going to do,
even though she wears all her emotions on her face.
So that's why I picked it.
- So, Alison, have you read the book?
- I have read the book.
I read the book when I was supposed to.
- Well, all right.
(laughs)
- I read it pretty quickly.
It's quite a long book.
This is a young adult book, which is pretty chewy.
It's about 500 pages, which feels like quite a big book.
I read it in two or three chunks.
I read quite a lot.
And then I got to a point where I went,
because as Liz says, a lot of different stuff's going on.
There's this and there's that.
It's got multiple great premises.
It's got these craft projects
that are imbued with magic.
And it's got the whole face thing
about which I'm going to talk a bit more about.
And it's got an extraordinarily interesting cat burglar.
And it's got this really strange society.
And it's got underground living.
And just huge amounts of stuff.
And so I got to about halfway through over and I was like,
okay, I do not myself like to be delighted on every page.
I like books that tell me a story
where all the words support the overall theme
and the underlying message.
And I like to, you know,
I like to be absorbed in a world.
But she kept bringing in a new thing
and I'd be going like,
one more thing, she's never going to pull this back together.
And there's far too many loose ends
and why am I bothering really?
And I guess I'll just have to go on.
And then I think literally in the next chapter,
she starts bringing it back together.
And in fact, everything turns out to be all one part of one.
Fairly well put together whole and it all fits in.
And it's fine.
It's better than fine.
It's a really good book.
I liked it a lot.
- I will say I find it like,
the episode title is going to be,
I don't like being delighted on every page
'cause I never heard such a nihilistic view of picture.
It makes me very happy.
- I mean, I do know what you mean.
I mean, sorry, don't you care.
I mean, it can get a little bit like it is,
I mean, for a book which is all about delicacies,
it's like it's too much rich food.
- So the other Francis Harding book I read,
I've slightly forgotten the name,
is the one about the coastal divers
and the old ones and piracy
and that had far too much stuff.
And I didn't feel it came back together in a satisfying whole.
I got to the end of the book, read it one going,
"Oh, I wish I'd read the book
that this is obviously a sequel to
that she didn't actually write.
She wrote this book."
That would have been my only previous experience.
But I think this one,
she does actually pull the whole story together.
It's got a very good ending, I think.
It's pretty great.
I wanted to say a little bit more about a couple of things.
So my subtitle for this book would be
"A Child's Guide to the Class War,"
because this is not actually a book about cheeses
and magic and caverns and wonders
and delights at every turn.
This is a book about how you systematically
oppress an underclass.
And that's good, that's the sort of nihilistic theme
I like to see in novels.
So I really like that.
And I wanted to pick up one thing about the faces,
which ties into that,
which is if you are a member of said underclass,
you are delivered five faces,
which include things like expectantly waiting for orders
and diligently carrying out your tasks.
And if you're kind of an artisan,
a middle-class sort of person,
you get a fairly good range of faces
that gives you a lot of emotions.
But only the super rich people in this world
actually get a really good range of faces
and can go and get custom faces
for particular emotions they want to exhibit
and things like that.
And I thought that was quite clever
and also ties into the whole
class war theme of this novel.
- I enjoyed it.
I read it quicker than I thought I would
'cause as Alison and Elizabeth said,
it's not a short book,
but it does read very quickly.
And I did find several of the concepts very delightful.
I found the ending a bit disappointing.
I wished it had ended 30 pages earlier.
I just, the bit where they all actually make it up
to the surface, I was like, I didn't need to see that
because it just felt,
I would much rather an end
where the judges had actually taken over caverna
rather than being refugees.
I don't know if I like the underlying message of
if you are the oppressed, you can leave
rather than if you are the oppressed, you can rise up.
I think that is a very British take on an underclass.
I imagine if Francis Harding was French,
this book would have gone a different way.
I think I would have rather the French ending.
But it's a very minor quibble.
It's the only thing I didn't like about the novel.
And I did very much enjoy,
especially how Harding brings together some of the characters
which don't seem obviously related at the start
and brings them together and also kind of make sense
of some of the things that have been happening
that as soon as she points them out,
you're like, oh, I should have realized that's what's happening,
but you're not necessarily thinking about it in a way
that would let you notice, which I thought was good.
I very much enjoyed that.
I did love the Claptomancer.
I did think the end of his story arc was like,
this is a really interesting character.
I don't really know what to do with him.
So it ends now.
And I'm like, no, I didn't like, yeah,
I didn't think it could hit as well as Alison did,
I don't think, but I did still very much enjoy it.
- Yes, so the Claptomancer is basically
a celebrity thief and we discover that the only way
he has managed to pull off his many heists
is that he's kind of come up with his entire plan,
then erased it all from his memory
and now just systematically remembers tiny bits of it
at a time so that he never ends up ruining his plan
by doing something which would let you predict
the rest of his plan, which is just kind of convoluted
and brilliant and in the end of it,
he basically gets a point where he gets a message.
He obviously, his past self wrote to him saying,
if you're reading this message,
well done, your grand plan has come to fruition,
enjoy essentially ruling the city.
And it's kind of about like,
clearly what the Claptomancer wanted originally
was power, but now he's ended up with power
that he doesn't really know why he ended up wanting the power.
So basically by raising his own memory,
he's almost become a different person.
And I don't know, I kind of like the symbolism
of the ruler of this kind of very empty,
hollow society being a man who's basically erased
all of his memories and now can't remember why
he spent years in the assessing up this elaborate plan
to be the ruler because he wasn't,
he's not the same person who set it up.
- That's a good read of it
and I hadn't thought about it like that, that's good.
- That delivered the ending that John wants as well
because I think it's made pretty explicit
that he is on the side of the drudges
and is now going to deliver a more egalitarian society
where they don't do all the nonsense
that you see at the beginning of the novel.
And in exchange in the outside world,
because we assume that we're gonna get some free trade
as a result of this, in the outside world,
they will now have the artisanal skills
that Coverna's been holding to itself and all the magic.
So it is extremely disruptive.
There's no suggestion that Coverna's going to go on
as before, I thought that was fine
and I liked the kleptomancer's ending
and I really liked the way that selectively
removing bits of memory was key to the plot of this novel
and I would have quite liked to have seen a bit more of that.
I'd also liked to have seen it brought into play earlier
in the novel, but this may be a thing
that would make it more like an adult novel.
So there is a how much can you do with this in young adults?
So they do a certain amount of it
and they explicitly say that's what they're doing.
You know, if this had been written for adults,
I think you'd probably have had lacuna in the plot earlier
on that you would realize made sense
because of the memory removals.
But that doesn't happen because it's not a very complicated,
it's complicated in kind of plot and structure,
but it doesn't have that second level of complication
that a more tricksy adult novel would probably have.
- Yeah, I think it's a fairly straightforward plot
and it is kind of a little bit episodic,
kind of have the first section where, you know,
she's with grande-ball, the cheese, the cheese manga,
I love the name grande-ball.
- And then she's coming out
and discovering this new society
and you get to do the very lovely thing
where the central character is discovering the society
at the same time as we are
and so you can introduce everything through her eyes.
And then there's kind of a segment with the leader
of Kavurna who never fell,
ends up working for as a poison tester
and who comes to a not particularly sad end
and then you kind of get into the end section
where, you know, never fell, is on the run,
discovers what's going on with the judges
and then, you know, leads them,
many of them to the surface of Kavurna.
So it's kind of like split into chunks,
but it kind of has a section with the leader of Kavurna
and kind of gets that done and out of the way.
So it's not trying to pull in every single thing together
at the end.
I don't know if that's a way of making sure
you don't necessarily have to remember
a crucial thing that happened on page 200
by the time you get to page 500.
- Yeah, I think that's fair.
Oh no, it does though because the poisoning
is all part of one of the many grand plans
that are playing out through this novel.
So many of the characters have a plan,
never fells really the only one who doesn't.
I did have, 'cause I think about the faces a lot.
I was like, this book has several great premises,
but the faces are, I think, the most great of them.
There are a couple of things that I felt unclear about.
I believe that the reason that the judges
have very few faces is because the children
are separated from their parents
and then put into a nursery where nurses
have only shown them the faces they want to learn.
But that doesn't really explain to me
why the rest of the people in the society
are going along with the whole separating children
so that they don't learn all of the possible emotions.
And I'm also quite skeptical about the idea
that you'd actually be able to interpret
facial recognitions if you'd never learnt
to be a baby.
So those two things I feel were kind of big holes
that, you know, Fadsley books
could have big holes in them, it's fine.
But I always go, well, this feels like a big hole to me.
- I don't think the first one is a hole
because it's kind of explicitly mentioned
that all the babies are strange and silent.
And I think the implication is
it's something about being in caverna.
Who is implied as a sort of maybe a living magical organism?
- They specifically say that babies born in caverna
don't have facial expressions
and it's not just the judges,
it's all babies born in caverna, they have to be taught them.
And it makes perfect sense to me that, you know,
in a world where I think in this world
we have a severe disparity between the quality of care
that newborns get depending on how much money
their parents have.
So I think criticizing hardening for reflecting that
in a fantasy novel is maybe,
is maybe looking at our own world
with too rosy in a complexion.
'Cause, you know, well, as I said,
it's a class one novel, right?
- So I think criticizing it for accurately reflecting
the class war is probably not a fair criticism.
But I also think that in terms of
not fully explaining caverna, it is fully explained,
it's magic.
Like, I do not mind a fantasy novel
being like, there's some magic.
That, that, like, I don't need, I don't need,
like, I love that the Expanse explains FTL
and like has like a coherent thing.
But I also don't mind that Star Wars is just like,
there are hyper drives and it's fine.
And Star Trek is like, we have warps and those are numbers
and they don't really make any sense.
But, we didn't, we,
- But if you go up 10, you turn into a lizard, John.
(laughing)
- Like, I think you're allowed one kind of,
this is just, this is just like a thing
you're gonna have to go along with,
especially in fantasy, but I think a large genre novels
do tend to, um.
- I think this novel might have more than one thing
like that.
- I don't, I didn't, the only thing I don't think
is fully explained is like, well, like the true delicacies.
Like, and the fact that it's magic, but it is magic.
And that is enough explanation for me.
I don't know.
I, I, and I think she uses it to do interesting enough stuff
that I'm not annoyed, I guess.
- When I said I didn't think caverna was properly explained,
it's just kind of, it's suggested that caverna is a kind of
magical living organism,
but I would have liked a bit more about why,
you know, motivations for my magical living city.
- So I, one of the things I kind of love is how
she sets up the faces being like, you know,
you can literally read someone's class from their face
because of how many emotions they have.
But she also doesn't neglect to say, you know,
the dredges are shorter, the dredges, you know,
do not have access to good food and water.
The dredges do not look to be in good health,
whereas the higher citizens of caverna are functionally immortal,
thanks to delicacies they can afford to take.
So I like that they're all ties together.
About caverna, the city, I mean, I don't know.
I like, I like a bit of, bit of uncertainty.
I mean, it was not really clear to me
whether caverna is a really a living organism
and the cartographers are learning to speak the language
of the place or whether the cartographers are just having
some kind of enormous shared mass delusion
and what's going on there.
So, you know, I'm gonna, I'm gonna,
I'm alright to go with that as just a thing.
- Your point about the dredges and not having access to faces
that let them kind of express themselves
is really interesting because I think it reflects
the state of media.
I'm wondering whether it's designed to reflect
how much more control the people in our culture
who have wealth and power have over what we see in here
versus like you and me, like the number of times
that you're like, oh, the reason everyone thinks X
is because someone with a lot of money
bought a lot of Twitter accounts and like fed that message
and like kind of affected the conversation
and before that people like Murdoch and stuff.
I'm wondering whether the dredges lack of ability to emote
is kind of getting at that a little bit, which is interesting.
I do think this book clearly has a lot to say about class
and is doing it very cleverly in general
and I liked that a lot.
- Yeah, and it feels like, I don't really know enough
about children's, as you just say this,
we need Ali Baker on this.
- Farah.
- But I'm sure there's like a long tradition
of kind of like little lost orphans who go
and find their magical city and see what's going on.
So it feels kind of very much in that sort of tradition
of children's books, but with it just loads going on.
- I have a question that might be unfair.
Do you think that never fell being the catalyst
for the dredges like at the end of the book
is a sort of saviour thing?
Is that problematic because she is not a drudge,
she is an outsider?
Or like, is it understandable that a children's book
that you have a heroine and they make the plot go?
And how do you square that circle, I guess?
- That's interesting 'cause she is kind of an outsider,
but you could argue what she brings them is,
she literally brings them the tools of rebellion on her face
and she does catalyzes, but you know,
it's not that she persuades them all to rebel.
They were kind of almost primed to do it,
but didn't have the tools to do it themselves.
And I think hiding does bring in erstwhile a lot
to his never-fell's dredge friend
and really kind of maybe only genuine friend in the book
who doesn't have his own sort of hidden agenda
for which he's using never-fell.
Yeah, you could argue you could maybe
have made a bit more of that because she is the outsider.
But that's also a classic plot, isn't it?
Kind of the outsider who brings something new in
or stories of something new and that leads to
a rebellion happening.
- Yes, and I think the society's been structured,
so the judges needed a catalyst here.
I'm not sure how you could have told this story
to have a dredge-led rebellion given the premise.
They never-fell does point out that the judges
have found other ways that are not their faces
to express emotion to each other and do that quite a lot.
And you don't hear that about the upper-class family
that we meet and spend time with.
- Yeah, who are, I think it's fair to say, arseholes.
Although no, the cheesemaker isn't,
but most of the other upper-class people
we meet are not nice people.
- Cheesemakers artisanal class.
Well, the cheesemaker has been at court
but has rejected it, which I think is the key thing, right?
Like he has the class and then reject it.
- So the courtiers are kind of soaked in it
and it's not that they're all being actively terrible.
It's that quite a few of them haven't really thought about it.
You know, they're very unquestioning about their privilege.
So that's one of the themes, isn't it?
You know, they don't wonder why it is
that they're growing stronger and fitter
than other people around them.
- Yeah, and we see that, you know, grandeble rejects that
in one way by essentially walling himself off
from the rest of the city.
And then we see Zuelle, the niece of our villain,
Maxim Tilderson, who she didn't really befriend
never fell at the start.
She's happily going along with her uncle's schemes
and using never fell where she fits in with it.
But she is the character who really does come
to have all that challenged and in the end,
reject it and decide actually, yeah, this is a corrupt city.
And I'm getting out.
- It's interesting because although at the beginning,
I completely believe like Zuelle
is a very manipulative person who is using never fell for
whatever she can use never fell for.
By the end, I also completely believe
that never fell has won her over.
And I like the book's kind of testament to sometimes
if you put trust in someone
or if you put your friendship in someone,
they will like that will kind of reap its own dividend.
And I like that as a message generally,
maybe because I am a sap.
- Trusting soul, John.
- I am.
- It did also ring true to me that you can see how
being friends with never fell could be incredibly annoying
at times.
I mean, she's a wonderful character,
but she can be quite irritating.
She's kind of constantly on the move.
Everything is new to her.
She takes an interest in everything.
She's got a 10 second attention span.
And I find that to be a very realistic,
you know, a very realistic depiction of someone.
You don't want her to be the perfect saying
to come to bring rebellion.
- Okay, so, so yes, she's taking the role of a child
in this novel.
And so yes, she does all the things that children do.
She's very naive, she's very trusting.
She fails to appreciate the political shenanigans,
which are completely ludicrous.
I mean, they're very much ramped up from even the,
even the madest real world courts,
because, and that's shown as a function of the grand steward
having had a 500 year reign in which everyone else at court
has been developing backstabbing strategies.
I mean, I really like never fell.
I thought she was a very enjoyable character
to follow along with.
- I didn't interpret never fell as the child at all.
I interpreted her as a love letter to ADHD.
And I was like, I saw a lot of me and never fell.
I very much liked the solution of maybe just not planning
will work.
And it did.
And I was like, good, 'cause that is, again,
it speaks to me.
I don't know whether that was on purpose.
I don't know whether Harding has any experience
with ADHD or any friends with ADHD.
But certainly I saw aspects of me in the character
on that, that made me happy.
I did also, there's, I dunno, there's a lot.
The part at the end where the novel turns into a heist.
Oh, we haven't really talked about that,
but there's a part at the end where Harding uses
like a very kind of tried and tested heist movie trope
to great effect, which I enjoyed very thoroughly.
And that was very good.
'Cause this, I guess this is as much about memory
as it is about class, but it's, I dunno,
quite what it's trying to say about memory as much.
But it's clearly a recurring theme.
- The ending basically puts in the position
where the readers know less than never fell, does.
- Yeah.
- I guess you're trying to say she has now figured out
this world a bit, we're not learning about it with her,
but she knows what's going on.
And so it is one of these complicated things
where everyone's erased parts of their own memories,
which is like in a high-smithy way,
you see things going on and you don't really know
the secret twist that's gonna occur.
And in this case, no one knows the secret twist
that's gonna happen because they erase a bit
their brain that knows about the secret twist.
So I enjoyed all that.
- Yup, that's great Liz.
I've got a soft spot for heists in general,
so I did, I very much enjoyed that whole thing.
- There's a lot of different stuff in this book.
- Yeah.
- Yeah, and I think that might be,
that might be why I picked it.
I mean, there's, you know,
quite a few Francis Harding books,
and I think most people would probably pick
maybe Fly By Night from her early ones,
or, you know, something like The Lightree,
which I think got more widespread acclaim.
I think I just like this one for having a sort of,
let's kind of cram in six different ideas
and make them work.
Maybe a later one's a bit more kind of focusing on one thing
and in a more kind of controlled way,
but I've got a soft spot for this one,
'cause it's just got everything in there.
- This book has everything,
but imagine I'm saying it like Bill Hader in SNL
to get the joke listeners.
Now, and this actually might be,
'cause I've always preferred early Pratchett
to late Pratchett, like I,
colour of magic is one of my very favourite books,
and I think that might be also because
he's not trying to tell tight satires
that have like a central message.
He's just telling loads of jokes and having a good time,
and I very much enjoy that kind of just romp through,
like, romp through a thing.
Yeah, I wonder whether that is something
that I also feel.
I haven't read any late hardings,
so maybe I should read it and let you know.
- Let me give you one minute to look up her bibliography,
and then I will tell you which one of the late ones
I might recommend.
I mean, I think Alice in Red Deep liked
which I quite like, but it's not,
I would say, one of the best.
- I mean, I think it may be,
I suspect that some of her ambition with that novel
is in areas that I'm not very interested in,
and I found the kind of central adventure story
to be rather dull.
I enjoyed this one a great deal more than that.
But I will read more farting, probably.
- Yeah, I mean, I do like fly by night
and the sequel Twilight Robert robbery,
and they've got a goose.
- Yeah, and I think other than that,
I like the light tree, which is essentially,
there's a tree which bears fruit if you lie to it.
And again, it's one of these great ideas
where you then kind of unravel all the possibilities of it.
- John, you really need to read fly by night
and Twilight robbery, because you need to know
why "Moska the Cat" is called "Moska."
- I have read, I have read one other hardening book,
and I should have, if I was a good co-host,
looked up which one it was in advance.
A skin full of shadows.
Is that the other one I've read?
I gave it four stars.
- Skin full shadows is the one with the Civil War setting,
isn't it, I think?
Yeah.
- Yep, and "Make Peace" has a ghost dinner.
- Yes.
- I remember enjoying it.
I don't remember many of the actual details.
I just have an impression of having enjoyed it.
But now I will probably read more hardening in the future,
'cause I have liked the two books of hers I read.
I think I would give this book a five star.
So maybe I liked it more than "Skin full of Shadows."
- Whoa, I'm gonna declare my pick a success
even before we hear what Alice and I give it.
- Yeah, 'cause I, as John finds very annoying,
I have stopped giving star ratings to things.
- It's true that my goodreads rankings are sort of like,
they're not like a nice normal distribution.
They're sort of really like tightly compressed
around like the 3.5 to four star mark.
Because, I don't know, I feel bad like,
because everything on goodreads is like pushed up
to the higher end of the star rating distribution.
So I feel bad if I just like, oh, that was all right.
And I give it two stars and it drags the rating down.
But I also try not to put star ratings
on books by friends or not for a little while later.
- Anyway, what did you think of the book, "Allison?"
- Overall, I thought it was jolly good.
I think people should read it if they like,
you know, fantasy that's got some,
some pretensions to doing more than just telling a story,
books about interesting societies,
I think it's fine.
And it is quite long, but it's an easy read.
So, you know, it's a great book to just get stuck into
and enjoy.
Recommended.
- Do you have, oh, do you want to sum up Liz?
Do you have anything you want to sum?
- No, just I'm glad you like the book.
I'm glad I liked rereading the book.
And I'm glad that, you know,
sometimes when everyone likes a book,
the discussion is not actually that interesting
because it's like, oh, we all like that.
Hmm.
So I'm glad we got a good discussion out of it
without having to pick a really contentious choice
or anything.
- Don't worry listeners,
'cause when we've done the first three of these
we'll be starting to pick more avant-garde choices.
And I'm sure Liz will pick a couple of absolute shockers
in that bit. (laughs)
But they will be, they will be shockers that Liz picks
as revenge for the fact that at some point
I will make both of my co-hosts read Rogue Squadron
by Michael A. Stackfall,
a book with no redeeming literary merit whatsoever,
but which I still love.
- Okay, so, (laughs)
I'm not convinced you you're gonna like my choice, guys.
I should probably reread it
so that make sure I am happy to still recommend it.
- I can't remember either of your choices.
Anyway, that's what made me w-
- That was the "Ock to Thought" podcast.
And it's goodbye from me.
- It's goodbye from me.
- And it's goodbye from me.
(upbeat music)
- What was the cat behind you, John?
- What?
- The cat behind you.
- Is there?
- Oh, hello, Ellen.
- She says meow.
She enjoyed the book too,
because I read it under her most of it.
And so she got a lot of cuddles this week.
So she was a big fan of that.
The theme music for this episode was "Surf Shimmy"
by Kevin MacLeod and Combertec.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
- This podcast will end at the beep.