Hello everyone and welcome to the very 79th episode of Octa Thorpe. This episode is coming
to you on the 16th of March 2023. I am John Coxon.
I am Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty. John, are you doing your best presenter voice in a
way to be on match the day or something? We stand with Gary Lineker because he's a legend and he's
the only match of the day host, whoever sold vegetables on Lester Market. The BBC's announced there's
going to be no punditry. I woke up and it was like everyone's saying, I'm not going to do it and
then are you right saying, well, I'm not going to do it. And then everyone else followed by saying,
well, if you're right, it's not doing it. We won't do it either. In the comment, it's like, well,
we won't commentate and I woke up to all this and it was like, yeah, that is an overnight cluster
fucking it. Anyway, sorry, off topic. Yup. Did you see that Joe Lysit said I'll do it?
Yes. Yeah, I really want Joe Lysit to do it so much. I love them so much.
I think they'd be great because I'm also sure that Joe Lysit does not know a whole lot about
Premier League football. But he does know a whole lot about being right-wing.
He does. Right. Yeah, anyway, we're going to do a podcast. Anyone who's not British is like,
what is going on? And we're going to refuse to explain. Sorry, American listeners.
Just Google. Oh, no, I can't imagine there's going to be a single sensible roundup of this
that incorporates everything we just said. We have a letter as a comment. I wanted to come back to
a letter of comment from Raj on episode 77 because I didn't say something and then I regretted not
saying something, which is that when I had been discussing Ms Marvel and representation,
I'd had conversations with a couple of people who had doubted whether or not Ms Marvel would
be good representation for people who were not American, like basically for members of the
Pakistani diaspora from around the rest of the world. And Raj did say in his episode 77
in luck that he really enjoyed Ms Marvel and he thought it was great for representation.
And it was nice to see people who looked like me represented in genre fiction in the MCU no less.
And Raj, to the best of my knowledge, is not a young girl living in New Jersey being as how
he is a man who lives in Glasgow. We also heard from other people, Bridget, for instance.
Yeah, so Bridget came on Cafe Moose, which is my regular weekday zoom thing and said,
can I give you a lock here on Cafe Moose? And we said, if you must.
We said, yes, that would be lovely. We did not grumble. John said, yes, that would be lovely.
And I said, oh, I'm not sure I'll remember it. But luckily John wrote it down. So there we go.
And Bridget said, fandom has great policies for things, but individual people in fandom can be
obstreperous and obstrative. And this is very true. This is why we have great policies, honestly.
Strew in a lot of places, to be honest.
Yeah, it is not just fandom, but it is definitely true of fandom.
Oh, I think that's a particular streak of stubborn in fandom. You might be right.
We also heard from Christopher J Garcia, who's a legend like Gary Linnaker.
I've answered several of our queries about sentences which he left halfway through in the
last legend comment. Yep. And so he recommends a single best thing he watched last year,
a film called Big Book, which is, according to the internet, a French science fiction black
comedy film that you can watch on Netflix. So,
that sounds like a good shout, actually. So it might be worth watching. I certainly have not
watched any recent French black comedy science fiction films. So I might give that a go.
It was Chris who showed me OSS Sandy Set for the first time, which is a delightful and ridiculous
French movie, which I did wholly enjoy. It was not Chris that showed me Breece. And honestly,
Chris, I will never forgive you because Breece is the best movie in the world. And the only reason I
want the world con to be a niece. Breece is the word. And if anyone is listening who hasn't seen
Breece, you should go see it because it's very good and extremely silly. Do we want to get into
Chris's comment on the pronunciation of a particular word, which I think is now a running
top view conversation for three whole episodes? Yes. So. Chris's on team, a mock rhymes with a lock.
It's pronounced a mock if it follows the same pronunciation as a mock time,
which I heard Theodore Sturgeon called a mock time in the before four times back when he was alive.
I'm not sure if his ghost says it the same. On the other hand, you pronounce Spock, Spock.
So thanks, Chris. That is valuable input to the debate, as always.
Yeah. I mean, I think pulling out the I heard Theodore Sturgeon say it card is a powerful argument
that Chris, thank you. It conflicts with Laurie from Hugo Girl saying that she pronounces it a
muck, but she fails to note which legend of the science fiction genre taught her this pronunciation.
So can we really trust her? Yeah, Laurie, if it turns out that you learned the pronunciation from
like Ursula Le Guin, then. Well, I now want to do next time we're at the Glasgow World con,
is every time one of us bumps into a famous author, we just record on our phone how they say the word.
We have it on a little sign and we say, please read this word out and we record it.
And then we play them all on a future episode of Octa Thorpe and we have ribbons.
This would certainly be the best use of Octa Thorpe's time interviewing famous authors that are welcome.
Yup. I might do it to Adrian Tchaikovsky at Eastcom and see whether he's confused.
We could ask them about a few different words while we're at it.
Could we? What else do we disagree on?
Muffie!
[laughs]
Thank you to Kurt Phillips who once saw me eat a cheeseburger.
I don't know whether we want to unpack that or not.
Well, we're just gonna leave it there.
I think so. I also like that Kurt says, I find that I agree with most everything you all said.
Thank you, Kurt.
Hey.
On the subject of agreeing, he says, he assumes over the next episode or two of Octa Thorpe
will start making Hugo World suggestions and that will surely give him something to disagree with.
He says, I'm sure you'll do your best for me.
And yes, we will attempt to be opinionated.
Obviously, we're usually very diplomatic and unopinionated, so it is hard, but we'll try.
Yeah, I mean, usually we all agree with each other all of the time.
Yup.
Makes very difficult to do a podcast.
Do we?
Why do we appear?
Why do we agree with each other?
[laughs]
I love jokes.
I love the wishing noise they make as they speed by.
And he just makes some comments about the Chengdu Worldcon.
Will there ever come a day when fans read or hear that name without a cold finger of dread
playfully poking us in our hippocampus?
Well, we're going to do our best with our regular Chengdu segment right up until October and probably beyond.
Yes.
Good segue Liz.
Our regular segment about Chengdu is beginning to have more information and less whining,
because this time Chengdu have opened Hugo nominations.
Liz, do you want to summarize what is happening here?
Chengdu opened Hugo nominations, which I know because they sent me an email about how
Hugo nominations are open and how to nominate, and I went to the website and logged in and nominated
some stuff, so it's all working, guys.
But I was hoping you might go into more detail.
Generally, the fact they've opened Hugo nominations would not be a big deal.
It is a big deal, I guess, because it shows them doing something vaguely on time,
and so it all makes us feel that maybe if they can open Hugo nominations on time,
this is a sign you can maybe run a welcome.
But also they have a special clause, which is about conversion factors for Chinese language nominees,
because four of the categories for the Hugo Awards have word count limits on them.
So you break short story, novelt, novella and novella up by the number of words in a story,
and this in previous times has always been used to mean English language words,
and they have thought about this, and since they're expecting nominations for items written in Chinese,
they've decided that there will be a factor of 1.6 when converting.
I don't know how they came up with that number, but I presume there's some
statistics about this somewhere that you can calculate what the conversion factor is for language,
and so essentially a short story is, say, fewer than 7,500 English words or 12,000 Chinese characters.
It seems like a very sensible way to do it to me. I mean, it's not in the constitution,
probably because the constitution has never really had to think about that before.
I guess we've had World Cons in, we have had World Cons of the Countries,
I mean, the only one I think we've had that uses a non, not the same character set as English is in
Japan, and then there were no Japanese language nominees, so it didn't have to get thought about,
but this is clearly going to be a thing, and so it's good that they've announced this now,
because then if you're nominating something in the Chinese language, you can put it in the right
category straight away, otherwise you're going to have this horrible mess where there's tons of
stuff nominated because it has 12,000 Chinese characters, and then they have to try and do a
conversion factor and say, "Oh, well, actually, this should be a novelist and move everything around,"
and you'd also presumably, because the word limits are slightly different, end up with a lot of what
we would think of as novellas that just get shoved in the novel category with everything else,
so I think it's a good move to announce this ahead of time, and probably something other
World Cons in the future will have to think about. So yes, my question was how did they decide
how many characters you got, and I googled very quickly while Liz was explaining and got
19 different answers ranging from 1.2 to 2.1, so you know, I think 1.6 is probably somewhere in the
middle, and they probably took some advice. I do wonder, there are many other languages which use
the same alphabet as English, but which are more or less compact, and I wonder whether this is
setting an interesting precedent for items written in other languages.
It does, I mean, I guess if you were a German World Cons, since you might want to set one for German,
but I don't know if the conversion factors for other languages are quite so dramatically different.
Because the average 8000 word short story will translate into 14 German words.
Yeah, so has there ever been a non-English language work nominated for Hugo?
Not in the written fiction categories, I don't think.
Because I was going to ask, when you said about, you made a comment, I can't remember exactly what
it was of this, but I was wondering, like, obviously this is the first time that there's been a likelihood
of things written not in Roman characters, but I was curious as to whether or not there had been
anything that was not in English that had been nominated. Because I don't see why this precedent
wouldn't hold if you had like a German book. I don't, I mean, unless it is very similar to English,
which I don't know, so I'd be very interested to find out.
I think it does depend language by language.
There's also a 20% kind of wiggle room on the limits anyway, right? So if you're translating
into a language that doesn't add a lot of verbosity or take it away, then it will make a lot of
difference and it should be within the limits anyway. It's when you get to things where the
conversion factor is this high that I guess is an issue. I don't think there's been any fiction
nominees not in the English language. I think we have had things nominated which were originally
not published in English, but it was the English translation that was nominated, but I don't think
anything that was actually not in English has been nominated in the written fiction categories.
If I've missed something again, expert should write in and let me know. But I feel I'm on
steady ground with this one.
Nebula nominees are out. Yes, we are all awards all the time this week. It's award season.
Nebula Awards will be presented on May the 14th, 2023 and there will be a live stream
and in-person event as part of the 2023 Nebula Conference online.
So I read a few of these stories and I think you've read a few as well, John.
Yeah, I have. There's a couple of stories, so obviously there are uncanny stories in here.
There's one that was nominated that I thought was very good up until the end,
at which point I thought that it really did just sort of not have an ending. It just sort of fizzled.
And I find that very difficult with short stories because it's very easy to have a great setup
for a short story and not stick the landing. It's interesting because the Nebula Award for
Novella is only 60% tour.com, which is a shockingly poor showing given previous awards late.
But yeah, no, some interesting stuff. I suspect Beiball and Nona the 9th will be on the Hugo
Ballot. I suspect Netland Bone will be on the load star Ballot. I don't think it'll be on the
novel for Hugo. Might be wrong. I don't know what else will come up. It's usually like about half
and half, right? There's usually about three that cross over? Is that fair? That's not based
on any stats listeners. That's based on gut intuition. Yeah, I'd have to do some stats. So,
yeah. But I mean, I wonder if the mountain, the sea will make it because I have heard quite a
lot of people talking about that. Usually it's a an unexpected thing that came out because,
you know, I think everyone was expecting like Nona the 9th to be a good and on there, but the
mountain, the sea has come about out of nowhere. I have read a few of the short fiction nominees,
and I thought they were mostly good, but not super amazing. But mostly ones that I
thought would be, you know, if I saw them on a short list, I would be happy with them being on
a short list. Quite a few of them are from horror magazines and short story, which I don't tend to
read, so I haven't read those. Yeah, so this is actually Four Shadows, something we will talk
about later. But two of the novelets are novelets I will be nominating for the Hugo award. I will
talk about those when I talk about that. And one of them is One Eye and I think it doesn't overlap,
but maybe that's too much foreshadowing. I would say I am a little bit confused by how the Bradbury
award works for dramatic breast dramatic presentation, because there's nominations for three complete
series of TV shows and then one episode of Andor. So I don't quite understand how it works,
you know, do all the nominations for different TV episodes get combined into one nomination for
series, or do you have to explicitly nominate series? I don't know how it works. And as discussed,
else always some friends, I don't really think our flag means death is particularly science
fictional, fantastic. No. As opposed to being a thing fans like watching, but I don't think
it's going to win anyway, because it's probably going to be a big fight between
both of the other nominees, to be honest. I'm confused by dramatic presentation, because I'm
confused. Are you confused, Sean? Are you confused? I'm a bit surprised that Andor got nominated for
one episode and like not the whole season, but I guess that's just what people nominated. I do
think that's probably the best episode. And then our flag means death definitely isn't science fiction
and also definitely won't win. So I think it's probably fine. Yeah. Also, the Nebula Award for
game writing is interesting. It's Elden Ring, Horizon Forbidden West, journeys through the
radiant citadel, Pentiment, Stray, and Vampire the Masquerade, Sins of the Spires. Sins of the
Sires, sorry. Yeah, it's Vampire but the Sires, John. The Sires. I think it's fair to say that
not all of these games have been well received for their gameplay. And I'm not going to say which
one I'm thinking of particularly, but I can't pronounce it. I'm sure they will have extremely
good writing. This is one of the things that makes the Nebula game category a bit different
from the Proceugo one is the very much focuses on the writing and not the gameplay.
But I hope Horizon wins because Horizon is great. I'm sure Horizon will win. I don't know.
I'm not. I'm not sure it will. I'm not because it is game writing. So really, it's like,
oh, instead of making a game, why don't you just tell a story in game form?
Stray and Elden Ring are both like, were both incredibly well received. So I wouldn't want to
bet money that they wouldn't take it. So journeys through the radiant citadel is a
Dungeons and Dragons anthology of one shot venture modules. I think it's 13 modules. I'm
right wrong about that. It's very tricky to evaluate how you compare the writing in a game
that will take like 200 hours to play versus the writing in a series of one shots that are
designed for players to like interact with on the table. I have no idea how you made that
judgement. But yeah, it's kind of interesting that there's one tabletop product on there.
It's two tabletop products on there, right? No. Vampire the Masquerade since of the Sires is
like an interactive steam game. Oh, I see. Okay. That's why I was saying not all of them have
been well received for gameplay. Because as far as I can tell, it is basically you occasionally
click and it gets to the end of a very linear story. But perhaps a very well written linear story.
I really liked Stray, but I think it's going to be hard to think about the writing,
as opposed to kind of how that interacts with the gameplay. Because would it be half as much fun
if you were not a little cat rubbing up against robots and getting pets and sleeping on little
cushions and things. But the writing's not really part of that. It's just you get to be a little cat.
So we'll see.
Anyway, shall we do the final final part of our three part award roundup this week?
The BSFA. Yes, the BSA. We should say here that we would link to the BSFA website's list of the
BSFA award nominees. But the BSFA does not have a list of the BSA award nominees. So we're listing
the file 771 instead. I feel like we said that in 2022. We're going to keep saying it.
Yup. Some interesting stuff on here. Friend of the podcast. Fiona Moore is nominated in
best non-fiction for her book Management Lessons from Game of Thrones organization,
Theory and Strategy in Westeros. Which one day we will talk about on the podcast.
I am reading it. I'm not at the end yet. I've been meaning to have it as a pick for ages.
Yeah, some other stuff as well. It's all very good. Very different to the Nebula shortlist,
but that is often the case. Yes. And also, I find it quite notable that Adrian Trieskoski
is nominated for Best Novel for I think one of his five novels out last year, maybe four.
But you could conceivably have had an all-Adrian Trieskoski Best Novel shortlist.
And the fact that we didn't is cowardice on the part of BSFA nominators. Come on guys.
All Trieskoski all the time. It would have been quite funny and all the ones I've read were good
anyway and I'd be happy to have them nominated. So yeah, come on, let's just do it. Yup. All
Adrian all the time. I'm hoping that they will do they have done in previous years a little
voter like booklet for BSFA members. I'm kind of hoping they will do that.
So I'd quite like to see some of this gorgeous artwork before I actually cast my vote. And you
know, it'd be good if someone sent me a PDF of it rather than having to quote unquote Google.
Yeah. Also, I Googled and got the wrong book because there's one with the same name as a book
which is nominated, but it's not the nominee. And so I got a bit confused. I was like, why is
this on that? It doesn't look science fiction at all. And it wasn't. Which one was it?
It was the way the light bends because there's more than one book called the way the light bends.
Oh, I'm crying.
Hi everyone. This is John. I'm recording this while I'm editing the podcast in a hotel room.
And I just wanted to let you know that the BSFA sent the voter ban flat out shortly after
you recorded. Now back to the episode. And we don't have any news on whether or not
the how the voting is going to work. So no, you can probably vote for the awards. We can't tell
you how, but you probably can. But yeah, BSFA members and Eastcon members are eligible to vote
in the BSFA awards. So if you have if you think, oh, I'm coming to the Eastcon, but it's never
occurred to me to vote in the BSFA awards, you should be able to do that. We haven't, I don't think
we've announced how that's happening yet, but it will be. It looks like BSFA members can vote
on the BSFA website, but only BSFA members.
Oh, did we mention the everything everywhere all at once? Propulsion last time.
Yeah, but we didn't put it out because it's in the weird bit. Okay, because it has now closed.
And it was $90,000 for Raccoonie. Oh man, I could have afforded that.
And also the rock with Googly eyes is a surprisingly big rock.
Is it? Is it like? I thought it was a small rock, but it's got dimensions and it's like a
foot wide. Hmm. Yeah, 42 pounds, which in real money is about 20 kilos. Yeah, it's quite a big
rock. There's a massive Googly eyes. Ordeter of the month trophy with $60,000. Yeah.
And I mean, that you can see how that would be a great present for somebody.
Yup, yup. But that also is this is being two pounds. That is like a not a very solid artifact.
Raccoonie was two kilos and someone had to have it on their head. So, you know,
that seems pretty light for an actual puppet. There is a shot on the prop auction site where you
can buy things, including the hot dog fingers gloves, like just for $36, which doesn't not
pay $6,000 just a $6. So, you know, but that's merch rather than props. Oh yeah, but I don't know
anywhere else you can buy hot dog finger gloves. And you can get for $35 and everything everywhere
pet rock, which comes in a little box that says pet rock on it. This is great. Rock size may vary.
Oh, oh, there's also a book. It is a pretty great idea to start selling the hot dog fingers.
Yes. So basically listeners, on the last episode when we recorded, we discussed the prop auction
very slightly as part of a Hugo discussion we had that we have not yet put out because we're
going to do it as bonus material. And so this discussion is sort of time difficult, but there
was a prop auction. It's gone. You just had us talk about it, but I will put a link in the
show notes because there is also things you can just buy normally without spending that
spending $1,000. So that might be of interest to people, including the laughing rocks multiverse
poster, which is an image you can download and print out. Oh, I kind of want that.
And I think as Alison is spotted, there is a book basically about the multiverse, but
it's got a forward by Ted Jiang and a Douglas Adams quote in it.
Oh, nice. Yeah, and a load of interesting things, three short stories,
all beginning with the same sentence and parallel short fictions and it looks quite an interesting
book. So if anyone's got that and has read it, it would be great if you could talk to us about it.
I don't know if there's an e-book. I don't think there's an e-book.
I think it's just a giant, hardback $50 one unfortunately.
Boo, it's kind of a giant, hardback art book. Yeah, three tipping booklets, silver cold foil cover.
Looks very nice, but also very heavy. Oh, they also sell official everything
everywhere all at once, googly eyes, but they have sold out of those.
They've sold out.
Probably them. I don't feel they need to have official googly eyes. I feel googly eyes
are available in sufficient places. They don't need official branded googly eyes because they've
already got googly eyes to put the rumble. You put the money on, you put the money on the river.
I did.
I've got googly eyes on my rumble too.
Right, picks. Yeah.
We'll go on then.
It's like a first.
You can do.
All right. My pick is "Losses bookies" or rather the first series of "Losses bookies"
is an HBO comedy show about a group of friends who create kind of fake horror scenarios for people
who pay them to do this. So they set up a fake alien invasion and a fake exorcism and things
like this with their love of horror films and horror makeup and horror props. But it's also just
unbelievably weird and I can't think of anything else quite like it. It's Spanish language for
starters. It is set in an unnamed Latin American country, but it's got things like they meet the
American ambassador where everything is Barbie Pink and she has a load of sort of clean-cut
Americans who can't do anything at all in the embassy. And it's just all played very, very straight
while being completely weird and off the wall. And it's just kind of lots of fun to watch and
is not the sort of thing you would ever expect anyone to make a show about but works really well.
Anyway, I've watched series one because that is once available on my streaming service.
Series two is out, but I haven't watched it yet because I don't have it on streaming yet,
but it wasn't 2022. So I'm going to try and get to it in case it is a potential Hugo
nominee. And yeah, I just really enjoyed spending half an hour in this kind of
strange universe where they're faking up horror things working through props and makeup and so on.
But also there is clearly like an actual real supernatural element going on. Someone possessed
by a demon and a cursed mirror. And then, you know, they buy the cursed mirror like we told
you to buy a non-cursed mirror. Like it's just all very kind of straight and day to day. And
John is laughing so I presume John has also watched lots of spooky and enjoyed it.
It was so good. He's like, well, I bought the cursed mirror because I'm spooky. It's
isn't helpful. Like, oh, the cursed mirror looked the best. They're like, yes, that's because it's
cursed mirror. Yeah. And she's so cross. And I, yeah, I love, I don't want to spoil it, but I love
the way that plotline resolves the end of the episode is bloody brilliant. No, it's great.
Yeah, for all the reasons you've said, just very, very good. It's Fred Armisen in part.
Julio Torres, Anna Faberge and Fred Armisen. So Anna Faberge plays Tati and Julio Torres plays
Andres Valdez, who is the adopted heir to a chocolate empire. And his parents, his parents
are mysterious. I don't think that ever come. I don't know why. So mysterious.
There's mysterious memories. You never see their faces. They're never shot full on you. We see
them like obscured by something. But there's no reason because they're just obviously completely
like boring normal people, but you only ever see them shot in a really mysterious way.
And it's never explained. It's so weird. And Tati like has, she's been catfished, but she
is being catfished. She definitely thinks she's been catfished. Yeah, she's talking to
prince on the internet. Nothing we are saying makes any sense to any of your listeners.
I am so sorry, but you should watch this show because it is ridiculous. Or indeed to me.
It's so good. Yeah, I recommend. Yeah. Ask a pick. I should have picked that at some point,
but I'm glad I waited until you picked it because it is good to have someone to basically just make
completely incomprehensible statements across one another. Yeah, we are this people going,
oh, you remember that bit? Wasn't really good that bit. And then there was that thing with the dog.
And it was really good. And then, you know, there was a bit with the mirror. And yeah,
people who do that are really, really annoying.
Okay, so no, I just sewn that guys. So I hope that was interesting. Should I do my pick?
All right, Johnny, you're going to do your pick. Yeah, what did you pick at an allison?
I still haven't done very many genre appropriate things, but I went last night to see Allegiance,
which is a musical. It is the passion project of George Takai, who was interned as a small boy,
as part of the Interment of Japanese Americans in the Second World War. And he got some help and
produced a musical about this. And it ran on Broadway for a short while, and then closed,
and has had several revivals because of Takai basically going, no, no, no, I really
bought this story out there. I really wanted to be told. And it is currently playing until I think
the 8th of April at the Charing Cross Theatre in London, which is technically not a Western
theatre, though you would think it was in the West End. It's a very tiny theatre under the arches
by Charing Cross Station. And the musical is, I think, it has mixed reviews. And I think I didn't
think it was very good, but you might want to go and see it anyway. It's an important story,
so if you don't know the story, then I think that's a good reason to go and see it. And there are
some good performances. And in particular, Takai is very, very good and very well worth watching.
And the man is 85. So if you would like to see him live on stage and afterwards go and meet him in
the Q&A stage door and get your programme signed, they were very careful to say, we are only signing
items from Allegiance. We are not going to sign items from any other show that any of the actors
might have been involved in at any time. Then you can do that. And the tickets are not particularly
expensive by London standards. I think there are 20-pound tickets for every show, but obviously,
you know, it's hard to get those ones. But I think our tickets are about 40 quid, which is not
unusual for which is not bad for London. And it's tiny theatre, so everyone has a good view.
And so you might well want to go and see it, because Takai is very good. And the man is 85.
He's exactly the same age as my dad was, just about a month older than my dad.
And one of the things we said at my parents' funeral was, oh, one of the things they kept telling us
was we were brought up in the war, don't you know? And I think that is also very true of Takai
and very relevant to this show. And it's possible that war didn't affect him in quite the way it
affected my parents. I think it's a different experience. But it was interesting seeing that experience
and having the relevance to it. So yeah, enjoy myself. Thank you to Farah, friend of the show,
Farah Mendelssohn, for sorting out that theatre trip. Weirdly related. I mean, it's not, I'm going
to kind of have a bonus pick here, but if anyone hasn't read "Like, Petrol" by Francis Buffard,
it's not really science fictional, but it's just kind of he imagines an alternate world in which
five children were killed during a bomb attack in London in the war. And just imagines kind of
the alternate universe if they lived. And it's about, you know, what their stories would have been.
And it's just kind of very kind of sweetly written, kind of imagining, you know, these five people's
lives with their ups and downs and what would have happened to them if they'd grown up, but they
all died in 1944. It's all fictional, but I thought that was quite a nice novel from the
past couple of years that's similarly about what would have happened if things were different.
I have read something since last time, but I probably don't want to pick it.
In episode 42 listeners, I'm sure you all remember episode 42. It was "I'm Up for Running
Control Con". I used to have a different face. Alison was going to Smothcon, and Liz was in disguise.
And we did picks and Liz picked a book by a man called Adrian Tchaikovsky, and it was an easy
decision to pick a book by him because he's written half of all books. So, you know,
you're going to end up picking one at some point.
He's written the entire 2024 BSFA shortlist.
You heard it here first. And Liz picked children of ruin, Eibley.
Sounds quite possible. I read it.
I'm current. I am currently reading children of ruin, but I'm not going to pick children of ruin
because I have not finished it yet. But I am going to pick children of time,
which we haven't picked before, and is therefore a completely crombulent pick.
So children of time is good book. Children of time won the Arthur C. Clark Award. It was published
in 2015. If you are an arachnophobe, I don't know whether you should read this book. If anyone
listening is an arachnophobe that has read it, please write in because I would find that very
interesting to hear. Liz is putting her hand up in her.
I'm not a super arachnophobe, but like I will scroll past pictures of spiders on Facebook very,
very quickly. And I read it and it was all right.
Okay, that's good. So yeah, so this is a novel about spiders.
It's a novel about a very strange lady and a planet which hasn't gone so well,
and how that all pans out. And it's incredible. I think it was the first
Tricosteky novel I read because I was like, I should really read some by him because he's very good.
Everyone says so. And I decided to read that one because it was the one that would want the
Clark. But it is fantastic. It has the benefit that children of memory has just come out,
which is the third in this series. I'm reading Children of Ruin, and it has been a while since
I read Children of Time, but Children of Ruin is also really, really good so far.
I have just reached the point where I think the shit has hit the fan, and I'm curious to see
how it will be distributed. But yeah, it's just amazing and I highly recommend it.
So if you are thinking I should really read some Tricosteky before Easton,
and you are at a loss for which of his many books you should dive into,
I would highly recommend Children of Time as your entry point. I think it would be a good pick
for anyone in that situation. And I would say I think, I mean, I'd read Empire of Black and Gold.
So I'd read Men of Tricosteky before Children of Time. But that seems to me to mark the point
where I think he's writing a step up. And also his kind of recognition and notice took a step up,
because that was the point where I think he started to see him really getting on award short lists.
And you know, I've seen it and chopped the Little Clark Award winner logo on and everything.
So I think it's been doing quite well. No, Children of Ruin has a little sticker saying
the previous book in the series won the Clark Award on it. It's very nice. Also, another little
cheeky pick, which is if anyone here listening is a fan of podcasts and also tabletop games,
there is an actual play podcast called Force Mature. And I'm not going to recommend the entire podcast.
I'm going to recommend a very specific sub part of the podcast, which is that they have recently
finished an arc. Well, I think they actually finished their main campaign. So they have been
doing some other stuff since they have finished. They did a little four episode arc, which is called
the outer dark trilogy part two. I admit I did not listen to the outer dark trilogy part one.
They played the first parts using an OSR system that I wasn't particularly interested in listening
to. So I didn't listen. But the second part they played using the Skomon villainy system,
which I was very interested in listening to because it's a sci-fi hack of Blade in the Dark. And
basically it has some of the usual suspects, but it also has Agent Shrykowski, who is very good
and plays a very interesting character. And it also has John Robertson, who does the Dark Room.
And if you have watched the Dark Room, you can imagine John Robertson role playing
and imagine how fun that might be. He plays a satire of an American author who likes guns too
much, which I think he's doing Larry Corea. I think not sure, but very, very funny.
There's a few.
Yeah, there are. Yes, it doesn't necessarily narrow it down to one, but it is very, very good. So if
you do like actual plays and people being ridiculous, I would recommend listening to the outer dark
trilogy part two episodes one to four. It's very good. And also another sneaky bonus pick. The Dark
Room. If you get the opportunity to see the Dark Room, the Dark Room is amazing. I saw it at
EasterCon for the first time a while back. And yeah, just if it's near you, go see it,
because it is very funny. And it is SF-NOL. For shadowing. That was The Ultimate Podcast.
And it's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me.
[Music]
A short list of science fiction novels. You should not read if you're a director of
hope. There's a few. Yep. Esther, if you're listening. That's my nomination for the Glasgow
special category for Hugo's best spider-related novel. Because you know, it's about time we had
an all-aidery Tchaikovsky Hugo category. So let's make it happen. The theme music for this
episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod and Competec.com used under a creative commons
attribution 4.0 license. This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.
[BLANK_AUDIO]