I'm going to eat a quarter of shit.
Well, that's the cold open.
Hello everyone and welcome to the 19th episode of Octa Thorpe, a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom. I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Betty.
We're tired.
I'm not dead though.
That's good.
You're not dead.
No.
Contrary to rumors that were propagated by a trio of degenerates at a closing ceremony for a recent convention, Liz lives.
We thought it was funny.
It was funny, but we were sleeved deprived and had been drinking.
It was funny.
I just want to, you know, set any rumors to bed.
I think we did clarify immediately because I think at the point where we put up that photo and said we're going to take a moment to remember Liz.
Some people in our audience might have actually been shocked for a few seconds.
So we did.
We did want to correct that impression very fast.
Yeah, we are great.
We have had letters of comment.
So we will start with a letter to comment.
Firstly, Claire Breyerley from Croydon collected her point for her house by correctly identifying the reference.
And Claire Breyerley from Croydon also sent me 108 weetabix.
So I must now take a bath with them.
In them.
Will this be?
No, no, I can't.
I can't hollow them out.
I can make them into a bath.
I'm not just for the record.
I'm not making a bath out of weebix categorically, though.
I think that would be a very special, very niche fanzying, John.
I also think that after plotters investigations into the efficacy of chocolate teapots,
you might find that the efficacy of weetabix baths is not that great.
And that at the point where you put a liquid into your weetabix bath, it would do the
weetabix thing and you would then just kind of have a pile of mush.
Yeah, I mean, that that is one of the myriad of reasons that I am not going to make about
our weebix.
It is true.
Liz looks.
I am very sad listener that you can't see Liz's face.
Have you just exchanged myriad for plethora in your vocabulary now, John?
Yes, because you kept telling me off for losing plethora.
I think any members of the Octo-thorpe audience who would like John to take a bath in weetabix
should definitely write to us and let John know how ardently they desire to see him taking a bath in weetabix.
I'm going to take a bath with my I'm going to take a bath with my weetabix.
That is going to happen in his Star Wars underpants.
Sorry.
I could not say that without corpseing.
I need to say it again with with without corpseing.
I think you corpseing makes the point wonderfully.
In his Star Wars underpants.
At least now we've got the episode title.
So that's good.
You've got it both ways.
And now, of course, you need to mention the the lock on the convention that mentioned
that which you're probably going to do anyway.
We were not actually recording at the point where you said that no, well, I think it was it observed your
Star Wars underpants in your convention zoom background, which feels like a comment on the
convention.
Oh, I thought you said no one spotted them.
No one noticed.
No, all didn't notice.
Unless you did know all if you're listening right in.
I'm just going to watch.
We're going to have to use a screenshot from the YouTube on.
Yeah, basically every every panel or program item I did at punctuation.
There was a pair of my Star Wars underpants drying on my radiator in my room that I zoom from.
And so yeah, if you were an eagle-eyed viewer, you may have noticed my apparel.
Adorning my my view, but you know, they're dry now.
So they're in the airing cupboard because you put dry things in a warm cupboard to make sure I think.
I don't have an airing cupboard, but I mean, effectively, I could say live in a giant airing cupboard.
So I mean, I've never heard anyone call title.
I was going for the same joke, but I'll have to be to it.
Devoomtish.
Claire also criticizes by use of the word onboarding.
And I promise to immediately deplane my use of that word.
Oh, what was wrong with your use of the word onboarding?
I don't think Claire thinks it's a real word.
Oh, well, that's because Claire is an old person.
Oh, boarding is clearly a real word.
It works.
Everyone knows what it means.
It's if we were onboarding people to the convention.
Tech stack.
My plan, my plan, my future plans going forward is not to use the word onboarding again.
Going forward is also on the list of, of, I know, English phrases that old people don't like.
As is forward planning.
Oh, well, forward planning is actually an oxen moral, isn't it?
Because you're right.
Yes.
Because you probably shouldn't spend any time backward planning and and yeah, forward planning is just planning.
But it but it's like these people don't understand the use of adjectives to provide emphasis.
They literally don't, John.
Exactly.
They literally don't.
Which is odd because metaphorically they do.
Um, right.
So having safely ensured that we will get at least one letter of comment next episode,
let's progress to the next one.
One letter of comment from Claire, like at 15 second intervals as she gets progressively more irate.
I don't know.
Maybe maybe she'll be distracted by the thought of you in a bath of wheat picks.
We were onboarding her or attitude.
Right.
It's causing now, John.
We got, we got an, we got a letter of comment.
Helena McCallum said as a letter of comment saying regarding the punching game,
if it was multiplayer, we could bring back the classic small phone convention gag of boxing.
Helena, if VR didn't make her very ill.
So, yeah, I don't know what that is.
Do you know what that is, Alison?
Um, if you had come to our panel item on small fund conventions and actually pop pickers,
there's a few days to still watch our YouTube videos after this podcast goes live.
But before we take them down, which we'll talk about at some point because I want to say
something about captioning as well.
So I'm actually anyway, if you'd gone to the item that we ran on small phone
conventions at punctuation, John, you might have been a bit busy, but it's one of the ones
that I have watched again, because we have the punctuation equivalent of iPlayer.
Yes.
A couple of weeks, which I really love because I never, there is no way on earth.
I'd go to a panel at 10 o'clock on a Sunday morning in the real world, but I have now
watched that panel and very thoroughly enjoyed it.
And they did talk a little bit about Dan Feinkon, which was a convention I was at,
and which was one of the small fund conventions that happened, I think not necessarily
ever made by holiday, but was a Twin Peaks themed convention.
And it made a number of David Lynch jokes because Twin Peaks and because Twin Peaks
was dotted itself funny enough to sustain an entire weekend, though it was pretty good.
You know, there was a lot, we ran a back, Stephen and I ran a workshop at that
convention on talking backwards, because that's a thing that Twin Peaks has quite a lot of.
I am digressing and you did.
Oh, because David Lynch also did a film called Boxing Helena, and they had somebody who
was called Helena, which is quite close.
They put her in a box as you do.
Hey, now, I know what to say, though, I happen to have a chance to go back through
the panels. There are several I do need to do that with, but I have basically the last
week has been doing as little as possible.
Yeah.
So the other I do want to try and catch nearly everything.
I've done about a third of them now.
So bloody hell.
Fair enough.
I should watch that one, though.
So I've been quite good.
But that's because, remember, I have a job at which I need something to listen to.
And while I'm working, which makes it.
We have a final letter of comment from Roman Orzansky, who writes with regards to
setting lakes on fire.
There are two clear reasons why you might not want to set a lake on fire.
Firstly, Christina wouldn't like it.
And secondly, it would set off an alarm bell if you did so.
I would have thought that obvious.
Surely Roman says I just liked I just liked the pun of set off and alarm bell and
set off an alarm bell.
I thought I was a good pun.
So thank you, Roman.
Yes, it was good.
It's pretty good as far as funds go.
It was in the fine tradition of puns.
I like when I like when Liz, we should have a podcast, which is just Liz reviewing
puns.
Oh, God, can we please not have a podcast, which is me reviewing puns.
I've heard some skanky explanations for why a podcast happens in my time, but that's
pretty bad.
Anyway, we do also have one more letter of comment, but it's a little bit.
Well, I say we I have a letter of comment, which I'm going to talk about on the show
because I can't talk about it in a fanzine.
And that's because it was a letter of comment on my TAF report from Mark Plummer,
who titled the email most John title imaginable, which is good.
There is I very much enjoyed your letter.
Thank you very much for writing it, Mark.
But I will say my favourite line was I had completely forgotten that I had interviewed
you in Reno.
Indeed, I'm not sure I can remember it even now that you've reminded me.
And rather the best I can hope for is that I will now remember that you told me I
interviewed you and so it must have happened.
And I like that.
But yes, also, he pointed out a mistake I'd made at a text, which I might just leave
in because it's all I don't know.
But we'll see.
So deliberate error.
You're just checking to see if people are reading the report properly.
Sort of.
That's what a thing.
And also just a note that you could buy by TAF Trip Report now.
It's a Fiverr if you buy it from my website or it's about £20 if you buy it from Lulu.
And then once you get it, you can put a word in from it as a discount code or website
to get a free copy of the PDF, like one of the oldest structure manuals from a 1970s
computer game.
I was very proud.
That's quite nifty.
End of plug.
Yeah.
By John's TAF report, TAF reports are cool.
Trip reports are cool.
The fan funds are cool.
Have we done anything recently to raise money for the fan funds, boys and girls?
I finished my TAF report, Alison.
We literally just talked about that.
No, we ran a convention.
Sorry, it was intended to be a segue, John.
Oh, were we on?
Were we onboarding people to the discussion about our convention?
Segue.
A segue is a term for an onboarding activity at a podcast.
We ran a convention.
It was good.
I mean, it's going to be a while before I've got my energy back, I think.
The committee all talking to each other still.
I think that's right.
We haven't checked with Steve.
Yeah.
Steve, if you're not talking to us, please write in and let us know.
If there's something we need to wrap up that you know about, you should get in touch.
Yes, we need to.
So we need to
announce the results of the charity split.
So we are giving our excess is going to
effectively going to some charities and then also to fan funds and efforts to run
more punctuations, if we decide that we want to do that.
Alison will make me wash my mouth out with soap at this juncture.
But we are dispersing our funds to the Good Things Foundation, shelter, the
Stephen Lawrence Trust and the swad lifeline.
Each each of us picked a cause and then we asked members to vote on the causes.
And so we will be splitting the muddies between the charities in accordance with
the percentages of the votes.
And because we ran the convention in a very cheap skate sort of way, I think all of
those are going to get a moderate amount of money because it turns out that it doesn't
cost a fiver a head to run a convention in a very cheap skate way.
Yes.
Yeah.
How much do you think it cost us?
Oh, I know the answer to that.
Yeah.
Two little pounds give or take.
OK.
So all in all, I believe we spent 184 pounds and 15 p.
That's all of the things that the committee put in the split wise.
So if there's anything that isn't counted in there, we haven't yet got like the receipts
together and stuff.
But yeah, so under 200 pounds, we will eventually put out some sort of post con thing that
details, you know, what we spent money on and kind of how we did things and why we did
things and what people thought about the things we did.
I was going to do this bright and early on the Monday after the convention, but it
turns out I didn't want to.
So I haven't yet.
I love the fact that John, who had never run a convention before, was kind of after
the con, we will do all these things.
And everyone who had run a convention was what was like.
Traditionally, this does not happen to the extent you think it will, though I have had
less post con slow down after this convention than any other convention I have ever been
involved in by miles.
So I think that's quite good.
I have done activities this week.
I have not been that tired.
I would have had less slow down except that I felt very ill on the Sunday night, which is
in some ways very good because it means it was a proper convention, but in some ways
it was a little bit of a pain because I did not want to feel very ill on the Sunday
night.
You wanted to stay up for partying till after Liz got up.
Liz got up and then regretted having to go to work on Monday morning.
I did.
Liz, what did you think of our convention?
I thought it went quite well.
It was certainly much less work than running a 200 person convention in person would be
because there was just a whole host of stuff we didn't have to bother about at all.
I think it went relatively smoothly.
I don't think we had, which I said, I don't think we had any reports to our listeners
team that I know about.
I don't think anyone came to the committee with any urgent problems.
So in many ways running a two day convention online is much, much easier than running one
in person.
Not that I ever run a 200 person convention.
I did just skip that phase and gone straight to big ones.
200 people, 200 person conventions are reasonably chill in person, but obviously those 200
individuals can have things go wrong in their lives over the course of the weekend that need
the conventions attention and do sometimes.
So there normally are things that do actually go wrong.
You would want you would want slightly more people.
I think that I really noticed that when something did go wrong, you were kind of right at your
desk in the place you could fix it.
Whereas at a convention, it's very common that your committee members need to sort out a
problem at the far end of the hotel.
So so your problem solving consists of stopping what you're doing and going to a different
place and then learning about the problem of dealing with it and then returning to where you
were before at which point something else would have gone wrong.
And I feel that we didn't really that when stuff got wrong, there was always a committee
member right there at their desk ready to sort it out.
That is extremely true.
So for instance, when are you know, we're having a problem with the streaming solution, the
solution is one of the committee logs in from their desk where they are and fixes it.
It's not like if your projector breaks down, you have to go running around to find the
three people who know where the spare projector bulbs are and change the bulb or whatever.
It's more like, Oh, I'll just log in and oh yeah, it's running again.
Fine. So yeah, it is a lot easier from that standpoint.
People are very nice about the convention.
Nobody was horrible about the convention.
That's lovely.
There are of course things we do differently next time.
I think the biggest, I think our program was fine.
But I think the biggest downside to the short lead time was that one of the things you
could do with a longer lead time for a small convention is build interesting program that
takes weeks or months to sort out.
And I think that was harder for us and I think we could have, you know, you could do more
in that space if you'd had more lead time.
That's the only thing.
I'm not sure you could do much more in the other ways by having a long lead time.
But that thing I think you could have done.
So I think, yeah, I think I think there are things we would do differently.
I think next time the thing I would want to try and do is a better job of getting
members information into the database we were using.
That was not particularly trivial to do.
And the way we took payments added a lot of work to our lives that was potentially
not necessary and added stress.
I will say that it reduced stress in the sense that the way we took payments meant
that we didn't have to think about it, it just worked.
And that was very nice.
But what it did mean was that we got hardly any information, which then meant we had a
lot more work to do in other aspects.
I'm hopeful that there would be a way to have it just work with payments and have
it just work with people filling in the membership form.
But that will be something we investigate if we run another one.
Well, stood, I think we could have done a little bit better.
And I think we need to do, we might need to do like a couple of test panels
next time for new wranglers because I was a little bit.
I think there's no substitute for actually actually wrangling a real panel.
We did do kind of workshops prior to the convention, but I think we perhaps needed
to do more, more high stress workshops.
That sounds like a weird thing to say.
But I do wonder whether we needed to more thoroughly onboard our programme ops people.
But yeah, but again, that's something we'd know for next time, I think.
I can mention one that John mentioned, which was that John
thought that having two versions of the air table programme was
wasn't perfect.
And I kind of got what he said, but I'm not.
I'm not sure I agree.
I mean, I think I'm saying I'm sure I don't agree, but I think there's things we could do.
We made the decision to use to publish the programme on air table very, very late
because we'd be kind of looking at other solutions for printing a schedule.
And they were all way complicated and cost money.
I think that's that's not too strong a statement, is it?
Liz or both way complicated or cost money or both.
Yeah, I mean, it's not necessarily way complicated.
It's more that if we are doing everything in the air table and then we have to take
the data out of the air table and put it into whatever other scheduling thing we are using.
Then as soon as you start making changes, you now have to update changes in two places
and that becomes a massive hassle.
You really want to have one central store.
And since the air table was our working programme, it was trivial to update it.
Whereas if we start having some kind of link from air table to shed, say, then we really
need to start working there and changing everything there.
And so that just changes your workflow.
Also money.
And I think we discovered very late that the basic output of air table was an
adequate programme publication for a small convention.
Again, that was not we didn't nobody said they hated it.
So I think that was probably all right.
I thought it worked very, very well.
But the reason I thought the problem I thought it had was that I had conversation
with two or three people through the weekend that they hadn't.
They were not sure why when they went to the punctuation programme,
sometimes it had the links to programme items and sometimes it didn't.
And I think it's one of those things where I completely see it saved us at
all for a lot of time.
And I think I understand why we did it that way.
But I think next time, I think I would want to only ever
publicise the programme in places where only members could see it and maybe have
like a kind of provisional programme on the website with a note saying this
programme might not be up to date, please check for the most recent version in the
discord, just because I think it was confusing to some people that there were
two versions and it wasn't clear why there were two versions or how you got from
one to the other.
And the answer was you didn't, you had to go on the discord and find the other link.
And I just, but it might have been that we could have communicated that better.
It's just something I think we need to be aware of for next time that it could
potentially be a point of pain.
Yeah.
So so my view is that the that having the online programme be correct all the time,
which is what it was correct within tiny, tiny details, all of the time.
Was so useful that that it made up for everything, made up for anything else.
But it would be good to be able to embed the programme in a web page that said,
note this version of the programme doesn't have the links to programme items.
For that, you'll need to go to either your members email or or the discord to
get the version that's got the links because that's a paywall is as far as we
add. But I think having the whole programme on the web is quite good for
people. It's obviously no link.
That ties into what I think we could have done better, which is to have a website
which had everything within it.
So you join through our website, you can then log in and see the schedule and see
the links and get a link to the discord, give us your member information, change
member information, you know, just have one unified website.
And basically, we didn't really have that because we just had a WordPress site,
which was extremely easy for us to handle.
We should say we just had a WordPress.com site.
And what we probably should have had was a WordPress.org site.
But by the time we worked out this, we discovered that you can't move your
URL for 60 days after registering it.
This is like one of these really technical things.
Ironically, the thing is is proposing we should have done would have been much
easier to do on a WordPress.com site than a WordPress.org site because WordPress.com
provides you with all the tools because we were using the WordPress.com membership
scheme. You can make pages that are only visible to members because WordPress.com
is designed around that kind of workflow.
Have we just had a slapping out forehead moment?
No, I think it would have been it would have been so much more admin for
though I think it would because the thing getting our program to people who were
members was easy.
It was it was having a second version of the program that was available to the
public that was hard having members only pages on the website wouldn't have helped.
I don't think that addresses the pain point I saw.
OK, so maybe what you're saying is actually what we should have done is just
had published the program, published the program once for the purposes of getting
people into the convention.
But then yeah, with a with a big banner saying like, please don't take this as
the official program.
This is just the advert.
The official program is in the paywall because I think.
But yeah, but I think these are all things.
The our the reason we didn't do that with the website is because I think it would
have added quite a bit of admin for not much gain.
But I'd be keen to hear from people who disagreed and it's one of the questions
I want to ask in my big feedback form.
Oh, yes, that's what you were going to do this week.
I remember.
I am working on it exists.
I think one of our key issues was we sent people to a lot of places like they went
to the website to join and then they got a link to the discord to log in and then
somewhere in the discord, there was a link to an air table that told you where
the program was and then that sent you to zoom and that sent you to YouTube.
And and I don't if there's a way to just streamline this and make it all kind of
more obvious what the workflow is.
I mean, possibly doing literally everything through discord would have been better.
So you can only get the program through discord about this would have then, you
know, not been friendly to everyone who really doesn't like discord.
But just I think sometimes we were like, well, if you check your email, you've got
a link to the air table, which tells you where you go to the zoom and then when
you're on the zoom, you can then discuss it in the discord.
If you like, it gets a bit like lots of not to platforms on top of each other.
Yeah, I think we could have done a better job of having the current set of places
you might want to go visible at the top of the discord all of the time.
Yeah, I think so it was difficult because I heard people say like, well, there are
a lot of places to go to. So we used primarily three platforms, which was
we using discord for the spine of the convention.
We were using zoom for interactive program items and sort of parties and the bar.
And we were using, well, if you're a panelist, we were using StreamYard.
But if you were a person in the audience, we were using YouTube for the panels.
And I think the thing is that each of those three options represents a solution to a
problem that the other two doesn't solve.
So like discord is persistent in a way that YouTube and zoom aren't.
So it's very useful to have the discord is like the persistent spine of the convention.
Zoom allows much better audio visual chat and social space than discord does.
And YouTube allows much easier streaming.
You can cast it to your TV very easily in a lot of cases.
You get the YouTube chat, which integrates with StreamYard.
So the panelists can I respond to the chat and stuff.
And so each of them had a thing we needed that the other two didn't have.
I think the problem when you start trying to combine them is that you end up finding
that the software that tries to do the things like, so if we came up with a list of all the
things we needed and tried to find a one piece software that did it, I think the problem is
those pieces of software are usually not very good or very expensive.
And the problem we're doing at Fiverr ahead is that is a whole that is a bad choice.
I think that but I think it's something to bear in mind that people did find it too much.
I will also say on top of that that one of the people kept suggesting ways we could make it
easier and every time it's all suggested something so it's just the exact opposite thing to posts later.
So I saw it would be like you could just turn the YouTube chat on and have all the chat and discord.
And then someone was like I'm so glad there's the YouTube chat because I really hate having
the discord open when I watch your panels. And it's like the problem is that you can streamline it,
but I do wonder whether the problem with going to lots of places would be is a bad
problem that we do need to think carefully about. But I do wonder whether people would have
found it more frustrating if we had gotten rid of a place that they enjoyed going in favor of a place
they didn't. Yeah I mean I think giving people a lot of choices for how to interact with the
convention was part of the design philosophy of the convention but we could maybe have done a bit
more about getting that word out to people. I think we need better signposting for sure.
No and I think Liz is entirely right which is even if even if for all the reasons,
even if we think about it really harder we decide that it was inevitable. It is still it was still
obviously a undesirable aspect which if we find a way of fixing we should try to address.
I just wanted to give listeners some context as to why we didn't kind of come out of the gate
having addressed it already if that makes sense. But I think Liz is completely right that.
If you were at the convention and you haven't found it already there's a next time thread in
Discord which was designed to capture your first impressions but you can still post to it at the
moment. I don't you probably still be able to post to it on Thursday. The Discord is not causing us
any problems at the moment. I think we can also take feedback directly by writing to the con or
yeah or messaging any of us. Yes and John is going to do a giant form which is going to send out to
everyone before people have totally forgotten the convention. Yes it will be it will if you haven't
had it by the time you listen to this episode it has gone into your spam folder so please let me
know and I will send you another link. That's a strong commitment John strong commitment.
That is thank you that's good. Rachel Livermore as part of her massive burst of post-colon
enthusiasm before she came down said that her next project was going to be designing a front end
to stitch all of these good free services and cheap services together to make a better
convention experience. So yeah no I hope she's getting on with that but she kind of said it on
about like in the immediate post-ineffable period where she was probably still very excited about
options. No no one would blame her for having a little bit of a breather after a defable con too.
Rachel gave a talk at a convention about conventions which was the same weekend as punctuation
and we will put a link to that talk in the show notes if we are able to find it.
I want to say a little bit more about virtual con because it was a convention about running
virtual conventions kind of as if smoth con had gone virtual but but not smoth con is going
virtual but they're talking about running real conventions because that's what they do.
They are talking a bit about running virtual conventions but this convention I was involved
in the setup of the convention and was obviously very excited about it and then they decided to
hold it on the Sunday of punctuation about which I was not excited at all and blew a big virtual
raspberry but I mean that's not obviously it's not their fault. No but I was sad. I get about it.
And so Rachel did a talk at it and there were several other talks and they are all available
online so if you're interested I suspect other people are not as interested in the nuts and bolts
of running virtual conventions as we are so but we will put that link into the show notes.
I also think that we kind of made the decision that we were going to run everything through
Discord and so we were in Discord planning things and people trickled into Discord but I think we didn't
say, we thought we said this often enough and early enough but we didn't say often enough and
early enough please come to the Discord and get involved. And the second thing I would say is that
running a virtual program for a 200 person convention is not that much less work than running a real
one except the scheduling is easier at the moment because most of our participants did not have a
lot of pressing engagements outside the house right now. So that was a lot easier but it meant that
we, you know, people didn't get involved early enough and so maybe we had a smaller pool of people
who we knew were willing and able to be called on. You have the same problem of if you have a smaller
group of people then you can't really get into the super niche areas unless you know you have the
people for those super niche areas and the really niche discussions and if we got people together
earlier maybe we would have found the five people who are interested in something really
obscure and interesting to get them all together to talk about it. We could have taken a link,
despite the fact that we decided we weren't going to have a guest of honor or anything like that,
we could have taken a link from Mexico's book. We know that science fiction authors are pretty
happy to come along to virtual conventions if you get in touch with them and ask them and we
didn't really do a lot of that and we probably could have done some of that to shift our program
more over to the, we could have invited, we did invite a couple of interesting people but we could
have invited a few more interesting people if again this is a more time thing. I think a little
bit longer to plan would probably have been a benefit. Yes. Yeah and I would end by saying that
I was really happy with the program we had and I saw some really great stuff and I think everyone
who was on it did really interesting things but we could have had a little more time to plan it
and maybe a bit more time to put together the stuff that needed more time to be put together.
Yes having said that our program was about the right size, it was about the size I had envisaged
it being or maybe slightly bigger and it had an almost everything on it was really interesting.
So there's a good question about well where would you cut things? So I realized I forgot
something that we needed to mention in the things that didn't go so well. We didn't sort out a
rotor for manning the persistent bar and the persistent bar didn't persist except at times
when there was someone in there, even there was a scheduled item in it or there was someone in
there persisting it. It persisted very nicely whenever there was somebody to take a chart to look after
it but people would decide to come along see that there was nobody there and go away again
which kind of makes sense. That happens in the real world as well but for next time I would
absolutely staff that bar the whole time. I just have somebody whose job title was bought and
I don't know why I didn't. I think another thing is we had, so for those who weren't on the
committee we had three zoom accounts running Punturation, we had the big zoom which was called the space bar.
We came up with that name about two hours before the opening ceremony so there was a brief period
where not everything said space bar and our messaging was slightly poor but we enthusiastically
embraced it and it was good. Then we had zoom 1 and zoom 2 to run the program items in. I will
say obviously there were some program items that went for quite a long time and started chats but
then if you went for more than about 90 minutes you kind of needed to wind down so that the next
program item in that zoom could come in and start setting up and I do wonder whether there'd be
myelage especially for some of the more conversational items in having just had them in breakout rooms
in the space bar and I do wonder whether that's something we could do next time.
We did put things in breakout rooms in the space bar and we probably should have done more of that.
There is a slight, there's a kind of technical problem which is that you can't
change the names of breakout rooms except by closing the breakout rooms which in practice was fine
because there were times where nobody was in the bar but in principle would be a horrible thing to do.
So in back in the real world hotel rooms, hotel conference spaces have names so we could have said
your item will be at 2 o'clock in x where x is the name of a breakout room within the zoom.
Yes and we could have named them the "We to Bix Breakout" room and another one I don't know,
I run out of steam with that. That felt like one of those jokes that...
Yeah it needs work shopping. Listeners, if you can construct a good joke out of what I just said,
please write it and we'll read it out on the cast. Excellent. Yeah so that does tell us quite
nicely into kind of discussing what we thought went well. I mean I think this now, we need to be
careful because obviously we ran a convention in the sort of way that we would quite like
ventures to happen and so we may be biased. I also don't want it to sound like we're just
massively patting ourselves on the back despite the fact that that is what we will be doing for
the next 10 to 20 minutes. So strap in listeners but basically I think for me it was the closest
we've gotten to a convention that felt like a British convention in cyberspace and in general
I really enjoyed that. I really enjoyed the program partly because I suggested all the program items
I wanted to see and then watched them which is cunning and I recommend it to anyone. It turns
out you just write ideas to the program team and if they're good ideas you get to watch them later.
Life hack. New A. This even works at conventions you're not officially
involved with. I've been doing at East Cods for years, you just just four or five game panels,
hope you don't get put on all of them and then you've got some good panels to go to.
Is grand. I will even extend John's hack for people who don't know. It is possible to fill in a
program questionnaire for a convention and say actually I don't want to be on the program at all
but have you considered doing x, y and z which are all panels that have either A
worked really well in the past or items not panels and I'll talk a bit about that in a minute.
Items that have worked really well in the past or B. Things I've been dying to see and that I know
the ex convention is capable of doing but I haven't yet ceded to convention and that does work very
well in stimulating the thinking of the program team. I mean they may not do it but they may not be
able to do it for reasons you haven't thought of but they might well take your ideas up.
Particularly for a larger convention where there are more spaces on the program.
And yeah so I like the program and I also liked the social spaces and hanging out in the bar and
having drinks and also breakfast really liked breakfast. I thought that worked well and
surprisingly doing park run while voice collected to discord in the pouring rain.
Several people joined discord voice before I set off and joined again after I got back
but it was it was really fun to run through the park like with people even if it was virtually.
Yeah it was it was damn good fun I was a bit I would be a bit worried about it being spectacularly
crap but only quite funny but it was actually super fulfilling so yeah there's a discord
server for it now and everything. So those were my highlights I think. Liz what did you think
worked well about the convention? I just had a nice reasonably low stress weekend I thought
that was good like as far as being convention committee goes I haven't done it that often but it
was for me certainly lower stress than it has been in the past. You stayed up too late.
I did stay up too late but that's because I knew that was going to happen right there's no way
that I'm going to help run a convention which is in a different time zone and only go to like
the six hours of it there are actually during my normal waking hours obviously I was always
going to stay up late but it is still weird that like everyone else is like so I think it was
Saturday night when I had assumed I would go to bed long before the cheese tasting started and I
did not I was still awake and so I had not prepared any cheese and that was a bit sad because everyone
was eating cheese and I did not have any cheese but it was also I think 1.30 so it was probably not
a good time to be eating cheese but I did really like it I found a sort of smaller breakout room
with just a few people and we had a little bit of discussion of cheese and a little bit of
discussion of wine and just a nice friendly chat and I haven't missed those sort of convention
chats with people that I only really see at conventions but this time noticeably
some of my chats were I monitored the big zoom over breakfast and breakfast was me and some Australian
and New Zealand fans that I hadn't chatted to a huge amount in the past and we had a very nice
sort of little breakfast conversation I enjoyed that I enjoyed the sort of crafty
meeting greet partly because people were in like their craft rooms where they had all their stuff
so they could not only show some of their current projects they could show like the things they've
been doing over lockdown because they'd have like the the past 10 projects or whatever
to hand because they were in their houses where you had them so you got more of an idea of what
people had been doing than if it was just sort of a stitch and bitch style one at a convention and
you bring the thing you're working on and show it you could do a bit more of that. I thought
the technical side worked about as well as could be expected which is I think we had
I felt we had remarkably few issues with getting people up and running on stream yard and zoom
compared to what I feared which is that it was going to be like every you know it was going to be
every technical nightmare that anyone has had over the past six months of you know screen sharing
failures and lack of sound and lack of video and lots of always this thing on and is it working
and actually I thought it went pretty well and I think they work quite well I was quite glad we
found stream yard which I found from a recommendation from the roguelike conference where I was reading
up about it because they had that nice mud and they said they use stream yard and it just seems
you're pretty simple to use and you can stream to YouTube and you can stream to Twitch and they
actually recommend streaming to YouTube because the signal degrades nicely so it's a lot easier to
say okay just show me this at low res if your connection is a bit dodgy and my connection sometimes
is a bit dodgy so that was quite crucial to me I think some of the people who are suggesting that
we do more technical things including zoom probably I'm fairly sure we had members who watched things
on YouTube and nothing else and and we probably won't hear as much from them because they're not
in the discord and they're not all the zooms but there are people for whom YouTube is a technology
they understand and zoom and discord aren't are a valid a valued part of especially the British
fan community and I would and I like to think that by having some stuff on YouTube I mean I think at
this point in the cycle of the world everyone can manage YouTube right I mean certainly certainly if
certainly you are not excluding a large part of the bell curve if you if you set up around YouTube
I think that's 100% true and I think it's a good point it's one of the things I'm hoping to find
out with my big evaluation form do you have to be logged into your YouTube account to comment on
YouTube which I think did put some people off commenting on the YouTube yes so they didn't want
their like accounts to be publicly used but then they could come in and comment on discord which
was fine when we had the sort of bifurcated comments going on I mean I will say that it is
possible to have many Google accounts and it is also possible to have within one Google account
more than one YouTube account so I have both of these I have two YouTube accounts on my primary
Google account but no so I will say that I do appreciate there were people who said that they
did what's going on YouTube but that's why we had the discord open and there were people who said
they did what's coming on discord and that's why we had the YouTube open and I think if we had closed
either one the group of people who had been preferring to comment on that one would have been annoyed
at us which is one of the reasons why we didn't close either one I strongly suspect that there are
different people with different priorities who who had strong preferences there and it like it
was a little bit of work for the Wrangler in each panel to keep an eye on both chats but there was
a reason we did it like that so what I think well well I had a lovely time I liked the fact that it
came despite the fact that we gone it's a British convention we're doing a British thing it actually
came closest to being the permanent floating global party off my dreams of stuff that I've done so far
and I do quite want to run a permanent floating global party of my dreams at some point but that
would require a much more global team to run it I but we did in fact have members from Australia
who were propping up the bar at breakfast time and we had members from the west coast of the
United States who were keeping that bar open extremely effectively in the early hours of the
morning and everything in between and that was quite nice it wasn't true that we never closed but
we did have a nice long patch of enjoyment I thought a lot of our individual program items
which we did do some things that you can't do in a real space we had some talks that were
that would have been different difficult to deliver because people were talking about
stuff where they had stuff to had this was something we'd observed from
concealant had some talks where people were talking about something practical that it's
useful to have props to hand and I think that we did some of that we had things like the
trip to the fan museum that everyone loved bits that again you just don't get to do those things
in the physical world we had the collaborative jigsaw I want to shout out was successful beyond
my wildest dreams and I now know of three servers that have acquired collaborative jigsaw since
punctuation so you know that's clearly something that people like
um I really liked that I could find people to chat to it whenever I pretty well whenever I
wanted to chat um I liked the fact that people were very appreciative of the ribbons and I really
liked the fact that um that people noticed lots of people noticed that the ribbons changed to
Sharpie if you joined the convention after five o'clock on friday and somebody even observed it
was probably more work to do a ribbon with Sharpie on it that we was to do a ribbon on
with the the original ribbon font we'd been using which was true so that was fun
um a learning is that I should definitely have done the ribbons a lot greater advance I'm an idiot
um yeah I can't really just do I can't split things everything I think this was good I think
this was bad at the same time I think there's quite a few things where I was like yeah this was great
and we should have really thought about it you know a week in advance of when we did think about it
oh there was loads of stuff that we didn't really think about until two minutes before we did it
several people there's quite a bit of feedback about it would have been useful to have this earlier
and I'm like it would have been useful to have thought of it earlier yeah every time I was all
said like I would have been useful to have more like notice of this I was thinking yeah for us too
like believe me of all the people who are aware of the fact that we could have used a bit more
time to plan we were very aware of that oh but but also because you've because we've not done it before
when you when you're doing the second or subsequent to something you you have a kind of starting point
of all the ideas that other people have had and we did get some ideas um Claire Boothby ran an
amazing treasure hunt for us and I think if you haven't if you haven't done it it's worth going
into discord and seeing all the imaginative and interpretive ways people delivered their treasure
hunt clues because they were they were fantastic and very entertaining um and also Claire Boothby
did a great job Claire Boothby did a fantastic job for us I think pulling in Naspics she used the
code base from Naspics treasure hunt was basically the idea and um and I think that actually showed
gave me a sense of where people were because it because because a lot of the things
asked people to go outside the house you got a sense of how all of our members fit within their
local environment and I would like to I would like to lean into that another time I'd like to see
more stuff that took people outside of I mean I guess we know what people's studies look like now
but actually taking people outside of that space to show their environment yeah so um I think I
think we've talked um probably flog it off about what we will what we liked um but I do want to
note that like from what we've all said it it does sound to me like one of the themes in what we
like was the interactivity like you've both mentioned the kind of the crafting rooms and the social
spaces and the interactive program items quite a bit and and I do think that makes me happy because
one of the things we were setting out to try and do was do something that was a little bit more
interactive than than some things that have been happening previously and I think I hope that we
did manage to do that I mean obviously people whom this was your first online convention won't have
a point of reference but hopefully people who have been to a couple um will have recognized where we
were trying to kind of um encourage that so I hope to be fair we're all people for whom our
model will have worked because we designed it yes yes that has been the 19th episode of the
Octa Thought podcast it is goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
I would say that one of the things I did for the first time at punctuation that I've not done before
this is an indication of how it wasn't as much work as running a real con because often when
you run a real con you don't really do anything at the convention that's not running the convention
um is I played Among Us for the first time which is a social card game social board game yes John
yes it's sort of it's kind of werewolves in space and I was so crap at it how crap at it was I John
you weren't as crap as you thought you were but still quite crap but it was your first time
playing crap I was like I am I am doing a good job of bluffing about how I'm not the imposterer
they were like Alice is the imposter let's spacer and we have one game that lasted for a total of
about two and a half minutes which I think is probably not very much fun for other people
and it reminded me that I don't really like that sort of bluffing game very much um because
as everyone who knows me knows I'm not very good at bluffing I mean yes so I was I was trying to
work out how to come around to maybe saying that out loud without being mean but yes um I think so
for those who haven't heard um so Among Us is a a video game that's been out for a while but has
taken off in popularity during lockdown um it is a kind of combination of a top-down um game about
spaceships and a social deduction game um the problem with games like Blood on the Clock Tower
and Werewolf and the Resistance and other games like that um when you're playing over video or
audio is that obviously when you're not in a room with other people you lose out on a lot of the
um ways that you can tell things about what people are saying from their cues that they're
giving you through body language and through facial expressions and what Among Us does is it replaces
the need to do that with a computer game where you can see what people are doing in the computer
game and you can infer things about their um motivations from the things they're doing in a virtual world
where you have different cues and I think that is the reason it has become so staggeringly popular
in lockdown because it is a game which introduces a layer which makes it a lot easier to play it
remotely um I think in real life you'd still probably want to play Werewolf or something similar
although not everyone loves Werewolf um but yes we were playing that punctuation um a couple of nights
it was basically third row plus like a lot of the people playing gays were third rowers um but like
Alison came along Sandra Bond played with us for a while um and said I know I have a noob but I
just scold you at one point which was great um and like yeah no it was it was actually really good fun
um and it turns out if you have a group of about five people playing games eventually that group
people balloons to about 10 or 15 people playing games um even at a virtual convention um but yeah
no it was really good um I I sort of I had ambitions of playing more complex games but most nights I'd
run out of energy to do anything other than play like little social deduction games which is not a
problem because I love them I'm going to suggest to my friends running a very large party in the
near future that they take one room of their very large party for a particular game that we all
used to play in the bar when we were young which is charades because I believe that zoom is the
perfect environment for playing charades because you can make the person who's doing the charade
be on mute and I'm like you go on mute and and all of those things where people are trying not to
say anything but they inevitably do um and then everyone else can be guessing it can be not on mute
and the person could jump up or down and I think I think that will be I have never tried it but I
am I am going to offer that this is a thing we might try is um and you can use you can use the
private chatter to give somebody the name of a thing to charade as well so the the bar version of
this game just has whoever guesses the charade gets to do the next one and the person who has just
been chararding gives the next person something terrible to charade yeah and I am quite excited
by the prospect for doing this in zoom I think it will be a laugh and also be a social game that
does not require any activity and um yeah and because it's charades people can do yeah it'll be
funny that's my that's my plan so yeah so carol i'd you heard it here first I don't know if carol
and listens to the show that is my my one big regret is that I did not stay up late enough to play
games with you guys but it would have been you would have had to stay up very late I would have
I think I would have had to get up very early he's more accurate so now that people know the format
for a convention we can do things like booking people into the game into run games in the bar
yeah I mean that is something that is something that we definitely could have done um I will say
that when we were playing games this I think it was 4 a.m. your time so I don't think it's one of
those really awkward times where it's not pleasant from either direction um yeah it's not my other end
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud@ancompetech.com
used under a creative commons attribution 3.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep