I think we should just go down the bullets in order, John.
Yeah, no, but that's why I'm proposing a change.
I'd like to move that the discussion of the motion for the change is over the minutes.
No, no, no, no.
All right, 17.
Yes, OK, so let's move.
One.
So this, two, three.
Yay!
That's not setting in the episode, but I enjoyed it a great deal.
That could have cold happened.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Hello, everyone, and welcome to the 50th episode of OctoThought, the podcast for science fiction
and science fiction fandom, which is coming to you on the 3rd of February 2022.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And we're 50.
That's fantastic, isn't it?
It's kind of unbelievable.
What do you think, guys?
I think it's very good that we're 50.
I think it's less good that I don't know what date it is.
So yes, we are 50.
It has been a wild ride.
And as we do the last episode of OctoThought, I just want to tell all our listeners that
we really appreciate you being here with us.
We've, like, actually just been planning the next three, John.
John, what are you about to say that means there will be no more OctoThought
stops ever?
I mean, is it that you're not going to edit anymore because that would be an end, Dr.
Thor?
No, we'll just have Liz edit it.
I'll just be like, I'll throw the files over to Liz and say, Liz, can you do a quick
edit to then four months later?
I'll go ask that edit coming along, Liz.
Oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, I'm tired.
Shot's very much fired.
I mean, I did not intend to start this argument, which will end the podcast.
Like, Joe, I appear to have done.
We had some letters of comment.
And first up was Bill Burns sending us an email entitled, "What is a fanzine?"
And he went into some details on how he and Nick Ferry originated that definition of fanzine.
It was first published in the incomplete register for the 2018 van awards.
Bill has kind of accepted the summary of the chain of emails, but I don't want to put
it in the show, no, it's just in case because I kind of feel like it would go quite well
in one of Nick's fanzines or maybe even a fanzine by Bill.
So, but it's very good.
Thank you for writing in, Bill.
It was very interesting.
Yeah, even if you disagree with people, it's nice to see kind of their reasoning and
how they get to that position.
Well, it's the fan nature, isn't it, to disagree in entertaining ways?
We tried to hold that a lot to Thorpe, don't we, guys?
We do.
We also got an email from Chris Garcia and he says, "John has a tedious NPC hat.
It would go very well with my me and my thousands of friends won a Hugo in 2019/ and yes, it
would, Chris."
If you need that decorating for you, I guarantee you that I will misuse the Hugo Awards logo
and get a cease and desist and promise to do it again and do it almost exactly the same
way but slightly differently and they're up tie up the NPC for years.
Sorry, guys.
Chris, if you do have that/please send us a photo.
And then he talked a little bit about news resolutions.
He doesn't commit himself to resolutions just because his calendar is obsolete.
Most years he just tries to do the same thing.
Watch more wrestling, put out a few issues of various things and record a bunch of podcast.
When you're as vague as he is, it's hard not to meet your goal.
That is a good philosophy.
So Peter Sullibar said, "You're all fluent enough in management speak to know that New
Year's resolutions that I'd like to achieve but don't get too fast if I don't have to
be referred to these days as "stretch goals" and "I just wanted to say that I can't do
that because I have stretch goals which involve me standing up every hour and stretching."
Is this because your Apple Watch instructs you to do that?
Pretty sure John also has stretch goals?
Liz, do you have stretch goals?
No, I find that I naturally get out of my chair and stretch every hour when I need a
no cup of coffee.
We have a rule in our house that if Spania is not allowed to bring me coffee because otherwise
I would never get out of my chair and stretch.
And that is, I think, a good rule.
It is what I would call a life hack.
Yeah, no, no.
We have a rule in our house which is that Stephen is going to bring me a coffee halfway through
this podcast otherwise I'm going to fall asleep in the second half of the podcast.
I mean, you know, different strokes for different folks.
Let's try it out and see if the listeners notice.
Hahaha.
I heard the clipping in my earphones so that is going to be sorry listeners.
If that doesn't normalise down, I was loud laugh.
The Dave Coxen writes in to ask us, well, he asks us two questions.
Firstly, he asks whether he can follow us on Goodreads.
And so yes, anyone who would like to can follow us on Goodreads and I've put links
in the show notes and Alison and I are also on Letterbox, Board Game Geek and Untapped
if you'd like to see what we're watching, drinking and playing.
And so yeah, feel free to follow us on there.
Dave also asks us probably more importantly what style of beer and maybe even sub-style
of beer you'd go for as a threesome which will require us to agree on something which
might be tricky.
Um, milk stout.
I am partial to a milk stout.
Oh, I do like a good milk stout actually.
There we go.
Hey.
[Music]
Octa Thorpe Podcast Corner.
Oh, I would just thought Podcast Corner which is a feature I just invented is basically I
quite like Alison telling us about Hugo Girl last week, last fortnight on the podcast.
And so I thought I would tell you about what I've been listening to over the past couple
of weeks which is the Caribbean SF podcast, a podcast about all things science fiction,
fantasy, horror and folklore coming from the Caribbean.
It's just a really well done, really interesting podcast.
It's always entirely interviews with different authors and creators from the Caribbean.
A couple of episodes I will recommend is I listened to the one with Karen Lord and they
talk about, she wrote a story called The Plague Doctors before the current pandemic came out
but which does have a lot of resonances with the current pandemic and so that was a really
interesting thing to listen to.
There's also an interview with an author called Brandon O'Brien and it is about his poetry
chat book, Can You Sign My Tentacle?
Which is about hip hop and the Thulu mythos which are two things that I did not imagine
would make for like a good topic for poetry but it's really good and he kind of gets into
how like he's using this kind of the hip hop kind of as a vehicle to you know interrogate
the Lovecraft mythos.
It's interesting, it's well produced.
It's about topics in science fiction that I am not completely aware of and so it's given
me some good book recommendations as well so I recommend giving it a listen.
Yeah, I was hoping to get a chance to listen to that before this weekend but I picked the
Brandon O'Brien one, it's really interesting and I then went and bought his poetry chat
book which is like two quid on Amazon.
So eBooks have been great for poetry chat books because the poets weren't getting any
money when Faber and Faber sold you their chat book for 12.99 but you were thinking
that 12.99 was a bit too much for a chat book but £2 is fun.
There we are, I will take, I thought I'd already deleted that but I might be, right there we
are, I found it, good, right, Nino, ooh but they have an interview with Malcolm Alder
and I like Malcolm Alder and I've never heard of Brandon O'Brien but I do like Cthulhu's
so.
Yeah I would recommend you listen to it.
Tentacles, like tentacles, like a bit of tentacle.
Oi and indeed Oi.
Thank you Liz, I will listen to the episode with Brandon O'Brien because it mentions
Cthulhu's and I like Cthulhu's.
We have convention corner.
Conventions have been postponed so redemption has been postponed by a year, it was going
to be, it was going to be this month as you're listening to the podcast listeners but it
has been postponed to February in 2023 and court flu pang loss has been postponed to
October 2022.
I am a little bit worried that the big COVID numbers we've seen in winter the last couple
of years might also recur in time to ruin redemption next year but it is true that we
only have two years of data and so it's very difficult to make a pattern.
I mean just about draw a line but a line of best fit or a model is not yet possible and
so maybe it will be fine and court flu pang loss is postponed to October which Alison
thinks is sensible.
Yeah, now I have the exact opposite argument which is that court flu as we remember is
the only science fiction convention that managed not to miss the year due to the pandemic
because it just managed to slip a court flu in immediately before the pandemic for people
who weren't worried.
They got to go to college station in Texas and then it slipped in another one last October
because it turns out you can have conventions in that period between kind of September and
November and I went to three last year plus of course, this gone happened in December
and I'm hoping that the same thing will happen this year so I say move to the autumn because
I think it's got a better bet for working for you than moving a year.
I've been looking at an answerable and answerable is full of stories of people delaying their
convention either to 2023 or to later in 2022.
I think the saddest story on the answerable list is Chillicon which was due to be 63,
19th April 2020 was postponed first to August 2020 then to January 2021 then to March 2022
and has now been postponed again.
The last we've heard of PicoCon is that they're still planning to run in person in early March
2022.
ICSF which is the organization that holds PicoCon are aiming for an in person convention on
the 5th of March.
Their argument is that they might as well plan for in person because it's much easier
to switch from in person to online at the last minute than the reverse which is true
and also they do everything at the last minute anyway so you know.
I worry slightly that if we say well October is probably going to be better than February
which it probably is but I think we honestly don't know.
The problem is that then everyone will try and postpone themselves into October or November
and we'll end up with this kind of crunch around the autumn.
I can see why conventions are like okay we're just going to postpone for a year because
that means we can keep our regular weekend which is the time you know we know our regular
attendees don't have a huge number of clashes when our staff have time to work on it in
the preceding few months that kind of thing.
So I think it is in some ways a lot you just say okay we're going to bump it by year then
bump it by six months and I think bumping to the pre-Christmas week for WorldCon probably
did have knock on effects other than the fact they end up unfortunately in right in the
middle of another COVID wave but I bet there were people who traditionally go to WorldCon's
who could not attend just because of timing.
I think you're probably right there Liz.
I mean especially with a small con as well where you may have like a limited pool of
staff if someone say actually October is no good for me because that's the start of
academic year or something like that then you could have a big gap in your staffing.
You may well be thinking Bob Pickers how all this pertains to the EasterCon and I think
we're going to pick that up next time we record and pontificate about the EasterCon a lot at
that point and maybe future Eastercons because there's lots of stuff coming out that we're
learning about what people are thinking about going to in-person conventions.
The fan awards are not moving they're going to be on March 20th and they're going to zoom
so even though golf flu was moved that's going to be a zoom event and when we have the link
we will I don't know if we will let you know I think probably it's one of these things
where if you know you know and if you don't ask one of us.
That's me because I won't know that's John or Alison.
If you ask Liz Liz will text us and we will answer.
Yeah it will work just in there really.
Sounds good.
I hope the zoom event will be the time that's appropriate for UK people as well as West Coast
Americans because it's very easy for things that are timed for the West Coast to not suit
UK people very well being as they're in the middle of the night.
And vice versa.
So I want to talk a bit about the terrible decision of the fan award administrators to
scrap best website because I think the TAF free eBooks page which we will put we will
link to is well worth everyone's time to go and have a look at.
I have spent some of this week reading True Rat which is one of the books on there and
there's all sorts of cool and interesting stuff if you have any interest about what fans have
been writing about over the last hundred years or so.
There's a lot of stuff on there and a lot of it is very good and very funny.
We're all free donations to TAF encouraged but it should win best website except apparently
the fan awards are scrap best websites so boo bring back best websites so I can vote
for the TAF eBooks page.
We're going to talk a little bit about self promotion today.
This is something that has become very common in the Hugo award electorate people putting
up eligibility posts and talking about kind of what they've done that's eligible and
kind of not quite plugging their work but making people aware of their work depending
on.
I think there are probably people who think people are plugging but there's a spectrum
of opinion as we'll get into and one of the things that that does is potentially shake
up the odd category where the same things tend to win quite a bit and that kind of gets
to the difference between awarding the objectively best thing in a field versus the thing that
has caught the imagination at the moment in time.
So Alison do you want to start on self promotion and then we can kind of spin off your robust
opinions?
Well I'm Alison Scott and here's a list of everything I've done this year that's eligible
for the Hugo awards.
Oh I think I'm eligible in seven categories.
Seven?
Good Lord.
No obviously not.
I'm eligible for best novel.
Are you?
I contain at least a hundred thousand words and I am fictional.
I have written more than 40,000.
Are you fictional?
That would explain a lot.
So I wanted to start here by kind of expressing the traditional British view on self promotion
and the reason I'm doing it as the traditional British view is that I've kind of moved a
little way from this.
So this is where I would have been about ten years again.
Oh what?
You mean there's an award that I might know I don't have anything to say about that.
No it would be it would be mad because obviously there are all these many better things than
me that have been nominated in this space or that are eligible and you should go and
vote for them.
And what you'll hope to have well it's very kind of you but really I don't think you should
and I certainly wouldn't be voted for myself and oh oh we've won.
That's very, oh that's so very kind.
It never occurred to me that we might have won this.
So you know you don't self promote, you don't omit even if pressed that you think what you
do is good and is worthy of an award and if people nevertheless say it's worthy of award
you kind of deny it wholeheartedly and you certainly don't vote for yourself and you
don't encourage anyone else to vote for you and you dampen down any tendencies that you
see amongst your intimates that they might be running a campaign for you.
That feels like a very traditional British attitude.
That's where I was 10 years ago.
That's probably not one I have come across.
Like I think that is more like I think the attitude I have come across is slightly more
towards well I'm not going to go out and tell everyone to vote for it but if you ask
me I'll say yeah I think I did a good thing and if you want to vote for it that's good.
Kind of attitude.
Oh no.
When when pressed.
When pressed I might admit actually I think this thing I did is alright probably and if
you liked it that's very nice you know that kind of.
But that's kind of where I am now.
So I wanted to go a bit further over to that because definitely how I was brought up is
very much in line with that is and I think the thing I wanted to say about it is that
it's rooted in a world in which everyone knows who the good chaps are and what they've done.
So it's a very it's a it's a model that comes from privilege because it assumes that you
can survey the field and have a good sense of all the stuff that is good out there which
for the hugos and even to be honest for the fan awards is manifestly not true.
So we need a new model.
This ties into something I've thought for a while which is that I think that the distaste
for self-promotion comes with it a implicit opinion that things that have tended to win
awards are things which are deserving of winning awards in that in the last kind of maybe sort
of sort of I would argue and I don't know maybe my my view of the history here is is
is deficient and I'm sure you do both chip in if that is true.
But I think I think self-promotion is getting more common especially in the hugos but in
general in the field and that has been happening maybe over the last 15 or 20 years particularly
would that do you think that's a fair statement or do you think I'm off base there.
I got into a row with John Scalsy about this.
So old man's war when was that guys.
2004 I think.
Yeah so that's nearly 20 years ago and I think that was the point at which I was kind
of like I got into row with him because I was basically channeling Britain and he was
like no no it's completely fine to say what's good and he was right and I was wrong and
so that's 20 years really 17 years.
2005 when the Hugo in 2006 I was a year out so so about 15 or 20 years excellent and so
I think I think I can see why people have this to stay for self-promotion because what
it does is it means that the people with the loudest voices have the most power in controlling
the conversation and that is not always a good thing.
Having said that prior to self-promotion I think what was mostly affecting the conversation
and kind of where the power was vested was to a large extent gender and ethnicity in
that a lot of the Hugo winners before kind of 2000 are predominantly white males and
people who are privileged enough to have been able to be on the ballot before because
it means that if you don't have the ability to self-promote the only way of coming to
the attention of the electorate is to win the Hugo and what that means is that people
who have already won the Hugo's are much more likely to win more Hugo's than people
who haven't and so I think self-promotion is a good way of trying to dismantle that
power structure of kind of what has gone before and bring in a new power structure.
Now that power structure also has privilege in it it just has different privileges in
it and I'm not saying it's necessarily perfect but I do think that it does a better job
of surfacing diverse voices than the old paradigm did and I think it is not a coincidence that
in the last certainly in the last five years but I think starting about 15 years ago you
did start to see more and more diverse works when Hugo's and that's part of why we had
the reaction in 2015 of the Sadpuppy and that whole frick heart was because that was
beginning to really gain steam and begin to anger the people who had had that power before.
I do think in general I am a fan of the way that self-promotion has opened the field up
a bit now I am very British listeners so I don't self-promote.
I think we might be talking about two separate things here which is I see self-promotion
as promoting your own works is one thing but self-promotion as promoting your own works
specifically for awards is a separate thing. Every author now has to promote their own
works it is kind of the expected thing I think the new authors will have Twitter feed
they will guest on podcasts and so on so I don't think I'm so much talking about that
as a specific thing of saying this is what I wrote this year and it is eligible for a
Hugo in best level. I post Opto-Talk to Ephranzines Facebook Twitter file 770 two discords and I
have a reminder every two weeks to do that and I think that is probably self-promotion
in the sense that I think I want people to know that I'm doing a podcast and if they would like
to listen to it they can. So when I say I don't self-promote I very much mean in the sense of
I don't say I'm eligible for a Hugo award because that's not my jam but I do tell people I do a
podcast so I think the one you said about authors I'm completely like yeah authors should talk about
their books grand the thing I think I was talking about more is the awards side.
I'm going to follow up with that I mean it's not we're not really the controversial thing isn't about
saying is it about marketing right it's not about saying oh I have a podcast and I'm going to make
try and make sure that wherever I am on the internet I mentioned the fact that I have a podcast
that people might like if I think I'm in the sort of community that might enjoy what we do here I'm
going to try and tell them about the podcast I don't think that's that's not self-promote it's
not in the same way of you know it's not like the author who who who stacks their books up in front
of their space in the panel and whenever I asked a question says well in my book X I did Y I don't
you know you could go too far even in the marketing line but in terms of eligibility for awards I
think that we're primarily saying is it sensible when it comes to award time to promote a desert.
Yeah now I just wanted to clarify what we were talking about and then my question is I think
you can say that like the timing of people becoming more open about their eligibility and more open
to kind of promoting their own eligibility for awards probably does coincide with award sets of
nominees and finalists becoming more diverse but I'm not sure how much of that is actually
kind of causative as opposed to just a correlation but I basically mellowed a lot and I'm like okay
if you want to promote your Hugo eligibility that's fine but it almost never prompts me to actually
vote for something because I'm going to vote to nominate for things that I have read and
light it's more effective if I get told about something earlier on so I can go and seek it out
and read it if it sounds interesting to me if you say I did this thing and it should go eligible
you know probably that's not going to make much of an influence on what I actually know and
I invoke for there are ways to do this that are more objectionable and there are ways that are
less objectionable or the less objectionable ones may in fact be more effective depending on
what it is that you are telling people about. In general the stuff I nominate for the Hugos is
not stuff that I saw someone on Twitter say oh I am eligible because I did this thing because usually
I am already aware that they did the thing. In some cases it is useful for instance if you are a
short story writer it is actually quite useful to do an eligibility post where you're like these
ones are the novelettes because that is helpful I do appreciate that and even if you're not a big
fan of self-promotion that's just numbers folks numbers are grand. I like the general trend of people
being more open to talking about what they have done regularly and often on their you know Twitter
feed to blogs or whatever on the grounds and if I'm following you it's probably because I'm
interested in your work and so I think that is good to try and raise my awareness and remind me
oh yeah you did you know your book came out this week and maybe I like to go and pick it up or
your book is out and pay back this week and maybe I'd like to go and check it out but the specific
eligibility posts I just sort of you know usually drift over and don't pay much attention to.
It's all very well saying here's what's eligible but you do have to be pushing it to
an open door to some extent if you say oh actually you know that night in the pub where I ranted for
93 minutes without drawing breath that's eligible for best dramatic presentation that is I feel like
that's not necessarily the best use of eligibility post. Not nominating your pub
rant, Alison. I'm hurt now. People have nominated worse. Got them. The other thing that's really useful
is when you've got someone who writes a series and they're like actually not not eligible this
year because I've not written enough new words since the last time I got nominated and that is
also quite useful and again like that that gets back to Alison's point about pushing it an open
door like I'm not going to care whether or not your series is eligible this year unless I was
already thinking of nominating it but what I might do is realize you are writing a series
and end up reading it. But also that thing where you're like oh my series not eligible this year
but it yeah because I haven't written less words that's a bit like going oh no this chap was ahead
of me at the bar. Yeah no it is. You're doing it to the hopes that you'll get surfed at. Yes
getting back to what I said right at the beginning about the things that win being the most effective
form of promotion. Most of my maybe not most of my favorite authors but certainly like a chunk of
the people I read in the field I read because I saw the one a Hugo ballot and now I follow their work.
So for instance I got into NK Jemisin's fiction because the 100,000 kingdoms was in the Hugo
voter packet in 2011 maybe and like I'm sure that that's not true for everyone but it's definitely
true for me and Ditto, Nettie or Corifor like I discovered their work through the Hugo
voter packet Martha Wells you know a lot of people and so and so even with this uptick in self-promotion
that the most effective way of getting your name out there is still to be on the ballot.
So two things both from last episodes the first is that this is why the long list is such a good
place to find interesting things because the things that don't quite get on the ballot are often
amazing and actually getting to learn about those creators and what they're doing is often more
exciting than seeing the same names that are actually on the ballot for the sixth time so there's that
and the other thing is that we talked a little bit last time about the practice of fan winners
recusing themselves for a year and I think that's kind of very very good for helping break that
sense of I will vote for the things that I am that I am used to voting for. That sense of we can
break up the category a bit just by just by spiking ourselves for a year to get people to think about
the broader category is quite good in this regard. Yeah and this is of course a form of self-promotion
because the people they're now magnanimous in addition to all their other virtues. Indeed one
and the other thing is that like so I got two comments on that which is firstly I think my
point about self-promotion being good because it helps to break up the established pool of people
who make it onto the ballot. I think the people who match that by also recusing themselves when
they have won or when they have run one like several I think those go hand in hand I think
if you are self-promoting and then you just win the Hugo year after year after year and never say
actually let's let someone else have a go that is a sign that you are self-promoting for the wrong
reasons because I think self-promotion is great because it makes everyone more aware of what's there
but I don't think it should be a tool for like dominating the field if that makes sense and so
especially and I'm really sorry to uncanny I subscribe to uncanny I like them very much
but especially uncanny I'm like you see the eligibility process and it's like but you guys
you clearly just want more rockets on your mantle piece and I find that understandable on a personal
level but I don't think it's good for the field and so I really do wish that that they would recuse
themselves uh I'm gonna keep banging this drum apparently. Part of the other thing about self-promotion
is and maybe this is unfair because um fire do great work but it's also you get into self-promotion
where fire ran a convention and then after that convention won best pro-scene and obviously the
convention was also nominated for best-related work and didn't win and so there's an element here
where you're beginning to see people do things in different arenas and that kind of feed back into
into promoting their works in kind of their more established categories I think and that's quite
interesting um yeah so I would say it would be it would be strange for uncanny to recuse
themselves at this point I think because they didn't win I think it makes more sense to recuse
yourself just after you won I think it's weird to recuse yourself after you he didn't win. True that.
That's fair. I mean I will I and I take I take your point on like fire having a convention but I
mean that's a valid way to to show people your magazine is out there and oh yeah I might even
say that we ran some conventions and possibly picked up more listeners for our podcast because
we gave ourselves a live recording in the middle of it so look right we did that because we didn't
have any better ideas for program on a Sunday morning list and you know it um also I don't
think we did put live recordings in either of our conventions did we because we were busy running
the conventions I thought we did a live opt-off for punctuation too we did do a live opt-off
for punctuation too. So dear. We did do it on Sunday morning you you suffer it so effectively you have
for forgotten yourself promoted yourself. Self-promoting bastards. I was also going to say that the
Hugo Award eligibility spreadsheet as mentioned on this podcast before is also excellent for those
questions of how many words are there in this story or is this particular magazine actually eligible
under the you know arcane rules for determining what percentage of your income makes you a semi-prosine
and so on and also for best series which I find to have very confusing eligibility rules.
And here's a little plug for lady business because Renee does a ton of work making all that happen.
Indeed. So I'm quite happy to see that out there because I know if someone else has gone and like
calculated how many words were in these two new novels and is this thing eligible and best series
and they share it with everyone else and then I don't have to go and try and do word counts on
things. This may be a sign that we should reform some of the Hugo rules. Oh no wait that's a separate
podcast isn't it? I think I will just say I didn't mean to imply that I thought fire was like
I think if your form of self-promotion is running a convention that brings a community together and
highlights a bunch of great work and discussions of the genre like that that is a fantastic way
to self-promote like 10 out of 10. I agree that uncanny shouldn't have recused themselves given
that they didn't win but also I don't think fire should have recused themselves after winning either
just because I think that would just mean it went immediately back to how it was for the last five
years and so I think there is an interesting dynamic there which is I like the winners in
best fanzine recusing themselves because best fanzine has been a vibrant category that has
been swapping around a lot but I'm glad fire didn't recuse themselves because I think it will be good
if fire acts to break that category up a little bit and so like my thoughts they're actually
quite complicated but I completely agree that recusing yourself when you don't win that that
would be a weird flex well we didn't win so we're not playing anymore would be very much how it
came across and that would be bad we have taken our ball away exactly yeah and that and throw the
game across the table yeah I understand why they didn't do that I can see you can get into a weird
loop though you might get into a weird loop where something wins and recuse itself you know thing a
wins recuse themselves for a year thing be wins because themselves for a year thing a wins again
you know I believe this is how boxing championships work oh is that a left field there's a lot of them
because essentially they they carve it up a little bit so that every so they have six different
world champions it's okay there's also a thing going on where people who maybe don't have the
chops self-promote very aggressively and even having said that I think self-promotion is quite
good and useful and eligibility person quite good and useful it's possible to overdo that
quite a lot sometimes and people should watch out for it yeah one thing I actually like is when I
see someone I know on my Twitter feed retweet someone else's eligibility post because presumably
they mean I think this is a thing a wider audience should see and so that kind of gives it a layer
of extra not only does the person who wrote this say yes eligible I'd love it if you would vote for
it but someone else also thinks it's great and you should you should look into it so that's pretty
nice that may be implicit so of course one form of self-promotion that isn't self-promotion at all
is the fanfans where what you do is you run for a fan fund but you get a slate of nominators
before you run for your fan fund in fact in many cases as in this one your nominators may have
pressed you to run and then your nominators go around saying that you are an excellent person
who should win the fan fund and in this case I want to say a little bit about Anders Hompstrom
who is running for TAF this year there are four candidates for TAF for they're all great
but I am one of Anders nominators and I think you should all vote for him and I kind of struggled
with this a bit because I kind of spent a little while going well why should everyone vote for Anders
it's because he's a great bloke isn't it and that's not you can see that might not be enough to sway
your your voting but in fact he is an extremely interesting and gregarious chap who just makes
friends very easily all over the world wherever he goes and that is a reason why as a representative
for fandom he obviously does a ton of actual fanak in Sweden none of which I've personally
experienced because I've never been to Sweden but wherever he goes he makes friends with everybody
and gets to know lots and lots of different people and he would be a marvelous ambassador for
European fandom in that sense and that's really what fandom what TAF is all about so you know if
you're in North America please vote for him and if you're in the UK or Europe please vote for him
and yet everyone please vote for Anders for TAF that's not self-promotion that's Anders's promotion
Anders will be a very good TAF winner should he win but I am casting my first preference vote
for fear kalston who will introduce the entire of north america to dill chips this is not wrong
so north americans which is more important to you dill chips or beer why not both i mean you know
i don't know what happens in the taffrels if there is a straight tie i assume you flip a coin but i
don't know i could look i could look it up but someone should write a lock instead so i'm not
going to octa thought listeners we wonder what happens if there is a straight tie no actually
sorry no there's a better way of doing this if there's a straight tie in the taffcom test what
happens is each of the two people who have tied chooses a five person football team and a football
match is played in the gardens of the hilton metropole at bermingham and that is how it's decided that
is fact and you would have to write in to dissuade me that it wasn't on the subject of promoting
selves who are not us professor esta mccallum stewart is having her in nor'grill professorial
lecture at the university of staphaiture and that lecture is on dungeons and dragons at 50 and it is
being streamed online and you can get tickets for free it is the same day that i'm going to go see
the book of mormon allegedly in a theater although i don't know whether that will be postponed again
but i will be there with bells on i'm very excited i am going to be listening to esta's
thing you'll probably be able to tune in afterwards to her talk so if you can imagine me when i was 10
which is quite a long time ago and i just learned of the existence of a new game called
dungeons and dragons and it was in a magazine so i didn't actually get to play it with anyone
i was just very excited about it but if you imagine that somebody had handed me a science fiction book
which opened up with oh i i i was a student and i was late for my lecture i logged into the
computer and there on the video screen in front of me appeared the pink head frame of my
video game professor of video games dr esta mccallum stewart she said right i hope you've all
been studying hard because this is the lecture on dungeons and dragons
that would have provided every bit of future sense of wonder i could ever have possibly imagined
whatever anyone's like we don't live in a good enough future i i just want to just want to point
them to the fact that we have a professor in professorial in all your lecture online on dungeons and
dragons at 50 and i am very excited by a female professor of gaming and that is just like unbelievably
wonderful so um yeah in her spare time she she is also the vid chair of class good 2024 hi guys
and there is a link in the show notes it's at 6 p.m on the 28th of february 2022 so it will be late
for liz gosh wow oh boy oh boy oh boy did i not say that bit i mean you can watch my in order
or doctoral lecture online but it is not about dungeons and dragons so it is there actually
when you do your in order or professorial lecture online i will come and watch it but i might play
halfstone at the same time that is fair we are on the bsfa long list and so that means at least
one person has nominated us for the best non-fiction thing at the bsfa awards so thank you very much
to whoever that person or persons were and yeah bsfa members are now able to vote for the things
that they want to be on the shortlist and then the shortlist will be voted on at easter con and
easter con and bsfa members can vote on those awards there and they are presented at easter con
so um yes if you're a bsfa member you should go and vote uh you shouldn't necessarily vote for
us but you should definitely vote for things thank you to our fam thank you to whoever thought
that oct thought was non-fiction when as we've established i'm a novel you're novel
and not really i'm another white bloke doing a podcast how novel can i be i'd give myself a two out of ten
right so one of the things that happened in the real news this week is um the vibes boots index
and i wanted to talk a little bit about it because it is relevant to i guess science fiction being
relevant which is that jackman roe who is a poverty campaigner here observed that poor people are
paying more for stuff than everybody else and the poorer you are the more of your money you pay for
stuff that you have to have necessities and the more the faster the cost of those necessities is
currently rising in the uk and um spoiler it's about to get a great deal worse over the next few
months um and that this was affecting poor people much more than rich people and that the current
price index is used in the united kingdom do not properly reflect that and it our office of national
statistics said yeah they're right that's the case and jack said i am going to start a new index that
will more accurately reflect what real people are paying for food so that we know how much these
prices are rising in a time when they're about to rise a lot and i want to call it the vibes boots
index after terry pratchett's observation that if you're poor you can't afford to buy boots that will
last any amount of time whereas if you're rich you can buy but boots that will last much longer
than this applies to many things not just boots and the pratchett estate said yep we're very happy
with that off you go so that's what it's going to be called and well done sir terry for accurately
identifying this in a way that really resonates with a lot of people it's not a new observation
but i think he made it a lot clearer and well done jackman roe for highlighting this problem
in uk society and boo to the government can i say that boo to inequality and or i think i'm very
much on the um side of the vibes boots index that benefits rather than doesn't and so i think it is
good that people are drawing attention to this i'm glad that people are talking about the cost of
living as it pertains to the people for whom it really matters which are the people who don't
have a little money and can't really afford stuff yep
uh and then shall we do picks remember that self-promotion thing at the beginning of this year i said
on facebook tell me about a good book that was published in 2021 and lots of people gave me
suggestions which i am now trying to get hold of copies of without buying because i am a cheap
skate and one of the ones that was suggested was that graham slight said oh there's a kind of very
big and grand sf novel called the actual star by monica bern and it's great and this is you
will like it and um i went i said oh i looked at her but i thought oh that sounds like exactly my
sort of thing and i looked at my library and it said you will get it in approximately 24 weeks which
is after the hugo nominations close and then um there was a tweet which we will link to with the
show notes from monica saying if you're a hugo voter and you would like to read my book please get
in touch so she sent me a copy so i've now read it and it's fantastic it is a magnificent book really
really enjoyed it i'll say a tiny bit about it which is it is three linked stories one of which
is a historical novel um with totally imaginary characters rather than a historical novel about
real characters set a thousand years ago in um a main civilization um which is now in belise
and um a strand that is set is a contemporary novel about somebody travels to the same location
and a set that is set and a novel that is set a thousand years in the future um in a new utopia
society where nobody stays or very few people stay anywhere very much but people travel around a
lot and come together temporarily and it's a very interesting society so you've kind of got she
intended to do it as a three novel series but was persuaded i think entirely correctly to
intertwine all of these novels and there are many um points of commonality between the three stories
and it's all comes together in an ending which i think she more or less lands um obviously the
problem with these are hugely ambitious novels is quite hard to land the ending i've got a couple
of it's out of trigger warning for cutting for self-harm at the front of the book so there is that
because it's actual ritual cutting as part of the um societies and there is there is not but might
also be trigger warnings for a whole host of other um fairly extraordinary scenes there's quite a
lot of a lot of the thing this novel is doing is making you think feel different things and and
it does that quite well with some quite shocking scenes um it is quite hard to read one of the
things that people come up with is they say oh this is more like literary fiction than most sf and
it definitely is so it's kind of got the those literary fiction books which people say oh these
are really really good but the actual science fiction bits of it are a bit rubbish it doesn't
have that the actual science fiction bit of a solid um really enjoyed it um it'll be on my
balance unless i read five better 2021 novels so well done Monica for self-promoting it exactly
the right time your description your description is interesting because it it sounds quite a lot
like cloud atlas by david mitchell which i hugely enjoyed so i'm looking forward to reading the
actual star but that is also an sf no work and is also literary so it kind of has a lot of those
same hallmarks so like i i really loved cloud atlas and so i am i am excited to read the actual star
and i also have my copy from uh monica and as i say we'll put a link in the show notes um i would say
that the author it totally reminded me of was because it as well as having the sense of ritual
place it also has some ritual objects and it reminded me of alan garners work in terms of
evoking that sense of place through history which is something that i'm very interested in um on the
subject of books that stick the landing my pick for this episode is leviathan falls by james sa
kori this is the ninth book in the expanse series and i really really liked it i thought it did a
fantastic job of wrapping all of the different plot strands up there is one more book in the series
to come but that's like a compilation of all of the short fiction that they've written in the
universe uh so i will be picking that up at some point the one thing i found really interesting
is how the end of the nine book arc is very different to the end of the tv series which ends
at the end of book six and it makes sense because the tv series ends very much in the same way as
book six but book nine kind of does a lot to kind of manipulate that ending and kind of i don't know
i don't know whether it subverts it necessarily but like i really found it interesting comparing
and contrasting the two given that i kind of experienced the two endings very close together
but yeah i really enjoyed it well worth well worth reading the nine books and um and yeah
i am glad that they managed to kind of get to the end and and bring it to a close you know it's not
often that you read a nine book uh series and it actually ends without like the author's dying and
need to employ brandon sanderson so uh ten out ten for that it's that three episodes in a row
that we've had the expanse as one of the picks can we carry on for managing to bring it up every
couple of weeks for the rest of the year because that will be quite funny well i've got another
seven books to read and you've got another like 150 episodes so maybe more like 50 i think
let's you know i'm a sixth way through it so so baby how's the expanse had the best series you go
yeah the expanse won best series two years ago i think which i think was richly deserved and
exactly the sort of thing that that award uh should be being awarded to does that mean it's out of the
running forever yeah you can't it things can only win best series once so if it lo if it had lost
it would come back into play but because it won it's not in play because otherwise miles more cozy
can would just win best series for the rest of time yeah she's not right they went that great speed
anymore though i mean she's only written like but she did win both of the first two best series
hugos so like i do think even at the reduced pace uh it might still happen she could have just
alternated vorkos again and chalion yeah so i quite like that they built in the recusements
basically in the in the category definition yeah that makes sense but yeah i don't i don't i mean
it's not i wouldn't be eligible again yet it's not reached that point so would be a good few years
uh so my pick is a novella by Adrian Tchaikovsky called elder race which basically has a really
neat central gimmick premise anyway what's going on is that you get the first chapter of this novella
which is the fourth daughter of the queen and the demon is terrorizing the land and she must go and
see the sorcerer who lives that in the tower on the hill to get him to help save her peoples and
then the next chapter we get is from the perspective of the sorcerer who lives on the hill there is in
fact an anthropologist from a technologically advanced civilization who is here to research
these people so they're all from earth but you know it's one of these like it's a colony and it
has been lost and over the years and it's become you know technologically less advanced and he has
come to uh study them and it basically goes through this fancy princess and the anthropologist
slash sorcerer going off to find the demon and essentially the anthropologist's decision of like
how much can i remain objective here how much should i try and stick to my mission of
not interfering and just observing or how much have i already become you know entangled with this
civilization and the right thing to do now is to is to aid them uh in this and that's basically
that the plot of the novella so the chapters alternate for a while until they become you know
they stop alternating because we've kind of got to point where they're more entwined and he's
decided you know he's going to take more of a role and he is actually going to go on this quest and
try and you know tell them what's going on and it follows things like you know he's tried to tell
them what the situation is that because nothing he says about like science and technology translates
they still think he's a wizard with magic powers it's also got this interesting thing where our you
know anthropologist protagonist is extremely depressed and has a lot of problems with depression
especially as he's had no contact from his homeworld for a long time and and is alone but he has a
technological device which allows him to put off feeling these emotions for a time and then at some
point he has to choose when to turn this off and like feel all this crushing depression but
allows it could have turned them off so he can function and it's an interesting portrayal of you
know his uh you know mental illness and how this is also perceived by this civilization which really
can't conceive an idea that he has something in his head where he can kind of delay feeling these
emotions and his you know feelings around having this and his feelings around his mental illness
and it adds the kind of extra dimension that i like so it's pretty good it's 2021 so i guess it is
eligible for a cue girl although the fact that Adrian Tragowski wrote three novellas last year might
might mean he sort of split his vote yeah i will say i will say so Adrian Tragowski is like amazing
i've liked everything i've read of his uh i wouldn't say i've read loads but like i've liked everything
i have he's won the clock award twice one once they children have time but he doesn't seem to get
much of a look in at the he goes and i don't really know why because he is amazing and he should
more people should vote for him and i guess maybe he's just appealing too much to the British market
and not enough overseas i don't know but would highly recommend people go and look his stuff up
because he is great well if we were to read all three of the 2021 Tragowski novellas we could have
an argument about which one people should put on their Hugo nomination but i feel like Tragowski is
under under recognized at this point he he has not been sufficiently award-shaped i think that is
true i i think i would agree with that i think i like this because you know i've read you know i read
some of his Empire and Black and Gold series i've read you know children of time and children of
earth and this feels like again it's kind of another departure from those he's not writing the same
work over and over again he's really writing kind of completely different things at novella
length and that giant novel length so i find uh really interesting maybe it's not the best way to
grow your readership if you kind of write something different every every time you write a work
uh but i i enjoyed this one i think you mean children of ruin not children of earth but yes
oh children of earth is torture one isn't it so shards of earth which is Tragowski's 2021 novel
is on my hold list from the library with a 21 24 week wait so Adrien if you're listening to this
and you'd like me to read your novel before nomination times don't send me it get the London
libraries consortium to buy a load more ebooks of it and then lots of people can read it not just me
there was one more thing i was going to say on on the actual star um so one of the reasons it's
difficult to read is that um as well as english it's got quite a lot of text in um spanish of
which i have absolutely none though as a person of privilege i have quite a bit of French latin
Portuguese and Italian so i got away with it um it's got quite a lot of it in a Belize Creole
and i went i bet if i just read these words out loud it'll be fine and it was um it's got quite
a lot of stuff in a future invented language in a future invented language that is based on spanish
and for which there is a glossary i gleaned nearly all of those from context so all of this makes it
a little bit tricky in a kind of it doesn't read through like an invention of all words so
so if if you like if you like science fiction it's very easy to read this one might not be for you
some people do bounce off that fortunately i have quite a lot of Spanish at this point so i should
be all right with the spanish bits i am very glad i'm still very annoyed that my school decided that
French German and latin were more sensible choices than spanish which i would argue is obvious nonsense
it wasn't obvious nonsense when i was in school but it was obvious when i was in school in Texas
that having spanish was very very useful i couldn't really switch because i already have french at
that point it's clear now to me that a lot of actual creativity is happening in in the united
states in spanish and as the u.s still has most of the cultural hegemony we probably do need to be
learning some spanish in the same way that we do need to be learning some mandarin if we want to
enjoy the next 20 or 30 years i will just say i also had like some french but it turns out if
you just keep persistently learning spanish all the french goes away eventually that was the octa
thought podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
[Music]
oh i do like a good milks that actually i mean not here obviously here i drink lager with ice in it
yeah but but for easter so whoever wants to brew us beer for easter con i'm sure we can
sell a few cans um and it could be the octa thought milk stout and then you could do an oat
you could do an oat meal stout called oat to thorp and you could that would be good
yes
so your milk stout's lacto thorp is it uh i don't know no no i'm much prefer milk
stout's that have milk in them or has lactose in them rather than milk stout's that don't
that's legit i also i mean like i don't know what other beer styles what beer styles don't
you guys like um crisp tylogger with like wedges of life though i would do if i was in
tylod in 35 degree yeah yeah i was in tylod in 35 degree heat i would be googling flights to the
uk i don't really like anything overly sour and i'm not keen on things which are overly
hoppy either yeah no i don't like if you put so much hops of a particular type in your beer that
it tastes like toilet cleaner then it tastes like toilet cleaner smells because i have no idea how
toilet cleaner tastes then it's probably not for me so i i slightly worry about any beer with the
word pine on the label yeah i i i am much the same uh as my co-hosts in that i i don't like very bitter
hoppy beers very much um i do quite like incredibly sour beers though some inliz do differ there um
but yes yeah it's like i can see the kind of the the craft and the artistry of making it a good
like lambic i just don't like drinking them no and and like and i will say that like there are some
beers lately that have been like double and triple IPAs that i have actually quite liked so i do think
like beer makers are getting better at making very hoppy beers that are not just very hoppy if
that makes sense um which i am kind of enjoying it's uh yeah what i just like is that i think of it
as being a sort of American strand of brewing all that might be a total slight on the americans but
i've definitely had it in some kind of american breweries where it's just a it just feels very
bitter and not much else in there so i guess now we know what the aftershoe is going to be right
maybe we shouldn't put that in because then all our american listeners will know maybe we should
because then all american listeners will write into me with suggestions of beers i should drink
and possibly even beers yes listeners please write in with a kind of beer tasting list a stretch
goal for octa thought for 2022 is to drink more interesting beer and Liz will drink all of these
interesting beers and she will not log any of them because she is not on untapped and you will be
none the wiser listeners you will be in darkness and ignorance i am actually on i am actually on
are you on untapped what shoot you're on the head taps whoa hang on did i know that i think i might
have known that actually the last time i used untapped is when i was sat in the brewery with you
guys drinking beer i think so you didn't really need to be on untapped nailed it do you not log
all of your tylargas like tylarga definitely a lager Liz don't drink a lot i basically drink
the same two or three and so it wouldn't be very interesting yeah i mean i don't tend to log like
corona uh if i ever have a corona so that is fair i don't i don't tell the log except when
chair gives me a paddington hardster not only is Liz on untapped but she's my friend on untapped so
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud and competec.com
used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
Keep your eyes closed.