We do and I think we are vaguely organized and I put people's names in front of letters.
Randomly.
Randomly? What?
Well, in a sort of semi-order but not with any particular thought.
Oh, I see what you mean. I thought you'd just like matched random names to random letters and it's like, well, a spaniel wrote in.
[laughs]
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 120th episode of OctaThor for
Podcast for Science Fiction and Science Fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 10th of October 2024.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And we're starting with some letters of comments.
But not as many as last week.
True.
So my wife told me that Dev Patel has said he isn't interested in being James Bond.
Sorry Liz.
What about M?
Right, OK, I don't know if they went through a full roster.
[laughs]
Ispania right in.
Every letter of the alphabet, test him.
But presumably if he said he wasn't interested in being James Bond, that was so that the people from James Bond would get in touch and say, can we offer you more money?
I don't want the second guest, Dev Patel's methods.
Yeah, that's what politicians do is to have no interest in becoming Prime Minister.
It's like, why are you in this game then?
Chris Garcia writes, "Hello Chris."
You never write.
Another close parenthesis for Alison as she left another one open, did I?
I think we did have multiple people report this.
So I think yes.
I didn't notice this at all.
I have not noticed this now twice, but I'm inferring that you did it again.
Oh no.
So do another close quickly.
Close parenthesis.
So listeners, what I'm going to recommend is don't.
So this is the 120 episode I've done with Alison.
And I have learned that Alison has a lot of wisdom in her head, but imposing your
strictures on how that information should be structured or delivered will only lead
to insanity listeners.
You've got to reach Zen.
I recommend Zen.
I recommend clipping out the little bit of audio where Alison says close parenthesis
and just like keeping it on your phone in case you need it in an emergency.
Good plan.
I'll put that in B3 in the show, those listeners, for anyone who needs
Alison to close a parenthesis, that will be available to you.
Yeah, no, I'm going to.
This is going to happen in a bar at some point, isn't it?
Anyway, what Chris says is I have in fact full archives of several podcasts,
including Dr.
Thorpe, some I've even less ought to transcribe.
So he's got his own transcripts of his own podcasts.
I got to I am going to digress now.
I'm not going to say open parenthesis because that will be bad.
I got a paper fancy that the first this week, you know who it's from that says
this is not available on PDF.
So I wrote to the people and immediately said, can I have a PDF?
And they were like, no.
And I was like, OK, so you know how much I've got to do?
Some of it just for you.
I have to now unstable this fanzine, stick it through my scanner,
source to allow it into scanned pages and then restapled it and dropped it
in the fanfans box.
And you could save me 20 minutes of work by sending me a PDF.
And they were like, no, it's a point of principle.
So there we go.
You know who you are.
Thank you for the paper fancy.
I very much appreciated it.
Chris also says on recusal's, I'm leaning towards that they are a bad idea
for an absent part of nomination.
We should be celebrating the best.
If you're really uncomfortable repeating, just decline the nomination when it comes.
I disagree with you there.
Sorry.
I don't think it's right to have our people waste their nominations.
If we know when I go to decline it.
That's fair.
I have listened to the business meeting episode at least three times.
The kids enjoyed it as well, at least twice.
I mean, did the kids listen three times?
So Tammy Cox and left us a Facebook message, which dovetails neatly with that.
In which she said something spinning off of Meg's lot of class episode as well.
She says, count me as one who would be sad if I were to talk permanently recused.
I'm a con runner, but not much of a consumer as ever.
SFF media.
I'm not aware of other fan casters that focus on fandom in the way I thought
does.
And that's why I like it so much.
Nominating or to book is something I can do to indicate that I find this kind
of content valuable.
And maybe that would encourage others to start similar podcasts.
But if there's never anything like it on the ballot, that's one less signal that
there's demand.
And that is a good point, Terry, and very kind.
So thank you.
We also had from Farrah on Facebook saying, I think one should win three times
consecutively before accusing oneself, which is also an interesting way of doing
it.
Basically, the point that you start to dominate the category, that is when you
should graciously step back.
I think that also is the thing where I wonder if we're going to get like,
I think we've kind of been thinking about things like Ansible and Locusts and
some very, very long running fanzines and fan writers.
Fan casters knew enough that not many fan customer running for years and years
and years.
I mean, I think there is like writing excuses, but they were in best related work.
There is Verity, which is always somewhere bubbling under on the ballot.
But I can't think of many things which kind of have been going for, you know,
10 years.
Emily of January wrote and said, I missed your postbag episode, but have some
thoughts anyway, which is fine.
Alan Bond didn't get the DDH title until the convention, but they were
acting as committee for much before that.
So that happened in practice.
John suggested that the online convention should be part of promotions,
but Emily suggested it probably touches all parts of the convention.
So needs to have people from all different areas of the convention.
I mean, I'm kind of like it's, it's a convention like the in person
convention is a convention.
And anyway, it is, I think I probably agree with this to some extent.
I think it is still the fact that there are a lot of people involved in
Worldcon running who think that the online convention is something that can
be put in a box is something that slightly bothers me.
I think if you're working on a Worldcon, every job should have this
sense of and how does that work online?
Perhaps not the person who's responsible for negotiating with the SEC
so they don't do bag checks, but you know, everybody else.
And then a thing on formatting and saying, oh, but if you are going to use
print formats, you should have use re flowable ones.
I understand that fandom is attached to PDFs, but they are awful to zoom
around and scroll on your phone.
And I mean, I understand where Emily is coming from here.
I am probably always going to be the person who thinks that beautiful print
publications are lovely.
But then I guess I also used to like 12 inch record sleeves.
Look where that got me.
I think we'll see a resurgence of interest in beautifully formatted
print publications in the same way that the young people apparently buy
vinyl records.
I think the point about needing people to think about how it touches the
physical convention and the online convention is probably true, like down
the road.
But I do think like three years on is probably too soon to expect that to
have been completely embedded in everyone's brains at a level where you
just don't need to have anyone worrying about it anymore.
Like, I think I think that's going to be a I would I would guess that won't
be true for years and years because we have done this thing in this way for
over 80 years and it takes a long time to unlearn those habits.
So I don't I think I think in the long, long run, you're right.
But in the short term, I don't see it happening soon.
But yeah, it's a timescale argument more than anything else.
And John's timescale argument also applies to publications, right?
Like we have made the shift from we provide everyone at the con with a paper
thing to we expect them to use their device of whatever size to look at
important content while they're at the con, but maybe not quite got the hang
of providing that in the right format.
And at some point, someone will be like, OK, this is not primarily a print
thing. This is primarily information and we put it into the format.
It needs to be, but we haven't quite got that.
But in 10 years, I think we will.
Maybe five.
How optimistic are we feeling?
I don't know.
It depends on the day, Liz.
I didn't sleep well.
So less than usual.
We also heard from noted science fiction critic Abigail Nusbaum, who
email does what I think is a spoiler for the acolyte.
So anyone who hasn't watched the acolyte yet and doesn't want to know the twist,
say your fingers and your ears.
Alison has in fact done this.
Alison, take your headphones off and I will wave at you and it's time to put
them back on Abigail the email is to say she's honored to be known as
appreciated of Mani Gittinto's arms.
It is a Star Wars show that finally figured out how to make the dark side of
the force a seductive to its audience as it apparently is to characters within
the universe and the key to that turns out to be arms.
I mean, correct.
I don't know about John, but I would probably go to the dark side for
Mani Gittinto's arms.
I do have a ribbon from my first Gallifrey one convention that says I heard
Kylo Ren was shredded.
I heard he had an eight pack.
So, you know, it's not only Mani Gissino, who is a hot dark side user.
Our Adam Driver is quite pretty.
Hugo Girl in their report from Glasgow talked a little bit about us in in that
episode, namely a report from the Hugo reception and a report from our live
panel. If you're interested in what that was like, go listen to that episode.
I think it's the most recent episode as we record, but it might not be when you
download this.
But yeah, no, it was very sweet and it made me smile.
And thank you to Laurie and Kevin for being me and Espani's plus ones for the
reception because it was very lovely to have such beautiful dates.
And also for being my airport buddies.
Yes.
Makes the con less longer when you just basically tap someone until they have to
run away and get on a plane like the very end of the con.
Yep, yup, yup.
We also heard from Nicholas White, who points out that there's an eclipse in
Spain before the one in Australia.
So if you're a fan of eclipses, go look that up.
Listeners will put link in the three notes.
We also heard from Ivan Sinha, who has discovered that at sea, the pineapple is
the universal symbol of the swinger.
And therefore, the pre-support for Brisbane being pineapple could be quite
funny.
Brisbane, right in.
Yeah, Brisbane, were you making a secret coded message about swinging or is it
just that you pick some food?
Wait, wait, wait, wait.
Where are you?
Newcastle.
No, no, I'm wrong.
Ignore me.
Talking, talking rots right now.
So I thought the big pineapple was in Brisbane, but it's not.
So what could have been a really interesting point is, oh, you were going to
say there was a giant pineapple thing.
Yeah, but OK.
Yeah, there is a big pineapple, but it's not in Brisbane.
So I was going to say, oh, but the big pineapple is a noted feature of Brisbane.
And what does that tell us about the walk on?
So, you know, but it's not.
But it is in Queensland, which is nowhere near Brisbane.
Brisbane is the capital city of Queensland.
So I assume that it is in it.
OK, maybe it's in Brisbane.
Hang on.
And I know that Australians have a different perspective of what is near to
things than we do on account of how their island is way bigger than ours.
Yes, it is.
It is close to Brisbane.
And it's about 150 miles away.
That's close to Brisbane, even by a British perspective.
It's probably because of the big pineapple.
So it's pineapples because the big pineapple is a noted symbol of Brisbane.
And I hesitate to think what that tells us about Brisbane, Fandom.
And I know that Pat McMurry was very taken with the big pineapple on his fan
fund trip.
So I hesitate to think what that tells us about Pat.
I think it means that the Australian Worldcon is going to take some big swings.
[Music]
Do we want to do Hugo Stats?
I am prepared for doing Hugo Stats, I think.
For those people who were sad that Liz does not get enough airtime.
Ho-ho listeners, do we have an episode for you?
Yes.
Activate Liz.
And it's amazing it's taken us this long to get to doing it on the show.
But straight after the Hugo's, we got Stats, which is quite funny when I went
to get a drink and came back to a whole group of people just like with their
heads buried in their smartphones, checking out Stats.
And there's some interesting things in the Stats.
So let's talk about them.
So as we've discussed before, nominees are, well, finalists for Hugo's are
generated using E-pluribus Hugo, the quite complicated method of giving you like
a set of points for your nominations, which gets split over all the nominees
you've put on and then they get removed and then they get reallocated.
Anyway, if you want a long description of how it works, I'm pretty sure I've
done it before on the podcast or we'll link to one in the show notes.
But the interesting thing is this means that you can be on the ballot.
Like you can be in the top six without getting the sixth highest number of
nominations or whatever.
This year, there are quite a lot finalists who were helped by E-pluribus Hugo
to get on the ballot because they obviously did not share a strong voting
constituency with anything else on the ballot.
And in some cases, this might be an indication that because the
nominators from Chengdu maybe nominated different things than the
nominators from the UK and the US.
And so there's a few instances of this.
For instance, if you go to Best Short Story without E-P-H, there would have
been a joint sixth nominee, which was another, I think originally,
Chinese story called Heaven's Vol by Lu Guicha.
And if you go to Best Dramatic Presentation Long Form, where as we know,
there was a motion to extend the eligibility for Godzilla minus one.
And as we later found out, it got the same number of votes as poor things.
And so it was sort of knocked out there by E-P-H.
But actually, the Wandering Earth 2 got fewer actual votes than Godzilla
minus one and good Omen series two and the Marvels and Asteroid City and
Guardians of Galaxy Vol 3.
But because of E-P-H, it seems like the people who nominated the Wandering
Earth 2 mostly just nominated Wandering Earth 2, whereas the people who
nominated the other things probably split there, like they had multiple
successful finalists on the ballot.
So that really helped the Wandering Earth, which otherwise, you know, would have
not been anywhere near the ballot.
And how many how many votes did how many nominations did Wandering Earth 2 get?
There's 69.
Nice.
Low right.
I might be 35, but I'm 12 at heart.
And there are a few other examples of this worth noting Nicholas also explicitly
notes Godzilla minus one would have needed one more vote and it would have been
on the ballot.
Yes.
So it was it was you can tell it's very close to the tables, but Nicholas does
do a good job of pulling out little things that are not necessarily clear and
just highlighting them for the reader.
Yeah, because if it had one more vote, then it would not have been in the final
runoff.
I think Nicholas knows Nicholas knows all the details.
There were a few other instances of like where a nominee got on with a
slightly lower number of nominations due to E-P-H.
I think Godzilla minus one is the biggest example, but for instance,
Yao Hijun is on the ballot for a better long form, just by getting one fewer
nomination than Gillian Redfern, although this did say that Gillian would have
needed another five votes to get on the ballot.
It was not quite as close.
We also see this in best fanzine.
And in this case, I don't think this is due to a Chinese nominating block.
This is because idea made it onto the ballot, but the idea actually got fewer
nominations than answer review books, which I nominated,
Galactic Journey and Zero Gravity News, both previous finalists.
So that's another case of that idea is an example of something that gets a lot
of votes from people who are not otherwise voting for anything, because
they don't actually read or like the other things in the category, or they
like read and like other fanzines, but they're not the fanzines that are on the
ballot.
If you nominate something and other things that are not in contention, then
your nomination has more power under EPH.
Yeah.
So for instance, you can see that when banana wings is eliminated,
idea picks up quite a lot of points.
And some of the others do pick up points, but not nearly as many.
So clearly, a bunch of those points are going to idea.
Oh, is this a good place for me to talk about?
Thank you, diagrams.
And yeah, this is basically showing the like the immutable artifact
fanzine community and the it's on the internet as a HTML fanzine community,
which any better snappy names for, you can see the two communities both
nominating with remarkably little overlap.
But yeah, it's interesting.
I think the overlap is in Journey Planet.
Yes, but even then not loads, although definitely some.
But like, certainly when the rec center comes out, none of those people
transfer to Journey Planet, whereas when Galactic Journey comes out, a few do.
It's interesting.
It is interesting.
And we're not going to call them archaic and modern fanzines were agreed,
dare I?
I used, I didn't, I don't think retro has a value judgement in the way
you think it does, but I understand the point.
It's like retro games.
I play a lot of retro games.
Oh, yeah.
Might be talking about that a bit later.
For Shadow Week.
The game convention I just went to had several mega drives for sale at 50
quid each, including all cables.
And I was like, what's old is new again.
Well, I'm guessing, and I mean to a category with arguably no one retro
because it's fan cast.
And I already talked about how there are no, you know, fan cast from the 60s
unless you can't work cylinders, see previous episodes.
Anyway, the nominations in fan cast were interesting given that the two
nominees with by far the most number of nominations were both eligible due to
being professional and indeed, Discovery X didn't end up in the finalists.
But also interesting that Hugo Girl were pretty close to making the ballot.
And if Antman EPH, they would have been on there despite having deemed
themselves to be ineligible.
So those 30 people, unfortunately, like, yeah, they would have an example of what
we were talking about earlier that you would have got your nominee onto
ballot and then they would have declined.
So yeah, you'd have got your nominee onto the ballot without I assert
listening to the podcast where they'd clearly recused.
Recuse early, recuse often because you might not listen to every single episode.
Yeah, indeed.
There's tricky, right?
Because we don't encourage people during Hugo season, we are going to have to say at
the start of every episode that we have recused because anyone who starts
listening during Hugo season, we are going to feel just start and listen, right?
And so we can't then be like, well, why didn't you listen to the back catalog
when we repeatedly tell people they don't know, you know, like, it is hard.
It is hard.
The thing I love about this is that when Hugo Girl gets taken out, you can see
that like four points get transferred to Octa thought.
So there is a
Oh, thank you, chaps.
Big Venn diagram there, which makes sense because we are transatlantic
podcast besties, but it's still lovely to see it in actual numbers.
The first time we got on the Hugo Baller, EPH did us a massive solid.
And this time we are like, yes, yeah, I won't go into it too much because it makes
me want to curl up and cringe into a little ball, but it is very nice.
Then that's that's people.
So what else say something so I don't have to do that voice anymore?
Yeah, let's move on.
I'm cringing and killing a flippable listening to that voice, actually.
Yeah.
So just the other two instances where someone made it on the ballot by EPH this year
were all hand-westering in fan writer and also Dan Taylor is in fan artists,
but they are both very close and indeed in fan artists, you may need it.
Not point eight more points. So like, you know, that's one or two nominations.
So very close, but also there's a pretty low number of nominations still in fan
artist, not your fan artists.
And it is interesting.
Fan artists is one of the categories where the highest number of nominations is not a
good predictor of who eventually won, which I think is something will probably come to
later on in this discussion for shadowing.
More shadowing, but now all the Alison get word in Ed
on used for the hugos before. And it makes it very clear where the votes are going in the,
in the process. And I thought this was interesting. And we have a link.
The person in question was Zoe O'Connell, who I believe is a listener.
Certainly they are in our Facebook community.
Hello.
Hello, Zoe. So that is great. And I love these and I looked at them a lot.
And I particularly looked at the octave thought while.
Because, you know, what am I like? But I thought it was very interesting because it does present
this information in graphical form, which is quite nice.
Yeah, no, it does. So Zoe credits Alexandra lanes for the idea in the last post in the chain,
which we'll put a link to in the show notes listeners.
And so if I have had thoughts of volunteering to help with the Hugo administration team for Seattle,
because we will be recused, so there'll be no conflict of interest.
And this is the sort of thing I would, I've always thought it would be nice to see more
visualizations in the actual tables. Because one of the things I repeatedly tell PhD students at
work is don't put tables in your papers because it's really difficult to read a table and draw
any meaningful conclusions, which I'm thinking very hard and graphs to let you highlight stuff
really well. But yeah, no, these are absolutely amazing.
I have a couple comments. One is definitely also put the tables in the paper though, John.
Then I can steal the data from them.
Oh, yeah, yeah. No, no, no. Well, you put the tables in.
Well, actually, no. Okay, so we're not allowed to put the tables in the paper anymore, Liz.
We have to put them on a separate data repository.
Yeah, that's also fair. NIRDY NIRDS NIRDS.
Yeah. So it's the woman who put, oh, look at these beautiful visualizations and diagrams into the
show notes. We're not out learning on this one. I am however, going to out-nerdy both by saying
that actually the first Sanqui diagrams I saw for the Hugo Awards are in 2020 by a Twitter user
called Martin P. I don't know how they made them. Oh, it looks like they use Sanqui Matics.
So the same tool that Zouio Connell has used, which I've also used to make Sanqui diagrams,
but I think the great idea was to like suck all the stats out of the Hugo Minestrator's report
and write a Python script to feed them in Sanqui Matics, which is great because I had once tried
to automate the making of Sanqui diagrams through R and found just the most complicated packages
I'd ever seen in my life. So it looks like Sanqui Matics is the way to go. I will put a link in
the show notes to the 2021s, which are quite fun. We probably missed them because we're having a
pandemic at the time, you know, so yeah. Looking at like Python options for Sanqui diagrams, the
Matplotlib ones look absolutely awful. And then you have to go to other packages and they look very
complicated. So yeah, you might be getting into the weeds. Maybe. Although I will say
that the ones you can make in Python, let you have interactive HTML ones with tooltips. So
if you were going to do the EPH ones, that might be super good. But but but it's all going on a PDF
anyway. So there's no reason that the Hugo stats have to be in a PDF, you know, they could be in
a sensible day of format. Sorry, it's oh, there's a good reason for having them in a PDF. Well,
they should also be in a PDF, but they should also be in HTML with CSV files that you can read in
and do hacking with. But no, good. Thank you diagrams. Very good. Zoey. Thank you very much for this,
because it is wonderful. And we love data. Now Liz, you what did you want to do things about
the relationship of nominations to winners? There's also because the preferential vote,
you can get winners in the who goes who do not have the most first preferences. And you sometimes
get interesting voting patterns. And just to pull out a few in best novella seeds of mercury,
which had quite a lot of nominations, but not the most has like a pretty whopping advantage in first
preferences. It has like 280 more than the next nearest, which is Donhenge. But as you watch all
the preferences get redistributed, basically these mercury only manage to gain about 200. And
Donhenge gains like an extra 680 votes. So basically, Donhenge ends up coming from behind on the second
to last round and winning it, which I thought was quite interesting. And you do get that in a few
other, few other categories as well. That's one I was going to pull out. So the other one that's
noticeable is three body problem is winning in best graphic story, quite comfortably again until
the final round where when all the preferences get redistributed, it is saga again. And three body
problem also got nominated with like five times as many nominations as the next nearest nominee.
That was a pretty whopping. It's not only a giant kind of set of nominations, but also it has 151
points from 151 nominators throughout the last 10 rounds, basically. So no one nominated three
body problem nominated anything else that made it so final well. Dungeons and Dragons. I mean,
we haven't had a chance to talk about Dungeons and Dragons, but it was a weird winner, wasn't it?
So Spiderman had was had the most first round votes. There's not a huge amount in it above
Dungeons and Dragons. And it carried on having the first votes right until the point where
Barbie got eliminated and Barbie's extra votes were enough to make the difference and tip D&D
to the top. So people who like Barbie like D&D better than they like Spiderman. I don't know if
I think that's even likely to be true. Yeah, it's interesting because D&D did get the most
nominations. So like it is interesting that that it ended up winning and got the most
nominations, which was not true in every category. But I mean, I think these are examples of why
it's important to have a ranked preference ballot and not just first post post because yeah,
I love I love that D&D one. I mean, I did like this movie, but I'm not sure it was the better
but it's not the best of the year. Poor things was best of the year. But I absolutely love
that it won because I love that there was kind of an everyone was shocked and it beat out a lot of
much bigger, bigger films because you know, nerds be nerdy. It was very old Brad for the
World Card, I thought. It's fine, but it's not like, you know, it's a small independent production
that makes it because no, it's like which one of these like top, I guess the top three are all
big budget Hollywood films. It's more like poor things basically get smashed by bigger budget
productions. That's just the motor, I think. Yeah, but pneumonia being streaming only
possibly hurt it a bit if people hadn't picked it up. It also had low, it didn't have a lot of
buzz around it, whereas I think all of the other movies here did have quite a bit of buzz. I think
that's to do with theatrical release, if I'm honest. I think the theatrical releases do quite a lot
for buzz for movies and I don't fully understand Netflix's model in terms of building excitement
for properties in that sense, but you know, I'm not in charge. Netflix certainly never told me to
watch it. I mean, it was a weird one anyway because Netflix kind of picked it up when it was dropped
partway through by the studio and so on. So yeah, maybe it like they picked it up, but it was not in
their plans as a big thing to promote. It's great though. So if you didn't watch it, and there are a
couple of other categories that basically end up being very close. I mean, we're all cheered, I
think when Strange Horizons was best-selling Proxin, but they did win by six votes and they got it on
the final, on the final redistribution. Like they were on Kenny Wai-Zing were very close again,
which is interesting. And yeah, the lead changed in Best Fan Zine three times. Yes, it did. The
Best Fan Zine Sankey is quite interesting. I wanted to do best editor short form, which I found
interesting because Lin and Lin-M and Michael Damian Thomas are winning for the first three rounds,
and then when Yang Feng is excluded, the redistribution goes to Neil Clark, which I assume is because Neil
has done a lot of work in China, and I assume is him having recognition with Chinese fandom,
because I'm going to guess Yang Feng had supporters in Chinese fandom. So I thought that was interesting,
just seeing that effect in the stats. I think it is also worth noting that Discover X, which
we covered, was kind of had enough votes to be on the ballot in both fan cast and best related work,
but as it is a professional production, it went in best related work. And as we know,
Discover X was part of the Chengdu science fiction fandom in some way, and it managed to get 343
nominations, but then when you look at the actual votes in best related work, it got 25 first
preferences, which was below no award. So that is a pretty dramatic difference. So obviously,
a lot of people who liked that and had nominating rights from Chengdu, but potentially did not join
Glasgow and so did not have voting rights. So I think that is the only case of a finalist,
which ends up with fewer first preferences than no award. And I mean, you do sometimes get no
award a bit higher up, especially if it's in categories where there is just a sort of dedicated
set of people who don't think that the category should exist. And you can see this in best fan cast.
I do want to thank the one person again, who put no award top and then put a second.
[Laughter]
That was a vote for fan cast to not exist, but it does exist, it should be optimal.
Yeah, I mean, you get that in quite a few categories, right? You get the, I don't think this category
should exist, but if someone's going to win, I'm going to help choose the winner. And so some of
their votes do redistribute. There was only that one case where an actual finalist was below.
No award. That is my hu-kobit.
A, thank you very much, correspondent Liz.
Do we want to mention Reconnect?
Reconnect has its PR2 out. It is an extremely beautiful PDF. Sorry, Emily.
And I think it was one of the Januarys who alerted me to the, I am reading this on my phone and I'm
like, why would you do that? But I know that a lot of people, the majority of people,
data, read everything on their phones. So, you know, that's why you would do that. So I guess,
but anyway, it's lovely, but it has lots of information in it. You should go and find it.
They are also looking for somebody to run out, run that discord, because Emily and Andrew are
taking a year off. So I think it would be a good idea for somebody to step up to the plate.
Someone should do this. I have put a top by someone list. It will not be me.
There are other things in there as well. I will put a link in the show notes.
Oh, and hotel bookings are opening. I think they said in September, and I feel like that's not
going to happen given that we are recording on the 29th, but you know.
Real soon now. Real soon now. Maybe by the time you get this podcast, because we are recording
slightly early. The news came out since we last recorded that David Curry, who people might know
as Jersey Griffin, passed away after an illness. He was listener. He listened for a long time.
I knew him through East Confandom, and he will be missed. He was lovely bloke.
And yeah, very sad news. Yeah, he was one of our first regular listeners, I think. Yeah.
Shall we do pics? I could go first, because I know what I'm picking.
I know what I'm picking. All right. So I'm going to pick. So I'm going to pick.
I'm not going to pick a thing, and then I'm going to pick a thing in the time-honoured John tradition.
Oh, the thing I'm not picking is a play that I saw in Whitley Bay last night,
which was called Subterrania. And the reason I'm not picking it is that this is spectacularly
unhelpful recommendation for two reasons. Firstly, it was playing in Whitley Bay, and secondly,
the last day was yesterday. But it was a really good little local production about a post-apocalyptic
northeast with people living in the Metro tunnels. And it was just really nice. And I liked it very
much. And I was happy to see a genre piece of local theatre playing. And yeah, really enjoyed it.
My actual pick is The Substance, which is an incredibly stressful movie that honestly still
makes me anxious when I think about it now, when I saw it on Wednesday. So that's like five days
ago listeners. It was a lot. It is amazing. It is not subtle. It is absolutely haunting.
It has like a list of content warnings as long as you're armed, and it's absolutely terrifying
and incredibly gory. I thought it was incredible, mostly how angry it is. There are some people on
Letterbox to are determined to read it as pro-objectifying women, which I think is a
incomplete reading, I think I would say, because I think, I don't know, it was very
obviously very angry about everything to me. But it was just, it was amazing. And yeah,
we very much enjoyed it. But do be kind to yourself when you go and see it, because
oh, it was hard. It was real hard. So yeah. And it's genre. It's science fiction. I won't go into
the plot because yeah, but it's a kind of body horror science fiction piece. I wonder whether it'll
be on the Hugo ballot. I can't decide. It might be a bit much.
Fun fact listeners, Johnny Badley, noticed that this was the best film at Frightfest this year,
and noticed that it's got a general release. I noticed that it was the only interesting film
available for the magical Wednesday afternoon slot at Ascinemo, where two of us can watch a film
for 6.75, the pair. And I said, should I go and watch this movie? And several people said,
no, Alison, you should not. And I have put it down for streaming. So watch it streaming,
possibly in quite small bits to determine whether it should be on my Hugo ballot or not.
Yeah, I don't. Yeah, you're a horror. You have described yourself as a horror worse.
I am. I am. And Steven is a bit as well. Yeah. You know, I sort of at the bits in movies where
I flage, I noticed that Steven flitchers more. So, you know. So, I don't know. But I mean,
it's obviously a very interesting movie with a lot, a lot to go on, but it's probably not quite
my cup of tea. It'll be a bit scary for me. Yeah. Yeah. I don't know. I think it's a masterpiece.
I will never watch it ever again, because it is too stressful. So, you know.
Anyway, someone else can do a pic. So my pic is UFO 50. I mentioned retro games earlier,
and this is a game which is out this week. The premise of the game is it's a collection like
Atari 50 that collects together all of the greatest games of a particular console. In this case,
the LX, an 80s console that existed in three generations from 1982 to 1989. So, the 50 games
go from the earliest game released on the console and it has to the last one. And the thing about
this is that the LX, the games and all the developers listed in the game never existed,
and all of the and all of these games are new. They all have the hardware constraints of the
non-existent console. So, it has a 384 by 216 screen with 32 bits of color and a four-way
controller with with a and B buttons. This is a game for steam. It's produced by Derek Yu,
who did Spelunky and brought in his old childhood mate, John Perry, who is now a board game designer
known for spots amongst other things and Airland and Sea. They also brought in the designer of
Aduro from Oto, who designed Downwell and Point P, if you know those games, and then they have
some ex probably the best chip tune composer working in the industry, Eric Sucra, and then there's a
couple of actual developers who probably did all the hard work of developing this game.
The games, like in the 80s, the games come in a huge range of genres. So, some of them
really quite in keeping of real games of the time, and some of them kind of use modern
tropes. So, for example, there is a deck builder in here, and there is a tower defense in here,
and there are a lot of games that did not in fact exist at the time. The very first game of the
collection, Babuta, is they, I guess they knew that people would play it first, but it's supposed
to be the very oldest game. So, it's really janky, it's got no music, there's a kind of little glitchy
noise when you change screens, the character travels very slowly, and a lot of people are kind of
bounced off this one, and yet if you actually play it, which I have extremely extensively,
it's fabulous, it's full of secrets, there's lots of extremely cool things about it, and
and yes, so I played it all week really, that's what I've done, it's I've fallen into a hole,
and then having fallen into the hole, oh, and it's Windows only, so because I've not heard of this
game, but as soon as, I mean it's obviously very much sort of game I like, as soon as I heard about
it, I said, well I'm buying that, but of course it runs on Windows only under Steam, so I've got,
I've got all that running under Whiskey, Whiskey is stronger wine, so Whiskey is a wine that
additionally includes Max Game Port in Kit, so if you're from Mac, this is how you can do this
with your Steam thing, and I didn't just put it onto my regular Mac, I also then put it onto the
Mac in the living room, synced by controllers, so we can sit on the sofa playing the console games,
like God intended with our little controllers, and discovered at that point that as well as there
being 50 games here, which is an enormous number of games, quite a lot of the games have multiplayer,
and the multiplayer games are not just everyone takes a turn at the single player game, or people
fight head to head, they are really different, they are interesting takes on how you would do this,
so one of them is semi-collaborative, because they haven't quite worked out that a collaborative
game should have one score, one of them is competitive and you can also beat up your,
beat up the person who is trying to do the thing at the same time as you are, and there's a lot of
we've only played a couple of them so far, so it's very exciting, and I don't know, I may be sometime,
50 games, 50 games buy some really good retro game designers, it's like, it is like Christmas,
it is like imagine you got at NES and 50 games, oh it's amazing, and people say well it's like the
experience of having a console and a load and a bunch of games for it for the first time, but it's
also like, I think the only time I've had an experience quite like this is main, but this is
better because there's some quality control that didn't really exist when I downloaded main and also
625 dodgy ROMs for it, so all the games, when you read reviews of UFO 50 people are kind of like
well this was not very good and this was not very good, but I've really got into this one,
and if you read 10 reviews there'll be 10 different games, so fabulous, strongly recommend if you
like any sort of retro games at all, which obviously I do, because no issue with things like narrative
or like cutscenes or video or voice acting or any of the things that I think get away from the
the pure core of actually playing the game. Okay, fair enough. So this will certainly be on
like Hugo Ballot because look alternative reality, yeah 100% Hugo pick. That is that is quite a
conceptual, um, argument by like it. Oh there's also a meta game about which I think is probably
about the history of the development studio, so there's quite a lot of actual starts
fiction in there, there's a lot of history gaming in there. Ah fair enough. Liz, do you have a pick?
Yes, basically I haven't read anything particularly exciting since we last recorded, and so I'm
falling back on my old standby of saying you should just read an Aiden Tricoste book because
they're all pretty great. So I'm going to pick Alien Clay by Adrian Tricoski, this is his
one of his 2024 science fiction novels, it is about a dissident scientist, um in a society where,
you know, earth is run by the mandate and dissidents essentially get deported onto alien
planets for use as work parties in a way that you know shows they don't really care if you live
or die, it's just a way to kind of get you out of the way and use your wise labour.
We follow a dissident art on Dagdev who gets dumped on the planet and it's kind of all about the
politics inside the work camp, um both within like the prisoners there and the kind of
soldiers and scientists who are there but aren't prisoners but they are kind of trapped on an
alien planet and this alien planet is weird, I mean this is why you really age in Tricoski book,
it's maybe not quite as weird as like children of time but it is still weird, it's all kind of
weird symbiotic creatures where every thing you could point to and say that's an animal is kind of
a symbiotic relationship between different ones and you know how does that even work for evolution
for things like that and then at the end it kind of all comes together and kind of ties up this
alien planet and evolution and revolutions and the politics of that in a fairly satisfying way.
I don't think it is my favourite favourite age in Tricoski book, I haven't read his other 2024 one
so it may not even be my favourite 2024 age in Tricoski book but I think it is worth a read.
That is legit, I'm just looking to see whether I've read this one, I don't think I have, I will add
it to the list. I like that he helpfully labels the books on his website as to whether they're
science fiction or fantasy or both, um because I'm going to have to read his science fiction 2024
novels on a counter how I am a judge for the Clark Award this year. Oh so I have to read all of the
UK published 2024 novels and make judgements listeners judgements. I'll talk about that in
future episodes probably as it goes through although there's limits on what I can and can't say
but yes I am a judge and I don't get a little shield or a helmet but that's all right I do get a
little badge. Oh oh I've got an art prompts. Yes yes yes yes yes but you know I'm looking forward
to looking forward to reading a lot of the genre this year and um my fellow judges are
our Nick Clark, Dolly Garland, Glenn Morgan and Jean Rowe this year so um yeah I'm really looking
forward to it, it'd be good. That was the Oct Thought Podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me.
I am going to want carved on my gravestone and well I mean obviously this is an immutable object.
The point about the PDF is that it can then stand as a historical record so even if you decide that
you always want everything that you're um releasing at the time to be in reflowable versions it is
incredibly useful to have something that you could point to that you could basically put in a file
and say five years later yes this is what was used. So I wanted to write a letter of comment to
Oct Thought because when you read Chris's letter last episode you completely misconstrued what he
was saying because he was making that argument and specifically saying that's true of paper and it's
not true of any electronic file and so I agree with you it's important that there is a paper
record of this and I think that is what Chris was saying last episode. Paper records yeah no I
don't think I'd ask you as you know Bob I have yes a yes you can all sorts of examples of that
but B no if they don't need to be paper they just need to be they just need to be files that are
a pain to change and and that it's obvious if they've been changed. I think Chris's point is that as
an information archivist he's seen digital files go AWOL enough that he thinks the only reliable way
of doing it was paper and I did when I was editing it as I always should bring this up because this
is an interesting thing and this is a massive digression for this part of the podcast but I think
that was what Chris was getting at specifically. Indeed yes no he did and I did I did a lie that
point and I shouldn't have done I'm sorry Chris I feel like that was true when I first got into
computers the file formats were really janky in that sort of way I mean one of the things I lost
was my wedding invitation and all of the files for my wedding invitation and all the stuff around
that I do have the printed copies in this case but the since I think PDF and MP3 have been
are old file formats that have been relatively stable and jpeg has been pretty good and png
and they've been good for like a generate you know 25 30 years at this point which I think is
probably enough that it will always be easy to read those files. Archivist do I encourage to write
in and me angry at Alison? Archivist be angry. The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for
Space by Kevin McLeod in Competec.com used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.
You