No it's before the clap you can't use things before the clap boy.
Okay, new rule I guess.
I can.
That was my traditional free podcast burp.
If the title of this podcast wasn't very definitely going to be,
Mothia, that would be a contender.
It's the title of this podcast going to...
Do you think anyone else is going to find Mothia?
Funny.
I mean, if they don't, they're better strap in because they're in for a long one.
Anyway, hello everyone and welcome to the 20th episode of OctaThort,
a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Liz Batty.
Uh, Alison, are you okay?
Alison has dissolved into gagors.
We're sorry, listeners.
Alison is here.
She's just can't come to the podcast right now.
Oh, I'm Alison Scott.
This episode will be going out on the 10th of December, um, 2020.
And we have some letters of comment, but first we have a very serious plea.
Uh, we want to talk to you about something that's very close to our hearts, all three of us.
Um, and, and we urge you to take this very seriously.
Um, please don't send me any more We To Bix.
I'm begging you.
Please stop.
Please.
I think I've got time to change my shopping list for tomorrow.
I've got enough.
Someone sent me Claire, Claire, Claire, Breiley of Croydon, sent me 108 We To Bix.
And then my half brother, Dave, who I didn't know listened to the show, but hi, Dave.
Uh, he also threatened to send me 108 We To Bix.
And I just, I don't need more than 200 We To Bix in my house.
Um, so please, please everyone consider me closed for We To Bix at this time.
But thank you very much for thinking of me.
If your correspondence involved We To Bix, this correspondence is closed.
But if your correspondence was about We To Bix, that's probably still fine.
And indeed we have letters of comment, all of which mentioned We To Bix.
And if you, if you do threaten to send We To Bix, you may find, um, that you get a surprise.
God, that sounds ominous.
So letters of comment.
Duncan McGregor has tweeted out as to say a minor point of contention is that boxing Helena was directed by Jennifer Lynch, who is David Lynch's daughter.
And then he tweeted again saying, I just realized I meant to type correction, but also correct my mind.
So thank you, listen to Duncan, uh, for letting us know, uh, we apologize for the error.
And and wrote in tweeted at us to say that she finds the modern phrase key learnings makes her teeth grind.
Um, and so we will attempt, we will treat that as a key learning and we will avoid it here with.
Who said key learnings?
I don't think I don't know if anyone actually said it, but, um, okay.
How does she feel about onboarding?
I don't know how she feels about onboarding. She didn't mention it, but we did get a letter from Claire Riley of Croydon.
So Claire sent us a poem, uh, which is very excellent. Thank you, Claire.
And, um, she, she didn't say that onboard it. Is it a real word?
She just thinks it's a horrible verbed contraction.
Um, and then Mark, she says this lock and Mark has not locked us.
That's important for you to know listeners, although I would, I would like him to, because I am now curious because she says this lock comes so late that Mark has surely written to you already and mentioned his proposed companion terms, which he feels helped to mitigate the horror
off boarding for managing the process when someone leaves and over boarding for when they've been sacked.
And that, I think, are, those two words I think are valuable additions to the lexicon.
I'm, I'm not convinced we didn't use off boarding at my last job, and I left it in 2012, so.
I don't know. I've never worked in a job that had jargon.
Oh, you haven't lived. You know, you have, obviously, you just, if you don't think your job has jargon, you've...
No, and my job just has real words that everyone understands like Magnetosphere and Plasmusheet Dynamics.
And then she says, she thanks us for the autotop fridge bag that, that we sent her, and she explains that she shall unfridge it immediately, which we are glad to hear Claire.
We should mention the fact that if you're stuck for a Christmas present or stocking filler, you can now get fantastic octotop merch in the form of fridge magnets.
I'm possibly some other merch as well if I get my act together by Thursday, but don't hold your breath. There will be a link in the show notes to how you can buy a fine octotop magnet with our logo on.
And, and we're going to use it as the art for the chapter heading so that you'll be able to see a picture of it if you actually look at your chapter headings, which obviously you don't, because nobody actually does that.
If you go to the show notes, there will be links to places where you can buy Allison's excellent octotop fridge magnets and where you can buy Allison's excellent octotop t-shirts, because I want an octotopop t-shirt, Allison, and if I say you're going to put it in the show notes, it will happen magically.
Frid round it's a three pounds plus a pound for delivery and all of the details will be somewhere.
Octotop t-shirts are purple.
Yeah, I mean, there could not be a purple, that would be crazy.
Okay, and we should read the poem. Lines on receiving a most unexpected fridge magnet in the post. You might have just run an online punctuation.
But Octotop still had a clear obligation.
What must you do in the cons aftermath?
Ducking a challenge would seem quite pathetic.
So would a lie, but his proof quite magnetic.
Covered in weetabics, John in the bath.
Thank you, Claire.
Jerry Kaufman emailed me about my trip report, Best Trip Ever, and he says he enjoyed it quite a bit.
It was cool and awesome.
And then he apologizes and says that Claire has probably, he's beat enough about awesome.
He's sure.
And that is true.
Over the last 15 years, Claire has indeed teased me quite a lot about the word awesome.
But you know, it's good.
Did you just start that sentence with that's fair?
That's fair.
It was fair, Allison.
Look, right?
I'm a very egalitarian man.
Discon 3 have sent out a poll to, um, initially I thought to members, but I think they're trying to spread it as far and as wide as they can.
So if you're listening to this, hopefully you saw it.
I'm asking whether or not people would rather, they ran a virtual event in their original dates,
or they ran a physical event the weekend before Christmas in 2021.
And I filled in this survey and although I'm not sure whether or not I would go to DC the weekend before Christmas,
I do think I'd rather they try and do a physical world comment of virtual one.
So I tentatively voted for that option.
Um, Liz and Allison, did you do this survey?
And what did you think?
I did do the survey. Um, I mean, I'm not currently a member of Discon 3 and to be honest, whether they held a,
if they held it in person in August, I probably wouldn't go.
And if they held it in person in December, I probably wouldn't go.
Um, but for different reasons, because I think if they try and hold it in person in August,
no one is going to know whether that is actually possible for a good few months yet.
And so no one will actually be able to plan.
And the reason I wouldn't go in person in December is because it dates the 15th to the 19th of December,
and that is much too close to the end of the year.
So I think I said that I might attend their virtual one if they run, if they run that one,
but I want to end in person and I would not attend an in person.
Well, but I can definitely, I can definitely see why they've done it.
Because if you have put all that time and effort into thinking about a Worldcon and it's going to get dumped on by a pandemic,
and you could possibly just shift it a few months and do it in person,
then I could definitely see why that is a very tempting option.
However, I'm not sure it's a good idea.
I have not answered the survey and I think it might be a bit late now, even when we record,
um, because I felt that I was rather a biased observer in that I'm,
I certainly wouldn't be going to an August physical convention under the circumstances,
though I had previously had some plans to try and go to disc on.
I, there is no chance that I am ever going to go to a convention anywhere the weekend before Christmas,
unless I can, um, trade and I think that will be too difficult.
So, and in fact, I really couldn't anyway.
And, um, so, but if it was a virtual convention, I might go, particularly if they,
they've got a lot of things have developed from where Conzeland was,
and I think they could probably run an awesome virtual Worldcon if they put their minds to it.
And this might, if the, if the, if the decision comes down in favour of virtualising,
they've got quite a few months to get that right.
Um, I am unconvinced that they're certainly going to have a,
be able to have a physical convention in December.
Um, so I think there's a chance that they will be forced to virtualize,
again, and we'll find themselves virtualising at an unbelievably terrible time,
and it will all be a big mess.
Um, I wonder that they may have some, they may have some commitments with the hotel,
that are difficult for them because that's, all these conventions do have issues with hotels.
Um, why don't you think they'll be able to do an in-person convention in December?
Because I think that does look like a reasonably good bet.
Yeah, I mean, they think they will be able to.
I mean, I think there has to be some chance that they won't be able to.
Um, if they do, I think it will be quite small because it's a difficult time for travellers,
everyone has said.
The Smoffs have also got their, um, nickers in a collective twist about it because it's after Smofcon,
and that, um, that, that messes up all of the ways that Smoffs do things,
but I don't think that matters.
Well, surely it messes up even more things than Smofcon.
Uh, sure, because it would, well, for one thing, it would mean that site selection for 2022
would take place extremely late and basically cut six months off their convention cycle.
Um, I can't wear the bids are for 2022.
Um, not 2022, 2023, I mean, actually.
The two bids for 2023 are Chengdu in China and Memphis in Tennessee.
Okay, so a potentially very late 2021 Worldcon, if they chose to run site selection at the convention,
would potentially mess up the 2023 bid by giving them six months less to prepare,
and also potentially mess up anyone who wanted to run a 2023, uh, NASVIC if they wanted to do that
because they won't know who will be required.
Um, so I think there's, there's stuff like that, which would almost certainly cause more problems,
and I guess if you start wearing the Q goes right at the end of 2021,
it doesn't cause the same issues, but it does push them back quite a long way.
I was going to say, as, as has been noted, um, by many of the people on Facebook, um, it kind of causes havoc to all the other conventions that are also thinking about whether they can run, say between November and February 2021 to 2022,
because people who've made commitments to do things and work on this con are now thinking, oh, but hang on, now you're going to be two weeks after my own little local science fiction convention.
Um, and that messes those up.
So that could be a problem.
I think, I think I hadn't thought about the problem with science selection, but, um, I suppose, I suppose that is an important question, which is how would you do that? Would you, would you try and do science selection at the physical convention, or would you have a virtual thing earlier?
And how would you do the hugos?
Um, I guess, I guess there's not really a huge problem with having the hugos at Christmas, but it, it seems a bit of an odd thing.
I mean, you could just run a much more relaxed Hugo nomination, Hugo voting program process with a few moments in there, and then the administrators would have plenty of time to count the votes in your ward them in December.
Did discana having an all staff weekend? And I assume that this is the sort of thing that they are working through at the all staff weekend before coming to a conclusion?
That's why I think I've probably too late to fill in the survey.
I see, yes. I assume that they are taking the views of the staff at the all staff weekend, working through the issues at the all staff weekend, and then the board is going to make a decision shortly.
I do think site selection is very interesting.
Listeners who are not mired in, um, Worldcon politics may not know that the 2023 Worldcon bid is really spectacularly contested to a degree that I think is, is, is quite contested even by Worldcon standards because it's not a case of there are two bids and they both have very,
they both have proponents and detractors and they have some very, they are offering very different propositions being, um, Chengdu and Memphis.
Yes, I think we could probably discuss that in more detail, kind of in a different episode.
For listeners who may not know, Alison's busiest time of the year is Christmas because she is a person what sells things on that internet.
Like Octa Thorpe fridge magnets and t-shirts. Yes, and that means that she is busy over Christmas, so a convention for her would be a significant drop in income.
I don't have that problem because I'm an academic.
I could probably take time off and go to DC in December.
So I did vote because I think if it was rescheduled, I would probably go.
I've got family in the US and I'd be cool to have Christmas with them.
And yeah, I could see it happening if there was a vaccine and if it was safe.
I mean, obviously those are two gigantic ifs, but so, and I think I'd be more likely to go to that than I would a online convention because I don't know.
I'm not, I didn't go to Conzeland and I'm not, I'm not sure if I'd go to DC online, but maybe I'm, maybe I'm selling it.
It slightly depends how well they do the social spaces.
I suppose. But yes, Liz, would you, would you, what was the chance that you would go to DC in December if they rescheduled?
I think it's very unlikely for a couple of reasons.
One is that I would like to see my family at Christmas, which I will not be able to do this year.
And it is just infeasible really for me to go all the way to the US for the 15th to 19th and then go to the UK for Christmas straight after.
The second one is just my issue, which is that the big conference in my field, which is held in the US tends to be held in very late November,
in which case I would probably not want to go to the US twice.
I actually definitely wouldn't want to go to the US twice, but they're not quite close enough together.
I could do both of them in one go.
And I think there is also a third reason, which is, I think we're sort of assuming that there will be widespread, you know, vaccination by the end of 2021.
But that is actually not an assumption, which is going to hold true for everywhere.
So we don't know what the requirements are going to be for requiring vaccination if it would be required to enter the US.
It would be required to go on airplanes to the US.
But even if you think nearly everyone in the US will have been vaccinated by the end of 2021, this definitely does not hold true for countries which have less money and have not pre bought 600 million doses of vaccine.
So for instance, vaccination here is currently scheduled to start in June 2021 and to maybe finish sometime mid 2022. So it seems highly unlikely that I will have been vaccinated.
And I think that's going to be a problem for those Worldcon attendees.
I mean, I don't think it's an insurmountable problem because there's already like a million other.
A million other problems for people trying to attend Worldcon's from low and in middle income countries like visas and the cost and all of those things.
But this might just be an extra one on top of that. And we don't know how it's going to work yet.
Yeah, that's all fair. I think I support the decision they're making because I think basically it was clear from the server they sent out that basically these are the two choices like they can't hold it in 2022 because the 2021 Worldcon.
And like this is the only date they could move to if they want to try and do it physically.
So I do think it's worth asking the question.
I will be very curious to see what happens as a result.
Another thing that this con three have done is they have announced that they are exercising their their special was for skivin right to assign a special Hugo category.
And they're going to do a Hugo for the best video game. They follow in the footsteps of LA con four. I think that did this in the mid noughties.
It didn't work then. Will it work now? Liz your opinions.
I was going to say you say LA con did it didn't LA con run the nominations and then realize that they didn't have enough nominations to run a sensible.
So that's what category and then not run it. I think it is definitely I think it's actually well overdue that we have another go at this.
I think probably there are more people playing games when you.
I think there might be more people playing games when I think there are definitely more people playing a variety of stuff because they have access to phones and tablets and more mobile gaming devices.
So people who might not think they play games definitely do play games are and maybe more of them will now have stuff they want to nominate.
So I think it's definitely worth a go. I think the difficulty might be that I think games have quite a long life and sometimes have quite a high time investment.
So for instance, I've played quite a lot of games this year, but I'm not sure any of them were released in 2020.
And you also get to have fun with things like what about long running games which release updates or new content in 2020.
Because there is for instance a new World of Warcraft expansion, but are you awarding the World of Warcraft expansion or are you sort of tacitly awarding 15 years worth of World of Warcraft, which is not a problem right now because we haven't had any other video game.
So I think it's a very important thing to do with this game.
I think it's a very important thing to do with this game.
But then it's like if you wanted to do this more often, you wanted to make it a permanent category, then you have to think about that.
So it is a subcommittee which is chaired by Ira Alexander day.
I apologize if I got that name wrong.
And is the games Hugo subcommittee of the Hugo study committee and they gathered a bunch of data and evidence according to file 770.
I think if we want to go deep into the nuts and bolts of how the award will work, we probably ought to go away and before next episode, learn how it does work and have opinions based on that.
Because if we say a bunch of things about it would never work and then we read it and we're like, actually that's all questionable.
Yeah, okay. So before we do this properly, which we will do in a future episode, we can go, "Ah ha, we've done our homework."
But this is just a hot take on the announcement, which is a different thing.
Hot take.
So hot take.
And my hot take is that most people in the world, and certainly most attenders of Worldcons play video games, how many of those...
play video games that are narrative, I am not persuaded by.
Most of the video games that people actually play are not either not narrative at all, or the narrative element is so unbelievably shallow compared to actual, actual science fictional content, even the science fictional content on television and movies.
The amount of the typical Marvel movie, which as you know I criticise quite a lot, still has a ton more narrative content than even quite...
That is 100% steaming bullshit, Alison. And you know it is.
Like, I've played Horizon Zero Dawn, there is more world building in the first 20 minutes of that game than there is the entirety of the MCU.
And if that doesn't count as narrative, then what does?
Was it released in 2020?
I don't think so, but I believe that the sequel is either this year or next year.
But I don't think... I definitely think... So there are two things here, which is firstly, dot all narrative has to be...
You can have emergent narrative through world building, and I think that is something the games do very well, which virtually all other media that's recognised with the Hugo doesn't.
And I think the fact that that is a different sort of science fiction narrative doesn't make it a less valid science fiction narrative.
But secondly, there are loads of highly narrative games that tell really complex stories over hours of gameplay.
And I think it will be interesting because I think if it doesn't work, that will tell us a lot, but I don't think there's an inherent reason why it couldn't.
It will be down to whether or not people who vote for the Hugo's also play recent video games.
I think if they do, this will be a successful category.
My question is whether that is true. And that, I think, might end up being it's downfall.
Because I know I play a lot of games, but I haven't played much from 2020 in terms of video games.
I have just started playing a multiple award winning game from 2020, which...
Is it called "Dynamo Crossing"?
Where one group of people are saying this has amazing emergent narrative, and the other group of people are going, "Nah, it's a junkie Chinese free-to-play game that is just stealing your money."
And I think both of these things are probably true.
But I will be interested to see whether the narrative that emerges is actually...
I don't know, satisfying stories from emergent narrative.
Yeah, okay. They've probably got a lot in this.
So reading through the report from the games Hugo people, a couple of examples they gave of recent games,
are Assassin's Creed Odyssey, God of War, the Marvel Spider-Man game, Monster Hunter.
So they're all Death Stranding.
Oh, they missed Star Wars Jedi IV in order.
So I think it's twofold, which is firstly, emergent narrative is important.
But secondly, I think video games over the last...
I mean, it's probably not fair to say they never did this,
but I definitely think that in recent times there has been a shift towards video games telling more and more complex narratives.
And whether or not that's necessarily a good thing, it's kind of up for debate,
because I remember we had a panel at the two... at your EasterCon, I was in at Follicon,
where one of the panelists was like, "I've been agitating for games to tell more directed narratives for ages,
and now they've started, I don't like it."
I'm like, I mean, you know, who cares what you wish for?
Yeah, it's fair.
So the other half of my hot take, before John interrupted and said that is Stephen Pylov-Bollocks,
the other half of my hot take is, I also don't think it will work because I think there are far too many possible nominees
and the nominations will be spread way too thin, and the ones that will actually emerge to the finalists
will indeed be games which are the latest instalment in some massive franchise,
and I just don't think there's any joy in any of that, but there we go.
We wouldn't want a Hugo Cateri to be repeatedly dominated by the latest iteration of the same thing over and over again.
You wouldn't want something like Best Dramatic Presentation Long Form or Best Dramatic Presentation Short Form
or Selly Proceed or Fanzied or FanRite or Best Novel or Best Novella. That would be terrible.
But I think that the best video game, because of the lack of familiarity with the...
I mean, you can still watch every major genre movie that's released in a year, for example,
which is why discussions of Best Dramatic Presentation Long Form have such legs.
You cannot possibly play every relevant quality video game that's released in a year,
or even a tiny fraction of them. Most people are only going to be playing a few,
even if they're very keen gamers. And AAA games are extremely expensive,
so most people can't afford to actually survey the field in them, even if they had no other life.
That's actually really interesting. So just to follow up on that, that's a really interesting point,
because I was about to say there, you just wait for them to be cheap, and then I'm like,
"I have, but if you do that, you can't nominate."
Not in 2020, you don't.
Yeah, exactly. So that is actually a really interesting point, which is, like,
if you bought Horizon Zero Dawn today, it would cost you about £15.
But if you had bought it when it was actually first out, it would have been three or four times more expensive.
And so this is a Hugo category in a field where... I mean, obviously books get cheaper,
but they don't... And movies get cheaper because they come on Netflix.
The initial outlay in what sort of being up to date is far less, and there's...
Yeah, that is a very interesting point.
Since I'm currently... I'm currently skimming through the big report about best gamer and Tractic Experience category,
which I believe none of us has read, and does actually cover quite a number of these points.
So maybe we should read it. Also, it's got a link to a speedrun of Dragon Age Origins in 40 minutes,
which I'm dying to go and watch because it took me, like, 120 hours to finish that game.
So... Yeah, that's the other problem. They say there's 100 hours of gameplay in this, and I look at it and I go,
"I know that if I were to do this, it would be more like 400 hours."
I think we should... I think Jon should cobble together some kind of sensible saying anything else.
Good luck with the edit, Jon!
I knew it would be a nightmare.
When I'm not here this weekend, I am at an event that is being run in Gathertown.
Now, Gathertown's an online service that we didn't use, that we did consider for punctuation.
And in this thing, you can move around. There are places you can sit and chat to people.
Some of those are private, so your conversation is private.
When you go to sit and a place, it turns into a video chat, or when you are near people, you turn into a video chat.
So I had a brilliant interactive moment because I walked into this thing for the first time yesterday morning,
and immediately found myself in conversation with somebody who's basically a superstar in the field, and that was quite nice.
And, you know, I wouldn't have thought that he'd be a person I was likely to meet.
So that was quite nice, and I liked some of that, but more generally, my experience has not been entirely pleasant,
but partly because they're doing something where they're streaming.
People are making the talks in Gathertown, and then that is being streamed to an overflow space,
and then also streamed to YouTube, and all of those streams are way clunky compared to what you get to say a Zoom webinar.
So the actual video and audio experience is not as good, the little windows that you see people in a tiny.
It's got all of the problems that Zoom has in large numbers of people needing to turn off their microphone and video,
but not necessarily being able to see how to do that.
But the primary problem I'm having is one that people might have had by a punctuation, but we wouldn't know about it,
which is that apart from one person who told me it was happening, I don't actually know anyone there,
and because of the way it set up, the ability to meet new people is not that straightforward.
And they had interactive items, but they had all their interactive items at the same time,
so if that wasn't a time that was good for you, it wouldn't work.
So I feel like one of the things that made me feel was there might be people out there for who punctuation felt a bit like that.
They're probably not listening to this podcast, but if you know people who punctuation didn't work,
I'd really like those people to answer the feedback questionnaire.
But also, Gavitow is quite expensive, so this convention had a proper fee, not a fiver.
And that fee seems to be, it's also non-profit, it's being organised by enthusiasts.
Almost the entire amount I paid is covered by the amount they will have paid Gavitow for my per user for the weekend.
So it's absolutely not a good example of something that costs money, but doesn't necessarily deliver the outcome any better than what we've got.
I will say just very quickly, so firstly it sounds like Gavitow.
It doesn't sound like, I've used Gavitow to a great effect, we used it for a post-assession at a professional conference,
I was at yesterday and the day before, no sorry Thursday and Friday, and it worked very well for what we were using it for,
but I think you do have to be very careful, there are things that it won't work for at all,
and it sounds like what your experience is, one of them.
But I will also say that I think the problem meeting people at conferences or conventions where you don't know anyone is really difficult to solve.
So I think that might be a topic that we could discuss in a future episode, both from the perspective of trying to crack it at virtual conventions,
but also trying to crack it for people who come to physical conventions after the event has subsided.
Yeah, I think the things that we didn't crack are not so much, I think there's probably lots of things that we didn't crack,
but some of the things that we didn't crack that I would really like to crack are also things that affect physical conventions,
like essentially the flow of social space, like this was sometimes a proper punctuation either, there was no one in the bar,
or the bar was a big noisy conversation, it didn't work for me, but there was no one in a smaller conversation,
or we didn't really do enough to introduce people to each other and get people more involved early on,
I don't think we've really cracked those at many in-person conventions, there are always times when I've gone,
"Oh, the bar is too noisy, I'm going to give up and go home."
Oh, there's lots of people in the bar, but I don't know any of them, and I don't know who to talk to, that kind of thing.
So yeah, maybe we can crack them in virtual conventions, but then when we go back to physical conventions,
we can bring some of the lessons along.
I think that a friend of me and Liz are, I had a conversation with a friend who said that one by a punctuation,
they'd sort of wandered through the bar, not seen anyone they recognised or got to bed early,
and for them, that was incredibly similar to the feeling of a real convention, and I was like,
"Yay, I think, I'm not sure, but I do think I don't want to, I think it is a problem that persists,
and there's been a problem since Kvitjes started, and I am very keen to try and solve it by not going to,
I'm not going to say we're going to crack it, but we'll discuss it, I will try to go up with some ideas."
I mean, obviously, some of it is like, if you, you know, you might not want to meet lots of strangers.
But yeah, like, so I think in general, like, as an extrovert, I want to meet all the people all the time
and talk to them loudly, but I am aware that I am an extrovert, and so there might be people for whom
it's not their ultimate goal in any situation.
I actually, at this event, I did actually have a little moment of going,
"Well, I am an extrovert, and I am happy to talk to people loudly and meet all the people.
I'm not necessarily in a space of my life where I want, I necessarily want to make 60 new friends in a new fandom this weekend."
So I kind of turned it off in a way that I might not have done in real life.
So, real life, sorry.
I'm trying to avoid that.
If I'd actually been there for the weekend and I'd be committed to spending the whole weekend there,
"Oh, you betcha, I would have worked the room until I found myself with a companion of people to spend the rest of the weekend with you."
Which I don't think would have taken long.
I mean, I think they were nice people that have things in common with me.
Yeah, I think I am less extroverted than either of you.
I mean, that's not hard.
Did we mention the bell curve earlier, Liz?
Yeah, I mean, I think on the bell curve, I'm somewhere in the middle, which is,
I like coming and chatting to people, but I don't necessarily need it to be like a loud,
"I'm gonna meet everyone."
I'm also old and grumpy at this point, and so sometimes it's like,
"Well, I'd like to talk to people, but I don't really want to talk to new people.
I want to talk to people I already know."
It's hard to subtly nip into the zoom, see if there's anyone you know,
and then if it's not nip out again, I guess I could claim technical problems.
Whereas in the bar, you can kind of walk through the bar in a purposeful manner,
like you have somewhere to go, and if there's no in the bar,
you want to sit and chat to you, walk straight through to the side.
Okay, so here's the thing.
Gathertown is great for that.
Ah.
You walk through the Gathertown, and you see all the people in the little groups,
and you see the little names, and you have a list of everyone who's online at Gathertown.
Yep, and you can get directions.
You can click the person.
And you can locate people and go and find them, which is unbelievably useful,
and I would like that for the real world right now, please.
You could go and find them, even if they don't know you're doing that.
That would be great.
That would solve many of my zoom.
It's a bit stalky, but it's very, very good.
So, I mean, I want to give this platform it's to you.
It has some really good features.
Oh, yeah, 100%.
If you haven't looked it up and you enjoy video or Pokemon, go and look it up,
or, you know, other top-down RPGs with Pixlaid Graphics are available.
I think what I'm saying is I'd happily run a party in Gathertown for people I already know.
Oh, yeah, 100%.
I just wouldn't try to put talks and panels into it at all.
And the thing is, like, we could have used Gathertown for the social spaces punctuation,
and in some ways that would have given us something we didn't have
with the other three services we were using.
But I am, one of the things we were trying to do was every time we added a new service
to that mix of services we were trying to make sure it added enough to be worth the extra complexity.
And that is something I think is because we had people for whom it was already too complex,
and we had people for whom they wanted things that we had deprioritized in the favor of keeping it
as uncomplicated as we could, and, like, making that series of trade-offs is incredibly difficult.
And I know that we didn't hit upon the trade-offs that everyone would have preferred,
but I think, from my perspective, we'd probably hit on the most universal set of trade-offs we could.
But I think this is a bit like when you're running an Eastercon
and you've got a choice between kind of easy to get to by public transport,
big enough to have an Eastercon, and in a place people want to go pick any two.
And, you know, that is one of those awkward situations where you always have to compromise.
The physical event version of the thing I was at this weekend
is often held at one of those ex-civil service training centers
of which I was not previously aware, and I was kind of looking at its website going,
"Ooh, ooh, you could run a nice convention here."
You mean, like, the place where you've previously run a plopter.com?
Yeah, we ran Plopter at the civil service college.
I think it was still called the civil service college when we did it,
but it turns out that many large organizations that were once in the UK public sector
have a kind of training space of this kind, and I knew about a few of them
and had rejected them for one reason or another.
But this one looks quite promising.
They've mostly been public, they've been privatized now,
but most of them have been privatized in a way that still makes them quite affordable for a convention.
Because they are fundamentally quite, they were quite simple places,
a bit like, because they were kind of, I think the civil service college explicitly did this,
that part of its remit was to try and give people in the civil service
who had not had the obviously helpful experience of going to a boarding school,
a sense of what going to a boarding school was like.
So the original way these places were designed as residential training centers
was to evoke a past age of British privation.
And so there's a limit to how luxurious you could make them,
and that means there's a limit to how much you can charge for them.
And that's quite good because science fiction conventions are always looking for places that are kind of a bit cheap
rather than go for state of the art hotels that are too expensive.
That might have been about, yeah, I mean, I'm not really thinking,
it's going to be a long time before I run a convention in the physical world again, actually.
[Music]
I want to talk about meeting people in VR, which we did a little bit of punctuation,
but have then have done since.
Sell me on, Alison.
Sell me on an event I go to with my BB8 Google Cardboard,
which I had to get a friend from the US to get for me.
We used Mozilla Hubster on a VR event at punctuation,
and it was kind of a bit crap. It was okay, but it was...
I think you pronounced it wrong.
I think it's actually pronounced "Mothia" because it's Spanish.
Mozilla?
Mothia is possible that I've interrupted you to make a terrible joke for no very good reason.
Okay, I just, you know, I kind of like, I've been using Mozilla things since the beginning of time.
Well, you know, since before John was born, maybe?
It's just much better if you assume it's a Spanish word and pronounce it "Mothia" with the ham gesture.
Mothia!
Mothia, Firefox.
See?
Mothia, yeah, so, um, Mothia...
This is gold, it's all staying in.
You were about like five or six when Mothia came into being, I think,
so I've been using it for a very, very long time, but anyway,
so you did quite surprise me there.
But, um, Proofax said, um, oh, you will find that AltSpaceVR is much better.
And she said this enough before the convention that we could have switched, but I was like,
"But to use AltSpaceVR, people need a cap. They need a free account."
But AltSpaceVR exists, has free accounts, has two declines.
And, um, I like...
We went back last night, this was four of us, who include Max, who is a regular podcast listener,
and Proofax, who I'm not sure, is, and Lisa Conrad.
And we went back to this space, and we had a fantastic time, I think I can say,
partly because when you meet people in VR, you feel like you're in a space meeting people.
I've probably said this before, but that's kind of...
That's kind of one of the things I've been missing that I'm not getting from Zoom,
is that sense that people are in the same space as you, and at the moment,
that trick is happening for me in VR, and it is not happening for me in any of the...
Any of the flat things.
Um, Proofax had created a bar for us to meet, which would be big enough for, I don't know,
50 or 60, um, SF fans to hang out.
And when you arrive, it is a bit like being in a bar.
You can see that there's people over to one side talking, so you walk over to where they are.
That's kind of nice. I mean, you don't walk, you wiggle your controller, or move an arrow key or something.
Um, but then she'd got a lot of different worlds for us to visit.
And we went and visited a few other worlds, and in one of those worlds...
So there was a world with a functioning Stargate, and there was a...
Um...
Bridge of a spaceship and things like that.
And then in one of those worlds, some other people turned up, because what happens is, um,
people, for public worlds, you can see how many people are in them,
and because not very many people are in most of them, the four of us going into a world made it a popular world.
And so then other people would turn up, and we fell into conversation with somebody who said,
"It was like a middle-aged American man who said, 'Oh, you should come see my world, because I've got a castle with a rock club and a dungeon.'
And we went, 'Sure, let's do that in a way that, in real life, I think you're just there to say,
you would never go anywhere with somebody.'
He was like talking about his experiences of Burning Man, okay?
You know.
You're not wrong.
That is one of those situations that definitely plays out differently on the internet.
[laughs]
- His dungeon was not actually creepy, and we had an absolutely great time, and then he'd very cleverly, I think.
It turns out that one of the things you can do in old space is texture your walls by importing photographs to use as a texture,
and he'd got a photograph of him, which looked quite like his avatar.
He did a better job of looking like his avatar, and he'd got a photo of him on one of the walls,
and I was like, 'Well, that's actually, that's...'
If this was a real dungeon, that would be creepy, but in fact,
it's not particularly creepy in this context, because when you've been invited to somebody's dungeon music club,
you kind of want to know what they look like in the physical world.
And this was all...
We had a load of time...
You know, we like practiced flying, and we hung out on a pirate ship, and we just had a fantastically good time.
That's probably a little bit...
None of this stuff would be any fun on your own, but just having four or five of you doing it is enough for it to be a lark.
And again, something I've not been getting in the apocalypse, so that was quite nice.
I know that Liz obviously gets to go out and see real people in the real world, and that's something that's going to happen.
But some of us aren't going to be for a while.
VR, if you have headsets, if any of you have a headset and fancy coming and hanging out in some weird,
grandos, creepy dungeon with me, do let me know.
But it was so much fun, and it reminded me, because actually, we were talking about mods and text chat.
I'm wondering whether Jod has just logged on to Alt Space VR.
I'm riding a roller coaster, and I'm genuinely getting vertigo.
It's weird.
Okay, you need to be careful about that, because you can become quite sick in these circumstances, so...
Yeah, I might stop watching when I vomit.
Do you want to start watching, like, just while we do the podcast, maybe?
He slightly... he slightly derailed me. See what I did there.
Ha! Yes.
You were talking about how you went to some run's dungeon where the giant picture himself on the wall,
and it was somehow not as weird as it sounds.
Yeah, okay, so I do remember, and I'm going to cast one, but if you remember back in time to when we had text mods,
which we were talking about last time,
and one of the things about text mods is that it was possible to, in text mods, go off with creepy strangers
in a way that you would never do in reality as well, and go to their interesting, interesting mods that they'd set up.
But this was more of that, and more interesting, and it was all quite good fun, and we had a good time.
Well, I mean, I had a good time, and I think the others had a good time, it seemed to be.
But eventually, the other thing about VR headsets is that you could only do it for a certain amount of time,
and then you go, "No, no, no, I'm going to get my brain is frying."
If anybody has a headset out there and has not yet got involved in this tiny little bit of fandom,
then get in touch, and I'll give you the secret codes, or I'll introduce you to prove actually to give you the secret codes.
Right. So can I... so I can access this, so if I have an iOS device and a Google Cardboard, I can come along?
I don't... it has Windows and Mac clients. I don't know whether it has a Cardboard client. You should check.
Okay. It's owned by Microsoft, so I think there's a good chance it doesn't have a Cardboard client.
I'm basically waiting for my wife to buy VR, because she keeps saying she wants it, and I'm like, "Well, that's very nice here."
And pointless technology things I want, I pay for it. She doesn't go splitsies with Beyond, so I'll kide.
Hopefully this is where all of that comes back to really, like, I really get Baker return away investment,
and she randomly buys a VR one day. But it's one of those things which is highly expensive,
so I've never quite been able to justify it.
Okay. So the other thing about the creepy random with the underground dungeon, and if you're listening to this...
Creepy Rambo.
By the way, you're fine, okay? He was a cool guy.
Please tell me that you didn't give him the link to our podcast, and then exclusively refer to him as Creepy Rondo.
I don't think... I mean, I think I was in there with my real name there, because I only have one online identity these days, so...
Okay.
So he could probably look me up and find the podcast. I mean, I don't think he might.
But... Well, your band from his dungeon now, I think.
But we've been... So we've been kind of wandering around his world for a little while, and he said,
"Oh, and of course I don't actually have a heads. I can't really do the flying thing, because I don't have a heads set. I'm doing this on a laptop."
And we were like, "You what?"
Oh.
So he is somebody who had actually built the whole world, just using the 2D card. He wasn't actually viewing it in VR.
So... So that's the... It's quite strange.
Apparently it's all based on Unity. So theoretically, you could get any Unity 3D object in there, which...
I feel like there's quite a lot of scope there for quite exciting things.
If you wanted to, like, be Mario or some equivalent thereof, which I personally wouldn't on account of how I keep falling into bits,
and by being stomped on by Goombas, but, you know...
So yeah, I don't have a proper VR, but I've got a Google Cardboard.
If I can interact with this in any way using that, then do let me know, but it sounds like, from a quick Google, I cannot.
No, I don't have a VR headset. I am tempted to get one, but it would only be for the purposes of playing Beat Saber, so it would be on my PlayStation.
So... I still couldn't come and join you.
Beat Saber is just a game... I guarantee you'd quite enjoy hanging out at our bar.
Yeah, but can I do it from a PlayStation?
Yeah, I don't know, check.
Oh, that's the thing.
Anyone in my room?
Maybe not.
From my PlayStation, so I can play...
And this is the real problem.
I don't have any computer that would feasibly run a VR rig, so...
Oh, but remember, that's the whole point of the Oculus Quest, which is just standalone.
That's why I have one. I would never have one if you had to plug it into a thing.
Yeah, but can I play Beat Saber on it?
One day is manual by one.
So, but the problem is that the Star Wars Battlefront VR experience is only on PlayStation 4, but PlayStation 4 won't do the buy you've told me about, so I'd have to buy two VRs, Alison.
Two!
So if you had to choose, though, between the PlayStation Battlefront experience and the VR bar, it's gonna be the...
Hang on, did you just seriously tell me to choose between Star Wars or friendships?
Not difficult decision, Liz.
Star Wars every time.
Yeah, that's what I was gonna say.
To be fair, it might well be that it has come out on PC since then, but it was.
I know it was a PlayStation exclusive, but yeah.
I like that the Oculus Quest apparently comes with Oculus Quest color-coded batteries.
So for those who don't know, the Oculus Quest is sort of a mostly white with black trim, and it looks very good, and it comes with two AA batteries, which are mostly white with black trim as well.
I should say this is the Oculus Quest 2, I have the Oculus Quest 1, which is Chop Liver.
Ah, what?
Maybe I should get an Oculus Quest 2, just so I can repeatedly tell you to buy the second one.
It's... I'm not saying it's not gonna happen.
[laughs]
Um... Oh, I could get a Quest 2 Elite strap.
Yeah, it's complicated, John.
Right, so...
[laughs]
It's 49 pounds is what it is, Alison.
HTC... HTC Vive Oculus Rift, Rift S Goad Quest, Windows Mixed Reality in 2D mode on PC, and they have a beta-club for the 2D mode on Mac.
So although it says available wherever you are on for free, I think that doesn't include PlayStation or iOS or Android, all of which are places that you might well be.
So, no. Um... Mozilla Hubs or Mafia Hubs?
[laughs]
It's so worth it.
They've all done on the Mac.
They're so happy. They can't possibly express you.
Because every time you do it, you probably do the hand gesture, and it's beautiful.
Always.
[laughs]
Ah, I have no regrets.
Okay, no, I should look up the Mac client then. The beta.
Mafia Hubs runs in a web browser, so that might also work on devices.
Okay, good night.
Alison will send me lots of links, and there will... Alison will send me lots of links, and there will be links in the show notes, listeners.
Um...
You use Chrome on a Google Cardboard to get it to Mozilla Hubs.
Mafia Hubs!
Mafia Hubs? Okay, cool.
Good stuff.
I will not be joining you, but I am going to mention it quite a lot in order to now get Alison to do the hand gesture.
[laughs]
Yeah, well, I mean, I'm kind of like...
As also seated, Mafia Netscape!
[laughs]
Ah, dearie me.
I will have to content myself with the whole going out and seeing people in person, which...
Alright, Liz.
On that bombshell! That was Episode 20 of Octa Thorpe, and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
[music]
Yes, now you have a delivery.
Now, we won't mention it, but it's not Weetabix.
I thought from it that Alex Horne was behind you in a hat.
I am.
If we ever do Faddish Taskmaster, we have to get Steven to play Alex Horne.
I'm sure Steven's up for that. We don't know what to do.
Have we had to get Alison to play Greg?
Wallace.
No, Greg, have you not seen Taskmaster?
No!
Your homework is to go and see Taskmaster.
And then you will understand why we think you would make a good Greg Davis and Steven would make a good Alex Horne.
Okay, so this is like for when, in the after times, when we actually do punctuation live.
Yes, yes. I mean, it would work. But I would highly, I would say to you Alison, Taskmaster may be the best thing on British television at the moment.
Alright, and I don't think I'm exaggerating.
Okay, now that the Great British Bake Off is over, that is not actually saying a lot.
And I do not think any British shows are currently queued up in my life at all.
Watch Taskmaster.
But many, many, many non-British shows are.
How much Taskmaster do I need to watch in the busiest two weeks of my professional year?
And how much Taskmaster could I possibly leave to the two weeks between the two weeks between the final post for first class post and the second of January during which I do no work at all?
Yes. The answer to your question is yes.
I got confused with dates.
Yeah, I promise to watch Taskmaster a bit over Christmas.
And, and is it one of these shows like House of Games? Because Richard Osman was extremely funny on Stuart and Maconey.
And he was saying that House of Games, he couldn't get anyone to let him do it.
Because he wanted celebs to be on for the whole week.
And he couldn't get anyone to let him do it until Taskmaster.
And then everyone was like, "Oh, you mean like Taskmaster?" And he was like, "Yes, I've been banging on about this for years. You're nuts."
Anyway, he didn't say that because he's a very polite man on the radio.
Yeah, so basically Richard Osman was interviewed by Richard Herring on the Richard Herring Less Square Theatre podcast.
"Riholest to per."
And the thing he said is basically Taskmaster has kind of almost, has done an awful lot to reinvigorate the kind of game show genre.
Because it is the first show that has let you have a persistent panel and has demonstrated that that can actually be funny and a thing worth doing.
So yes, I think Richard Osman has mentioned this on other podcasts as well.
Taskmaster is almost infinitely better than House of Games to be fair, but...
Oh, I quite love House of Games though, so...
While I do fucking love Taskmaster, I will say that when we were chatting earlier and we said, "Oh, we won't need very much this episode."
Because we've already got a bunch of stuff in the last one.
We are now talking about even more shit, which is definitely not going to go into podcast.
So, should we move on to something that's podcastable? Yeah.
That's all after show to be fair.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod at Encompetech.com, used under a Creative Commons attribution 3.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.