Inhursing this joke for months, can I make it funny? Right.
*laughs*
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 68th episode of Octa Thorpe.
This episode is coming to you on the 13th of October 2022.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
I know, I'm Liz Batty.
And we have some letters of comment on the previous episode.
Well, we actually have a letter of comment on episode 63.
Yes.
Kev McVay wrote to us about episode 63, as said this is the first time I've written
a letter for several years, and we rewarded him by totally forgetting about it.
Sorry, Kev.
I mean, to be fair, it came in after we recorded 64 and then we went to wait to Chicago and
then all of that.
He talks about thoughts on fantasy con and he kind of talks about what happened there
a little bit.
And then he talks about Deep Wheel Acadia and the other Clark Award books and says that
Deep Wheel Acadia is a fascinating prose poem and he would have fought for it had he been
a judge.
But he says he would have been even more passionate about Burnt coat by Sarah Hall, which he seems
to be alone in talking about as SF.
So I might have to look that up.
Yes, I will go and check that out.
I read it, but I've read other, I've read other Sarah Hall novels, which I've enjoyed.
So I will go and check that out.
I possibly read them because Kev told me to read them actually.
So thank you, Kev.
I went on Zoom to a presentation or a performance of parts of Deep Wheel Acadia by Harry Josephine's
Giles at the Edinburgh Festival.
And it was very good.
She did the recitation in Acadian and then there were subtitles with the English translation.
But I would say that the practice of translating a Scots word, including some Scots words, to
common in English, like "cally" and "bide."
Into every possible translation in English and then mashing them together is a great
load of testicles nonsense.
I see what you did there.
Brilliant.
Is that funny enough?
It certainly, it echoed something we said when we talked about it the first time.
It made John laugh, so...
That's a lot.
I think that's the harshest lizards ever been about what about us as jokes listeners.
So Liz didn't find it funny, but she might have found it funny the first six times I've
said it.
Yeah, I think you may.
Somebody who isn't one of you guys caught me out doing this at a party a couple of weeks
ago and I was like, "Yeah, no, it's fair."
You go to workshop your jokes with different groups of people, Alison.
Yeah, but thank you very much for writing in Kev.
We liked your letter a bunch.
And Kev also says he finally started listening to Octa.
Recently and asks us not to tell him off.
We're never going to tell Eddie what off for starting to listen to our podcast.
I don't know much about growing communities, but I think part of it is not yelling at people
when they join.
Unless you're in a church that does that sort of thing, in which case it works for them,
but that's not us.
Yeah, you've never been church with Scotland, have you?
That did occur to be halfway through what I was saying.
And I was like, "Hmm."
And we should also in other news or in other mentions that we didn't pick up.
Last episode, congratulations to Raj for catching up.
We're very sorry that you have to wait two weeks for each episode now.
There's a lot of Octa though now.
There's going to be like three whole days of Octa thought soon.
That's a lot of Octa to catch up on.
Oh, no.
But I mean, if you don't, if you don't, then you're not going to, you know, get all the
Injokes and backstory.
So...
Yeah, I mean, if you're listening to this and you haven't listened from the beginning,
that is fine.
Do not listen from the beginning.
This is too late for Raj, but the rest of you can save yourselves.
Our sound quality was terrible.
The jokes are much the same.
We also heard from the very vulnerable and respected Mark Plummer.
Basically, I said on episode 66 that sending a fanzine to efansines.com was similar to
putting a book in the British Library.
And Mark points out that you do actually have to deposit fanzines in the British Library
if you apply for an ISBN for your fanzine or an ISSN, how common boy to one mine has.
The British Library will hound you for copies until you tell them that you stopped publishing.
So all of the issues of procrastinations are in the British Library.
Although I don't know if we've...
I don't...
I assume that copies of Journey Planet go into, but...
Chris, do copies of Journey Planet go into the British Library?
Please write to us.
I'd be astonished.
Plucked and never deposited, blocked up with the British Library.
Boo.
And was rather sniffy about fanzines that did, because we thought it was a sign that fanzine
might be a bit up itself.
So obviously if the British Library had written to us and said, "Send us your fans, you know,
we will prosecute them, we might have done."
What is fascinating about this is that there is one of the three of us that is the most
interested in fan history, and it is that person that did not bother to chronicle any
of the fan history with the Library of Record of the UK, and the person who is less bothered
did.
Yeah, that's because the British Library's record on actually looking after its ephemera
and stopping it from rotting is not great.
Other archivers are doing a much better job with fanzines.
Yeah, no, I have a whole rant.
Mark Plummer says that it's his understanding that old time fans were fairly diligent about
depositing their fanzines, and so the British Library probably has one of the best collections
of fanzines around.
I will apply for a reader card forthwith for the night to go and look at 1967 fanzines.
Oh, now.
Yeah, no, that would be a great galactic journey column.
Oh, god, it would.
That would be quite funny.
Oh, no, but the British Library didn't exist in that building until really recently, so
you'd have to be, it would be maybe more difficult than I think it would be.
I could still talk about going to the British Library with my readers cards and getting them
to say the things, so I could talk about the, the rotunda and so on.
And I have to be like, there must be some kind of paper catalogue in 1967.
Oh, yes.
I would be kind of interested if you'd go and do it though and find out what has happened
to anything they do have from 1967 what quality is it and how easy is it to actually get them?
Could be interesting.
Well, I mean, I'd have to get a reader's card first of all.
I will talk to one of, I know lots of people who do have reader's cards for the British
Library much more legitimately than this, but I am obviously researching fanzines from
1967 now, so it's fine.
You should be able to get one.
You don't have to have a good reason to have a library card.
Wanting a library card is enough, surely.
Not for the British Library, not for a reader's card for the British Library.
We also heard from Christopher J. Garcia and Christopher said that he was at the 1993 World
Con, Conference Cisco, and it was his graduation present to himself, and he's pretty sure that's
where he first met Alison, although anything more than 25 years ago is myth legend and subject
to hyperbole.
I mean, okay, so Conference Cisco is a blur.
Yeah, it is, it is like one five day blur to a degree that, I mean, more so than like
most things that happened in 1993 at this point, is it in a special blur?
Or is it just, it was 1993.
The extent to which my 1993 holiday in the United States is a blur is one of the reasons
why I texted Claire a thousand words on what I'd been doing the day before every single
day of World Con this year.
That's practice for the guff trip, but I am concerned that my ability to remember things
is not great.
I had not previously appreciated that one method of writing your trip report is just
to text it all to Claire as it happens so she can compile it for you.
It's definitely a way of doing it.
Claire is a saint.
Claire is an actual saint.
Hello Claire.
Oh, there's, there's some foreshadowing.
Do we do foreshadowing?
Yes, we do foreshadowing every week.
We can do foreshadowing.
That's foreshadowing.
Chris also says that he thinks the mic situation might have been due to conflicts between the
hotel and the union that made the costs more than we would think they should have been.
So yes, I had an author of that, but it is possible that there were some more political
things happening that made those costs less than just buying some more microphones.
And thank you for pointing that out.
Chris.
Yeah, there is definitely some stuff which seems quite foreign to me about like things
which have to be done by unionized employees, which yeah, I think does sometimes involve
anything that involves like plugging things in and wiring things up.
And I'm not sure how far that goes in terms of also managing stuff like that.
They clearly had volunteers who were managing like the live streams, but I don't know for
instance if running around with an audience microphone would be deemed to be, you know,
something you should have a union person doing.
I'm just not sure how far it goes.
But yeah, I think it is more complicated.
You couldn't just like go and borrow a bunch of microphones from somewhere and set them
up.
Yeah.
So listening, we do not think that Easter contact consists of borrowing a bunch of microphones
from somewhere and setting them up.
Just say.
No, but I mean, the fact there were four microphones in most rooms.
You couldn't have just gone and got a fifth one and plugged it in to the existing setup
and things like that.
Faramenderson was rolling with laughter on Facebook about the con running panels.
Faram said that they couldn't be filled at discount three because yes, the con runners
were con running.
So it might be that con running programming has been a problem at both of the previous
two world cons.
I mean, I don't know whether this is unique to us world cons, but it's definitely something
for future world con program teams to think about because, you know, you don't want to
put all that fantastic work in if it's going to go to waste.
Yeah.
And you might get a lot of people who say one of the things they can talk about on programs
is con running, but they might basically be able to go to those items and not actually
attend any because they're too busy.
Yeah.
So con runners or people who are interested in con running are high risk for not actually
getting to the program.
And that was the letters of comment.
So since we last recorded the British Fantasy Society have held fancy con and they awarded
the British Fantasy Society awards there.
Not many of them I've actually read, but I will call out the Sydney Bounds Award for
Best Newcomer, went to Shelley Parker Chan, who also got the astounding award from Wilcon.
So they're doubling up on that one.
They also presented one to a best on thought he went to Synopticon, the celebration of
Chinese science fiction, which is definitely on my to read list.
And his previous pick of mine in octa thought I had completely forgotten.
And they also presented the Carl Edward Wagner Special Award to Maureen Kincaid Speller,
a fan and critic and former Taff winner and lately senior reviews editor at Strange Horizons.
Maureen sadly died the day after this award was presented, which is a really a great loss
to science fiction fandom and to everyone who knew her personally.
I met Maureen very shortly after I came into fandom in the mid 80s and she was hugely influential
on me.
I mean she was a good friend back in the 80s and she was also very influential on developing
my thinking, critical thinking as a science fiction reader, because I've been extremely
voracious about kind of gosh wow oh boy oh boy oh boy before that.
And I think Maureen was one of the people who really encouraged me to slow down and think
a little bit harder about what I was reading and why I was reading and what I was getting
out of it and I hugely valued that.
And she wrote enormously entertainingly on huge ranges of subjects that were not science
fiction as well, including especially her cats of which she had a succession all with
great characters.
And for many years she's been living out in Folkestone, which feels like it shouldn't be
as far away as it feels like in Kent with her husband Paul Kincaid.
So I was very sorry to learn of her illness and then her death.
Yes I mean she produced great critical works but I also just remember when I came into
fandom I must have met a pretty early on which would you know make me probably a very over
enthusiastic and like annoying, like 20 something.
And she was just terribly friendly.
I mean even though I was not a critic and I had no standing in the field, there was no
snobby about it.
She was just welcoming to people who read books and wanted to discuss books.
I was very privileged to know her and to read what she wrote.
And she was I think the world's leading critic on the works of Alan Garner and I heard one
thing that people have said in In A Bitchory's of Thoughts is it's a shame that the fantastic
book that she clearly had in her about Garner is not now ever going to get written because
I think that's an enormous loss to studies of Garner and his work.
Yes a very great shame.
One interesting thing that happened this week is that they announced that The Last of Us
is going to be a major television series from HBO.
Now The Last of Us Part 2 was one of the Hugo finalists in the best video game Hugo.
But this is quite interesting because unlike I think most movies and TV shows that have
been made out of games, they're not saying we need to design a whole plot around this
world that was used for gaming.
They're basically saying no we've got a perfectly good plot here and we're just going to film
it to bring it to new audiences.
And I thought that was a really interesting development.
A lot of people who are not me are very excited about this.
I probably won't want to watch the series anymore than I wanted to play the game but
you know.
I mean when you said they announced it, they announced it several years ago.
Just to find that out.
Sorry it's got a schedule release date right?
Top it go.
It's got a trailer because it's now done and it's about to be released but I mean they've
been filming it for years and they announced like three years ago.
Okay sorry the trailer's excited people because the trailer looks like it might be quite good
by which I mean it looks exactly like the video game.
So the people who really like the video game are very excited.
Yes that is fair.
I just like the video game.
Glasgow in 2024 has seamlessly morphed like Caterpillar to a butterfly into Glasgow 2024,
a world con for our futures.
And they are going to be the 82nd world con and they're going to be in Glasgow, Scotland
from the 8th to the 12th of August 2024 and you can join now.
So we're going to talk about the guest of Honorslate which was announced at ChaiCon
and then we'll talk about other things as well.
You're going to tell us who the guests are John?
The guests of honour for Glasgow are Chris Baker who may be better known as Fangorn to
our listeners, Claire Briley and Mark Plummer, Ken McLeod, Neddie Okorafor and Terry Windling.
That is a pretty good roster especially I think Ken McLeod is a very good choice as
a preeminent science fiction author of Scotland.
Chris Baker has been a noted artist in the community for a very long time so it is good
to see him being recognised on the World Constage as well.
And we ought to have Claire Briley and Mark Plummer, Friends of the Podcast.
Yay!
So it turns out that I had been not paying attention to my email and to the promotions
chat and to the Glasgow at ChaiCon WhatsApp group as a result of which I had no idea who
any of the guests were when we stood up behind Esther at the business meeting on Sunday morning
when they announced the site selection results.
And because I've been a bit busy over the last few days it has not occurred to me to
ever wonder who the guests of honour for Glasgow might be.
So they started reading the essay out and the first one was Chris who obviously I've
known since the 80s definitely and so I was like oh they're probably going to be people
and authors who are active in the UK.
I hadn't thought about this at all so I was very pleased to hear Chris's name be read
out.
And our next guest come at the other ends of the alphabet and Esther this kind of leader
at about half a sentence into the leader and I was like oh this is Claire and Mark.
Oh!
Yes it was quite, I clued in very quickly because I was like well it's a pair of people who
are going to be read out together and I was like well it's probably Claire and Mark then
because there's no one else I can think of in British fandom who meet this definition.
Well yeah it was the point where they talked about their fan writing.
Oh no I got it before I got it just from the names.
Oh okay well so John is cleverer than me but at any rate John I was I was um were you
up at the front as well.
I'm definitely in John on my Cluedo team not Alison I think so I've learned.
Oh definitely you should have John on your Cluedo team and not Alison because I'm very
bad at Cluedo I just kind of wander off and get a drink and stop paying attention about
the third of the way in and it's not good.
I'm bad for Cluedo.
I lost it and I was on stage at the time and you know along with a thousand other Glasgow
people it wasn't too bad.
I lost my composure at that point and I didn't really get it back but I do what I was also
very excited by Ken McLeod because the first British convention that Ken McLeod was guest
of Vodirat was plopped.com which I was on the committee for and I was very excited about
Nadia Cora for because the first British convention that Nadia was a guest of Vodirav was Volekon
which I was on the chair of and this was on the committee for at least for part of it
and so it was really great list really well done guys excellent, excellent guest of honor
I don't think I could have done better if I'd personally been picking them so I'm very
very happy with your guests that was really really good.
Yeah I was also at the front I did eventually retreat to my chair because my back was hurting
a lot but it was really good it was nice the announcement was very good I had successfully
guessed that Fangorn would be one of the guests in the lift with Liz I did not guess
correctly the other guests but I had a pretty good stab.
What you doing 24 John?
Oh I have resigned.
No no no 24 Worldcon because you got called up to the front.
Oh I've been just generally occasionally helping they said anyone who's helped at all come
to the front and I was like I guess that is including me smuggling Jin.
And also Esther asked for us specifically and for you specifically I feel like she thinks
with the official podcast of the Glasgow 2024 Worldcon which we are 100% not guys.
Well but we do have the same purple and in fact we do not have the same purple but we
do have purple so you know.
It's true I only need to buy one set of like convention t-shirts for 2024 because I'll
just wear the same purple one and maybe turn it inside out.
I think you'll find that Glasgow 2024 merchandise is going to be using a lot of different
purples and I can talk about why that is at length but it's very very boring.
Is it because you can't get the same purple in all the different types of shirt?
It's because every shirt blank company has a slightly different purple.
We could be the official thorn in the side of podcast of the Glasgow 2024 Worldcon.
I mean I like to think of myself as an ally.
Would you say Glasgow 2024 also have their own official Glasgow tartan?
Yes, landing zone it's called.
It's very fetching.
If you watch the Hugos you would have seen Vince Dokoty as one of the people who you know
the glamorous people who hold the Hugos on stage so people can go and receive them in
his full landing zone tartan kit and it was very impressive.
If you watch the was for Christmas meeting for Sunday morning which we're going to put
a link to in the show notes because it's got all the Glasgow presentations and stuff.
There's a lot of people wearing tartan kit and looking lovely in it because it's a really
nice tartan.
It was designed by Sarah Felix and you can buy a kiln or you can go and buy the cloth
which unfortunately is wildly expensive because that's how much traditionally made tartan
costs.
It's not because they're making a huge profit or anything but yeah and it's a really lovely
tartan.
I said we're going to make our own tart and I was like oh oh but it's beautiful so well
done guys.
Now it was very good and it was modelled by Sarah Felix as well as Vince.
You probably find pictures on various Glasgow outlets.
Esther has a beautiful mini dress.
Ian Stockdale had a very fetching kilt.
Yeah it's a lovely, it feels like a lovely balanced set of guests.
You know it's got some guests who are very well associated with British fandom but it's
got some guests who are maybe a little bit newer and have only appeared at one or never
at a convention in the UK.
It's got writer of science fiction, got writers of fantasy, we've got artists, we've got fan
writers.
It's a good set basically.
Yeah I'm going to have to read some of Terry Windling's books which I have not yet done
but I've read Ken McLeod and Nedy Okoraford and enjoyed their fiction in the past.
I've always wanted to own a piece of Fangorn's art but he's really good to say his art's
quite expensive.
Ok so Stephen and I bought ourselves a piece of Fangorn art as a kind of present to ourselves
at the 2014 Wilcon and it has been sitting waiting to be framed ever since so that might
be my present for myself which is that I should get it framed and get it on the wall
like somebody who's not a complete idiot.
I think you should.
The challenge is to get it framed and on the wall before the 2024 Wilcon.
Yes.
It's the most expensive painting I've ever bought.
We should talk about memberships.
We should talk about how you can join Glasgow yeah.
So I am a member of Glasgow, I'm fairly sure I owe them 20 quid but I need to work out
whether that's true and then give them the 20 quid.
If you were a friend of the bid and you voted at Choycon you are an attending member now.
If you were a friend of the bid and then you didn't vote at Choycon I believe you can
pay an uplift which is equal to a WUSFUS membership and you will be a full member of
the bid but that includes within it the concept of the WUSFUS membership which is what used
to be a supporting membership.
Basically you have to have a supporting membership to go to Glasgow or to support Glasgow and
you can't sell that on once you have bought it is non transferable but once you have bought
your supporting membership you can then buy an attending upgrade which allows you to actually
attend the convention and if you later want to sell that attending chunk you can do that
if you so desire.
There are discounts for various tiers and there are discounts for young adults and teenagers
as well.
The cost of a new participant is £170 all in which is £45 for the WUSFUS or the supporting
membership and £125 to actually attend.
WUSF's memberships is fair to say have caused a little bit of confusion in the community
despite really just being the new name for supporting membership.
This is a change that's been made by the business meeting.
I think to make it clearer that everyone is a member of the WUSF because a lot of WUSF
members don't realise that and believe that the things that WUSF does are somehow separated
from them and they're not part of that.
So this is to make it more obvious that you are if you're at the WELKON or if you're
a supporting member of the WELKON just to get a vote packet or whatever your involvement
with the WELKON is you're a member of the WUSFUSFUS society.
That gives you all of the rights and responsibilities that go with that.
Are there any responsibilities?
The thing is it doesn't really give you all the rights that go with it.
It's my argument about this.
No, so it gives you the right to vote in site selection and in the Hugos which are both
obviously key parts of WUSFUS but it doesn't give you the right to vote in WUSFUS.
So you can't go to the WUSFUS business meeting and you can't affect WUSFUS in any way if
you only have a WUSFUS membership and that is silly and it is more silly.
It was silly before they renamed it but now they've renamed it and it really makes it
clear how silly it is.
Ooh, that's quite good.
So they could start to do things like my bank or my building society does where it sends
me out a pack of papers saying do you want to exercise your proxy votes at the meeting
and people could turn up at the WUSFUSPISPY meeting with a huge handful of proxy votes that
they collected from people online and that would be awesome.
Yes.
I can't do that moment because there's obviously no way of doing any proxy voting.
No.
And so it can only be introduced by a vote of the people who are actually attending.
Yes, it's supposed to make people feel more like members but what it seems to actually
do unfortunately is be a bit confusing and then when people say, okay, so a member of
WUSFUS can I vote in the WUSFUS like annual meetings?
No.
My second argument against it is I have occasionally sat on bid tables and chattered to people
who are thinking about coming to conventions and they will say things like, oh, well, I'd
like to but it's a bit expensive and previously I've been able to say, well, you can just
buy a membership now because it will never be cheaper and then you can, if you can't
attend, plan to set it on to a third party and it'll always be at a discount.
If you, if you sell it to them for what you paid for it, it's probably going to be a discount
for what it's being sold for currently and so you can usually manage to sell them up.
This is no longer true because you can't sell the, uh, supporting bit.
You can always sell the attending bit.
So unless you really want that supporting membership, it, it's not as good a deal anymore.
And of course, there are people who like to have supporting memberships anyway, but if
you're thinking I would love to go to a worldcon, I've never been to a worldcon, but they're
really expensive.
Shall I buy my membership now when it's cheapest, knowing I could then sell it on if necessary?
Kind of that goes away.
I don't know how many people that does affect.
I don't know how many memberships actually get transferred, but it feels a bit sad I
can't actually tell people that's an option anymore.
I will just say that if you are an American worldcon attendee, you should absolutely
buy it now because the ratio of pounds to dollars will not.
I mean, might get better if something's got really horribly wrong, but like equally why
get quite a lot worse.
So I would say that advice from Liz, if you're in the state, is still pretty good advice.
That's the OctaThorp currency speculation podcast.
Um, but yeah, it basically means you can't sell on the, it means you can't sell on the
Wussfuss bit, which means that you could probably get what you paid for it minus 45 pounds.
And if you are sufficiently hard up, that that is a big chunk of money for you.
That does change a lot of your thoughts around it probably.
The reason this was done was because they didn't want people to be able to buy memberships
to worldcons that didn't include the right to vote in the Hugo's or insight selection,
which is I think in theory, a very good and noble thing because in the old days, what
you could do is buy an attending membership, use the rights to vote and then sell it on.
And the person you sold it to would therefore not have the right to vote.
And there was a thing about kind of the principle of the thing being that every member should
have the right to vote.
And they've decided to square the circle in this manner.
I mean, I'm not sure how many people that affects, but I think that was part of the logic.
That's the nobility thing, but there was also a practical argument, which is that the business
of tracking, when memberships were transferred, the business of tracking, which rights have
been used and which rights hadn't, was a massive headache for Worldcon organizations
and the membership team.
And it's quite unusual for the worldcons to actually, the con-running bit of the World
Con to actually come to Wispers and say, "This is a major pain point for us, and can you
do this thing that reduces the amount of pain it is to run the convention?"
And this is a case where that happened, which is why Glasgow was planning to do the whole
Wispers membership thing, even if it hadn't been ratified, they would do it.
Well, there was a much simpler way of, well, I think there's a simpler way of doing it,
which is you just declare that you can't split the membership rights in that way and whoever
owns the membership, owns the voting rights.
Because if it's Hugo nominations and voting, I guess that would only affect the paypons
because if it's online Hugo nomination and voting, you can always go in and overwrite
your form on the website.
And if it's site selection voting, you can vote twice anyway.
I can see how that would be a logistical nightmare from the administration perspective, though.
So this is a rare case where Wispers has done something that the Worldcon-running community
that's not the Wispers see bits of it wanted them to do to make their lives easier.
So, and I would strongly recommend that if you're interested in site selection and fantasy
and you're in this community, if you're any of the people listening to this podcast, then
if you can afford it and obviously pay your rent first, buying a supporting membership
for the Worldcon each year is quite a good way to get your hands on a ton of interesting
site selection and fantasy and be part of this really excellent global community that talks
about it.
I'd strongly recommend having a supporting membership every year.
And as you know, Bob, I get to a Worldcon about once every five years.
Sting Lee Sheryl Morgan wrote about Tricon 8 in her fanzine Salon Futura.
And she writes about Wispers memberships and seems to think that it's unpopular with
the people who are Worldcon runners.
And she says that, and this is a quote, "I am already seeing people complaining they
are being ripped off because they are forced to join Wispers when they only want to attend
Worldcon and that is absolutely a result of the way the changes being explained to fans
by Worldcons.
That's a very hard padding to stare for you, Glasgow."
And so I think she particularly is unimpressed with the job that Glasgow is doing communicating
this to its membership.
And so it is interesting to me that you said that Glasgow was planning to do this anyway.
I might be wrong about that.
I think they were there.
Because I have to say that although I think it is a little bit complex, I don't think
Glasgow has explained it very well.
And so I had assumed that they had not been planning to do it and had done it at the last
minute.
And maybe that's unfair and a sorry for anyone who's listening from Glasgow who's like,
"No, we definitely were planning to do it all along.
John is being very mean."
But yeah, I do think the Glasgow pages that explain this, they make it sound very Byzantine
and I think there are ways to explain this which make it sound quite a lot less Byzantine.
If you could explain something so it sounds simple, it often feels simple and if you explain
something so it sounds complicated, it often feels complicated.
So if Glasgow, if you're listening to this, right, it's a lock.
I might have been completely wrong there in which I was sorry but also tell us what you're
doing to make sure that Wilcott and potential members are not put off by having to buy a
wistous as Angiproted very, very cogently in anonymous flair.
I do think it's getting horrendously complicated just because of all the kind of permutations
of friends and good friends and bid supporting and so on.
And the fact that you have, especially if you have full attending and young adult prices
and child prices and team prices, the matrix of how much it costs you is really, really
complicated.
I think if it applies to you, you probably know, so maybe we need to think about how
we communicate.
Maybe it needs to be upfront on the pages, it needs to be the cost for the interested
person who is just this minute heard about Glasgow in 2024 and just wants to know what's
involved and then a bit late to have the and if you are a friend or a supporter or a pre-supportor,
this is like how much it costs you because, to be honest, I looked at the matrix of how
much things cost and was like, I'm just going to ignore this because I know I've rented
the bin voted so I don't have to worry about it.
And it was the same for Chengdu, I think they had to basically redraw their list of how much
it would cost you to do various things because it was so confusing.
So I think that is an area where we need to be thinking about like what do we communicate
to prospective members?
I will say, I think you're right, I think that is not as much to do with wistous memberships
as it is to do with how world con bids are funded.
Yeah.
Because I also found that very confusing with London Con 3 and obviously that was a long
time before this but like you get friends and super friends and like really really fantastic
friends and fuck buddies and all of these things and it gets very confusing.
Is this something I can sign up to for Glasgow 2024?
I'll ask you for a friend.
I don't want to make any pronouncements on behalf of the Glasgow 24 con con.
Sorry, I'm very inappropriate.
But we are generally very excited about Glasgow, I will be there with bells on.
I already have my attending membership on account of having pre-friended and then voted.
So I will be definitely there and definitely voting on all the things and etc.
I am a friend.
I am a super, I was a super friend.
So I think that might be the first time I've ever super friended a convention?
Because that's how excited I was about Glasgow.
So for people who don't know because I sell t-shirts for a living, I have a lot of money
in January and no money any other time of the year.
So either this last January or the one before that, I was like, I have all the money.
I'll give some money to Esther.
And Liz has already said that she was also a friend and then voted.
So is also an attending member.
So we will see you there.
If Glasgow is listening, we'd quite like a programme slot to a live octa thought, please.
It might be a bit early, but yes, happy bit.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's assuming we're still doing the podcast in 2024, which is, yeah, John.
Even if we're not, we'll do a reunion episode.
Yeah, no, for that.
Not for that.
Unless we're not doing the podcast because we've had a massive dust up of the sort that
resonates through fandom for generations and people, even if it's me on my own with
two sock puppets that I have painted, Alison and Liz on.
Fuck you, John.
No, you cannot do that.
And here begins the massive row, isn't it?
I'm totally fine with that, but I will be judging you for my image rights on the sock
puppet, obviously.
Liz is the Bruce Willis of Octorpe.
We should get one of those galaxy edge artisans to make sock puppets of me and Liz that you
can only buy at work on.
Yes.
OK, who wants to do their pick first?
I'm going to go last because I haven't picked anything yet.
I'm frantically scrolling through my good reads.
This is going first in case you struck by lightning before the end of this podcast.
So my pick is slightly cheating because I haven't finished it because I spent a lot
of this week reading a book for various reasons that we will discuss on Octorpe later and possibly
I will send.
Oh yeah, I spent a lot of this week reading a book too.
What coincidence?
John, did you spend a lot of this week reading a book?
Now this answer is not going to make you happy because the answer is yes, but it wasn't
the book I was supposed to be reading.
Right, Liz, do your pick.
Yes, so my pick is a video game.
It is a video game.
I haven't finished yet, but really I'm already getting the value out of it.
My pick is Return to Monkey Island, which is the sixth video game.
I think it's the sixth video game in the Monkey Island series, a series which started
30 years ago.
Yup.
When was the first Monkey Island game game that came out because I played it when it
was new?
See, this is the thing.
I'm pretty sure I played the secret Monkey Island when it was new.
1990.
So we both played the first one when it was new and that although it wasn't before John
was alive, it was before John could manipulate point and click video games.
So the secret Monkey Island games are classic point and click adventure games from Lucas
film, which anyone of a certain age range really remembers fondly.
They had several sequels, which to me have been a little bit diminishing returns, although
I haven't played the fifth one, which is supposed to be really good.
And they suddenly announced a couple of months ago that they had been making a sixth game
and it was going to come out.
And it's the creators of the first two games, which I feel are the best classic ones.
Yeah, and it's out and I'm playing it and it is very much like a classic Lucas film
adventure.
It no longer has like a big chunk of the screen taken up with verbs that you can use, but
it's all very inventive so that instead of looking at things when you hover over them,
it kind of tells you what might happen if you click on them.
And for instance, I was hovering over a poster and it told me if I clicked on it, I would
not look at the poster, but I would make a terrible pun about the poster and things
like this.
It is, I mean, it has a lot of fanservice.
I cannot really say how this places someone who does not know why it is a joke that there's
a pirate with an ask me about loom button in the bar.
But if you think that is funny, ask me about loom.
Yes.
Because I played loom when it came out too.
Well, that was your mistake.
It was amazing.
Fantastic game.
Amazing.
Just kind of also jit in.
Anyway, it's got the same puzzle.
I think the puzzles are a little simpler.
I haven't had to combine like four items in incredibly weird ways yet, but I have had
to make a mop from scratch, which was quite fun.
And so I'm about a third of the way through it and I'm enjoying it immensely and it's
available for Mac and PC.
And yeah, if you played any Monkey Island games, you would probably enjoy this one.
And Nintendo Switch.
And Nintendo Switch, but I haven't bought one of those yet.
And it's interesting because the first ones were developed by LucasArts and one of the
things that Disney did when it bought Lucasfilm was shut.
LucasArts, which was probably a fair decision at the time because LucasArts hadn't done
anything good for a while at that point.
But this is kind of being published by Devolver Digital and they are doing it, I guess, because
they have negotiated the rights of the Lucasfilm.
But it's nice to see that kind of Gordian not get cut through because this is the first
game by the creator of the original two games since he left LucasArts in 1992.
To be fair, I think the fifth Monkey Island, which I haven't played, is a collaboration
with Telltale Games.
Yeah, it was not entirely done by LucasArts all the way through.
That age range that remembers the first Monkey Island extremely fondly has to be quite large
because it includes people who are Liz's age and also people who are my age and probably
even some people who are a bit older than me.
Do you think I've played it very young?
I've played the Monkey Island games when they got remastered.
Do you want to do your pick, Alison?
I do, I do.
So I read a book all week, but obviously I'm not talking about that.
And I've probably got a pick for, I'm also watching a bit more of the Expanse, but I'm
not going to pick that again.
So this time I am going to pick the very timely WandaVision, which I think is about three years
old now.
Well, it was up for a Hugo, wasn't it?
So it was 2021.
It was up for Hugo this year.
So it was a 2021 series, but I finally got around to watching it.
People are tracking my progress through the Marvel Cinematic Universe.
We'll know the time even slightly less behind than I was, but I'm still very behind.
I thought WandaVision was really quite good.
So as you know, I have a complicated relationship with the Marvel Cinematic Universe.
There is a explanation of senility that says that one of the ways that you can first see
your deteriorating mental state is that you can't quite hold all the elements of plots
and characters in your head at once.
So this has happened to me with the MCU.
So I significantly failed to remember key bits about the Marvel canon that it would have
been quite useful to know before I started watching WandaVision, but it didn't really
matter.
For those who don't know, it starts as a sitcom featuring Wanda Maximoff, who is an
ongoing character in the Marvel Cinematic Universe and her husband, Vision, who is also
an ongoing character in the MCU, kind of channeling.
I love Lucy and comedy shows of that type.
And you kind of watch this show.
But apart from just a couple of moments, the first episode is an exact prestige of '50s
and early '60s comedy shows.
And then over the next several episodes, it goes forward in time when you gradually work
out what is really going on.
And it turns out that it all is not what it seems, which I mean a clever reader will
have known from the beginning.
Nine episodes in total, it wouldn't be the MCU without a pointless superhero battle at
some point.
The '50s does happen, but there's not that much of that.
And it all gets wound up in a very interesting way, I think.
And there's some really good bits about philosophy and identity and culture.
And I thought it was quite a good thing to have on one's 2022 Hugo Ballot.
It didn't win, did it?
What did win?
-Tune.
-Arrakis, a desert planet.
-But it went on as a single series, which is quite right.
None of the episodes stand alone.
So I thought it was pretty good.
I think I would commend it to you.
-I also liked it.
It doesn't stick the landing as much as it might have done, but it was filmed from
November 2019 to March 2020, and then something happened in March 2020 that made it difficult
to keep filming.
So I do kind of give it largely a bit of a pass on the ending, because I do suspect that
if the Covid pandemic hadn't happened, we might have seen it end slightly differently.
Especially stuff like, "Oh, what's Kat Denning's character's name?
Liz, who just Kat Denning's play?"
-Darsie.
Darcy in particular kind of just vanishes, and like, it's like, "Oh, where did Darcy
go?"
And the answer is probably locked down.
But generally speaking, I really liked it, and I especially liked seeing the kind of,
the return of Darcy and Randall to the MCU, because they are both people I very much
like are not, not Randall.
Oh, Randall Park is the actor.
What's the character's name?
-Liz, what's the character's name?
-Don't know.
Go and Google it.
-Jimmy, Jimmy Wu.
-Oh, yeah, Jimmy Wu's great.
-Jimmy Wu is great.
He should be a more things.
If anyone hasn't seen "Always Be My Maybe," you should, because he is the lead and writer
on that movie, and he is extremely good in it with Ali Wong, who was also a writer and
the other lead.
-Didn't we have some pick a few weeks ago where someone recommended something, and then
John said you should watch "Always Be My Maybe"?
-Yep.
I will keep recommending it, because it is...
I just love that movie so much.
-Okay, well, that's my pick for next episode sorted then.
-It's not science fiction though.
-It's genre, right?
You promised me it's genre.
-No.
-It is genre, just the genre is rom-com.
-There.
-But it has the best celebrity stunt casting of any movie in the history of cinema.
-Speaking of celebrity stunt casting and WandaVision, there's a very good bit of celebrity stunt
casting that is taking advantage of the fact that the X-Men is now owned by Disney along
with everything else.
-And is quite a funny joke, which I didn't get because I really wasn't paying close enough
attention to the MCU.
But there's some funny stuff going on around that that I think probably if you're kind
of into reading Marvel tea leaves gives you some hints about where Marvel might be going
with the X-Men.
That's not too much for spoiler is it?
I don't think that was a spoiler.
-It's a TV show from 2021 that was nominated for a Hugo.
So I think you can fairly say the statute limitations is up.
-Yeah, I don't think that was a spoiler anyway.
But there's some really funny things in WandaVision as well as some really quite clever things
as well as some really interesting discussions on how you're affected by major life changes
and what it means to be human and all of that stuff.
And I really liked it.
And I like the fact that I was trying to do something a bit more complicated.
-Have you seen Doctor Strange and the multiverse of madness yet?
-I can't.
I've got homework, John.
There are prerequisites.
There are a lot of prerequisites, right?
-No, WandaVision is basically the prerequisite.
-I would argue WandaVision is a strict anti-prerequisites.
I think maybe by...
No, not even Spider-Man.
Maybe Spider-Man.
But like, WandaVision should be a prerequisite except that the two don't make sense together
at all.
-Oh, I thought that WandaVision was the prerequisite for Doctor Strange and the multiverse of madness.
That was one of the reasons I was watching WandaVision.
-WandaVision was filmed and written after Doctor Strange was but released before.
And it doesn't really...the character of Wanda doesn't really make any sense between the
two movies, I would argue.
I liked Doctor Strange but I think having seen WandaVision might actually be an impediment,
not a plus.
Doctor Strange and the multiverse of madness I think has a much stronger reading as to
what they're going to do with the X-Men than WandaVision does.
Again, celebrities don't casting.
-Okay, so are there any other...
I wanted to watch the Spider-Man's before Doctor Strange?
-All of them?
-I don't know, which ones?
-I mean, it depends how much you want to do your homework but I mean, they're all referenced.
-I watched "Hemcoming."
-I mean, spoilers for a movie that came out a while back.
I think we've already spoiled this on the pod anyway but the Spider-Man's from the original
Sam Raimi trilogy and from the amazing Spider-Man are in it so you'd need to watch those five
and then you'd probably want to watch both of the Tom Holland ones if you want to like
fully do your homework.
Oh, and you need to watch Doctor Strange one.
Or you could just watch it because it's fine.
-Yeah, are you vaguely aware that there has been more than one actor who played Spider-Man?
Because just go ahead and watch Spider-Man no way home, it's fine.
-Yeah, no, I think I've had this spoiler already.
-Yeah, just go ahead, just go and watch this.
-I love Spider-Man.
-And also I've seen Spider-Piggle, whatever it's called, Spider-Man of the multiverse of...
-You don't have to have seen that one.
-Oh, boo.
-I mean, you do on account of how it's a great movie.
It's a good film.
-I will say the thing I really like about No Way Home is that it gives Andrew Garfield
Spider-Man like an actual ending, which I really enjoyed because Andrew Garfield, although
I don't think, especially the amazing Spider-Man 2 was a hot mess by like Andrew Garfield's
portrayal of Spider-Man the best out of the Spider's men there have been.
-On the count of Andrew Garfield's a really fantastic actor and he's good in every single
thing he does to the extent that...
-Yes, he is.
-I will actually go and look for things that have Garfield attached to them now because
I think he's very good.
-He's just great.
-So, yes, I was thinking of watching So Homecoming and then there's probably another one after
Homecoming.
I've seen Homecoming.
-There's Spider-Man No Way Home.
-There's Homecoming and then there's Far From Home.
-Oh, it's Far From Home, yeah.
-Homecoming then Far From Home then No Way Home.
-Right, so we need to see Far From Home and No Way Home.
So that should be doable.
I can probably fit a Spider-Man into today probably.
-So, with a month maybe.
-I'm going to do my pick.
My pick for today is a vertical empire, History of the British Rocketry Program by C.N. Hill
which is a book that was recommended to me by Nick Gibbons.
This book is really good.
It explains kind of the history of British Rocketry and why British Rocketry didn't continue.
Spoiler, it turns out it was mostly the Civil Services fault which is really interesting
but basically it's mostly because the Treasury really hated the British Rocketry Program
and blocked it until it went away.
But it's really fascinating.
It has like all the documents and stuff and the appendices actually list like a bunch of
them in full if you're very, very interested.
It's interesting because it deals with the different parts of the program in different
chapters.
It's not the way I would have structured it.
I think there are parts where it repeats itself because of the way it chooses to structure
the history but it's still extremely, extremely compelling.
And I did find it fascinating and it has a lot of really good detail.
I think another reading of this is that the boffins did not even bother to do the minimal
political work, putting the minimal political work to ensure that there were people in the
right places who cared about what they were doing.
No, you haven't read the book, have you?
But that's a book written by somebody who has romantic attachment to the British Rocketry
Program.
The book concludes with the message that the British Rocketry Program should have been
cancelled.
So the book has no particular attachment to it from a...
It does, from the perspective that the author really likes rockets but the book is very
clear that the British Rocketry Program did not make sense, almost the whole way through.
The civil service was sharply divided and you get a real sense of the politicians who were
supporting the project versus the politicians who weren't and did tell you the civil servants
who were versus the civil servants who weren't.
The real problem, I think, is in the fact that the civil service after World War II had a
very fragmented structure around particularly aerospace.
There were like five different ministries, each of whom had a slice of the jurisdiction
for this project, whereas the treasury was a single entity.
And so I don't think the problem was that the boffins didn't do their homework.
I think the problem was that the civil service was hopelessly disorganized on the side that
was pro this project and extremely organized on the side that wasn't.
Most of the politicians were in favour.
It was definitely the civil servants that were the issue.
Politicians are normally in favour of extremely public friendly construction projects.
So the fact that politicians are in favour of this, politicians like to build things right
and rockets are a thing that you can build and then you can put them into the sky and
it makes a big splash.
Like I say, I would strongly recommend reading the book before interpreting the book, but
it's a very interesting book.
And it gave me a good, a very good insight into how much British policy is nothing at
all to do with the party that's in power.
Historically, you are right.
In terms of the way things are now, so many good people have left at this point.
That was the OctaThought Podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
[Music]
Would it be too harsh at this point to note the dictionary definition of narcissism?
Of sentinus from a rising from failure to distinguish the self from the external.
I never deny it.
I have never denied this.
But I did like Google help with narcissism and it's all, and it turns out that the internet's
full of what you do if there are narcissists in your life and not, and there's not a lot
about what to do if you are one of them.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod in Computec.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.
*Silence*