Not very interesting content to carry on.
#Concent
Hello everyone and welcome to the 42nd episode of OctaThorp, a podcast for science fiction and
science fiction fandom. This episode is coming to you on the 14th of October 2021. I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott. And I'm Liz Batty.
And we have some letters of comment. In fact, we have quite a lot of letters of comment owing to
having recorded the previous episode quite soon after the previous previous episode.
You're making sausages. We have lots of letters of comment. I also wanted to say
it's episode 42, which surprised me because I thought OctaThort was the answer to life,
the universe and everything.
[Laughs]
Possibly. Possibly.
I do hope there's no one who is actually taking, you know, life advice from OctaThorp. I think that would be
bad.
If you're taking life advice from OctaThorp, please email us. And also, OctaThorp should be taken
only as directed. Ask your physician before taking life advice from OctaThorp. OctaThorp is not a
substitute for medical advice.
But two thirds of OctaThorp is doctors.
Yeah, but if they came to me on a plane and said, "Oh, Dr. That Man's Having a Hardstack," I would be like,
"Yep."
Oh, there's a brilliant meme going around about that at the moment.
No, there's a very tedious meme going around about that.
[Laughs]
How many times have you seen it?
Literally, like, dozens and dozens about different niche areas.
There will be a tedious meme about that in the show notes.
[Laughs]
I'm not sure I've seen this meme because I do not do as much social media as some people.
Okay, well, actually, I know that Liz has got a million copies of the remails in a text, so maybe she should send you one.
All right, deal.
All right, it'd be my Twitter. I'll try it. It's like when XKCD did that good thing about, like,
you know, the different types of scientific paper, which was immediately done to death.
And I saw like 100 different versions. And it's like you have sucked all the joy out of XKCD.
How? Anyway, maybe I should spend less time on Twitter.
On the subject of sucking all of the joy about things, let's start this episode with Jonathan Badly's
Lock about Dragon Meat's COVID restrictions. Straight into COVID listeners, you know it, we love it.
So they're going to have mandatory masking unless people have a medical exemption,
and they are going to require NHS COVID passes.
Good, correct. We like this. Good job, Dragon Meat. 10 out of 10. Excellent.
Thank you to Jonathan for letting us know. So Ali posted to Facebook to let us know that there
have been no reports of COVID from Francicon attendees. And also, she wrote us an email to let us know
her experiences from Francicon. Yeah, she basically said she did a lot of program.
She recorded fantasy book swap live with Tiffany Aching. She doesn't mean Tiffany Aching, does she?
She used Tiffany Angus. Yes, I think so. I don't know whether it's an intentional joke,
but it did make me thoughtful. So thank you, Ali. Give me some joy.
And said social distancing was easy because there weren't that many people there. She was a bit
worried about the masking of other hotel guests. But in fact, as she says, nobody at fantasy con
appears to have caught COVID. And the thing that I wanted to say here is that there is a there is a
lock element because one of the things that probably happened is that nobody went to fantasy con with
COVID. And if nobody's infected at your convention, it won't spread no matter how much eyeball licking
you do. So what you're doing when you have COVID so really the yes, it's all about risk.
This is going to be very mathematical now. Nobody getting COVID isn't good evidence of your policies
working. Lots of people getting COVID is strong evidence that your policies didn't work. But
the evidence for your policies working well is that one or two people get COVID. Yeah, because
there's a little bit of it about, but it did not spread. We had a good policy.
What I like about this is the very British redefinition of doing well as like a small number of COVID
rather than no COVID. No, no, no, it's not that obviously not having anyone getting COVID is great,
but it provides zero evidence for or against your policy. Okay, so Liz, the actual epidemiologist
with statistical background is going to tell me that I'm talking out my head. I think it might not
be a strong evidence as you think, because you could have a person. We know that we know the
distribution of like how many people you infect is heavily skewed, right? And many people in fact
know one and some people in fact, lots of people, but there's also people in the middle of the
vet one or two. So I think you probably can't tell the difference between someone comes to your
con who is not exhaling a lot of virus and infects one or two people, and someone comes to your
con and exhales lots of virus because they're in a very high viral load and infect lots of people
based on, you know, use that to whether you think your policies are working. You need kind of an
actual, I think you need a better comparator, basically. And all of this tells us that the Swiss
cheese model of health and safety work is important. You have to have your various levels of COVID
prevention and then also be lucky or ideally not unlucky. So what we have discovered here is that
the fact that no one got COVID may or may not be good. No, it's definitely good. It's whether it's
good evidence. Yeah, I mean, I think the better thing to say is, you know, if we have two conventions
and one is where everyone is masked up and there's a strict vaccination policy, no one gets COVID
and one where they have a much more relaxed masking of vaccination policy, no one gets COVID. That
doesn't necessarily mean that we should automatically go for the more relaxed one because it was fine
and no one got COVID. I think that's not strong enough evidence. Bingo. Are you advocating that we
run Control-Con? Because I'm up for running Control-Con. I'm fairly sure that if we wait long enough,
someone is going to run Control-Con for us. Excellent. Ali also mentions that the book
launches were in a big room with small separated tables, which is something we mentioned in the
previous episode. One of the things we had mentioned previously was that FantasyCon didn't have a
policy on mandatory masking. They were like, please wear a mask if you feel like it, but like they
weren't saying you had to. But very much from Ali's lock, I get the impression that almost all of
the convention attendees were still wearing a mask. So I suspect that conventions are going to find
that even if they don't mandate mask wearing, everyone will wear a mask anyway, so you're not.
There's no reason not in a way. There's no reason not to mandate mask wearing because everyone who's
going is already going to be wearing a mask. So you're not really going to annoy anyone as long
as you've got like stuff in place for like medical exemptions. I saw a lot of photos from FantasyCon
and nobody was wearing any masks in any of them. And what's going on as somebody said to me
in a meeting for a different convention is that everyone stops masking where they're socializing
with their friends. And over the course of the whole weekend, everyone socializes with all their
friends, which covers everybody at the convention. So this is the great fallacy of COVID prevention.
So when you actually go and do a thing with specific people and not any other people,
you are exposing yourself to far less risk and your friends to far less risk than if you go to a
convention and spend the weekend socializing in small groups, none of whom are masked.
But if you have masks on in the common spaces outside of like your table at the bar and being
on panels, your risk is lower than it would be if you didn't mask in those times. So,
and because we know COVID is exponential, small decreases in risk are important to control and
spread. Yes, they are. I think the other thing to consider is that sometimes people take their
masks off to take a nice photo and then put the mask back on it. Oh, that would be that that's
great if it's true. If you're anymore posted a picture to Instagram, which she said, don't worry,
I only took my mask off for this photo. So I did see some evidence of of that, as Liz said.
But yeah, it's good. I think it's good that FantasyCon went off and it's good that it seemed to go
well. I didn't go because I'm a bit concerned. I was a bit concerned about the masking, but
but I'm glad it went well. And actually it kind of reassures me for conventions coming up in the
rest of the year. So that is good. On the topic of Novicon, we got a suite of comments or a talk
from Andr Rosen, where she says, "Pause his octa-thorp, goes to read Novicon policy she knew
nothing about on page. She didn't know existed." So putting the news out, glad to be of service and
and also and bought the witness, which I have not yet done, but I'm excited to
when I finished SpiritFairer, 94% complete on SpiritFairer, so it's not far off.
Sounds like you really liked it then and I should give it another go.
I'm not really sure. It definitely gets better in the middle. Like there's a point in the middle
where you have enough to do that the bit where you have to actually do the management of your
boat becomes like compelling enough to keep you playing. And then at the end when it starts
tailing off again, you're like, "Okay." And at the beginning there's not enough happening
for it to keep you engaged, I think. So it's very definitely a game with the bell curve
in terms of like excitement over time. On the subject of COVID policies at conventions,
Bill Burns writes in to say that he was listening to episode 40 and Chris was a bit wrong about
US privacy laws not allowing anyone to ask about medical information such as vaccine status,
the applicable federal law is HIPAA, which requires that personal health information be
kept confidential, but it applies only to information held by doctors, hospitals, pharmacies, etc.
But it doesn't apply to interactions between an individual and organizations not defined in the
act. So if an airline or a convention or a shop wants to say, "You've got to show vaccine status,"
and if you don't, we won't let you in, they are more than able to do that. And because Bill
writes business software for companies which supply medical equipment, Bill is covered under
HIPAA, and so is intimately familiar with all of these various bits of US law. So thank you very
much, Bill, expert knowledge. Thank you for letting us know. Very interesting stuff.
And then Chris Garcia writes in saying that sanitizing mics is actually quite easy,
because the other thing he knows you can do the 20-minute ultraviolet boxes,
which were mentioned last time, but he says that you can also just remove the phone, toss it,
wipe the electronic bits down with bleach, and then put new foam on, which is slightly less
environmentally friendly, but I can see that it would be a lot quicker if you had lots of people
kind of all doing things in quick succession. And that's something we hadn't mentioned. So thank
you for writing in Chris. He also says I do the best in podcasting. You can store all these for
later, John. And when we launch our Patreon, there will be a soundboard, which is Alison,
just doing different mhmms and Liz doing different cheeses.
Jesus. Doing different cheeses is title of your sex tape. On the subject of high school movies,
which is apparently the gift that keeps on giving, Bridget Bradshaw tweets at us to say that
election is also a very good film. I searched letterbox for election, and there are a number of movies
by this name. So I'm assuming one of them is a high school movie, but I've asked Bridget,
which one she actually means. So I can put a link in the show notes. Eddie Cochran wrote in to say
that one of his favorite high school movies was The Faculty, which he found surprising as he's not
usually a horror fan. Lily and Edwards mentioned Buffy the Vampire Slayer and how she was surprised
that none of us mentioned it. And I wonder whether I cut us mentioning it out. So I'm sure we said
something about that. I'm going to say I definitely 100% mention Buffy the Vampire Slayer. And if John
cut it out of the episode, then that was clearly a cut too far. So I take full responsibility for
this as editor. But then I should have noticed and said, Oh no, we need to put it back in. Otherwise
Lillian will write. I mean, and we got a lock. So really, it's good. And then Farah also wrote in
to say that I needed to watch Romy and Michelle's high school reunion. And I have indeed seen that
movie and I very much enjoyed it. And I would say that Farah is probably right about that. So yes,
high school movie update. I was going to say that I suspect Bridget is meaning the 1999 film
election, which I have seen a long time ago. And yeah, it is pretty good. It is a kind of like
dark comedy with Reese Witherspoon and Matthew Broderick. And I suspect that's the one she means
gonna remember that getting quite a lot of attention at the time. And the director's gone on to make
a load of other films like sideways and the descendants and so on. It's probably that.
Live follow up Bridget tweets to say that she does indeed mean the 1999 Broderick Witherspoon movie.
So, hoorah, well done Liz. I'll put a link to that in the show notes. And I'll put links to all
of the other movies we've mentioned in the show notes as well. So yeah, thank you to everyone who
wrote in. Farah also mentions that Asterix is a classic choice for language expansion. And that
had not occurred to me. But now it has occurred to me I will be buying lots of Spanish language
editions of Asterix books. So thank you very much Farah.
We'll be talking about language acquisition because and it is actually on topic because I
am going to smothcon, which is at the beginning of December, and it's in Lisboa. And I am therefore
learning Portuguese, a language which I had no idea I needed to learn for fun just a bit.
It's full of words that don't look like I should know them. But when they're pronounced,
I go, oh yes, that's cheese. And so on.
We are going in person. I am. No, I want to. I should say this here because I've been actually
holding this up and not posting about it. Dublin 2019 offered I think 19 scholarships to people
from around the world to attend smothcon. And I don't know how many of these have been taken up.
But I am I am going to smothcon on a Dublin 19 scholarship. It doesn't cover the whole cost,
but it covers quite a lot of costs. And I'm taking my husband with me for a three-day
mini break because it turns out that Ryanair do cheap flights. There's a song about that and
we'll put a link to it in the show notes. And the hotel only costs 10 euros extra if there's
two of you rather than one. And the convention has a five-year-old membership rate for people
who don't actually want to attend the programme. I'm kind of wondering whether I can ask for that
one for free instead of the full one. And I hadn't counted on the cost of getting COVID tests,
but I don't think it's going to be that great because I think it's just lateral flow test.
Now I'm going to go to Lisbon. I'm very excited but also very scared because flying.
Congratulations. It's huge news and it's very good.
And then I'm going to hide in my house for a fortnight when I get home.
That's no longer required. I've done it and it was fine.
I can't promise to do this, but when Liz did it, I always sent her an AeroPress.
Oh no, don't do that. I have obviously.
Yeah, no, I'm not going to, but Liz needed a way to get good coffee in her hotel in
Toyland. So I provided her with an AeroPress. I was getting rid of anyway, so yes.
I'm very confident that I will be able to get good coffee in Portugal.
And I am even more confident that there are many, many ways to make coffee in this house,
including at least two AeroPresses. Oh, well, I now have two AeroPresses because I've got
John's. The thing is I didn't consider. So ship one from Toyland to...
Yeah, I didn't consider when leaving that I would need one on the way back.
I could have got good coffee, but it would have been like £3.50 a cup and I am a cheapskate and
I was staying in hotels. So I got John's AeroPress and took it back with me and some bags of coffee
and probably confused the maid. Yeah, when we stay in hotels in the UK, we take cold brew with us,
but that's not going to be an option for this trip. So we're not going to fly with cold brew
in the suitcase. Could you not buy any baggage because you're going on Ryaner? Yeah.
Yeah, it makes sense. Anyway, I will be excited to hear
from your first in-person convention. It will be my third in-person convention.
By then it will, yeah. Because we'll have been to Corflu in Novacron.
Haven't got to know conventions for two years. I'm going to three and six weeks because I'm
absolutely insane. I just want to say thanks ever so much to Dublin 2019 for the scholarship,
because although it's not a huge amount of money, it really does genuinely make a massive
difference to me. And I'm sure that's true for a lot of other people. And I haven't been able to
attend a smofcon in person before. So I am very excited. I think also I need to do a personal
shout out to James Bacon who posted everywhere saying, "Do not self-exclude from these scholarships.
Do not think that they're not for you or the likes of you." Because had he not done that,
I would definitely not have applied. So because I would have self-excluded, I'd have gone, oh no,
they're really for younger fans or fans who are more interested in World Cons rather than
Easter Cons or fans who don't run snitty podcasts about the World Cons.
I was just going to say that I have been to a smofcon because I went to a smofcon in Amsterdam in
2012, maybe? The reason I went to a smofcon is because James was like, "Come to smofcon,
it'll be a laugh and also you need to meet Ian because you're going to run a division with him
and I need you to actually sit down and chat." I think maybe, and then maybe I think he couldn't
go. Anyway, I went and it was extremely World Con heavy and the vanishing position, that's forever,
but it was Amsterdam and I had a very nice time messing with Amsterdam basically.
And James and I went to a bunch of comic shops when Andy has some drinking.
I think that was also the one in which Aimely stood up and proposed a bid for World Con in
Mairam, which eventually turned into an actual bid for World Con.
I joked earlier about not wanting to go to the con. What I mean is, of course, that when I went
to the long con staff weekends, I found they were best the more time I spent in the bar having the
side conversations with people and maybe going to see the delights of not Amsterdam, but more
Stephenage was particularly valuable and that actually the formal plenary and even breakout sessions for
these conventions are not necessarily as useful as people think they are. I mean,
the vanishing position is very important, but the thing that's important is the process of answering
all the questions ready for it rather than the actual event which I agree is like watching paint
dry. Smuffcon Europe has a commitment to con running more broadly than just
Wilcon, I should say, and they are about the European regional conventions and encouraging
people who are planning to do those. I think partly because that's where we get the next generation of
European Wilcon runners from, they're not in my case. You know, I'm going to run a European
Wilcon? No, obviously not. There are plenty of people who want to do this who are younger than me.
I'd like to go to one eventually. I also missed out there were a couple of cons in the UK called
con runner that I also did not manage to get to. I did go to con runner which is very focused on
Easter cons actually as you might expect, so it's kind of an ideal convention for
people who run Easter cons and their friends. Cool. All right con runner, that's my sole comment.
Was it good? I think so. Must have been good then. I can't remember to be honest.
Yeah, I mean it sounds good. That I usually find is not a bad sign. I remember it was in Steve,
oh basically all I remember was I think I went to Stevenage, having ever been to Stevenage and
probably I just spent a lot of time drinking anyway. Maybe we should move on to broadcastable
things. We've got more locks to get through, so. Okay, God.
Jesus. Karen Shaffer says they don't really have traybakes except as imported from the
Great British Bake Off. So the Bake Off transferring traybakes to the rest of the world.
Hoorah. Soft power. Is that all our letters in the comment? Yes. Now we move on to the other
letters of comment that we solicited. So this is episode 42 listeners and so I thought it might
be nice to talk a little bit about Douglas Adams. For those who don't know who Douglas Adams is,
he was a British writer who wrote a book called The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy and in the
Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy the ultimate answer to life, the universe and everything,
is revealed to be 42 and this leads to a much longer period of time in which people try and
work out what the hell the question is. I feel like that's not actually true. I feel like what
was actually revealed was the computer that was designed to establish what the answer to life,
the universe and everything was came up with 42. I believe this is a piece of commentary on
on computers and the things that they do. Anyway, never mind. Yes. So if you if you are listening
to this podcast and you don't know who Douglas Adams is already, yeah, no, that would be great.
Let us know. I mean, Hara for you because you've got a lot of good content ahead of you.
I don't think it's very likely, but you know, that would be amazing.
But yes, so we had multiple people writing with their Douglas Adams-Z kind of anecdotes and
tidbits and I'll read Chris's first so that I can close his email after I've done so.
Chris Garcia wrote in to say that he met Douglas Adams once and when he met Douglas Adams,
he told him, "Arthur C. Clarke said hi and if you want to know more about that anecdote,
talk to Chris in the bar." And then Alex Holden wrote in to say that he watched a repeat of the
BBC TV series as a young lad and learned there was an accompanying novel and then he went on a
shopping expedition to a second-hand bookshop and he was surprised and impressed when the shopkeeper
had not only heard of the book. He supplied the full title and author when it was only partially
out of my mouth. Alex still has it and it remains one of his favorite novels. I remember when I
got into H.I.K. as realizing other people knew about it and they liked it was a bit of a revelation
because at that point several of my hobbies were not things that other people liked and
or at the very least I had not yet found the other people who liked them. I think it's probably
a better way of putting it. I suspect this is something with many of our listeners sympathize
with. I have some things I want to talk about my experience of H.I.K. as which is that it
completely passed me by not because I hadn't been born yet like some people I could mention
but because I was living in America at the time and it didn't really quite catch on there.
What happened was that I came back to the UK and went to university in Britain and discovered
that I met all these science fiction fans. They were all like, "Oh, hitchhikers, it's amazing."
They were kind of like really into it. They're not as into it as the people who were actually
into it who they called Towleys and who included our very own Claire Barley friend of the show.
But when I went to my first work on, which was the, I guess the 87 work on, there was a vast
amount of hitchhikers. Everything everywhere there because it really was incredibly popular
amongst UK science fiction fans as you probably expect because it's very good and by then I caught
up. I didn't buy the official hitchhikers Towel which was a proprietary Towel with the stuff on it
weaved into the fabric and I kind of have regretted that ever since. It was extremely
expensive which was wired and buy it but I hadn't have any money. They now trade hands for stupid
amounts of money because that's the way the world works these days. I have one. I bought it
on eBay for the princely sum of $100 and that was back at the time when the exchange rate between
pounds and dollars was not as silly as it currently is. It was back in the day when it was roughly
two to one so surfing for merchandise on eBay in the States was like a super viable way of
getting good stuff in the UK. It wouldn't work these days. And it is much rarer now and people
know how rare things are a bit more now I think. When Max wrote an article for my very first
fanzine she described to me as the hitchhikers fan who was indexed linked to the eBay prices for
hitchhikers merch which I took at the time as a great compliment. Lillian Edwards wrote to
us to say she was on the committee of the first ever convention Adams came to which was Hichakon
and Glasgow. She says "I ought to have lots of really great stories but all I can remember is
that he was very very tall." So thanks Lillian. Lillian herself is not very very tall and has the
same problem with very tall people that I do which is they're a very long way away from you in the
bar. They sent photos of their people bears. They did send photos of their people bears.
I think people might have heard of Douglas Adams and still not know what a people bear is but there's
a cottage industry here in the UK where a woman makes teddy bears with two heads and three arms
and they're very adorable. Every single one is different. She never repeats and we have a couple
of people bears around here. Jonathan's people bear had to go to the People Bear Hospital on
multiple occasions so they were kind of like "do not do that" Jonathan but there we go.
Yeah I have a people bear. I have a people bear called Barry. He is blue and he has tartan paws
and I love him extremely much. There are various... We should put a photo of a people bear in the
show notes. Can we have a picture of Barry? So people did post photos of their people bears on
Facebook and there is a link to that Facebook post in the show notes but I will also try and put
the pictures as chapter art and there are a number of brilliant pictures of people bears.
A bunch of people posted basically saying like "I was in his Tigers fandom through ZZ9 and ZZ9
was a big formative thing for me" and so Johnny I just wanted to pick out one
called one that Johnny had posted saying that he met a bunch of people from ZZ9 at his first
con in 1999 and they started going to the ZZ9 pub meets and now Johnny like a lot of his friends
were in London fandom and that was their route in and then you know of course there was that one
AGM where a 14 year old member came along and we had to convince his dad we were responsible adults
and that that was me. I was the 14 year old that they had to persuade my dad that they were
responsible adults before my dad would drop me off. They had the AGM at Peterborough and I was a member
of the society I got the magazine and I said to my dad "I want to go to the AGM" and that was when I
met Doug Spencer, I met Flick, I met Simo, God who I was there, um Red.
And did you meet any responsible adults?
I don't remember me any responsible adults but I think I remember meeting people who were able to
convince my dad that they were so yes. Johnny does note that that was also the same AGM that the
BBC filmed the AGM for the BBC Big Read so I was on the telly with my braces and I got the
Babel Fish t-shirt. So that was my first, there is, there is televisual evidence of my first
Spanish meeting rather bewilderingly. It was good and it was just, it was weird and great and I loved
it. And now I'm in fandom, yeah, more. Oh do I have a link for you? Oh God I love the internet.
What's I have a link to? Is the BBC Big Read on the hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy?
Hey, I've got... Is this gonna have John age 14? I've opened so yes. Yes I was gonna say is it on
the internet, brilliant. Yeah yeah it will and if you've actually got, if you've got a good version
because the version I've got was like ripped off of VHS so... Oh no it will be ripped off VHS,
I mean there's various people saying it's very terrible. I've got one I could probably put on
YouTube actually. When I was reading science fiction in my 20s, if you had asked of the things in
science fiction, which one is going to be reality in 30 years, a device that you put into your ears
that ought to translate to every language in the universe would not have been one of them.
And yet here we are. It's just unbelievable. It's, it's, it's my biggest gosh wow oh boy oh boy
moment of my entire life. That is completely fair. So well done Douglas Adams who also went to my
college and has something to say on Big Sofas which is another things going on in my life.
What do you have to say on Big Sofas? I take rotated the sofa through four-dimensional space
to get stuck flat. Don't gently right? Yeah yeah yeah. A bunch of people posted on Facebook to let
us know their experiences from kind of Douglas Adams and how they experienced him and there is a
link in the show notes if you want to go and read all the reminiscing. It's really good.
It's really positive. Just loads of people being like I love that and I love how it got me into
the stories and hurrah. And so yes Liz you read Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy.
I did read Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy. I read it at quite an early age I think because my dad
had it and he had these great covers where if you had all four of them you could arrange them in
four different ways to get four different, four different pictures. Oh god I feel so old now.
Sorry Alison. When were you born Liz? Is this the first little question? 1982.
Three. I was one year out. Before John is the crucial thing I think. Before John but critically
so that you could have it read to you as bedtime stories. No no no I read it but I'm not that you.
I read it myself because there was a copy in the house when I was growing up because my dad
owned that four book box set is the thing. But he also had taped the tv show off the tv so he had
it on a VHS and so I think I watched that before I even read the books. So interestingly I came through
the tv show and not the books and never listened to the radio show until much later. But I also
had a bunch of other stuff around. So I picked up a copy of the radio scripts in a second damn
bookshop and I liked Adam's philosophy on taking lots of baths and eating lots of bovril sandwiches.
I also read Don't Panic the kind of guide the Hitchhiker's Galaxy that Neil Gaiman wrote
and I think that may have been the first like Neil Gaiman book. Nice. Sorry I all these quite
but I never I never found I never went to ZZ9 or even thought about looking for ZZ9. I think
it just never occurred to me so I didn't know the ZZ9 existed until I started coming to conventions
and then with all the stores selling two headed three-armed bears. So the thing that happened to me
was I was in the Lego Club and so I knew that if I liked something enough there might be someone who
would send me a magazine about it and so every hobby I then developed after Lego I would look on
the internet to see if there was a club I could join that sent me a newsletter about it and with
leather bookmarks there was not but with Douglas Adams there was and that was how I going to find
them. So it's actually the Lego Club that really I guess gave me the impetus. So John is young enough
that he grew up with the internet which is really weird because I thought that was only two of
children but clearly isn't now. Liz is going to say yeah I sort of grew up with the internet but
not really right. Well I mean I knew when I was 13 but then it was internet where you know you had
to go to the specific computer and connect it to the internet and then you know had a certain
amount of time because you were paying a penny a minute for the phone call not like it is in my
pocket and always on. So I think it has a fundamentally different relationship with the internet.
I have uploaded a video which is my rip of the AGM clip and I am in it I am in three bits
and I am young. Right excuse me briefly while I go and look at little tiny baby John.
I am like I am sorry. So we could just rather link you to the entire thing we could just
insert John because that is the only thing that is very interesting about this. Because it has also
got like young Doug young Heidi flick. Yeah well I mean I have got I have linked to the 30 minute
shows so I have thought that I have put a link in the show notes to it on YouTube so it might be
the same thing. But no it is not. Oh no this is the ZZ9 AGM not the thing yeah okay. The ZZ9 AGM
wasn't in the Hitchhiker's Guide episode it was in the weathering Heights episode for reasons I still
don't quite understand. Wow. So the Hitchhiker's Guide episode did not have the ZZ9 plug in it.
It was in a different episode. So yeah thank you to everyone who wrote in. I think it's probably
people can tell from the way I describe it that it was a huge formative part of like my
I guess my like teenage years really I came across them when I was 11 so
and like kind of is my route into fandom and I think even if that's not true for you I think
people do still have very fond memories of it because it's still such a great
thing and it really stands up. It's also still very the radio shows are still very very very
funny and very well produced and I think it was very influential on British fandom in lots of ways
when you're thinking about ways in which British and American fandom differ the fact that we like
things that are funny has to be one of the main ones. Don't all right. I'm sorry I watched this clip
John is that you like right in the middle right at the very end? Yep that is me. Yeah you're almost
unrecognizable. I do not I had to get a new passport earlier than I should have done because
when I started going to conferences my passport photo was when I was like 17 and there was a point
where US security they stop they nearly stopped me getting on a plane because they were like
we do not believe this is your passport which is I was like I'm gonna get a new passport now
because I was terrifying. I recognize like Duggan and Heidi and and Flick and Alex but I think if
you hadn't told me that was you I would not have realized it was you. I do look quite different now.
Yeah it's amazing. I bulked out I used to think when I was that age I thought I was fat I'm looking
back oh like body image is a hell of a drug isn't it? You're a skinny wee thing. I was. It's
why that your face is different. Okay but yes like I say thank you very much for everyone who wrote
in. Brilliant. Oh god I remember something else I should have said about Douglas Adams.
Douglas Adams also the first absolute died in the wool will accept no substitutes Mac
Junkie who I ever really encountered not in person but but in his writings really very
had the way of it. Yeah one of the very large formative influences he had on me was his I
remember it was there's a piece of writing in the salmon of doubt where he talks about how to make
tea and he's like a lot of people will tell you you don't really need to know how to make tea
because you made tea and it's like no those people are wrong there is a way to make tea and it is
this and I was like that that I think had a huge influence on my thinking as like teenager was like
you know trying to do things in order to get good quality things rather than just saying
ah before you. I think I think I think a lot of that in me comes from Douglas.
He was uncompromising about doing things to make them good and hence deadlines.
And yeah exactly.
Since last time we recorded it has been announced that there will be a world
con bid for Dublin in 2029 and Liz you are our roving reporter who brought this to our attention.
Yeah so a tweet.
Um so they announced it I believe at the end of octa con I'm going to say I signed up to octa
con but then and this is a thing that doesn't really happen for like in person conventions but it
does seem to occasionally have a virtual convention. I basically didn't really feel much like a
convention last weekend so I dipped in and out of the discord but didn't really attend octa con
but I did technically have a membership and but I believe they announced it at the end of the
convention which would make sense. A place you're going to announce your Irish binses and Irish
convention announcing it for 10 years after the last one seems pretty sensible and it also puts
you on a cycle where you are five years away from the next British one so you're kind of
not competing for people's time and energy at the same time in the cycle. Yeah seems good I really
like 2019 I'd have to go back to Dublin. Seems like a good thing. Yep I agree. I'm not hugely keen on
world con bids announcing further and further and further in advance just because it seems to
then sort of take well why am I not keen? I'm not keen on world con bids announcing further and
further in advance because I think it's sort of then like can end up with you doing a lot of active
things a very long way in advance which can sometimes mean the whole cycle of world con bidding and
world con running takes a very long time and takes a lot of people's effort but I guess it does make
sense if you are trying to maximise your bid energy into bidding for a year when you have little
competition there's a sense to which if we have a certain number of world con bids that is about
the same as the number of world con gears then it makes sense to kind of plan in advance when
you want to do it. Does that make sense? I mean I think things like three way and four way bidding
can sometimes result in people putting a lot of effort into bidding and then having to decide
if they lose whether they want to immediately turn around a bit again at which point you might
have been bidding for five years before you start even running your convention but in this case I
think it makes total sense because you know it says look Dublin did a great world con we would
like to do it again. I think taking a space where we're saying actually we think Britain and Ireland
between them are up for a world con every five years is quite interesting I think that probably
does reflect the amount of um fanish energy in the countries compared to the United States and
North America generally and um I think that's quite interesting I we might be a bit tired by
2019. I'll definitely be tired by 2019. 2029. 20 did I just say 20? You see this is how tired I am.
Alison is so tired she was tired two years ago. One of the things that seems to happen to you
when you're old and also me is that you lose decades out of your life quite a lot so you keep
thinking that things are 10 years less ago than they actually are or that something happened in a
decade 10 years out from when it did or that we're actually in the something we're actually in 2011
2021. We are in 2021 right? I'm losing track. Pretty sure. We are still in 2021. Also in world
confutures um there's Sarah Felix has a Texas bid going on. Yes which is very exciting.
Which I have pre-supported. I have pre-supported this is outrageous really. This is how merchandise
works guys. I pre-supported um the Texas bid because Sarah has a bunch of ribbons saying I
pre-supported Texas before it was cool that she's going to give out at smothcon and I want one.
Um I mean that is fair. I have a question for you Alison. Which year is the Texas bid?
I don't know. It's for the future. Is it on the internet? It's not for the past is it? No I
don't think I mean literally I think this is Sarah and a bunch of $20 bills. Yeah I mean I don't
think it's launched and the says I mean this is people thrusting $20 bills on Sarah. If I pay
you $20 can you get me a iPre-supported Texas before it was cool ribbon please? No what you need
to do is pay um I'll send you we'll put the link in the show notes. Basically you pay pal her she's
got a link in her. I think she's actually got a one-click link now for pay palang and then if you
tell her you'll get your ribbon from me at smothcon um after smothcon that's what we'll do.
A nice good stuff. They're not not I don't know what I'm going to see but I'll push it in the
blip. Okay brilliant and if that Facebook post is public there'll be a link in the show notes
and then you can pre-support Texas too. I want to send us dollars PayPal none of your flim flam.
Stop pay paling people money for cons while we're recording the podcast. Roger that.
[Music]
I want to plug the science fiction encyclopedia. This is a big thing that has happened in the last two
weeks which is it's now in its fourth edition on its own website. We'll put a link in the show notes.
It has parted ways with Galance who have been looking after it for the last little while
and is now being run by its own holding company and answerable editions which
is the publishing arm of Dave Langford. Dave Langford clearly has three arms like Beable Bear
two regular ones and one publishing one and it is in fact edited by Fred of the Show Dave Langford
and also John Clute and Graham Slight is the managing editor which I assume means he does
all the grunt work and gets none of the major credit and they also remember Peter Nichols as
the founding editor. So yeah it remains an extremely good resource for everything in Azure.
That probably won't tell you how to pre-support the Texas bid. It's not very funny.
It's not a sort of thing I expect to get from an encyclopedia to be fair.
Fine. If you are going to NovaCon then we are doing OctaThorp Live. We will have an exclusive
stunt Lizz. Lizz why aren't you coming to NovaCon? Because I live 6,000 miles away and the UK
doesn't believe I am vaccinated. That's fair. I explained it to the head of programme at NovaCon
by saying that the train links between Bangkok and Buxton were poor which I believe is true.
I mean to be fair the trains to Buxton are rubbish it's probably still paces or something.
You technically could get the train from Bangkok to Buxton because of the Eurostar but it just
wouldn't be like quick. You can't. So this is a complete digression but I don't think you actually
can get any trains internationally from Thailand that cross into another country at the moment.
I think I actually have to get a non-train link somewhere. I did obviously look at this at some
point and I think actually what I would have to do is start in Vietnam and from Vietnam you can do
the whole loop through up to the Trans-Siberian Railway to Moscow and then through to Paris and
then on the Eurostar. But I don't think I can do the first bit. Anyway obviously at this point I
can't do any of that but in general. Sarah says it's 10 years out so I think it's a bid for 2020-30
one. Jesus I'm gonna be dead. You heard it here first folks. Yes we'll be doing OctaThorp Live with
a stunt Liz who at this moment is a secret. We have asked them and they have said yes but we're
keeping a secret to raise the suspense. Can I get a new? And it'll be good. It's a one o'clock on
Sunday in the afternoon not in the morning. So it'll be good and we're really looking forward to doing
it and we will see you all there. Haven't thought about how to actually do the technical side yet but
I'm sure it'll be fine. Yeah it'll be the first OctaThorp Live that is actually like live and in person
isn't it? Yes and also the first OctaThorp without Liz. Yeah so I feel that really truly the first
OctaThorp Live and in person will not be to lie in there obviously. Oh yeah obviously it will be a
pretend OctaThorp. We will get you round we will get you on to OctaThorp Live at some point. You will
come to the UK for a calm one day right? Yes I will come back at some points yeah. So let's go
to 2024 put us on the program or we'll hunt you down.
Okay so... Picks. Picks. My so I've got a choice of two picks this time around and I think I'm going
to pick Lovecraft Country. Now I appreciate this is an old I say old. This is a TV series that
everyone already watched and talked about and I am aware of that but at the time it was on now TV
I did not have now TV and now I have now TV which is now called now but it is still on now so I
have now watched it. It is very good. I liked it a great deal. I was a little bit worried it would
end on a cliffhanger because I know that they only got the news they weren't doing a second season
kind of quite recently like a couple of months ago I think but actually the first season ends on
quite a good note if that is the end of the whole series and yeah I thoroughly enjoyed it. Really
thought it was good and reminded me quite a lot of watchmen in some ways not in plot ways but more
like it's cool that we've now got a couple of different SFNal shows that show the black experience
and parts of that that I had not really been exposed to before so I thought that was really
really neat. So yeah really enjoyed it would recommend it's on now. Now is £10 a month but
there are often like discounts and deals you can find if you slough on the internet so yeah
I enjoyed it. Have I either reviewed seeing Lovecraft Country? I have the book in my To Be
Red pile. Oh yes it's based on a book I need to... I had it out of the library and the library said
you need to bring this back so I took it back and said oh I'll buy the ebook instead and the
ebook is 99p so yeah that's a good idea I would recommend it despite the fact that I haven't read
it yet but yeah by Matt Ruff I think. Yes and I've read other things by Matt Ruff but not Lovecraft
Country. I also haven't watched it because I would need to subscribe to another streaming service
to watch it and I just haven't got round to you know rotating my streaming services round to HBO
yeah see also television bankruptcy and the fact that apps have sprung up where
that are designed to allow you to easily subscribe or unsubscribe from all these different things
month and month by month which might be good but yeah no I'll put it on my list for next time I get
now TV I will watch it along with whatever else I'm watching on now. Very quickly I watched Avengers
Endgame which is a load of all Bobbins and I've picked up Bobbins from the Sudoku guy.
I watched Avengers Endgame which is a load of all Bobbins and John said perhaps you don't like the
MCU very much why do you keep watching it and I realized that we're going through a process in
my house I live with somebody else which is something that you know in general I recommend
but I go let's watch a movie tonight we could watch this well-remarked Korean drama or we could
watch this short funny modern comedy or this Hugo nominated movie or Hugo finalist movie or we could
watch the latest round of extruded MCU product and on every occasion when I do this my husband says
oh I quite fancy the next round of extruded MCU product he doesn't say that he says oh let's watch
Avengers Endgame that sounds great so I am actually going to tackle this domestically
but I probably am going to carry on watching MCU for this reason because sometimes you just
live with somebody else and they like the MCU more than you do. I also want to talk a bit about
Foundation which is on Apple TV which Apple TV plus which as we know is the streaming service
that nobody has #WatchTedLasso I've watched two episodes so far quite like it it takes massive
liberties with the plot and obviously taking massive liberties with the plot is quite good
thing in the case of Foundation because the original books have quite a lot one with them
and I think the TV CEO will have different things wrong with it and they've done quite a lot of
quite clever things to cope with the fact that the action in this story happens over a very long
time which makes things harder if you're trying to cast a TV show with a recurring cast
so and it's very pretty it's they've spent a lot of money on CGI visitors I don't much like CGI
visitors but you know I know understand that a lot of people do so I'm glad you're enjoying it
I mean I'm also watching Foundation and I have Ted Lasso having finished I'm now at the stage of
do I keep subscribing to Apple TV basically just so I can watch Foundation and maybe I did enjoy
the first two and well trying to spoil too much I mean I haven't read any books it does set up
stuff like the end of episode two ends in a reasonably dramatic fashion which episode three
basically ignores because they've definitely got a plan which is to do things quite slowly
but after quite enjoying the first two the third one is like oh are you going to tell me anything
about that thing that happened at the end of episode two? No not yet I saw a fan theory about the end
of episode two and in fact even even if somebody has said to me there's a fan theory I'd have known
what the fan theory was and having heard the fan theory I'm like oh of course that's what's
what happened there so it's it it doesn't come out that way I'll be very surprised I mean I do
like the kind of eternal emperor of different age clones but I understand that's not in the books
that's a made up for the series thing yeah they've made a top so they can use the same actor all
the way through which is really clever you know I'm going to give them props for that that's a
really good choice in how you move things on to on to uh television transfer things from
from book to television whilst keeping their essential nature but being able to cast an actor
or three actors in this case it's very clever yeah if you recall last time I said I was reading a
book that was pretty good but I hadn't finished it yet and so I could not recommend it for pick
because I need to know if it had a good ending unfortunately I have finished a book and it's got
a pretty good ending so I can recommend Children of Ruin by Adrian Tchaikovsky which is a sequel to
his earlier book Children of Time but it's a fairly loose sequel so if you haven't read Children of
Time for a few years like you'll be fine it's not one of these giant fantasy novels where you need
to know exactly you know who is married to who and who fell out with who it's kind of a fairly like
loose sequel using the same concept and the same some of the same characters it's essentially about
you know far future humanity colonizing planets but also they set up in Children of Time a
planet full of uplifted super intelligent spiders and Children of Ruin takes that but also adds
kind of uplifted super intelligent octopuses and also they they they meet some alien life and
it's basically a space opera novel all about communication so it has all you know your nice
space opera sense of wonder stuff there's lots of you know interplanetary travel and spaceships
and aliens and also octopuses and spiders but it's basically about kind of like
how do you communicate when your fundamental ideas about the nature of communication
may be completely different or your kind of you know how your species notion of like the
transmission of information works is totally different and it really really digs into that
in quite a lot of detail and I find it really fascinating I do think it's a little bit too long
and so I was flagging towards the end and also I'd slightly lost track of who was in which spaceship
on or on which space station and where the other spaceship had gone and so on and so I recommend
reading it when you think you can kind of plow through it fairly quickly so you don't lose track
of what's going on but I do I do recommend it and it is it's very good and it scratched that
particular kind of I want to read a book with spaceships in each so it's good nice I haven't
read Children of Ruin but I have read Children of Time and I really enjoyed it so Children of Ruin
is on my on my list of things to read I believe Children of Time won the Arthur C. Clarke award
and I really enjoyed it so I'm looking forward to reading the next one. In terms of books that deal
with kind of language and what it is to communicate with people who don't understand you I really
like that genre of book in general so Ian Watson wrote The Embedding which I loved
Trying to Mayville wrote Embassy Town which I loved and the movie Arrival kind of deals with
similar things I haven't read the short story that Arrival is based on but I have seen the
movie and loved it so yeah it's something I'm excited to do at some point. John how have you
have you not read that sorry sorry just like I mean it's fair it's now one like giving you
stories of your life and others and locked you in a room until you've read it all. I've read
Exhalation the compilation that was up for the Hugo award but I don't think it's in that.
Oh no this is the previous one it's not this it's in the previous one which I have not yet read
which I should which is maybe even better you should it's got some of like the best short stories
ever in it. I mean on the subject of languages I read I think last year Native Tongue by
Suzette Hayden Elgin which is about language in a slightly different way it's it's a dystopian
future American and essentially women create their own new language as an act of resistance.
Oh that's cool what's that one called? And it's really interesting it's called Native Tongue and
it was it was published in the the mid 80s. Cool. And it I mean it is about translation with
alien species but also about how the women then use these powers of translation to
yeah kind of have their own list. So that's definitely worth reading.
Good stuff. That was the 42nd episode of the OctoThore podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me. Oh it's goodbye from me.
[Music]
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod in Competech.com
Used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license. This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.
[BLANK_AUDIO]