"Prisperter?" You remember the letter of comment that we were discussing before this one?
You know. You remember the one where I read out the name of the film? Maybe three or four minutes
ago. It is possible I was not paying close attention at that exact moment.
Fair enough. We also heard... Sorry. That's all right. I can't really criticize anyone for
having a lapse of attention. John like joins conventions and so on like during the pod, so I don't
think we can ding anyone for, you know, reading another link.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 128th episode of Octothorpe, a podcast of
science fiction and science fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 13th of February 2025.
I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty. And we have some letters of comment.
So first up we heard from Andreas Devauer who sent us both a toot and an email. He says,
he remembers how people used to say they needed a window system to play games and then they claimed
that they needed a window system or a Mac. Now Alison says you can play games quite well on a
Mac as long as they're not using graphics but his Steam Decks runs the Linux that he's been
sticking with all these years. I'm going to say I don't ever remember the time people said you
needed a Mac to run games. I am going to say also that as Macs are Unix under the hood they can
generally run anything that you can run on. Linux is generally though of course Steam Decks are
tweaked for games so that's a bit different but in general. Macs will do anything Linux can.
Yeah but you've got to recompile everything for the ARM chips now.
Yes it's the trade off. It's the trade off so I've got a friend with a Steam Deck and I've got
a friend and I've got a Switch and it is noticeable how much better the battery life is on my Mac
book than it is on the Switch or the Steam Deck because of ARM. Those Intel processors
pour they battery hungry. We need to heat our houses with something don't we?
My our house is noticeably harder to heat since we went to ARM processors and also LED lights.
But yeah I always say as a Mac as a Mac person I've never really played games on Mac like I played
them on my PlayStation. I used to play them on Windows but then I don't now. Having noticed last
time that I had been playing loads of games on my Mac and this had prevented me from doing any
work I have got better and I've done it much less this two weeks I've just played loads of
board games instead I'm not sure that's actually better but it feels more worthy.
But I mean this all kind of started I seem to remember when Mac gaming started becoming more
common that was like alongside Linux gaming because it was the humble bundles that got this all
kind of kicked off in the old days and it very much seemed like they were both being done at the
same time but I don't know if that's true or not. But I see relatively few games on Steam that are
Windows and Mac but not Linux. It does seem to be either Windows only or all three in general.
He also emailed in to say he wonders are fan funds as relevant as they used to be. These days we're
seeing more exchange of ideas across other electronic media and people are traveling more
freely than they did when fan funds like TAF were first brought up maybe he's totally off his
rocker or has history moving on made fan funds less of a thing. I've always said ultimately the
fan funds will die when they're no longer relevant because they rely on people voting for them to
work. So if people thought TAF was irrelevant TAF would have gone and they don't so it hasn't.
So I think the answer is in the fact that it's still there but also international travel I think
is getting more expensive now or not less. So I think that's the other half of the thing.
I'm going to say I've been on this item three times now at conventions because it's a favorite
topic for convention pedals and as well as the points that John has just raised I would also say
my guff drip was completely unlike a holiday I might have taken to Australia and New Zealand
even if that was holiday was a to a convention because that focus on meeting and hanging out and
spending time with science fiction fans makes a big difference in lots of different ways.
There were a couple of times when I had meetups in a city and as a result of those meetups people
who were science fiction fans in the same area but never previously met got to meet and hang out
because they both came to see the fan fund delegate. So there are lots of ways in which the fan funds
make a difference that is not just otherwise available. Also people do donate money to us and
you know people don't like it they don't need to do that which is also fine. It has the non-fan
fund delegate. I would say I think we looked into this because I looked at all the past TAF races
certainly there on Dave Langford's website thank you and you can look at the votes and the votes
go up and down but I would not say the votes have been going down consistently and I think the thing
to worry about or maybe not worry about but I think the thing to think about is whether TAF is
becoming a smaller pool of fans donating more generously than it might have been in previous years
which might be an issue in the future if some of those fans and like you know you're relying more
on a smaller pool of people and if more of those people pull out then you have an issue and also
it's going to be interesting to see because we now you know we have three fan funds now in Europe
sending fans to you know around Europe North America and Australia and does that mean we end up
raising more money or do we end up raising the same amount of money but slicing it more thinly
like I think it's not unreasonable to check where we are but they still feel they do still feel
relevant in that people can choose or not whether they want to give them money by their stuff in
auctions etc and so in a way people kind of vote with their money. I think that's evidenced in the
fact that like if cuff and naph are kind of if the if the within country fan funds are beginning to
struggle that might make sense because it might be getting easier to talk to other people in the
same country as you and that sort of thing but I think the other thing is that we're seeing that
there are people in the community who struggle to come to conventions and we have bursaries and
stuff so I think you know there was at least there are at least on occasion people who do run who
otherwise would not be able to do the thing and it's not always true but certainly if I had not
one taf I would not have gone to any of the places I went and would not have been able to afford to
do so so I think that's the other thing which is it might be true in general that you know people
can travel but it might not be true that the person can travel that was Andreas thank you very
much for writing in Andreas we have definitely talked about the relevance of fan funds on the pod
so we could if we had a really fabulous index in the form of our listeners somebody could write
in and tell us when that was oh Alison could go and search our own transcripts or our own website
and figure that out itself I could but you know listeners if you feel that this request for
outsource work it's reasonable please write to Alison don't don't fox Alison's plans by pointing
out that we're making the listeners do work that that is a poor precedent to set list
so we heard from Chris Garcia and Chris said there is no more fanish form of recording than the real
to real tape the real to real has magnetic audio tape has been recording fanish events since world
cons in the 1950s and some of those recordings still exist to this day it is remarkably robust
technique in almost every tape so long as it's not physically damaged can be read decades later
I have recordings from the 1960s that played perfectly well when I fard them up I own 10 real
to real recorders one with eight track recording capabilities and should really drag one to a
con someday so much of the stuff still exists I recently found a trove of reels that were audio
books from the 70s and 80s they're so much clearer than the cassette tapes I have from the same period
we should be doing real to real I still think we should not be doing real to real but we should
be making sure that we solidly archive the digital recordings that we're making do any of you have
anything so about real to real I uh no I do not myself own 10 real to real tape recorders however
David Bamford has written to us and said reconnecters reconnect program is being coordinated by himself
and med mcdonald we cannot put recordings on real to real tape I'm afraid but if you bring a mini
disc player along we'll do our best so I have two comments on that the first is that you do not
need a mini disc player you need a mini disc recorder a mini disc player will do you no good
um but fortunately I have several mini disc recorders and now that I know it's a thing I will be
put bringing them along so that you can give me a feed off the sand desk for the whole
convention that sounds great I would like to say thanks Chris Garcia because as usual I think I
may like a joke about real to real tapes and Chris comes in with the archivist knowledge mic drop
thank you Chris also I will not actually take real
mini disc recorders to easter con I would do were it not for the fact that we're flying
so somebody else if you're driving to easter con or or don't mind putting real mini disc
recorders in your luggage then off you go yarrick i think i only have about six i don't have as many
mini disc recorders as chris has real to real tape recorders and they're a lot smaller i have
none of either we heard from karen shafer who is catching up on octa-thorpe so some of these
comments are about previous episodes in fact episodes where we may forgotten that we talked
about what karen is commenting on but we're gonna i'm gonna put her head anyway she read the tainty
cup on my recommendation and loved it yes yes i'm gonna convert you all eventually um yes and we made
we really have made jokes about the miniapolis in 75 bid which we have messed up isn't highly
possible so they were bidding for the 1973 world con for decades and then they decided to bid for
2073 but we were never bidding for 75 which is apparently the joke that we made so yes it was
basically a silly joke where they were bidding for the 1973 world con at the 1973 world con and
continued to do that for a long time and then people started joking about 2073 and now maybe
there will be a bid for 2073 but basically it's all a bunch of fannish fun nice karen also sent
us another email um saying in a past podcast you asserted that it's easier for us fans to attend
virtual uk conventions which just agrees because the time zone means that programming in the uk starts
in the morning which is super early in the morning for the us and it's much better the opposite way
around where us programming starts in the morning and is at a nice civilized afternoon time for the
uk now i agree and i'm not sure why we asserted it was easier for us fans to attend virtual uk
conventions but i suspect Alison asserted that i think i might have asserted this easier for me
it's not difficult for me to attend west coast us conventions because i'm not so interested in the
program but i'm very interested in the parties and they always happen after i go to bed
now which is very sad karen does acknowledge that yes if you're interested in socializing in the
evening then this is true us fans can socialize in our daytime with uk fans in the evening as we
have amply proved time and time again and indeed prove on a daily basis in cafe mousse and elsewhere
so i do want to say obviously uh catch up also makes this kind of work in the opposite direction
to an extent where if you have catch up you can watch it regardless of time zone and a lot of
streamed stuff is on catch up as well so i guess that's another confounding factor but no i do
think like if you want to be on discord chatting along with other people watching the program
then that is a very good point for virtual seattle if seattle does streaming and gets its catch up
online fairly quickly it's really nice to in our kind of early daytime get online when america's
asleep and watch a bunch of catch up on the previous day there's the things that people thought were
really good and i did that at this con and i'm sure it'll work for this as well and it's
important listeners who have not been listening since the dawn of time do you want to explain what
cafe mousse is cafe mousse is a zoom that i do get in touch with me lot the cupboard if you're
interested and it's just basically people hanging out but i also do one in the afternoon sometimes
for that americans come to and then americans do all come quite a lot of them come to our evening
events like the london first thursday virtual meeting and things of that kind raj wrote in
mastodon he says he was initially very disappointed when he read for the blurb for lady's last con
because he had assumed it was about her last science fiction convention rather than a confidence
trick which is hilarious me too raj i don't understand why anyone would think that but fair
enough two people did he says glasco has lots of architectural obscenities the building of the
m8 through the heart of the city but the m8's such a lovely road and he also writes in with some
things he's planning to nominate for the hugos so he uh recommends bond bond and james bond by
eric malinsky which is a short story on the podcast imaginary worlds he also talks about the novelette
lake of souls from the recent um short fiction collection by an lechie um which is also called
lake of souls and then in novella he recommends last stop by jango wexler so thank you very much
raj and we also heard from tami coxin about hugo uh nominations and she just notes on
administrators transferring nominations in in best dramatic presentation they can only do that
if you have room on your balla in the category that the nomination would need to move too so you
should try and make sure that you put it where you think it goes and if you're very worried you
should leave a gap in the other um in the other category so thank you very much for pointing that
out tami that is useful info we heard from dc who would like to point out that sliding doors was
probably inspired by 1987 polish film prismideck uh english title blind chance in which a man
runs for train and three different timelines unfold and dc thinks it's a better film because
sliding doors and end in a very good way but it does have john hannah i really like the ending of
sliding doors but maybe that is just me also um as far as i can tell uh pris bidetck like i can't
buy or rent anywhere dc where sliding doors did have the advantage like press a button and watch
it that was a key uh feature of it for me british bradshaw writes to us to say that we live in time
has we to bix content for those interested which i actually knew and i've been intended to go and
see this movie in the cinema but i have missed it so i'm gonna have to pick it up on streaming
um but i do want to see it because i'm not sure it's a very good movie but it's got hantrick car
fields of florince pureed it oh that's good love for me i got confused with in time which is genre
and isn't very good uh we also heard on facebook from farimenderson who notes that there was at
least one nominee who submitted a package to the hugo finalist um packet that was two thirds co-written
with a very well known sf writer um but they don't mention who that was uh and megbert donald says
bellfast program the aim is that program will open in late february to participants for sign up
so go sign up on plan z now so you're all set to go do do that if you also want to see some
terrible puns i recommend going and reading the comments on the facebook post because meg got her
pun on i want to know who this person is who kept on making him submit everything that was cool it
was somewhat now i'm really curious i'm very fascinated far if you want to name names do get back to us
if you want to name name secretly we won't do on the podcast then you can also do this
on the subject of the bellfast easter con um i have volunteered to do the discord
or i've been asked to do the discord and i have wanted to do the discord uh so i'm doing that i'm
learning java i'm not learning java uh but i sort of imploking java to see what happens um so yes
so if anyone's interested in volunteering for moderating a discord um do volunteer at bellfast
website um i think people already have which is good i'm extremely pleased about this because
i said to the notes saying i will absolutely do the discord if nobody else volunteers so yay
well done john and i would not have done it as well as john will do it because i would have done
a discord where i was like oh you want a thread on a program item here's a place you could put that
thread yeah no me i think that's um hmm interesting yeah i'd have been kind of
here's here's a discord guys off you go and build it i'm sure the discord will be particularly
looking for people who are coming to um bellfast virtually and it strikes me that our listeners
might include quite a lot of people like that because people who are actually in bellfast will
probably have less time to moderate the discord than people who are not in bellfast so if if you're
not going to be in bellfast this is a job you could do that will be really helpful to the con and also
a great deal of fun i'm sure yes another bellfast update they've also said that they will be closing
the application process for bursaries to cover travel accommodation on sunday 16th of february
12 noon so if you're listening to this now and you if you're listening to this right now
and you would like to apply for some bursaries to help you make it to bellfast you have
probably about two and a half days to do so so do get onto the website and take a look
we have also some news from iridescence which is the bid for the 2026 easter con um they
sent a email around there is a zoom forum which is on the day we're recording um it only got announced
the day before um so sorry we haven't told you about this in advance listeners but if you would
like to know when future things like this are happening you should go to easter con 2026.org
and you should sign up for their mailing list because that is how i have found out about it
listeners and we will probably report on whatever happens at that zoom in the next episode
allyson do you want to tell us what is the bsfa we thought it would be good to do a segment on the bsfa
i am i am a member of the bsfa um and let's talk a little bit about what it is it is the
british science fiction association it has been going since um 1958 and members include
authors academics fans editors other interested people you can join joining gets you a ton of
publications and the chance to vote in the bsfa awards which you also get if you go to easter
con but um i think not if you attend easter con virtually i'm not sure about that probably though
and it also gets you just a sense that you're part of this big uk community of science fiction fans
which or science fiction related people which i think is good and i having spent quite a lot
of years not being a member of the bsfa i rejoined a few years ago and i have not
regretted that decision and we're going to talk about the bsfa a lot and we will put a link so
that you too can join the british science fiction association if you would like to in the show notes
so one thing uh we heard from the bsfa this week was we got the long lists for the bsfa awards
so for those of you who are not fully up to date with the bsfa awards the current process is a
two-stage one where everyone in the bsfa can nominate things and they go on a long list and
then you can vote for things from the long list to make a short list and then uh at easter con
and shortly before you vote things on the shortlist and they win and the long list is good i mean
if nothing else it basically acts as a sort of big long recommendation list of things that bsfa
members like which is quite nice there's a whole bunch of categories at the moment and i was
worried when they expanded the number of categories that maybe it was an expansion too far but actually
there's a lot of stuff in all of the categories so it's not like there is a shortage of things to be
uh voting on in the shortlist and yeah it's generally a pretty interesting list of stuff and i would say
that because we are on it i should say we are in best short nonfiction yes for episode 122
which is true because we are best we are short nonfiction um we are short nonfiction but we are not
crucially written short nonfiction which is what the awards actually is for according to the website
yes i'm very confused by this because i thought they were going to take the word written out of
this after the last time we were put on the long last time we got all the shortlist in fact i thought
they put the word written in after we got on the shortlist no they no so i noticed when they read
the when we were in the bsfa award ceremony in 2022 they read the definition of the category
out before reading out the nominees and it was at that point i noticed that there a definition
they had read out definitely didn't mean we were eligible and i was like oh i just assumed we were
on the basis that we're in it but now i also agree with Alison when they split this category up i
thought there had been discussion about making it not purely written but Liz is right that it does
still say written so i am a little bit confused and i'm wondering if i if that was something i
misremembered or or whether it kind of got changed after i had paid attention to it or or what the
deal was but i do want to say we have been nominated we have been nominated specifically for episode
122 which was the episode in which we talked about the world fantasy awards and the kitschies and
the Ursula K Le Guin Award but also the episode where we reported on the news about
organotrovwe Donald Epecchi for the first time and Liz didn't get free tickets to Disneyland
oh no i got very excited about peppers ghosts didn't i yeah you did yeah but yes i don't know why
that episode is the one that has been nominated but i guess if we were making a Hugo packet
we would have a good signal as to which one we should put in it but thank you very much
it's an honor to be on the long list i mean i mean it's although the answer for the long list is
one person like live so thank you one person um i will also say that there is the whole of the
podcast eight days of dino in jones is nominated in best nonfiction long form and a blog of book
reviews is also nominated in the nonfiction short form so obviously these categories are a little
bit fuzzy uh the category just says we have to be under 30 000 words i'm pretty sure one of our
episodes is under 30 000 words but i confess i've never put the transcript through a word counter
that's true yeah because on the long list it just says for short articles and they're equivalent
they'll all be then because um if you're if you're reading out of speech you're going to be reading
it out at between a hundred and hundred and twenty words a minute so 30 000 words is kind of nearly
300 minutes of podcast which is way longer than we manage in an episode ever even let's have most
extreme yeah i was joking a bit i mean my thesis is like 35 000 words so okay that's a special we
can record can that would be absolutely because me and Liz both do have PhD theses and as far as i
know no one's ever except for Ian recording the start of it no Ian did the start of my TAF report
hi Ian because i subscribed to his patreon so that he would respect me no respect my opinions
i don't think he ever respected me so you both have thesis's and i have or theses theses
and you have fees it no and i have oh god john and i have a light hearted ten minutes to article
about almond croissant which i do want to that will be good that will be good it's part of my
guff report now that i have actually submitted an article to another editor we should record this
where are the bsfa awards defined because i can't actually find it i looked on the website on the
page that says about towards okay yeah so they took the requirement for the written word out of the
fiction um categories but they did not take it out of the non-fiction categories um maybe that's
why i'm getting confused don't know anyway unclear if we're eligible but thank you very
much for putting us on the long list but we appreciate it anyway i'm also going to suggest
that when you're doing an award it's a great idea to have an eligibility team
collect checking whether things are eligible before publishing a list of nominations that's just me
it's tricky isn't it because the long list is i think literally everything that got nominated
and so it's not clear to me whether the eligibility checking should happen before or after that step
it's also possible they did do a quick check and i also appreciate that i think the bsfa awards is
run by a single person who does a pretty good job yeah i mean that's the thing you can't possibly check
everything on that long list there's hundreds of things i assume someone is in a cursory check
that like there weren't any spam bots just like you know sticking in the name of beta books they
got about ai or something i think someone's probably checked the works exist but that's really i think
as far as you can go with that number of stuff otherwise you'd spend like three months vetting
them and then it would be easter and on that subject laser you looking forward to doing the
Hugo Awards yeah but there's no long list phase in the Hugo Awards is there yeah so it's going to be
you know prevery category you just do the you know the top ones that look like they might be on
the ballot and you don't need to do the you know 27 000 short stories that got one vote true i can
hear different music now by the way over the last few weeks we've been hearing i think rumors is
probably gossip gossip to the effect that the bsfa have been rejecting incoming reviews
so we were alerted last week to a blog comment from a reviewer who reviews for the bsfa reviews
steven french and they say all the reviews i wrote for bs reviews reviews the reviews journal of the
bish sites fixed association have to discarded by the new editor and then says because the bsfa is
going for charitable status and so reviews of books that the review is not happy with or did not
understand are not acceptable which is interesting because i think we'd heard the same rumors from a
couple of other sources that the new incoming bsfa reviews editor was not publishing reviews that
were a bit negative or possibly a book they didn't understand and was trying to go for a much more
positive tone yeah and we we subsequently talked to another reviewer who essentially only learned
that there were guidelines about reviews being positive after they'd already written some reviews
and so then those reviews would either not be published or need significant alteration
we were a little bit concerned by this because they seem to be a bit of a divergence from how
like reviewing should work and also it was strange to me that it was linked to their charitable status
by one of the commenters because i don't think there's any reason that charitable status should
preclude negative reviews for instance the science fiction foundation publishes an academic journal
which definitely has not you know non-positive reviews in there so we did a little bit of journalism
which is i think a new a new thing for us
Stephen French said that this was linked to bsfa's um application for charitable status which is
a rumor that had been going around and i wondered whether it was simply that the bsfa thought
charitable meant being nice and wasn't meaning being a charity and so i don't know it could be that
but i thought i'd ask so i emailed and i asked is there a change in policy if there is what's
the new policy and is this linked to any application for charitable status and we heard back from the
chair of the bsfa Alan Stroud who wrote this is a simple misunderstanding on the part of the reviews
editor in relation to bsfa's oversight of its publications the editorial policy of bsfa publications
is usually determined by the editors there is no connection between bsfa review editorial policy
and the bsfa transition to being a charity the transition has not been confirmed and will need
to be confirmed or rejected as a motion at the forthcoming e gm on the 23rd of February the bsfa's
constitution is to approach science fiction and science fiction criticism and there's no priority
to favor either over the other and we will be working with the reviews editor to produce a clearer
set of guidelines so the answer seems to be that there is no from the top change in policy but
something has happened at bsfa review and that that is something that the bsfa is currently having
discussions about shall we say and i think the the really telling thing in the responses the
part where Alan says there's no priority to favor either part of the bsfa mission over the other
and therefore i assume that means that criticism will continue to be something the bsfa does well
which is for the better i think i hope and to be fair criticism is something that bsfa has been
doing well over almost all of its um how long ago was 1958 60 some odd years ages yeah ages
i wanted to pick out one of the things from Alan's statement i'd like to thank Alan for getting back
to us in good time with a very clear statement that was great but i want to pick one thing out of it
which is that Alan has said that there is an e gm on the 23rd of February to discuss converting
to charitable status if you remember you might be going oh i'm not sure i knew about this and it
will happen before our next recording so our or before our next episode comes out so it is on the
23rd of um February for a bsfa member in the newsletter kind of about halfway down a several
thousand word newsletter there is a thing for bsfa events which includes that there is an e gm on
but on zoom on the 23rd of February um it it doesn't have anything about the agenda though so so this
is the first that i'd heard that this was going to be put to the membership on that date so i am
raising the signal on it and we'll continue to do so and hopefully we'll get an agenda and full
details well in advance of that meeting the other thing that newsletter said was that a new chair
is to be voted on because Alan is coming to the end of his two terms and the person that Alan is
recommending for the next chair is Stuart Haughson and Stuart gave a very good talk on the intersection
of ethnicity and games at the previous east con and uh he's a top chap so that seems like a good
pick to me but i don't know if i don't know exactly how it works i don't know whether anyone will be
i don't know how competitive bsfa elections tend to be so i don't know whether it's a sure thing or
not but um but yes that was a bit of news as well um so one of the things that Alan says in the
newsletter is that he's going to continue support Stuart for as long as necessary in a decision-making
role as Stuart has long covid i think we'll want to see how that works really because
you know you want to you want to make sure that in practice it is Stuart sharing the
organization and and not Alan though when we were talking about this in our back chat we did say
actually a four-year term limit seems very very short for the bsfa um it seems it seems way
shorter than it would need to be for a chair but there we go
do we have anything else to talk about or is it picks so we we mentioned last episode the
eight days of dino in jones podcast which is emily tesh and rebecca frame oh and i noted that
rebecca frame oh's book was on sale and it looked good so i bought it and i made it and it's pretty
good um so as as noted it is called lady eve's last con it is uh basically lesbian romance from
some uh hostlers who um it's it's essentially a pair of sisters who have been hustling and
essentially have been one of them has been jilted by a very rich man named estiban menders yuki
and so the other sister goes to try and essentially trap him into marriage as revenge
which is a pretty fun uh a pretty fun plot she disguises herself like as an extremely young naive
debutante and then goes off to have swanky parties and go to rich people uh parties and fun and
make sure that no one no one spots her until she has enacted her con but her target has a sister
who is smart and obviously attractive and is she going to figure out what is going on
before ruth has a chance to enact this con and i'm not going to give too many spoilers away but
one thing i will say is that i went into it thinking okay this is going to be the sort of thing where
you know at some point there's going to be a reveal of her hidden identity and actually the reveal
of the hidden identity ends up happening fairly early on in the book which is very refreshing
it's like you could have like eked this out forever and instead she goes no actually i'm gonna
tell soul what's going on here and then this changes like the whole the whole book so it just
unexpected things it is a romance but there's a very solid um like crimey mystery plot under there
it's got lots of interesting relationships because you've got like the different sibling
relationships on different sides um it is all kind of in like you know they're on a
a satellite and they go off to the like man-made beach in space okay i think i just end up picking
books that i say it's fun but this is fun and satisfying and the resolution of the mystery
crime plot gets a little bit complicated for me and i wasn't 100% sure what was going on there
but i was kind of 100% sold by the emotions of what was going on so that was fine yeah and it has kind
of a happy ending but it's not like a kind of super sappy happy ending it is very much a yeah
this is where we have got to and this is a happy ending but it's not like let's see where it goes
i liked it i think alison is reading it now as well yes so after um this says she would take one for
the team last week i checked in my library they had a copy on ebooks to download so i immediately
downloaded and i am reading it and i will expect to finish it this week yeah and i was pleasantly
surprised but i think probably it might not be a book for me because it's probably a bit too fun
for me i don't i believe that books should be detergent and serious and not fun at all so i don't
know that's but i will i mean it's i don't think it would be likely to be a pick but i'm very glad
ceaseless picking it i think it's very interesting book one to watch so my pick this week which is
not genre at all um is the brutalist which is one of the Oscar nominations and is a three and a half
hour film uh about an architect who is who escapes from well is liberated from a concentration
camp at the end of world war two and travels to america and there gets starts off kind of
trying to just get his feet on the ground but very rapidly gets an architectural commission for
um an enormous project and this spins out slowly and very beautifully and not necessarily in
ways you're going to expect for yeah three hours and thirty five minutes running time but that
includes a 15 minute intermission which was extremely welcome in our in acid of a head as a chance
to stretch our legs and and get another beer and so on one of my friends said this is four hours
of my life i'm not getting back and another one said within about two minutes well i found it
absolutely compelling throughout i really liked it i thought it was excellent i am not
convinced it needed to be three hours or thirty minutes five minutes long i think it could easily
have been you know two and three quarter hours without an intermission um and and i i have notes
on where i would recommend um brady kobe takes the takes the cuts for that um adrian brody is the
star as the architect of the title and um he is absolutely amazing throughout but obviously
lots of good performances everywhere it's not really about brutalism if you think it's called
the brothe list and there is a sort of implication that this is a bow house trained architect um
from hongary um there's a kind of implication that it's about brutalism but it kind of isn't
really so if you're if you're kind of really into 20th century architecture this might not be
the movie for you architects hate it um though they probably don't hate it as much as they hated
begalopolis so you know i think that would be an interesting panel discussion to listen to
because it has all the same cliches about architecture being a field where torture
geniuses work alone and and cannot stand any sort of a dilution of their vision and and
everyone who actually works in architecture will be like well it's all about what you can do with
the resources and space you have available it's it's the most compromising field of all
so so architects don't like this movie i did like this movie a lot listeners all you have to do is
find a single friend of yours who is an architect who likes this movie and you too can write a letter
of comment uh yeah that's true if you're an architect and you love this movie write in if you
love 20th century architecture write in that means new nick givers i will say that as a physicist i
regularly enjoy movies where the physics is not always up to snuff um but yes no i take the point
now i i i am sort of vaguely intrigued by this but not intrigued enough to spend the three and
a half hours it would take to satisfy my intrigue think you take it i might well do i generally think
films should not be allowed to be over two hours maybe not allowed is too strong but so so this is
one of those movies where the critic response is very much more positive than the fewer response
i am gonna pick and um it's an ongoing pick but i am gonna pick severance season two oh
because i was a bit worried that severance season two would not be quite as good as severance season
one and that worry it turns out was unfounded because it is still great uh very much enjoying it
if you have seen severance season one uh you know you need to watch season two now if you have not
seen severance season one go go and watch severance season one now it's really good i mean i think
you can still get a seven-day trial for apple tv plus but you know it's worth a month of apple tv
plus to watch severance and you can watch some other things while you're at it it is great we're
going to bleep on about this every single week so you know oh my god this we're recording on sunday
friday's episode by word anyway it's just really good and like yeah it's just really good
did we not in fact pick season one at some point probably but this is season two it's completely
different so so severance was three they've had three years to think about the direction they
want to take this which is interesting because i think if they'd made season two immediately after
season one wrapped i think it would have been much less daring than season two has actually been
i don't know how i don't know whether they yeah i don't know what the production timeline was but
but yeah certainly they do seem to be doing interesting things still and like yeah just really
really thought it was i think it is very good so far i'm fascinated by what is going on yeah
Alison picked season one in episode 59 she did i'm not saying we can't pick it again i'm saying
that we did pick it previously well no we picked season one season two that's a whole different thing
it's like i could pick guardians of the galaxy two even if someone already picked
colonies a galaxy one but does that mean i'm allowed to pick severance episodes after episode four
season two as a separate pick or have you preemptively picked the whole of season two we need some sort
of eligibility team don't we what at the end is rubbish john i mean i'm confident it won't be but
we will cross that bridge when we come to it fair fun factlessness i did not pick seats
severance season two this week because i thought that we've only had four episodes and it could
all go to tosh before the end of the season so john has trumped me and i thought i would wait till
the season is finished but that's fine john has picked it i mean the thing is i can't pick any of
the books i've read because they're all dreadful no i mean they're great but i don't know if i
should pick them no it's fine this is this is a reasonable pick uh i just think it's funny to
complain about it yeah no that's right it's fine it's fine i'm quite glad you picked it because
as i thought about it and that was the Octothorpe podcast and it's goodbye for me it's goodbye for me and goodbye
from me
[Music]
all right so this is completely off topic but there is very faint flute music in my headphones
which i'm not as far as i know playing i don't think i hear any flute music no but i wonder if like
my headphones the big cable is somehow acting as an antenna and i'm picking up some kind of
weird broadcast signal i mean maybe it's only one ear it's only in one ear sure it's not just a
weird form of tinnitus i mean it's only when i'm wearing my headphones so probably not
anyway continue and i will give you updates as warranted the theme music for this episode was
fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in competec.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0
license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]