You could just put it on Git or something and we could all simultaneously edit it and push it back.
Yes! The best!
We should have a Git repo for the show notes. Absolutely.
I love that.
That's hilarious.
Because we're not actually a tech podcast.
I just feel that sharing text files on the internet should be simpler than this.
I mean, I feel like your computer shouldn't be haunted, Alison, but like, we work with what we've got.
My computer honestly isn't haunted.
I mean, none of the evidence supports that perspective.
Definitely haunted.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very eighth episode of the Octothorpe podcast, a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And we have a raft of letters of comment this week.
We're very sorry.
We did not correctly set up our email forwarding and that means that we had inadvertently ignored all emails for the last two months.
So, we've got a lot to talk about.
And thanks very much to listener Claire Briley of Croydon, who pointed this out to us helpfully.
Also, when you say we failed to set up our email, John.
I'm blaming John.
I mean, to be fair, none of us checked and we probably should have done.
It's true.
I probably should not just blame John.
We can leave that bit out.
I will not blame John personally for our rudeness.
But for other things.
It's probably mostly my fault.
Right then.
So, from the top.
Our first email of comment was on the 13th of April 2020, which at the time of recording is two months and four days ago.
And it is from one Andrew January of Reading.
And he says that he came across a website that does special video chat.
And you move around in a 2D space.
And as you get near people, you can have group video chats with them.
And it lets you kind of treat a big group gathering on the internet as a kind of space rather than just a kind of set of rooms as in Zoom or a set of channels as in Discord.
He doesn't mention what the name of the website was.
We did talk about something a little bit similar to this last episode, which was Kala.
But yeah, that sounds cool.
Wouldn't it be cool if it was 3D and you could do it in VR on your VR headset?
That would be awesome.
I have been very sad to not discover.
I was expecting to go into the Oculus store and find all manner of VR experiences of this kind.
But they don't appear to exist yet.
I don't really want to spend an entire evening with my VR headset on, much as I love it.
It's quite heavy and not entirely conducive.
And it would be hard to, like, drink.
One of the things I do on these Zoom chats is drink.
And I cannot drink and play Oculus Quest at the same time.
I would need to drink my beer with a straw.
And, you know, there, that gets you.
I think we did on a previous podcast.
I think Liz suggested one of those beer hats.
I was going to suggest that again because it's such a good idea.
A VR headset with integrated beer hat.
I may need one of these.
Yes.
I'm going to be a billionaire.
If Andrew has seen this thing, has he actually seen it used for a large event?
Because I feel like there's a number of people saying, well, there's a proof of concept of these things.
But I'm not sure to what extent they actually exist and also whether they're actually being used for large events or whether they're just kind of tech demos.
I'm also slightly worried that the problem we've talked about before, that it's relatively easy in a physical conversation to say, this is amazing, but I absolutely have to go to the loo now,
is much harder in these video conferencing chats and it can be hard to just kind of slip off the edge of one of them without people kind of noticing, especially if they then see from their VR environment that you're engaged in conversation with more interesting people across the room.
Differently interesting.
It's a good save.
It's, I suppose, hard to hide at the other end of the bar when it's a 2D space with no hiding places.
But I've done, I've done kind of abrupt goodbyes from Zoom calls and people don't seem to have been too offended.
So I don't, I don't know.
I think people are usually pretty chill about, maybe I'm wrong, but I feel like people are pretty chill about that kind of thing.
Right, on to letter of comment two.
So this is from Mark Olson on the 25th of April, 2020.
And he says that he stumbled across us and listened to our first podcast, which he enjoyed.
But he does say that he thinks we might want to mention the date because he did not read it.
Sorry.
He did not listen to it close to the time of recording.
And so some of it didn't make a lot of sense.
And if you remember, episode one, we had not fully gone into lockdown yet.
So a lot of it was immediately rendered quite dated.
Today is Wednesday, the 17th of June, 2020.
It is.
And this show will probably be going out on the 24th of June, I don't guess.
Oh yes, we're recording early.
That's kind of showing behind the curtain, isn't it?
It is.
It is indeed.
But yeah, we were talking in episode one about the lack of a written constitution for Eastercon.
And he mentions the Lunarians, which were New York fandom.
And I did not appreciate this.
But because of a series of very, very rigidly defined rules in the club constitution,
the club was invalid because they had not sent notice of elections,
which meant the old officers' terms had expired.
The new officers had been improperly elected because the notices had not been sent out.
And so there were no officers.
There was no secretary.
So there was no one who could send out a notice of any elections.
And so there could never be any new officers.
And therefore the club stopped.
And this was a club with fewer than 20 people, all of whom saw each other frequently.
So there is a sort of risk in having rigorously defined systems,
which is if you don't have the imagination to foresee the way in which the system could go wrong,
you can end up painting yourself into rather a corner.
The problem was solved by forming a new club called Lunarians 2.0.
And that failed because they couldn't agree about who they would let into the new club.
So it stopped.
I have thoughts about this, which will come later in the episode,
with regards to the Worcestershire Business Meeting this year.
But it is a cautionary tale and one I would encourage people to listen to.
I particularly liked his phrase of the club was, what did he say?
The club accumulated noxious dead wood.
And I wouldn't like to comment as to whether that applies to the World Science Fiction Society.
This just feels a bit like, you know, when I have an account on a website somewhere
and then I forget my password and forget to update the email address
and basically just have to make a new account all over again.
Just keep making new clubs called Lunarians 2.0, 3.0, 3.14, whatever you like.
Just go for it.
Yes, there's a good way of dealing with it, I think.
I think there's a spectrum of fandom and you can tell which end I'm on.
Yeah, the east end.
Well, I mean, I've always been on the spectrum of fandom that said we shouldn't really organise anything.
And I mean, we can organise stuff in the sense of making things happen.
It's just the point where you decide that it's easier to make things happen with a written constitution.
I'm always slightly sceptical about because in my experience,
things of that kind tend to be used in order to prevent things from happening rather than making them happen.
And anyone who is a co-host on the Octothought podcast will know how true it is that Alison is opposed to formal organisation of things.
That's harsh.
It is harsh. I don't regret it, but it is harsh.
To be fair, when John got in touch and said,
are you interested in doing a podcast? I did warn him about this at that exact point.
I knew what I was getting into. It's true.
Mark also wrote to us to comment on later episodes.
So he said that he thought our point about fandom doing virtual socialising from day one was quite perspective
and commented on our talking about the first Thursday and then talked about Con Zealand.
And he is, I think, quite sceptical of Con Zealand because he isn't convinced that you can have a time zone
which sufficiently sort of encompasses everyone who needs to be encompassed
because you need to encompass kind of traditional world con fandom in the US,
but also you need to encompass New Zealand fandom, obviously,
because it's a New Zealand con and so on.
And he also says that he's sceptical of having programming for such a thing
because you need to have enough programme that you can call it a world con,
but not so much programming.
If you have a level of programming that won't tire people out,
it will feel like a much smaller con.
And he basically concludes by saying this, that he's not criticising Con Zealand's competence.
He's just not sure that it's a workable proposition in any way.
I think since he wrote that stuff like Balticon has happened,
which has shown that you can, I think, get around some of those problems quite well.
But it's an interesting take as to kind of at what point do you sort of change things
enough to make it workable online to the point where it doesn't really feel as big as a world con should anymore.
Yes, I think a lot of the points Mark raises have possibly been addressed by other virtual conventions in the meantime.
So if Mark is not too upset with us for failing to read his emails in a timely fashion and he has any updates,
we'd love to hear them.
Yeah, definitely.
And I think you can cat-hurt.
I mean, we can cat-hurt panellists to showing up in the right rooms at the right time,
just about, and in the case of the Eastercon, usually by bribing them with a free beer if they'd like that.
So I'm sure you can get them to show up for the right Zoom.
You might just need a team of Zoom wranglers.
Yes, and send beer sort of to panellists through various delivery services.
And I also think about the Hugos, I think part of the problem with the Hugos is you do have this tension
between providing the best experience for people in the room and also providing a good experience for people
watching online at home.
And possibly if you're only trying to do one of those things at once, it will simplify things eventually.
That is fair.
That's a good point.
Alison, do you have anything you'd like to say?
I've promised to myself I'm going to be quieter this week.
I mean, firstly, episode title, so that's great.
Secondly, we like you talking.
It's a key part of our shtick is that we talk.
But actually, I feel I've probably said all I've got to say about Con Zealand
until I see the draft programme and their draft plans for social space, at which point I expect
to have enormous amounts to say.
So I am holding my fire on that.
But I did like his final thing saying that we seemed very reasonable and are we sure we're fans?
Yes, that did make me chuckle.
I liked that.
We've definitely disproved that in subsequent episodes, haven't we?
Yep, yep.
Well, we've proven our lack of reasonability both in terms of having had very wide-ranging opinions
on future episodes, but also by having not done a reasonable job of reading letters of comment.
So we've neatly put ourselves straight back into the fan category.
Also, I will say I edited out all of the really acrimonious bits, obviously.
So it's very easy to be reasonable when you can edit out the arguments afterwards.
Yes, I was going to say, I meant to say it's clearly, we're clearly reasonable in the edit.
Andrew Hogg sent us an email on the 19th of May, and he was worried that we're mispronouncing
Claire Briley of Corrigan's surname, because he remembers hearing it differently while watching
a stream of the 2011 Hugo Awards, and wouldn't want any of us to be embarrassed publicly by getting
it wrong.
I am 99% certain we are pronouncing Claire Briley's surname correctly.
Because I have been harangued on that matter on many times, on many occasions.
When I gave Claire her Hugo Award, I pronounced her surname incorrectly.
And so if I ever win my own Hugo Award, my entire acceptance speech will just be to say
her name correctly, and then moonwalk off the stage.
Can you moonwalk?
No, I'm going to have to learn to moonwalk.
Okay, so you better get practising then, hadn't you?
I'm not going to win a Hugo, Alison, so I'm not sure it's going to come up.
Are you a Hugo finalist?
I am, as mentioned by Mark Plummer in his letter of comment from the 23rd of May 2020, which
is addressed dear Alison Liz and Hugo Award finalist, the boy Coxon.
Dr. Hugo Award finalist, the boy Coxon.
That's me.
That is you.
And so he says he's enjoying the Octothorpe podcast, which is good.
And he also asked whether or not we could give ourselves names as according to the style of the kids TV show Octonauts, in which they're a character called Vegemoles, which are half animal and half vegetable.
Hence, tunip is half tuna, half turnip.
And carprica is half carp and half paprika.
So tell me about Octothorpe.
Octonauts.
I know nothing of this.
It's a children's programme about basically a crew of underwater explorers who are all animals.
And they go on, they have like, they have like a set of vehicles, a bit like Thunderbirds.
Nice.
And then they go on adventures.
And I haven't really watched it in that much detail, but apparently it is like scientifically accurate about all its underwater adventures.
And they also, for some reason, have these things which are half animal, half vegetable.
And all their names are like a, you know, mashup of the two names.
So, what's a good one?
Albachoy is half bok choy, half albacore.
According to Wikipedia anyway.
It's good, isn't it?
Ten out of ten.
I could be hadtato.
Half haddock, half potato.
That's pretty good.
Yeah.
I was proud.
Or, hmm.
Try to think what my favourite, my favourite fish is definitely haddock.
But what's my favourite vegetable?
Courgette.
Hadette.
Um, yeah.
So, is that good?
I think that's pretty good.
Are we limited to vegetables only or can we have fruit?
No, it's vegetables only, isn't it?
Hmm.
But it does say animals.
It doesn't necessarily say it has to be fish.
That's true, but I mean.
Just both of the examples of fish.
Generally, the theme of the show is fish related.
I've only seen like snippets of Octonauts when babysitting children who loved Octonauts.
That is fair.
I have never seen any Octonauts, but feel I should now go and look them up.
Maybe we should have a special episode next week.
About Octonauts.
And I'm going to be a crab to choke.
Yes.
Nailed it.
Oh, great name.
That is a flimmy great name.
Love it.
Okay.
Straight in the show.
But Alison, have you got a Octonauts name?
I have been thinking about this.
I may have to return to you next week.
But in the meantime, I quite like moose rot, which is a combination of a moose and a carrot.
Hmm.
I like that.
But when I first thought that, it said a combination of an animal and a vegetable.
And I was like, oh, you mean like salmon and sushi rice.
But I think I may have been missing the point there.
Also, neither of those is a vegetable.
Sushi rice is definitely a vegetable.
Is rice as a vegetable?
Yeah.
It's not meat.
I mean, it's as much of a vegetable as paprika.
Paprika is a pepper.
Chili pepper.
Paprika?
Paprika.
One of those is a chili pepper.
Plus, we are getting that off Wikipedia.
I'm not sure if that is a fully canonical Octonauts name.
Andrew Hogg asked, is there a piece of media you waited over a decade for and it actually lived up to expectations?
Um, yeah.
Which is such a good question that I think we should bring it back at a future episode.
Not least because I've got a hook to tie it to one of the Hugo nominated fancasts.
Oh, hello.
Interesting.
Which talks about books that haven't come out yet, which is not, is kind of irritating.
But they were saying that Susanna Clarke's Piranesi lives up to expectations.
There is nothing like Jonathan Strange and Mr Norrell.
And he also says he's looking forward to further updates on LOF, the Liz Only fan fund.
It's not clear to me whether this is only for visiting Liz, whether this is only for Liz to visit or both.
But, yeah.
Got to get that going.
I think this is a follow up to our previous discussion where I threatened to send you a map and point out where Australia was, if you recall.
It could well be.
I'm basically my own, you know, fan fund zone for now.
Ha ha ha ha ha!
And Mark very kindly described Octothorpe as similar to listening, sitting in the bar, listening to the three of you having a conversation and being unable to get a word in edgeways.
Ha ha ha ha ha ha!
It's not untrue.
To which he said, Alison will add, so exactly like that then.
Ha ha ha ha ha!
And also I will say that Claire has mentioned a similar sentiment to me, but she says she always wins the arguments she has with us because we can't answer back to her witty repartee.
So this is actually a feature rather than a bug, I feel.
If you want to have the last word, just mutter under your breath as you listen and it will go well.
I thought that was a huge benefit of podcasts generally.
I mean, I'm forever shouting at podcasts.
And now you shout during them, as do we all.
Another man called Joseph Norton sent me an email to the podcast email address thanking me for putting MP3s of the vinyl albums of the Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy on my website,
which I did ages and ages ago because I have the vinyl albums and they're different to the original radio series.
So I recorded them from my dad's turntable using some audio recording software on a laptop.
And then because no one else had put them online, I thought, well, you know, no one's going to lose out.
Since then, there has been a vinyl release of Hitchhiker's, but I think it is a vinyl release of the BBC show.
I don't think it's a vinyl release of the original vinyl albums.
But yes, so he said thank you and you're welcome, Joseph.
Glad you're enjoying them.
And thanks for listening to the podcast.
It's nice that we have listeners who aren't actually already our personal friends.
It's not, it's actually not 100% clear to me whether he listens to the podcast or whether he found the podcast by googling my name.
Either one, that's an outcome.
That is an outcome.
Because I mean, there is so, I mean, he might have found your professional work.
He might have found your Hugo finalist things, you know.
Yeah.
You have a wide internet footprint.
Then we have Claire's.
Claire Briarley.
Get me.
I can pronounce it now.
And her letter of comment.
Does any, do either of you want to go through that?
You mean, would you like me to do some summarising?
Because you've done quite a lot of summarising on this podcast already.
I'm worried the listeners will be very bored of my voice.
Yes.
So Claire sent us a letter, having caught up with episodes six and seven.
Wishing all the best to John's microphone, which is no longer unwell.
And revealing she has drunk a beer called Edgelord.
She does not reveal whether she knew the meaning of the name of the beer at that time.
She's also asked if Stow Shirts make a grumpy old fart cap for Worldcon X Division heads.
Anything can be, things can be arranged.
They do now.
Anything can be arranged with Stow Shirts.
So Claire is.
Pretty much.
We discussed briefly, I think, this is how you lose the time war, which I think I had read and you guys had not read, correct?
Not yet.
Still haven't.
Still not read it.
It is on my iPad waiting.
It's very nice because I enjoyed it and thought it was good, but it did not speak to my heart.
Claire's written in because it did speak to her heart about the love story and about finding people and how truly distinct that is from sex and or friendship.
And also recommended the books by Nick Bantock called Griffin and Sabine, which I have never read, but I might look into because they're apparently a reminder of this is how you lose a time war.
Yeah, I'm looking forward to reading it because I have obviously heard an awful lot about it at this point.
I'm currently reading the Becky Chambers one, which I do not remember the name of.
I think it's To Be Taught If Fortunate.
To Be Taught If Fortunate.
And the reason I'm currently reading that is that because in the Hugo voter packet it only came as a PDF and I currently have a e-book version on loan from the library so I can read in a slightly nicer format, but I have to read it first.
But after that I shall probably do the rest of the novellas, so I will hopefully have listened to it by next time.
I'm sure nobody with any influence in these matters ever reads this, but I have taken the view that if your submission to the Hugo voter packet only comes in PDF format, then I will deprioritise it in my Hugo reading.
And seeing as I never managed to get all the Hugo reading done anyway, this means that you are less likely to get my vote.
I am sure I'm not the only person, but I thought I wanted to say this publicly so that the people out there who make the decision to put these things in as PDFs know that it's not actually as efficient as putting things in as e-pubs or any other e-book format.
And if you're doing it because you're worried that people will pirate the e-book, then you're being a bit silly because obviously the PDF is sufficient for people to be able to do that.
Anyway, I know that this has no effect, but I just kind of want to shout into the void occasionally.
Yeah, that's fair.
No, and I will say I do agree with you in that if a book is only available in a format that I don't, that I find stressful to read, or if a book is not available in full, then I'll try and read it.
I'll try and borrow it from the library.
But if the book doesn't come through by the time the deadline happens, then yeah, that will mean I don't vote for it.
Last year that was The Calculating Stars by Mary Robinette Cole, but then that won.
So I'm not sure that my failure to read it in time really affected it meaningfully at all.
It was a fantastic book.
Thoroughly enjoyed it.
Think it deserved to win.
Did not read it until after the ceremony because that was when my library hold came through.
I know it's really never up to the authors, is it?
It's decisions made at a publisher level, so I don't know to what extent that could be helped.
I agree with Alison entirely on the PDF thing, but I also read 100 pages of The Calculating Stars and decided, nope, and put it down and read something else.
Not every book has to be for everyone.
No, and I felt quite pleased myself for reading it and going, no, this is not my thing.
I'm putting it down and reading another book.
And I was on a reading holiday at the time, so there were probably several hundred other books around for me to choose from.
Did anyone write to us suggesting things that we could read or do to improve our awareness of Black Lives Matter and related issues, John?
No.
Have either of you done anything to enhance your awareness of your white privilege?
Yes.
I have read Superior by Angela Saini, and that was very good.
I think that it helped me see kind of some of the issues around ethnicity as a kind of categorisation system.
And I read it while on strike as part of the Black in the Ivory slash Black Lives in STEM strikes, which happened a week or two ago now.
I've also bought How to Be an Anti-Racist by Ibromex Kendi.
And also looking forward to reading that, but I have not yet read it.
I've also started monthly donations to a couple of other organisations that were on the Google sheet of organisations that we had in last week's show notes.
So that's what I did since last time.
Either of you do anything?
I put a load of books on my hold list for my local library, which were all extremely popular and will no doubt come through in about November.
But I mean, they will come through and I will then read them.
I listened to some podcasts by black creators.
The one I enjoyed most is called Nerds of Prey and hasn't actually had a new episode out since December.
So I'm not entirely sure I want to mention it specifically.
I liked some other ones, but they're more in my kind of normal tech and scientific niches rather than science fiction and fantasy ones.
I'm still looking for some recommendations there.
And I also donated some money to charities that work with disadvantaged people and with legal defence for people in the UK.
So my recommendation would be there is a list posted by Sirens Conference, which runs every year in the US, have posted a list of 50 works by black authors, which I am basically working my way through.
I've read some of them, some of them going on my wish list.
A couple of which I actually owned and will be now coming to the top of my reading list.
I am making an effort to read more books by black authors and buy more books by black authors, especially over the next couple of weeks, as I think there was a drive to try and buy them in a particular week and thus bring them to the top of the bestseller lists.
So I read The Nickel Boys by Colson Whitehead, which is not science fictional, but is another spectacular novel from him.
Quite a harrowing read about two young black men in a juvenile facility in the US in the 1960s, which is great.
Like John, I'm also an academic, so I'm reading a lot of the black in the ivory stories about the experiences of black academics and trying to think of ways that we can help in this area.
And I have also donated to some organisations from the list we put in the show notes last week.
Claire also sent me, she sent, I think, many people a short fanzine about Weetabix.
She didn't just send a short fanzine about Weetabix, she sent Weetabix. Have you not had your Weetabix yet?
I have had my Weetabix, but I don't want to talk.
What?
I have also had my Weetabix.
Oh, she sent you Weetabix as well.
There was a picture of an entire carrier bag full of Weetabix.
I don't know to whom Weetabix was sent, but I think it was a large operation.
I think I may have failed to, because obviously I got a Weetabix because I had sent Weetabix.
Yes.
My Weetabix arrived completely unharmed, but it did not go large letter.
I think the question of how you get a Weetabix through at large letter rate without harming it is still an open one.
That presumably means that you'll have a Weetabix impounded by Thai customs at some point, Liz.
I don't believe Claire has sent me a Weetabix, if only because she's not at any point asked for my post address in order to send me a Weetabix.
So unless she somehow intuited my address, or she decided to just put Weetabix care of Lizbathy, Thailand, hopefully they have not impounded a Weetabix.
Has anyone tried just sending a Weetabix to Claire Briley Fishlifter Towers Croydon and seeing if it arrived?
It might arrive.
The Royal Mail can really surprise you.
And Claire Briley, I assume, is not a terrifically common name.
Right, so if you work for the Royal Mail and you find a package in 50 years when you listen back to this historical record that looks to be some fossilised Weetabix, now you know where it came from.
Fossilised Weetabix looks exactly like Weetabix.
Well, I will say, and I also will say, that I did, in response to her fanzine about Weetabix, implore her to write three more fanzines about Weetabix so I could nominate them for Best Fanzine at the Hugo Awards, which I think would be brilliant.
I'm not super hopeful it would win, but I'd definitely nominate it.
I think we should be going for a new category, Best Fanzine about Weetabix.
Start the process!
On the subject of Wusfus procedures...
Have we now finished follow-up, John?
We have finished follow-up, Alison.
Some of you may be aware that Con Zealand is being held online this year, but this is not stopping the World Science Fiction Society holding a physical business meeting in Wellington,
because, according to File 770, and I quote, it cannot be moved online.
What do I think about that, peeps?
The Octothorpe rant.
See, we've got a new show segment name.
He he he.
Why can it not be moved online?
Like, I have not delved into the Wusfus constitution for a little while.
So I can't remember what the exact wording is.
Is it that we literally can't move online because something says you cannot do it online?
Or is it that we can't move online because there's not a way of doing all the things the business meeting needs to do online?
Or it's some other reason?
It's possible that we cannot do it online because Wusfus has a brush up its collective arse.
So here we're in a world where the UK Parliament, Mother of Parliaments, run by Erskine May since the beginning of time, manages to move itself online in a couple of weeks.
Just by basically going, huh, does it make sense to not do this?
No, it does not.
Let's go online.
Whereas Wusfus, run by, as we know, Robert's Rules of Order, goes, oh, no, we have to have a physical meeting in the location specified.
Because, I mean, if Wellington was bombed, what would they have done?
You know, I mean, you can see them going, oh, it's ground zero, but we have to be there because the Wusfus Constitution requires us to be there to hold our physical business meeting.
And there is no other way to do it.
And the Worldcon will come down around our ears if we do not hold a physical meeting.
Now, there is another argument that says, actually, you know, we could have brought it online.
But in fact, having a micro meeting on site is the sensible way forward, because otherwise every rules lawyer in Wusfus would just...
I'm trying to think of a metaphor here that's not extremely sexist and a bit dodgy over the prospect of arguing about this for three solid years.
Right.
Anyway, that's all I had to say on the subject.
How does that relate to...
How does that compare to your rants?
I don't know.
It can...
It depends how passionate I am about the rant.
As far as I can tell, and I am...
I am interpreting a constitution and I am not a lawyer.
And to be honest, you'd need to be a lawyer to appreciate all of the nuances and subtleties of the Wusfus Constitution.
But as far as I can tell, the problem is Article 5, Section 5.1, Subsection 5, which states that the quorum for the business meeting shall be 12 members of the society physically present.
Now, I have double-checked, and as far as I can tell, the word physically is not actually defined anywhere in the Constitution.
So I assume that they're relying on a definition according to the dictionary.
And my dictionary defines physically as...
In a way that relates to the real world and things perceived through the senses as opposed to the mind.
So, I would argue that if you wanted to, and you had the mental gymnastics present, you could interpret that to allow an online meeting.
As long as everyone was at the online meeting and you could see them with your senses.
But perhaps there would be a point of order raised and people would get very frowny.
It does also say in the Constitution that any member of the Worldcon should be allowed to attend the meeting.
So I'm also sort of tempted to arrange some sort of splinter group where we all threaten to attend the meeting in strict contravention of international law unless they don't hold it.
And I wonder what they would do then.
But yeah, it's ludicrous.
And it comes down to the point made earlier in the episode about if you have a set of rules that is sufficiently rigorous,
that it does not permit for certain things that may go wrong to go wrong,
then those rules can end up with silly situations like having a situation where 12 people have to meet in Wellington to have the business meeting.
And I would argue that if it does have to be held at the Worldcon and the Worldcon is in cyberspace,
a physical business meeting in Wellington is in contravention of the Worcester's Constitution and should be immediately disallowed.
I'm genuinely like, this Constitution does not provide for this circumstance,
so you've got to do some imaginative reading of the rules.
But given that you have to do some imaginative reading of the rules,
why on earth not imaginatively read the rules to allow a virtual business meeting that we could actually attend and participate in?
This is the end of my rant.
Because they don't wanna.
Because they think it would be too hard.
I feel that the Eastercon managed to make this happen perfectly adequately.
And that it doesn't seem...
I mean, obviously we did it without the benefit of a constitution or rules of engagement.
We just did sensible stuff in a way that was kind of quite English of us.
You know, I don't feel that they've necessarily taken the best option.
And there's clearly nothing to stop them having a meeting in which people join physically,
but the meeting is also online and people can make comments and suggestions online using some form of Q&A system.
I feel that with rules lawyering like that, John, you have a great future ahead of you at the Worcester's business meeting.
You take that back, Batty!
How do you feel about mornings?
I mean, I am...
I don't like that the fact that the business meeting is held at the Worldcon because it means I can't go to panels or the bar.
And to my mind, the exciting things about Worldcon are panels and the bar.
So I guess I have less ranty opinions, which are mostly just because I'm, I think, less bothered.
I'm OK with them deciding this year, OK, we can't do a virtual one.
And it says we should have an actual physical gathering of 12 people.
So let's have a physical gathering of 12 people to the absolute minimum and punt this to next year.
But I do think next year needs to be thinking about this now and working out how they will do a virtual business meeting if necessary,
or if not, how they can put in place all the structures in 2021 to enable us to do this in the future,
because we don't know when this might happen again.
But 2021 is a good bet.
For being online or for...
For when it might happen again.
I mean, I think the most likely outcome for the Worldcon next year is not that it doesn't happen physically.
It's that most of its foreign visitors are effectively disenfranchised,
along with a lot of the older and sicker members of the Worldcon community, which is quite a lot of people.
And Worldcon has a tendency to be the convention for a bunch of people in the northeastern United States anyway.
And having the business meeting only open to those people would be a major problem that I think they need to address.
Is that fair?
That's not too ranty.
Was that ranty?
That was quite ranty.
That ranty, and it is completely fair.
It's not going to land well with Worcestersh fandom who regard any attempt to change or modernise anything as if you are literally the devil.
The comments on the File 770 article declaring this are proof of that.
I think, in general, if the WUSFUS Constitution doesn't allow for this sort of thing, it needs changing.
And if the WUSFUS Constitution cannot be changed, or if the WUSFUS Business Meeting cannot be held virtually,
we need to have a serious think about whether that means those two things are fit for purpose.
Because I would argue it means they are not, and we need to seriously rethink them.
The fact that World Cons were held completely successfully up until 1980 without any formal constitution rather makes me think we don't need it.
But perhaps we do, and perhaps it's very important.
But in that case, we need to fix the problems with it.
I think any political system that responds to a crisis that requires immediate and well thought through, but nevertheless speedy action,
with a decision to delay absolutely everything for a year, is demonstrating that it's not fit for purpose.
You know, it's demonstrating that it does not work at the thing it's supposed to do.
Unless the thing it's supposed to do is retard change.
And obviously there are people in the WUSFUS fandom for whom retarding change is a feature, not a bug.
And I don't know, I feel like there's something every episode that causes me to go,
Angie, call yourself science fiction fans.
Though they might say, but that's why we want to be careful of change.
Because, you know, we've read those books and it never comes out well.
Our email address is octothorpecast at gmail.com.
And we will read it, we promise.
I know our history is not good on this, but we will.
Thank you everyone for listening to the eighth episode of the Octothorpe podcast,
which will come out on the 24th of June 2020.
And it's goodbye from me.
Yay!
Podcast.
Have a fantastic weekend, Liz.
Started strong, but almost immediately devolved into passive-aggressive.
It's the title of your podcast.
Yes, I'm not sure that was one of our more coherent podcasts.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod at incompetech.com.
Used under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 license.
Where are you putting these?
At the bottom.
Oh, I see.
Who'd have been sending those nice letters of comment and they think we've been ignoring
them?
Is this like for weeks and weeks and weeks?
No.
I think Andrew January knows we're not ignoring him.
But we do apparently have one from Mark Olsen.
Two from Mark Olsen.
Oh my God.
Oops.
I am John.
I am bad at emails.
Hi, Liz.
We're also, hello, we're also bad at Twitter.
Oh, I like the letter from Hulk.
It's very nice, isn't it?
It is.
Now I can't hear you at all.
Maybe this can be, oh no, maybe this can be an all letter of comment episode.
I was actually thinking that because I don't think we've got a lot of, I don't know if we've
got a lot of topics.
I've got the big business meeting, but like, I don't want to go on about that too much because
it's a bit niche.
And also at some point, like, just complaining about things gets wearing because that's what
ATP does.
What, my favourite podcast in the whole world?
I, yeah, and I respect that.
I was very confused.
So I'm like, ATP, do you mean adenosine triphosphate?
Probably not.
All tomorrow's parties?
No, also not.
That podcast that you and Alison like, all right, fine.
Or the, um, or the, like, tennis pro circuit.
The problem with ATP is that because, the thing that typifies the problem with ATP is because
they complain all the time, it means that when they're complaining about things that actually
need people to pay attention, people ignore them because it's just ATP complaining again.
And the thing that makes this the most obvious is when they were complaining about the MacBook
Pro keyboards, no one paid attention.
And then as soon as other people started complaining about the MacBook Pro keyboards, everyone was
like, oh, this is a real problem.
And the point where you complain so often that the things you complain about become non-remarkable
is the point at which you complain too much.
Like, if you're just relentlessly negative about everything, it removes any value to your
criticism.
So I get a little bit frustrated.
Relentlessly negative about everything.
There's this week's title.
So what are our topics for today then, John?
We're going to look at letters of comment, Alison.
I've put them in the show notes.
And there are thousands of them.
There are four.
So we can start with a big old apology.
Yes.
Plus the new one from Claire.
And I think we owe a debt of thanks to Claire because if it had not been for her mentioning
that we weren't getting our emails, we would not have known we were not getting our emails.
We would have believed we were podcasting into a void.
Yes.
Also, Mark sent us an email about, John, just copy and paste them and we'll sort the line
spacing out later.
Because I can see you're doing it.
Yeah.
And also, the vegetables are great.
I do not know what that is, but I am curious.
Well, you haven't watched Octonauts, have you?
No.
You have not watched Octonauts.
Is this the Welsh show that Farah likes?
Possibly.
I'm not sure it is Welsh, but you can get it in Welsh, which is so delightful.
Apparently, there's some transcripts.
We have the other thing in our Gmail thing is a pile of things from otter.ai saying,
we've transcribed your podcast.
Would you like to go and look at it?
So at some point we will do that.
Are you going anywhere nice this weekend, Liz?
Yes, I'm just going to go and sit in a house with a pool and I am taking my inflatable pool
hammock, my inflatable pool drinks holder and my waterproof Kindle cover.
And that's my weekend.
So you're basically having a long weekend in a large bath.
Yeah, pretty much.
It does sound nice, though.
I feel like a holiday, a relaxing holiday somewhere warm would quite suit me about now.
I think crucially, I haven't left Bangkok at this point for six months, which is probably
the longest.
Oh, no, that's not true.
I haven't left Bangkok for three months and I've spent most of that time kind of in my own
neighborhood with only occasional visits to any other bit of the city.
I am feeling quite cooped up, as I assume most of you are.
So it feels like now is a good time to take the chance to go somewhere a whole three hours
away because I don't know how long we will all have that chance to do that.
So we've got to the point where having a weekend away seems like the most enormous luxury.
Yeah.
So we're all very, we're all very envious of you.
I guess the question is, does our podcast feeling a lot like a conversation that we've had in
the bar put off people who have not already had a conversation in a bar with us in the past?
Write to octothorpecast at gmail.com.
We promise we'll read it this time.
That actually feels like the title of this episode.
We'll promise we really will read it this time.
So Marianne tells me that title of your sex tape comes directly from Brooklyn Nine-Nine and
had no antecedents before that.
And I was quite fascinated by that.
that it comes more from that's what she said.
And then of course, for people who are 10 years older than me, people 10 years older than me used to say,
as the actress said to the bishop.
Yeah.
Which is exactly the same thing as title of your sex tape.
I think it is the same.
It is the same linguistic construction.
I'm not sure that's apropos of anything.
But apparently it's Brooklyn Nine-Nine.
Brooklyn Nine-Nine is a fine, fine show, which has the problem that all shows about the police have.
Of being a show about the police now.
Yeah.
Well, all television shows about the police have a structural problem with them.
And Brooklyn Nine-Nine is not an exception, which is that they almost invariably show either the police in general
or the particular policeman who is the focus of the show as being a very upstanding member of society
who does no or does very little wrong in kind of peccadillo ways rather than, oh, the Sweeney, I suppose.
Well, I mean, I think we have maybe, this is not entirely on the subject of our podcast,
but there's been quite a lot of interesting writing about this,
of how like most police things are procedurals and kind of to do a procedural kind of requires that
the police end up being sort of the protagonist.
And, you know, you can wrap it up neatly because they catch the bad guys.
But then you get things like the shield where the policeman is definitely not one of the good guys.
Or you get something like the wire where the police are, you know, sometimes good and sometimes bad,
but, you know, presented as this force which has all these different effects and ramifications on a neighbourhood.
And I think there's some more examples.
I am now going to pitch my lockdown show, which is a wuss-fuss procedural drama.
Thereby bringing us back on topic.