I would totally take a sausage sandwich above a sausage roll, I think.
So there is a stall on Leicester. There's a stall on the Greyja market here in Newcastle called
Jordi Bangers and they do a very good sausage roll but they also do a very good sausage roll.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 124th episode of OctaThorpe, a podcast for Science Fiction
and Science Fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 5th of December 2024. I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty. We are coming to you in Advent.
So you will have eaten your first five Advent chocolates today listeners and I hope it's going well.
We've got some letters of comment listeners. We heard from June Young. In episode 110,
I mentioned that I had an Aurora app on my phone and June asks what app I have and what app I
recommend. She knows she lives in New Zealand and has a Samsung Android phone even if she only has
a tiny chance of seeing Aurora she has to try. So I got in touch with my chum Craig who works
at the University of Otago in New Zealand and he sent through a link to the University of Otago's
page for Aurora Alerts in New Zealand. So June I recommend that. I will pop a link to that in the
show notes and it has advice for when to go looking and like how to see Aurora and various graphs and
it all looks very good. In general I sent June an email with a couple of links to apps but the two
I as my colleagues about are Space Weather Live and the Glendale app and I'll put links to those in
the show notes as well. The one I use is Aurora Alerts UK but as the name might suggest that is
really mostly helpful if you live in the UK and so yes not as helpful for international listeners
and I'll pop some iPhone recommendations in the show notes as well for all your iPhone is out there
but yeah. Andrew Hogg says GTA 2 is not available on Netflix. I'm guessing Alice does misunderstood
which three games are involved in the Grand Theft Auto in Grand Theft Auto the trilogy and yes you
are completely correct this is true. 100% I wasn't paying close attention. For those who are wondering
for those who are wondering Grand Theft Auto 2 is the last good one. I think I've only actually
played Grand Theft Auto 1. In general games get worse games get worse when they go 3D. Zelda is a
very notable exception to this rule but like 2D games they be good. Like all the 2D Zelda's quite
a lot. I like the 2D Zelda's but Ocarina of Time might be the best game ever made and it is 3D so
it is a compelling counter example to my point but like I always prefer the 2D Mario's to the 3D
Mario's for instance. I just sold my copy of Ocarina of Time 3D in my giant mountain of things I'm
selling. Liz how many d's do you like? Oh that could go the wrong way. I'm not answering that one John.
As many as is necessary. Wow wow correct answer. I mean technically you could say
braid is like a 4D platform all right and I like braid so there you go. Yes braid is good. I would
say braid is 3D but the third d isn't what you think. 3D? Hmm yeah I guess it is yeah. Braid is 3D
platformer. I don't think anyone's done braid 3D but actually 4D. Oh no there is a very weird golf
game. 4D golf. Have you seen any of the videos of 4D golf? Nope. Absolutely like my brain little brain
just cannot comprehend 4D golf. Brilliant. Okay I apparently I need to go and play 4D golf.
I mean I think you need to watch a video of 4D golf and then decide if you think your brain can
cope with the fourth dimension of the golf. It's 30% off right now Alison and it's available on your
Mac. I'll look at the video. It looks it looks pretty mad. Mmm. Preef pause whatever you want to
the video of 4D golf. We also heard from Chris Garcia. I think we're here from Chris Garcia twice
since we lasted any letters of comment so that is a lot of Chris Garcia. Chris talks about the
costs of comms for attendees. He says basically they're too high which yeah and the problem is that
higher prices on a traveling comm can mean that the locals who might only be able to go to that
warm comm still can't make it so even if they don't have to take into account hotel prices sometimes
high prices can price the locals out. Yeah he says in the 1990s some cons tried a thing we'd have
a rate for people staying in the hotel it was lower than people not staying in the hotel which
does sound just very complicated basically and he's very much looking forward to an
Edmonton WorldCom. I didn't quite understand the thing about people in the hotel paying less.
That didn't quite make sense to me. I do think having a local person's rate which is slightly
cheaper is very good idea and that's kind of what Belfast are doing right and it's something Glasgow
did as well so I have no I think that's a good point to well-made Chris to that sort of thing
might be good. I think the idea is if you are a con where you have to fill your room block in order
to not get in trouble with the hotel then giving people a slight discount and encouraging them to
fill the hotel room block could be a good thing but it just sounds very complicated to keep track
off and as Chris says could be kind of subverted by booking and then cancelling hotels. Yeah in
general I do like it when cons are sort of unbundled from a hotel because then it does give you the
freedom to stay in whatever hotel you like without worrying that you are going to cause the cons
financial difficulties. Yeah I know what you mean do you want to do Chris's other letter Liz or do
you want me to do that? Well shall I do Tommy and then you could do Chris too. Chris to electric
Boogaloo. I might do Chris's now because the other Chris one is the one that comes before the Chris
one that Liz just did. Okay so you can do we also heard from Chris Garcia. Oh this is 4D letters of
comment. Yeah I'm going to keep all this in obviously but the fourth dimension is time I feel like
podcasts may only be 1D there so it's 2D if you've got timey it's timey wiry stuff in it. So Chris
does note that they did listen to the grass episode on the way to wrestling and JP said this sounds
like a weird book. Yes JP that is not an unfair you might have gotten to the hearts of the situation
there fair enough. He mentions Ekpeki and sort of talks about that we should just note there is a
file service every article in which it turns out that the initial child that was levied against
Ekpeki might not be true because Kens' name does appear on the story that Ekpeki submitted so we're
we'll link to that in the show notes but that whole thing is rapidly getting into
it's all just very strange now and then Chris says everything feeds into smothcon smothconning
with virtual hybrid concept and then he says for a group that often complains that people see them
as a shadowy group who doesn't want to have that action seen they sure make choices that make that
impression easy to justify is not not a bad point. So yes thank you very much Chris we now return to
the period of time after the time that Chris wrote to us after the one I just read. So Tommy Ferguson
wrote to us as said made three points as reconnect treasurer I am very I am very confused by the
concept of a combined treasurer and co-chair of an east cod that seems like quite a lot of work to me
but there we go. Saying we are not in financial trouble which I think is what I said last time
they have 622 members are certain they will be able to pay their bills there may be some limits
on what they can and cannot do e.g. streaming and they may not have as much past as long as they
would like and so he's passed that on to the next east cod to know. On membership prices they
want as many members as early as possible which is why they went for an early rate and they knew
that they were getting a subvention of £50 a person approximately for every member outside
Northern Ireland from the Belfast local government tourist subsidy. So that actually totally explains
it because if you if what you're paying is £70 plus £50 that's 120 isn't it so yeah and and he said
without that money they could not have considered putting on the con but then he also says we anticipate
a small or no virtual component reconnect get it and I would like to take issue with you there Tommy
because what you do when you say we want to reconnect in person because reconnecting in person is
better than virtual conventions is this is an exclusionary policy virtual conventions aren't
I don't think there's anybody who goes oh I'd rather attend a convention virtually than travel
people are too frail to travel or they do not have enough money to travel to a convention in person
or they still feel that they're actually not safe to travel because of being immunocompromised or
for other reasons and all of those things are access issues and having a virtual component to
your convention and having it be as broad as you could possibly manage and I understand that finance
might constrain it isn't it's not about saying oh it's better to meet a person it's about saying
oh well but we want to encourage as many people as possible to come to our convention even if the
way that they do that is virtually you know as it happens liz in Thailand is flying next year but
many of the people in the East Kong community who are scattered around the world cannot possibly
afford to come to Belfast and his third point is this he's got a finance subcommittee which
includes several people who have worked on previous Easter cons he's also getting advice and help
from other East Kong treasurers and so they're kind of little little net of East Kong treasurers
keeping informed and trying to make sure that the money um that that we are actually making
the kind of year on year decisions about the money which I think is is very sensible and he's
shared all of their income and budgets he's kind of like well it's transparent and if anyone really
wants to see the um budget and expenditure lines do get in touch so you know if that's you listeners
I mean I'm I'm pretty confident that they're doing the right sort of thing and I'll let them
get on with it but if that's you then um get in touch I am going to be fascinated to know so if
this convention's real cost to be profitable is 120 pounds a member which it sounds like it is
I don't envy Phil and the 2026 bid which we'll discuss later I don't envy them in their decision
making about where they start their prices given that reconnects started at 70 I that's going to
be there's going to be gasps in the room again but again every convention makes the decisions it makes
that are right for it and reconnect clearly feel that that is what they have done and I can't as we
went over last time we can't criticize an individual convention for making the decisions that are
right for them right so yeah it's hard I gotta say 50 quid is pretty good to mention from the
Belfast stories board I mean I'm trying to remember how much kind of what was the kind of range of
stuff Glasgow was getting for bringing a whole world con to Scotland and I think it was probably
not out the realm of like what will come what Easter gone is going to get for coming to Belfast I
mean they have succeeded in that I am having made the decision to go to the Belfast Eastacom I will
also then like spend some more time in Northern Ireland and spend more of my tourist monies and
you know fly I mean although actually I will fly to Dublin which probably was not their intention but
it's working 50 quid is is buttons compared to the amount of money I'm going to spend in the hotels
restaurants and bars of Belfast that weekend and also I think that we're probably not as influential
as we used to be but I think that there are still plenty of influential people in in East
conf anthem who are going around saying oh Belfast is actually a great place to go for a weekend and
that's really important as part of the part of the discussion when tourist boards are making these
sorts of choices so somebody who shall be nameless um sidled up to me in the nivcon bar and said
smofcon's decision to scrap its virtual program is particularly vexing because the reason they won
the bid over Suicon was that they promised virtual and Suicon couldn't oh I thought that's interesting
that is proper gossip yeah that that is I had I confess I had not realized that the smofcon
right I saw of assume that most convention bid processes are not actually contested because in
general listeners they tend not to be I mean world cons is an exception obviously but like
east con is technically a competitive bidding process but hasn't been for many years but I
didn't as a result I hadn't occurred to me that part of the um problem here might be that Seattle
had promised something in the bidding that they are then going back on and that is an interesting
consideration that we didn't pick up last episode indeed and and when I say contested bidding I mean
obviously this I said Suicon earlier but it is just Sweden rather than Suicon it's smofcon 42
um I think it's just switched so they will do it this year so next year so it's not that
it's not that that will never happen I guess it's also that if you say you're going to do
hybrid and people vote for you on the ground that you're going to do hybrid but then none of them
actually join as virtual members then that's also tricky yeah true also didn't we have quite
contested east con bidding in um 20 21 but I think that's one time in the nearly 20 years I've been
going so I feel like it's fair to say it's not common yes I'm not saying it's literally impossible
I think we worked out there's been there's been four contested east comptons and I was part of
all four of them so oops I'm also gonna so I'm also gonna say um we don't have many comments from
them but we have picked up a very large number of followers on blue sky which is obviously the
new hotness as far as social media goes partly because we are in some starter packs which is
I think on blue sky where if you would like to um mass follow basically a bunch of interesting
people who are related in some particular way then you can say go and find a starter pack of
science fictional podcasters and click follow and you'll get to follow all of them and sort of
populate your feed with people which is I think a really nice thing actually because my main
problem with blue sky in the early days is it was very slow because I wasn't following tons of
people because there weren't tons of people I wanted to follow and now it has massively perked up
and so completely replaced twitter for me and I think part of it might be the following
being a follow start back not what I have followed any starter packs but I like to use them as a way
to go so go through and find interesting people I might like to follow even if I don't tend to
mass follow all of them because in case they might be super prolific yeah so we're on blue sky
we are octa-thorpe cast as usual um come and say hi leave us comments we might read them out um I
promise to get a slightly better corrupt version of our icon that fits nicely in a circle before
next episode and we have also and I don't know if we mentioned this on the podcast we are also now
on instagram so if you want to follow us on instagram we are octa-thorpe sf because meta are
shit but we are on instagram so if you're on there come and give us a follow we posted a show art
cunning um we should do we also on um mastodon we got a letter of comment from archipelacon 2
who says uh we appreciate the kind words about archipelacon 1 and we look forward to seeing
alison archipelacon 2 thanks archipelacon 2 monkey king says that they are envious of
alison going to archipelacon 2 because they went to the first one and they loved both the con and
mariham so yeah I've heard this from quite a lot of people actually so people saying oh
I don't think I can go but I loved the first one and people saying oh I'm really trying to get
it together to go and then it's attracting a really interesting international crowd so that
that's kind of cool it's very dangerous for alison though i will predict because it's i think
it's very dangerous for you because my problem was I would be sitting in the bar having a nice beer
awesome long drink and then realized that it was maybe 1 a.m because it just hadn't gone dark
and so it had not triggered my oh maybe it is time to stop drinking and go to sleep so okay so
fortunately I do not have um a flag that says maybe it's time to stop drinking and go to sleep
the i mean essentially it happens for me when I fall asleep in my beer which means that which
means that when the cues that should trigger that flag go away it will be even worse is my
prediction you won't sleep for five days hoorah things only a three day come or four day maybe
and that really illustrates how bad it is that alison won't sleep for five days Liz
and then you can go and dance with the moomins on the ferry hey oh i don't think i'm gonna be on a
ferry i think well i don't know we haven't done our travel yet i think i've put that in a problem for
2025 first time writer on facebook um Sheila R says Glasgow was their first wokan first convention
of any sort and they cannot get over the value of money of the weekend ticket people pay more
than that for one night to giggle the theater wokan gives five days of back-to-back entertainment
i think that we all know that this is why we do this this is why we go to these conventions
this is what they are like come to easter cod did i say that sorry i want to pick up on this which
is um yeah and i think one thing we might not have made enough of in the last few months of discussing
the cost of conventions is that it is very expensive to go to conventions but they are like pound for
pound some of the best value entertainment you can possibly have like and we i do think we
discussed the price a lot and that's probably good and wise and price is obviously a barrier and
being able to afford that price is a privilege but also it is terrific value if you can afford to go
like far superior to many other forms of entertainment will might pay to attend and Glasgow is especially
Glasgow was very very good it was this is why i am firmly on the it is okay for easter cod to
increase its membership rates side of the force and then Johnny badly said best pre-credits ever
thank you Johnny my slightly damp electronic equipment thanks you it's all dry now yeah
clearly you should pour coffee into your laptop um more often nope i thought it was tea was it not
tea uh no um this said it was tea but it was obviously coffee it's really it's really tea
round here coffee in coffee drinking hours it's often it's often like chamomile or fennel or
the kursti like at ten o'clock at night before anyone writes in we appreciate those things are
technically infusions and are not technically tea just to head off that lock ahead of time
that's fair because i get very grumpy when people say that soil liquidized soil or liquidized
almond or liquidized oats are somehow milk so you know i was not i was not going to make any
suggestion that if you were listening to this pod if you were listening to a podcast and they
had said that you would be the one writing in but i am not not saying that either um but yes
thank you very much to Johnny big oat milk sorry i was saying big oat milk i am quite happy to call
it milk if you would like to you know send me your oat milk so i will call it oat milk on the
podcast as often as possible hi alla fair oh and i will get annoyed every single time hmm
which is great advertising for the oat milk lobby Johnny also wrote in to say that there's an
article about me in the latest issue of mostly harmless uh and i did not know this and if anyone
is listening that has a pdf please could they send it to me because i would like to know what it
says thank you please send it to the podcast because i also want to know what it says and also i'm mortified
normally when you're writing articles about people you check with the subject to see if it's
got they've got everything correct it's got much that is inaccurate or at least wildly apocryphal
or is that alley baker books writes in about um about traveling as an academic
the long and the straw here is yes i am very lucky alley if it makes you feel better i went all
the way to the u.s for a conference and then got flew so it was not quite as glamorous as it seemed
because then i spent 25 hours on plane with a very congested nose but well done to my conference
which did give us all a combined flu and covid test on day one all that's partly because i think
they were sponsored by a flu and covid test diagnostic test manufacturer yeah that that'll
that'll help or two yeah but it worked got a little length of flu yeah easter con should also look
at getting that sponsorship mmm yeah i mean might not be quite as likely like to make i don't know
yeah so we heard from the chairs of the last two easter cons in addition to the chair of next year's
easter con we have been very chaired um this month so we heard from caroline mullen and fara Mendelssohn
far enough that they think we should move away from a model that there is such thing as too much
surplus because um it's good to have surplus for easter cons and i have to say i think i agree with
that and then uh far it also notes that the budget that levitation did for their membership curve
assumed the same curve as the last time there was a Glasgow world con and then the membership
stalled after christmas in a way that is very unusual for easter cons um and they also had problems
with their tech budget so those are considerations in what happened there um caroline rights to say
that conversation did in fact um budget to have a large event but they couldn't land a booking because
in 2022 the touring scene was struggling when they were trying to do so and so they ended up putting
that unspent money into the pass along for future conventions and so thank you very much to both
of those chairs for writing in we also heard from leavin on facebook who says back to our futures
was great so well done you two hey i think that the biggest compliment i can pay it is that it's
made me seriously consider virtual attendance at a world con so that is uh a pretty awesome bit of
feedback to get basically you are converting people to virtual cons so yeah oh and then rosanna
pendleberry wrote in to say um she went to clasco as her first world con as now going to her first
easter con because she really rather enjoyed that whole con thing i'm hoping to get another fix and
this is this is the way join us and it anecdotally i haven't heard from andy open sure but i know this
to also be true of andy where we were like you should come to a convention they came to a convention
she's like where is the next convention and we're like it's coming it's coming we promise i have had
several conversations with people who are coming to belfast having been at world con and this is good
and i understand that we probably dragged morian if the next convention was in london but you know
the next year is at the lec and that's pretty easy so we if you're going oh i'd really want to do
another one but i cannot get to belfast then then it's probably going to be the nac in 2026 and i
getting ahead of myself because i think that's our next topic segwaying from what rosanna says i
think this is part of the legacy that glasco will leave which is reinvigorating and bringing people
into uh fandom in the uk um and that's really good and obviously part of the way they're doing that
is by dispersing some of their surplus funds to other conventions so i believe it is known that
glasco has distributed some of their surplus to the next three easter cons or will distribute it to
the next three easter con has made it is what i was told at nova con and i was not told it was secret
um was that glasco had decided that to donate five thousand pounds to each of the next three
easter cons to help in some ways recover the surplus the the puzzle of funds that we lost over
over the pandemic and if that was secret you're gonna have to start telling us everything that is
whether everything is a secret when you're at the bar no i mean i don't i don't think
i don't think there was any suggestion it was it was a secret so if it was i'm very sorry i
seem glasco would have done this even if there had not been a pandemic because i think one of the
ways in which british world cons help british fandom is that they put money into british conventions
but loncon three did not um give money to the easter cons subsequent to it because it did not
make a surplus um but this is something i think most british world cons that do make a surplus do
is they help out the easter cons and other ventures in the country going forward and i'm sure that
there is a team of elves beavering away behind the scenes at glasco working out how they want to give
the money um that they've made to british fandom and cement the glasco legacy
um i want to introduce the easter con better if that's okay because i want to say i went to
nova con all right yeah i went to nova con and my normal practice in nova con is to spend the
entire weekend in bars um and a variety as well as the nova con bar also all the lovely bars in
buxin which is a place with a lot of very nice drinking holes but i sacrificed some of my drinking
time so that i could go to the future easter cons presentation at which i discovered some useful
things um first that phil dyson will be bidding um for the easter con at bell first and he's going to
be bidding for 26 with a bid called iridescence to be held in the hilton at the nes which of course
we went to in 2023 and has many virtues none of which are its immediate environment they've got a
deal it's going to be they can do it i'm very much looking forward to going back for a convention
that i am not on the commissive for so do you guys have anything to say about 26 or should i move
on to 27 26 sounds good i will probably go i'm quite happy to go back to Birmingham i quite like
as a venue and it seems like it is relatively easy travel wise and there are alternative hotels
in the vicinity it is just a bit of a slow to get to anything but it's a lot better now they've
built that um what's it called train airport hotel no that big shopping center thing with loads
of restaurants in oh yeah the shopping center made a big difference yeah yeah the first time i went
to an east con i know i'm going to sound really old here was back on 87 and it was absolutely in
the middle of a wasteland we were told there were plenty of food and drink spots at the nes but they
were all closed resort world that's his name it's good it has a nambo's and the five guys i mean i
wouldn't go there as like a holiday in resort would you but i mean it's got shops and stuff no but
for a convention it's great i really like five guys i know i shouldn't but there's something about
that sort of burger that's just like oh this is what fast food should be like five guys are
immense i will hear nothing against them i had one on friday yeah no 2026 sounds good
allen flummying and david bamford announced that they are going to bid for Glasgow for 2027 and
mark meanen in the bar was like i'm definitely going to find them a site they have they're looking
up for hotels they are very confident they have a site you know that that one of those four will
will deliver what they need and mark is helping them get the negotiation landed and i'm quite
excited about going back to Glasgow for the east con because it has been a while um the last one
was satellite for mm-hmm it was i have heard some rumors about 2028 i have heard a couple of different
names in the frame for 2028 and i've also heard a site in the frame for 2828 which is the sage
gates head um and i guess it's going to get it because the old sage has got a new name gloss
house and then there's the new sage where phil dices said yeah they really wanted just to come
there for 2026 and they haven't actually broken ground yet so that's a really bad idea so hopefully
it'll get built at some point and then and then we might have a look at that so i'd quite like to go
to gate said because i i kind of like new castle and gate said is kind of easy to get to and yeah
it would be good i will say it would be interesting for um comrunners to look at new castle gates head
without coming to talk to the new castle first there's a group and having a chat with us um so
like you know if you are looking at these venues and you haven't come and said hello i would i would
recommend coming to say hello uh there's a facebook group and a mailing list novicon was a great
success and i really had a good time and they have announced that next year they will be back in the
buxdon palace which is a hotel i really like indeed because i very much do because i really
like being in a city center and although buxdon is not very big it has the things i want in a city
center which is a lot of nice restaurants and bars and it's you've got beautiful scenery as well so
you feel like you're in the fresh air in a nice place um as long as you leave the hotel um and their
guest of honor next year is emily tesh which i think is a great shout i think a lot of people thought
it was a great shout and their head of program next year is estan bakalam stewart and i was like
oh i suppose you are in the middle and so aren't you it will be interesting to see how esta balances
program from overcon and being the deputy administrator for the hugos at seattle and still being the
chair of a world con that's dispersing funds and running comrunner all in a year that that is an
adventurous schedulista i wish you the very best of luck i i think she'd say it's not going to be
anything like as um hard as running the ct d's to con i worked on the east con seated world con
with somebody who had just come off a world con and they've been on a world con committee and i was
like i assure you you want to be doing the east con so soon he was like oh it's like a rest cure and
i think that was steve coopers view on running the east con after being a world con chair was that it
was it was just like falling off a log compared to the difficulty of running a world con which i
can easily believe um but yes emo esta who is a busy woman is also going to be running um conrunner
in 2026 february 2026 conrunner is the kind of british equivalent of smoth con british european
i think she would probably say but it's all it's been britainal ways and i'm sure it will be this
time as well um and conners are great fun and if you have any interest in conrunning at all or indeed
if you like to hang out in a bar with conrunners then i would strongly recommend conrunner great con
do we know where it's going to be uh no somewhere i mean i was like the palace hotel buxton looks
like exactly the right size for what you're trying to do what did they have the last one
i'm sure i went to the last one but i've now completely forgotten where it was but it was
somewhere quite nice i thought it was in that awful hotel in stevenage correct me if i'm wrong
might have been wrong about that maybe or maybe i really did have a good time in stevenage
well i was probably under like some kind of conrunning delusion or something it was 2027 so
it's been a was it's supposed to be in a conrunner i'm reading a magnificent um round up from an
extremely thorough roundup from mochine which does not appear to say where it was
ah if you remember where conrunner was please write inlessness oh nothing um
notting them nothing at the park i would actually go to my team and get probably at the park yes
that sounds more like it so basically yes hold it at the nouvere con venue esta that's the tradition
please i mean if i was going to vote i would vote against that please no oh it's improved
actually they keep they're refurbishing it it's getting better it's better i probably will go to
nova con because emily tesh sounds good i don't go to every nova con but i go to nova cons if i'm
not going to a world con and if the program sounds great and if the guests of honor sounds
particularly my kind of thing and i think the next nova con fulfills some or all of those
briefs so i think i probably want to go to that two different people came up to me and over con
and said oh i want to run a little online con on a very niche topic john put something in the
show notes that i hadn't otherwise seen and was quite interested in so well done john hey
he has put in a note that wiskon 2025 is going to be online and wiskon is the um feminist
sf convention that has been running every year in wisconsin for many years and i think this is
their second consecutive year when they've basically gone online i think last year was a
planned we're going to go online and do it virtually to let everyone kind of recover a bit and then
2025 appears to be a we are doing it online because we don't have the volunteers to run an offline
con i'm going to be very interested to see if this kind of regenerates it for future years or if this
is sort of the the end of wiskons which would be a little bit a little bit strange they've been
running for a long time they've been running in the same venue i went quite a few years ago but
it was like a thousand person con but i guess if you don't have the people who are willing to
be involved in running it you know the people don't have the the time or the energy to do that then
yeah you have to try going online and then if you can't get people then you fold i guess i just sort
of always thought of it as a kind of fixture of the concert even though i didn't go so yeah but it's
an interesting contrast to i was saying here is the 2026 easter gone beers in 2027 and here in the
room is for 2028 um it fortunately does not appear easter gone by going that way uh we've just had a
local world con which as we know bob as long as it doesn't burn everybody out is extremely good for
generating enthusiasm among the community for more of this sort of i think if it hadn't been for
Glasgow 2024 we would in fact be we i mean we would still be managing to make use to cons happen but
we might be having some of the conversations about shrinking them changing their focus that sort of
thing that other places have done when it's become hard to get volunteers but we have lots of young
people it's very good Glasgow had lots of young people at it that was also very good and by young
i mean under 50 where yes so what we i guess need is a wiskonsin world con aisles to
bump up those volunteer numbers in wisconsin i know or minneapolis yeah in minnesota you know
some midwestern world con is what they need a wimpy zone will con i'd fucking love a minneapolis
world con and i'd quite like it to happen before 2073 and for listeners who don't understand why i
say that there is an extant world con bid for minneapolis in 2073 which has been going since
minneapolis did not win in 1973 and that joke gets less funny with every passing year presumably
as uh 2073 gets ever closer oh they they've been serious for a few years now they are planning
to run it in 2073 and they're not planning to run it before that but you know you could do it in
like 2033 or something that'd be good but yeah wiskons do specifically say like they don't have
enough volunteers to run in person so lizz is like um thing about they just yeah i hope that they
continue but they need the people i mean you think with minneapolis is they already have a world
con sized convention which happens annually in minneapolis so yeah why would you have a world con
i don't think they do anymore do they minicon shrunk a lot not minicon convergence what
oh convergence yeah no no well convert why does convergence not generate people who would like to
run a wiskon i don't know because they run in convergence one of the one of the things that world
con does is it recruits a lot of people and then it goes away again oh yes that's true if you if you
if you if you had done glasco in the next year you were doing the same thing in glasco again all
the people who had just worked on glasco would be working on the next glasco they wouldn't be going
into the community working on other stuff because they'd be busy so yeah non-traveling conventions do
less to invigorate local fandom uh in the sense that they probably invigorate a lot of local
fandom but then they invigorate it in a very specific direction i don't know historically how
much of the wiskon convention committee was actually local um to Wisconsin and how many
were people who came every year because this was kind of the big feminist f-compention well i might
just say emminton has a website now we're not going to talk about it in much detail but we will link
in the show notes or we will probably talk about it on future episodes almost certainly that includes
a list of the people who are working on emminton which is quite nice to have it's my favorite thing
about bid websites i know some of these people unlike them i do not know most of the people that's
probably fine at this stage and she knows some of them and dislikes them but we're not going to tell
you which we have a little real world thing this week which is kind of a psa which is that loyds
are introducing monthly charges of four pounds twenty five on community bank accounts many
fannish bank accounts have this and i think if you've got an active one you probably already know
this and you're probably already thinking about what you might do about it the charge of four
pounds twenty five is not very much compared to kind of the cost of putting on an easter con say
um the people it really matters for is if you're sitting with a small bank account that's got some
funds from a thing you did ten years ago or even longer then these charges will eat that all up
so you should probably go and have a look and change your bank account or close it if you don't
need it um yeah it's a bit it's a bit of pain yeah wonderful person of our parish claire brawley
has done quite a lot of work on looking at all of the alternatives so if if somebody's like out there
going i don't know what i might do about this then get in touch and we'll put you in touch with claire
indeed we will um she won't like that or i will maybe pass on some of the information that claire
has found but it is a bit of a pain
shall we do picks so i have a pick that is a steam game that is technically an early access
but we'll have its 1.0 release the day this podcast drops so if you've been waiting for the 1.0 of
caves of cudd you can i assume that's how you pronounce qud you can go and get it on
thursday in the 1.0 but actually it's been around for a decade but i only just recently started playing
it they've described it as a science fantasy rogue-like epic steeped in retrofuturism deep
simulation and of swathes of sentient plants and it's kind of a lot of it is procedurally generated
but actually there's quite a lot of underlying lore and plot so it is kind of like a giant
open world fantasy epic game but also it's kind of like an asky rogue like it has graphics but they're
they're little tiny little 16 by 16 pixel type graphics i love it it's so good
it is the only reason it hasn't eaten my life is that i drag myself away from it periodically to do
other things i keep dying there's a as well as the kind of proper rogue like permadeath
approach to it you can also set it up so you play it like an rpg and when you die you respawn
in the last town you were in so that might work and there's also a mode where you just wander
around and nothing kills you very much so that you can make progress but i kind of like the kind
of stabby version it's kind of in a post-apocalyptic world but it is it is much deeper than you might
expect and it is doing much more with with lore than is normal for a procedurally generated game
and i just want to say go and play it it's going to be on me hugo valet because it is getting its
1.0 release so clearly it is eligible for 2025 and for those of you who've been out there saying
well i've been playing it since 2030 or something well yeah no i know that's true but it's new and
old at the same time way sounds good and and like many rogue likes um amazing things happen to you
so you find you're in alliance with sentient worms and and meanwhile um and you get you get
artifacts that cause everybody to turn into goo which you know there's all sorts of all sorts of
bizarre things happen to you in this game every game nice i will put it on my steam wish list
it's also on itch.io and gog we will have links in the show notes listeners and it costs £24
and £99 but obviously if what you like in your life is huge 3d graphics then it is not for you
because it's really it is a game of alasky road like sense even though it's not actually using
asky as using it's using graphical bits i am also going to pick a game and i am also going to pick
a game that came out quite a while ago in a early access equivalent and has had its first
edition this year and i am going to pick mothership mothership is a science fiction horror role playing
game it is a tabletop role playing game not a video role playing game yeah so it came out in kind of
early 2024 in the first edition and i have been playing it lately and it's very very good
it's a very simple system which does a very good job of establishing how GMs should GM and players
should play through it's quite small and snappy um rule books and i'm really impressed with it and
i'm really enjoying um running it for some friends when i do and there's so much content for it available
kind of online through the um like the community doing third party material and that's something
that the developers Tuesday night games have really embraced and that's part of what makes it so
wonderful um but yeah it's very lovely very lovely very well done game and it's published by Tuesday
night games and i think Liz is familiar with two rooms in a boom um but Tuesday night games were
the publishers of two rooms in a boom and they are also the upcoming publishers of uh were wolf in
the dark um so they make some they make some neat games generally um but yeah mothership's really
good and thank you very much to laurie anderson and kevin anderson of the hugo girl podcast for
bringing me my mothership box to Glasgow because yeah that was very lovely of them tying into that
is currently mothership month which means on back a kit there's a bunch of mothership crowd
funding happening right now and you can go and get your grubby mitts on loads of different products
and by the time uh you listen to this there will be i think probably four or five days left on that
crowd funding experience um i have perhaps back to an unwise number of campaigns um but i have no
regrets mhm lizzy you're gonna pick something like a book or are you also going to pick a game
now well that's it now since you've both picked games i'm gonna pick a game just so we all match
yes i wasn't going to pick this game because i picked the precursor game not that long ago um as
one of my picks but i will pick rise of the golden idol which is a sequel to curse of the golden idol
it is another excellent little puzzle game which you can play on multiple platforms you can also
play it through netflix if you have netflix and basically did you like curse the golden idol then
you'll probably very much like rise a golden idol which is the same except i like the graphic style
a little bit better i think it's a little bit clearer on smaller screens and i think it's
um there were some puzzles in the expansions for curse of golden idol which were really like i
could not could not get through them i had to get some hints whereas this one um i think everything
was kind of at the right difficulty level there was only one bit where i got stuck and then when i
got a hint i was like oh fine that's what you meant kind of moment but basically they're just
they're just satisfying and i had them on my phone and kept kind of poking away at them for five or
ten minutes and like unlocking another little bit of the puzzle and then putting it away and trying
again and then i basically went through like the last final bit in like three hours one night and
had a lovely time hmm that sounds good i have not played the first one yet but it is on the list
it's on my phone i also thought it was pretty great that right after i bought a playstation 5 i decided
to play a tiny adventure game on my phone this is this is why i do not yet have a playstation 5
i actually the the reason the proper reason i have not um played your pick from tovah week is that i
almost never play games on my phone or on my computer i almost always play them on playstation
or switch so maybe i should look up to see whether these games are on consoles i'm pretty sure golden
idling on switch golden island is on switch um i don't know if it's via netflix on switch or
don't think so i think you have to get it life on that was the ott thought podcast and it's a good
bye for me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
it's an interesting interesting psychology there right i don't want to buy it for money on a platform
because i could play it for free but the thing i can play it for free on is the thing i never
play games on so therefore i don't play it and i'm like this is this is old psychology this is poor
psychology you know i understand why people do it but but there are lots of times for example do you
ever buy a coffee in a cafe rather than going oh no if i was a tome i could just make myself a cup of
coffee but i'm not a tome so i would have to buy a cup of coffee in this cafe and i don't do that
because i could be at home making coffee so you buy things this is this is a terrible analogy
no it's not it's exactly the same thing the point is it's convenient for you to have it on the switch
or your ps5 so you buy it rather than playing it for free on the thing that it's free on but the
thing is that when i am playing on my ps5 my phone is in my pocket if i was in a cafe and i had brought
with me a coffee that i had made at home i would drink the coffee from home and they would throw
me out the cafe that's where i'm at in this analogy do you ever get takeaway food because your kitchen
is right there in your house i get takeaway food i couldn't make i couldn't make as well as i can at
home but they're identical games us and i also sometimes pay for Netflix instead of watching
aspania do interpretive dance my point i think is that this analogy is limited i have a better
analogy but first can i pay to see aspania do interpretive dance uh aspania please write in i think
about analogy is when i own a book on paper and then i buy it on kindle so it's easier for me to
cart about with me on my kindle the preferred reading experience for me which i have done see i
don't i don't do that i just take the book with yeah but what if it's really big i mean i'm reading
the book of love by kelly link and it is really big at eliz but i am still ready to get on dead tree
oh yeah yeah i read that on the kindle it's fair i was going to say i guess you're reading a lot of
paper books still yes john at the moment for sure i do quite like paper books i basically like books
i am not quite as militant as some are in this i just like books and i don't really care what format
they're in yeah i mean i did buy i have bought handbags specifically because they are the correct
size to fit all minus s season including a kindle the theme music for this episode was
fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in comfatec.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license
this podcast will end at the beep beep
Thank you.