Oh shit! Shit shit shit shit shit shit shit shit shit shit shit shit shit!
Recording stopped.
I listened to just pour a bunch of tea on a computer I think.
That's definitely going in the edit.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 123rd episode of Octa Thorpe,
a podcast of science fiction and science fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 21st
of November 2024. I'm John Coxin.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty. I should do the intro one episode just to confuse everyone.
You did Dom the Zoo Corn F-Pierso, didn't you?
I don't remember that far back.
Right, that's fair. I remember we played with the format but yes it would be fun to play with
the format. We don't have any letters of comment this week on account of how we're
recording before the last episode has gone up so yeah we don't feel lonely.
So we're recording very early this week even earlier than we did last week.
On account if I'm going to trip again sorry listeners.
Oh but your last trip was amazing or all your trips amazing Liz.
Yes.
This one is a work conference so less amazing but it's in New Orleans so not bad.
I was going to say I was going to say I think less amazing is doing some work there because
less amazing than Japan.
Yeah my work trip is Washington DC in December which is less good than New Orleans I think but
oh you fuckers.
It's certainly colder.
Oh it's going.
Oh what it is to be a working academic.
It's so hard I just got to go to so many places so difficult.
I will say that I'm going to spend 23 hours in transit.
Yeah I mean that's horrible.
Did that for Australia it was worth it?
Yeah I mean it will be it will be.
I will say that I get to fly premium economy because of the travel and expenses rules.
I've never done that before so I'm excited.
Oh I'm not flying premium economy.
I'm doing the whole thing down the back of the plane John so thank your travel rules.
I really enjoyed my 19 and a half hour direct flight would do it again.
In the latest banana wings which dropped the other day there's a quote from Ella Parker about
she has this fantasy of being just slightly incapacitated so she can take her bed and read
for several months yes and and going on a very long plane journey is kind of a bit like that
because you can just kind of consume media for 24 hours so that's quite good.
Yeah planes I mean I'm looking forward to my flights to Washington DC because I have a large
number of books to read.
I knew this going in but as a clerk judge you get sent all of the books physically
and I cut my book around in my bag all the time yeah I don't I did had not realized how much I
didn't miss doing that.
The Belfast Eastercon has opened its hotel bookings.
To be fair they did that yeah they did that a while ago we just forgot to tell you.
It's time it's time to book your Eastercon hotel if you've not done so already they are in the
Hilton but as they say there are many other hotels in the Belfast area and they have rates at some
of them. There are also many other hotels in the Belfast area at which they do not have rates and
one of those is the one I am booked into and so other people might also like to go and have a look
at what hotels are available in Belfast.
Yes so there's a range of hotel options they vary from quite expensive to really very expensive.
I mean that is not a dig at Belfast that is just the reality of hotels in 2024 I think
but yes I am also staying I'm staying at the same hotel as Alison which is not a con hotel
and Liz I know has been looking at Airbnb's.
Yes I mean I also looked at Airbnb's in the vicinity and there are some and also bear in mind I think
there is a based on Google Maps I think there is a pedestrian bridge into or very close to the Hilton
which is not used for part of walking direction so there are some which look quite far
but are actually a shelter walk than you'd imagine.
Ah so like as the Bumblebee flies it is closer than it would look on the map.
Yeah it's close to the new because obviously there's some water and there's only various ways to
cross the water and one of them I think is not on the map.
Liz are you coming to the Belfast Eastercon?
Yeah probably. Excellent.
Yeah we can do what we thought live.
Eastercon have announced their rate rises.
The first rate rise to 90 pounds has already happened it took effect on the 1st of November.
Sorry we didn't tell you about that before it happened but you know sorry.
And then there is going to be another rate rise to 100 pounds on the 1st of January
and another rate rise on the door to 120 pounds.
Day rates will also be available.
The first Eastercon discount and the All Ireland rate will rise to 70 pounds on the 14th of November.
So you will also have missed that.
We have spoken before on the podcast about the way that increasing rates for Eastercon
is a great deal after the initial offering rather than merely a little bit.
Privileges are the people who can afford to buy their Eastercon membership to years in advance
which is not everybody coming to Eastercon by any means.
I kind of have a regular moan about the quality of Eastercon budgeting but my feeling is that if
you are budgeting in the best possible way then you would set a higher rate to begin with and then
have only modest rate rises subsequently.
That's probably me being a slightly mean because obviously running a Belfast Eastercon is quite hard
and it's an unknown quantity in quite a lot of ways so you know but we did think when the original
rate was announced that it was quite low.
Well I think in particular the very specific problem that Reconnect have is that they have an All Ireland
price and I think it's very hard to know how many people will be joining at that rate before you
start.
So it might be that they're... I mean and I also don't know how you budget but it might be that
you expect tons of people to join at the All Ireland rate and then even if it's a lower rate
they don't and so you kind of raise all your rates or you want to keep that steady to try and let
people join from Ireland who would not otherwise be able to go to Eastercon and raise the rate for
maybe all people from the UK and the US.
It's a really tricky balance and I don't know which way I would have done it but I think they have
significantly more uncertainty than many Eastercons although they've all been uncertain since 2020
and Worldcon is also an extra uncertainty because that normally brings in a bunch of people who have
decided they kind of like this convention thing and let's go to the next one but I don't know how many
of them would say go if it was in York but won't go to Belfast.
I'm sure there'll be some of those but one of the things that's
happened and we'll be talking a little bit about back to our futures later but one of the things
that's happened this weekend is that I've had a couple of conversations with people whose first
Worldcon was Glasgow and who are now going to the Belfast Eastercon which is quite exciting really
and I like to know that those people exist.
I think it's very good there's obviously been an influx of new people to community which is very
good and I think obviously it's very good that there's an Eastercon Belfast because I hope that
will bring more people into the community and it's also very good and I do think there's like
a... the comment about privilege is an interesting one right because on the one hand
it does advantage people who can afford to budget in advance to have it very cheap at the start and
then raise it quite dramatically at the end but I guess the counter-argument to that is if you have
just all the rate to be high you never like if you can't afford that high rate you just never can
whereas if you have it low for a little bit at least like there's a window but like I don't know
how that works and also I am aware that the price of a membership is not necessarily the
the biggest slice of the pie when it comes to the cost of attending an Eastercon but the other
thing is that even when they announced that 70 pound membership I remember them announcing it
and I was like I was genuinely astounded that it was so low when they announced it and the fact that
they're announced three rate rises in the course of six months does rather indicate that they might
not be having a financially great time because I feel like if they were all just like tik-a-tiboo
they wouldn't need to do that so I don't know I wonder whether they had it I think you're right
that they had it far too cheap early doors and I wonder whether that was a mistake and I think
ultimately we are probably entering a period of time when Eastercon memberships do need to go up
because everything has gone up like there hasn't been a massive jump like levitation was a jump
compared to the previous two and then the Belfast went back down to the conversation level and I
think that was probably a mistake I think probably that was not sustainable I think they might be
finding out yeah there's a real sense in which conversation was sitting on a pre-pandemic hotel
contract and and I feel that that's part a big part of why our our rates could be as low as they
were we knew that rates would have to rise I mean I think Farah came to talk to us about
when she was planning levitation and said will people whether a higher rate and I said you know
yes they will it'll be fine much more than they'll weather Telford I didn't say that
well I think and I think actually conversation saying it's so low has made the conversation
more difficult because I think part of why reconnects level is so low is because people
reacted very badly to the jump with Telford and I think as a community we probably should have
pitched that differently and conversation probably shouldn't have had such a low rate in order that
levitations would seem less dramatic and then reconnect wouldn't feel a need to react to it
I'm gonna I'm gonna say no conversation budgeted correctly and carefully and we also deliberately
did not do a lot of the things that cost a lot of money the last time I ran an easter con we booked
a band I've been thinking about booking bands because Glasgow didn't book any bands they just
booked orchestras and we booked a band for for Follicon because it was a thing we could do and we
came to levitation well came to do conversation and we went oh what is our events budget going to be
oh people are going to be feeling poor pandemic all of that and we just want to make the convention
run we are not going to have that events budget that would bring in a name band we actually did have
we had some quite good events but they were basically because we got them for free or very very very
cheap but we basically did not have an ends budget and and that saves you a lot of money on both
tech and events and and so we actually made budgeting choices to keep the price down and the notion
that that having budgeted correctly and run the convention at a made a reasonable amount of money
that is in some way suggesting it's all right for people to go off and spend what they want
want and then and then go oh but the problem here is conversation to charge a load more money
that's just nonsense you were like conversation should have charged more that that that's not
why he said i mean that's not what i said so that's fair but i think easter con as a whole if you have
an event which is being run by the same people every year and that event went 70 70 110 everyone
complained it would be quite natural for the next event to pick their level at 70 and i think
that's probably why reconnect picked it at 70 and reconnect is now in trouble and i think what you
probably wanted to do is do 70 90 110 and so i think it's i think it is if you look at easter con as a
holistic thing rather than a sequence of warring committees there is a different logic and i agree
that easter con is a sequence of warring committees but like we don't have to make every decision on
that basis you are still making it sound like a membership rate is something that you pluck from
thin air you don't you make oh no no i'm not i'm absolutely not you said they picked their membership
you don't pick it from thin air they picked it from thin air job well but they didn't that's wrong
i i don't know which one you you are talking about when you say they by the way because you
could be referring to multiple committees i think she's talking about Belfast but i think
Belfast picked their membership level because there was so much chunkering at levitation and they
wanted to pick it cheaper so that they wouldn't get the the the feedback the backlash and i think
that's part of if you don't condition people slowly to these sorts of changes in the financial
reality of the convention then then you are going to have that backlash and if you can reduce that
backlash so that people aren't as grumpy then that is good and i think as a community we did not do
a good job of that i think every convention made choices which in a vacuum for that convention
made a lot of sense but i think when you look at the overall trend those decisions look a bit
weird because it's like well we're not all operating in a vacuum this is a series of
conventions which all work together but we don't work together financially very well i don't think
yeah but i mean i think i'm a little bit more than i listen on this one because imagine you'd have
to here have a situation where conversation knew what tellford were aiming at in order to set it
higher i think one you need to know very much kind of how much cons are going to cost before
the time because it would have needed like you know i we don't know what i can't and what conversation
would have known but they would have had to like know a bunch of stuff about tellford but the thing
is imagine that conversation you know they knew that the next one was going to be more expensive so
do they kind of set the rate at 90 so that they make a big chunk of money which sits and pass along
or do they have to then set it at 90 and then say okay but we'll spend spend more money
or are you saying they should end up with the same amount of money just set the initial rate higher
and and not raise it i mean i think i think it's tricky i'm not saying anything about the budgets
which i think is what might be confusing i'm saying stuff about the consumer perception to
increasing price of events over time yeah and i don't disagree with you on that one but i can't
see a way in which you mitigate this that doesn't involve conversation setting their rate artificially
high and they prefer to make choices not to do that the so the first thing is the hospitality
industry is also about to take another big hit um they've already they're getting hammered in the
budget and things are going to be even worse so i don't think we're going to see this improving
anytime soon i think we do have to accept east coast is going to get more expensive
feel comfortable to set a much higher starting rate it will be fine um levitation also set a
low starting rate and only then increased a lot it so it did the same trick where the people who
were in the know can get their tickets and i'd have money can get their tickets early yes um the
other thing i thought about was i i go to a folk club sometimes and about 50 years ago the people
who ran the precursors of this folk club said the ticket the price for a ticket to see the band on
the folk club night should be about the same as two pints of ale because you know you'd have two
pints of ale you buy your ticket so that would be about right and and what we've got to is that the
price of an easter con membership is now way less than the price of even a single night in the hotel
and that seems to me to be quite low if you're likely to go to an easter con and have three or
four nights at a hotel then it doesn't seem to be unreasonable the the cost of the convention is
about the same as one of those nights you know and and so so that's kind of the starting of a place
where you might look and say oh yes a hotel room a membership but yes easter cons are expensive
they've always been expensive you know the conventions are expensive except for back to our futures
which is not expensive yeah i think i think that's it basically if prices are going up you have to be
prepared to put your prices higher and then when people say well your prices are you say because
that's how much it costs for things because everything is much more expensive now especially in the
hospitality industry where all of our costs are incurred as you just said yeah and the last thing
i'll say is that you know i think we connect our pains to say look we have our main hotel but look
there are other hotels around which are much cheaper than our extremely high hotel rate but
for the people who have no choice to be in that hotel because they need to be close to the con
it doesn't matter if they're paying an extra 20 pounds a night at an extra 20 pounds from membership
because they're going to be paying hundreds pounds more for a hotel room than say i would have to pay
so that i think is a much bigger thing anyway and even without sorry even without having
tired hotel rooms i think you still need to think a little bit about what your main hotel
price is and whether they're any that are very very close by part of this comes from so alla
some mentioned that levitation also says it's opening rate low and the reason we did that was
because we had known so obviously e-sicon committees talked to each other we knew that
conversation was going for 70 pounds and we knew we couldn't do the budget we actually needed to do
immediately because we knew people would already be angry it was so much higher
and we knew we couldn't do it properly at the level we actually needed it and that
kind of ties into the thing i saying right at the beginning which is if we assume that the cost
of this is going up and it seems to be going up like it might be that this is a blip and it's
going to return back to where it was but i don't think so and i think alla says point about the
budget is a good one where i think it's going to get more expensive not less in the imminent future
if we accept that then that i think implies that the membership over the sort of decade from 2020
onwards is going to be a straight line going up at some gradient and i just want easter cons to
make that gradient a gradient rather than a sort of series of big jumps and then plateaus
because i think that makes it easier for everyone to see the shape of what's happening
and it comes as less of a shock and i think i don't mean to disparage any individual convention
for making decisions that made sense in their budget i just think for a very high level
perspective i want the membership to be able to see that shape and not be surprised when that
shape is like i don't want that shape to be unpredictable because i think that doesn't work well for
our members and our community and that's the point i'm trying to make i want i want people to understand
what's happening which part of the reason we're having this discussion now i think yeah that's right
but i think every convention does make the decisions they have to make in their own budget
and like i'm not it's hard running conventions especially budgeting conventions is difficult
yeah i think every other time i've run an easter con we've put the rate up and explained why
because easter con because this pressure to keep the membership artificially low is is
absolutely real hmm yeah and especially to have a very low rate so i i go to a lot of festivals
and they have early bird rates which are maybe 10 or 20 pounds less than the eventual rate
and then you get to easter con where the where it could be like 40 or 50 or 60 pounds between
the starting rate and the flatness feeling the bit off i went to an academic sorry academic conference
space whether it was like space by the conference and the early bird rate was 260 and the rate if
you registered four weeks before was 360 and the rate on the door was 460 and because i missed the
first jump i was like i was just not going then because it's not worth the money like and i was
like i do wonder the other thing is if your jumps are high enough i do wonder how many people are
like oh well i missed the early bird so i'm just not gonna go because it feels like it's not value
for money if you did and that is another part of the psychology which is very tricky i mean i think
there was an enormous amount of money in the bank at the point where conversation started and i think
if we had budgeted to make because we did make a surplus as well as all the parcel long right i
think if we made a significantly larger surplus than that people would have started nobody got
upset with the amount of surplus we made but people would have got seriously upset if if we had made
a lot more than that and that's the disadvantage of not having a central east con body but let's not
have that argument now i know we can have that argument another time but i feel like we'd be there
many times we are getting to the point where we'll have to the um they're closing up the sorts of
bank accounts we use and things like that so it's gonna be it's gonna be very very hard
we've touched on this before but we didn't have a central east con body but what we did have
was a set of past along that would get you out if you made a horrendous you know if you had made a
horrendous misjudgment in your price and you ended up down a few thousand pounds on what you needed
we had a past along that would get us through it when we don't have that you've got to be a lot
more cautious about your rates yeah that's that's the other problem no no past along
got nothing to talk about this week guys it's terrible
Seattle also announced hotels they are also expensive are they more expensive than Belfast
oh yes yeah but you can put four people in a room yes we could if Liz was coming Liz are you
coming to Seattle no boo yeah you could if we were coming are you coming to Seattle no boo
you see I went on holiday and I only have a finite amount of annual leave jump I know it
sucks doesn't it as of as of may we will have an infinite amount of annual leave or rather
only 365 days of it yeah yeah my parents are retired and they keep saying things like oh I
just forget what day it is and I want I just oh my goodness it's so smug it's so smug I am not
retired and but I do work for myself and can pick exactly my own hours and um and that will continue
we're going to go to Ocapellicon which is something I might mention on the podcast we have joined
we haven't done any of the other stuff about sorting out the speaking of 23-hour transit times
to the Aland Islands but I'm hoping it will be quite nice and a nice place to be like the end of
June which is also my 60th birthday start 23-hour transit to the island islands I hope not there's
an airport if you go by ferry which we're not going to do we're going to fly the take a ferry
yeah you could fly to Stockholm and take ferry right is that what you think that's the plan
yeah either Stockholm or Helsinki but probably Stockholm Helsinki doesn't have ferries
Helsinki does have ferries I mean it doesn't have ferries to the island I'm going to go
double check this one to make sure I have not completely made this up so I got to the Helsinki
World Con by taking a ferry from Stockholm to Helsinki which went through the Orland Island
but I don't know whether it does it but I don't know I confess I don't know whether it does stop
both ways oh it does know okay oh no I'm talking nonsense it does have one it's just that that
is overnight the Stockholm one's better because it's during the day so you can do like looking out
over the I look like the archipelago and stuff and it's good I was gonna say you can go from
from Toku instead and that will do it yeah I mean there's also an airport on the island
it's dinky it's the smallest airport I've ever been in but there isn't an airport
Liz can tell us if she's going to archipelacon too I am not because as we have previously discussed
our E.C.F.T.L. Wilcons I have a finite amount of annual leave and it does not cover the amount
I would need to get back and go to Finland but I am a bit sad because I went to archipelacon
one and it was great this is one of the reasons I'm going to archipelacon too is that not you
were not the only person who said it was a fabulous convention it is I just we have a finite amount of
we have the annual leave the problem is the money yeah yeah we have the annual leave and we sort of
have the money but we only kind of have a finite amount of money for the whole of the rest of our
lives so we we need to kind of spread it out a bit now and also I'm going to go to I'm going to go
to L.A.Con so I feel like I can do a different thing and have a year off from WELCOME.
On the subject of WELCOME and conventions we have been running back to our futures this weekend
which is an online convention where we watch all the catch up from Glasgow and talk about it
I say all the catch up it's not all the catch up on account of how there was quite a lot of catch
up but yeah and we're going to talk a little bit about the stuff we've seen and whether we thought
it was good we did mostly think it was good I want to talk I didn't want to talk about the actual
content of back to our futures so much except for um it was the Glasgow program turns out to
have been really pretty good well done Liz and crew um and especially when people gave a little
thought to curating some things out of it and saying here it's a program slot you could you
could go to two items or you can do anything else you like but here are two things we think you might
like and everyone seems to have really liked all of the things in those item slots yeah I went to
some panels I went to the opening ceremony which I kind of had to because I was on it
and then I went to writing Future Scotland which was good very good I did a team quiz and when
Liz answered the questions she messaged me to say John because she did not like one of the
connections between the answers or maybe she did like it so much she wanted to pay me a
compliment no one knows all right I will not you know reveal which one of those it was we
as may decide for themselves reveal reveal your secrets Liz it wasn't the first one John
or it wasn't the second one uh you didn't like it you did like it yeah my ton of voice would be
John okay that's why I was attempting to convey through all caps then I went to the
the mathematics of games fairies in fantasy literature the nitty ochora four panel and from
Antarctica to space and then there was a gin tasting and I had rather a lot of gin and was
quite squiffy oh I tasted a lot of gin and it was all terrible I didn't have any good gin in the
house because apparently when we have good gin in the house we drink gin and when we have bad
gin in the house we drink other things I realized but we drank quite a lot of our bad gin and we
also drank some some good gin liqueur which we had forgotten that we had and yeah no gin gin good
but I got to bed at a very sensible time there may be not as sensible as some people have you
seen any cat chup at Glasgow Liz um I have independently I went back and watched the dark room oh which is
good I mean it is the dark room but it does have some good you know gags about welcome yeah it does
and I just want to buy John Robertson like infinite supplies of like honey and lemon
I think he's gonna need them I think he's a performer who is not taking good care of his throat
I think he's got very good I mean he's very good performer and I'm sure he's very good at
projection but I do feel a little bit like oh I wanted you to just have a sit down and not talk
for an hour and maybe have some like throat sweeties um yeah so that was great um I've started
watching the tip tree play which I think is on back to our futures for later but I will not be there
so yeah that's but that's actually it's all I've watched I feel I'm not a person who sits down and
puts a panel on I think that's partly because mostly they are not visually interesting I think if
they were all as a bunch of podcasts and an RSS feed I could download and listen to I would be
more likely to do some catch up and future world cons take note because that's something you can
just do because I treat catch up in general like podcasts as in I put it on while I am working
especially panels I mean there are obviously some more visual items that I do watch but the
majority of Glasgow stuff I have put on and treated as podcasts and then I have also watched some of
the program this weekend but about half of the things that were recommended that are on our schedule
I've already watched so so that was it was quite nice to know that I have actually been
getting through it because I've been working quite hard on on program I felt stung by the
suggestion that I never go to program at conventions and so I am taking great use of where where
conventions have replay programs I am watching as much program as anyone might reasonably watch
in the weekend just afterwards I like program perfectly well as long as I don't have other
things I could be doing one of the things I've always sort of wanted I keep meaning to volunteer
to program at conventions and keep not doing but it would I think when we did the punctuations I
did because obviously we had the access to the replay videos so the ones that were on replay I
just hived the audio off and put on my podcast app and just listened to them while running and
that was very good and I don't know the obviously the problem is that podcasts are publicly available
and then if you want to make them privately available I guess that there's work involved there and I
don't really have an idea for how much work that is I mean it might be very little work and it might
be very a lot work and I have literally no clue which way you'd jump but yeah I think it is the
sort of thing that I would very much enjoy being able to do but also I don't know how many people
would like I know I would is that enough to make it worth the effort no one knows I mean we know
that people listen to podcasts right it'll be the same crew as the crew who listen to podcasts who
would like this yeah I think I think it is I think it is much work because it basically has to be
an individual URL basically I think the way people normally do podcasts which have
memberships is to give you like a special RSS feed right yeah but some places have one per person
and that is a lot more work but we could just have one and put it behind the paywall in the same way
that we've done back to our futures because back to our futures is just all tucked behind the Glasgow
paywall yes but I don't think you can have an RSS feed for podcasts took behind the paywall that
I can't email to someone it doesn't matter but yes it potentially it potentially does because if
you tell people your audio video is only available to Glasgow members and then you put it somewhere
it isn't then 99 cent the time you'll be fine and 1 cent of the time you won't be and then you've
got a problem this ties into something else that I've been thinking about which is that jondie berry
said in a place I'm not supposed to talk about but I don't think you'll like this if you do mind
John I'm very sorry that he speaks at a type conference every year and they hold the they hold
replay for the members for a certain amount of time and then they just pushed all on YouTube and
I said well what we did this was one of the punctuations we actually asked people about replay in
YouTube's and public YouTube separately and presumably you could actually ask those permissions at
WILCON and then just dump everything on YouTube at the end of the replay period at which point
you could also make these are a public RSS feed and the answer I got was that you can do that but
you could do that in theory but Planarama didn't have the permission so I've put this as a very vague
feature request in the in the Vay in the fandom development discord but I feel like that model
where you hold the stuff for a certain amount of time for members and then where people have
previously given permission you then dump it into a public space at the end of that time which is
also what we're using for the Taffa Guff reports now and that's a really good model because actually
there's there's infinite amounts of stuff on the internet and really people don't often want to
look at stuff at the six months old but sometimes they might yes that would be fine but my point
was Glasgow did not ask permission to do that so they can't no no no Glasgow clearly can't do that
this is this is I'm not saying Glasgow do this I'm saying future conventions have a think about this
also we were talking about the great cost of conventions and I'm going to say that
back to our futures obviously Glasgow was quite expensive to put on back to our futures have
been extremely cheap both to have make happen and to attend and I still think there's space for some
online conventions in the mix because they are very cheap and can be accessible to a lot of people
who couldn't necessarily get to a physical convention yeah but back to our futures a terrible example
of that right because there's a reason about our futures is cheap which is you haven't generated
any content I mean you generate you have generated a small amount of content but you know how dare
you Liz I wrote 25 quiz questions at least five of which made you make a noise I think you can still
do this but what I'm saying is back to our futures is basically building off a half million pound
you know turnover convention it is I have another but however I have another idea for an online
convention which is that you could do this but instead of getting your program from Glasgow you
get your program from the internet and you basically curate stuff that's already out there as say
we're going to watch these fabulous things in the world one of the things so Nicholas Jackson
gave a talk on the mathematics of games which I really liked but oh you have to you have to have
a head for maths like he is not he is not like walking you slowly through maths on that one
like the equations come thick and fast and those equations are made in LaTeX I watched that a
couple of days ago and I was like oh this I know two thirds of the stuff in this already and the
third that I don't know is very interesting and I really enjoy this and it is great and yes I
was like oh it's it's it's it's proper game theory it's good but I will say is so the reason I bring
that up is that he mentioned a talk that was given as the hey lecture the other year by a
mathematician and someone pointed out that that talk has been given at a different event where they
did put it on YouTube so like I think Alison is on something here where there are like
fanist style program things that you could cobble something out of now the question is
if you build it do they come I don't know the answer to that yes because not that many people
I mean we've got about we've got about 160 people have joined the discord something like four
back to our futures and quite a lot of people have come in but not all at once very often so we've
typically had about between probably 30 or 40 engaging with the program a lot of the time and
and I mean that's small I it's enough but I would like to it would be twice the size so I'll know
that for next time I mean we kind of we kind of didn't publicize this very much for fear of getting
a thousand so yeah we could we could on our current setup we could have it have had it be two or three
times the size it is and also in the pandemic large zooms were a thing that happened and like
you just had to basically be okay with that but outside the pandemic I've forgotten how much I
hate big zooms like I find it really difficult to work out when I can join a conversation without
interrupting and when I'm welcome to talk and stuff and like above about five people I just
start finding it completely isolating and lonely and so yeah there is an element there which is
in the pandemic this was much better than nothing but outside the pandemic it's much worse than
being at a convention and that is hard I think I have enjoyed this weekend very greatly but yeah
I think it is interesting going back to that kind of pandemic mode of discourse and being like oh oh oh
I think I could have done with setting up more rooms that were kind of maximum four maximum six
maximum eight I can do that of course but I think now it's probably a next time thing
a lot of the time it's been fine it's just sometimes there's a huge bunch of people in one room and
it's quite hard that we still haven't solved that problem of how to organically split a group in a
bar that is too big into two groups that are the right size that just happens naturally in bars
but never happens at all in zoom there's also been another welcome bit announced and it is a bid for
Edmonton in 2030 hey I've always wanted to go to Edmonton I would like to go to Canada be nice
yeah so there's basically just an announcement saying we are going to do an Edmonton bid
and a blue sky account and then further details will be forthcoming this is one of your you know
placeholders for the future things yeah that placeholder has a very strong graphic design
I was very pleased to see this it has very strong graphic design and also they have four grounded
the name used for Edmonton by the indigenous people of Canada because we later named it Edmonton
and that is a nice thing to see upfront on your big materials and this is something that came up
on the fame fantasy panel was a discussion about indigenous people was because Jo Walton was offered
basically she was asked if she wanted to write a sequel to among others and she was like financially
that would bring quite a good idea so I looked at like how I could do it and she was like basically
there are two options which is do the do the thing like what if it's in a different country or do
the thing in space now I will go on the record of saying I want to read the sequel to among among
others sell on the moon like she talked about it he sounded cracking I would be well up for it
Jo I assume you don't listen but if you do I'm in a friend of Jo let her know tell her to listen
John will buy one copy yeah you will you will get one sale but she talked about like you know
one of the other obvious things you could do is just like well what would this look like in the
States and then she was like but I don't want to erase the indigenous peoples like own kind of
fantastical cultures and heritages by transplanting like the British fantastical on it to erase the
indigenous fantastical and I think they're a really fascinating thing but I'd love to see
I'm kind of hoping that if this convention is selected they would have like some really
interesting stuff on indigenous science fiction and fantasy and I think that would be really really
interesting Belfast Easton has Ruecke Rowan horses a guest of honor and obviously there is a
consideration there is you could probably do some quite good intersectional program about
English colonialism of the fantastic in Ireland and in the States and do some interesting
crossovers there so I'm hoping that there'll be some interesting panels about that
shall we do picks I guess so all right who wants to pick first I'll pick they've got a book a pick
it's a book oh this is going to surprise zero listeners but I read a book by Robert Jackson
Bennett and it was great and I'm going to pick it uh-huh I know I've become predictable but the book
is called Tainted Cup by Robert Jackson Bennett it is yet another brilliant fantasy world um it's
basically an empire where giant leviathans are real and in the rainy season they will basically
need to be stopped from destroying the outlying areas of the empire um and also all the magic is
magic where you engineer plants anyway it's great and it also kind of sets up this very
this class structure where there's obviously a big military who are there to defeat the leviathans
you have this structure where living in the inside of the empire is more desirable because if you
live in outside provinces there's a possibility that a giant whale will come and destroy you oh and
also people are magically altered to have things like say a perfect memory so our main characters are
Anna who is an investigator of mysteries and she is investigating a murder through her assistant
Dinh, Dinh has a perfect memory Anna basically does not leave the house and sends Dinh out to do
all the investigating with his perfect memory and then come back and relate to her what he sees
and I think the best review I've seen is stealing a sort of good news from goodreads
approach from the Hugo Girl people the review is it's like knives out but if knives out was set
to fancy world and Benoit Blanc was an old woman who had hired the most disaster bisexual to be
her eyes and ears thank you Robin on goodreads yeah and it is I would say it is a bit more plotty
and so rid of the books a bit less character driven because it is both a great fancy world
and a good murder mystery and it feels like a nice well-paced murder mystery where things come out
you know at the right time to be a surprise and yeah I just sort of devoured it in a day
well that sounds awesome the other the other thing I think it's probably in conversation with is the
Lincoln Rime novels by Jeffrey Deaver in which the main character is paraplegic and has a
detective who does the crime scene work for them so yeah it sounds interesting I love those books
so I shall look it up I just I do like Robert Jackson Bennett and I need to read more of it so
thank you for the recommendation is it going to be like Adrian Shekoski where the person
writes faster than I read books thank you right it's about one book a year I think you can manage
that very normal I could definitely read one Robert Jackson Bennett book a year he's very good
oh Liz you have an Adrian Shekoski scoop well it's not it's not really a scoop so much as I read
Amazon is it mmm mmm there's a cancer scoop yeah basically I'm reading I'm reading an
agent Shekoski book as I do quite often so I'm reading House of Open Wounds so I went to add
Days of Shattered Faith his next book in the series to my Amazon wishlist and I saw there was a fourth
book listed and I couldn't find any information about it on the internet so I did what everyone
does which is I skated at the author to say oh what's going on and he said it's an
avilla-length book in the same world so there you go is that a scoop yeah it's quite exciting
I presume at some point is going to be announced and someone accidentally put it on the Amazon
listing Adrian right rather than skipp forget from Amazon well I found the name on Amazon because
someone had uploaded it to the listing so it's not like it's a secret but then I probably the only
person who's gone oh what's going on here doing so far so I am picking Time Stalker which is a
small indie movie it is written and directed on stars the comedian Alice Lowe and it's sort of a
comedy and it's got some funny bits which has also got some really not funny bits which is kind of
how comedy works these days I guess but I really really like to tell the premise of the movie is
that Alice Lowe has a absolutely disastrous obsession crush on someone that is so completely all
encompassing that she goes through Time repeatedly in order to declare her passion for this man who
is then completely oblivious and that bit is very funny and then she dies horribly so there's a bit
of gore in it Stephen was like I do not understand why this film is so gory but it is just cartoon
violence it's not very gory in the in the great scheme of things and I thought it had a lot of
very interesting things to say and this is made up on a budget of about 2.50 and it doesn't
entirely work but apart from that it's really really good and I liked it and would recommend it
and you will have to look quite hard to find it because we had to go to Hackney Pitch House to
see this film we could not see it in a Waltham state this was trailed before the substance when we
didn't see the substance and I have it has been on my list but it did leave all of the cinemas near us
before we could get to it but I'm a huge fan of Alice Lowe because she was in
Goveringay's Dark Place among other things horrible histories is the other thing and also
the film just looked absolutely mad so I was like very down it's absolutely bananas it's bananas yeah
because I came in and I was like this doesn't make any sense it also includes John's favourite
Mike Wozniak so you know John's excited about that who just might Wozniak play in this movie he plays
Dan I'm gonna suggest it's not a big role but yeah I want to see it very much and I will be excited
when it comes to streaming because as well as Alice Lowe going back and forth through history
several of the other characters do which is almost it's not immediately obvious whether that's a
deliberate artistic choice or whether it's much cheaper if all of your main characters take
several parts rather than having to recast in time but I think it is a bit of a bit of a
bit of a bit of a bit of a choice so there is so that sets up this question of whether Alice
is really going through time or if it is all in her head which it could be and there's kind of a
telling scene where she gets some therapy for this which is a fairly sensible therapy I think
and I it's a very strange movie I did like it a lot I'm gonna pick a role-playing game so I've been
playing in a campaign of a role-playing game called Roth and Glory which is a Warhammer 40,000 role-playing
game by Cubicle 7 Games and this is a D6 based system and it's very good and the reason I'm
gonna pick it is because it does something cool with its dice mechanic where you have a thing called
the Wrath Dice you basically in every time you roll you roll a number of D6s and you're looking
for basically successes on your D6s but the Wrath Dice if it rolls a six or a one something weird
happens or like something very bad or very good happens and I've seen this kind of mechanic before
in a role-playing game called Genesis which is the underpinning for the most recent Star Wars RPG
and I really like games that make you think about what's going on beyond the immediate
success or fail of the thing you've said you're doing and this system does that encourages you
to think about the wider context of your actions without needing like a bunch of specialist dice
and so yeah I've been enjoying it very much the other thing I quite like about this game is that
when you're going to combat you're basically paying miniature games of Warhammer 40,000 and
the people I'm playing with are very nerdy so they have all the little toy soldiers and I get to
move the round the map and I'm like I remember this from when I was an undergraduate it was very fun
I have no desire to go back into collecting Warhammer 40,000 on account of how I have to pay my mortgage
but yeah I'm very much enjoying playing this and and I would recommend it to any role players out
there especially role players who fancy some grim darkness yeah I hear what you're saying
there about little toy soldiers and it's a it's a hugely consuming hobby that people spend tens of
thousands of pounds on I'm always slightly amazed by it but I'm sure but the people who do it should
do it I'm sure they're having fun it's one of those things that seems expensive until you work
at how much time you're spending playing and then it seems a lot less expensive like board games
much more expensive than book and also I'm not sure some of them spend a lot of time playing but
a lot of them just spend a lot of time kind of painting and organizing and looking at their little
toy soldiers painting is also a hobby time spent painting is fun it is well an unless you hate
painting in which case it's not that was the art thought podcast and it's goodbye from me it's
goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
[Music]
recording in progress hey Alison how's it going I know sorry guys
not well so so I was basically sitting chatting away while I noticed and then suddenly I noticed
this weird slightly increasing pool of brown liquid yeah Liz Liz I think called it behind my
eye found did any get into a computer um I believe I have a I have a three pin British plug here
that just had some coffee spilled on it but I believe our plugs are very safe and I have
a plastic container that holds a battery and I don't think any will have got inside the plastic
containers to get all the battery because it's a it's a battery for a insta 360 and they're pretty
I mean it is this is a reminder that I should probably have tidied up this nest a bit better
but in fact it's fine the main the main problem is that my lovely lovely flat white from the lovely
lovely coffee shop is much reduced but it was it only got through a hole that size in the top of
my keep cup so the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud and
compotec.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
(silence)