Oh shit, hang on one more.
This is our normal level of organisation, Sandra, or maybe slightly better.
Er, it's all come out in the edits.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 98th episode of OctaThorp, a podcast for Science
Fiction and Science Fiction fandom, which is WENDING its way to you on the 7th of December
2023.
I'm John Coxon, I'm Alison Scott, and I am NOT Ms. Batty, and in her place you get
on this episode you get me Sandra Bond.
Hello Sandra Bond.
Hello Sandra, I'm very excited, what have you done with Liz?
Hah!
Erm, nothing Brad, why do you think I ought?
Yes, so Liz is on assignment, erm, I can't remember what she's doing, is she on holiday?
She's on a beach, she's on a beach.
She's doing something.
And so we have invited the lovely and talented Sandra Bond, who is the current TAF administrator
for Europe, and who has been on a TAF trip, and we're going to talk about that a little
bit later in the episode for shadowing.
But first we have some letters of comment, we have letters of comment from two TAF delegates
and one very knowledgeable man.
Not to imply that the TAF delegates are not knowledgeable, or indeed not men, for they
are.
So let's start with Christopher J. Garcia, who wrote in to say, "The first time that
fandom changed his life was meeting James Bacon."
And I think it's fair to say that everyone who's met James Bacon has had their life changed.
And he also says that we need more Hugo categories, which, erm...
Good Lord.
I respect his right to be wrong.
Isn't the ceremony long enough already?
He makes some good arguments about why it would be a good idea to have an indie film
Hugo, or a couple of indie film he goes, saying that it would be good to have more non-professional
he goes, and obviously I can see the logic in that.
But the problem with this Hugo is that we haven't really worked out what that would look like
and at the moment it just kind of gives extra Hugo's for things that are already getting
Hugo's, so.
Or also there is the problem that anything indie, is it any category of creativity, is
immediately taken over by the corporates who sort of will label it indie and put it out
under an indie studio or an indie record label's name, but in fact it's...
Or an indie brewery's name, or they'll buy an indie brewery.
I mean there's a lot of beer out there that used to be independent.
Cough cough, brew dog cough cough cough.
Oof.
Cough cough, little creatures, cough cough.
Cough cough, Camden brewery, cough cough.
Oh dear, there's a terrible cough going around this studio, isn't there?
Yes there is.
But we talked about Glasgow's asking policy last week.
No we didn't, did we?
But Glasgow haven't asked me policy now.
Yes, you can go and look at it.
There will be a link in the show notes.
Yes, Glasgow are getting docs in a row incredibly early by Worldcon standards, but more of this
when we come to talk about fanfons no doubt.
For shadowing.
Chris also says, still no stats from Chengdu, at this point I'm not surprised anymore, and
that is one of the most negative things I've ever heard Chris Garcia say.
Mark Plumber's written to us twice.
Mark Plumber has written to us twice.
Mark Plumber sent us a very lovely email about Lee's emails.
I failed you listeners because I did not put Lee's emails up on the internet anywhere because
I had to go to the train station that I posted up to talk and I ran out of time.
But rest assured I will put them up in full and Mark adds some more context about the
rotation policy.
Basically it starts in the early 1960s and Nastvik was introduced in 1975.
So he notes that the situation is more complicated than we made it seem.
John, they used a time machine.
Ah, they used a time machine.
Obviously 1965 was after Dr. Huard come around.
So time machines were plentiful and available.
And they used a time machine disguised as a Tiki Dialik which they'd picked up from
the 2014 London Wilcon.
And they used that in order to travel back in time and set the rotation.
So I think I'm reading Mark Plumber's right.
It all seems very wise to me.
It does seem very wise.
We are going to put the full, we just need to put some full text of our locks on the website
somewhere.
I don't know how we do that, but we'll work it out.
We should probably have a website.
Three years without a website.
What's to do guys?
Do we have to?
The Tiki Dialik, of course, made by friend of the show Kevin Roche and Andrew Tremblay.
I'm not sure they're actually friends of the show.
They may just be friends of us.
Um, well, what are our friends really?
I don't think they listen.
That seems to be drawing on rather a hairs, breaths distinction there.
I did.
I will just say Mark's letter did make me giggle quite a lot.
So, um, so thank you very much, Mark.
Mark did also write in.
He says he very much agrees with Liz's assessment.
This is why we're reading it out now so that Liz can't be too pleased with herself.
The experience of the Chengdu WorldCon might have been very different for overseas fans
and Chinese fans.
I'm going to quote from him.
"I've seen a couple of reports commenting that Chengdu was particularly international
worldcon, but I wonder whether that's really true."
I would guess proportionately at least it may have been the least international worldcon
in recent history and that more than usual percentage of the members were from the host
country.
And then notes that Dublin had about 30% of the attending membership that were not
from the USA, the UK or Ireland.
So that's actually, I hadn't really thought about it like that, but it is an interesting
point and I thought it was worth saying on the pot.
So thank you very much, Mark.
Yes.
So, I mean, I think by most international, the people who are reporting may just mean
the most people who don't obviously look like us, which is certainly true.
Mm.
Well, and there is, there is definitely, there's probably an argument that it's the most different
from any other worldcon in terms of the demographics.
Although I guess I would have to cross check with Nippon because I assume that that has
a claim.
Finland.
I don't know, quite a lot of American and British fans at Finland.
Well, quite.
Yeah, but there were an awful lot of Finns at Finland.
That was why they had to build new rooms.
That is true, there were a lot of Finns.
But were there more Chinese and Chengdu than there were Finns in Helsinki?
Yes, there were, there were an enormous number of Chinese in Chengdu, I believe.
They think that they've claimed to be the largest walk on ever.
Well, such was my impression, but what do I know?
I bought an egg.
I think you're a good egg.
Oh, God bless you, sir.
And then finally, we heard from Taffet delegate Kurt Phillips.
Kurt says that he thinks there are already too many hughos and he shares some of our concerns
about the goings-on at the business meetings in Chengdu.
He hopes that they get voted down at Glasgow.
But he did say that our book, Recommendation Sound Interesting, and he plans to pick up
a copy of Goliath and a copy of Moon.
He says, although he usually allows his ears to go numb whenever we talk about games.
So Kurt and Mark could have a little support group, it sounds like.
Something about my review of Moon broke through and since there is a gaming store where he
lives, he's going to go and see if they have it and see if someone there might play it
with him if they do.
So Kurt, report back.
Let us know how you found it.
We have heard through Securitous Roots that some people might have had trouble tracking
down Moon after the last episode and, hopefully, John put a link in the show notes to the
board game geek link for it so that you can see a lot more about it and probably where
to get it, they're not necessarily where to get it.
There is more than one game called Moon because it's one of those simple words.
Yes.
But there's only more website called board game geek so far as I'm aware.
So yes, and we have mentioned board game geek before, I'm sure, but it is the one many
times, many, many times.
One critical website for board gamers.
There's nothing like it.
It's like Ravelry for Ditters.
If you are still struggling to locate a copy then the websites boardgameprices.co.uk in
the UK and boardgameoracle.com in the USA are both basically websites that let you check
friendly local game stores for stock of games.
I will put links to the Moon listings on both those websites in the show notes.
We like them all for it is close to us.
And that was the let us a comment.
Thank you very much everyone who wrote in.
Oh, we should note Duncan McGregor also really enjoyed Titanium Noir.
I am going to read it, but, you know, when I find time.
But not least Dave Coxen posted on our Facebook to thank us for the birthday shout out.
He's still listening to every episode.
Even though his SF status is noob, he enjoys the discussions and debates about gaming books
and movies.
He may not fully appreciate all elements of the podcast, but he enjoys the debates and
how we articulate ourselves.
We're a well balanced panel.
The balancing is you just make sure that you're all the appropriate distance away from the
middle of the seesaw and then it goes well.
That was a joke about physics.
Yeah, sometimes I find that if I'm on a seesaw with somebody, sometimes it needs to be
quite a big seesaw.
That's the name of the episode.
Um, Okey-dokey.
Thanks to everyone who wrote in.
Hello, you are here to talk about TAF.
Hey, how?
For those listening who may not be aware, do you want to give us a very brief explanation
of what TAF might be?
With the greatest of pleasure job, yes, TAF stands for Transatlantic Fan Fund.
There are many fan funds and have been for a while, but TAF is the oldest of them all.
And it exists to send the European fan to North America or conversely a North American
fan to Europe in order to attend a convention.
Generally the Worldcon or Anista con, though I, as it happens, was the first ever delegate
not to attend a North American Worldcon because there wasn't one, see Chengdu in earlier discussions.
The point of the fan fund is that it is effectively it is crowdfunding, except that it's been
going since before crowdfunding was really a thing.
Kind fans donate their time, their money, their curios and their collectibles to it.
And they get some auction that conventions are online in order to raise them a dough.
And once that has been raised, then some lucky person gets to go and, you know, experience
fandom on the other side of the Atlantic.
And this year, that was me.
Well, wait.
And you went to Pemicon if I'm not much mistaken.
I did.
And you've done well with that, so don't, don't, don't, don't indulge in figures of speech.
And does this, does this marvelous prize come with any form of a downside, Sandra?
I don't know what that depends on whether you enjoy the, the, the admittest trivia of
having to run the thing after you get back home.
I am starting to take up the reins of running it.
This has its good points and its bad points, but we will see what happens now that things
are getting, you know, getting underway again and it's because next year in 2024, the transatlantic
fan fund is expecting to send the North American fan to the Glasgow Worldcon.
Cheers, cheers, cheers.
Yeah, I shall be in charge of the European end of trying to make sure that that happens
without any snags.
I'm sure it will go swimmingly.
Glasgow are fans of the fan funds, as it were.
They're, they're kind of right thinking sort of folks.
So very much so.
And in fact, Glasgow has appointed a fan funds coordinator.
Indeed, they have.
Who is the very lovely Jerry Sullivan.
I'm going to be talking to Jerry on, on behalf of Guff with Sandra for TAF and I guess other
people who are interested in the fan funds.
And we're going to be setting up, starting to talk about what Glasgow is going to do for
fan funds.
There will also be, as well as the, although TAF has, has announced their race, I'm hoping
Guff will have announced its race by the time we, by the time this episode comes out,
but it might not quite have, but very soon, Guff will also be announcing that there's going
to be a race from Australia, New Zealand or, or islands in that area to, to Glasgow for
the, for the 2024 Worldcon.
Yeah.
And I do want to say that the Glasgow committee have been exemplary in their support.
As Alison says, they've appointed a fan fund liaison to try and make sure that the TAF
and Guff winners, you know, everything goes smoothly for them.
They've also confirmed, you know, hospitality and, you know, hotel arrangements, etc, which
in my understanding this early in the game is almost unheard of.
So Bravo Glasgow, I say.
Thank you very much, Glasgow.
You're excellent.
It's quite the coincidence that both fan funds are sending delegates to the same convention.
That's a happy accident.
Well, I mean, not really given that that convention is a European Worldcon.
Well, it's exactly so.
I think we have done that every time.
I mean, maybe not every time, but certainly for Dublin and Helsinki and Lancome and my
memory of fan funds doesn't really go back further than that.
Yeah.
Every now and again, things have to be tweaked very slightly to make that work.
For instance, there was no fan truck, no TAF race in 1978 because they wanted to save
it from 1979 to send a American fan to the Brighton Worldcon.
That's indeed they did.
And it was the late Terry Hughes.
Where Taf is concerned, there tend to be two different kinds of race.
Either you get a ton of people all clamoring to stand and having to vote against each other,
or you get tumble beads blowing around and then the administrator has to go around poking
at people with a stick saying, you want to stand, don't you?
The fact that it is going to a Worldcon rather than an Eastercon next year, I hope, will make
it more likely to be the first kind of race than the second as far as I'm concerned as
admin because it makes life a lot easier if the candidates come out of the bush themselves
and stand rather than having to be chased up.
Yeah, that makes sense.
You mentioned Jerry Sullivan was the fan fund.
What was the title?
He said, "fan fund coordinator?"
That's what I believe her role is titled, yes.
Jerry, of course, is a former Taf winner herself.
And I believe she is about to relaunch her fanzine idea and it's going to have a very
special feature in it.
Yes, Jerry has not published a fanzine for over 20 years, but she has now taken up that
gauntlet once again and is as we're recording the release of the new issue of idea is supposedly
imminent.
Oh, and the very special feature.
And the very special feature, if you can so call it, you flattera, is that it's got
the first chapter of my Taf report in.
One thing about fanfolds is that it is generally considered the done thing for a delegate after
they've got home and had a reasonable time to recover.
That they will write up a trip report of everything that they did and saw and engaged in that's
actually printable.
Hm, hm, hm.
Hollow laugh there from John.
Definitely don't want a report of everything you didn't saw on a trip report.
Yeah, indeed.
Indeed.
So, yeah, there are some bits that need avail drawn over them for the sake of modesty or
simple kindness.
But on the whole, yes.
More often than not, you know, the report will get written either in one lump or in
several serialised ones.
I have taken the latter approach to it on the grounds that fandom nowadays is such an
enormous and diverse community that by serialising it across different places, it has a larger
chance, at least one episode will come to the attention of more fans than if I just
put out one booklet.
Hm, yeah, that makes sense.
Jerry is actually the fanfolds liaison.
Oh.
I thought you meant that the very special feature was the article that I've got on in
idea.
Ha ha!
Well, I mean, it's an exercise left for the reader as to…
It's the article about how I met Stephen that I think Joel's already seen.
Oh, it's a very good article.
It's been to a few places because I kind of snuck it out bit by bit rather than kind
of give it to a fancy edge straight away.
I want it on the record that there is a line in that article where you note that it passes
two to one with one abstention and I think I was the one.
So when you read it…
I think you might have been.
Note that listeners, note that.
But Sandra has very kindly agreed to take us through part of the chapter which is to do
with her time in Canada.
Yes, I should perhaps also have clarified that I'm not writing this in order because
Jerry was my first host when I arrived in North America and if I'd written it in chronological
order I would have ended up writing a chapter largely about Jerry Sullivan before Jerry Sullivan
and that seemed a little awkward.
So I've started off by jumping forwards and writing up to Pemikon and Alison, I had no
idea I'm afraid, this has come out of left field to me that you have a piece in idea.
I look forward to reading it but I bet you anybody in my pieces longer than yours.
Yes, how long is your piece?
I don't know how long my piece is.
I mean my piece is about six hours long.
Yeah, the official length of my piece is too long.
But yes, the piece I'm going to be reading out on this here, a very episode of Octo
4, what it is, is basically deals with the day after I left Pemikon.
Don't doubt.
I don't actually know the answer to this question which is dreadfully bad form as an
interviewer.
You're supposed to know the answers wherever a question you ask, right?
So are you planning to do a compiled version of the report after it's kind of been published
elsewhere?
So Luke, I am, yes.
I think people who do serialize their reports and then actually get it finished do tend
to then produce a one-volume edition afterwards.
But obviously enough, that is a debothor of future occasion.
At the moment, I have various people who have asked me for an instalment and I've said yes
to them all.
Ulrich O'Brien, Nick Farrey, Mark Plummer and Claire Brierly are getting won because
Banana Wings is coming out again regularly, they say.
Hooray, hooray.
Oh, it's possible that Claire will be listening to this episode on Thursday because she's
going to be at in-hospital having a little day operation that day.
So we should wish her all lots of, said lots of love in case she's listening or Mark is
listening and hope everything goes well.
Yes.
Absolutely.
Octo thought, you know, wishes you, you know, the swiftest and quick and most pointless
recovery possible.
Yes it does.
So if you enjoy what Sandra reads, you can look up her full TAF report and when that
comes out we will, indubitably, talk about it on the podcast.
And in the meantime, you can buy her novels which are very good.
Yes, The Devil's Finger and The Psychopath Club, both excellent books, go and buy them.
Thank you, thank you, thank you.
Yes, The Psychopath Club is a former pick of the episode on Octo 4.
Yes, so Sandra, take us through the world of post-Pemicon.
So Octo 4, listen as I present to you, chapter 6, part 1 of my TAF report, whose overall
title is Her Beautiful Mistake.
And this chapter's title is Moose Hats and Medicine Jaws and it deals with the 24th of
July 2023.
Excellent.
I think crayons such as my belongings, into my various bad cases and containers as I could.
One small case, one large case, one very small case with CPAP machine, one cardboard box with
unsalted TAF auction donations from Gary Farber, one tote bad with various goodies from Joyce
Scribner and Diversicott.
I headed downstairs.
There is an air of sadness, emptiness that hangs around a hotel which has just finished
toasted the convention.
Revenism to the odour from a pile of bobbitties, some spot that is unseen, it is too near
the comfort.
That air assaulted my nostrils and other senses as I reached the hot lobby.
Guests and fish, they say, become obnoxious after three days, so to do conventions.
Pemicon was no more and the constituent parts of it were beginning their diaspora to all
part of the compass.
Some of them were still around.
I finally found Kurt Gibson again and apologised for not having seen him at Alice during the
con after that, after their kindness in driving me up there.
He had it transpired seeing me, but since he hadn't stepped out in front of me like
a traffic cop to stop me and since I've been wandering about in a day as I generally do
at any convention, we've missed our opportunity, alas.
Marie Moore and Darth Spencer, who had done so much to make the con bearable for me, were
knocking about two and oh joy there were luggage trolleys a plenty to be had in stark contrast
to the beginning of the con.
I conveyed my bags to the front door and happily found that the taxi rank, not being organised
by Pemicon, actually had taxis in it.
I'd almost forgotten that things in Willy-Pecard workers they were intended to.
I gave the driver the address of the rental car joint to the airport, sat back to watch
the scenery pass by.
After planning my trip, I'd reasoned that by the time Pemicon ended, I would probably
be ready for a few days break from having to deal with other people in any quantity
at a time or for long periods.
Safe perhaps for the written word format, behind the wheel of a vehicle is the place
I feel most secure, content and free.
I can assign the driving to the part of my brain that deals with medial tasks and free
up the part concerned with higher functions, to enjoying the scenery, plotting my writing
or wild speculation on the nature of the universe.
And I'd found that one way vehicle rentals no longer appeared to carry the financial penalty
that I was used to being attached, before Covid had given the rental car business a
kicking.
So, my plans allowed me three days to drive to British Columbia, play tourist and kickback
before flying from Calgary to Las Vegas and once more, lunging into the swells of Spanish
partying.
People, the most insistent of them being far a mentalist, than whom few do insistant better.
Had heard me that if I was in the western parts of Canada, I should upon no account
this the Royal Tunnel Museum in Drumheller, home to countless dinosaur fossils and related
attractions.
And I decided to make that my next point of call.
Sure, I could have flown in far less time, but where, I asked an imaginary interlocutor,
was the funny in that.
The car was applied without hitch, luggage loaded aboard and the westward road, the trans-Canada
highway, indeed, beckoned.
I missed a turn on my way out, but little did I care, especially since in finding my way
back to the TCH.
I discovered that Winnipeg boasts a suburb named Toxedo.
It was wonderful, I was free.
I passed across the psychological barrier of Winnipeg's ring road and pulled my chariot
into a truck stop not far beyond in head English.
Over breakfast at the Denny's, I didn't know they had those in Canada, I used their
Wi-Fi to plan my day.
Drumheller, as I already knew, was certainly not achievable in one day.
I traced the TCH with my finger across the map.
Originally I planned to spend the night in or around the ginour, but all the hotels there
were either unreasonably expensive or got vile reviews on TripAdvisor.
And I got off to my, got off to such an efficient early start, but time for once was on my
side.
I let my finger wander on westward.
After Regina, everywhere was smaller, yet with longer names as though they sought to
make up for their signs of an extra-mentature.
Bell claims, moose jaw, swift current, gunnal ache, maple creek, medicine hat.
Thinking of future me writing this report, I decided that the writing at place with a
silly name was just what was called for.
I checked my watch.
Yes, moose jaw looked just about right.
Recent hotels, affordable rates, craft beer bars with positive write-ups, and I had a
book back home called Beauty Tips for Moose Jaw by Will Ferguson that I had enjoyed.
And furthermore, I ought to just about be able to make it there on the full tank of
gas that had put me with my rental.
I finished breakfast and was itching to be back on the road.
I hastily pulled out my credit card, hit backspace a few times in my browser to reach a hotel
I thought looked promising, and booked a room for one night.
My heart was featherlight now as I strode out of the denny's and hit the road once more.
I'd been warned that between Winnipeg and British Columbia there was a whole lot of
flack-waffy.
I didn't care.
All around me, the Horizons did their best to surrender their claim on the name and retreat
out of sight.
The few other cars on the road bore my sense plates in ornate script.
We should first I read as 'Finally, Manitoba' before I finally figured them to be 'Friendly
Manitoba'.
The divided highway stretched on ahead, reaching out for the elusive horizon, never quite touching
it.
For the sheer hell of it, I stuck to the old road rather than taking the bypass around
my first silly long name of the day.
Portage luxury.
No need to stop.
I had road slats and energy drinks from the truckstopper headingly.
The road bore the epithet.
'Manitobas, highway of heroes'.
I felt like a hero myself, and I felt happy.
Britain's roads were crowding, twisted and confining.
Manitobas are a joy.
A comfort break at Kirkheller, and I was across the border into Saskatumon.
If Saskatumon isn't a swear word, it ought to be Bill Watterson.
The boundary made no appreciable deference to the road or to the scenery.
A sandwich for lunch from a gas station at Whitewood, onward, onward, west-west, west.
'Near Capell, something shut across my vision.
I dapped the brakes by instinct before realizing it was.
I could hardly believe they had the solids.
An actual, lots of tumbleweed.
I took the bypass around the China to the south.
Like Croydon, they built three quarters of a ring road and then given up before completing
the final 25%.
To my rise, the city's tall buildings, loomed like a child's building blocks and conquer
us in the prairie flatness.
Not far now to moose jaw.
A pair of eyes met mine from the short grass at the roadside.
'Fox,' I thought for a second.
But the colour was all wrong.
A moment's hasty thought made me provide my opinion to 'wolf'.
No, surely not.
Not so close to the road and not alone.
Also, its features were leaner and more anguier than a wolf.
It's no longer a coyote.
I'd seen an actual honest to God coyote in the wild.
Could it be long before I spied a roadrunner?
The main highway, skirt, passed moose jaw at an oblique angle.
I veered left onto the old main road and down into moose jaw.
Everything around me was a small town suburb and neat and pretty at first.
Closer to the centre of town, I was reminded of certain small towns about this far west
in the USA.
Venerable, weather but still sturdy brick buildings, housing some old businesses but more newer
ones.
A huge expanse of railroad side is spread across my leftward vision.
I drifted from street to street.
I'dly looking for a parking spot.
I was in no hurry.
I was relaxed.
Everything was good.
I congratulated past me on having made such wide choices.
A bar hoe to sight on one side.
Rosie's on the river street.
Hey, I'd seen that on my tablet back in Manitoba.
It got good trip adviser reviews.
And indeed it had an attractive air with plenty of tables outside and people tucking
into meals at them.
I found a parking lot that would become free in ten minutes.
I could have paid or chanced it but again I was in no rush.
I waited for the clock to tip to the end of pay parking and stroll back up the street
to Rosie's.
I wanted a beer and a beer deal and unhorriedly enjoyed them both at an outside table, watching
moose JVians pass by and admiring the local architecture.
I was tempted to order a second beer from their class of redesigned pint glasses but
providing a sell but I still needed to find a hotel before I could stop driving for the
evening.
I could walk his walk back after I checked in, right?
For shattering.
I pulled out my tablet to check the address of my hotel and nearly spat out a wasteful
mouthful of that excellent beer.
I had, in a moment of inattention, booked myself into a hotel, not in moose JVian, but in
medicine had 250 miles away.
Four hours per the westward and it was already past seven o'clock in the evening.
Oh no.
The sip of beer I hadn't spat out suddenly tasted flat and sour in my mouth and at that
point I shall break off this extract.
No.
But what happens now Sandra?
Oh no but what happens?
We don't know what happens.
It's a cliffhanger.
Leave me sitting there in moose, you're on a cliffhanger.
So find out what happens next.
You will have to read the next bit of my report.
Ah, well fair enough.
You know how to leave them wanting more.
Choose your own adventure.
So yes that was great.
Thank you very much.
Yeah no very good.
We'll wait till we hear the next.
So the next, where are you publishing this extract?
Where should we expect to see it?
The full chapter of which you've just heard an extract, this has not quite been analysed
but definitely yet but I would be going to appear in the fanzine beam from Nick Farrie
and Ulrich O'Brien.
If he doesn't appear there then they are so big to get a chapter but I'm expecting that
this will be this one.
Fair enough.
Excellent.
But if you want to keep up to date with anything to do with the Transatlantic Fan Fund
or my report or anything else that's appitates to it, go to TAF.org.
.uk and you will find everything that you need to know and probably some stuff that
you didn't.
How's it good we're putting it?
TAF.org.uk is presumably run by Mr Langford.
Indeed Dave Langford is one of long term heroes.
He was the TAF winner in 1980.
Is that right?
A long, long time ago.
The Galaxy far, far away.
I can still remember when that music...
Yes, but we have.
He has been doing great things for TAF.
He has on that site, many of them written by Rob Hansen a few of them not.
Yes, there are lots and lots of really excellent books and actually a few rubbish ones but
you know, you can't have everything can you?
No, lots of extremely good, fan-ish content there. Some of the very best collections of
fandom anywhere are available for free download in exchange for a donation to TAF.
Yes, and Sandra was indeed correct.
Dave Langford did indeed win TAF in 1980.
I will also mention whilst we're talking about the chat that his trip report, which is the
TAF transatlantic hearing aid, is one of the absolute paragons of the genre and it's
one to which I had frequent reference when planning mine.
I will not set myself up as being able to write half as wittliest Dave but in my own
little way I'm trying.
Very trying.
The oldies are the goodies.
Excellent stuff. Thank you very much for reading out and I will look forward to appearing
in Beam.
Do we want to have a chat about fanfums generally and I guess the big question is why are fanfums
still relevant here in 2023?
We can get on zoom and chat to people all over the world.
We have hundreds or thousands of people attending conventions across the Atlantic.
Why is it still a good idea to have a fanfund?
Well, I can give you an answer whether it's the answer I don't know.
I think there are as with most things in fandom there are several interlocking causes and
reasons.
But fanfums have been going, as I mentioned earlier, for a long, long time, for longer
than any of us have been in fandom.
That's the saying goes, once something's been done twice in fandom it's a tradition.
So after something's been done in fandom for 50 times, well, it's absolutely graven in
snow, isn't it?
I do think that this is partly being flippant but I do think there is also the aspect that
nobody wants to be the administrator who says, well, isn't it about time that we wrap this
up because everyone who wants to have won this fund has already won it.
I don't think that's the case at all, just to clarify.
Yeah, I think from my part, my answer is that as long as people want to stand and as long
as people want to vote, then it'll keep going.
And in some ways I think the question of why is almost a bit by the bike because I'm
not interested in telling people they've got to stop.
I mean, I don't think they should stop.
I think it's good that they do it.
But even if you don't, they're going to do it anyway.
Fansons, I'm speaking here for TAF in particular, which, you know, because it's the one that
I, you know, had the one who I'm currently trying to juggle things for, go back to the
time when transatlantic travel was not just the sort of thing you could just whip out
a credit card and book a flight.
The first two TAF delegates travelled by ocean ship and not talking at sort of luxury crews
here.
We're talking, you know, they sort of sprung into a cabin on a sort of tramp steamer type
thing and got across on the cheap.
Yeah.
Fund them around the world, you know, used to be almost entirely conducted by mail between
North America and Europe and Europe and Australia and Australia and North America.
And obviously there was a great deal of enthusiasm back in the early days for members of one
fandom to meet representative members of another.
And I do think that is still the case.
Even though, you know, it's so much easier to make a trip onto your own steam these days,
there is still something about being a TAF delegate or a Gough delegate or any, yeah, any
fan fund delegate where it's not just an honor, but you, but it also means you get to represent
the fandom that you've come from and you get to tell people about it in convention programming
and social belier and it helps to bind fandom closer together.
And obviously, fandom is a great deal, larger and more disparate and diverse now than it
was in the earliest days of fan funds.
But, you know, it's like the app that's had two new heads and three new handles.
It's still fandom.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's fair.
Very much so.
That's a good way of putting it.
I think it does help to bring fandom together.
I certainly did a lot of zooms in 2020 that had a lot of fans from both Europe and Australia
at them.
And these people hadn't met before though.
There were often people that they had contacted online and they knew the names of, but they
were seeing on Zoom for the first time.
When I went out, obviously, I met a lot of people for the first time, including many people
that had just been legends to me like, like Robert Johnson and Lee Evans, who's now a
correspondent throughout the book, of course.
But also in at least one city, I organized gatherings and there were people there who
didn't know each other because I'd just kind of reached out to everyone I knew in that
city and some of them, they weren't necessarily moving in the same bits of fandom.
They were all people I happen to know from all the various different things that I've
done.
So, I mean, I think it's just, it's one of the things that basically says, in a very public
way, fandom is a community and this is these trips are one of the ways that we celebrate
the fact that it's a global community of people.
It is not just about adulating the people who are writing books and making TV shows,
it is also about getting together with other fans because those people are interesting
in their own right.
Yeah.
And by the same token, Alison, you know, @Pemicon, which you'll be able to read in the chapter
in idea, I met a couple of people from Las Vegas who were grumbling that they didn't know
with any other fans in Las Vegas.
Wow.
Oh, I said, have you spoken to the right person, I said, in another week's time, those two
were invited to an attended the TAF party in Las Vegas and met all the Las Vegas fans
that I already knew.
TAFs and other fans do still serve to introduce people who ought to know each other but somehow
haven't met yet.
This is why Spaniel and I have started the Newcastle First Thursday group because I think
this is one of the things that in-person meetings still do best.
Even locally is there's a chap who has started coming to that called Andy.
Hello, Andy, if you're listening.
And you know, he doesn't know anyone else who would be up for going to a convention.
Like he knows other science fiction nerds but they're not particularly fussed about the
idea of going to a con but now he knows us all and a lot of us go to cons.
If he goes to a con he'll have people there he recognizes because I think going to a convention
where you know you'll know literally no one is very daunting or going to a gathering where
you know where you know you will know literally no one but trying to do those smaller more
low key gatherings is a good way of trying to overcome that I think.
So I think there's a lot here as it were.
But the thing about so much of fandom happening in an online or a virtual environment these
days is that it is actually possible in a way that it was a lot harder to be in the past
to be in a city or an urban area where there are all of other fancies but you just don't
happen ever to have come across them.
Yeah, yeah, baby up.
And yeah and all three of us who obviously have all been cast or current fan fund delegates
you know we've all just given our own examples of this kind of thing.
So yes fan funds are one of the specimens of glue that helps to bind fandom together.
Like the poly cement of fandom.
Basically hanging out with people is good.
Shall we do pics?
Oddly enough.
Yeah, I dropped a hint earlier that TAF has amongst its many attractions on TAF.org.uk
a slew of e-books which you can download in return for a donation.
The newest one of these is going to be my pick for the episode.
It is called Beyond fandom.
Films, culture and politics in the 20th century edited by Rob Hanson for it is he.
Now I must say that that subtitle makes it sad to be an academic book which I think does
it know favours.
But on the other hand, yeah it does pretty much sum up.
Basically what Rob has done in this book is taken over two dozen fans from the earliest
days of fandom up until the turn of the current century.
All of whom became famous for something other than what you might expect a science fiction
fan to become famous for.
So for instance Michael Moorcock and Robert Silverberg aren't in the book because tons
of fans have become professional science fiction writers after having started off in
fandom.
But what he has dog up are people who've achieved fame outside this.
So there's one of America's leading jazz journalists.
There was the editor and publisher of America's first ever lesbian magazine.
There was the guy who founded the newspaper Mersey Beat which had John Lennon writing a
column for it immediately before the Beatles suddenly became worldwide famous.
The founders of C&D, the musicians, the music mogul, the guy who promoted early comic bands,
the Pope's astronomer.
Did you know that the Pope's astronomer was a science fiction fan?
Well I've had dinner with him.
Oh wow listen you've always got to wallop be havin' you.
But I mean but brother guy does come to conventions you should keep an eye out for him at them.
He's very entertaining and interesting.
But yes but yeah this book Rob has written large chunks of it.
There are also as often with Rob's books fairly hefty chunks from period forces to prove that
this is actually here what was written about it at the time.
It's in 31 different chapters so it's the sort of book you dip in and out of at the
measure and that is my pick for the episodes recommendation.
Lovely stuff.
I shall have to look out for that.
So the three books is generally a very good thing, there are so many things on there that
it can be a bit daunting so it's good to have a sort of window or a way in that's a bit
more accessible than just the entire wall of titles.
Alison do you want to do your pick?
Yes so my pick I don't think I have been, so people have been saying to me for approximately
four seasons now Alison you really should be watching For All Mankind because it is
right up your street and I've been going oh yes I'm going to get round to it and I have
now got round to it and for those people who have been watching the glacial pace at which
we watched the expanse I should say that on current viewing speed we are going to catch
up with the latest episode of For All Mankind in less than a week.
So it clearly is hitting a nerve for me.
I'm one of these people who thinks that historical dramas about space exploration are not science
fictioners should not appear on science fiction award ballots but this is an alt historical
drama about space travelers so it's completely fine it is obviously science fiction and it
is for people who don't know an alternative history where as a result of a change this
happens in the mid 60s the Soviet space program is just a little bit more effective than it
was in reality and as a result of that the space race continues with some verb much for
much longer than it did in our timeline and the creator Ron Moore is the was the creator
of Bratislav Galactica the reboot and he read an interview with him where or listen to an
interview with him where he said that people of his sort of age which is also my sort of
age because we are very nearly the same age have an existential tragedy in our lives this
is nerds of our age in that we grew up believing that there was going to be a massive space
exploration program and that we were just witnessing the start of it and that it didn't
happen so this is really a television show about what might happen if that tragedy had
been averted and a space program does happen and obviously there's quite a lot of other
stuff going on in the show it is not merely a space exploration show every time you read
a Reddit thread about this show there are people there going this would be a much better show
if they cut out all the messy people stuff and just had the space stuff and the space danger
we like space danger that is what we watch for and there is plenty of space danger but there's
also a lot of ordinary drama plots some of which are ramped up quite a lot so they are
they tend to be very high stakes drama and it feels a bit like extremely excessive soap opera
sometimes that you see that is that a or tone of allers that a development happens and you go
well that is absolutely bananas that you know in order for that to happen so many people have
to have done things that are very stupid and like any television show the writing is not always
in some episodes the writing is absolutely acting and everything is absolutely first rated in
other episodes you go oh they kind of didn't quite deliver enough to let us believe that moment so
it is not perfect but it is generally amazing and I'm absolutely loving it it's like catnip for me
I love all the there's a point very early on where there's Apollo 11 and and you realize that
this is an alternative history they might not land safely and you go oh oh wait you know he
may be about to kill them all off gosh you you intrigued me Allison you know I never watch anything
on television oh it's great yeah in part because I have sort of agnosia which makes it rather
awkward for me to keep track of which character is which but you actually you know made this sound
so interesting but I may have to give you to go if any if any if if Allison says that something has
verb then verb in jolly well has is my experience it has it also has time skips so the first series
starts in 1969 and carries on to I think about 1974 and then the second series skips forward to
about 1995 and then the third series is the early 80s so you see he's kind of catching up in the
same way as I'm catching up with his show so and I have watched always the end of season three as
season three's finale was shocking but then so was season two's finale season one's finale so you
know you keep going well how are they gonna top this and as I said sometimes it's sometimes it's
over the top so sometimes it does go it it has moments that's strange credulity hang on science
fiction where credulity is strained that seems very unlikely but it's funny because my just
my disbelief suspenders never snap when they're kind of exploring or whatever but they do snap
when it's kind of and here is the way that this relationship between these two people has progressed
and I'm like oh no that doesn't make any sense I mean I would say I think so I do think there is
a common misconception that relationships between people make sense because I do often see people
complaining about things and I'm like I have relationships in my life that make less sense to that
yes no well indeed and I think one of the things that this show makes me think about is that most of
us have experiences in our past that could have been absolutely catastrophic for one reason or
another and because we were probably lucky they weren't or you know they were really somewhat yeah
and one of the things that happens to this show is that some things that are the sorts of things
that people actually do in real life quite often they just kind of explore the natural consequences
of that and its cat and because Ron Moore designed the entire series before he started he went to
Apple and said give me a ton of money and I'll make you some six seasons maybe seven you know
and he's got a plan and so we've just got to the end of season three and there is something that
has happened at the end of season three in this final episode and it's like oh that's why that
character had that name and you go so at the point where they were designing the show and casting
people they've clearly got this beat in the show planned in three seasons down the line where they
were going to go oh right and this is a parrot because this is an alternate universe parallel with
something that happened in our timeline so they weren't all just making it up as they went along
indeed but to an amazing degree and that and even even good television actually doesn't often do
this as well as it ought to do so and the other point I wanted to say about it is it's on Apple TV
plus I know I keep saying this I've been saying for god knows how many episodes that Apple TV
plus is a five or a month it turns out it's not it's 8.99 sorry guys apparently apparently inflation
happened and prices went up when I wasn't looking no it's a very good show I have I'm behind
because I find it very difficult to watch but it is very good and I do enjoy it it is it is petrified
I mean bits of it are real behind the sofa stuff um happy anniversary dr who yes behind the
behind the sofa stuff for grownups yes that actually the seed I'm mostly thinking of that I really
wanted to be able to turn the TV off and not watch was set on earth didn't involve any spacecraft
I am going to not I'm gonna I'm gonna spin off something you said in your or you you don't think
historical drama about space travel is science fiction or you you say it's not
fanny and I have been recently talking about this and I think that space travel is so wrapped up in
the history of the genre that it kind of got grandfathered in in that it doesn't really make any sense
that people consider it part of the genre but it very definitely still feels like it is
well do you remember john or the kafuffel when Apollo 13 came out and people kept trying to
nominate it for for the awards and so the science in the science fiction genre and people and
other people were saying but it's not science fiction it's a documentary and like I say I mean
I can see the point but equally I can see the point but equally I do think that space travel did
eventually get sort of grandfathered into the genre because it is so so wrapped up with the early
early science fiction all this to say that my pick is a city on Mars by Kelly and Zach Wienerschmith
if you've heard of Zach Wienersmith he is the person who draws Saturday morning breakfast cereal
which is a webcomic and Kelly is his wife and is a noted bacteriologist I think a biologist of
some description if Liz was here should be annoyed that I don't know but she's not so I can run free
and they've written a book about space settlement and it is it is absolutely excellent and I will be
probably nominating it in best related work because it is a very good look at what it would take to
get to the sort of future that for instance for all mankind is positing and exploring some of
the issues with that partly the issues in terms of like the physics but also issues
that are a bit more esoteric and perhaps aren't quite as well considered by the sort of space nerd
that tends to talk about these things for instance the I mean starting with the biology of it all
but then moving on to things like the considerations of international space law and how that would
affect these things and it's just really really interesting and I really loved it so I devoured it
and I would highly recommend it to anyone with an interest in in you know our future in the stars
well possibly you know put it back there of put your copy up for sales the Taff and
written that you know it's because it advertised as being having John Cox's genuine back marks
you desire it yeah no I'm happy to buy to book and then put it on to put it on sale
but it does mean that if I ever die there's like a record all my teeth look like so that's
probably useful don't you go to the dentist regularly well yeah but I don't know if they know what my
teeth look like do you think they've made a model yeah teeth teeth are like a light bullet
every every one fingerprints everyone has their own unique you know bite mark indeed indeed yes
can I can I can I can I can I jump one more small piece in and before we wrap everything up
this is something that I've been reminded of by total happenstance because somebody has just
post-poked I'll name him it's Nigel Rose just posted about it the very very first British
transatlantic fan for the winner was a fan called Vince Clark he he was the winner in 1954
unfortunately he lost his job at a crucial time and because the fan from was only very new
that meant he come before to go and Vince never made it to America
in 1987 Vince was one of the first fans I met when I was when I discovered found them
and did more than any other fans probably to make sure that I actually stayed around
I think it's fair to say that without him I wouldn't be sitting here doing this recording with you today
and that's it happens today marks the 25th anniversary to the day of Vince's death
and I just want to say I don't know what Vince was made of the whole concept of the podcast
but I you know I think it's entirely in keeping that you know that we give the man a mention he
was the loveliest man ever I I would second that and in fact when I did my very first fanzine
which was the sort of rather pathetic krodsine that that people do when they do their very first
fanzine before we started doing plotter Vince wrote me an extremely lovely letter saying how
much he'd enjoyed it which I took which greatly encouraged me at the time but of course a long time
later I could go well I'm actually Vince was very good at I'd say that to all of the new
fanlets and I'm sure that he would be equally enthusiastic about about podcasts and other
modern things of fandom because he was indeed a very very lovely person
it's very very grateful for that letter which did indeed encourage me to do fanzines
yeah thanks for letting me jam that in Alison and John 25 years I know he doesn't seem possible
time in it times we can get to chariot yada yada one day you'll have somebody older than me on the
podcast if there are any left but today is not that day I'm not that much younger than you
I don't think you're that much younger than me but I think you are younger than me to be fair
I think next time we record we'll have someone older than you on the pod
what me you mean me yeah yeah because you'll be older oh thank you Sean that's helpful
is that good you're all about you've ever been and now you're even all
we can't clear the rights under a stop singing uh um right that was the octa thought podcast
and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
thank you very much indeed sardre you've been a great stunt list did we actually say stunt
laser teddy point now we just plowed straight on
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in comfatec.com
used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license right this podcast will end at the beak
(beep)