[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome to a very special episode of Octothorpe, the podcast for
science fiction and science fiction fandom which is coming to you at some point in the future.
I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty. Today we are talking about um
Grass by Sherry Tepper which is a 1989 novel that was a hugo finalist.
This is the third of the three books where we picked one each and talked about them so if you
want to go and check the other ones they were A Face Like Glass by Fraszadein which Liz picked
and Six Wakes by Merlaffity which John picked and I knew when we were picking this I wanted to
pick an older book and one that should be influential on me. I think Tepper was an
influential on me her corpus of work rather than this book in particular but this book is widely
considered to be her best novel and I remember thinking it was very good when I read it but
because I have a terrible memory I remembered very little about it so I was very glad to revisit it.
This is a novel about um we are in a universe where Earth has expanded and colonized a bunch
of planets. The Earth is being run by a religious patriarchy that is inducted to
Mormonism and that is the model of living that they want to impart to the universe.
We, an novel starts on the planet Grass which is what it is about um this planet is entirely
covered with strange grass and we learn a little bit. We learn that um there's a hunt that is a key
factor of life on this planet for the aristocracy there and that the hunt is not like earth hunts
different things are going on and we discover that the earth-based um empire is being has a mysterious
plague and a lead character and her family are shuffled off to grass to see what is going on
because grass uniquely does not appear to have anyone who suffers from this plague and they are
chosen for the trip because the they don't know very much about grass but they know that people hunt
there and um uh heroine is an Olympic equestrian um champion who is also who is also aristocratic
so they think that she will fit it right in spoiler not so much. Is that is that a fairly good start?
I think that's a reasonable start. I always say the other reason they're sent is because um her
husband is related to the person running the religious sect on earth. They are not members of the
the controlling religious sect. They are old Catholics um but the but her husband is the nephew
of the higher art. I didn't I don't know how important it is you mentioned Mormonism I did not
think about Mormonism once when reading the novel. Is that an important thing? I don't know
okay it's it's relevant that one of the things that the does Mormonism take genetics samples from
all their followers? No it just it's the genealogy thing this is just an extension of the genealogy
thing this is like do you think the Mormon church might be interested in um in having a complete
genome for everybody on earth and I think they might you know. So I I didn't really know too
as much I mean I didn't really think about it that much I guess but I didn't it wasn't screaming
out to me Mormonism but I guess um there is some part of Mormon doctrine which is about the genealogy
and the listing everyone so that they can be part of their part of their kind of temple
and that you can baptize and you can baptize people who have died in order that they can be
you know enter into the kingdom of God. In 2008 the Vatican issued a statement calling
the practice known as baptism for the dead erroneous and directing Catholic diocese to keep parish
records from Latter-day Saints I did not know that there enough did you not know that the Mormons
did this I know why would I I don't pay any attention to Mormons at all this is your one of
today's ten thousand but for bad things hmm I will never forget it quickly and there's also
it turns out the Mormon Geem-Nome project having just quickly Googled so yeah they are in fact doing
exact they would quite like to do exactly what what's is done in this book they just aren't yet
that's a total side note maybe we should talk about the book more before we talk about Mormonism
yes I think Alison should tell us why she picked it but anyway I thought that John and Liz would
like this book or at least find it an interesting book to read that helped helped them learn something
about the way that science fiction was in the late 80s. Here's this book representative of what
science fiction was like in the late 80s. No it was radical and wild in the late 80s
it's representative of what jolly good science fiction was like in the late 80s.
One of the things I like about the book and one of the things one of the reasons why I think you're
beginning preamble might have gone a little bit too too much into the plot for me was I really
liked the sort of the way tipper slowly makes it clear that everything is not what it seems on
the surface and she does that extremely well in a way that talking too much about
specifics of what's different like you lose some of that I posted a question on discord what music
should I listen to when listening to this book and I ended up listening to the Annihilation soundtrack
and it turns out that was incredibly good choice from a vibes perspective so so yeah because it is
very insidious you mentioned you mentioned the lead character was Marjorie who is who is the
ambassador's wife which is weird because she has many many more things than that but she is
referred to in the text as the ambassador's wife but the other kind of point of view characters are
green brothers which initially reminded me of the hammer brothers from Mario which Chuck hammers
at you and you have to jump on them but it turns out they're quite different.
Do you want to explain what they are John? The hammer brothers were like coopers and they had
hammers and then about halfway through the no no come on come on so the green brothers are people
who have been cast out so that the central overriding church in the books is called sanctity and it
sounds absolutely awful and the green brothers are um acolytes of sanctity that have been sent to
grass to do penitence for having lost their way and we follow two of them one who has been on
grass for a very long time and one called Rillaby who is new to grass and that whole side of the book
I also found absolutely fascinating. Yeah so I think the other key thing to say is that the green
brothers is there because grass has an archaeological dig which is a city from a long dead population
called the Rby and I think yeah one of the one of the nice things John was saying is how she kind
of slowly uncovers things but you do know right from the start that everything is super creepy and
weird shit is going on and one of the things is that the Rby city rather than seeming to have
been kind of deserted and a slow death is full of people who died quickly and horribly.
I wonder how that happened. Yep yeah no it's there's a point where they're like oh there are many
more mummies found in this city than in any other Rby city and you're like oh no that seems like
it's going to be relevant. Yeah so this book has a bit of a horror vibe going on but I didn't find
it to be as as long-time listeners will know I struggle with horror and I don't remember finding
this particularly horrible at the time. We recorded this episode at the same time as episode
105 and I talked about monolith in that episode and it's kind of horror in the same way that monolith
is horror where it's this creepy sense that not all is as it should be and that everything is at
some level awful. It's not sort of it's not sort of have nightmares at night scary it's
I would not want to live in this universe scary but it does that very well that creeping sense of
horror and dread is very good. What themes do we want to cover? So I think there's a few themes
we've covered religion is a clear theme in the novel environmentalism ecology is a clear theme
I think gender is a clear theme patriarchy and I think class is a clear theme oh and I think action
is a clear theme the ability to do the right thing even when like the laws and strictures around you
would suggest that it would be difficult to do so. There's also taking action versus not taking
action so it's not quite the same but I mean in centibrate doors which I finished it just in time
for the Hugo deadline so it's on my mind you know mother of glory says that the only way to
change the world is through intentional directed violence and maybe it's not the quite same thing
here but I think there is the strong you know the overt theme of when should you take action and
when should you not take action even if that action is sometimes violence that you think will lead
to a better outcome. I don't think it's it's a much earlier take on it and I don't think it's
quite as clever or as interesting as it is in the centibrate doors but I think that's definitely
there and all tied up with the religion and the sin. Yeah I think that's fair. Now I think I think
one of the interesting things I found about this is that we are I think it's very relevant especially
now in the kind of you see it in the kind of you know should you punch an artsy discourse
and stuff like that like I think it is still very relevant maybe more relevant today
and I think the novel kind of does some interesting things with that question and
and answers in a way I found very compelling. So appeasement. There are lots of people who don't
want to rock the boat and it gets in the way of doing what's right and that all kind of comes up
later in the story. Do we have anything else to add on kind of action? Yeah I think it is we're saying
and I think we're going to get into some spoilers for this book but not like cute ones and it is
quite old so you know go out there and read it before you listen on. Yeah do you like it did you
like it guys would you recommend it? I did like it yeah. You didn't ask you launched straight into
plot summary we were talking about Mormonism but yes no it was good. So I did like it I'm not sure
if I'd recommend it um and would be caveats which we'll get to. You might want some trigger warnings.
Yeah exactly so to get back to this so one thing we find out later on is the kind of the arbai
civilization had a like the very optimistic view of the world and that their view was like
true evil does not exist that everyone can be improved and given second chances and this
probably led to their downfall and then it becomes more of a discussion between Marjorie and some
of the life on the planet as to when you should take action but I think it was interesting this
sort of set up the arbai as a civilization who kind of don't believe that anything is
unredeemable anyone is unredeemable and then set up some examples of potentially characters
who are unredeemable as a contrast and also the issue of intelligent life and having an example
of creatures who are intelligent but maybe not sentient and go on instinct and about the evils
of that and how you should deal with that. It is really interesting that the arbai basically
die because they can't conceive of a race that would act with malice. Their conception of
intelligence is that intelligence and malice are kind of malice has no place in intelligence
almost and it's very interesting to see the book portray this kind of dead society as a
society that never really ended up being able to grapple with that so that was very interesting.
I liked that a lot. The book makes that more and more explicit as you go through so it kind of
sows the seeds early and then reaps what it sows later on and I guess in some ways it's also about
trust, about how trust is a two way street and about how you can't abuse trust because the ending
where sanctity is revealed in its full horror is one where the reason is overthrown is because it
has abused the trust its followers have in it. They do know right from the beginning or very
nearly the beginning that sanctity is awful. It's not sugar coated. No, no, no, it's not.
But I think it's not in the text of the novel. It's not possible for it to end until
the abuse of trust is revealed in the text. See, I thought all of that was very good. The
depiction of horses, it's amazing how much of this comes from the points of the book that are
from the horses points of view. I thought that was hilarious. It was like a chapter when I realized
like, oh, and now we're listening to the horse. Then we get that like twice in the horse book. It's so
strange. I had totally forgotten. Amongst the many things I've forgotten about this book,
I, you mentioned vibes earlier and essentially all I had remembered about the book was the vibes.
But I've totally forgotten that there were chapters from the point of view of the horses
and having just been incredibly rude about a television series with with a
it was some scenes from the point of view of the dog. I am. I did like this a lot more.
I started off going, oh no, but then it was fine. It was fine. I don't think they were really
necessary though. It felt like everything we were getting from the horse could have been
conveyed with the human perspectives. And again, there's a chapter towards the end where she gives
us like the perspective of every single human and it's like, this is very long when did just move
things along. Maybe today I don't know anything about horses so I also don't know if any of the
horse stuff was accurate, but I assume the horse stuff is fakie realistic, although the horses seem
to be able to ride for a very long time. Horses are real. I'm here to tell you that, Liz. It's a good
jump. Thank you. And this kind of the theme about doing what's right versus doing what's expected
I think comes from the theme of gender. And so I think that segues quite nicely because
Marjorie is in a relationship with a man who it's fair to say that they're not very well-matched.
So they have a poor marriage. I thought I thought that relationship was interesting because
yeah, I think it lays out like how they are not matched. And it was also interesting to have the
kind of the son taking after the mother and the daughter taking after their father. And you know,
there were kind of being echoes of their parents. And you can see that in kind of how they end up
and what they do. I thought it was interesting that Rigo, the man who is kind of portrayed as not
really listening to his wife and going off basically to prove his masculinity by joining one of these
hunts, later ends up making a really important contribution by learning to join the hunt and
being very good at riding these not horse-like malicious animals. And then that becomes like a
precipitating bit of the plot. Because I was thinking that was just going to be, it would all go badly
wrong and his cubers just catch up with him. And it does. But it is also kind of, he does have
an effect that's quite useful when he ends up winning a fight basically. I think one of the
interesting things about the book is that obviously I sympathize with Marjorie and I sympathize
rather less with Rigo. But I thought the book did a pretty compelling job of characterizing both of
them as people who were incompatible. And it wasn't like it wasn't that either of them were
deliberately trying to do that. They were both trying to be what they needed to be for the other
and both just not being able to be that person. And I thought I liked that because Marjorie at
several points feels guilty that she is not able to be who Rigo needs her to be and goes to confession
and her priest basically says you just need to obey him or recite the catechism of obedience.
And I think that's deeply unhelpful advice. But I think the relationship itself is just sort of
doomed to fail because of how different they are and how incompatible they are. And I thought that
was very well done to give you those insights into gender and into patriarchy. But in a way that
wasn't like Rigo's just like evil. I didn't like him very much, but he wasn't just a bastard.
Does that make sense? Yeah, I think he is two-dimensional. And I did like that we see her going to confession
and there are two Catholic priests that she can go to confession with. And we see that like one
of them is obviously younger and more reasonable and maybe sticks less strictly to doctrine than
the other. And she's kind of surprised when she goes and gets a different outcome by going to a
different priest. Yeah, which I thought was a nice way to add a few extra dimensions to this
theme of religion. In my head Marjorie is played by Rachel Weiss and Rigo is played by Oscar Isaac.
That'd be fine, costing this movie. I think that would work very well.
One also the way that gender is used in the ruling families of grass where it starts out,
you sort of think, oh this is normal kind of patriarchal stuff. And then it becomes more and
more clear that in fact, again, that is also not what it seems and that something much worse is
happening in the families. Especially Sylvan, there's a point where one of the aristocrats
sons is talking to Marjorie and says, well, you know, it wouldn't, you know, it affairs a common
place in our minds. And it's like, oh, that is not, that is not necessarily compatible with his image
in which the ruler of the house is very patriarchal. And that's the first hint. I think that something
is very different here. Do we want to dig more into gender? Because there's some nots of good
stuff as well. Yeah, I mean, this is a book of its time. So the way we talk about gender and the way
we talk about gender and science fiction books in particular has moved on a great deal since 1989.
And I think that is relevant here. That's probably one of the things you'd want to trigger.
Yes, I think, you know, I'm never keen with saying it's of its time, but it does feel definitely kind
of of of a body of work that was happening kind of in the the 70s and 80s that is feminist
but I'm trying to think I had to put this. It's it's feminist, but in a way that basically has
strong female characters, but also has some female characters who exist only to show us how bad the
men are. And it's also a very binary men, women feminism and does not have anything like the kind
of gender diversity, which I think is a hallmark of more modern science fiction. So I was trying
to think in the parrotist book, because what I was thinking when I was looking at this is,
okay, so it was nominated for Hugo in 1990 and it lost her a Hyperion. And then in 1991,
the winner of the Hugo and in 1992 as well was Lois McBashtaboojold and it's those early
burial novels, the vaud game and burial, which I like but have this very strong theme of basically
rape and sexual assault being something that happens to a lot of the main characters and is a way to
kind of show that some of the men are bad. And this happens quite a lot in grass and quite a lot
of the female characters seem to exist only for this to happen. And also the book, like the narration
of the book is very negative about them, while also having like Marjorie who is like a female
character who is basically in control of her own destiny and making her own choices. And then you
know there's a female doctor who is crucial to stopping the plague later on and there are
characters like this. But then there's also the characters, you know there's multiple characters
who end up getting abducted and kind of having their brains rewired and people treat them like pets
and they're sexually assaulted. And I'm thinking like, "Rigo brings his mistress to the planet" and
basically no one likes her because she is shallow and she's what Rigo needs which is like an
uncomplicated woman who likes being his mistress and being a catwoman and being available to him.
But basically no one likes her and she's just described as being shallow and never thinking of
anything else. And oh well, she gets killed. Or possibly gets abducted and has her mind wiped,
but no one really knows and no one seems to be too upset that she's dumb. Yeah so there's a lot
of fringing in this novel. Yes. No I mean it's one of the things which I think is there's a lot of
abuse both sexual and physical and it is hard to read and it is also tricky because it does that
thing where well let me know if you disagree with this peeps. But I think the intention is that the
I think the novel wants you to conclude that the reason that the male bonds are being quite so
awful is that they are basically being mind controlled by the hippie by I'm also very reluctant
to go along with any narrative that's like, "Ah well you know the men that are raping people are
doing it because they're mind controlled." And it's like that gives them a lot of a...
it's a really hard thing because it basically gives them kind of an excuse or the text wants
to give them an excuse and it's like, but I don't think that's helpful to the message the novel is
trying to portray. I have a lot of misgivings around that. I didn't feel it was trying entirely
to absolve them. I think it was also clear that this hippie who are these like horse-like creatures on
the planet who we discover are kind of mind controlling all the aristocrats subtly into running this
hunt for their benefit. And so they are kind of under their control in a way but it didn't feel
like they were... it didn't feel that was used really as an excuse for the the violence of the men
in the family. And they're also kind of being sexually manipulated by the hippie as well. You know
I mean I think all of the aristocrats are being manipulated by the hippie. I think that's just...
I thought it was just to perpetuate the hunt. So things they do to perpetuate the hunt but maybe
not anything else. So he beats her when it becomes clear. So um Oberman, the main... there's one
Bond family which we follow more than the other. I can't remember its name. Who was his first name,
S something solder. Stavinger von Damfald. Stavinger beats Rowena like to a bloody pulp basically.
And the reason he does that is because she has given information about the hippie to Marjorie.
And my inference there was that Rowena was acting against the will of the hunt and Stavinger was
being used to punish her for that. But I don't like a reading where rape and abuse their wives but
it's all because of alien influences trying to perpetuate this situation because I don't know...
I would find it much more palatable if it was happening in both. If there was like some families
where men were being abused and some women were being abused but I understand that I would undercut
what the book is trying to do with gender but I think the abuse undercuts what the book is trying
to do with gender anyway so I don't know. My feelings are very mixed. I read that as the
hippie are determined to perpetuate the hunt and they are controlling sexually manipulating the
hunters to make that happen. Stavinger is a free agent though where he's abusing his wife
but it's like an alcoholic going where somebody has tried to take their vodka away.
It's like an alcoholic where someone just tries to take their vodka away but also an alcoholic
where the addiction has been foisted upon them by alien mind control and the result of the
addiction when the mind control leaves is to perpetuate the alien mind control. I don't think
he has much agency. That's what I'm trying to say. I don't think any of the aristocrats have much
agency which I think is where they're so much more backwards than the commoners.
Yeah so that there is a class thing in this book as well. Oh yeah yeah 100%.
The where the aristocrats are they believe they're in charge but they're not and the
commoners are busy off running the economic matters of the planet and rather leaving the
hippie's great game with the aristocrats and not having any part of it but also not doing anything
to stop it which comes back into that there's questions of inaction and action that
they're so relevant to the book. I think a lot of the commoners just have a vague sense of unease
but they mostly just think that the aristocrats are mad and nuts. Yes. Yeah I mean there is that
I mean we do fight we do see from the start that the hippie are adopting only young women
from the hunt and I think at the end when we get kind of what you know when we get the
explanation of why they've been doing this there's absolutely no reason it had to be young women
I don't think it could have been anyone and so the saying that has been the young women is to kind
of I think make up a gender politics point but it's not really supported by that will text the book.
So if we talk about Tepper more generally um Tepper is often seen as being somebody who is
writing strident and polemical books and I've been thinking about this because I don't think
this book is particularly one of them and whether that's true and that can occur to me that quite a
lot of the books that men were writing at the time were really had quite a lot of bias in them
in terms of the sorts of stories they were telling and and that there was maybe some unconscious
bias there that if women were writing books they should be subtle and certainly a lot of the worst
subtle and a lot of Tepper's books are not subtle and um but you know a lot of the other science
fiction around at the time was not subtle either so I don't think it's fair criticism.
With Liz's point I was also confused about and maybe I'm wrong but it seems like there's a bit
of a plot hole right at the end where the hippie are abducting these young women
brainwashing them like removing everything except for their sex drives which is just a choice
and like then sending them into town naked with dead bats but as far as I can tell the first
time this happens it's intercepted in town so are we supposed to assume that this has happened
before that like people have successfully stowed away to spread the plague or are we supposed to
assume that this is like the first time the hippie have done it and if so why now when they're about
to successfully invade the village anyway I don't really get that it all it all seemed a bit odd
it's a minor point like I didn't spoil my enjoyment of the book much I just I was a bit
I didn't think the book had really thought that part through I didn't think that when
we're starting away they just need to um big spy with the book chuck a dead bat onto the ship and
run away but are they just nakedly running through town trucking something onto a ship and running
away and no one has ever noticed yeah so I think the implication is yes see that that doesn't make
any sense to me at all no but the plague also I don't think makes a lot of sense so yes so so there
is a very weak speaking of things that are not so great about this book there is a kind of explanation
for the play works that is not the finest moment of science fiction it feels like it's been attached
to the novel in a not very useful way it would be better to just kind of hand wave over that bit
that have the explanation they actually have in my view yeah I've I think that's I think that's fair
I mean I very often think that explicit explanations of what's going on are overrated in science fiction
though so I know I am not necessarily representative in that way it just distract me because I started
thinking about enzymes oh no nine times especially in the context of this book which is all about the
vibes up it's a book about creating a sense of a place and a world that is very alien and and when
you get into but actually it all works this way here are how all the nuts and bolts fit together
even if it was done well I feel like it would detract from the overall sense of the novel yeah
undermines your vibes although I do quite like the thing where it turned out to be bats because
just just to explain it's set up that they're hippie who I don't know if you said explicitly
the hippie are these wholes like creatures who take the arest to crats out on hunts we learn
only on that one of their kind of gestures of like insult is to do something which is described
as kicking up dead bats and everyone just thinks it's like they're kicking the soil up then and
but it turns out the reason that they do this kicking up of dead bats is because they've been
using it's to spread plague throughout the galaxy for millennia so I like that sort of maybe clue
was there in plain sight well tell well put on the twitters and the face books that you should
read grass if you don't want to be spalled by our episode a little later class is a really
interesting one because it kind of it it's done both in terms of like it's done multiple different
ways and I guess it's more generic than class because it's it's power dynamics more generally
because they do kind of aristocracy versus the the commons and then they but they also do kind of
margery on earth going round the town where she's doing charity work but they also talk about
religious hierarchy and kind of especially in sanctity and in the green brothers where there
are multiple different cults at work within sanctity and all of them have hierarchy in ways that is
perhaps not helpful to the goals of those organizations I think it's kind of about who is running things
is it the people at the top who seem to be running things or is it actually someone else who's getting
things done I don't know if that ties into the gender politics as well well I will also say
in some ways this is very much a book of its time because it is a book that imagines that the
people who seem to have the power don't have the power and it's actually the common folks that
have the power and in the current discourse about like billionaires and their effects on the world
it's a very retro take on on where the power lies oh I think that's true on grass but I think
I think on earth thanks she absolutely has the power doesn't it yeah oh yes probably yeah I mean
it's got the power on many places it's got this whole thing going on where if you are an illegal
person you get shipped off to a penal colony yeah you know it's not it's not great and that's all
very relevant at the moment because they're basically talking about kind of women's rights to control
their body the answer to which is none there are no rights in this novel and that is very uh
relevant at the moment very relevant today yeah so in that sense I think it does have quite a
lot you know just speak to us now it's not something where you just read it as historical artifact
oh no absolutely I mean the bit of the start where she's going to you know see the alleles who are
you know essentially if you have a third child which is not allowed under sanctity or other
children will disavow you if you you know don't disavow your third child and you'll be sent to a
penal colony and you receive no medical treatment do you receive no care you receive no nothing it
just feels like a maybe not even exaggerated version of the world but it was written in 1989
I was just thinking about the Chinese one one-shell policy which was in effect then
and probably one of the things that have formed that aspect of the novel but yeah it does feel very
relevant today Alison said like you know it's not just interesting as a historical artifact and I
think that's right like I would Liz said that she wouldn't necessarily recommend this to someone and
I think I would I'd recommend it to them with like a trigger warning but like I did enjoy it enough
that I would say to other people it is worth reading it's good I would recommend it in the
same way I would recommend stuff like in the way that I actually do still recommend like those
early lowest at master boot jolt or potentially some amma kaffrey which is yeah there's some really
great stuff here but there is this one particularly big thing that's going to stick out that you need
to be aware of I'm warned about before you read it I was just thinking about particularly big
things sticking out um Alison just like way um I do I do always want to say I love the I love the
foxen I thought they were great maybe that's because I'm a cat person and they read like cats to
me but like well they're kind of described as being tiger like I think I think your reading of them
as cat like is not wrong and they purr do you want to explain what the foxen are John they're
sort of like cats I really hope I really hope that that's how he came out on the recording
they're sort of like cats in the way that the hippie is sort of like horses aren't they
the the the the foxen are the object of the hunts on on the planet and they are
an intelligent species who can communicate telepathically and they are basically have decided
or it's not clear to what extent this is true like whether it's a universal thing amongst their
community or whether it's just like some people but there are definitely some of them who feel
that it would be better if they stopped procreating and went away and um that's one of the main that's
one of the other main ways in which the novel talks about this theme of kind of action versus
inaction but the one we are kind of introduced to them through is very cute and lovely yeah well
I'm really think they are they are fine when they're not being hunted down and killed by
the aristocrats and the hippie hmm yeah I mean I think that that's how because they're
introduced as as a species that needs to be eradicated but it like foxes but spoiler that's not true
I mean I think there is a big thing in not mentioning when you talk about them being like cats
and we all mean it's a couple of things one is that obviously they're quite scary because they
are quite powerful physically powerful beings but also Marjorie has sex with one of them trigger
warning in a weirdly written kind of mostly by illusion but you know what's going on section yeah
so so human aliens sex trigger warning probably both consenting intelligent species definitely
oh yeah there's definitely more consent there than there are in basically any other
incidence of sex that's portrayed in the book there's absolutely no like human sex
positivity going on is there there's only the only good thing is when you have sex with the
cation when also I have a question for you which is do you think it is sex or do you think it's
some sort of mind-meld thing that fox and do that humans don't really have a direct analogy to
because I didn't necessarily get the impression it had much of a physical component but maybe I
did not read it closely enough and of course we know that this is a thing in this world because
of the thing that the hip-eye are doing to the aristocrats in the as part of the hunt yeah that's
actually true there is a reading where basically the hip-eye are repeatedly raping all of the humans
who hunt but in their minds the aristocrats are up for it that's right that's why they're
perpetrating the hunt they really like it I don't think I got that impression from dimmities
chapter I mean it's referred to as orgasm at some point right yeah it's an orgasm um yeah but
also it's it's but dimmity doesn't know it's gonna happen and feels like ashamed and dirty
no that's right sorry there's no consent at the beginning they don't they nobody is telling the
kids that this is going to happen it's it's consent in the same way that if someone rapes someone and
that person then psychologically comes to depend on their rapist they're consenting no it's definitely
no no sorry if I give you any suggestions that was fine I was I was not meeting too it's clearly
it's clearly very not fine but that's I I always took it that that was the same process as that
as what the foxen were up to yes but I think I I guess the distinct chamtraduros I think with
Marjorie is consensual and I don't think in any other time we see it it really is it's a very
complicated book that has some very difficult big themes yeah sorry for that I could have given
you sort of I'll pick something easier next time no I mean I enjoyed reading it um Alison did you
enjoy getting to the end of this novel that you made us read I didn't quite for for complicated
reasons I think I probably would have done if we'd started recording at 10 oh no I've heard of and
of course I'd read it before so I did I did basically know the bare bones of the structure of the plot
and but I was really I really enjoyed reading it again I mean obviously there were things that
kind of had oh I've recommended these these guys at this and this scene the whole sort of doll like
the empty-headed doll like stuff it's very hard to read it's it's just weird to read from this
perspective in that you can have a book which is simultaneously you know both thing like it has
very progressive gender politics and you know Marjorie figuring out her role in things and the kind of
equality between men and women that there is in in the the commoners but then also this you know
perspective basically of every man as a potential rapist oh yeah so yeah welcome to welcome to
welcome to the works of Sherry Tepper yeah I mean I enjoyed reading it I mean some of the stuff I
heard about later Sherry Tepper's like when she released the malgret's her last novel that was a
Clark Award nominee I remember there being some pretty negative reviews of that so I was pleasantly
surprised because I've only read one of the Sherry Tepper and Sherry Tepper and this one seems to be
on the side that I would recommend to people rather than the side that I would not.
In the book How to Suppress Women's Writing by Joanna Russ one of the things that happens is that
after women even where women are celebrated in their lifetimes after they die their work is
forgotten much faster than men of a similar stature so one of the reasons to talk about
older books by women writers is to get people talking about them because I think these books
all three of them, Russ raising the stones which is my favorite but I didn't want to give you the
second even if it's a loosely collected series I didn't want to give you the second of the series
to read and side show they're all great and and people don't talk about these books anymore
they've just kind of vanished in a way that I think a lot of the male writers of similar quality
people are still talking about and I don't and I think this is something that people say happens
to women creators a lot so I just want to say these books are good, go read them.
I mean I would say this is also an SF Masterwork which is why we can we get to read it right but
it is also true if you look at the SF Masterworks they are not gender balanced.
Oh I also want to say a little bit about SF Gateway so it's not just the SF Masterworks this is one
of the ones in the actual Masterworks collection but SF Gateway has done a fabulous job of
getting old SF onto ebook format so that you can go and read them go and read vast numbers of books
which 20 years ago you'd have had to pay some book dealer a lot of money to get a copy of
and SF Gateway grew out of the SF Masterworks program but yeah no the Masterworks were obviously
not gender balanced but that's partly because science fiction was really not gender balanced
but they could probably have done more to make the Masterworks more more diverse than they did.
Well it's an ongoing project isn't it? I think the recent ones the recent ones are much yeah the
more recent ones are much more balanced but yeah if you look at kind of what was available up to
I don't know maybe 2000 we can look at it in a future episode maybe yeah so yeah anything else
on this book or shall we wrap up that was the old thought podcast and it's goodbye from me
it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in compotec.com
used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]