I'm really sorry this is all my fault. I'm so sorry.
Hello everyone and welcome to the unlucky 13th episode of the
author podcast, a podcast for science fiction and science
fiction fandom. I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Betty.
This is the episode for the third of September 2020.
Maybe this will be our final episode.
Why will it be our final episode?
It's unlucky 13th. You just said.
Well, yeah, but I still want to keep going.
Yeah, quite enjoying it.
I'm worried now.
I'm not saying that I'm just saying you just said it was a lucky
maybe you'll be unlucky.
I'm being a political podcast.
Why you follow up from Liz?
She's breaking up with us on the podcast.
You heard it here first.
Oh, we have letters of comment from two usual
commenters and one unusual commenter.
And I knew the first one is Mark Plummer, who notes that Alison
described Robert Silverberg as the only person left who has attended every
Worldcon. Yeah, I don't know what I was thinking.
He knows that she probably means every Hugo presentation unless he went to the
first Worldcon when he was in like when he was four.
But Mark expresses doubt.
Yeah, no, I'm just talking bollocks there.
Sorry, we knew what you meant.
So we didn't even question it.
That is true.
We should have stepped in a bit like Alison, but then Mark wouldn't have
written to us and that would have been a dream.
So, you know,
or we could fact check the podcast.
That's not ever going to happen.
We rely on our listeners for that.
Yes, we have fact checkers.
This is the fact check in.
Claire Breiley of Croydon writes in to comment on our podcast.
She writes lots of lovely things.
She notes the same comment about Robert Silverberg, but she also says that
Mark's mentioned that to us already.
Or no, she says, I bet Mark's mentioned that to you already and she was right.
So you win the bet, Claire.
We owe you a pint.
It was a very, very good luck.
And we very much enjoyed it.
So thank you very much for that.
And then Ian Sorenson writes Hello, PODIFILES.
He notes that his concern with the Saudi Arabian bid for Worldcon was that if
they had been nefarious, they could have bought a few thousand Worldcon
memberships and just won.
And that is a good point that I hadn't thought of and is an interesting thing
to kind of contemplate.
I don't think there's a really good way of avoiding that ever happening.
Because yeah, I'm going to say that that's a kind of, oh, but any bit could
see, or any bit could actually do it.
The it's it's when people say, well, any bid from a new country.
Obviously, that could be its government planning to move in and do that.
And you say that about Saudi Arabia and you say it about China, but you do not
say it about New Zealand or Finland.
I think you have to take a little step back and go, what what is going on when
I say this?
Because it's it's not entirely a justifiable point with China.
There's a real risk of that because we know that the Chinese government is
funneling money into the Chinese bidding process.
Or we see we assume that it is because there's kind of because the Chinese bid
gets, I'm doing square quotes here, sponsorship in a way that you would not
normally expect a bid to get.
But I don't think you can say that about Saudi Arabia and I don't think it
has ever been any suggestion.
I suspect that if the Saudi Arabian government were familiar with the work
of the people who are putting on the Saudi Arabian bid, they would not only not
want to win the Worldcon for Saudi Arabia.
They would prefer it didn't happen at all.
We say that the Chinese government are sponsoring or funding money into Chinese
bid, but so far they've mostly funneled the money in by helping them have more
people at a big convention they ran.
Whereas I think using lots of money to essentially pay people to be supporting
members of the Worldcon and pay the voting fees.
I think it's a different use of your money really.
Yes, I should say we've seen no sign of that from China.
No, and I think if you're the government, you say, well, why don't we just, you
know, help you hold this convention rather than, you know, essentially send a
bunch of money in to fix you getting it.
But for China, I can see that one way it might happen in a way that the Chinese
government and the Chinese think is perfectly reasonable is for the Chinese
government to say, oh, all of you people who are going to start switching
conventions in China anyway, we will help you get involved in this
international thing by paying for your membership in, is supporting membership
in the bidding convention.
And also he says that he has sent Lillian and Christina instructions on how
to start editing a podcast, which is excellent because he says that the
online tutorials he's done with them will either go on the podcast or in a
video compilation on YouTube. And can I just say in that when that happens,
I will be enthusiastically watching because that sounds amazing.
I have not tried to get Alice in all this to edit the podcast because I
quite quite like edited the podcast.
So it's all right.
I do think this was hilarious.
I thought that this podcast was made up of two people who very much wanted to be
on a podcast that somebody else said it's on one person who very much wants to
edit a podcast.
And I'm assuming that most podcasts are like that.
Yes.
And I was quite surprised to hear that Ian was actually trying to pass the
editing duties off to one of the others.
Listen to this never happens, which has now had four, four episodes, and which
talks about all sorts of things that are not science fiction or fandom.
It talks about everything.
In the last week, the news came out that Chadrick Boseman had died of cancer.
This is incredibly sad. People listening to this podcast might know him best for
his work as a T'Challa or Black Panther in the Marvel Cinematic Universe.
And obviously this is a huge shock because I think we've all gotten used to
the horrible headlines around COVID-19 and coronavirus and kind of a lot of
illness and death.
But Boseman died of cancer and he's very young.
So this is a great shame.
43, I was very sad to hear of Chadrick Boseman's death.
I thought I was a great shame, etc.
He's very, he was a very good actor.
Did you see there was a link going round of him?
They got people who thought they were talking to a Black Panther poster and he
was hiding behind a curtain and would pop out and surprise them.
And it's brilliant.
That is, that is quite excellent, isn't it?
Because there's lots of people and they're, I think they thought they were
going to be on, they thought they were going to be on something.
So it's like, basically, you talk to these big Black Panther posts and, you know,
tell us what you really feel.
And they're all so, it's all Black people and they're all so sort of excited and
they're so grateful to him and things like that.
And there's, but there's one guy who says things like, you know, I've seen it twice.
It's cinema.
And then once I bootleg and then like Chadrick Boseman pops out, I was like,
you bootleg my film and the guy's like, no.
That is excellent.
But he comes out and says the guy's name, you know, and the guy's name was
obviously like quite a long complicated one.
And the guy's just like, he's like, and you said my name right.
So I thought it was quite, yeah.
Just watch the video because it was so, and it's so lovely.
And it's someone who went to same college as him saying, you know, how
lovely it is to see that representation on the big screen.
And then of course, like he pops out and it's like super charming and super cool.
And they're all like, God's mad.
It's amazing.
So I watched Black Panther last night.
It's trending on Apple TV because everyone is doing that.
I said to Mariano, I guess a lot of white folks who haven't quite got
round to Black Panther are going to watch it this weekend.
Yeah, that's a good point as well.
I hadn't thought of that, but yes.
And that was me.
I was that person.
It's quite a good film.
Yeah.
I mean, I should say that I was not watching.
I was not watching Black Panther from the point of view.
I was watching it and looking at it as am I enjoying this?
Movie do I think it is a good movie?
Is it the sort of movie I like to see all of that?
Taken as look how much money they spent on a film where almost every
major character is black.
It's an absolute masterpiece.
I've been kind of going, Oh, I wish they were making more use of Black Panther
because he's a really good character.
And I'm not sure why he's not getting more time in Marvel movies.
I think I now know the answer to that question.
And Marianne was like, who is the next Black Panther going to be?
Because it could be it could be his his sister or his son that we don't know
about yet or his girlfriend or or a random Black boy from America.
I think it will be it would be cool if they did.
Sure.
But obviously because she has like her own, I'm not sure if she's ever been the
Black Panther.
She might well have been.
But like I think of her more as like she is so much better suited in that kind
of being the amazing scientist role that making her into the Black Panther
seems like it would almost be a demotion.
Cue the code name for that role is cue.
I understand that Shuri in the comics has been Black Panther, but it's kind of
instead of that she'd always wanted to be Black Panther.
Please comics more avid comics, please, please write it and correct me if any of
that is wrong.
And so I could see her taking up the back panther mantle.
And I think it's it would be interesting to see someone who is more sort of
technology focused really take that on.
I guess maybe they're shying away from that a little bit because it's a bit
similar to say Iron Man and you know, using a lot of technology.
But I think it could be really good.
I agree that I don't think they're going to want, you know, they're not going to
want to recast Black Panther.
They're never going to recast a chalice.
So I am confident that if Ryan Coogler continues to make Black Panther
two that he will come up with a really good way of handling it.
I hope that they'll get to do it is Winston Duke, the guy who played Dominic
in person of interest.
He was the co lead in us.
Oh, you think that they'll recast the same character?
No, no, I don't.
Oh, Winston Duke was already in, right?
Yeah, he played Baku, the chief that doesn't take part in Woodcander and
to Charla brings him into the fold. I think he would make a great Black Panther
because I think he's a great actor.
He's his profile has been rising.
He was in us.
He's been a person of interest.
He's been in a few other things as well.
He did have the funniest line in that film also.
And yeah, and I just think he would be a really great choice.
So if they're not going to make it shurry, then I think he would be a good pick.
He's not done much movie work, but he's great.
Is he in the bloodline?
You don't have to be.
That's not how a condom politics works.
OK.
But you probably do have to challenge, but you probably could challenge.
So that's and that will kind of fit in quite well, depending on how good they are
with like, they're going to have to.
I don't know what happens in work, under if I see this is in the comic somewhere,
but I don't know what happens if the King dies before someone can challenge for the throne.
The Jabara. Is it Jabara?
I'm sorry.
I'm not really up on the Marvel Cinematic Universe.
It should probably get the name right.
I think they are the Jabari Jabari.
One wrinkle with that is that he and Baku in the comics is the villain,
Manape, who is like, obviously a baddie, whether or not the Marvel Cinematic Universe
will go with a black supervillain called Manape, given that that seems like an obviously
terrible name for a supervillain who is black.
I suspect means that he's not going to do that with that character either way.
So I think he would be a good choice, but we will see.
He certainly to me, he's to me, he seems like the best choice.
I hope they could with him because I'm a huge fan of his work.
I think the fact that they actually played, they played with the fact in the film,
that comic book viewers or readers will have known that that was the character.
So they played quite hard with the, is this a villain or not in the film?
So they've already, they've already gone there.
They've made it clear he's not a villain.
I think so.
This is a spoiler for Black Panther, so here's a spoiler warning.
There is a point in the movie where these guys turn up, having previously said
they're not going to it.
It's like bloody Gandalf riding down on Shadow Fact.
Hey, that's a spoiler for Lord of the Rings, Alison.
It is also a spoiler for Lord of the Rings, but tough.
Well, she didn't say what Shadow Facts was.
Shadow Facts could be like a tank.
Yeah, or a giant armor plated rhino.
I did like the giant armor plated rhinos.
Yeah, in the, it's in the positive qualities of Black Panther.
The fact that I enjoyed it, that it used a lot of African cultural stuff in a way
that was actually not crappy.
And in the list of things I did not really like about it were the fact that
enormous amounts of it appeared to be cliches bolted on from other bits of other
movies. And I suppose that is normal and, and the general level of comprehension
required to understand the movie was consistent with a movie where you had
Lillian sitting next to you talking all the way through it, which I, I kind of, I
kind of missed Lillian.
I would really have liked to have Lillian sitting on myself for drinking red wine
for, for yesterday evening, for that movie and talking all the way through the film,
which is what she does.
You froze for like 30 seconds and then I just got a Lillian drinking red wine on
myself.
So I do what you said.
Oh, and also I, I watched a fascinating video on, I don't know how much was this
we're going to use on movie music, which is, okay, there's a very good video on
the internet about why a lot of the music in the Marvel Cinematic Universe
and other modern movies is bad.
And it's because they basically send the composer a kind of George Lucas
like made up list of things that they think are the sort of thing they would
like the music to sound like.
And then the composer goes and writes music that sounds a bit like that.
Right. Well, one of the, one of the things that they have used for the score of
Black Panther is the opening music for the Lion King.
And that was a really, really, really bad choice.
So there's this side, oh, and, and Marianne's like singing along with Disney
movies at that point.
Or you would be Taylor with a Disney movie, you're watching one.
I understand that.
And I just say to her then, well, MCU has been bought by Disney, but I'm not sure.
Was it Disney owner at that point?
Yeah, Disney owned it well before.
Yeah, Disney's owned it for years.
OK, so in general, I guess my, my, my problem with the whole of the MCU and is
that, and maybe the whole of Disney plus apart from Hamilton is that the entire
thing appears to be pitched at a reasonably literate 11 year old child.
And I am not that person.
No, you're an illiterate 11 year old child.
Oh, thanks for that.
That's all right.
Someone actually made a really good point, which is Disney is the last entertainment
company, because all the others are now just the video divisions of mobile phone
companies or dot com startups.
And Disney is the last movie studio standing, which is a really, really
discombobulating statement that doesn't make any sense to start thinking about it.
You're like, Oh, yeah, because it's Disney, AT&T, Comcast, Netflix, Amazon, and Apple.
So any time Warner isn't it?
I don't know.
Maybe I don't time Warner's owned by AT&T.
Yeah.
OK.
No, they're they're all they're all they're all either dot com startups, the video
divisions of mobile phone companies or Disney.
Those are the options.
It's weird.
I'm feeling better about my Disney plus subscription, because I the only reason we
were watching Black Panther in the first place support independent artists by
Disney by Disney by Disney.
Also, Disney acquired Marvel 11 years ago, 11 years ago tomorrow, in fact.
I feel like it may have become more like a Disney company more recently.
Disney acquired Marvel like before they even released the Fenders
assemble.
So I guess the sort of second and third phases of the Marvel universe have been
completely well, they've been a Disney owned subsidiary.
I guess.
Yeah, it should be pivot to being a Marvel podcast because we probably get a lot
more viewers that way.
We're getting any viewers for a podcast listeners.
Should we pivot to being a Marvel podcast?
Because we probably get a lot more listeners that way.
No, because every time you say that every every time you give your opinions on
Marvel movies, we will lose listeners.
So this is a net drop in listeners almost certainly.
So you think that people who like Marvel podcasts think that Marvel movies are
clever and more?
Yeah, they probably do think they're clever than they are.
Yeah.
I think I think you said they were aimed at mostly literate 11 year old.
And I suspect the people who are listening to Marvel podcasts would object to that
characterization of themselves.
Possibly.
It's like there's a chance.
They are kind of towards the lower end of the middle brow.
That I think you think that's you being tactful, which I very much enjoy.
But they really they just they're very, very easy to consume, aren't they?
Well, I mean, I think that's probably true.
But I'm not sure.
It doesn't make them bad.
Last weekend, as we record was NASFIC, the North American Science Fiction Convention.
NASFIC has held in years where the world can't be held in America.
And obviously this year, the WorldCon was held on the internet.
So therefore, a NASFIC had to be held.
It was held in Columbus, Ohio, except it wasn't.
It was also held on the internet because of just as our window.
Liz and Alison spent some time at NASFIC.
What would your experiences like Liz and Alison?
I have to start with a kind of contractual statement, which I will say every time
the NASFIC is mentioned, that the provision for NASFIC is contained in the World
Science Fiction Society's constitution.
And it definitely shouldn't be.
And this wines, Europe fans who are not from North America up quite immeasurably,
but nevertheless, it never goes away.
So there is always a NASFIC, but only in years, there is a dewilcon.
And it's slightly strange convention for that reason, normally, because it
normally comprises those fans who are rich enough to go to both the WorldCon
and NASFIC, and those fans who cannot possibly attend a European or Australian
worldcon, but would quite like to go to a national convention anyway.
And so therefore, I've never been to a NASFIC before, but I
got invited to sign up for programming for this one.
So I did do and they put me on some program.
All of my program was on Friday and I did that and then I hung out with people
and I made some arrangements to work on the Glasgow desk.
And then I actually had actual life things on the Saturday and the Sunday when I
went out and met real people in the real world, you know, like we used to do.
So I ended up not spending anything like as much time at the NASFIC as I might
otherwise have done. But I did sit on the Glasgow desk, which was a lot of fun,
support Glasgow in 2024. If you haven't supported it yet, it's very easy to do so
at their website, a link to which will be in the show notes.
And the program items I was on, which were about doing fanac in the age of
COVID and trying to sell things at online events were quite interesting and I
enjoyed them a lot, but I didn't get a lot of the program otherwise.
And I feel that this is one of the things that's now happening with online
conventions, which is that the real world is more exciting a lot of the time.
So yeah, this was the first virtual convention.
I've actually been too largely because it was free so I could just pop it out.
So I did join the discord and had fun poking around a bit on the discord.
I went to two panels because the problem is that Columbus, Ohio is 11 hours behind.
I would say that it took me quite a lot of digging to figure that out because
the front page of the NASFIC website does not at any point tell you it's time
zone or even tell you that it's the Columbus in Ohio.
So I will reiterate my plea for every convention to either put the like times
in UTC or at least tell me the time zone.
But I managed to figure this out.
And so I could basically go to maybe two program items because they were the ones
that were held while I was awake.
So I went to the item that was Farmendelson and Alec Navalle talking about
researching Golden Age science fiction in the present day.
I really wanted to go to that.
Moderated by Nicholas White and it was great.
It was one where it was exactly the right, it was exactly the right set of people
with a very good moderator and the two of them probably could have talked for
at least two hours and I would not have been bored.
And I found it really interesting and you can go back and watch that.
I also went to a panel on Afrofuturism, which was straight after that with a
large number of people on and that was good, but it worked a little less well,
partly because one of the participants was having internet issues and sort of
dropped in and out.
And secondly, because it was a larger panel and I think it is much harder to
moderate a panel of four or five people on Zoom because a lot of the things you
might do just don't really come across.
Like I think if you're sitting in the same room as people, you can kind of try
and encourage them to maybe wrap up and we'll move on to the next person if someone
is, you know, basically every time they respond to a question, they have a lot to
say, you can sort of try and push that along, I think more gently or maybe break
in at a point where there's a break.
But I feel on Zoom people, because of there's a time delay and because you're
not in the same room, you have to basically let everything play out.
And so that was a little detrimental because it felt like some people didn't
quite get to say quite as much as other people on the panel.
But actually everyone on the panel, what they were saying was really interesting.
So maybe the solution is that it should have been a 90 minute panel with more
room for these things, two more room for discussion to happen.
And I also did find the fact that there were sort of 50 minute panels with then
10 minutes to sort of change over.
I think you could have pushed that a little bit because there's no reason it
couldn't be 55 minutes.
I don't think you need the massive 10 minute gap.
You could get away with just a five minute quick break.
I'm going to I'm going to slightly disagree with that in that.
I think that the 10 minute break is very nice because and this is going to be very
base, but if one needs a poo, one needs 10 minutes.
And the number of professional meetings I've had where it's a five minute break
and it just be the entire day I don't have room to do certain biological things
I would quite like to be able to do.
I'm going to progressively pissed off for people who are like five minutes
will be fine. No, no, 10 minutes is good.
I don't need I don't need 10 minutes every time.
But the time I do need the 10 minutes, I really need the 10 minutes.
So yes, sorry to our listeners who may not want to know these things.
I'm going to disagree with this from the other point of view, which is that I was
Zoom host for a few things at Conzeland and the amount of the amount of hardness
it is to change a room over in five minutes is very great.
Now, in fact, this got that's like actually had two was running two rooms in parallel.
So I don't think anyone actually had to do that.
But if you are having to change over a Zoom room in five minutes, it's it's
impossible and people might have been programmed sequentially, which and 10 minutes
is not really enough time for panelists to to get sorted for another item.
So so I think 10 minutes is fine.
So I will I will push back that if you're paneling, you probably should not be putting
people on back to back panels anyway, because whether you give them a 10 minute break
or not, it is hard work.
They did have two different rooms they could be using.
And it just felt like we were cutting off at, you know, 10 50 when they hadn't
really had much time in those 50 minutes to expound on it.
Once we actually get the hang of how to get people to buy from dealers at an online
event, which, you know, they would like to do dealers have things that the members
would have not seen before and would really like to own.
And the members are inclined to buy things from dealers.
But the process of putting them together is completely failing at the moment in a way
that's making everybody very sad.
And if we had a 10 minute break, I think one of the things we could be doing with the
10 minute break is here's here's the sponsored deal.
Here's the feature dealer for this 10 minute break.
Go and see that stuff.
I mean, the other thing about dealers rooms is even if you showed me a bunch of stuff
in that 10 minute gap, I likely wouldn't buy it.
And the reason I likely I'm not buying anything from dealers is unless it is like
ebooks or something, I'm not buying anything because I don't know when it will arrive
at my house.
So, you know, electronic dealers rooms fundamentally for me are a thing that doesn't
work because I have no idea how long the post is currently taking to get to me.
But it could be, I think it's probably months.
So overall online sales remains strong.
One of the things that was really interesting about this at the UK Games Expo is a lot
of dealers had a lot of trouble.
Like the number of people that they expected to get through was was vastly
lower and the problem with dealers of the internet.
And I think I think Alison is slightly wrong here is that I impulse by stuff in
person that I would not impulse by at home.
And I think the context of a convention where you get to go on holiday, I buy things
on holiday that I would never ever buy when I was not on holiday.
Conventions are very much an example of that mindset.
And this UK Games Expo, I didn't spend anything.
My usual budget for UK Games Expo is around 200 pounds.
So like the disparity there between like my usual behaviour and my own
line behaviour is vast.
And I can imagine for a lot of other people is too.
So I think dealers are a really difficult thing.
But I think a lot of that is psychological and I'm not sure to what extent
it's because we don't have the platforms versus other considerations.
Sorry, Alison, tell me why I'm wrong.
I feel that this is it's like parties.
It's one of the things where you could either ring your hands or you could look
at what will help worked out with that.
Yes, fair enough.
And I feel because it's kind of a third way of selling.
So you've got people who they've been saying, oh, it's been really difficult
for people who are used to selling face to face to move online.
And all the dealers are like, no, we do have established online shops because
we're not actually dealing from the past year.
It's not about physical sales or online sales and online sales remains strong.
There's no in general people are still buying things online.
It's actually trying to find whether it is possible to create a market
for selling at these online events and in particular for finding a way to highlight
the fact that you can get unique things from dealers in our field that you cannot
that you will probably not find just by browsing the internet because because
they are marketing that they can market directly to you.
Now it won't work for dealers who are selling things that are easily available
from from other large companies, but lots of dealers are selling unique things.
And I feel like those dealers ought to be able to do.
We ought to be able to find a way to make that work.
Anyway, and if we can't, I will just walk away.
I've I've said I'm not ever I'm not paying any more money for a dealer's table.
It's an online event until until this is cracked.
You know, I feel that that although I did not lose money at
Consilent, the money I spent for a dealer's table, there was largely waste.
Dealers, it sounds a little bit similar to something that Bristol Con
does or at least used to when I went to a couple, which is between
panels, they would have like a very short five to 10 minute reading slot,
usually for an up and coming author to come and read their work out.
And it didn't really work for me because I'm distracted by moving rooms
and working out where I put my phone and getting myself set for the next panel.
So I'm not listening to this poor person reading at the front of the room.
So I worry if you use that 10 minutes to kind of advertise dealer stuff,
you would see like the number of people in the zoom, just like ticking slowly
downwards that could be quite demoralizing.
But I don't I don't have a good solution to the online dealers room thing.
The point I was trying to make is that I think that is a really difficult
problem and I don't I also don't have any good ideas about how to solve it.
I think is I think you're right.
I think people are not in really the right places to be spending the sort of money
that they might spend in a dealers room if they're at an in person
convention right now as well.
When I think I will actually say I tell a lie slightly because I did buy some swag.
Um, from both the UK Games Expo and from FarcomCon, which was a, so the UK, sorry,
I should have said this.
The UK Games Expo was a convention held at the same time as NASFIC, which I spent my time at.
The one thing I bought at the UK Games Expo was a Games Expo 2020 dice bag.
And the one thing I bought at FarcomCon was a set of alt-art cards for
Akmara and the thing they both had in common was that there was a time limited
aspect to the purchase.
Um, the alt-art cards had a discount for the duration of the convention and the
dice pouch was only available to buy that weekend.
And so I didn't think, oh, I can just put this off for a month and it will be fine.
I'll book out the page and then never buy it.
Why did I bought it then?
Because there was a reason to buy it then.
And I think the way that you capture the impulse purchase thing is you have like,
all my stuff is 20% off if you use this convention specific code that is valid until
Monday. And I think that might help.
But obviously, my great revelation here is that making things cheaper makes things
people more likely to buy them.
And I'm sure that most traders have already thought of that.
Um, it does, but you can put your prices up by 20% and they give people a 20% discount code.
It works just as well.
But Alison, that would be dishonest.
You'd think, wouldn't you?
Um, so in Britain, there's some trading laws that don't that limit the extent to
which you could do this, but when you're trading globally, those really don't apply.
And I think the trading standards would have very great difficulty in enforcing them on
you, but often when you see things being sold at a discount, you should just assume,
just assume that the price of being charged is the actual price for that item.
And it is not in fact a discount.
You do have to put it back up to the regular cost afterwards.
Otherwise, people will notice and get abandoned with you.
You could have time limited ones.
But limited edition things just for an event are good.
And I might use them in the future.
Time limited stuff seems like a good, a good idea, something you can only buy that weekend.
And hopefully in price ranges where people do think, Oh, and impulse, I can impulse buy it this weekend.
Um, the other thing I wanted to say about this was because they're five hours behind parties
were at an inconvenient time and they had two lots of parties.
They had one using a scheme called Gather Town, which is a large space in which people can move,
little avatars of people can move around.
And then when you get into groups close to people, it's set, it spits up a zoom-like window
with their video faces.
And this actually worked OK.
It felt very bitter, but it felt like an I've used similar systems in the past as test.
It worked look like something that could be made to work with a bit of, with a bit of work.
Um, it had it suffered one attendee was letting their child run all around the space.
And so that child kept kind of their video would appear for about three seconds
through your through your party as they were laughing and joking.
And that really accurately recreated the experience of having an eight year old running
around a bar to me.
And while I didn't enjoy it, I thought, Oh, well, maybe we're getting somewhere with this
replicating the feeling of being in a bar.
So I quite liked it.
The actual video as ever is not as good as zoom.
If zoom put a layer like that on top of the zoom function we've already got.
So in the corner, you would see the local area of your bar and a list of all the people
and you can see a list of all the people in the bar generally.
I think that would be pretty killer.
The other night's parties were on zoom, but because I'd actually been at a real party
in the real world with real people that day, I was not capable of attending a party at
what started at midnight, my time, by which time I was fast asleep.
So that was a normal zoom party of the sort that we've been doing.
And I think that was also pretty successful.
Again, I would like more parties at different times of the day, please.
I will say I didn't go to I didn't go to NASVIC.
And I in general, like with reconvene, which was the weekend before NASVIC, I think.
I think that's right.
I paid my $10 and I actually didn't really feel like I got $10 worth of enjoyment out of the convention.
I think the thing I am learning in lockdown is that conventions for me are very much
social spaces and not spaces to receive information.
I go to the panels because I enjoy them, but if it was just panels with no social space,
I would not go to conventions.
And I think what I'm learning is the online conventions, which are basically just panels
with no social space are very much not a value proposition for me, which is not a criticism of them.
Because I appreciate there is an audience for that.
But certainly it is not, it is not my cup of tea.
I will say as ever that I want more conventions to do more thinking about the virtual
social space and make it better.
The panels are quite useful so that you have something to talk about in the social spaces.
Something else we should probably say about NASVIC is that they tried a new method
of showing panels to people, which is that they only put the panel participants into the zoom
and they put every and then they used Vimeo, I think, to display to everyone the panel
and the Discord chat in a kind of single window.
And this had the effect of making the panel very, very small for a lot of people.
I don't know whether the person who came up with that idea was doing it on a 27 inch monitor.
But they were wrong and this was a mistake.
I mean, they've embedded in their website a thing that let you have the Vimeo and the Discord side by side.
But you could just have the Vimeo as a stream.
And in fact, I did it by eventually working out how to cast it to my TV.
So there's nothing saying you had to only view it on their site.
It worked perfectly fine. Oh, yeah.
I mean, it took a bit of budging because I couldn't get out of my Chromecast very well.
But once I've got it sorted, I did.
So I basically do this as, oh, well, I'm going to watch panels instead of TV for a couple of hours this evening.
And I didn't really engage with the Discord at the same time.
But there were people asking questions to the Discord.
Yes, that now we had two, I did two panels and in one of them.
So they said to us both tips for being a good online panelist and tips for being a good online panel moderator.
And I didn't moderate a panel at this one.
But one of the panel moderators was a very good panel moderator.
They were using the Zoom chat, which is because only the panelists are in Zoom.
It's only for the panelists.
They were using that to queue up the next topic of conversation and tell people to wrap up and invite people, say,
I'm going to ask you to talk about X.
So you can have a little bit of time to think about it.
And she was also very good at like bringing people in to the conversation
and just the way a good moderator should.
And the other moderator was appalling.
And I'm kind of like, why are people like this?
And they weren't a bad person or or or or or in your
anything. They just didn't do any of the things that you want a moderator to do at all.
So they weren't really directing the flow of conversation or bringing people in or asking them about particular topics.
And I've I've kind of lost my, you know, they start, you know, you're in trouble because you get to the panel early.
And I say, well, what are your plans for the panel?
A moderator, they're kind of like, Oh, I just thought I see where the conversation went.
Boo.
And I'm kind of done with this at this point.
I was on a panel at Dublin and the moderator the day before the convention started had not sent a message saying is the flow of conversation.
So I did.
I sent the message saying, I think the flow of conversation should be this.
I don't know whether the moderator will agree, but here is my initial pitch.
And then the moderator had to come up with a flow of conversation because otherwise it would be by default.
But when I had decided on, and I felt very passive, aggressive for doing it that way.
But I was like, I, I am as I get older, progressively less willing to put up with moderators who don't put any effort into their panels,
especially when I put effort into moderating my panels.
And so I'm quite happy to be like, well, as a panelist, here is the list of things I will ask my fellow panelists about.
And if you don't want that to be the conversation, you need to go up with a better one.
Because this is now my de facto plan.
I am perfectly happy for the moderator to do all that work,
that the work that the moderator has to do for the to prepare for a panel.
I am perfectly happy for them to do all that work in the 10 minutes before the panel in the green room.
This isn't going to cover the surprise to either of you guys, though I do actually manage to email round people.
I'm not that bad. But, um, but the kind of, oh, I'm just happy to let things drift,
especially in an online con where we know now that letting things drift really does not work in a really big way.
You know, it is just not good enough.
Yep. I mean, speaking as someone who edits a podcast, I can confirm that that is true.
So I will, I will, I will very quickly run through my experiences of UK Games Expo.
Firstly, Liz was there, which was delightful.
And I believe Alison was on the UK Games Expo Discord as well.
I couldn't get there. Couldn't get there too much on last weekend.
I got a lot of badges.
Part of the other shameful admission is the part of the reason I bought merch is because you had achievement badges on your profile through the weekend.
And there was a achievement badge for buying someone a virtual beer,
an achievement badge for buying someone a virtual hot dog, an achievement badge for donating to the UK Games Expo,
and an achievement badge for buying merch.
And I have all four of those achievement badges, which is about 20 credit.
I wouldn't have spent if they didn't have achievements.
So like, that's another way.
Game of fire and they game of fighting good.
I saw that the list of because I got despite the fact that I didn't do a lot in UK Games Expo,
I got some badges and I was like, oh, achievements.
I like achievements. I am, I am a monkey.
You can make me happy with gold stars.
And I went to the list of achievements and I saw that by something from a dealer
achievement, I was like, yeah, I didn't write it down anywhere.
But if you're organizing online, like on ribbons, virtual ribbons,
don't do it as virtual achievements.
Do it as virtual ribbons because that's more famish.
Virtual ribbons and have.
I bought something from the dealer's room and I bought something from the art show as virtual ribbons.
Yeah.
How did they implement them?
Because Nastvik had virtual ribbons, but you just clicked on a little emoji on a chat window.
So no, so in the UK Games Expo to get an achievement,
there was achievement for going to each of the key sponsors stands,
which were pages in the dealers hall, which was only accessible if you'd registered.
And if you went to them, you unlocked the badge for going to that stand.
And then each exhibitor exhibitors were given links that once you'd done a demo
with them or interacted with them, meaningfully, they could send you a unique link
and you clicked the link and it awarded you that badge.
So like if you took demos for games, you couldn't just farm a bunch of links cheekily.
You had to actually do demos and it worked.
It was very good.
I have no idea what level of technical
investment was required to settle this up, but it was great.
I think lower than the amount of technical investment than Conzil and put into its 3D dealers hall.
You know, I think.
Oh, yeah, 100%.
It's not that much. What they did was every member of the convention.
And I think this is something that every online pay con should do.
This is a really good idea.
Had essentially a profile page that people could visit.
And we could do that for any con.
And then when you met somebody, you could go and see their profile page and people could
I don't think they could at UK Games Expo, but you could have people personalise
that with their picture of their bio, just as if they were program participants,
but for everyone.
And then the achievements were all that could all be there.
You know, this feels like very basic web design to me that I could do.
I would have to spend a long time on it and I would cry and curse a lot,
but I could implement this thing.
And I should say I could not implement a 3D dealer hall no way.
So I think I think in general, the personalisation, the limit of the personalisation
of the UK Games Expo was basically like you can you can set people a list of the badges
you've got, but like there is no reason you couldn't have had it be like a customisation,
a customisable page I suspect.
And that could have worked really well.
I think that would be lovely.
And I think it would be really nice to because you do meet people in passing
at these online cons and I mean, you do in real life as well, but you it's hard
to get a sense of what they're like.
I'd have liked to do it for my fellow panelists as well.
I'd like more information about the people I was on panels with,
both before and after I was on the panels with them.
That was indeed the 13th episode of the Octa Thought Podcast.
So for now, it is goodbye from me.
It is goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
The theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by Kevin MacLeod
and Compatec.com used under a Creative Commons attribution 3.0 licence.
[Music]
Hello, sorry I was in a totally different zoom link.
Yeah.
You were right. John was John as one because
he had patriarchy.
What? It's an outrage.
I clicked the link.
I have a link favourite, which says "Allison Zoom" and I clicked that link.
And now I am with Allison and Liz.
I failed to see how I've done anything wrong.
OK, because that's the morning coffee zoom and a lot of people have that link.
So theoretically, we could get zoom bombed on it.
So I'd run these zooms off my personal zoom meeting link, but obviously there is no
actual risk here, really.
Someone who knows you from Coffee Morning joins in the podcast and then we have to
kick them out. It doesn't seem like a lot of risk.
That would actually probably be quite fun.
An improvement on the podcast.
Never tell Lillian that this is how she becomes a guest.
Yeah, never tell Lillian we're doing it.
[beep]
Do we have to bleep swears?
Yeah, we do.
If you are an explicit tagged podcast and someone has parental controls turned on,
their children cannot listen to any podcast that is listed as explicit.
Just so you can say, "Beep."
I mean, can they voluntarily block us?
Can parents decide, "No, I don't want my children listening to those reprobates
on the Octa though podcast," and like, "Preemptively block it?"
Obviously, this is a huge issue.
I think I should mention here that this is all that's based on a US
understanding of what is meant by a swear word.
Yeah, because we all know that if I call Alison a f*ck, that's just that's just that's
just pub talk, you know, that's not explicit.
It's just nice. That's gonna get go out.
Yeah, you can, but just bleep the swear words entirely so I have no idea what you
called Alison.
That's rare.
That's great, actually.
What if I say that John is an absolute, oh, let me think of a good.
Oh, no.
Yeah, if I say that John is an absolute muppet who talks nothing but bollocks,
none of that is going to be, is going to trouble the Americans in any sort of way,
because it's not part of the set of words that they consider rude.
Anyway, I'm not sure whether the Americans consider a f*ck rude.
They don't consider f*ck rude.
They don't consider bollocks rude in particular.
They don't consider bollocks rude at all.
They don't really understand that the British think the bollocks is quite a rude word.
Yeah, well, it's bollocks in it.
Well, it's Americans and it's bollocks.
Um, don't write it.
We were presumably going to a podcast and not just say British swear words.
I'd rather talk about swear words for 45 minutes than the the the retro hugos.
But I suppose this is.
Yeah, so let me get the show notes.