You should say that a bit closer microphone then it can be the outro.
I'm sorry apparently I am just talking bollocks. There we go.
What I like about that is that whole thing can be the pre-show.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 132nd episode of Octa Thorpe, a podcast for
science fiction and science fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 7th of April 2025.
I'm John Coxon, I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
This episode is coming to you early this week. There will be no episode on the Thursday.
But what we do have is some chat about the Hugo finalists.
It's opinions really. I mean I assume our listeners have mostly seen
the Hugo finalists if you haven't well we'll tell you about them but mostly you want our views
and opinions and thoughts and hot takes and all that.
And of course we have to be quite careful about this because John and I are the Hugo
finalists liaison team and we love all our Hugo finalists equally.
Yes and we really do. I think it's a very strong roster this year. I'm not just saying that.
I'm not liaison so presumably I can be the bad cop.
As rude as you like yep.
In the category of astounding award the finalists are
Monocool, Black Goose, Bethany Jacobs, Hannah Kana, Angela Liu, Jared Petcheczyk and Tia Tashiro.
I am familiar with Monocool, Black Goose and Hannah Kana because they were in last
year's Astounding Award roster but I confess the others are new to me and I will be looking forward
to looking them up.
So yes Bethany Jacobs has two novels out now I believe, Her debut novel was out in 2023.
Tia Tashiro and Angela Liu I know are short fiction writers and Jared Petcheczyk,
debut novel was out in 2024, The West Passage which is very well regarded.
I understand. I haven't read it yet because I don't think it's actually out in the UK
yet but it did win the Crawford Award for Best debut fancy novel.
Yes the Crawford Award which is administered by Friend of the Podcast, Farah Menderson.
Was I believe Farah has stepped down.
Farah was the administrator for the West Passage winning and is now being succeeded by Kelly Robson
who may be a friend of the podcast. Kelly if you're listening, re-in.
So yeah I mean I'm really keen to read the West Passage which I've heard good things about but
haven't got round to it because of the aforementioned not being out in the UK yet.
I have also heard good things about these burning stars by Bethany Jacobs from Friends Who've Read It
I was nominated for Locust Waterfest novel last year so yeah it seems like a solid solid list.
The Load Star Award for Best YA Book is The Feast Makers by H.A. Clark,
Heavenly Tyrant by Joanne Jayzau. The Made in the Crocodile by Jordan Ifueku. Moonstorm by Yoon Ha Lee.
Ah shiny Lendy. I'm so sorry that's definitely not right by Darcy Little Badger and So Let
Them Burn by Camilla Cole. I've not heard of Camilla Cole or H.A. Clark before but I look forward to
reading their books but everyone else I have read books by before and I enjoyed them all so I will
look forward to reading these books. So then we have The Category of Best Poem which is being run
as a special category by the Seattle Worldcon and this is a very interesting roster I think.
So we have Calypso by Oliver K. Langmead, Ever Noir by Marines. There are No Taxis for the Dead by Angela
Lu, A War of Words by Marie Brennan, We Drink Lava by A Zhang and You're Visiting Dragon by Devon Barlow.
And yeah that's a so Calypso is a long form poem it's it's sort of novel length. I think most of the
others of these are short poems so that is going to be interesting. I have not read any of the poems
except for Calypso and I will look forward to reading them as I say. I assume they're all freely
available online before the packet comes out it looks like they are the only one I'm not sure about.
The Devon Barlow is from the Fund Drive for Strange Horizons so I don't know if that's
only available to backers and Havens Spec Magazine I don't know if they put their issues online for
reading. So the Strange Horizons Fund Drive issues are also just online for everyone they're like
what you get when you meet certain stretch goals but they're not like private to any people who
paid for them and the Havens Spec poem is online so you can go and read all the nominees sorry all
the finalists. Except for Calypso which you might have to buy but it is I did enjoy it very much.
Yeah I think Calypso being novel length is probably something you'll have to buy but who knows it
might be in the packet. I haven't read any of them I'm very excited. I'm very pleased that
I mean I will say I did not nominate anything in poem because I don't really read poetry and
therefore had nothing to put in that box so I'm very pleased to see that there are enough people
who read Transfictional Poetry and nominate for you goes that that you know is enough to get us a
really interesting looking shortlist and yeah it's one of those years where there happens to be a
prominent novel in verse basically which in a lot of years there is not so you get this
interesting way you've got five shorter works and then one very long poem so yeah.
One honking great big thing. Mmm. Then we have Best Fan Artist which some of us may have opinions on
so we have Ian Clark, Sarah Felix, Meg Frank, Michelle Morell, Spanish Sheriff and Alison Scott,
longtime fan artist followers will know that five of those names are repeat finalists. Michelle
Morell is the new finalist she is the she is one of the DHS for Seattle and she did some beautiful
Seattle cross stitches which are very very lovely but I think all of these people do phenomenal art
and it is a very strong roster so hurrah. It's also a very traditional fanish roster like all of
these people are doing art for fanzines and conventions and that is not always true in fan
artists which is not an editorial comment it's just a note of a fact. I am obviously going to remain
scrupulously neutral about this category I don't want any of my co-hosts or co-hosts spouses to trap
you down. We know where you live Liz somewhere in Toyland. Oh it's true Alison knows where I live
she sent me a snow globe full of weed mix. I've sent you a few things sent you a postcard in Thai.
Ah yes but can you take that address I gave you in Thai and successfully work out where I live.
That is fair that is a fair question and then for best fan writer we have Camistross for Lapton,
Abigail Nussbaum, Rosanna Pendlebury, Jason Sanford, Alistair Stuart and Orgin Weston.
So I think that is is that five repeat nominees and one new nominee? I think it might be.
I don't think Rosanna or Camistross have been finalists previously but I might be wrong.
I need to find out but didn't Camistross get a best related work?
I mean spoilers for later. So yeah checking now I don't think Rosanna or Camistross have been
nominated in this category before. Yes I think you're right there. I think everyone else has been.
This is going to be a difficult category for me to voting because there's lots and lots of
good people in that one. Yeah that is not untrue. Yeah obviously this podcast is a paid up member of
the Rosanna Pendlebury Fan Club as you saw last week but also we're a paid up member of the Abigail
Nussbaum Fan Club as you saw in OctaThops Passives so I'm not sure what we're supposed to do here.
Yeah so this is going to be very tricky especially me because I nominated two of these people
and so which ones do I vote for? I might not tell you who I nominated.
Maybe you're into the suspense but it is probably obvious if you have been listening to OctaThop regularly
who I nominated so there we go. But yeah I think it is very nice to see some new faces in this
category because I think there are a lot of good fan writers and it is nice to share the glory
around but also nice to see Abigail back again after her 2017 victory. A lot of victory is not
really victory is it? 2017 win and then two best fan cast. Yes category obviously very interested
in and very excited by and the nominees are The Kootrute Podcast eight days of Diana and Jones,
Hugo Girl, Hugo's there, Amelia Thorns, world building for masochists and you'll get the full
credits from the finalists list. Obviously we love all the Hugo finalists equally but Hugo Girl are
our transatlantic besties so I'm a bit in the tank for them. However and we picked eight days of Diana
win Jones on the pod. Yeah and I'm very pleased to see Amelia Thorns on there which I think has
been doing great work. Interesting stuff. Yeah that's going to be a really hard one to pick.
So Amelia Thorns and eight days of Diana win Jones are the two new ones here. I think all of the
others are repeat. Yes Hugo Girl having recused in 2024 are back for 2025 as they said you know
they're going to basically go for it again. They did win in 2023 but we all know that 2023 was a bit
of a fuck up uh C. C Hugo nominations we're going to get to in a minute for that. Yeah.
A slightly tarnished Hugo yeah not that not that Peter Weston's rocket's ever tarnish. No not even
like ridiculous humidity it's still fine. The finalists in Best Fanzine are the insular review of books,
Blackler problems, the full lid, Galactic Journey, Journey Planet and the unofficial Hugo
Book Club blog. Five of these are repeat finalists but ancillary review of books is new and Liz is
championing for a little while so I bet she's pleased about that. Yes. I'm a previous contributor
to Galactic Journey and John is a previous editor of Journey Planet. Indeed indeed. I also believe I'm
right in saying that ancillary review of books is the first is the only new finalist but only one of
these has one previously which is Journey Planet so there is a five-sixth chance of a new Best
Fanzine and that's cool. That is pretty good. I will say this was the Journey Planet did the
excellent issue on unions in science fiction fantasy I believe in 2024 which I really enjoyed
which I think was edited by Ola Venamanda from an official Hugo Book Club blog so they are sort of
double nominees congratulations. Small and lovely small and lovely fandom this. So the few categories
where I don't think we have a huge amount to say but we're going to let you know who they are.
So Best Semi-Prozine we have The Deadlands, Escape Pod, Fire Magazine, a Black Specter to Fiction,
Correo, Strange Horizons and on Canny Magazine and I think there's three previous winners there.
I think Fire, Strange Horizons and on Canny have all won before. I think The Deadlands is a new
nomey. You must assume that it's different. No no that was I believe correct. The finalists
for Best Professional Artists are Michaela Alkaino, Audrey Benjaminson, Raveena Kai,
Maurithio Manthierdi, Tran Win and Alyssa Winans. I think there are three repeat finalists which are
Kai, Manthieri and Winans and I think the other three are new to the award so welcome welcome welcome
pro his stuff. And the nice thing about Pro Artist is it is very easy to go and catch up on their
works from the Hugo Packet and elsewhere and take a look and yeah Raveena Kai has one three
you goes and I don't believe the others have won any. There's another five six chance of a new
of a new winner. So the finalists in Best Editor long form are Carl Engelert, Ali Fisher, Lee Harris,
David Thomasmore, Diana Enfoe and Stephanie Stein. I don't know if we have anything to say
about this. I would like to say that David Thomasmore is an editor at Rebellion. Quite often the
editor categories are dominated by American editors as you may expect because the voting pool is
largely American. Lee Harris has been nominated before and I think has been nominated in Best Editor
long form and Best Editor short form in the same year but David Thomasmore was nominated
or was nominated previously in 2024 for his work with Solaris Aurelian but I think it's nice to see
a bit of non-US editors getting in there. Best Editor short form is Scott H Andrews, Jennifer
Brozek, Neil Clark, Jonathan Strand, Lynne Thomas and Michael Damien Thomas and Sheila Williams.
Many of whom edit for semi-prosines or pro-sines but some are editing also for anthologies as well.
Yeah, good bop bop bop bop. Well done to all of those people. But again I still find editor a very
difficult category to vote in. I just find it very difficult to decide on, you know, in Best Editor
long form to really know and I actually because a lot of the time I don't know who bought or
commissioned books either even if I'm not directly judging the editing of the manuscripts so I do
still find it a little bit tricky but that looks like a good slate of finalists.
Yeah let's talk about best game or interactive work. Who wants to introduce this category?
Mimi, me, me, me. So the finalists in Best Game are Caves of Could, Dragon Age the Vale Guard,
the Legend of Zelda, Echoes of Wisdom, Lorelai in the Laser Rise, Tactical Breach Wizards
and a Thousand Times Resist and I just want to say that I am absolutely delighted by this category
and in particular by how many of the sort of games that I typically really like which are
kind of slightly indie nerdy puzzle games have ended up on there or games that have got a lot of
indie vibe going on with them that it has not ended up just being AAA games and it's really great.
Yes. I mean obviously we love our AAA games equally. Yes so the only one of these games I have played
is Dragon Age the Vale Guard which I would rate as like a B+ game but maybe a B-game in terms of
Dragon Age and if anyone wants to discuss this in you know extensive detail I suggest you come
and find me Eastercon and buy me pint. I have previously picked on the podcast I believe the
Legend of Zelda, Echoes of Wisdom and Caves of Could both of which I enjoyed and I'm continuing
to enjoy very much. There are three games here which are very much on my radar but which I haven't
played because they're Windows games so I believe I can play them in emulation and I probably will
do and I haven't I didn't even know Dragon Age the Vale Guard existed sorry it's so far off of
why. It was your free PlayStation Plus game in March bafflingly given that it's an AAA game and it
came out six months ago but it's worth a bite but I mean have you played the previous three games
if you haven't then it may not make a lot of sense but yeah you can you can say that the Hugo
voters are clearly like PC gamers I mean all right they've also nominated you know Legend of Zelda
but there's some you know Windows only games on here it's not all you know PlayStation 5.
There is one Windows only game which is tactical breach results all the others are available
so Caves of Cud is available on Windows Mac and Linux. Dragon Age the Vale Guard is available on
PlayStation Lorelai is available on Switch as is 1000 X resist and Legend of Zelda is also available
on Switch so the only one which is Windows only is tactical breach wizards. What's I meant was
not Mac? Yes Windows only and not Mac are two vastly different things when it comes to video
games because almost everything is not Mac but almost everything is not Windows only.
I'm throwing a floral eyeliner laser eyes it's now out on PlayStation it was not when I checked a
few months ago because it came up seven months later for some reason. I think the only one I don't
think will eventually end up on other platforms is um tactical breach wizards because none of their
previous games have ever been ported to anything other than Windows. And also Zelda which will never
be on anything apart from your Nintendo's. Indeed but yeah I think it's a good roster I've not
played any of them and then we've got best dramatic presentation short form. In the category of best
dramatic presentation short form we have Fallout at the beginning I get that all along Death's Hand
in Mine. Dot two dot and bubble Star Trek Lowedex, Fisher Quest Star Trek Lowedex the new next
generation and Dot two 73 yards. I've seen the Doctor Who's. You've seen some Doctor Who's.
I've seen some Doctor Who's. You haven't seen Lowedex? Nope not yet. I haven't
researched the Paramount Plus yet. Okay I thought you were like a Lowedex on the same day guy.
I have seen Fallout. I enjoyed the series a lot and as did Stephen who has who had no familiarity
with the Fallout Villier game series and all I thought I feel like it was a series that would
probably land better for people who had seen who played the game or it does clearly stand alone.
It feels like all of one thing. I feel like in many ways it would fit better into
long form but you know it's very complicated. These episodes are not standalone. I've seen
the Doctor Who's and the Lowedex. I quite liked them. I mean I gave up on Dot two for a while
and then I got swept back in because it was also T. Debbie so I have seen those two and I did like
both of them but I think Dot and Bubble is better and Fisher Quest is from Star Trek
Lowedex's final series and the new next generation is the final episode and I did enjoy both of them.
I don't know which one I would pick as a standout but yeah it seems a reasonable shortlist. I might
get around to Agatha or along at some point when it's Disney+ time again which it will be shortly
because of Andor. So the finalists for Best Dramatic Presentation Long Form are Dune Part 2, Flow,
Furiosa and Mad Max Saga. I saw the TV Glow, Wicked Part 1 and The Wild Robot so I've seen
the first four of those and I am excited to watch the last two as you saw Flow yesterday as we
record in the cinema and I enjoyed it greatly but yeah I think this is another strong roster.
I've only seen two of these movies and I did say what my nominations for this category would be
in a previous episode of Octa the Upsun if you're interested you can run back. I'm very much hoping
to see Flow in the cinema in the next week only because everyone says it's amazing because I have
to say that as with the Wild Robot the trailer is indicated it was a film about cute animals which
is very much not the sort of film I liked. I have seen Dune. That's it actually. I'm not very good at
getting into films. Some of these I'm going to pick up on streaming so hopefully I'll pick
up. I do very much want to go and see Flow but it did not come out for very long here so I missed
it and I'm not sure I saw the TV Glow advertise anywhere so I think that's why I missed that one.
As to why I didn't go round to Wicked. I don't know I think I was sort of mentally like oh I'm
going to wait until the second part's out because it seemed very long. It's finally a loved Wicked
and I have not watched it yet but I'm sure I shall. I mean I've seen the musical. I have a hard time
thinking why they would want to make it into two longer films rather than like one reasonably
links film but I will wait and see. I would say I didn't feel that the I didn't feel it dragged at
all. I was thoroughly I thoroughly enjoyed the whole of the movie and you know it's very good
at what it does. And then we have best related work. This category is always the most like the
biggest mixture of stuff. So we've got Chiting the Cliff an investigation into the 2023 Hugo
nomination statistics by Camestros Flapton and Heather Rose Jones. We've got r/fantisees 2024
bingo reading challenge from Reddit. We've got the spectacular failure of the Star Wars hotel by
Jenny Nicholson. We've got speculative whiteness science fiction and the alt-right by Jordan S.
Carroll track changes by Abigail Nussbaum and the 2023 Hugo Awards are a report on censorship and
exclusion by Chris M. Barkley and Jason Sanford. So it's a mix of world-con drama Star Wars Reddit
and criticism. I mean it's always a bit of a part of this one. Yes. It's going to be really hard to
judge the Reddit fantasy 2024 bingo reading challenge because it's like it's a bingo card and you do a
reading challenge off it. I just don't know what I'm judging. Am I judging the bingo card? Am I judging
that people manage to make a bingo on it? It's one of those things that like it's going to be
difficult. I feel like it's I don't I mean I'll let them speak for themselves but I feel like this is
something that's a bit like what was the game? Plaza ball. That was where the what you were really
celebrating was the community that arose around the thing and and the bingo challenge is a very big
thing in Reddit fantasy and but it's been going for 10 years. So I don't know if I don't know if
they've been trying to get to on the ballot for 10 years or this is something that they've just
kind of drawn attention to. I'm very glad to know it exists because in in another part of the forest
for board games I absolutely love to be board games challenges particularly once the two are a little
bit scavenger hunting and I feel like that could be a way to direct reading in a in a very amusing
and fun way. But this is the this is the wild card on the Hugo ballot this year I think. Yeah I mean
there's two you know there's there's one book of criticism by Abigail Nussbaum and there's one
X and book which is linking you know the history of science fiction and right wing politics especially
like the new alt-right and they're both very good and so I'm almost certainly going to put one of
those at the top of my ballot and I will get round to the Star Wars hotel video at some point it's
just the four hours has put me off but I do actually want to watch that. If she'd split it into four
one-hour episodes it would have been eligible in forecast for in fact. Um might be professional.
Yeah surely Jenny Nicholson's professional. Professional YouTuber. She got 61,000 Patreon
subscribers or you can join for free but yeah I suspect it's probably pro I think it's a full
tan thing. Yeah she has 1.31 million subscribers on YouTuber I feel like she's making a living from it.
Uh in the category of Best Graphic Story or Comic uh the nominees are The Deep Dark by Molly Knox
Ostertag, The Hunger and the Dusk Vol 1 by Gee Willow Wilson and Chris Wild Goose,
Monstrus Vol 9 The Possessed by Marjorie Liu and Sana Takeda. My favorite thing is Monsters Vol 2
by Emile Ferris. Star Trek Lower Decks Warp Your Own Way by Ryan North and Chris Finoglio and
We Called Them Giants by Kieran Gillan and Stephanie Hance. So that is a roster of things I have not
read but at least two of them I already own and am waiting to read and the others are exciting.
I think Monstrus has been nominated before. I think my favorite thing is Monsters was nominated
for Volume 1 but all the others I believe are first-time nominees. Although I don't know like
obviously some of those authors and artists may have been on previous nomin- uh previous finalists but
like they're all standalones or volume ones so yeah cool stuff. I am very excited about
Warp Your Own Way which I haven't read yet but it's very much in my wheelhouse as the sort of thing
that ticks a lot of different buttons for me. Yeah Monstrus has been nominated seven times
previously and one three times previously I think. Yep so that is a definite repeat nominee
whereas yes the the first volume of my favorite thing is Monsters was nominated. I think some of
the others are first-time nominees so I don't think like Ryan North and Chris Van Olio who wrote
Star Trek Lower Jax Warp Your Own Way are I think they're both first-time nominees although
many of you will have read Dinosaur Comics obviously and yeah we call them Giants Kieran Gillan's
previous nominee and possibly Stephanie Hance for some of the art from previous Kieran Gillan
projects maybe. Depends which volumes of the Wicked and the Divine were nominated
but she might be a first-time nominee. I believe the whole of uh Wicked and Divine was
nominated as like a single work wasn't it? No no according to the internet. But I will say
Stephanie Hance is definitely a repeat finalist because Dye was definitely a finalist in previous
years. Ah yes that's it yeah and Dye has been nominated three times so yes and then we move on
we are now on to the uh written fiction categories and so we have Best Series and the nominees are
Between Earth and Sky by Rebecca Roanhalls, The Burning Kings by Tasha Suri, encrypted by Sean
McGuire, Southern meets by Jeff Vandermeer, Stormlight Archive by Brandon Sanderson and The Time
Final Asifers by Agent Tchaikovsky. Regular listeners will know which one of those makes me extremely
excited and it is obviously the one by Agent Tchaikovsky but I have read the first volume of
The Burning Kings by Tasha Suri when she was a guest runner, Eastagon and really liked it
and there's two more. We did an episode on it for this very podcast. Do we do a whole episode?
We definitely read and discussed it and I liked it and I have not got the other two volumes and now
I likely will. As for the and Between Earth and Sky the first volume was You Go Momma Lated, was it not?
The first volume of Between Earth and Sky by Rebecca Roanhalls was Black Sun which was nominated
when it was out as a novel. Yes and yeah the Jeff Vandermeer Southern Reak is an interesting one
because that was Annihilation and its two sequels which came out quite a while back and now there
is a fourth volume. The whole lot is eligible as well as presumably that book being eligible
in Best Novel. So yeah I'm right do I want to read the whole trilogy again to read the fourth one?
I'm not sure. Listeners tell me if it stands alone. I don't know where we want to say this but
wasn't the second volume of the turret philosophers eligible for the Hugo this year?
Didn't actually make it onto the Best Novel Ballot. Also there were two books and the
turret philosophers that were technically eligible for the Best Novel this year. I think it is not
uncommon that things that make good series don't always end up in Best Novel. All of the books
there's only so the first instalment of Between Earth and Sky was up for a Hugo as a novel
but I believe none of the and I don't I can't remember about the early southern
region of wars and Annihilation might have been on the ballot but I don't think there's ever been
an encrypted novel a burning kingdom novel or a stormlight archive novel on the Hugo ballot.
So it is not I think series rewards different writing to novel in general.
I think that's true. Which one of reasons I quite like it and we discussed the Jasmine
throwing by Tasha Siri in episode 52 whose Robert Piccardo and Liz is correct we didn't spend
the whole episode on it. I don't think Jeff Fandome has been nominated for Best Novel before
so interestingly Annihilation did not get on there. Oh interesting yeah so I think I think series
does reward quite different things but I think in a way that I enjoy. Yes I was the best series
of someone else to show. Sorry. We have Five Views of the Planet Tartarus by Rachel K Jones.
We have Marginalea by Mary Robinette Coel. We have Stitched to Skin Like Family is by Nivo.
We have Three Faces of a Beheading by Arcady Martine. We have We Will Teach You How to Read
Pipe. We Will Teach You How to Read by Caroline M. Joachim and we have Why Don't We Just Kill
The Kid in the Omeleth Hole by Isabelle J. Kim. Isabelle J. Kim was up for an astounding in
2023 or 2032. Can't remember which listeners go look up I'm not checking. I think Isabelle
J. Kim this might be their first nomination for fiction like in one of the fiction categories or
they have been up for astounding. I think all the others are multiple time nominees before.
Rachel K. Jones was nominated last year and I also did pick Five Views of Planet Tartarus which I
think is a very effective bit of flash fiction so you can go and read that in about a minute
and come back and give you views. I've read We Will Teach You How to Read We Will Teach You How to Read
which I think yeah is also pretty solid and there's a lot of interesting things with the kind of
formatting and structure. I have read Why Don't We Just Kill The Kid in the Omeleth Hole. It didn't
it didn't work quite as well for me as it seems to have done for a lot of people online. It is
basically sort of a modern remix almost of the ones who work away from Omeleth but yeah I didn't
feel it had like I didn't it didn't feel like it adds a huge amount to me to the original story
but I think it is very hard. It feels very hard to me to do anything if I try to remix such a
classic story. I think it's very hard to make a success of it. I think this one just okay but
doesn't really do it for me and I haven't read the other three yet. Yeah pretty good showing for
Uncanny Magazine here. Yep. And in general actually it is a good showing for Uncanny Magazine and also
Clotsworld does pretty well. I think Strange Horizons has one or two on this ballot. Yeah. Light speed
has a couple which I was I like light speed. Yeah I find light speed really solid. It's kind of
almost a shame there's no way you can actually put light speed as a magazine on the ballot with
it being you know professionally not semi-prosine but I think it generally has for me one of the
highest hit rates. Then we have Best Novel Let, The Brotherhood of Montague Sent Video by Thomas Hart,
by Salt, by Seabylight of Stars, by Premier Mohammed. The Force This is Overlooking the Sea
by Naomi Quitsa, Lake of Souls by Anne Lecky, Loneliness Universe by Eugenia Terrianta-Filou,
and Signs of Life by Sarah Pinska. I've read I believe two of these. I have read The Brotherhood
of Montague Sent Video by Thomas Hart and by Salt by Seabylight of Stars by Premier Mohammed which
I did both like. I think Thomas Hart had multiple eligible stories maybe not all in Best Novel Let
this year but I like pretty much all of them. Premier Mohammed very solid novel The Siege of
Burning Grass out last year but this is a good a good novel let all about a wizard and a wizard's
apprentice. I haven't read the others yet but probably will be the Anne Lecky collection and
yeah again they're all like solid names I recognize as short fiction writers. I think Eugenia
Dranta-Filou is a first time nominee. The finalists in Best Novela are The Brides of High Hill by
Nivo, The Butcher of the Forest by Premier Mohammed, navigational entanglements by Alliette Bodard,
The Practice of the Horizon in the Chain by Sophia Samatar, The Tux of Extinction by Ray Naylor,
and What Feasts at Night by T. Kingfisher. And five of these are Tour.com and one of them is
Tour Nightfire so I feel like we've um because last year I think we had a few that were Tour.com
but this is really cool Tour.com again. Well done Tour for championing the Nivella in a way that is
really very commendable. Nivella is a great length for science fiction and fantasy stories as we know
and although I have not in fact read any of these Nivellas I am very excited to because they
several authors I like very much are represented still this list. Yeah I haven't read any of them
but I confess I basically was expecting at least The Brides of High Hill by Nivo which is another
in the series called The Singing Hills. Yes yeah so I was expecting The Brides of High Hill by Nivo
which is another one in the Singing Hills series and definitely like The Practice of the Horizon
in the Chain to be nominated so I may have kind of thought when I could read them now but I'm
probably going to get them in the Hugo Vota packet anyway. I am so I haven't read any of these but I
did read two of the Neon Hemlock Nivellas last year and I was really hoping at least one of those
would make it on because I think that's another it's a small press which is having a go at having
a really solid Nivella line and I think it's a shame they can't kind of get any awards traction
so yeah I know that awards don't make and break necessary make and break it but it will be nice
I could just get one on there but yeah one of the Neon Hemlock Nivellas actually when I didn't
read the Drang Phragamba is on the the Nebula list which also has Countess Bices and Polumbo so that
you know there are a couple of non-tour.com books on the Nebula Nivella list. I don't think I've
read any of these but I've enjoyed previous Nivo Nivellas and I've enjoyed the works by all of
the finalists I think so I am excited to read these Nivellas and then we have the category of
Best Novel and we have Alien Clay by Adrian Tchaikovsky the Ministry of Time by Calliam Bradley
Service Model by Adrian Tchaikovsky someone you can build a nest in by John Whizwell a
sorceress comes to call by T. Kingfisher and The Tainted Cup by Robert Jackson Bennett and I don't
think I'm giving much away by saying that we're pretty delighted by this roster of Best Novels
I think peeps is that is that fair two Tchaikovsky's and a couple of previous picks on the pod so yeah
congratulations to Adrian Tchaikovsky for having two nominations in novel which has not been done
since Robert Silverberg in 1973 so yeah look at that fact good lord that's 50 years yeah I guess
this is the point where I can say that of course Adrian is also nominated for is also a finalist
for Best Series and both of the books in Best Series were first published in 2024 in the US I
believe no one was published in 24 in the US and one was 20 will be 2025 in the US although I haven't
read the Ursula Vernon or the John Whizwell I will say I don't think I've read anything I didn't like
by either Ursula Vernon or Charles Whizwell so you know T. Kingfisher I was listening to a podcast
the other day in and it was an episode of The Incompromable Game Show specifically inconceivable
hosted by Dan Moran which is very good I highly recommend Friend of Liz Liz Miles found out live
on the podcast that T. Kingfisher and Ursula Vernon were the same person and it is very delightful to
listen to people finding that news out for the first time so I do think it is sometimes worth
just highlighting because I don't think everyone knows that's true but T. Kingfisher I believe is
Ursula Vernon's adult pen name for more adult works so yeah but they're the same person oh that is
fascinating what is fascinating I like because I'm sure that I saw Liz Miles like in 2019 at the
Hugo Awards when T. Kingfisher was nominated there's so much stuff I can't know all the stuff that is
true that is true but yes so I have read one of the agent T. Kofsky's and I've read the Ministry
of Time and I've read the Tainty Cup and if you made me pick which one I'm gonna put at the top of my
ballot I'm just gonna go in a corner and go I don't know yet and yeah maybe one of the other three
will actually be better who knows we're gonna find out I don't know if we'll be able to do our
customary Hugo finalists episode this year I'll just do a monologue be fine we love all our
finalists equally this is a very strong Hugo list a very strong novel it's a very strong list I think
this is the first time we have had three men in the best novelist since 2018 this is a very
egalitarian list in that regard but yeah no it is notable well no hang on but and and four works
by men as well yeah no no the majority of works written by men which is unusual for the Hugo's
these days yes yeah I don't think that has happened since like it's hard because it hasn't happened
since we went up to six finalists one also it stands in stark contrast to best short story which is
all women best novella and best novellette I believe have one man each and then best series is
half and half men and women yeah interesting I didn't hear a lot about a source comes to call
whereas I had heard quite a bit about the other five books on the ballot but I think this may just
be that like teaking vicious novels are so solid that they're just getting a ton of nominations
every time she writes one hmm she's very good there's not a lot of crossover with the nebulas
there's two novels nominated for both Hugo and Nebula there's a bit more crossover in
in novella where there's three denominator both but yeah not kind of not a lot of crossover with
those other other awards this year I am interested in the goodreads because the goodreads awards are
also a user voted award right and the Ministry of Time won their science fiction award but none of
the other books appearing at the top of these are a sorceress came to call was 12th in fantasy
looking at this do you think the fact that Glasgow members had the opportunity to nominate
had an effect on this list yes because I think it is a somewhat more um British and European
list than it would have been if it was exclusively Seattle members I think I think as evidenced by
the fact that we were discussing the um the editor from rebellion David Thomas Moore
who got their first nomination last year and is a repeat finalist this year um and yeah I wonder
whether Adrian Tricowski has benefited from a British although I think Tricowski's star is rising in
the US so that might not be true the other the other categories don't seem particularly British to me
maybe Tasha's Siri has benefited a little bit from that because she is obviously British as well
but I can't see any other names where I'm like oh that's interesting maybe Abigail Nussbaum
invest fan writer because although she's not British she's very popular in the UK and maybe
Rosanna Pendelpre and best is she in best related work as well she is in best related work I think
related work yeah I don't know it'll be interesting to see whether color fields by Paul Kincaid ends up
on the ballot next year when it's an entirely US nominating Paul but I wonder whether Breyer
Dean books has benefited from British nominators I think Abigail has a large fan base and geographically
dispersed fan base and I think I mean I think Paul Kincaid is well known in the criticism field
but I suspect he's better known still in the UK and you know Abigail has things like the
column on Lois Gens and Money and so on I think he's just got a lot more accessible online
which probably helps in fan writer but it will be interesting to see yeah so that was the Hugo
award finalist congratulations to everyone and that was the Oct Thought podcast and it's goodbye
for me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
we haven't done letters of comment this week because we recorded early but we've
recorded a little pick up because we made some vital
errors with regards to handwriting so firstly we didn't offer to buy Doug Fawn half a pint
so Doug we will get you half a pint at the Dublin Worldcon and for those who didn't know
there's a bid for a Dublin Worldcon in 2029 because that was a question that was asked on
our Facebook group in reaction to Doug's suggestion and Raj notes that he correctly guessed
all three of our handwriting on blue sky so I said we'd buy him a point of his choice
and Raj does not drink so we are buying him a pint of tea well the bar do a pint of tea do you
have any idea how much that bar's likely to charge for a pint of tea don't know we're going to find
out I mean I can always just bring a thermos yeah that sounds good I mean it's basically just
a tea and then a buy a pint of milk right and we put it on the glass to make a he's concoction
classically it's a pint of hot water with a tea bag I can bring the tea bag hi Raj yeah
yes indeed the theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod in
Competec.com used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]