I've suddenly got donut induced in digestion.
I don't know if it's that or the prospect of the business meeting agenda.
Hello everybody and welcome to the very 164th episode of Octothorpe, a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom
Which is throwing a party because the self-help book told it to on the 16th of July 2026.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
And we have
Some letters of comment.
We heard from Christopher J.
Garcia.
He says, Have I ever been to Croatia?
No.
Do I know a ton of Croatian filmmakers because of programming film festivals?
Yes.
One of them makes science fiction films.
So that is good reportage.
Chris also says that he's got a friend who's been to every Legoland, and they say that San Diego is best with Denmark being third.
And I heard from Andrew Hogg saying that I don't actually want to go to Legoland.
I want to go to Lego House.
which is the home of the brick.
And I'll put a link in the show notes, listeners, but having having looked at Lego House, um Hog Hog may in indeed be correct.
Although you can get a ticket, which is a combi ticket with Legoland, so I could sneakily go to Legoland uh as well.
Um but yes, thank you very much for writing in uh Chris
Chris, have you yet met someone who works at Lego who has made a Chris Garcia minifig?
Because I assume that will happen at some point in your life, and if it hasn't happened yet, it's to look forward to.
Actually, that's a good question.
Which person do we know who is most likely to ever get a Lego minifigure?
I mean, i i s I don't know the criteria for getting a Lego minifig.
I mean
Marketability, Liz.
Don't know anyone marketable.
Ha ha!
Oh yeah, that's fair.
Maybe Briar Dean Books will get a licensing agreement with Lego.
To be fair, the covers would be quite good as Lego sets.
They'd be really difficult Lego sets.
Yeah.
So yeah, so if you're if you're listening to this and you've had a l Lego minifig made of you, um please write in.
Yes, we'll have some
Adult fans of Lego who might have had um like unofficial ones and that might be interesting.
Yes.
We heard from Farah
Uh who said it was lovely to hear a discussion of Eddie Clark's blog on Queerus F.
And I agree.
And Farah also mentions that Farah met Eddie on on their guff trip.
Which is a nice reminder that Farrest Gough Trip is finished and we look forward to hearing more about the Gough and indeed the the Taft trips in due course
Yes.
Paul Weimer wrote to us and sent us another eclipse photo, thank you very much, um, which also has his name in the sky, which is a weird astronomical
astronomical phenomenon.
I'm not sure I can say that in English.
He says he's sorry and the person responsible for that has been sacked.
Can you say it in any other language?
Yeah, Dutch.
I want Dutch.
Astronomicalish phenomenal Oh no.
Oh no.
Oh no, now we're going into a bad place.
I could probably have done 'cause like the Swedish chef isn't there.
Yeah, let's no, no.
Um he says he would lose to a wounded one bat at arm wrestling, so bet on Mike.
Hmm and hopes to get to Port Marion one day.
Yeah.
Seems good.
I feel like Mike would also lose to a wounded wombat, so you know.
I would bet on the wounded wombat generally.
They're vicious.
Aust Australia got wombats, right?
Brisbane, would you like a program item?
Ha ha 'cause 'cause Australia has wombats
But okay, so there's certain animal rights issues here, right?
You might need to get a volunteer dressed as a wombat in the style of hundreds of beavers and then wound them.
Ooh, I'm alright.
Which has no ethical uh problems whatsoever.
Alright, we need a volunteer to wear a one-back costume and have one arm tied behind their back at all times.
Yes.
Uh so as any fool know, wombats fight with their um armour plated asses, so I think that would be a thing to see.
Did you not know Wombat ars
No, all I know is that they do perfect cube poos.
Yes, so they they have armor plated bums so that or or st
plates on their backside so that when when something tries to attack them in their burrows they just kind of wham backwards with their arse to
to to repel invaders.
Right.
Kind of like a wombat version of twerking.
Sorry, I I got distracted by uh Googling Wombat bomb armour.
I'm not wrong.
No you're not wrong, and that's why I got distracted by it.
Yeah, 'cause uh I don't know if this spoils things for the listeners, but if we Google something and it turns out Alison is wrong, that is less distracting in episode one hundred and sixty four than it was at the beginning.
We heard on Blue Sky from Kevin and Rosanna, who had Expedition thirty three comments
Uh Kevin sends a picture of the Expedition Thirty Three uh cosplayers at Dragon Con who are all in the uh
What I believe is the baguette outfit, which is extremely French, they got stripey shirts and red berets and baguettes.
However
The only way to get the baguette outfit in Exhibition 33 is to fight a mime, and I have not fought any mimes because I don't want to fight any mimes.
Partly because they are mimes and partly because they are actually very difficult side bosses until you get the hang of the mechanism.
So uh I do not have my characters dressed uh in baguettes.
Uh several of them do have swimsuits
And one of them has an outfit which is labelled as swimsuit one, meaning that somewhere they must be aware of unlocking swimsuit too.
Their swimsuits are obviously uh stripey navy white because they're French.
Yes.
I have something to some things to say on um
Claire Obscure, which is I'm playing it.
I could not play it on my Mac using Crossover, but I have purchased a subscription
at to GeForce Now and I am playing it on that.
So I'm just mentioning the existence of GeForce Now in case people have been under a rock.
Um, it wasn't very expensive, um, because they had some sort of deal on, which I think they always do, but then that's how they suck you in and it's only a first year thing, but maybe I'll be fed up with it by then
So are you sort of renting a faster computer to play it on?
Yes.
So that's how GForce Now works is that you use your extremely expensive home internet connection to
go to one of their servers where they essentially have a something pretending to be a gaming rig and they and you play games that you already own.
So obviously I ha I own Claire Obscure because I got a code, because it I am a Hugo voter
And um and so it's good for that.
And I have some other plans for things that I can't play on Macs that I might quite like to play on G FOST now
I'm about half I think I'm about halfway through.
I too am playing on story mode, which I do not normally do, but I got my ass so kicked in the tutorial that I went, oh no, I'm gonna play on story mode
I was gonna say the timing on that thing is precise enough that I'd be re I'd I'd love to try playing on GeForce now and see like 'cause there must be zero lag.
It must have some kind of clever thing going on.
That's pretty good.
Um and also I tried on the free version of GFOS now and it did not work at all.
I needed to it needed to be the paid for.
So I b I bought one day
You can buy one day of G Force now for very little and having bought one day, it happened to be my birthday and I went, Huh no, I'm gonna buy a year of this as a present to myself.
Yes, fair enough.
Um when you say you're ha you're halfway through, so you're you've done act act one?
I've done Act One, I am somewhere in the middle of Act Two.
Okay.
Yeah, I mean I think I'm you know, uh big spoilers have started to happen in that way.
Yes, I uh Rosanna writes and say I did a better job of uh than she's generally managed of explaining care obscure without catastrophic spoilers.
And the bit I was avoiding is I wasn't even saying the character names because it is a spoiler.
Oh no.
So But the character names are a spoiler.
Yes.
Some of the well there are some things I could have said which would have given hints about what might happen early on.
Before you get to end.
Right.
I have unlocked all of the playable characters.
Yes.
Yeah, which I think is a thing that they say.
Congratulations, you've now unlocked all the playable characters.
Lovely feet.
I have not played Claire of Scure because I'm playing Blueprints.
It's a problem.
Oh, you still play bri Were you playing Blueprints last time?
I think you just started it.
So oh, so you are into blueprints, which is very good.
Yes!
What is time?
I made a dowsing rod.
Hmm?
Okay.
It was fucking useless
Yeah, no, that is the most useless of the things that you can make, I believe.
Uh, readers write in.
Um, one of the things about GFOS now is that no matter what
What tier of membership art you're on?
Your play is hard capped at a hundred hours a month, which is the sort of thing that wouldn't matter for most normal people, but feels quite good for me.
Yeah, no, that's interesting that
I will echo Liz's I would be fascinated to know how reaction-based games work with a internet-based lag.
Interesting.
I have I have fiber.
I mean I have quite a good internet connection.
I mean I haven't tried doing it on the run.
People say it works on the run.
Yeah, but like I couldn't I couldn't do the reactions in Jedi Survivor on a PlayStation that was connected to me, like, in the same room.
So introducing a lag seems like it would make that worse, but
Ma maybe maybe not.
There must there must be some way they a account for it.
Um otherwise I just don't think it would work, right?
Because you need kind of probably subsecond precision for some of the uh stuff in Clare Obscure.
Me maybe not for story mover for the expert modes, I believe like the parry and to one windows are smaller.
I mean remember I'm playing on story mode
Yeah, you're playing on sorry mode, but people who want to play on expert and g by GeForce now to play it would not be content with uh oh it's a bit tricky, play it on sorry mode, I'm sure.
Anyway, that was my bit Cassella wrote in about coffee and said
Uh well he's of course skeptical of number one thing in the world for any given category, calling Onyx Lac Coffee Lab the number one coffee in the world is supremely defensible.
Who can get a RogersCon
bid going so we can evaluate and I'm like, okay, fair enough.
It's clearly very good.
So I want to go now.
I've never been to Arkansas, because why would you?
But
If there's good coffee, that's why.
So alright.
Yep, someone have a com near there and we can have a road trip.
We also heard from Lillian Edwards who basically said
Haven't bothered to listen, but I could do with a recommendation for Swimfose and Lillian.
We recommend that you listen to the previous episode, or indeed the one before that.
Ali Baker Brooks asked whether um I would be trying Citre poured by a nonchalant waiter.
Um so I have had citre before.
Uh it's very nice.
Uh for those who don't know this is a northern Spain thing, it's a it's a cider.
Uh but they pour it, you pour it from head height into glasses on the ground to aerate it.
And this is quite wonderful watching someone do it.
I'm dyspraxic, so the chances I will ever do it are nil.
Uh but my brother-in-law owned and operated a bar in Malaga
for a number of years and so he is he's rather good at it and uh and is is usually very au fay with where the good bars are in any place he is.
Um you're you're actually gonna be not far from where we're going.
Um cuz yeah.
Um so I will have to try this.
This sounds good.
Yes, also um you should have um Favada, which is like
Spanish castle, effectively.
But it's basically just Spanish Spanish pig based meats in a stew with beans.
Though though n though not if the weather is like this, maybe.
No, have it anyway.
Okay, I hear you.
Yeah, you won't be eating it till like eleven PM or something, so it'll be fine.
Oh yeah, that's other th I bloody love Spain.
But I will say that like
So the thing with Hijon is that so this week it is not gonna get above 26 and in Newcastle it's not gonna get above 21
Oh sorry, not gonna get above twenty three.
Sahihon is about three degrees warmer than Newcastle.
So it's not like you're on the Costa del Sol, right
'Cause it's ill it's on the north coast which does a lot of good work.
But it will be pleasant sitting outside weather for many hours.
Yes.
Yeah, so so we are going to Olieros.
In Galicia.
Yeah yeah yeah we're in Galicia.
Psh Uh well ignore everything I've just said, 'cause all of the things I've just said are Asterias things, so Uh-huh.
Don't know how much any of that applies in Galicia.
They might I mean I assume they're not
I mean, you know, I assume they're not completely out of the question, but Asturias is the next one along.
Yeah, no, I'm very much wanting to go to Galicia because it's um it's one of the places that has Celtic music.
In the last couple of weeks, there has been Eurocon 2026, which was Metropolcon in Berlin.
And uh we had a roving reporter on the ground.
You did?
And I so I went to um Metropolitan in Berlin, which was held in an area of Berlin called Veding in a kind of
restored crematorium and modern conference centre.
Um there and I had never been to Berlin before um so I kind of every day we got up and we did some touristing in Berlin and then we got to the convention and then we
sat in the pleasant bar just outside the extremely hot conference centre and um drank beer with our friends and made arrangements for dinner and then went out to dinner
And um so luckily James Bacon did a fantastic job of reporting on Metropolcon, um, both to me at the time actually, uh where he said lots of interesting things and also
on file seven seventy, which we're going to link to that.
Um so I did get to just a couple of things and otherwise I really just
h hung out with people which was great.
Um the convention was clearly great, everyone was buzzing, everyone was talking about
Lots of S for stuff.
The S FIS meetings was one at nine o'clock in the morning, which I didn't go to, and one at twelve thirty, which I definitely should have gone to, but I didn't go to.
Um so I didn't actually get to any of the S for stuff because I was too busy enjoying Berlin.
I have no regrets.
Berlin is amazing.
It's a really it's like a world capital.
So it's got all sorts of world capital things and it also has a bunch of really interesting twentieth century history.
Um which is an understatement
Fortunately, James Bacon went to these meetings and so we can rely on his reportage.
So thank you very much to James for that.
We pretty well can.
Yeah.
Well I I just said that I think.
Yeah, but I think I think what we're implying is that maybe our roving reporter is not really much with the actual reporting.
Yup
Yeah, no.
I'm afraid your roving your roving reporter basically it took about two minutes before sh before she went, Oh wow, Balloon's amazing.
I need to do Berlin.
It's possible that sending a woman with uh definitely no ADHD diagnosis uh into a target-rich environment is not the good way to get uh linear reportage back out again.
But it does sound like you had a wonderful time.
Hmm.
I had a fantastic time.
I've written a little bit about it for um Lee Edmonds Fanzine Chatterbox, which is probably only Fanzines, which he does about every three days.
So my bit is published already.
I j I have this vision of Alison like in Berlin in the evening and she's like, I'm gonna go do some program and then she sees a lightning bug off in the distance and she just starts following it like in a Pixar movie.
I mean the lightning bug's kind of generally a person with some interesting chatter.
Like I I I twice went to cocktail bars with Tabby Coxon.
Yes.
Um which is the sort of thing that I like to do.
And one of them was okay and one of them was fantastic, so I have a recommendation for a cocktail bar if you're ever in Berlin.
And I twice went to kebab shops with Dave Hodson.
Uh it's the same kebab shop which is kind of funny.
Does Dave Hodson do a oh no, I was about to say does he do a kebab shop walking tour in the style of Tammy Coxon's cocktail tours?
But if it was the same one, you'd have had to go out, do a loop round the block and then eat another kebab, and I doubt that's what happened.
Yeah yeah.
No.
So we went to the we went to it the first time and we were just going, I don't sure if it's good or not, and we ran into Emma King.
and she said, Oh no, I had one of the best kebabs I've ever had in my life there And I was like, Oh, okay And then the next night, um s we were going with some other people and they said, Oh we really fancied trying this kebab shop and we went, Oh no, we don't mind going back, that was so good
Excellent.
I do I mean I bloody love a kebab.
I mean in this case it was a kebab shop with pretensions, so it kind of did stakes and things.
I didn't have a stake but I did have I did have shish not not in kebab form.
Um
But it is still shish, so it is a kebab, right?
I had um I had periperi donna kebab yesterday and it was very nice.
Oh that sounds good actually, as long as it's not too hot.
Um, it was it was probably beyond the Allison limit.
Yeah, I bet.
But I liked it.
So one of the things that's interesting about
Eurocon is that bidding for future Eurocons is a bit like Eastercon, actually, incredibly healthy.
So next year Eurocon will be in Lisbon.
I think
I s John is planning to go to that so we'll definitely do a better job of reporting than I did this time.
Yes, John?
Yes
I'm I'm going to Lisbon for Smovcon and I'm not sure I can weather a second trip to Lisbon in a year particularly Oh it's it's September, it's not gonna be that hot, so maybe.
Hmm
Lisbon is great though, so you know.
And then the year after, twenty twenty eight is um SFK SFKon in Zagreb, which will be the fiftieth
SF Ericon.
It's the oldest and longest established SFCon in Zagreb and I have never managed to get to it though I have thought about it in the past.
I don't think it's the first time they've had Eurocon by any means.
Um, so and then there are bids at the moment for twenty twenty-nine for Poland and Bulgaria, and both of those bids have s kind of talked about they might move to twenty tw
twenty thirty if they lose.
Twenty thirty currently has bids for Birmingham.
That's B S F A mega
Eastercon, Eurocon, BSFA extravaganza bid, and then one for Italy, and then there is a bid for
Belgrade, Serbia in twenty thirty one and a bid for Copenhagen in twenty thirty two.
So that's quite a lot of EuroCOB bids
Yes.
And we I also had a l couple of conversations with other people who were like, oh, it would be great to bring Eurocon to my city.
So so it was good.
I think there's a lot of there's a lot of excitement there for Eurocon.
And and Eurocons Eurocons are you know, this Eurocon was completely unlike last year's Eurocon.
And and although there is a s kind of small
travelling membership.
There are a lot of people at Eurocon are local people to the Eurocon every year.
I I got the list of upcoming Eurocon bids um primarily from from from James's um File770 uh reporting.
Um thank you very much James.
Um I've checked with the SFericon uh Discord and I did some Google translating to Croatian
And they say that SFERICON 50 is probably going to be the second weekend in May, but it's not confirmed yet, but that is usually the date of Sphericon.
So um probably then.
I'll put that in the show notes, listeners.
That partly inspired by um a lock from Kev McVeigh where they said effectively
the the dates were not well established for the Portugal EuroCon in advance.
But I mean they they announced their dates at least in in December 2025 because that's the earliest I go back on the Internet Archive
on the relevant website.
But yes, I do find it fascinating that Eurocons don't announce their dates at the SFIS meeting that they're selected at
And I think one of the things I said to Kev is like it would be good to have some more discussion and reporting on how Eurocom works.
So I'm very glad that that has uh ended up happening.
And hopefully it can carry on happening.
Although mostly from James Bacon.
Yes, I mean I think Esphys is still is still very interesting because one of the interesting things that happened, um
at this year's um Eurecon, which is that um Alan Stroud is one of the UK delegates because Alan was the person in the room.
when the delegates were chosen, right?
It's just who turns up.
And so then he presented for the S FIS Awards largely the winners of the BSFA Awards, which I think is completely reasonable, right?
That's a a not at all a bad way.
to say this is how the UK chooses its um it the things it wants to submit to the USFIS awards.
But Brian Lisbett sat in the bar with me and talked about how this is done in Ireland.
where I think Carol Connolly is the delegate and she spends quite a lot of time getting together thoughts from Irish fandom and
to to pull together suggestions for that.
So it's a different sort of thing.
I d I didn't I didn't think, oh God, if I had been in the room I could have become the um
UK delegate and that would have been great.
Um I didn't i i you know I thought, oh gosh, I might have missed a bullet there.
I don't really want to be the
UK delegate, but also equally I do not think that World Fantasy Convention would have been most people's pick for the best British convention of last year.
Possibly not.
Yeah, and that was what was put forward by the delegate who was the person in the room who had run World Fantasy Convention.
It does seem it does seem odd.
It's not clear to me how I was reading this and
'Cause 'cause I read James also mentioned Carol Connolly in his Far Seven Seventy write-ups and that's great.
Sounds sounds grand.
I guess I have two questions, which is firstly, it's not clear to me
what the difference between like a delegate going round and asking everyone at EastCon would be versus the award that everyone in Eastercom can vote for.
Uh and I know obviously you've got the BS FA component because BSFA members can also vote for it, but I'm like, yeah it does seem that seems fine
But also, it's not clear to me what happens if a nation who attends the Espros meeting what if what if there was a group of British fans who didn't think this is how didn't want Alan to represent them.
W does Esther have any rules about that?
Or do you arm wrestle with a wounded wombat?
It was unclear to me, because I don't know what to do if you disagree that this is how the British system should work
Turn up at Lisbon and and indeed arm wrestle with a wounded wombat.
I Yeah, that that is that that is a that is an extremely bad bad way for it to work.
Well I don't know
But I mean I I remember having almost this exact con conversation with somebody at the C my first convention, which was the C CON eighty-four
Eastercon, which was also the Eurocon, at which I was going around trying to achieve everything it was possible to do at an Eastercon in one weekend.
It doesn't sound like me, does it?
Because one of the things was all the S for stuff and I was like, Oh, should I go to these Esphys meetings?
Because, you know, it's interesting to know how all the European stuff, this is must be very exciting.
And the people I was with were basically like
Like, oh no, Esther's is super weird.
Nobody understands how it works, it's dark arts.
That's fair.
It does seem to me like now I know
that there's a British delegate to the Espos meeting, that should probably be a thing that British Fandom has input into.
But it's not clear to me how you would do that without seeming like
You were rather trying to force the issue, you know?
I i i I think it rather pres it either presumes everyone in the fandom cares little enough that one person can do it and no one will mind
Or it presumes that there are formal structures in the fandom whereby these things can be debated and voted on.
And I don't think either of of those is true in Britain, and that makes it hard.
'Cause I think there's no way there's no like it's not like I can go to East Con and be like, we need a standing committee, let's discuss it at the East Conferences meeting.
'Cause ha ha ha ha ha.
No, that's not how it works.
I find it very interesting, the assumptions it sort of tacitly makes about national fandoms.
I shall be interested to go to one.
If you are a Eurocon regular, write in.
Presumably at the meeting at which, like, Alan was selected as the UK delegate, no one else waved their hand.
So presumably if someone had turned up at the meeting and said, No, it is I who should be the UK delegate, then there's some kind of mech
Mechanism?
Because what European meetings need is more British people being loud and argumentative.
No, but presumably they're not can't we relying on a consensus forming in each one of many countries.
Or maybe maybe they are.
That's that's my yeah.
Alright.
If it 'cause if the mechanism is the people from that country have a giant argument in the room until it's settled
That that doesn't seem like good business.
Like and I also I don't want to be that guy.
Which isn't to say like I mean it might be that it's just fine and that we don't need to change anything
But like it is I would be curious to know how you go about changing things if you want to on a national level.
And now Birmingham is opposed by Fuigi in Italy.
But not Copenhagen, 'cause they've moved to twenty thirty two, so Don has time to decide which Legoland to go to.
Yes.
And also because both Sophia and Warsaw have said they might defer to twenty thirty if they don't win in twenty twenty-nine
It could be a three-way race potentially.
Mm-hmm So one of the things that was interesting so I think the thing about you s talking about the last thing Eurocon needs is
loud British people being argumentative.
I think it's quite right that it is a it is a it's a fanish space that is
Uh very much not about Britain or America and I think that is quite cool.
Um
And we have always been very much a sideline to it and and that is why Birmingham, even though we see it as being like the Eastercon, Eurocon, BSFA, extravaganza
Thing is not necessarily seen as a particularly strong bid by S Fus Regulus
Which I thought was really interesting.
To to be fair, it's not seen as a particularly strong bid by Eastercom regulars either.
Uh source have consulted an Eastercom regular in the mirror this morning
And asked him some tough questions about this, Alison.
I okay, I was trying to be polite.
Well no, but I think the way you describe it makes it sound like everyone in Britain is very excited about this bit.
And I and if you're listening to this episode for the first time
I think it's fair to say that even in Britain there is some scepticism about what the BSFA's motives are in doing this.
Yeah.
Yeah, but I mean that's a again like
Maybe a smallish chunk of people that we can consult and discuss and there may be a lot of people who are quite keen on it.
True.
Silent majority, yeah.
Um so
So one of the things about SFOS was that it i i it in at the meeting it's just referred to as the English bid, as if it is uh well, English for a start off because I don't know
rather than UK or British.
But it is seen as kind of English fandom is behind this, which in a way that I think it might not be.
Uh m Eurocon, although it's not the case for Archipelicon, most Eurocons are attached to an existing series of conventions.
And
So that I guess attaching it to Eastercon would do that, but it's not necessarily gonna be an Eastercon, so
It it it it's all quite complicated.
No, but by the time the bid happens it will be known if it's an Eastercon.
Yes.
There's but there's no way for both votes to know that the other one is true.
You have to pick one to go for first, because of linear time.
Yeah, you do.
And that is beyond all of our control.
The other one of the things I did do at Eurocon was go to the closing ceremony, which also had a
a fine auction which I learned lots of interesting things about auctions from.
But it awarded the Andreas Kushke Prize.
And the Andreas Kushke Prize is unexpectedly a uh a prize in honor of a fan Andreas Kushke who is no longer with us.
Um and it is given to ordinary helpers, room managers, bag checkers, table movers, the people who
The countless people working behind the scenes.
So therefore it is a Eurocon equivalent of the DocWeir Award.
And this year it went
to Constanza Hoffman, who um I think we all know and like a great deal and I'm assuming that's true for you too as well.
And I was absolutely delighted to see that.
Constanza is somebody who works incredibly hard for a bunch of conventions and it was really good to see.
Yes, that seems extremely delightful.
Yes, Constanza does amazing work.
And she's a lovely, lovely person.
Indeed.
And it it is nice when you have both, isn't it?
Yes, it is.
Ha ha Uh but yes, in this case we do, so that's lovely.
Both Eurocords I've been to you know, I I kind of feel like it's going to become a regular for us.
now that we're into our travelling years, though maybe not next year because of it being in the city we've just been to, but very much hoping to get to Zagreb
Yeah, I would say so Renee said in uh Intergalactic mixtape about Octop Octothop, raise your hand if you have never heard of Eurocon before they covered it.
And I don't think we're quite in that position.
I had heard of Eurocon.
I've even been to Eurocon, but I think I'm finding out a lot more about it and it does sound like a cool thing I would like to go to more of.
Even if I don't really understand how it works.
It I think it's the it's the flip side of what Alice has said about it's a vanish space that doesn't involve Brits and Americans.
And the flip side of that is that
there has not been like I was looking at File 770 reporting and there's like hardly any.
And I and and I would be very fascinated to know if there are any European fandom blogs in any language that do a similar thing to File 770.
But it does seem to me that having done Googling, it does not seem this stuff is being reported on in English anywhere.
Try and start covering that going forward.
Mm-mm.
And so other people, because there are other
Uh you know, there are are other British people who travel to Yuricons, so over eight hundred and fifty members, so it's actually a convention of some size.
I think
significantly bigger than last year when when it was a convention in a place that you had to take a plane and a ferry to get to from most places.
So co you know, Berlin's a very central European location.
Yes.
Alright, shall we talk about the Whispers Business Meeting?
Summer of FUN!
For new listeners, you'll have noticed the music changed and that is a signal that it's time for the Summer of Fun.
in which we will get into the minutiae of wusfus and as and all sorts of sufuses.
I could do my pick and then go off to the cricket and leave you two at it.
I mean you can if you like.
I'm also not completely opposed to that either.
If you want to do that.
Yeah, but you're you're not allowed to then send us objections later on.
Next time we record, I'm going to do an extended letter of comment live.
Okay, I'm not sure that's any better than I don't know if I want to give you like twenty uninterrupted minutes to tell me and John how we were wrong in hindsight
So we're going to discuss the business meeting agenda for the World Science Fiction Society.
So these are the business meetings which take place at Worldcon.
Or should I say these are business meetings held by Worldcon.
You should, Liz, because of because of F.
2.
Be because of amendment.
Uh foreshadowing.
And so the first one of these will take place as we mentioned last time on uh Friday for most people.
Saturday if you're Australian, sorry.
And we're going to go through some of the business in the agenda.
So for people who are new here, the WISF business meeting presides over the WISF Constitution
Uh and um was what they called the rules of something?
Oh the standing rules.
Yeah, standing rules.
Basically things that world cons have to do
And if you want to change the things that World Cons have to do, you propose to the business meeting that we amend the constitution.
And if people agree, they will vote with you and then Not always, but mostly.
Sometimes if people agree, they will accidentally vote against you if it gets confusing.
And that happens one year and then the vote has to be ratified by the business meeting of the subsequent Worldcon in order for it to take effect.
So you have to get things through two WorldCons.
So there are basically three types of business on the agenda.
There are the things labelled in D.
The D is the um resolutions, right?
And F is constitutional amendments
Yeah.
So the C which is disc uh changes to the standing rules, which we are not going to go into.
D is resolutions.
Uh E is business passed on.
Which means things that were ratified last things that were proposed last year and will be ratified this year.
We won't go into those in detail because we discussed them quite a lot last year
And last year it was like a 90-minute pod, so you can go back to that if you want.
And then there's section F which is new business, new things proposed this year.
And we will discuss that a bit, but we may not discuss it today.
Yes, and which thank God is quite a lot shorter than it was last year.
Mm.
So basically, yeah, so so Wuspus is governed by
Four things, the as Liz mentions, the Constitution, the standing rules, the resolutions and rulings of continuing effect, and Robert's rules of order.
And it is in that order that
things take precedence.
So if something says it so the constitution is like the top document and then you fall down the documents until you get to Robert's rules if you don't have a
was for specific ruling or standing rule or constitutional statement is my understanding.
It might be that that understanding is wrong, but that is my understanding.
Yeah, and let's be honest
I still don't understand Robert's rules for order.
So I think it means that Roberts have to stand in alphabetical order when they go to the business meeting.
Roberts, write in.
Do they stand before or behind the marks?
That is a good question and I don't know.
Mark, write in.
M if Marl Plummer could tell us whether he's ever stood in front of or behind a robot and in what circumstances, that would be very useful to resolving this uh query.
But effectively the C's modify the standing rules, the D's modify the resolutions, and the Fs modify the Constitution, as do the E's.
I don't know why we do it that order, but that's the order it happens in.
There might be a special order to how things take effect, but let's just we'll just get on with it.
Yes, so shall we talk about the Sparkle Unicorn Committee?
Yes.
The Sparkle Unicorn Committee was the uh joke name for the Committee on Ethics and Whistleblowers.
which was chaired by Alana Vincent and included listener Farah Mendelson.
And basically this came out of last year's meeting.
It was decided last year that there should be a committee to work out whether or not
Um whispers should have a code of ethics and if it should, what it should be and how it should work.
And the the Ethics and Whistleblower Committee brought um three resolutions and a constitutional amendment.
The resolutions basically say here is a code of ethics, four whispers, uh, which is the first resolution, and it seems a fairly good code of ethics.
It covers stuff like whistleblowing and conflicts of interest uh and ethical standards.
And then the second proposal or the second resolution is a resolution uh to have a whistleblower policy.
The third resolution is to um create an office.
that would be the ombuds office and would basically give you a place for whistleblowers to blow the whistle.
And then the constitutional amendment is to make that office permanent.
So the constitutional amendment would make it an office that happened going forward, whereas D would make it uh D4, which is the third uh resolution, would make it a thing that happened now
So you need half of it to do the bit before the constitutional amendment is ratified and then you need the constitutional amendment to keep it going in perpetuity.
I think the the key bit is that
Resolutions don't need two years of ratification and constitutional amendments do.
So if the constitutional amendment goes through to have
uh an ethics ombuds office, then it would take two successive business meetings to get rid of it.
Whereas I think if the resolutions go through it would only take one.
And so therefore then you also have this backup that they can't be immediately undone by one meeting.
You'd need two.
Yes, exactly.
I think in general, this is good business.
In that I think it is probably true that there should be a code of ethics for Wispers.
just that we all know what we think ethical behavior is.
I think this code of ethics seems relatively uncontroversial to me.
There's nothing in there where I think, ooh, that's a bit weird.
I think the primary thing it does is uh create the whistleblower policy.
I think having an official route for whistleblowing that goes to the ombuds office
would be a good thing.
The stuff that came out from Chengdu eventually came out after the whistle was blown by Diane Lacey.
after the damage had been done.
But in order to blow the whistle she came out publicly, having an anonymous route to whistle blowing which communicates directly with the committee.
Um so the Ombuds Office would be constituted under the NPC.
And what that means is that the NPC as the body that can levy sanctions on organisations that are using the Hugo trademarks or service marks.
Having the Ombuds Committee be able to recommend the NPC take action means that the NPC can actually take action based on the anonymous whistleblowing that comes through to the Ombuds Committee.
It's impossible to tell whether this would have made a difference in Chengdu, 'cause we don't know whether anyone on the Hugo team would have blown the whistle anonymously, and there would be never any way you you can't you'd have to run the universe again.
Doesn't work.
But I think given that the whistle was eventually blown, it at least doesn't seem completely out of the question that Diane Lacey might have blown the whistle anonymously had that route been available.
earlier.
And I think that might have made a big change.
And if that happened, the NPC could have levied sanctions immediately.
And so it could have made a huge difference to what happened in Chengdu.
And I think I think that's a good thing.
I think if there's never a breach of ethics that leads to anyone blowing the whistle, none of this does anything.
Because all of the office that all the office would do in that take case would say we received zero reports.
So if the whistle is never blown, none of this actually triggers, really.
And so the only reason to oppose it is if you think someone's gonna blow the whistle on something that you want to do
And I am skeptical that that is a good counter-argument to this because I'm like, well, that probably means we should have the code of ethics then.
So yeah, that is my basic thoughts on this.
I think I largely agree and I I think I wanna like commend the Sparkle Unicorns for I think going away, discussing it for a year and coming back with something which I think is probably workable and is at least a starting point that we can get going now and then modify if
necessary.
I mean maybe it will never be necessary, but I can't see anything in these policies individually that I would disagree with having
My I think the only so the only thing I maybe s have slight issues with is that it feels like we're kind of um it feels like I have often thought of the Mark Protection Committee as those people
who make sure that we register the hero trademarks and no one treads on them and stuff.
And so we are I think in this case because the only kind of mechanism to do this is that we have to do this by having the Mark Protection Committee
Basically they have to agree and they have to enact this.
It puts more more kind of not really obligations but more kind of importance on the Mark Protection Committee
Yep.
And I mean I think the problem the thing with Chengdu is I guess the whistleblowers would be whistleblowing to an ethics onwards office
And then it's kind of how much the MPC is involved in this.
And then may it maybe puts a different weight for me on thinking about who I would elect to the MPC, knowing that this sort of also goes along with it.
But I do like the part they're talking about in that the NPC has some liability insurance and that would they'll try and extend that to the ombuds office so that we don't get into like uh sticky problems there.
Yeah, I think that's a fair point.
I mean I think the NPC is already the part of Wosfuss that deals with not necessarily in terms of the community aspect, but in terms of the assets that are held by Wosfus.
The asset that Wisfus has that is the most valuable is the Hugo Award, the service mark.
And so the NPC is the body that awards that service mark and is the body that makes sure that service mark is being used properly.
And so basically the the report says well the the most harsh censure that Wosphers can issue is retracting the right to use the Hugo Award service mark.
And that's only something that the NPC could do.
And so I think for that reason, having it under that committee is sensible.
And I think the liability insurance is also sensible.
But I do think you're right that we need to start thinking about the Mark Protection Committee in terms of the stewardship of the marks.
Having said that, I think anything that makes that clearer is good, because having served on the NPC, I think a lot of the time WorldConchairs will just put anyone on it.
who basically says, yeah, right, I'll do it, why not?
And I think given that that committee does actually wield a lot of the oversight
I think s taking that committee more seriously as an oversight body might be good.
Yes, I think maybe it's not really a change in what the Mark Protection Committee does, it's just a change in the way I think about it, because really they've
You're right, that they have had this power and they do kind of control the the the service mark of Whisfus.
I just haven't really I have thought about it like I think in the same way you're saying as like oh someone's gotta like be on the Market Protection Committee
Yeah, it's kinda boring, just see who wants to do it, we'll nominate someone, kind of thing.
Yeah.
And I think it's also that uh it feels a bit more if we were like World Fantasy or something, there is like a World FantasyCon overarching board.
Worldcon does not have that, but
It's clear if we want to have things like this we need some kind of mechanism which exists kind of over and above world cons
And just by the way we are designed, it has to be Democrat Protection Committee.
Given that the immediate fallout from Chengdu
happened on the NPC anyway, with Dave and Ben being asked to stand down.
I and given that like I think the NPC did hear evidence and have extraordinary meetings in the wake of Chengdu
I think the NPC is always going to be involved with significant breaches of ethics in Wisfas just because that's what happened in Chengdu.
So I think uh putting it under the NPC in recognition of that makes sense.
But I think the insurance, I mean the liability insurance is a huge reason why you'd want to have it under the NPC as well, as you say.
But like I say, it's very important to note that if no one if there's never a
If there is never a breach of a code of ethics that leads to someone blowing the whistle, as far as I can tell, the Ombuds Office will never do anything.
So this really is a if there is a problem
This will all ha this will do things, but if there is never a problem, it does not introduce anything extra other than three people are on a committee, which just reports that nothing happened.
Yeah, well I I mean I will say that
I think under this current code I have a conflict of interest which I would have to declare, potentially.
Is it that we're best buds, Liz?
Are you on the the Ombuds Office or the Mount Protection Committee right now, John?
No.
No, the
The thing is that I have volunteered in the administration of the Hugo Awards.
Yeah.
In some way.
I'm not on the Hugo Awards subcommittee, but I have helped out with the Hugo Awards while also being personally a named finalist.
And that I should potentially uh recuse myself from those roles.
And if that's what you know, if that's what the feeling is, is that you should not have any
role in Hugo Award administration.
I mean I should say that all I did this year was like uh verify uh nominations in categories which were not my own
But I mean if I think under this conflict of interest policy I would not do that, I would recuse myself.
Which I think also is fine.
If that's the general one we want to adopt, which is to have more separation.
then that is fine, but it does lose you a few volunteers.
It does, but I will also say that I thought when we volunteered to do Hugo Awards stuff last year, the reason we could do that is because we had recused ourselves.
And then it turned out that nothing we were volunteering for needed us to recuse ourselves, which I was genuinely astounded by, 'cause I was like but
I'm talking to the final like every single Hugo finalist is getting emails from me on the regular and like I can see spreadsheets that maybe if I was eligible for Hugo I should not be able to see
And I think in the end it turns out that there's more firewalling than I had thought, and maybe that's why.
But I think the other thing this does is it also establishes a
an expectation that is wuss for wide of how that works, because I suspect I'm not the only one that had that, oh, I thought these rules were more stringent than they are.
And so it might be that we do want to like so Liz is talking about the first bullet point in uh the third section of D2.
Yes.
And like it might be that that needs editing and that that is too stringent and if it was in force for a year we'd be like, oh no, this is actually very onerous.
Maybe we should make this a little bit more permissive.
But at least then we have a framework where we can have that discussion and decide as a community where our lines are.
And I think the thing that has become very clear over the last few years is that not everyone's lines are in the right place.
And it would be really useful
or not even the right place necessarily, but the same place.
I think it would be very useful when you discuss the ethics of how Wussfuss is is is conducted.
that we all actually have an agreement on what that should be.
So that I guess might cause very slight issues for the first couple of years, but I don't think it'd be a massive thing.
But yeah, uh certainly I don't think I would have been comfortable I don't think there's ever gonna be a situation in which I am comfortable doing a lot of work on the Hugo Awards.
while not being recused.
So for me, this bullet point doesn't make a difference to me because I'm already effectively following it.
Yeah, and I should say that I've
I mean, I guess the thing here is there's uh there's declaring a conflict of interest and this says that if you have that conflict of interest you must recuse yourself.
Um but there are obviously going to be conflicts of interest that people maybe just declare and don't recuse themselves.
Yes
This is this is a thing I discussed with the Hugo admins when I, you know, they said would you would you be happy to do the same task this year as you did last year?
and there's no way in which I could have influenced any category I couldn't see any any nominations in the category for which I'm eligible and there's nothing there's no h influence I have on the other categories anyway
But I can see that as currently written, yeah, I'd have to do a different I would do a different job.
And that's fine.
If someone else wants to try and figure out how many words there are in novellas, then
I'm sure they're happy to have volunteers for that.
Yeah.
I think this will have a very small effect, but I don't think it will have a massive effect.
Partly because I think
It might be true that we're the w the us, us three, are the only people affected.
So
Yep.
Like and also I think, I mean I hope listeners agree, but I think we have been very clear about what it is we're doing and how we're dealing with
You you have discussed openly during this whole process, like where your lines are and what your approach to not being conflicted has been, and I think that's been reasonable.
And I think probably if any listener had thought it was unreasonable, we would have got letters
Um because I've met our listeners and they write letters.
It might be that that needs it might be that there is that there does need to be some recognition of the facts.
that registering a conflict of interest doesn't always mean recusing.
Yeah.
It is I think because I I mean when I get asked to review for journals, I always declare anything I think could be a conflict and then I leave it to the ed editor
whether they think the conflict is material enough that it needs me to stand down.
And sometimes the answer is yes and sometimes it's no, but at least they're aware, which is the main thing.
Alright, yeah, I think this is mostly good stuff.
Yes.
So I think yes, uh we've digressed a little bit, but we broadly agree with this one.
And I broadly agree with the way of doing it in two parts, I think.
Well I yeah, I agree.
I think it is as you might expect from the people on the panel.
The way it's done constitutionally is um elegant and clever.
Shall we discuss I mean the nitpicking and fly specing committee have proposed some stuff which I think we can just say, yep, fine.
Yeah, in general, most of the kind of twiddling around the edges of constitutional things, I'm either like, yep, that clears things up, or ooh, that's a good loophole that you have found, or in a third class they appear to be just
Fiddling around with things for very little reason.
And I think most of the ones proposed this year fall into categories A and B.
I don't see anything where I'm like, oh, like everything is either oh yeah, I can see how that would make things a bit smoother.
Or oh yeah, I can see how that brings it more into line with what we actually do.
Fine.
C3 and F2 were moved by
various movers, including the Wisp Business Meeting Study Group, which I served on, and they basically aim to remove verbiage in the standing rules and the constitution that imply a physical
meeting to make virtual meetings permissible explicitly.
Virtual meetings are already really permissible due to a chair's ruling last year
Um but this just makes it crystal clear that that's fine.
Obviously I proposed I co-proposed them, so I think they're all right.
Am I wrong, Liz?
No, I think they're good.
Hey!
I mean, I think you know I am on team, yes virtual is fine
Um and this makes virtual explicitly fine and I think that's good.
Alright.
Shall we discuss
Bidding trust and safety.
Yes.
And then that could be the last one, because then we've done all the D's.
Cause we went on quite a long time on those ones, didn't we?
D5, Bidding Trust and Safety, proposed by Brandon O'Brien and Olav Rockney, would resolve that there be a committee, and that committee would discuss whether or not world cons should include safety statements.
Which would address stuff like international travel challenges, local transportation access, human rights policies of the local regime, and any other issues that might affect the safety or freedom of convention attendees.
and it would also discuss the official process of censure or other enforcement that would arise in the event of a convention committee's failure to adequately apply those resources or plans of actions that they had to mitigate such concerns.
And then there's like a full two pages of A4 on why.
In the one hand, creating a committee, I don't I mean like fine, go do it, have a committee.
Because it doesn't actually do anything this year, it will do things in the future, hypothetically.
However, I do think
Given this resolution and what it says about censure and resources for concern mitigation, I don't think this is a good idea if it's not
under the purview of the Sparkle Unicorn Committee.
Because they have just put a lot of thought into Worcester's ethics and how you might have a recourse if those ethical princes
principles are violated, and what this seems to be doing is creating a committee to look at the ethical obligations of world cons and creating processes for censure for world cons rather than Wusfass.
And I'm like, if we want first so firstly two things.
Firstly, it's not clear to me that we want to go down the road of doing that.
But secondly, if we do, I rather think it should be the committee that just spent a year thinking about
how to maintain the ethics of Wusfurus and how to make sure those ethics are adhered to is my basic thought.
Yeah.
I do think it has quite a lot of supporting text, but as you will discover next episode, listeners, I co-opposed a motion with like six pages of extra text, so I have absolutely no no standing to
the complaint on this one.
I think committees it used to be we sent stuff to committee to die.
I think we're actually sending stuff to committee and they are having the time to work through things outside the business meeting and coming back with good
proposals.
So I'm not so down on a committee.
But I think the thing is like, yeah, if you're gonna make obligations on a WorldCom bid
And then there has to be some official process of enforcement.
Then we need to think about what is the actual official process of enforcement, because we don't really have one
This is basically saying the stuff that we normally say will be taken care of by the voters, not voting for bids.
We're not sure that's actually a mechanism that we want to rely on as being the only mechanism until we want to add some extra things in.
um and let's discuss like how we might do it.
And so yeah, I invite a committee to see what comes of the Spark Unicorn committee motions and then think about how, if that's our new framework, how do you put these in there
and see if it is actually workable.
I do think it's good because I think we've had the same amendment moved in two successive years about uh putting requirements on locations to meet minimum human rights standards and
I don't think there's any point in going round that circle a third time.
Uh the way to do it is to go and have a committee go and think about it.
But as it is, I find it hard to I don't think there's any point us saying we
You could you could have like a resolution that bids should think about these things and have a safety statement, but it's got no teeth at the moment, so it's how you put the teeth on it.
Well and also it's worth noting that as written and I uh this is going to go to
Commissy, so like obviously it might change.
But if as written, what this says is that the convention would have to
detail the resources and plans of actions they would have and then there would be uh they would also have to describe the process of censure that would arise if they didn't follow that plan.
And so I guess my three questions are, firstly, I imagine a convention can just say, We're not going to and then if they get elected they get elected
Secondly, I assume it's on the convention to decide whether they did it or not.
So like, if the convention's like, well we did do it, and someone's like, no, you didn't, and they're like, well we did, alright, what happens then?
Nothing?
I don't know.
And and so yeah, I and and thirdly, I think I would quite like to have seen some Worldcon chairs on the proposal list, because maybe you could have gone to talk to people who run WorldCons
And been like what do you think is a workable way of doing this?
And
The fact that they're the only person who's involved with running a Worldcon is Olav who's bidding Edmonton 2030 and his DH4 promotion to LACOM.
But I'd really be curious to see what, you know, Esther thinks of this or Joyce Lloyd or or Kathy Bond.
Or
Anyone else who has run or is going to run a Worldcon, how workable is this?
And what would you want this policy to achieve as a chair?
Because ultimately if you don't have Chair Biden, it ain't gonna work, is my basic thought.
I will also say one of the things that came up in James Bacon's Esfus um reporting
which we didn't mention in the Eurocom bit listeners, is ESFAS have a method to this where they have something called appendix.
X They've got an appendix.
And basically the appendix is X makes it sound cool.
I know, right?
But they've got appendix, and the appendix is basically list.
Here is the list of countries where if they bid for Eurocom, they're not allowed.
And it is a vote as to how like if if if people vote to add countries to that appendix, they get added, and if they get voted removed, they're removed.
That seems quite an elegant way of doing it.
Hmm.
Because then it is the the will of the wuss first, like, well okay, which countries do we as a community not want to see run WorldCons?
The problem is with that
And I think the argument I would have with the Eurocon, although I don't know whether it's as as strong, is that if that process isn't open to
I i if that process is not at a virtual business meeting, it is obviously potentially open to gaming by partisan local crowds.
And I don't know how you I don't know how you get around that.
But I thought it was interesting
It becomes a bit of a self fulfilling thing like if Country X cannot bid for a Eurocom, then it might be unlikely that
it it's less likely that there will be a Eurocon with sufficient number of people from that country to ever vote themselves onto the list.
That might be a good thing, but it could make it quite tricky.
Because it esfaces the delegates that vote
There's only like 36 people in the room who get to vote.
Oh, I see.
Whereas it so I think it's less pronounced in Eurocon than it would be at Wosfuss, because obviously at Wisfurus you could just stuff the room
But I thought it was an interesting take off like how differently Espus thinks about this stuff.
Yes.
Which is just like, well, which countries do we think and for for those listening who are wondering, the countries are Russia and Belarus.
Which which given that those are the countries currently actively waging war in Europe made sense.
But I'm I mean, yeah, and I think you're right there, committee is probably the way to think about this.
I just think that as written
the ideas for what that committee might decide and the justifications do seem very woolly and not particularly well thought out.
And I would quite quite like a committee to have a clear mandate that starts from a position of here are some good ideas.
Yeah, and it sounds like a committee could go away and say, Okay, well this is how other traveling cons do it, right?
This is how Eurocon does it.
I don't know how like World Fantasy does it, but presumably there are also like other US traveling cons that might decide certain states are not going to be allowed to bid.
I don't know.
But they could go and like think about possibilities and come back.
Yeah, and I think we'll make more progress than just kind of trying to set a set of objective rules every year and not voting them in.
Alright.
Anything else?
I think that's all me on Ds.
I think that was all I had in D's.
Are there any more D's?
No, that's all the D's.
There are more resolution D's, but they are being proposed by the trial committee and therefore they're an executive session and so we don't know what they are yet and we can't talk about them on the pod anyway.
So you're just gonna have to come to the business meeting and then if you want Octhorpe commentary on them, go and find John in a bar in LA and ask him.
Yes, you you can also find Liz in a bar not in LA and ask her
So my pick for this week
So last y last month you'll remember I was playing board games about animals and this month, um, it's kind of they're like, Oh, it's a war game theme, so it can be any game with scenarios or dice rolling or wooden cubes or hex grids and I was like, Well, that doesn't leave much.
But we were travelling and I was like, what can I do?
What can I do?
How where can I play definitely play games like this, um, that have these things in or have one of these things in?
And I worked out that I could go to abstractplay.
com, which I have not picked before
Not board game arena is not the only place that you can play board games.
Abstractplay.
com is a website where you can play board games provided they're two-player combinational app
combinatorial abstracts, which is to say, perfect information games where it is just you and your opponent locked in
deadly intellectual combat.
And some of these games are quite headbanging and some of them are quite good fun.
And so in July I have ended up playing a game about a hexagon every day and the first five or six of these
were on all on abstractplay.
com because it was very easy to just go in, sort by the number of games that have been played for particular games and sort by hottest and play the ones that appear to be on a hex grid.
It's it's quite a basic website but it's it's jolly good.
It's got hundreds and hundreds of games, many of which you will never have heard of and some of which you will have done
Um some of which have been commercial games, some of which are just kind of the feverish inventions of the game designer, and I think it's pretty good.
And that is my pick for this month.
Oh board game corner.
Liz, you go.
I was gonna recommend Alison a game.
Uh-huh.
So in the grand tradition of
daily single serving games have popped up.
You could play gerrymandel, in which you have to gerrymander some political districts
in order to, you know, produce a completely unfair result.
And there's one every day.
Is it on a hexagrid?
Yes.
Fantastic.
It's basically mathematically dividing hexagons
And so I think you might enjoy it.
Oh, that sounds good.
Probably wouldn't count for board game for board game purposes, but that does sound like something I should play in July.
So I wanted to mention obviously Alison has mentioned board game arena.
I have recently been playing games on UKAT, which is um
German.
I assume it's German.
It's got a DE uh domain, but it's a German website.
The reason I have been playing it is because On the Underground by Sebastian Bliesdale is on there, which is one of my favourite games
Uh and it's basically a war game if trains are war.
And the other one that I've never played a game on, but has been recommended to me.
is 18xx.
games.
If you want to play tedious games involving trains and stock markets, then that is the website for you.
I sold Sandra Bond's copy of 1829, which fun fact was the original 18XX game.
And that game you know how you need to double the amount of time that it says on the box?
Yeah.
for how long the game is going to take to play.
That game said four to ten hours on the slide.
Which and I'm like, whoa.
That is a lot.
1829 is not one of the ones you can play, but it does have a list of, I would say, about 50 different 18 DX games.
So, um
So yeah.
I've always wanted to try one, but I th sort of think my love of trains would not would not outweigh my hatred of long, tedious games where it's possible to make a mistake in turn one that means you never ever uh could win but you still have to keep playing.
So you know I am gonna recommend to you Rollway Station, which is a it's a solo printer play that attempts to
Um condense the experience of playing an 18x game into a little game you could play on your iPad in half an hour
Maybe an hour.
Oh.
Okay.
And I really like them.
I'm Railway Station two, which I've never actually played because I always just play Railway Station, is gonna get a play in July someday when Stephen says
Not tonight, dear, I'm too tired when I suggest he play a game about a hexagon.
I mean, I heard that Stephen is horny for hexagons, and therefore I can't imagine him saying that.
Um, well, you know, turns out I appear to be I would have said I was like when I started this I was like, oh, combinatorial abstract, Steven is gonna love this because he
i it's his favorite sort of game and he doesn't get enough, but it turns out he doesn't want to play a different one of those every day either.
Okay, fair enough.
Uh right.
I mean I yes, I was gonna say isn't doesn't doesn't uh Stephen love Hexes, but no I'm wrong because uh Shoji is played with squares, isn't it?
So well no it's okay, so
Better X variant.
Now fun fact, the Shogi the the the squares on a Shogi board are actually slightly rectangular because in Japanese games they go, well you if you're looking at the board from an angle
it ne they need to be slightly elongated to appear as squares to the viewer.
So one of the things that pisses me off about all the
orientalist games that pre pr pretend to be Japanese but aren't is that they're all played on squares and the Japanese games are actually played on these elegant little rectangles.
So so my picks now are basically what did I last read for Hugo reading that I quite enjoyed.
And so my actual pick is Cinder House by Freya Mask.
Because I have read now all the twenty twenty-six Hugo Best Novella candidates, I think.
Oh
Yeah, so I've re now read all of the best novella candidates and I was quite surprised to find that while I have not
Quite settled on my ranking.
I think my top three are gonna be Cinder House by Freya Mask, The Summer War by Novi Novick, and The River Has Roots by Amel El Motar, all of which
are either like fairy tale retellings or are kind of set in a very fairy tale fantasy.
The Riverhouse roots and some more are both kind of about like, you know, fairy neighbourhoods next to your own
Cinder House is a retelling of Cinderella in which Cinderella is a ghost.
What twist?
Yep, that's a that's your gimmick.
Essentially, uh Cinderella is uh murdered and her ghost is trapped in uh the house she lived in with her, you know, stepmother and her evil stepsisters and kind of figures out
how far she can go from the house, finds herself far enough away to kind of make it make a deal with a fairy godmother for a night of freedom, goes to meet the prince.
Obviously it's got some twists on that, but
Given that I'm not massively into fairy tale retellings and this is not even the first Cinderella retelling I think we've had, I rather enjoyed it.
I had heard it was a Cinderella retelling because of discussions on the Hugo Girl Discord.
I have not yet read it.
Yes, that discussion was quite funny to me because um even without knowing it was Cinderella retelling, I think I would have noted that pretty early on.
But
It is enough of a a twist that you might might not get it.
It's interesting because I read all the novels and now I'm reading the astoundings, but I haven't gone to novella, novellette, and short story yet.
Mm-hmm.
I have a I mean I'm doing it in weird order.
I have a couple of novels left and a couple from uh a coup more sounding and more.
uh Lone Star to read.
But I think novellas fit quite nicely.
Novellas for me fit with a nice sort of Sunday morning with a coffee and a book
Size, space.
You sort of they're sort of they're sort of written down comics in length.
Maybe a bit longer than that.
But that's kind of the zone that comics occupy for me.
And I will say I do think uh one of the things is that Cinder House felt like a novella which was about the right length for the story it wanted to tell, which is always nice.
No interesting.
I'm looking forward to the novellas.
I usually I usually enjoy them.
So yeah, I will look forward to reading it.
I know Mask has been nominated for Hugo Awards before in Fancast and series
Yeah, they got the the three part series that was in best series.
Yeah, I I've read two of the three and quite enjoyed them
But they are the novels are more maybe overtly romances and also quite a bit spicier than this one.
What's your pick, John?
I am going to pick on the calculation of volume 1 to 3 by Solvage Baller.
Pfft, it's like three books, John.
Yeah, it's three books.
But it's basically the size of one slightly long book, so um
The first two were translated by Barbara Havilland, and the third one was translated by Jennifer Russell and Sophia Hersey Smith.
And this is a story
About a woman called Tara.
She's hiding from her husband, uh and h and and he doesn't know why.
Uh except for when she reminds him, which she does regularly, because she's trapped in a time loop.
And the first book is the first year of the time loop.
And I got to the end and I was like, well that was very nice, but I don't really understand where it's gonna go.
And then I read the second one and I was like, oh, it went to places.
And then the third one goes to more places.
So I liked it very much.
Um I think this has done
This has gone down very well with a few critics.
Notably, I know Neil Harrison has very much enjoyed these and Rosanna Pendlebury has blogged on them at length.
I think it's interesting because they're quite literary in mode and Tara is quite a
an odd perspective.
She handles it in a way that I'm not sure I would.
She she is much calmer about the whole thing.
I think I would have done things like gone to see a physicist, like in um oh God, what's the movie?
Palm Springs
Like, you know, learn some fundamental physics, understand the space-time continuum, bust yourself out.
That is not the way the book uh proceeds.
And they're I've very much enjoyed them.
I will say I enjoyed the third one less.
And I don't know whether that is because of the change of mode or the train change of translator.
I will also say I think it would have been stronger and probably be making more waves in the community if one and two had been published as a single work.
because I think they work better as a single work than they do as two instalments.
And and, you know, I think that's that's interesting.
But yeah, this is a seven part series and the I think the fourth and fifth have also been translated, but the sixth and seventh haven't yet.
So I'm basically waiting for sixth and seventh to be translated and then I'll read them all in one go, because they're all l they're all
just too long to be novellas for Hugo purposes, but they are fifty thousand words each, maybe?
So it's basically, you know
a Brandon Sanderson if you combine four into one.
Um so yeah, that's probably what I'm gonna do.
But I I do want to see where it goes.
Um but I am a little bit worried that
Given I enjoy three left, I'm hoping that that's an aberration and not a trend.
Um so we will see.
But I would recommend them to the listenership.
So that is interesting because I have read on the calculation of volume book one and I thought, yeah, that is
Pretty good, but maybe not really my thing and not planning to read the rest.
So maybe I do need to give two a go and as you say they are again would fit in that novella shaped
space in my reading.
But basically I read them and thought, you know, these are nice, but uh someone else will like them more than me.
Yeah.
I think two is better than one.
But I also think Ballet thoroughly explores what she's doing in one, and by the end of one, you've really thoroughly explored it.
And I do wonder whether if she hadn't been writing them
as fifty thousand word um sort of instalments in a seven part series, uh maybe one might have had a bit more to it.
And I do wonder whether there will be quite a lot of people that read one and they're like, well that was fine.
And I I yeah, I feel a bit I I think and and the th blah.
I guess what I'm saying is I think when I was translating it and publishing it into Engl English, I I might have
Done them as omnibuses.
Yes.
Yeah, I mean that's not it's not a huge part of my calculation, but I am was like looking at book two and going, Okay, that's
still a little bit pricey for a book that I know is about fifty thousand words.
I don't know why they are so short if like
I don't know if that is just the norm in Danish publishing or if she specifically wanted to write them all as particularly short books or what.
So I'll I will probably get around to another one at some point, but you're right, in that the way they have been published has not made me think, yes, that was amazing, I must go out and get the next one.
And if I'd read maybe uh two or three of them together, I might
That was the Octothorpe Podcast, and it's goodbye for me.
And it's goodbye for me
It's gonna be a lot easier to find you in a bar in a specific place.
If you wanna track me down and start asking me questions about like Worldcon committees, uh maybe not.
How how big is Bangkok compared to Los Angeles?
Uh well, are we are we doing the the Oh Bangkok's quite big, Liz, that's what I've just found out.
Are we doing the metropolitan population?
Bangkok is 12 million and Los Angeles is 4 million, but it's not clear to me which bits of Bangkok and slash or Los Angeles that's comparing in the true tradition of metro areas being hard.
Yeah, so this yeah, this i this is a good question because the uh Bangkok the city and Bangkok the province
are not um contiguous anymore because Bangkok the city basically expends into Nov into the neighbouring provinces.
Do you mean contiguous or do you mean like
Bangkok is no longer contained within Bangkok.
Yes, that's the way to put it.
But I think if you look on like world's biggest cities, it's up there.
That seems reasonable.
You know, there's no divide at the province line between one another.
So yeah, d but depending how you measure it, it's probably in the top twenty and LA is.
No.
What about if you do the metropolitan area of like Well I mean because that's the thing isn't it because technically LA Con's in Anaheim.
So if you look for me in a bar in LA, you won't find me listeners, because I'll be in Anaheim.
Yeah.
And Anaheim has a population of some.
Like three hundred and fifty thousand.
I think you should cut all this out.
Ha ha ha ha ha ha!
You know what we forgot to do before Alison left?
What?
The end of the pod.
Oh yeah.
The theme music for this episode was Surf Shimmy by Kevin McLeod at Incompetech.com used under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 license.
0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.