[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 125th episode of Octothorpe, a podcast for science fiction and
science fiction fandom which is coming to you with a twinkle in its eye and a Christmassy
Ho Ho Ho on the 19th of December 2024. I'm John Coxon, I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
Ho Ho Ho. I was going to say Bar Humbug. I just want to have it noted that John instructed us all to
come wearing our Christmas hats to record this episode and I brought a wide variety of festive
Christmas hats and they're discovered that they do not fit properly over my headphones and then
I discover that neither of the other two have bothered. I meant it metaphorically. John's not the boss
of me, I'm not wearing a hat just because he insists on it. I didn't insist it was a metaphor.
If you've said it, if you've meant it metaphorically you should have said metaphorical Christmas hats
not maybe get the box of hat Christmas hats down from the high shelf which is something that I
am not skilled in. I had to get a Christmas hat getting down helper elf. I see. I am sorry, I did
not bring a Christmas hat to the conference I've had so I can only apologize.
Alison waving Christmas hats at the screen is not a good podcast activity.
Is that a Christmas hat or is it just a moose hat? It's a moose hat. A moose inherently Christmassy?
I mean if you do want an art prompt then just draw the three of us wearing a variety of Christmas
hats perched on headphones. 100% done. And with that out of the way it's time for letters of comment.
Who would like to introduce the first one? We heard from Chris Garcia. Hi Chris. He is a tolerant man
but he can't hold with anyone saying the best GTA game isn't either San Andreas or Vice City.
I knew this was going to cause trouble. Definitely not. I knew this was going to cause trouble.
You started it. I've already made my opinions on these clear. Speaking of dimensions by the way
I've been playing Monument Valley 3. Which is more Monument Valley. Did you like one and two?
You were like more of the same. Yeah. Yes. Fair. I like one and then I thought well two is just the
same as one really. Yeah there's more of it. This is on topic for the on brand for me. Chris also says
he thinks having a treasurer who is also a co-chair makes sense especially to make sure there is not
kind of a distance where the treasurer is siloed off and the chairs are not aware of issues which is
also a good point. You just have to make sure that there are other people raining in if you have
a chair treasurer who likes to spend your cash. Yes. And also he agrees with me that coconut and almond
milk are clearly milks. Trees are evolutionarily older than cows. I was listening to the Beef and
Dairy Network podcast as one was talking about leaf milk which is where you take the liquid off the
leaves and it's very hydrating and that was pleasantly stupid. That's water isn't it? That is indeed
the joke. Yes. And Laurie did also comment I'm going to ask for liquidized oats next time she
orders her coffee. Bet it's on what happens. I think they'll ask me to leave. Laurie please
report back. We also heard from Raj on Mastodon where he said he's looking forward to reconnect but
he probably wouldn't have bothered if it wasn't the first Northern Ireland EasterCon so he thought
it feels he has to support it. So that's an interesting one right like I go to every EasterCon.
I think there are more people who would go to the convention straight after a WorldCon that
wouldn't but then he also notes that there will be hopefully two Glasgow cons in as many years
because there will be satellite 9 and the 2027 EasterCon bit and that means he's going to more
cons in a few years than the whole of the last decade and yay conventions. There are also conventions
outside of Northern Ireland and Glasgow, Raj which are also available. Conventions right in.
Indeed. I mean that sounds good to me because I don't think I have met Raj in person. No. Were
you at satellite 8? No. And Raj got Covid at WorldCon. Yes. So yeah no you wouldn't have done.
So reconnect. Raj say hi. Yes. Yeah definitely Raj. But it's a false
what's name isn't it? Because you're not reconnecting you're just connecting. Is that allowed?
I think at reconnect we can only talk to people we already know. I don't think meeting new people
will be sanctioned. Recollects, right in. Again. Right. And then there were Facebook things.
Alison do you want to read out the Facebooks? So lots of people agreed with me in whole or in part
about virtual and there's lots of interesting but not terribly summarisable commentary there.
I wanted to pick up one thing which is that JT wrote and said I think I am agreeing with you
that core offerings should focus on simple things that like hybrid that leverage existing work and
add benefit to impersonate Nd's rather than burdening over work teams by adding additional
layers like running completely virtual streams in parallel. And I want to kind of respond a
little bit on that because I think it's half true. I don't think there's a lot of merit in having
like panels in virtual at conventions except possibly for a very large convention because
I think panels in person are great and there are lots of them and unless you're specifically trying to
showcase somebody who wouldn't otherwise get and even if you are trying to do that I'm not sure
that panel is the very best way to do it. What I do think you have to do though is if you're
having an in-person event then your social happens automatically because there are a lot of people
in the same space and they want to socialise. And the social programme is provided by the bars
and restaurants and activities that you could do in the local area. If you're running a virtual
convention then you actually have to programme in your socialisation stuff and that is a stream
or maybe a couple of streams on its own. So although for Back to the Futures we took all of our
programme from Glasgow we did have I don't know about 10 or 15 items that people had offered to
us that were specific things to do virtually as a social event. And I think if I was running like
in EG if I was running the virtual social spaces for a Worldcon I would want to have some sort of
that programming of that kind going on almost all the time at the Worldcon as an option for people
to gather socially and do things in virtual spaces. This is not necessarily a job application.
It's important to clarify. Yeah. I guess there's an open thing about virtual streams which is like
if you do the social virtually does that mean that people from the convention don't join in
but I still don't know how you fix that. So yeah, it's tricky isn't it? I just I just be happy if
most of the virtual people did join in. That's my first goal in this rather than trying to say
oh if you're actually at the Worldcon in person what you want to be doing is going and looking at
all the virtual stuff as well. So one piece of news we had this week we don't normally talk about
like every award in the science fiction community however the Rotsler Award was announced at Los
Con. It is given annually for one to working with graphic art in amateur publications with
science fiction communities so it is very unusual and it is an actual award for fan artists. I know
there's a Hugo one but otherwise we are there are not that many awards fan artists and it comes
with an honorarium so there's actual cash attached to it rather than just a trophy so that's quite nice
and this year we were absolutely delighted to hear that it has been awarded to España Sheriff
who of course has done cover up for us. Do any of you know España? Who? No yes we're very proud
very proud of my lovely wife is brand new for winning this is um yes it was very lovely news
congratulations España. Excellent news yes very good news
Seattle in 2025 has given us an early Christmas present because they've made the business meeting
virtual and this is very good and no one minds or you know no one yeah don't say what you were
going to say there Tom. How are we feeling about this gang? Okay so what do you think we think about
it on a scale of one to oh that's fantastic holy fuck I'm so pleased I'm going to think nine yeah
some people have got their niches in a bit of a twist I mean I think I think I'm I'm positive
but I think I am slightly less positive than Alison just because I am at the moment we are it's a
pre-kind of a pre-announcement we're very low on detail of how Seattle will actually do the business
meeting the business they're not going to kind of just invent an entirely new set of rules I think
I think it's still going to be a thing where we have to figure out how to do Roberts Rules of Order
in a virtual space I do have confidence in the business meeting team to do that
but I think they've basically announced this a bit maybe a bit before they otherwise would have
because it was smough gone last weekend as we are recording and that is a good place for people
to have discussions about this I haven't seen anything that's come out of smoughcon about it but I think
that's possibly why they did and I guess the other interesting thing is that rather than designate say
a weekend when they're going to do this they have picked four dates to do it and they haven't said
the times yet but I think they're going to do it kind of at different times as they say they're
going to try and accommodate you know religious observance work commitments and times own differences
so I'm assuming there will be at different times on those dates so I can see that if what you want
to do is go to all the business meeting sessions it is probably going to require quite a bit of
rearrangement of your life on those four weekends to try and do that and those weekends do include
like the 4th of July which I understand is a holiday in America so you know you may have to
rearrange plans you have made if you really want to go to all the sessions I don't think there was a
good solution here you know if they decide oh we're going to hold them all on like four consecutive
Sundays at 10 a.m. Seattle time then that will eliminate some people from being able to tend
entirely you can't hold them all on say Saturdays for maximum which would probably maximize and
I'm hoping you could go say late on Friday night Saturday or like late into Saturday for different
time zones because that will exclude everyone who's got religious observances on those days so I
don't think there is a perfect solution but it's going to be interesting to see how this works if
you kind of look at this schedule in the end and say okay the only I can only reasonably get to one
of these business meetings but maybe the thing I really want to discuss is going to be in the one
after can I rearrange everything to do that so I think if you really want to go to all of them you
have some reasonable objections to this new system fair enough but I mean I'm in favor because I do
think we should try yeah I don't think we know the perfect solution but why not give this a go and
see how it works I'm sure if like everyone finds this to be an unworkable system then we'll come up
with a different one but at the moment we have a different unworkable system so I don't object
to conventions trying a different one see if it works better yeah and the the people who spend
their whole worldcon in the business meeting and will now find themselves nothing like as in control
of the power centers as they were before are pretty upset and but I mean I don't see that they
have any more right to speak for worldcon members than all of the other people at the worldcon who
are enjoying themselves all weekend and choosing not to spend all of their time in the business
meeting or all of the people who are working all weekend and so cannot spend their time in the
business meeting or all of the people who are not able to attend the worldcon every year and so
cannot spend all their time in the business meeting because this will in franchise the supporting
members that might or might not might go quite badly I don't know that's the thing that we'll have
to see it is very experimental so there's a couple of things which is like there has to be there has
to be a business meeting at the worldcon but there still will be because there will be a site
selection meeting so like site selection will still be done physically at the worldcon I assume
because I assume that's where the voting is going to happen and at the moment the constitution says
that business meeting shall be held at advertised times at each worldcon it's tricky because there's
wiggle room there as we found out in 2020 but and also it's tricky because there's no actual teeth
to the constitution but like in theory they have to be able to advertise times at each worldcon
the um and I can see that there's an argument for I can see that there's an argument for being
careful about allowing the worldcon government structure to be open to anyone who wants to sort
of buy enough supporting memberships that they can sway things which is kind of what happened with
the puppies in the mid 2010s whereas basically like the hugos ones we opened up to um supporting
members voting um without attending the convention were more vulnerable than they were previously
and that um limiting it to people who attend the convention is in its own way a it's obviously a
gate you're keeping a gate but that gate can be used to um prevent bad actors as well as
preventing good actors so it there are concerns there and I do think we need to go into their
discussion without eyes wide open about that but also I do think that the infraentroisment is
massively um a good thing and I also think that it's unfair to expect people who care about the
worldcon but don't actually want to spend their worldcon just in meetings um though those people
deserve to have their thoughts about how worldcon is governed listened to and and synthesized too so
yeah in general I'm pro um which will not really surprise anyone who has listened to previous
episodes um but yeah in general I am pro I think you're absolutely right that we have to be a
little bit careful because the as we yeah decreased the barrier to involvement we also decreased
the barrier to bad actors getting involved we do and so you have to be able to run this
meeting in such a way that it can't be easily disrupted by anyone who buys a supporting membership
basically just to you know try it but then again that's the thing we see we see how it works
if I had to pick a person on earth most able to deal with bad actors wanting to
troll the business meeting just look would be my choice yeah I do know that in class go
we repealed the standing rules thing about no meetings should we schedule to begin before 10am
or after 1pm local time which I didn't realize at the time didn't really think about the fact that
will give some more freedom to the scheduling of the virtual meetings I hadn't noticed that
say that again sorry I think the argument was no one is trying to start the business meetings
at 8am anymore and so that was kind of an unnecessary standing rule but it does give a lot more freedom
to the virtual ones oh yeah no okay yeah I see what you mean it is interesting because is the
internet a non-smoking environment because standing rule 1.4 says it has to be and who knows if if
someone is smoking on the zoom tricky no so there are like little um there are some little
things here and there that like it's kind of interesting to see how it all insects but like I
agree with you just because there will be difficulties though that doesn't mean that we shouldn't try to
do it and to make it good and like I think there is some gnashing of teeth I've seen a couple of
people being like oh anyone who's criticizing this plan is being seen as being like anti-progress
and it's like well I mean hmm that's tricky isn't it I have strong I do have a strong emotional
I think that there are a lot of people who for whom the the business meeting is the focus of
their world con and it's if you said oh we've just decided not to have filch this year at the
World con but they are going to have to find something else to do with their time at the
convention and and and it I don't think it's going to be easy for those people at all and I think
there's quite a lot of them yeah I wanted to touch on that because I think there is there are people
from the business meeting is there a bit of fandom just as there are people for whom all kinds of
little niches of the World con are there bits of fandom the problem is that in most cases you
enjoying your particular niche of the world con has no effect on what I enjoy but here keeping the
business meetings as a thing that happens in person at the World con for quite a long period of
time is basically preventing lots of people from being able to be fully engaged with the you know
business of the World con so I think it is a little bit different right you know like you stop having
filch it makes no difference to someone who loves the science program they can exist separately the
business meeting cannot exist as a fandom which is not also you know a really big part of how we
run things and so trying to make that accessible to more people I think has to take precedent over
you know the fact that it is going to disrupt the enjoyment of some people's World cons but you
know I get it like if you said we're not doing the thing you particularly love at World cons then I
would be probably pretty annoyed pretty grumpy and you know you probably need some time to
figure out your feelings on it and maybe by the time we get to virtual meetings people will have
at least talk this out for several months and have maybe different thoughts on it my further
point is that I can also see that it is you know there are ways to interpret the constitution which
would be that you can't have these virtual meetings you know and it is going to come down I think
to interpretation of some of the rules and it is tricky because as John has already said there's
basically no enforcement of any of this if a convention decided to ignore it wholesale then
there would be no I don't think there's a lot you could do so I do worry that we're kind of getting
down to kind of constitutional judgment and in this case they're doing something that I agree with
that you could argue is not constitutional and if they did something that I disagreed with
then I would probably be very strongly arguing that wasn't unconstitutional so I'm trying to
like check that I am not basically just being in favor of this because it's one I agree with
because I think if we do just start wholesaling ignoring the constitution then we don't need one
but again I'm not interpreting I do not spend a lot of time interpreting business meeting rules
and Jesse and the subtle BM team do firstly that's an hour I lie uh let's you spend a lot of time
interpreting rules that's why we have a jingle not in any official capacity John and I should
never be allowed to do it in official capacity um yeah so so basically the the arguments that I've
seen against it constitutionally seem to revolve around article 5.1.1 and 5.1.5 so 5.1.1 says
business meetings of us first shall we held at advertised times at East Worldcon and 5.1.5
says the quorum of the business meeting shall we 12 members of the society physically present
and um Kate Seacore on the business meeting discord basically sort of outlined a plan to
filibuster by challenging on both of those points every time one of these meetings is started and
yeah I think it's tricky I don't know what we already know that you can have a business meeting
in a place and the convention online so I would have argued that if the convention is a place the
business meeting can be online and that's exactly the same relationship between the two things because
Conzina did that so we know that that's fine from precedent and the fact that no one complained
when it happened last time um and then I think the quorum shall be 12 members of the society
physically present that gets harder and I don't know what physically present means because like
I'm physically present in this hotel room on this zoom but like yeah I don't know so I think
Mike Leib makes a point that I don't think he's totally unreasonable um he's clearly pretty
knocked this change has been executed without advanced proposals discussion attempt to build
consensus or any other hallmarks of democracy and and that's true but I kind of don't see how you
could because you said to the people if you went into the room whether people with all the power
because they're in the room where it happens have all the power and said we've decided we want to do
it this way they go oh no we're not going to let you do that so you know but but I do take the point
that you know using this sort of structure you could say we've decided to hold the business
meeting we'll have one element of business meeting in the in at the world con for the site selection
but we'll hold the other three in a bar in Seattle in July and no there won't be any online and as
long as I have 12 people there that would actually be legal and I feel like that's an issue so so
they are they're obviously saying no what we're doing here is widening participation and so therefore
we should be allowed to do that and and so they are trying to do it by cultural consensus and I
think that's fine but I think Mike's not wrong that that you could use this to indeed ignore any
parts of the Constitution you wanted to really but that's I would argue quite strongly that's
what they already did in Conziland in the other direction which is why I was so angry in earlier
episodes of this podcast so I think that precedent this fine podcast where we were just starting in
fact yeah and so I think there's already precedent that you can do that that's been used in the wrong
way so using that precedent in the right way doesn't bother me over much I will also say there's been
I think it's a bit unfair to say there's been no attempt to build consensus I think the consensus
has been building for years that this is the thing we should be doing and like there's a few
whole doubts but the reason this is being done is that at a high level in our community there is a
recognition that this needs to happen and like I say that does suck for the few people who really
do enjoy being in that room but I think people who run conventions at senior level are mostly
behind this change and that's the that's really what's going on here I mean I think that's a big claim
to make are the other people who run conventions at high level in the room with you I listen
and I don't know because I think it's wrong to kind of take some of them extra frightened
I think it's wrong to kind of say that to everyone's view is that or that lots of people of high
level are that I know well I think there is a group of people involved in running conventions
who are currently in charge of these these processes who are very much of the opinion that this is
the way it should happen and I think there are also a group of people who run conventions who are
very much of the opinion that it isn't and I think that just because we've had two conventions in a
row where the people seem to be on this side doesn't necessarily mean it follows that everyone
at that level does think this yeah no quite right I mean the example the example being
you know it looked for two conventions it looked like we'd moved to a model of having
world cons be called a world con number and then we had some conventions that were like no we don't
want to do that so we're not going to and it yeah drawing a line through two points is dangerous
but we will see I mean and and we'll discuss the um 20 27 world combat in a bit um but but yeah
sometimes it gives me a warm feeling in my heart to know that we will never run out of
material for the podcast yeah hey no but I think I think in general I think this is a good thing
the fact that like Mike and others have noted that you could use the same loopholes in the
Constitution to do bad things yes you could this is something again that I criticized four years ago
and was told I was wrong and now that this has been used against the people who told me I was wrong
they're like hang on a minute this is open to abuse and it's like yes yes I did point that out
the Constitution is badly written it has lots of loopholes in it anyone I've talked to who has
any understanding of how organizations such as this should be constituted as like this is not how
you do it and yeah was for this is not fit for purpose in the way it's done so we need to start
changing it and this is the first step on that road that's because it's a constitution and everyone
who's complaining about the loopholes in the Constitution that might allow this to happen is
fueling that fire because they have also noticed that it's not for purpose I would I would say
finally I would not put it past Seattle to get around this one by having 12 people physically in
one location that would count as a core business meeting and then we don't have to have that
particular debate this time hmm I'm sure they're going to do that well I'm not sure they're going
to do that but I would I would expect them to do that the question of whether it's at the World
Con there doesn't say that meeting has to be at the WorldCon it says the meetings it has to be at
times that are advertised at the WorldCon it doesn't say the times have to be in the future
this is the sort of loophole in the Constitution that I feel could be abused you know but there's
technically nothing stopping you saying and there's also technically nothing stopping you saying well
the WorldCon is technically speaking being held in Aberdeen but all of the program and the Hugo
ceremony will be held in Brighton like that is allowed in the Constitution there's nothing saying
the convention that people might actually want to attend could be hundreds of miles away from
whether the business meeting and the technical world like the Constitution does nothing there's
so much you could do if you were evil because when Nicholas said you want to run the business
meeting at Glasgow I was like can I have the business meeting in Peterborough and apparently
that wasn't allowed so I politely demurred but it's not not allowed because of the Constitution
it's only not allowed because of decency and I'm very indecent you know don't underestimate the
power of decency and constitutions I mean if you have an unwritten constitution you you rely on
it all of the time
there were updates from Smofcon which I'm picking up mostly from Vince Dockertie's report on file
770 which we will link to in the show notes Smofcon 42 next year will be in Stockholm
and the future bids of interest were a kind of DC Maryland Virginia I think the A is Virginia
bid in 2026 and then 2027 there are apparently two possible bids one being on a cruise ship
from LA to Mexico and one being a different European location oh yeah did you say cruise ship
yes interesting when's that I'm not totally opposed to ones that run on cruise ships but I mean
I'm never going to go on an LA California to Mexico cruise ship in order to go to a Smofcon
but yeah I can't think of any there's been any recent conventions on cruise ships apart from
like the Joko cruise which is similar but maybe not quite the same thing yeah there's the Joko
cruise there's um this isn't quite what you're talking about but there's a convention called
BGG at sea which is the board game geek cruise ooh which in summer 25 is sailing they do one from
Southampton in the UK which goes around Norway and they're doing one that goes from Los Angeles to
Mexico and like you know that does sound quite fun maybe my pick if I had managed to rewatch it
should be that um cruise is the gods thing with Rob Bryden and Steve Coogan oh from the mid-2000s
where it's about like old old stars of your sci-fi show who are on a fan cruise but I don't
remember it was being very good so maybe not a pick that's fair yeah I think they do different
ones every year so like the last one I think went from Spain and just went around the Mediterranean
but yeah but they are not cheap if you thought world cons are expensive I'm it's probably it might
not be too different actually because I guess you get all your food included but yeah you get
everything and there's there are lots of there are lots of festivals held on like folk festivals held
on little ship ship based festivals and um and resort based festivals and they seem to run quite
well despite the fact that the normal model is we all go and sleep intense so yeah I don't think
it's impossible the conventions might it might work for conventions as well actually that's not bad
they're not bad the cheapest end of cruises is not significantly more than you're going to pay
for five nights in Belfast all right I'm going to move on stop googling cruise prices
so there was also Q&A for future world combids and for 2027 there were two bids Montreal and Tel Aviv
and the Tel Aviv world combid has folded for 2027 so they've not folded completely but I think
that accepted that 2027 in Tel Aviv is just not a goa at this time so the only bid for 2027 is
currently Montreal and that will be voted on in 2025 at Seattle probably at the convention as
previously mentioned so I mean it's almost certain to be Montreal then unless someone starts up a
rival bid pretty quickly yeah so so this Montreal bid is being run by the team who demonstrated that
they couldn't run a 600% aspect very well so I feel like if you've got any desire to run a world comb
yeah I might like to put a bid together for 2027 and see if you can have a shout
does anyone have any desire we're not going to run punctuation of the work on are we guys
no but I will do a write-in vote for Alison's house in 2027 if you'd like
yes no I'm not sure we can actually get the 12 people here for the business meeting
the writing campaign starts here listeners
I'm not doing it I'm not sharing a world con never going to happen
look right we're not saying you are we're just saying that you will win the site selection
and you can do with that when you want when it arises
don't you have to file sign like a signed contract with a site because this site's definitely not
signing any world con related contract I don't know I reckon if I get Stephen drunk enough
I was gonna say there are other people in your house that's almost certainly true or
actually Jonathan is probably your best bet I'm gonna have to tell them now do not
not on any account sign anything say you'd like to hold the world con in your house
do you know how small our house is we had a letter of comment from one Claire Breuerley
where she said when Alison talks about her small house she must be talking a different one
about a different one to the five bedroom one in central London
it's not essential it is picking Wolfenstein and you might not think Wolfenstein is very
far from anywhere but if somebody's trying to put the world con here by God you'd hear about it
do you know how much griping we got about Excel we're a lot further out the next cell
Wolfenstein you can get to town quicker from Wolfenstein from Excel surely
that's not the point
what zone do you live in I'm in zone three yeah that's central as I'm concerned
we're at one eight one rather than a one seven one that's the key thing does anyone back in the
days when people are telephone numbers that means nothing to anyone anymore it will mean
nothing to our listeners also I can tell you categorically we can we have we have five bedrooms
all-side of which two of them will not be available to the convention as they're being used and the
other three are full of shite it's gonna be great incentive to declutter your house then isn't it
um yeah so the Montreal Worldcon I would be excited about going to Montreal I will agree
or I will kind of echo Alison's sentiment that given how poorly people felt Winnipeg was run I
am I'm genuinely curious how well a world con run by the same team would be so we'll see we'll see
if they win I should say it is not exactly the same team but it has many of the same elements
hmm I think it is however quite different to the Edmonton in 2030 bid team totally different team
yes yeah totally different team bidding for Edmonton they have they're not I think largely
world connell's hands but that's probably quite a good thing yeah more people more people coming
into the con running community is I think good for the con running community the 20 30 the 23rd
big crew is very interesting yes I'm excited they've put them all on their website you can have a
have a look they cover like a wide range of communities and fandoms and yeah looks interesting
yeah be up yeah but yes I think unfortunately the yeah I don't know I don't know what's going to
happen there because I think people might be reluctant to have two Canadian ones in three years
but if kind of Montreal wins by default that may just harm the chances of Edmonton in 2030
which is a bit of a shame but on the other hand no one else is bidding for 2030 yet so
the most exciting thing on that list for me is a suggested Dutch bid for 2032 and I very much
enjoyed the last Dutch world con that I went to so much that it's largely a haze it was a very
long time ago and I fervently believe that I can party just as hard 32 years 42 years later a long
time later that might not be true jumping back to 2028 there are still two bids Brisbane Australia
for their dates on the near the solar eclipse and the Kigali Rwanda in 2028 bid and they do appear
to both still be bidding and sent in you know communications and questionnaires to smoughcon
and so those that that's the only contested year at the moment now and then it's Dublin in
2029, Edmonton 2030, Texas in 2031 and potentially Maastricht in 2032.
No it's interesting right and the thing on Fast 7E ends by saying you know remember that 2039
would be the centenary of the centenary of the very first world con in New York I think I'm a
pre-support of a Texas it'll be interesting to see whether because here in the time I've been in
fandom the Chicago group have had 2012 and 2022 and so I kind of I guess I kind of thought 2032
might be a year they were thinking of but yeah it'd be interesting to see if that's contested or
whether there won't be a Chicago bid or whether like Chicago might go for a different year that
will be that will be interesting to see how it unfolds but yeah I think the Netherlands bid would
be lovely yeah I think it would be great I mean I don't know if there is any early planning for
the next UK one probably a little bit early to start that discussion only five months after we
finished the last one but maybe there'll be a Dutch one instead and the UK one will have more
than a tenure gap this is like three years after 2029 in Dublin and the last Dutch World con was
three years after a UK World con so it's cut they have very different flavours then and I think
they probably have quite different flavours now as well Dutch World con was smaller then and I'm
sure it would be smaller now than other European World cons but it still might be pretty big because
European World cons are pretty big these days that's a long time yeah still I didn't even think about
2039 2039 is like well the thing is if it's New York it needs to be thought about earlier than
you'd think great because we need to actually work out where on earth would hold it I suspect
2034 will be a UK bid but I don't know for sure but I would I don't know I got feeling in my waters
by which I mean I've given mega 20
did you give it straight back no no she did not there you go then you heard it here first
the news that Vanessa Mae had passed away came recently she died after a short illness and
it's very sad news for this did a lot for fandom and was like I always enjoyed talking to her
conventions and she will be sadly missed I worked with her on multiple conventions and she she
worked on 2018 East con and which I shared and I've known her a long time she was really one of the
people who was instrumental in getting the Glasgow bid off the ground I think people forget this but
it was originally Vanessa and Esther and Emma England but I mean you know we wouldn't necessarily
have had that Wilcon if it hadn't been for Vanessa's input right at the beginning saying which she
wanted the Wilcon to be in in the UK yeah so I think it was 2014 when I met all of Esther and Emma
and Vanessa while working on the London Wilcon and it was always great to chat to Vanessa and we got
along well and in 2016 she persuaded me that I should take the vacant position of precon access
coordinator for the Helsinki Wilcon and you know which is a position I could not at all have done
without Vanessa kind of supporting me and guiding me through the whole thing I had a lot of support
from other people who had done it previously but she was really like the main thing there and she
said you know Carlong do this it'll be it'll be fun and it was fun I remember we you know went to
Helsinki and spent like part of the afternoon just traveling around the Helsinki tram network
checking if you could actually get wheelchairs on off the trams so we could like report this
to everyone but it meant just like a fun afternoon just poodling around on trams so I have a lot of
little memories um like that and yeah very sad tears she has passed yeah I found I found her input on
on access issues absolutely invaluable we walked walked down to the to our site and things like that
at at Harrogate and spent quite a lot of time thinking about Harrogate and how it was going to
work and all of them because it was not an easy site for access have a little class of Grand Manié
in her honour yeah so we'll raise the toast to her I'd have thought we'd do something I would have
thought these could only do something for her as she's a former East Concher
shall we do pics yes although as mentioned I'm not sure I have a pic fine do do pics and I will
tell everyone that the Christmas Carol is great whichever one knows but I will tell them again
I've never seen it what I've never seen it because you know you've never told me to watch it so
how would I have seen it I mean you've you've not really watched or listened and played all the
rest of my pics so I don't know why this one will be different John
rude hang on no yes so 2020 2020 Christmas we didn't do anything like this
in the 2021 Christmas episode we did favorite Christmas songs 2022 you picked it by Stephen King
which you know great shout but festive it is not and then um and then 2023
2023 we talked about festive games and it's just got it's just got a note which says Liz hated by
Emily and Andrew and I don't know why well what did you do to Emily and Andrew Liz no one knows
I don't know Emily and Andrew what did I do Ryan okay see I don't think we've done
I don't think we've done I don't think we've done favorite Christmas films so we could do that as a
pic if you want yeah we could do that unless you guys have pics you actually want to do
Alison what's your thought I've put advent of code I'm um oh yeah that's good job I'm see that's
kind of what I want to do and I'm looking down timeouts best Christmas films and I'm going on Jesus
Christ I hate all of all right let's just do a Christmasy thing there's there's something about
the combination of sentimentality and I don't know just I know it's just the combination of
sentimentality and sentimentality that causes me to really dislike all the Christmas films
hello all right don't you have some kind of Christmasy pic then we can just be Christmasy fiend
yeah I mean advent of code is Christmasy yeah that's what I mean you can do have any code I'll do
my because Karen John could do something else and it will just be Christmas pics yeah all right
it's time for our Christmas pics listeners who wants to do their Christmasy pic first I basically
did not have a new pic for this week and so have changed the entire theme into Christmas pics
um because John asked me what is my favorite Christmas film and the answer is and always will
be the mop at Christmas Carol John gone watch the mop at Christmas Carol I can't believe you haven't
seen it I just love it what's it streaming on I am gonna guess it's on Disney plus but I don't
currently have a Disney plus sub so someone can check that for me apparently it's on Disney
plus you're right wait it's Disney in it someone was telling me the other day that I should try and
watch it on VHS because apparently there's like a song that's cut out of the one that's on streaming
oh yes so there is right let me just get this correct I think there is a song which was cut
um that they put back in for the VHS release and I think they may in fact have put it now back in
for the whole thing so I think possibly there's like a you know remastered full length version
and so I think the one that's on Disney plus um actually has that one in yes it looks like they do
excellent okay I'm quite confused because I remember this song being in there like when I
watched it on the TV mm-hmm but apparently wasn't I can absolutely see where they did it's basically
a slightly sad song that slows down the middle of the film a lot and you know cuts away from
important bits like jokes about Fossebear but it's fine to have it back in mm okay it's great I
mean it is one of those films where it feels like no one really thought about it and then it had
like this resurgence of interest and then it became almost overly a thing to love the Muppet
Christmas Carol but I do watch it most years at Christmas time I love it that's fair my pick is
advent of code so I like to do I always like to think well what has been occupying my time
I'll just pick that and advent of code is a advent um so there's a coding puzzle for every day in
December and all of the coding puzzles are kind of Christmassy themed but really they're just coding
puzzles and I every year the same thing happens which is that I started off and I'm having great
fun and I gradually get bogged down until someday about I don't know the 15th or 16th of December
the necessities of manifesting Christmas overwhelm me and I get stuck and then I never come back to
it but so far I'm not stuck we're on day 14 and I have done all of them almost all on the day
you're supposed to do them and there are people out there kind of when it releases at five o'clock
in the morning UK time there are people out there who are um who immediately type drop the code into
a variety of LLMs and spit out answers and solve it in two seconds and I am not that person so I
lovingly craft all my code very badly by hand and I have a great time and there are private
leaderboards one of them is on the fancon.dev server if you are there so we have a advent of code
channel hidden away somewhere and then I also have a leaderboard somewhere that's just got my family
and some people on it so so anyway if that's the sort of thing you like it's really really good
there's been this is the 10th year and they're kind of advertising the fact they'd be doing it for
10 years it's just one guy who thought this would be a fun thing to do and I think you know he gets
100,000 people doing it which is quite a lot really and it's good fun. I normally start and give up
about day three. More I remember that my job is partly writing code and I should probably
do the job bits of code with my code brain. Yeah I um we do we run it for um the students like
one of the lecturers does like a mince pies an advent of code afternoon at work and I'm always
like oh that's such a good idea. It's a very good idea just don't want to do it on my off time because
like you say Liz I do it a lot on my on time and that is tricky but yeah it is uh
no but it's very good for me because I only kind of code occasionally so doing advent of
codes quite good at kind of keeping all of that keeping some coding brain going and also this
year I've been really good about actually making a little file of helper apps and have helper
programs and making sure that I've noted down where I nicked algorithms from things like that which
will be very useful if I ever decided to do any real coding. That is fair. Yeah I kind of think I
should do it because it's like okay well help you brush up on your code skills because I do
increasingly less coding and I was like oh I should do it or I should like use it as an excuse to learn
new language but then I just don't but now I think with the permission of John's colleague
I'm like still that idea and next year get all the students who want to do coding to sit down and
puzzle their way through it and improve their coding skills. Nice. I'm actually thinking of
running a retrospective event of code thing starting in January on um on the fancon.dev server in
its currently non-existent death to productivity section where we just kind of do a puzzle a week
and say well if you haven't solved it starting from the 2015 one and saying well if you haven't
solved it then you can solve it and if you have solved it then you can make your solution better
or implement it in brainfuck or whatever you want. Yeah. Because some of my solutions are really ugly
I mean really ugly oh my god. I am gonna pick exit the game advent calendar the missing Hollywood
star. So this is this year's this is this year's advent calendar from the exit game series um
Espanar and I have done the exit advent calendars every year since my friend Josh got me the one in
2021 for my birthday which was the first one they did which was called the mystery of the ice cave
and so it's basically an advent calendar you got 24 doors um you do the uh puzzles in the doors
you have to solve the puzzle before you can move on to the next puzzle so like they are to get to
work out what door the next door is you have to have solved the previous door and that is uh
that is kind of a pleasant way of doing it you can't skip ahead and it comes with like hints and
stuff if you are struggling but yeah they're really good um this year's I feel like has been
easier than previous years but the theming is great um so I have been enjoying it very much
and yeah they're like 30 quid 35 quid which for like 24 kind of puzzles that you do over the course
of christmas it was very lovely and um I'm often as discussed I'm often away uh a conference in
December so um it's bany and I do it through like texting and cam photos that is banya sends me and
like or the odd FaceTime um and it's very good and yeah and in this year's one there's one where
you have to use they give you an elastic band and you have to make the box into a musical instrument
and that was very fun it was it's good they're really nice that I would highly commend them to
anyone who likes um puzzle games and yeah it's just it's very lovely I should say that 20
adverts of code is 24 puzzles that you do over the advert period and it is free but it's coding
it's just coding yeah like it as as previously mentioned coding is my day job yeah for for
but no it's it's good did you see anything about the mop it christmas carol apart from
it's the mop it christmas part carol I mean not really it's it's a mop it christmas carol it's
great it's like the christmas carol but with mop it's yeah Alison have you seen the mop it christmas
carol it's got Michael Kane in it um it's on my list I found out where it was streaming
I didn't realize I needed to explain the mop it christmas carol because I just assumed everyone
has seen it it is a really quite faithful retelling of um the Dickens christmas carol
except apart from Michael Kane who is screwed uh they're all mopets it's basically it and it's
got a few songs and it's good I'm familiar um it sounds like I'm more familiar with it than
Alison is but I need to watch it this year I think I mean if you've ever seen that trend on social
media for you know take a movie and replace all but one actor with mop it's that's basically
because that's what the mop it christmas carol is you've just got Michael Kane and everyone else
is mop it and it's never owned and no sorry that's wrong because um Michael Kane's like
Scrooge's family are also humans I guess otherwise that would be like complicated uh questions that
you don't really want to go into in a christmas carol yeah that's it it's like it's never questioned
why you know why why are all Scrooge's bookkeepers frogs frog mopets they just are and it has like
uh Dickens is the narrator so the great grandzo plays Charles Dickens as like the narrator
who knows what's going to happen because he wrote the book which is just an excellent conceit
yeah now I'm um I am it is on the list to watch this year I will be watching it uh a dear dear
friend has also told me that I must watch it this year so I shall I'm looking forward to it I would
suggest we just sit and watch it together don't like simultaneously except that I have let my
Disney+ sublaps and it isn't working in the UK anyway so ah right that was the Octothorpe
podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me and Merry Christmas
ho ho ho
[Music]
I had a really weird hydration drink today where they came and gave me a little free sample of
something which smelled like apples but did not at all taste of apples when you taste it it was
just water it was freaky oh I think they were saying if you like drinking sweet fizzy drinks
this will help you drink more water but it's like what I already drink a lot of water it's just
weird when it smells like apple flavor if I can find a link I will put it in the show notes okay
that makes sense probably cut all that out as being excess hydration checked no that's the after
show the hydration chat definitely not blocked a hydropyloxer bloody hell how does it be no one
knows I'm 25 episodes octa-thorf hydration quarter we already had gamers corner today as well we're
on a roll yep we're can we get to four corners can we be square no one knows the theme music for
this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud and competec.com used under a creative
commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]