Where's our style guide, John?
It's in the shared folder. It's called Octothorpe Style Guide.
Oh, actually, I thought, okay.
You called my bluff, Liz, and I was ready for you.
Hello, everybody, and welcome to the very 147th episode of Octothorpe,
which is finishing its brain surgery with Jeff Goldblum and making its way to the test track
on the 6th of November, 2025. I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
Can you tell I watched Buckaroo Banzai last night?
No.
Ah, never seen that, so no.
This episode is coming to you the day before the start of
No.
V.
Con.
So this is perfect listening for people who are doing that travelling.
And we will see you there, listeners.
Yeah, if you want to catch up on all the Octothorpe lore so that you are, you know,
sufficiently educated for the live podcast and not missing out on any inside jokes,
then, yeah, you've got to get going.
You've not got long, but we won't have any inside jokes at Nevercon.
Probably.
Liz, are you still incandescent with rage that you're going to miss our live
podcast?
Octothorpe?
I absolutely am, John.
Fair enough.
But I will let you have credit for that joke.
So we are on, I think, on the Sunday morning.
So we will see everyone then.
But yeah, I'm looking forward to it.
Be good.
And you know, if you don't go to Eastercon, we can make the same.
Oh, no, that's iridescent.
You'd be iridescent with rage.
Sorry, I'm not making any sense.
Well, also, I don't think that Stunt Liz has ever written a book called Iridescent.
No, I know.
I am not iridescent, as far as we know.
It took a lot of self-control not to call the previous episode iridescent.
But I exercise discretion.
We have some letters of comment from all of you lovely people.
And I'm going to start with Raj.
This is a letter of comment on the Tommy Ferguson episode.
That's 145 listeners, because we recorded the follow-up episode very quickly.
And so.
There are some letters on that one.
So Raj says that he really enjoyed having Tommy Ferguson as Stunt Liz.
And given that most people seem to run a con and then run a mile,
it was brilliant to hear Tommy's enthusiasm for continuing to run cons.
And after show, I'm sure she didn't mean it that way,
but it really sounded like Alison was arguing in favor of cruelty to animals.
I don't think she was.
What?
No.
But he does follow up with,
he owns a copy of the Abyss on DVD and it's classified by the BBFC as a 15.
And I think,
I think Cameron did compromise on the previous home release and is refusing to compromise on this one.
It was cut.
Yeah.
There is an extant UK DVD version that does not have the scene.
But if you want to see it in high quality,
then you will not be able to get a legal UK copy.
Although follow up to that.
Apparently the 4K version is like lazily AI,
upscaled.
If you Google it,
there are lots of film fans who are very angry about the quality of the,
of the restoration.
So,
which is weird given how anal Cameron is about the qualities of his works.
You'd think he would have not done that,
but I don't know.
Hmm.
It was also cut for its original cinema release.
So I did not see that film.
I did not see the rat scene in the cinema.
I think I've since seen it on YouTube.
So there you have it,
Raj.
Alison just watches Animal Cruelty on YouTube.
That's the.
Well,
no,
I'm teasing.
I do not think I do not seriously believe Alison is in favour of Animal Cruelty,
or I would not have made the joke.
Well,
I mean,
I like eating animals.
There's a whole,
whole thing there.
Vegetarians don't write in.
It just showed the weirdness now of like the BBFC in that they can say,
no,
this is something that you will never allow to be released on DVD.
But Alison's watched it on YouTube.
Well,
you know,
it's the dark web in it.
YouTube is not the dark web.
It's just the web.
Thank you very much for writing in Raj.
We got a letter from Paul Weimer who quotes me saying,
he actually quotes me verbatim,
which means I know how much I say like,
and you know now,
but I said basically that maybe if comms only have about $20,000 left,
they should just submit a final report and be done.
And Paul says that 20K is a lot of money and maybe that's super not great.
Yeah,
I can kind of also take that view,
but I'm also kind of going,
well,
by this point,
we've trusted them.
We've done stuff with many,
many hundreds of thousands of dollars.
So I'm prepared to give him a bit of a pass on the last 20K.
But then again,
if there's a comm that doesn't,
we don't think has done good stuff with our hundreds of thousands of dollars,
then maybe that's a good rationale for not just letting them,
you know,
stop doing reports.
And I think you have to bear in mind that 20,000 pounds or $20,000,
20,000 monetary units.
To me,
that's loads of money,
but to a world comm with a budget of like a million and a half dollars,
it's about a percent of their,
like money.
Most world comms are bringing in over a million dollars in revenue.
And so it sounds like a lot of money,
but I do think it is important to bear in mind that it is 1% of the budget.
So it's not to say that I think Paul's wrong,
but I don't think,
I think also you had more of a point than Paul gives you credit for in his
log.
I think.
Although he does mention that,
you know,
his jaw hit the floor when I said that con Zealand had 140,000 pounds.
I think the other point here is that if,
people,
when people are submitting reports,
very few people are reading them.
So very few people actually are paying any attention to what's going on.
Yeah.
That's the other thing,
right?
If we hadn't reported,
no one would have.
I mean,
there are people who do read this stuff,
but they're all called Liz.
No,
no.
Some of them are called Claire.
Yes,
it's true.
I wanted to pick up a comment from Terry Gibbs on Facebook in connection with
this,
who says,
I have been amazed at considering the size of money involved accounting for it
seems a little relaxed.
And so first of all,
Terry,
you have a wild faith in more formal accounting,
which is also extremely good at not letting people see money that they're not
interested in people seeing,
you know,
it,
the relax.
The fact that the accounting is relaxed is not the problem.
The fact that nobody cares,
nobody seems to pay very much attention might be a problem.
I mean,
as long as a few people pay attention,
I think that's enough.
You don't need a lot of people to know.
I mean,
Northumbria is very transparent with its,
its finances.
There's like a briefing every year where the head accountant basically goes through all the money means.
And he keeps having to say stuff like this.
This,
these numbers don't add up.
And the reason they don't add up is because of how we do it in accounting.
And I know it's confusing,
but the reason we do it this way in accounting is to confuse people.
And so I'm doing my best to D confuse you.
And,
and,
Oh,
that last bit's not entirely fair.
No,
but I think if you're an accountant trying to explain accounting things to non accountants,
it can be helpful to be like,
I know that this is,
this appears to be nonsense and it isn't nonsense,
but you're going to have to go with me on the journey for why.
So,
I mean,
I'm a physicist and I don't understand accounting.
Like I have a PhD in physics,
but I don't understand physics.
So,
you know,
I mean,
and lots of people don't understand physics.
And,
um,
seeing as I have twice in my life sat in a room saying everything you've previously learned about physics is wrong.
And let me explain why.
Oh,
but that's also true of accounting.
Um,
but point,
point,
point.
Yeah,
I think,
I think accounting is complicated and I don't think I,
I,
yeah,
I don't,
we,
it would be,
actually,
you know,
who would have been a good person to talk to about all this stuff,
Liz?
Tommy Ferguson on account of his professional background.
So maybe we should have Tommy back like as a fourth member,
because it might actually be interesting to talk about this with someone who understands more of the professional aspect of it.
I live with an accountant and I am not entirely sure that's true.
Uh,
yes.
And,
um,
and my daughter is about to be a tax accountant,
which is kind of related.
So,
um,
Terry Gibbs also says Brisbane in 2028 may rely heavily on the parcel long,
having an idea of how much that might be could have a bearing on their plans.
I think the kind of point about parcel long is that you don't know how much is going to be until after you've run the convention.
Um,
cause it's,
it's what you've got left over.
Yeah.
I mean,
I was going to say that the other thing is I am not an accountant and my accountancy skills go about as far as,
doing my own taxes.
So there's entirely possible that there's things I'm completely missing in the accounts from WorldCom.
Um,
but yes,
back to Paul,
who also says that,
uh,
he thinks Chengdu should make new statues,
all the money they have and personally deliver them,
especially to Chris Barkley.
Or maybe they can pay for a trip for Dave McCarty to visit Nepal so he can properly distinguish it from Tibet.
And I also want to say that Paul also left us a skeet of comment about his Nepal Tibet joke,
which has a nice picture of Nepal in.
So I will put it in the show notes.
Kev McVey says,
I could have tried to find parties,
but I was tired from traveling and a bit anxious of the crowds.
I did enjoy the con,
but it was much more of a solo experience rather than the community I'm used to.
So I'm wondering what could help people who aren't new,
but have maybe had a break or mostly only been to different conventions,
different styles of conventions.
The first world con type panel wouldn't normally attract me,
but maybe it should have.
I thought this was good.
We're going to touch on other styles of cons a little bit later in the episode,
Kev,
which is actually completely coincidental to your lock,
but it ties in nicely.
But no,
I mean,
I think I found the same thing going to gaming conventions.
I'm less familiar with like going to air con felt very lonely in a way that
going to other gaming conventions and going to sci-fi conventions doesn't
for me.
One thing I've been trying to do with the discord is try and bridge this gap
so that people who are new to the community who are into discord can find
other people.
And I did hear from people at Glasgow that found my scavenger hunt.
And if we ran the con channels were very good in kind of giving them names to
look out for the conventions.
They'd be like,
you,
you're wrong about Fran.
Shout out to Frandom.
And so I think there are things we are trying to do,
but I do think this is an area we could always do more.
Like it wouldn't,
it's,
cause it's never going to be a solved problem because human social dynamics
are complicated.
And we talked about the icebreaker that Tommy did at core flu.
And in that case,
like it might not have been there as necessary.
Cause like core flu,
a lot of people know a lot of people,
but like,
I do think,
I do think this is something people are trying to do.
If listeners have any thoughts on how we could do it better,
do write in.
But I do,
the thing I wanted to pick up on was,
I think we do a very good job with people who are at their first world con,
but I don't think we do anything at all for people who are at their first world
con.
Since the last world con they went to in 1990,
like you don't get a first world con ribbon.
You don't get any,
like,
I wonder whether a returning,
like we have scholarships in,
in academia for people who have had a career break and are coming back.
And I wonder if we need to have an approach for people who have had a fan
break and are coming back.
What do we reckon?
I think that's quite good.
But it was very interesting.
Lock Kevin.
Thank you very much.
If you're one of those people,
right in,
let us know if you're coming to Easter con and you haven't been to a con for
30 years.
We used to have a whole concept of the born again,
fifties fans who,
who returned to fandom in the eighties.
I think they'd left fandom to raise a family and then they returned or for
some other reason.
Well,
cause that,
that describes Tommy,
I think,
right?
Like we were talking about that with him two episodes ago and he very much
had that thing where he went away for a little bit and then came back in.
And I think it does,
you know,
life happens.
So yeah.
Yeah.
Carrie and Jim Moat,
I think,
yeah,
I think that's,
I think that's a really good idea because I think especially we do have a lot of
people who have taken time off to raise kids,
especially women.
And it's nice to give them kind of a,
a way back in when,
yeah,
you don't need someone to sit there and explain like,
Oh,
you should make sure to go and visit the dealer's room and know you should make
sure to get six hours of sleep or whatever,
but they might need a,
Oh yeah.
Since you've left,
this thing has become really,
really popular.
And that's why everyone's got 27,000 badge ribbons now and that kind of thing.
Yeah.
And also,
there's a code of conduct now,
please read it.
I'm thinking of an example person who I won't name where we basically had to sit
down and explain how codes of conduct work now.
Yes.
Chris Garcia wrote to us.
It's not common,
is it?
He says,
I did not expect this to break down into a subjective experience versus
objective observed reality discussion.
And it was brief,
too brief.
I don't even remember doing this.
He says he's hoping to go to Corflu in Santa Rosa,
which is close enough that he can drive,
but also far enough that it's almost like the wilds of wine County,
wilds of wine country,
even.
Um,
yes.
Santa Rosa is also the hometown of Guy Fieri.
Flavor town.
Who's Guy Fieri?
Uh,
he's the American service chef.
He wears good shirts made of fire.
I just want to say that I like that Chris is,
uh,
Chris has experienced a reality in which we had a discussion of experiential reality versus objective reality.
And none of us have experienced a reality in which we had a discussion of experiential reality versus objective reality.
And none of us have had that experience because none of us remember it.
So his experience of reality and our experience of reality is different,
despite the fact there is an objective reality.
And,
uh,
Chris,
I hope this small addition to whatever discussion it might be that we had is good.
He reminisces of times that convention shared the same hotel saying the best ever was the Lego con with the steampunk convention.
That sounds great.
But he also had a great time at the convention at the same hotel as a Bollywood fan convention.
Also sounds great.
Which does indeed sound great.
Um,
and I can confirm that Bollywood beats are a good thing to drink to Chris.
He has a guess at how our stunt Liz is next week.
It's not a correct guest.
It is John Oliver,
but yes,
John will be great on the podcast.
If you're listening,
do do right in any time.
He does say,
um,
letting world cons hold on to cash over time is not a bad thing.
There is of course the argument that world cons shouldn't make profits to have to move around,
but that's a religious argument.
I think it's also impossible in practice,
because you don't know if you're going to make profit until the last day of,
well,
until a week after the convention finishes.
I'm going to just do a tiny little accounting thing here,
which is that world cons don't make profit.
They make surpluses.
Ah,
yes.
No good point.
Hmm.
I think that's true everywhere for,
for fan round conventions.
Um,
and that's the issue actually,
is that they have surpluses that we need,
that they need to disperse,
make reasonably account for disperse.
Yes.
Anything you want to pull out?
Liz,
are you happy?
I am happy.
But we loved all of your lock,
Chris,
even though we don't read all of it out.
We also heard from Ed Morland,
who said,
may have to clip.
Thanks,
Ed.
You were right in order to play back,
uh,
when Rosanna is insufficiently appreciating my genius.
And he did footnote that,
but I won't read the footnotes because it's funnier.
Thank you,
Ed.
We have a similar,
there is a clip that exists for Liz,
which just says,
I agree with everything Liz said.
I'll try and work out if I can put that anywhere on the internet for the show notes.
Ming said two things.
The first is that he does not have a Steam deck.
Um,
I'm sorry for maligning you,
Ming,
but instead has an Asus ROG ally,
which I have never heard of,
but Ming has a lot of tech I've never heard of.
So that's not terribly surprising.
A PC based gaming,
handheld gaming console.
So ROG stands for,
if I'm not very much mistaken,
Republic of Gamers.
Uh,
and it's the Asus gaming brand.
We heard from Finbar,
O'Reilly,
um,
who was listening while waiting,
uh,
for the techs,
Octagon sort out streaming.
Um,
I hope that went well.
Uh,
Octagon's very,
um,
tech forward and I really respect that about them.
So I'm sure it did.
Finbar says that they agree with me and Tommy that social media is helpful as an attendee.
And that was,
was something we briefly mentioned during Kev's lock.
Um,
and it's especially true for people attending remotely.
And then asks,
while acknowledging the most cons of,
volunteer run and that Murphy's law applies to tech equipment everywhere.
What more could cons be doing to head off streaming issues at conventions?
I think this is a complicated question.
I think ultimately the thing we would need to do to head off streaming issues is to start trying to stream a day earlier with test streams.
But the cost of hiring the venue in advance to do that is prohibitive for our style of convention.
Yeah.
I think we are slowly accumulating ways in which your tech,
streaming can fail,
right?
Like insufficient bandwidth or things aren't,
we,
we don't have the,
the hardwired links or there's no one who can run the stream on an overly complicated backend or things like that.
So I think we're probably gradually accumulating like the sort of knowledge that we have in all the other areas of how to do stuff.
But we've started later,
so it's taking a bit longer.
And then the problem is that you just get like either a brand new problem that no one ever anticipated,
or,
we thought you'd sorted something out with an external vendor or the hotel or whatever.
And it turns out it didn't happen.
And that is the tricky one.
I think like,
I'm sure that like Seattle's problems with streaming bandwidth were something they thought they had discussed and had us fix for.
And then when you get there and you find that you don't,
there's not,
you're now at a very late stage to fix that.
I think I would agree.
I think we do do as much as we possibly can is the other thing.
Like,
I don't think this is something that we're like resting on our laurels around.
But I think even in like,
you know,
Easter cons do not like maybe have a completely standard setup that you can deploy.
Like,
you know,
the art show is like,
well,
everyone knows this is how the art show works.
And this is how all the bits fit together.
And this is what you have to do.
And so on and so forth.
We are not really at that sort of stage of like,
you plug it in and it works.
Yeah.
Maybe we're not for the art show anymore.
I haven't done an art show for a long time.
So I would say one thing I think about streaming is the fact that we are kind of still figuring out how it works means that maybe we are still incorporating it.
We're still incorporating advancements and new technology.
And maybe there are areas of con running where we should be adding some new stuff in,
but we've kind of got too used to how it works.
And we're not future discussion there.
Ah,
I think that's a very good point.
And I think,
I think it is.
I think that is one of the reasons why we are still trying to iron out the bugs is probably because we know there are still bugs.
And it's not as clear with stuff that's been working for a long time when bugs like gets introduced.
I think that's an interesting point.
All right.
I'm going to do one last lock and then let's move out of the letters section.
And that is,
thank you very much to Farah Mendelsohn for writing in.
Picked con two will be in Perth on the 17th of October,
2026.
Shall we discuss the Ursula K.
Le Guin award,
Liz?
Yes,
because I put this in the show notes for two reasons.
One is that the Ursula K.
Le Guin award winner was announced and it is Rake's Fall by Vajra Chandrasekara,
which means that I'm even more determined to get round to it.
Yup.
Fair,
fair.
I own it.
Having read like the same to Bright Doors and read lots of reviews of Rake's Fall,
I know I'm going to need like maximum brain power.
So I've been saving up for a special occasion and then haven't read it yet,
but I will be reading it.
Are you saying that you've got books in your house that you haven't read?
That's monstrous.
Yeah,
I've got a Kindle,
John.
I can have functionally almost infinite books I haven't read.
And I do have functionally infinite books I haven't read.
I've got several hundred.
I mean,
but this is one I'm definitely going to get round to reading.
The other thing is that we will put a link to the announcement in the show notes.
But I think the really nice thing they did is that,
the actor Eben Moss-Bachrach,
when he was asked during the promo tour for the Fantastic Four,
who would be in his personal Fantastic Four,
picked,
I think,
fair to say,
slightly unexpectedly for the rest of the internet,
Ursula K. Le Guin.
And so they got him to come and announce the award,
which is just kind of cool.
And a really nice way to kind of bounce off that very unexpected little bit of publicity
that Le Guin got from being picked as his personal Fantastic Four.
So that's pretty cool.
Well, and what's hilarious,
because I remember it happening,
and I remember that the other three people,
so Pedro Pascal,
Joe Quinn,
and Vanessa Kirby all said like,
oh,
the cast is my Fantastic Four,
my family.
And Eben Moss-Bachrach just went,
no,
it is these four people.
I've thought about this.
It was clearly like,
there was no,
on the red,
if you watch the video,
I'll link it in the show notes.
The video of him on the red carpet is also very good.
But yeah,
it's good.
It is good.
I presume like the whole cast had been primed that,
look,
this is an obvious question.
You're going to get it.
You should prepare a response.
And they'd all prepared like the usual sort of,
you know,
fairly bland celebrity response.
And then he was like,
nope,
I'm fully going for it.
So that was good.
And I hope he,
I hope he enjoyed presenting the award.
I mean,
online,
but yeah.
And so we'll put that in the show notes.
And you can also watch the acceptance speech for X4 as well.
Cool,
cool.
No,
it's,
I liked the Saint of Bright Doors a lot.
I gave it a four out of five on Goodreads listeners.
And so,
and so I am looking forward to Rakes Fall.
So yeah,
I will read it.
I keep waiting for it to turn up in any of my libraries,
which it has not done.
But I mean,
it's,
it's on Kindle.
I definitely posted in places where you're aware of when it was like Solaris,
in the Solaris ebook sale.
Yeah.
Skill issue.
So I think I own it.
Yes,
I do own it because I bought it cheap when Liz was posting about it in the,
in the appropriate Discord thread.
Don't worry.
We'll come around again.
I don't have notifications turned on for Anonymous Claire,
except for that one thread,
the discount books thread,
which does ping my phone when people post it.
That's a really good idea.
Let me just set that up.
Highly recommend.
All right.
We've distracted Alison.
So quick,
let's talk about things while Alison's distracted.
There has also been,
uh,
other award news.
So Los Angeles has opened their Hugo award base competition.
Listeners,
if you are thinking that you might want to submit a base to the Hugo base design contest,
LA con five.
If you think you might want to do this,
uh,
you can submit,
there are some restrictions.
You need to be able to,
you need to be able to deliver 40 completed bases.
You've got a,
the base must stand on their own.
You can't,
you can't require a person to be there holding it up.
That would be hugely inconvenient for everyone.
And et cetera.
Um,
so there's like a big old,
there's a big old list of things.
LA con five will pay a maximum of $300 per base to cover materials,
labor,
packing,
shipping and shipping insurance.
So timelines,
the submissions close on the 31st of December,
2025.
And then the convention might get back to you to request followup information.
And the deadline for that will be the end of January and they will make,
a decision on the 15th of February,
2026.
And then the,
you have to get the basis to LA con before LA con,
which seems reasonable.
It would be a giant pain in the butt.
If the base has arrived after LA con,
uh,
we will put a link in the show notes.
It won't be as pretty as my Hugo award base.
Cause it was done by the very lovely Ian Clark and,
you know,
tight and where Hugo represent unless Ian does it,
in which case it might be as lovely.
Yeah.
No,
Hugo basis ever as lovely as the one you actually won.
This is,
this is true,
especially when it's your first,
I imagine also true,
but yes,
however,
it is a great opportunity.
If anyone has a great idea for something kind of LA related,
I think that's probably also part of the,
you know,
criteria in which they will judge should be vaguely LA related.
And then there's also other awards news this time from China.
So the 36th galaxy awards were presented.
This is not,
I mean,
you know,
congratulations,
to all the winners,
most of whom I have not heard of.
And the ones I have heard of,
I have not read the,
or I will say that best translation was run by.
I'm so sorry.
I'm going to do,
this is not going to be correctly pronounced listeners,
but Lee key kin,
who is the Chinese translator of the city of last chances by one Adrian Tchaikovsky.
So well done,
Adrian.
And well done to Lee key chin.
But the reason this is notable is that there is a addendum,
to the bottom of the far seven 70 article reporting on it about galaxy cons ambitions to become world con.
This is interesting because basically during the panel,
there was a panel themed.
There's a panel called,
how can we turn galaxy con into world con,
but it's the person who won the galaxy award in Chinese translation for their novel star body,
whose name is Roderick Levenhart.
I'm sorry if I've pronounced that wrong.
But it's the person who won the galaxy award in Chinese translation for their novel star body,
they basically reported on a panel and file seven 70 reports.
Leevenhart reports.
There is interest in returning world con to the country,
but the thing that Leevenhart is actually written seems to be about galaxy con becoming the size of world con.
It doesn't seem to be about galaxy con bidding for world con.
And there is a comment in the below the article by Nicholas white,
basically saying that his conversations with galaxy con organizers that didn't indicate to him that they were thinking about bidding for world con.
So yeah,
I think this is probably based on a misreading of the con report,
but I don't know.
We will link to the original con report as well in the show notes listeners.
But yeah.
So what do you guys reckon?
Do you think this is indication that China is going for another world con?
Or do you think this is a wrong end of the stick?
Do we think China should go for another world con?
What's the,
what's the feeling here?
I mean,
it sounds like there's one,
one panel that may have been miss quoted in translation.
Um,
I don't really,
I don't really mind.
I mean,
I don't think,
I think it's interesting in that.
I don't think there's much perception from people.
I know that Chengdu is a success,
but again,
we've talked about how it's hard to know what the perception is like within Chengdu fandom and even within Chinese fandom about whether it's a success or not.
But it is interesting that they're still talking about things like,
you know,
if they're saying,
how can we make it world con scale?
They're obviously still kind of thinking about comparisons to world con in some way.
Um,
yeah,
I think,
I wouldn't be,
I'm not automatically against another world con bid in China at some point,
but we probably have quite a few questions along the lines of how do we know that we won't have the same problems as Chengdu,
which is fair,
which is what any bid is going to have,
right?
Like whenever there is a Japanese world con bid,
one of the questions is how will you make enough money for it to be sustainable this time?
You know,
people are always going to question that.
So it's going to be those kinds of questions as well as all the questions China had last time.
And if they've decided,
actually,
we'd rather just have our own large,
scale cons that aren't world con,
then I say they go for it.
Yeah.
I mean,
there are plenty of conventions in the United States that are as big as world con.
Hmm.
It's not that big.
No,
I think the,
the,
the unwritten part,
or maybe not the unwritten part is the,
the reach of world con as well,
right?
The,
the,
if you want to make galaxy con into world con,
I don't think you're just talking about attendees.
You're talking about like,
how do we make the galaxy award into the Chinese Hugo award in terms of not in terms of reach,
uh,
as well.
Yes.
And I'm sure that's a big part of what they're trying to do,
isn't it?
I mean,
I assume like,
I think if you're starting a new award,
the Hugo award is one of the more prestigious awards you could benchmark yourself against,
especially given all the discussion there always is about kind of like,
um,
you know,
there's a lot of people who are sort of invested and like get the prestige of the Hugos without
necessarily feeling particularly linked into world con.
And I think that's a weird situation for us to have ended up in.
It's essentially like,
our own little convention awards,
which have become a much bigger deal than most convention awards are just due to kind of history and time and so on.
And I don't know if you can recapture that without it being,
well,
the reason that people are kind of interested in the Hugos is they've been around for 70 years.
I don't know.
That's fair.
I think I would,
I would agree with that take.
How are we going to do a podcast if you just keep agreeing with my takes,
John?
Well,
uh,
hang on.
Be less sensible,
Liz.
I'm sorry.
Screw you,
Liz Bauer.
The reason that the Hugos are popular is because of other factors.
And it has nothing to do with the time length and constituency.
Longevity isn't everything you need.
There has to be something about a sense that in the past,
it has been awarded to some good things.
They don't all have to be good.
I mean,
the Hugo has been awarded to some terrible things.
But I think one of the things,
that makes awards prestigious over time is people going back and going,
oh,
actually that,
that is a fair reflection of the best of the body of work at the time.
Also,
but that thing about you having to keep doing it.
it can,
it's quite hard to sustain awards.
You know,
we,
we have a bunch of awards that have run their time and run out.
You know,
awards don't necessarily carry on forever.
Yeah.
I think that's interesting because I would say certainly,
uh,
for novel,
I think,
you know,
I think the guys have probably managed pretty well to,
yeah,
keep up with what historically 50 years hence we think,
okay,
yeah,
that was a pretty good novel.
If they consistently pick stuff that no one has ever read for 50 years,
and I don't think they would have quite the,
the reach and the cachet they do now.
And that's why there are,
you know,
obviously our podcast jumps going through and reading them all.
An award where someone's like,
okay,
we're going to actually go and read everything that this award has picked
for the past 60,
70 years.
Um,
it's only sustainable if there are some interesting,
things on there.
It's also interesting that it's a popular award.
If you look at most of the other longstanding awards that people know about
and talk about,
they're often industry awards that are either juried or voted on by,
um,
a group of people in an industry.
The,
you know,
the,
the Hugo's are quite a populist,
quite unusually populist and,
and come out quite well considering that.
Um,
a lot of the stuff is good and popular.
And then finally the Tianwen awards were awarded in Chengdu.
And one of the people awarding one of those awards was,
um,
Ben Yalow as reported by,
uh,
Sats Culture.
Um,
so yes,
that was interesting.
I thought,
um,
what did Ben get his award for?
I think he presented an award.
I'm not sure he received an award.
I might be wrong.
I failed to listen to the exact previous sentence properly.
File 770 just says,
but Ben was present and participated.
So I assume he was presenting.
Although I am basically assuming that on the fact he didn't win,
I guess he could have just been doing like an interstitial bit.
Um,
but yes.
So I hope,
I hope Ben enjoyed the awards.
There is a photo of him on stage,
um,
under a banner labeled top 10 Chinese sci-fi literature translations of the
decade that went global.
So maybe it was a feature about kind of,
you know,
stuff that has become popular overseas due to translations.
A lot of which are,
who six ends novels,
but also,
um,
a few others that might be recognizable to people from being on,
I think on the Hugo list or certainly on award lists.
All right.
Most influential sci-fi IP adaptation case.
I'm going to have to look into these,
um,
categories in more detail.
Before someone starts,
uh,
adding them to the proposing them as additions to the Hugo's.
Oh yeah.
That's because that's what we need.
We need more Hugo's.
I definitely think we need a Hugo for most influential sci-fi IP
adaptation case.
Maybe we do.
So I'm going to give the listeners a little spoiler for a future bonus
episode.
I am a fan of a podcast listeners called the incomparable and sometimes
they draft things.
And I thought it could be fun for us all to draft our own Hugo award
ceremony from a list of all of the categories that have existed or have
been proposed for the Hugo awards.
I have a collection.
I haven't put all of them,
all of them in because there are some weird ones from the fifties,
but I've left,
left out.
Um,
but at some point in the future,
you know,
I was going to pick number one fan face,
John.
All right.
It's going in there.
Liz is going in,
but yes.
So if you have any ideas for categories,
you think should be in the Hugo awards,
please write in so that we can include them in our big list.
And I won't read them out as locks in an episode before we get there,
but I will credit the ones that listeners,
uh,
suggested in that episode.
So yes,
write in with your writing,
write in with your Hugo categories that no one has ever suggested,
but you think would be great.
And,
uh,
and I will add,
I will add most influential sci-fi IP adaptation to the list.
I think that's enough on awards.
Should we talk about comics?
Comics?
Comics.
Okay.
They're sort of books with pictures.
All right.
So I,
I've been to a convention or rather I've been to a festival.
Um,
I went to the Bangkok comics art festival,
uh,
yesterday,
which is held in,
uh,
the Bangkok art and culture center,
which is a big city center,
sort of art gallery with revolving,
revolving exhibits.
Uh,
I think it's also sort of a cultural hub a bit as well.
There's coffee shops,
there's places you can buy art supplies,
uh,
et cetera,
et cetera.
There's bookstalls in there.
Um,
so it's quite an interesting place.
And I popped in because they have,
they have this comic art fest.
Essentially,
it's a display of art on the fifth floor.
the Bangkok art and cultural center is basically a big sort of circular
building.
And there's kind of exhibits around the curved walls of each floor.
So on the fifth floor,
they had an exhibit of comics art,
which I went to look at.
Um,
so which was from their special guests.
They had a couple of special guests.
Some of it was from like local artists.
Some of it was from,
um,
there's lots of these projects,
which are like jointly with different embassies and things like that.
That happen occasionally,
where they will kind of like fund a comic art project.
So some of that,
and there's also,
they have a partner called children of the forest foundation,
where they go to a children's home and school on the border to work with like
migrant children and their families.
And they showed some of the comic arts,
uh,
created by those children,
which was pretty great.
And there were also stalls where you could buy things.
You could buy art and stickers by comic creators.
You can also buy books by,
uh,
there's probably a house called bluff publishing that I've heard of who are
based out of India.
Who are there with a table.
There were signings and things.
There were some panels and workshops,
but I timed my visit to Pauly and did not go to any of the panels and
workshops,
but yeah,
it looked pretty neat.
And when I was there,
it had a lot,
there were lots of people wandering around looking at the art,
uh,
chatting to people.
There was some kind of,
uh,
art interactive art thing you could do where you were drawing with wood.
I think it was pretty cool.
And it's all free.
Uh,
the art is up for two weeks and then there's like a two day,
you know,
this two day thing where they have the panels and workshops and it was just a
cute little event.
And I think it happens annually.
So I'll go back next year and maybe time my visit slightly better and
actually make it to some of the panels.
That seems fair.
Two days of panels,
but then two weeks that the arts up.
So I guess it's like a kind of,
is the convention in the middle of those?
No,
it's on the,
it's a two week thing and it's on the convention on the last two days.
Oh,
interesting.
I,
I would have done it.
I mean,
I think I would have done it the other way around,
but fair enough.
So you can look at the arts and then you can have the discussions.
I guess that makes sense.
How long has it been running for?
Is that the first iteration or is it?
No,
it's the fourth one.
Fourth one.
Oh yeah.
I see.
BKK,
BKK comics art festival.
Number four.
That was a clue.
Liz,
the number four.
And I think I've,
I can't remember.
I've popped in before.
No,
I think what I've been to before was like,
they have a lot of like student art shows in there as well from like
graduating students.
And I'm sure I went to one where they'd all made comics.
And so it was a sort of very similar thing.
Nice.
So did you,
did you,
did you buy any comics?
Did you learn about comics?
I did not end up buying any comics.
I was looking to buy something from blast,
but I think their table person was having lunch.
So I did not because I have a big book called the book of the blast book of
anti-cast SF,
which got picked in some kind of year roundup of the year's best SF last year.
I look very good.
There were quite a few comics.
There was some like,
there was a table full of,
I think Marvel and DC stuff that was being sold.
And then there was some artists selling like little stickers and things.
And there were some people selling zines,
but most of the zines were in Thai and my ties,
no one a good enough to read a zine.
So I did not purchase them.
I was buying a game from a Spanish publisher about the Spanish resistance to
Franco.
And I was like,
do I buy this game in Spanish or do I buy it in English?
I mean,
for me,
it's also the fonts.
Like I have a very hard time buying the fonts.
Hard time with stylized fonts.
Oh,
in Thai because of the different alphabet.
That makes a lot of sense.
It's really hard for me to read anything other than a fairly standard alphabet.
And even then I'm not very good at reading standard alphabet.
So yeah,
that is one,
one issue,
but it's cute.
They all exist.
I find that with Japanese and then also for Japanese for puzzles and German for
board games.
I find that my,
like my German's good enough for most of the bits of board game rules,
except for fiddly,
fiddly little details,
which are the essence of board game rules.
And that,
and that's also what I found in Japanese with puzzles that,
that I'd,
I'd be going along quite well until,
until it got to the real detail of,
of how turns worked or whatever.
I had the same thing with,
my friend has the German version of,
of Hanabi.
We got the gist of the rules,
but then when I bought it in English,
I was like,
oh,
there were,
there was one key rule,
which we were playing completely wrong because we had slightly mistranslated the
German and that.
Yeah,
exactly that.
The Blast Book of Anticast SF does look fascinating.
I can get it shipped from India,
but it would cost me 25 pounds,
but it is kind of tempting.
I mean,
I think you can also buy an ebook off their website.
So I think I'll probably end up doing that instead.
It's a chunky book.
So yeah.
Uh,
okay.
But that looks good.
That looks like a really good thing.
I,
I wish I lived in Bangkok.
It's a cute little thing.
And yeah,
it's all free.
Apart from,
sorry,
apart from the work,
the jobs,
I guess.
How do they,
I guess,
is it then,
is it sponsored then?
Uh,
I do not know exactly what funding they get.
Oh,
the BKK Comics Art Festival is brought to you by Children of the Forest Foundation,
Clip Studio Paint,
the Japan Foundation,
Taika,
the Embassy of Belgium,
Nicholas,
and BKK Unzine.
So I,
I think it's funded by Nicholas White.
I'm pretty sure.
I think that's what I've just learned.
Uh,
Nicholas,
do write in,
do you fund
a Bangkok comic art festival?
Really?
Alison,
did you zone out at a key point that means that that makes no sense at all?
I'm,
I'm just permanently zoned this week.
Sorry,
guys.
That's all right.
I know that Nicholas does not work for the,
uh,
Thai Belgian Embassy,
but Nicholas is an,
a diplomat who lives in Belgium.
So,
uh,
I've arbitrarily decided that he represents all Belgian diplomatic missions.
That seems perfectly reasonable.
Let me,
it makes total sense though,
right?
Because of the,
you know,
strong comics history of Belgium.
And so I think there was some art from a Belgian artist in the displays.
And for listeners who thought we were being facetious about Belgian comics,
um,
Belgium is one of the preeminent countries for comics in the world.
Uh,
and the two you've probably heard of our Tintin and the Smurfs,
uh,
which is,
you know,
those are the two big Belgian exports,
but the,
there is a whole Wikipedia page on Belgian comics.
And if you're not familiar,
go look it up in the show notes,
but I'm a big Tintin fan.
Not,
I mean,
obviously there are problematic aspects to Tintin,
but,
um,
but I grew up with Tintin.
I love him.
I've got,
I got,
I got two of the comic,
uh,
covers,
as prints in my,
uh,
dining room.
Hmm.
Um,
so,
and in fact,
Herg is one of the seven famous Belgians.
Yes.
Along with Poirot.
Yeah.
He's fictional.
And Papa Smurf.
Also fictional.
And Tintin.
All of the best famous people from any country are fictional.
The best,
the best English person is Sherlock Holmes.
Oh,
grief,
no.
Unless it's Doctor Who.
No disputing matters of taste.
Doctor Who,
yeah,
much better choice.
Look,
there's lots of famous Belgians.
It's just,
they're all cyclists and you've never heard of them.
Then there,
I,
and I did,
do not write in with famous Belgians,
please.
I'm sorry for my co-hosts.
Listeners,
please write in with famous Belgians.
Oh,
no,
please don't.
Um,
then I was going to talk about only a little bit because I don't have first hand,
um,
experience,
but there is a,
a convention that I read about in Rascal called the Asian Board Games Festival,
which sounded absolutely fascinating and sounded like a very kind of,
um,
very,
pictures on Rascal and it seems really cozy and little,
but I'd love to have gone and some of the zine pictures of like stalls and the zines on offer look amazing.
Um,
so this was held in,
uh,
Georgetown on Penang Island,
which is part of Malaysia.
Um,
but it's also held in Singapore and they're about to hold one in the Philippines.
So if we have any,
um,
Singaporean,
Filipino or,
uh,
Malaysian listeners do write in and let us know if you've ever been to the Asian board game festival,
but it looks pretty great.
And I'm trying to persuade,
um,
basically my mission listeners is to get Liz to go and report back because Malaysia is not that far from Thailand compared with,
you know,
Birmingham.
I feel like the Tokyo game market is also very good in that space.
I mean,
famously,
maybe we need to have a patron just so we can send Liz to Asian conventions and report back.
Come on.
Why,
why limit our sites?
Why not?
So,
um,
I can go to Asian game conventions and I can report back.
This is closer.
Cause I can get the train to Georgetown.
It'll cost me about 30 quid is why.
Wow.
Trains are great.
Uh,
yes.
Sadly,
John,
uh,
did not alert me to this convention until six months after it took place,
but maybe next year.
In my defense,
I only found out about it when Rascal wrote the retrospective.
So I did.
I also did not know about it in advance.
Awesome.
Well,
thank you very much,
Liz.
That sounds very interesting.
And,
um,
I hope you go to the next one.
Shall we do picks?
Yes.
And let's continue the Le Guin theme of the episode with Alison's pick.
Oh yeah.
No.
So my pick is an exhibition and I'm,
I'm told I have to stop picking things that you can't go to if you're not in London,
but I think it will be touring after it's only a little exhibition.
So if you are in London,
over the next month or so,
um,
the architectural association has an exhibition of Le Guin's maps called the word for world.
And it is one of,
it's not a very big exhibition.
It's just a little gallery room.
It is one of the most arrestingly lovely exhibitions I think I've ever been to.
Um,
they have printed a bunch of Le Guin's maps,
most of which you will be already familiar with,
but some of which are new on like cyanotype blue fabric,
so they're basically blue and white wall hangings.
Um,
they have put around the walls,
some of her original,
um,
sketches for maps and maps and other information about maps and sings from publishers and so on,
and ways in which maps are different from the way they appeared in the book and so on.
Um,
and they have laser etched a bunch of talismanic maps onto rocks and they've strewn those around the room,
um,
along with a lot of other rocks,
some of which are rocks,
which are wrapped and it's all very delightful.
You probably want to allow half an hour or so.
It's just a single room,
but it's great.
So,
and I said,
I think there's various things have been going on in conjunction with it.
None of which I have,
I've seen and will be going on.
I think it is touring,
but I don't know the details.
I will be in London just before that closes.
I will be going to the,
um,
Royal Astronomical Society for a convention.
And it isn't,
it isn't that far away.
So I could just wander over.
Yeah,
it can't be very far.
Really.
All those places are in the same sort of bit posh bit of the West end.
Europe.
That sounds really good.
It reminds me.
Did you go to the exhibition of Tolkien stuff for the Bodleian?
I can't remember when it was.
Yes,
I did.
It was amazing.
This is,
this is less grand than that.
Oh,
I mean,
that that's fair,
but I just remember one of the things I remember and the thing I like most,
a lot of people like Tolkien for his writing,
but,
um,
I have always preferred Tolkien as an artist to talking as an author and the hand illustrated maps,
getting to see the original picture of the Aurora from the father Christmas letters,
and also getting to see his illustrated cryptic crosswords,
um,
was the highlight of that exhibition for me.
So,
um,
anything where you're like,
you know,
hand drawn maps etched on rocks.
I'm like,
yes,
deal.
I'm excited.
And,
uh,
I think Alison might have already said this,
but,
no harm in saying it again.
Um,
that is wrapping up on the 6th of December,
2025 listeners.
And,
um,
it looks like it's easily accessible from a little thing.
I like to call the underground,
um,
Tottenham court road looks like the closest or gooch street,
which is just a funny word to say.
Gooch.
The same day that we saw this,
we also saw,
um,
the new exhibition at the British library,
which is called secret maps.
No relation.
Um,
that's not fictional maps,
but you know,
if you like maps,
that might be a good one to combine with the exhibition.
I would just say that if you're planning to go to the British library for the,
um,
secret maps exhibition that Alison just mentioned,
the other thing to bear in mind,
the British library often has a large selection of great events that tie in with their exhibitions.
So I highly recommend looking up to see whether they are doing anything around,
uh,
that.
All right,
Liz,
do you want to pick next or shall I?
I can pick next if you want.
So,
you know how last time I picked,
one big fat fantasy book.
Yeah.
This time you're picking several big fat fantasy books.
I'm picking seven big fat books.
Sorry.
Whoa.
I know.
I'm just making it harder and harder for John to ever,
ever complete his,
uh,
quest to read all my picks.
Okay.
I'm going to pick a series called dungeon crawler,
Carl,
which I picked up on a whim because they were down in the kind of long list for best series last year for the Hugos.
And since then,
since I was determining eligibility,
I went and looked him up and thought,
Oh,
that sounds interesting in a kind of like,
it's a big self published series.
And I don't think that many self published series get enough nominations to get even into the kind of the bottom realms of the long list,
which was kind of an indication of kind of quality.
And then I realized they're on Kindle.
So I thought,
I'll pick one up and read it.
And dungeon crawler,
Carl.
So it's basically what if aliens came to earth and turned up,
turned earth into like a giant kind of MMORPG,
um,
which is a reality TV show,
broadcast across the galaxy and everyone on earth who,
uh,
hasn't been,
killed in the collapse,
which is when all buildings clap.
So anyone who's outside gets kind of,
you know,
they can choose to come into the dungeon and play the crawl for the chance at basically winning,
winning their lives back.
Interesting.
So it's like a fan.
It's almost like a fantasy chain.
Gang.
All stars.
Yeah.
It's not,
I mean,
it's not really fantasy.
It's science fiction,
but because the kind of the crawl is often very fantasy themed,
there's lots of orcs and goblins and things.
Oh,
okay.
That's interesting.
But it's also very like self-referential.
Well,
yeah,
I don't mean self-referential.
I bought it.
It's kind of meta.
So we follow Carl who was outside trying to rescue his ex-girlfriend's cat,
princess donut.
And so he was barefoot and in boxes.
And so he has to enter the dungeon barefoot and in boxes with princess donut.
Who becomes sentient very quickly.
And it's seven books,
basically of their adventures in which they realize that they are part of
galactic geopolitics in a way that no one had foreseen at the start.
There is an AI,
which is getting gradually more and more and hinged.
The game is not fair in that because Carl comes in,
in his boxes and in bare feet,
he keeps getting upgrades that mean he has to keep his boxes on and not ever
get any trousers.
Brilliant.
And the AI is pushing this.
The,
the,
civilizations run the crawl in
different years, every time they find a new
planet they do this again basically
and so there's a long long history of this
and it just builds and builds and builds all this world building
and backstory into it
and of course kind of Carl and Princess
Donut get allies and become
more and more powerful until
by the last book I read, which is the seventh one, they're basically
just sort of fighting a
big fantasy war
against different factions from
the galaxy which is having repercussions
outside the dungeon
Okay, this sounds
fascinating
Yeah, so the first one is just sort of like, I was like
okay, well that was a bit fun, they you know
crawl through the dungeon, it was fun
Carl's quite fun, he's got a sentient cat
who now only talks in capitals in the in-game
chat because he won't ever like
not have the caps lock on, that kind of thing
When I was midway through book three or four I was like
okay, these are dragging a little bit, this crawl
is going on a little bit long
every book is basically like a floor
of the dungeon and they're getting deeper and deeper into the dungeon
you know, this is going on a bit and then
sometime about book five or six I was like, oh
I see what this is kind of building to now
I can see where this is going and they're just very enjoyable
they are very long
probably a little bit too long
they're very heavily
serialised, so if you forget who
a character is from a previous
book, they might come back again
and then you're looking through the wiki to try and find
out who they are without getting any spoilers
So their books, it sounds to me like
they're books to buy an e-book because I find
that being able to search e-books
for the names
of characters is the single
most useful thing to have
an e-book for. So the thing is
they might be books to buy an e-book but
I believe that the author
Matt Dinaman still self-publishes
the e-books himself
and the audiobooks, which apparently are great
but they've been picked up by
Ace as actual physical novels
but I think they don't have the e-book
rights and I don't know how heavily edited
they have edited
them in the time of transition. I suspect not
that heavily. I suspect they're maybe
not that much changed but it is
possible that the paperbacks are different
than the e-books. I haven't dug into that.
So this could actually be one to read in paperback
if they've kind of cleared up a few
bits where it's just like, you know, there's one where
they're all on trains
the floor is train themed
and there's a little author's note at the beginning saying
don't worry about how confusing this is, it's supposed to be
confusing for the crawlers and I'm like yeah but
if it's confusing for me then that's not
great. But yeah, I thought
I would read one and see how they go and
then like I'd read all
seven? I just read the
Wikipedia page so to try and find out
the answer about the editing
so
in response to
questions about whether the publisher would make changes
Dinaman responded that the story would remain the same
but the series had undergone rigorous edits
which sounds like yes. But also
the Wikipedia page notes that
he had a spreadsheet with
198 pages to keep
track of the characters and storylines, eventually
had to create a second spreadsheet to
track content on the first spreadsheet
and then the spreadsheet got big enough that it
didn't work on his computer anymore
so he had to hire someone to make him a Notion database
Yeah, I'd be
interested to, I would be interested to
see the difference between them
because there are a few bits where I'm like oh you could maybe
have like trimmed this down a bit. I can't tell in
page count but some of the books are like over 800 pages
they are long books. These did not
sound like for me. Oh they're probably not
for you but like honestly
I picked up the first one and thought oh well
some people nominate for this you go oh there's a
seven books I may as well give the first one a go and by the end
of it I was like yeah I'm getting into this and
then by like book four or five you're like
oh this is what's happening now and
yeah. They've stopped becoming just kind
of straightforward Carl and Donut
get a quest and find out the floor's overarching
theme and into like yeah this is
what's going on in the world
and like not really a spoiler but like
the possibility is these are such a big
thing in the universe that there's a possibility
you know when there's a possibility that they could
change this and basically improve
society for everyone
then they're taking it yeah.
That sounds fascinating. I could buy the hardback
from Waterstones for 26.
I'd read an e-book first and if
you really like their first e-book then maybe consider
getting some of the later ones in Harbour. No Liz
I'm going to buy the first hardback
I'm doing it. Oh no no
now I feel like what if John doesn't like it?
It'll be alright. I
am going to
pick The Lord of the Rings
Fate of the Fellowship
This is
a board game listeners.
Pause for ooze.
Ooh that's not
like you to pick a board game. Is it
Octothorpe Gaming Corner?
Octothorpe Gaming Corner. Yay!
So this
is the latest
pandemic game by
Matt Leacock. It is
it doesn't even have
the word pandemic in the title
and BGG confidently says it
re-implements pandemic and I think the word re-implements
is doing a hell of a lot of work there. So
this is a game where you
control two characters from
the books
so there's like suggested
characters for your first play
and I don't know all of the characters but like
you've got everyone from the fellowships in there obviously
you've also got Eomer, Eowyn
Galadriel, Gollum
other various
people. The aim of the game
is to complete
four objectives one of which is
always to
unforge the one ring by casting
it into Mount Doom
and you have to move
around the map and instead of having
little cubes to know in
pandemics you have tiny little meeples
with little swords and they're red
and they're orcs and
you add orcs to the board
in a similar way to the way you would add
cubes to the board in pandemic. So
basically you have a deck of cards that tells
you sometimes orcs
arrive on the board and you put them on the board or
sometimes they're moving from place to place along
arrows that are drawn on the board and you move
them. But in true pandemic style
the cards you've just had every so often
will shuffle and go back on top of the deck
so places that have orcs will keep getting orcs
and orcs moving will keep moving.
You lose by running out of hope
various things influence hope
but the one that kind of is the most relevant
is if an orc gets into one of the
havens on the board and you
can't defend it then you will lose three hope and given
that the hope track maxes at eight
if that happens three or four times in a game
you will almost certainly lose.
And so it's recognisably pandemic
like you can see the bits in it which are
pandemic but also you have things like
you can muster troops
it also comes with a cardboard
Eye of Sauron dice tower which is
the single best thing I've ever seen come in a board
game. It is absolutely great
it is really good
so I think the
truest indication of how good it was
was we played it at
Cottaging and we lost
and then we just
started again straight away
we were like now we are going to play this again
immediately and then we
were all sitting down like at one
point and like it was quite late and everyone
was like I don't really want to play anything
and Rob was like I mean I'm always tempted to suggest
Fate of the Fellowship but I don't think people would go for it
and then four people went yes I'll
play that and we immediately just played
like this game like
I don't know what time of day it was
but like every time someone suggested playing it
there was immediately four people being like yes I will
play that game and I think it was probably
one of my two favourite
games of this Cottaging.
I can't say much that hasn't
been said better by Shut Up and Sit Down
so I will link to their
review video in
the show notes but this is just
it really shows off
how good
Leacock is as a
designer that he's made something based
on the pandemic underlying mechanics
that feels so different to
pandemic itself
and there are multiple people in our group who really don't like
OG pandemic who liked
this quite a lot so yeah
I highly recommend. I've just looked up
the Eye of Sauron
Dice Tower and it does look cool.
Well it's also it's not plastic it's
made of cardboard and you assemble it at the start
so like because they could have made
it like a stupid like really
expensive loads of plastic
components game but it's
all wooden meeples and cardboard components
and I really like that
because I don't really like plastic in my
board games. So I have a
slight dissenting opinion
here which is that it was on Board Game
Arena
and
we had a go at it and bounced
off it pretty hard. We kind of
were like well this is like pandemic
but with a load of fairly random
extra stuff and
then we so we kind of played it until we were
fed up and then stopped so that was probably an hour and a half
or two hours and then later
Jonathan played some solo
and came back and said
ooh but there's quite a lot more
to this so maybe we have not given it a fair shout.
I would say I don't think there's
much. It has
dice but
you... No not random
in that way. Random in a kind of
oh complexity. So we have
at least one person in our gaming group that
is very anti
complexity in board games.
Really would prefer games where you
just sit and think at each other for four hours.
It is not that.
And it is also a game where
it is a game I think
in the best cooperative mould
where the parameter
space for the options
for each character is large
enough that it is very difficult for one
player to play the whole game on
their own so you can't
really quarterback which is a marked
departure from base pandemic
and I think I very much like
games like Spirit Island has the same
thing and so does Arkham Horror the card game
where you don't have enough
information about the game state
and the game state is sufficiently
complicated that you can't hold it in one person's head.
That. That's the problem.
That's not the problem.
No I know.
Because the worst cooperative games
are the ones where one person can play and three people
watch. Oh no but we like
to chat right?
So we did get bogged
down in this one. But I mean I'm not
saying we would necessarily get bogged down in it again.
We might have another go at this.
Because as I said it is on Board Game Arena.
So if you fancy a go at this you don't have to pay money
for it. You can just go and play it on Board Game Arena
and see if you like it.
And then you can buy it later.
I think it is also on
Tabletop Simulator but I don't know how
I don't know how official that implementation is.
It's worth noting if you
look it up on Board Game Arena
if you type Lord of the Rings it will tell you
that there are no results. You have to type Fate of the Fellowship
which I think is
a search bug in
Board Game Arena perhaps.
Of which there are many.
On that bombshell that was the Octothorpe Podcast
and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me.
Bye for now.
The theme music for this episode
was Fanfare for Space
by Kevin MacLeod and Compotech.com
used under a Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 licence.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.
Thank you.