We haven't actually finished our preparatory reading for the next episode.
I have, except for John, who's who gets a gold star.
Gold star for John.
Yay.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to the 62nd episode of Octa Thorpe, the podcast for
science fiction and science fiction fandom, which is coming to you on the 21st of July, 2022.
I'm John Coxson.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And this is a unusual episode because we are recording it because we can't record
next week a peek behind the curtain.
So we're going to talk about the Hugo Award finalists for Best Novel.
If you are very spoiler-verse, you may wish to save this episode for when you have
read the finalists.
And if you are not, dive in.
Why not?
And in the grand tradition of Octa Thorpe, you can, of course, feel free to listen to this
episode in six months time and still send us a comment.
I guess this is a spoiler for our discussion, but none of these, I think, are books
where spoilers are really going to be a big deal.
There's nothing where you are waiting, I think, for the final reveal, although I
haven't finished one of the books.
So which does, in fact, have a kind of final twist or two.
So, you know, yeah, but the whole book is twisted.
It's all like revealing slowly things.
So.
So we're going to start off discussing Project Hail Mary by Andy Weir.
Andy Weir, of course, is an author who catapulted to recognition for his work, The
Martian, and the film of which won a Hugo Award at some point.
And this is his third novel, and it is about a man nailed this description.
Yeah, I would say that Andy was first book.
The Martian was about a hyper-competent man left alone in space to spend the whole
book being extremely competent at physics and discovering things from first principles
and science, seeing the shit out of it.
And Hail Mary is a book in which a hyper-competent man gets trapped in space alone,
a long way from anywhere else, and spends a whole book science and the shit out of it
with his body, who is very like him.
Yes.
So I think one of the things that is critical about this book is that it's got 10 times
as many good reads, reviews as any of the books on the shortlist.
And quite a lot of those reviews say, Oh, God, this is Weir and it's Weir.
It is very best.
And it's even better than it was before because he managed just to introduce a completely
alien alien that is not like any alien ever.
And then they science the shit out of things together.
And that is even better. And although I will grant you that the alien doesn't necessarily
look like other aliens and Weir does quite a good job of explaining why that is.
The alien is a middle aged or late 30s American man who is very good at science
and likes to science to the shit out of things except he's more on the practical
side of science rather than theoretical side of science.
So what you have here is a theoretical scientist and an engineer.
So obviously we've now covered all of the possible varieties of human and alien existence.
I think I disagree with several bits of that, though.
He's particularly American.
It did annoy me.
He's gendered as a man given that presumably this alien does not have the concept of gender.
We do. And like it would have been a very.
They have a sexual reproduction that he chooses to he says, probably some other gender.
I'm assuming he's a man and that is a problem and I have a problem with that.
And like I have a problem with that way more than the implied middle agedness
slash Americanism of him, which I think was much less clear than the implied manhood of him
given that he has used him throughout.
It just really annoyed me.
I'm like, you could have just had.
I grew up in the 60s and 70s.
We used he and him to mean people all of the time.
And you know, it was a thing then.
I don't like how this book portrays gender.
I think it is an own goal to decide that there is this alien and it would have been very easy
in the point where he's like, I don't know what gender this alien is.
I'm going to call it they and we had chooses not to do that.
And I think that is annoying in 2022.
And I am slightly sad that that approach was the one taken,
especially because I think most of the rest of the books on the ballot do a really great job with gender.
This sticks out as one that does not.
I mean, I think the thing is it seems entirely in character for our main character to go.
Well, maybe they say in, you know, has a different to a potential gender.
I'm just going to call him he all the time because his innermost narrative voice basically
seems like it spends absolutely no time thinking about anything that isn't science.
So he's just going to be like, yeah, I don't care about that sort of stuff.
It doesn't you can't measure it in like meters per second.
It is exactly the same sort of misogyny that is rife in science.
Generally, I think.
Yeah. So I can get behind it.
The thing is it doesn't really strike me as being a deliberate choice.
It seems just like a sort of casual well.
That's that's why I think, you know, it doesn't strike me as being an author's
deliberate choice and which is just a kind of like throw away line and then he defaults to he because it's easier.
I think it definitely reflects the thoughtlessness of the author.
I would agree with that.
OK, so this is only the third least thing I liked about this book.
And I really enjoyed the book. I should say I read it all the way through without any difficulty.
It's a perfectly pacy novel.
It is founded on two pernicious lies, both of which are much worse than what pronouns you use.
The first is the perception of dictatorial tyranny is the best way of dealing with a crisis.
That if you have a crisis, the best way to sort it out is to find a strong
personal and give them all the power and then solutions will follow.
And that is what happens in this book in the first part of the book that's told in flashback.
And the second and that's a lie.
That's a comfortable lie that lots of people like, including lots of other people who like this book.
And the second problem, which is even worse, if anything, is the belief that given any problem,
the way to sort it out is for one person to use their kind of generalized understanding
or maybe even two people to use their generalized understanding of things to tackle every problem
as it comes up and solves it without any reference to anybody else.
And that is possibly even more popular amongst readers of this book.
So it's basically these are completely cozy things that are not true.
This is not how any problems in the real world ever get solved.
And if you put it into your book, yes, you've generated an escapist fantasy.
But, you know, it's a terrible, it's a terrible way to write books.
Come on, don't do it.
And so it's really it's a book for 10 year olds.
Oh, God, it's awful, terrible book.
But I enjoyed it a lot.
Has lots of funny things in it.
We're writes his nerdy scientist quite well.
Do you agree with that one?
I think it does portray like, I mean, I haven't finished the book.
So I am assuming that, you know, it turns out well and that, you know, giving one person the power
to literally do anything to solve a crisis is the way that we should have solved it.
But I think, yeah, more interesting is this portrayal of like the individual who can
solve things and the book even kind of like tries to lampshade it.
So there's a scene at the start where our hero protagonist who wasn't wasn't
academic and then has gone back to be a high school teacher.
I think so that he'll know all the stuff, you know, we need to know to teach high school
science, which apparently equips you for, you know, being in deep space and solving
all problems.
Sorry, I'm digressing.
You know, the scene at the start where they're like, OK, we want you to be the only person
working with this new alien single-celled life that we have brought back.
And the guy is like, but why why me?
There's loads of other people and they try and like say, oh, we want you to be the
guinea pig, you know, because you're expendable.
And then if it turns out it kills everyone, you know, but it just seems like they're like,
who should get this first?
Oh, we've picked this one person and it doesn't feel like the way in which
science would work or does work.
And they nod towards it a bit because they then have a more international team, but it
does seem to be very much like, yeah, this one person will have the skills to do
everything they need to figure this whole thing out.
When really, I think like what he's doing would be a team of 50 people.
Well, Alison just said really concrete to me why I prefer the Martian to this book
quite a lot, which is that in the Martian and like in other films like it like Apollo 13,
it depicts the efforts of like a team of people to fix the problem because you have
like the NASA aspect of things that are happening and you have the person stranded
in space aspect of things that are happening.
And both of those are very interesting.
And obviously the sort of person that gets picked to go on a mission to Mars or
in the case of Apollo 13, the moon is very competent at the things they need to do
to get themselves out of tricky situations in space.
Prodigy, how Mary doesn't really have that.
And I do agree that that is that it is weaker for it because there's this myth of
the kind of, I mean, this myth of the gentleman scientist, which is a gendered
term, but basically kind of the idea that people work in a vacuum and solve all
these problems and are very clever themselves.
And modern science is not like that.
It may have been like that in the past, but it is definitely not like that now.
So the more you read about the history of science, the more you learn that wasn't
ever the case.
When I was taught genetics in school, I was taught about Mendrel, essentially,
in a little greenhouse somewhere, breeding peas.
And it was only, I think about five years ago that I learned that
monasteries across Europe specialized in the area of scientific and other
knowledge activity that they dealt with.
And the monastery that Mendrel was in, which he was poached from another
monastery to go to, specialized in breeding because sheep breed, it was a big
sheep area.
And he led a team of many, many, many monks engaged in the breeding of
peas to get better peas.
He was just the first person to work out what was going on.
And I have not learned any of that in school because we have a myth of an old
man pottering away in a greenhouse because he's a gardener or something.
I am employed on something called a fellowship, which is entirely based around
this lie, but it is also a lie that controls most of how science funding is
done in the Western world.
So it is a very, very prevalent lie.
So Project Hail Mary, I also very much enjoyed.
I thought it was good fun.
I do like first contact stories and the part where he's working out how to
communicate with an alien really scratched several of my itches around
kind of language and first contact stuff in a way I really, really liked.
So like, I will say that the floor for my Hugo ballot, because where is my sixth
place choice?
It's quite high because I did not hate this novel.
We talk about the male gaze a lot.
And this is a book that is written from the perspective of a prepubescent boy.
This novel is very, very much has a 10 year old's conceptions of all sorts of
things, but I think most notably a 10 year old's conception of sex.
There's a, there's a kind of weird scene in which we have has decided he has to
put some sex content in.
Maybe told he has to put some sex content in.
And, and the way he does it reminds me of the way that my children talked about
sex when they were quite young, like five or six, you know, people are going to go
and have sex now.
That's a thing that they're going to do.
And that's literally how it's handled here.
And otherwise we see, we see none of the way that the main character relates in his
relationship.
So there's a much better book struggling to get out of here, which is the book
about the person who cannot form adequate human relationships, who then has a really
valuable interpersonal relationship with an alien who is completely unlike them.
But unfortunately, we don't really see the first part of that when they fail to
handle human relationships properly.
And we don't see a really alien alien for them to have a really valuable
relationship with.
So it could be better.
Can I have one?
I've got one mini round, if I may, which is for a book, which I'm pretty sure kind
of all the physics is basically, I can't follow the physics, but I'm sure it is
meticulously derived.
I don't think the alien language makes sense.
So the alien speaks in chords, right?
And he speaks in chords of up to five notes.
Fine.
And we also get, but we also get hints that he's describing them as things like, oh,
it's the A below C major.
And, you know, he drops an octave.
This is the alien speaking.
He drops an octave when he's sad.
And I'm like, OK, how many five note chords are there, you know, within a
traditional octave, if we say that for some reason, the alien is using the same
tonality as humans with a 12 note scale, how many chords are there that this guy
is apparently managing to learn to understand language without having a laptop
sitting in front of him?
Because I'm pretty sure, even if you have perfect pitch, you're going to find
that quite tricky and that there must be an upper limit on the number of words,
which is, you know, a few thousand?
Now, and this is part of the problem I had with the novel was that I really
liked the initial bit where I'm like, oh, an alien that speaks in tones.
That's a really interesting concept and learning how to understand that is really
interesting.
And then about halfway through the novel, it's just like, oh, it's solved.
And it's like, oh, that is much less interesting because I do not believe that
would happen.
No, it's way too fast.
I thought that was going to be the meat of the novel and like the whole novel
is going to be a fascinating exploration of like, and then no, those, but
like that quarter of the book, I did really enjoy.
It didn't really mind learning language too quickly, which I'm sure is something
that also happens in the martin is something in fact, it has happened already
in the martin is something that I think you're allowed to have the free and
first contact novels, because otherwise three years of accidentally getting stabbed
because you've misinterpreted something is probably not that exciting.
It depends, I think on the book, if you're a book, which is presenting this is very
rigorously worked out and all very linearly extrapolated from what's possible.
I have a lot less time for it than I do in the martin, which is not doing that.
Only science in weir that is rigorously worked out is the things he expects
people to remember from high school with a bit of a nudge.
So nothing outside that space is ever is ever explained.
Right. Shall we move on to the mass a master of gin by PJ L E Clark?
This is the one I didn't finish because I didn't want to finish it.
Liz can introduce this one.
This really likes this one.
I was to say, I really liked it or more that I disliked more of Sophia.
The sort that's more than you two did.
But yes, I think I probably liked it the most.
So basically a master of gin by P.
Jelly Clark is a novel of an alternate Cairo, essentially, where there are
supernatural entities were released from their dimension kind of onto the world.
And this has completely changed like the balance of power in our world at the
start of the 20th century.
And we follow a eventually an investigative agent named Fatma, who is
investigating the murder of a secret brotherhood who seemed to be looking for
relics from the man who opened this doorway into other dimensions.
And of course, there's a strong supernatural element to it.
So she ends up, you know, roaming around Cairo with her, you know, agent who's
been assigned as her partner.
And she's kind of rubbing up against this new partner that she's been assigned
a mysterious girlfriend who is definitely more than meets the eye.
And uncovering basically what happened to this brotherhood and what it's what it
means to have to save Cairo from kind of the supernatural threat that is coming.
Yep.
I really liked this book.
I found it to be, as they say, a page turner.
I liked finding out what happened.
I liked some of the concepts a lot.
I liked the magic.
Yeah, I really generally enjoyed it.
And it makes me want to go back and read some of the preceding stuff in this
world, because I know that there have been kind of, I've read the tram, the
haunting of tram car zero or five, but I don't think I've read any other stories
in this universe.
So at some point I need to go and do that.
I think there's only one other story actually in the universe.
So you're nearly there.
Oh, so I would have happily carried on reading this if I hadn't run out of time,
but I didn't really like it very much.
And that's because it's a police procedural set in a kind of fantasy city.
And I feel I've read a lot of books like this before.
And I find I feel like it was competent, but it wasn't really doing anything that
wasn't beyond that. And I really didn't believe.
So the central character is a hard bitten cop who works alone, right, who is also
portrayed as being a young Muslim woman who is not very observant, as opposed to
her assigned partner who is a much more observant Muslim.
And I didn't believe in it.
So I read it and I was like, well, this is just Travis McGee.
You know, it has none of Clark is very pleased that he's got all these women
in his thing, but none of them do any women things at all.
So this is just a boy in a woman's suit.
And I really, really didn't have any time for that.
And when I was kind of going, I really didn't get into this book.
Stephen said, well, you know, the problem is that the central characters
don't ring true as women. And I was like, Oh, OK, so maybe it's not just me then.
So if you're a woman and you really identified with Fatma, then do please tell
me because I don't believe in that character at all.
Yeah, there's not like I say, oh, then I disagree with Alison.
And I really like the central character.
I mean, yes, it is the kind of hard bitten detective.
It's just that the hard bitten detective in this case is a woman.
But I didn't have any problems with her not doing specific women things to tell
me she was a woman. I'm quite happy with that.
And young and cynical despite being young.
Yeah.
Well, and also, well, Liz is quite cynical despite being young Alison.
So like I feel like that might have wrong true.
She's much younger than Liz.
She's like 28 or something.
Liz was quite cynical when this was 28 or something.
I've known Liz for a while, Alison.
Liz is a good egg.
Maybe that's why I got along with Fatma so well, because I was like,
also it's not the character I it's not the sort of character I
tend to want to read about.
It's more of a thing because police procedure, not my sort of book.
That's a very different criticism, though.
I would also say that, you know, in the setting, you know, it is rare for
there to be female detectives.
And so I think there's a lot of interesting stuff about one that she
probably would be extremely cynical if you were in that position as a coping
mechanism.
And I do like that, you know, it is a cliche of, oh, the grisled
detective is given, you know, I mean, she's not grizzled in age, but kind of
grizzled in mentality is given the partner.
She doesn't want.
And then, you know, comes to a kind of understanding with them.
But I did actually enjoy that sort of clash of approaches they had going.
And I thought that was quite well done.
I thought I definitely believed the thread in the novel where they
don't get along at the start and they become more and more aligned through the
book and I believed the arguments they have.
And I believe the friction and then I believe it kind of aligning towards
the end and the trust coming.
And I thought that was actually quite well done.
I did.
I enjoyed parts of the mythology, but like, I don't know, for me, as we have
discussed previously and as we will discuss later plots are a thing to hand
characters around.
So I was very much more focused on them just being awesome together, which I did
enjoy.
Ooh, also 1912.
Did this feel like 1912 to you?
Did this feel like a historical novel set in 1912 to you because it did not to me?
Yeah, I mean, that's tricky, right?
Because it isn't.
It's an old history.
I don't know.
Like steampunk books.
Like, I don't know how much a steampunk book needs to feel like it's
Victorian because it isn't Victorian.
So I don't know how much of a past to give it.
I think the bits where there's a bit where Fatma kind of interact with real
world characters given a kind of twist in this old history.
And that I didn't, I thought that was on the weaker parts.
That didn't really add much to me or feel particularly kind of completely
thought through.
But otherwise, I'm kind of happy to give everything a pass in a sort of like, oh,
it's an old history, 1912, where, you know, things have progressed very quickly
since they have this kind of supernatural power floating around everywhere.
Yeah.
So yeah, moved and bothered me.
And there are definitely, I will definitely say there are better old histories.
I do think it's probably easier to write old history that is within living memory.
We can research history even before people were born, John.
I mean, what outrageous.
We know what detective novels written in 1912 were like, for example, you know,
that there were plenty of them.
It definitely didn't feel like a Sherlock Holmes book.
Yeah, no, it didn't.
It felt like a, it felt like a kind of mid century police proceduralist.
Fine.
I mean, I will finish this book now.
I didn't, I don't want people to think I threw it aside.
I threw it aside with good for brute force or anything.
It's not that bad.
As a fantasy, I enjoyed it very much.
And I enjoyed it very much as a fantasy where you're using the old history basis
to have like interesting things happening in Europe that haven't quite boiled over yet.
I think that some of the geopolitics felt very cool and like Egypt positioning itself
in that as a result of the fact that Egypt is like a magical superpower.
That all felt really nice.
And I don't know how you do that if you said it in modern times.
So I do, I think the old history is more to get an interesting geopolitical
situation than it is to explore what it was like to live in 1912.
And I think that's valid because I think like you can pursue old histories
for different reasons and pursuing it for that reason didn't feel like a
pistach to me, if that makes sense.
And it's very specifically in that time and place where we can explore kind
of the colonialism of the great powers at the start of the 20th century.
So I think that's a very like deliberate choice to explore that.
I mean, and again, I think it's towards the bottom of my ballot, but again,
I did enjoy it quite a lot.
So, um, I will say I've just looked up the other books in the universe and I had
got the impression of reading it that there would probably be loads of other
stories that like all tied in.
And there's like two, one of which I've read and the other one is a novelette.
And I'm like, how you felt?
Definitely like, I think, and this is probably to the credit of Clark.
It felt like I was being dropped in media res into like a big universe that was
already there and I was seeing a snapshot of it and it felt big.
And looking at the universe, like the murder bot story, um, from last year,
felt nowhere near as much of a massive universe that I was just seeing a glimpse
of as this does despite the fact that there's been like four other books in that
series.
And this one is a much smaller series, but feels massive.
And I'm like, I did quite enjoy the scale.
I thought that was really cool.
And I think that suits Cairo and like the geopolitics again.
I think that that was neat.
But it just confused me slightly when I was like, oh, there's just one novelette.
Ha.
Yeah, I was surprised to discover there was a novelette and I wasn't
actually being dropped into the third or fourth novel involving these people.
Cause, you know, it could have been, I think there are going to be more now.
I think I think we are going to see this as a franchise-able product.
Hmm.
Um, I'm looking forward to the Netflix series.
Is there a Netflix series?
No, I just think there will be.
So sort of thing.
So next up, we're going to talk about the galaxy and the ground within.
Alison, do you want to introduce this one?
The galaxy in the ground within is the fourth of Becky Chambers Wayfarer's
series and I haven't read any of the other ones.
So, but people said, oh, it doesn't matter very much and I don't know whether it
does or not.
Um, Chambers says that this is a capstone for the series.
So it kind of makes sense if you think of it as this is showing how the universe
goes on after presumably the much more engaging events of the previous novels.
But this is, I described it as a bottle episode of her, of her series.
And I've seen other people describe it as the breakfast club with aliens, which
is probably a better way of looking at it.
You have some people who come together because they have been forced to stay
together due to circumstances and they come from four different alien species.
That's two of one.
And they have the sort of conversations that you have when you're stuck in one
place with people you don't know and send the bookends.
So if you're looking for plot in your science fiction novels, it's, there's not
a lot, but I'm not necessarily looking for plot.
And I am totally up for a novel of interiority where people have a massive
personal growth as a result of this sort of being thrown together.
And you could have that with aliens.
And I think that's a very interesting idea and I quite enjoyed it, but I'm not
sure I don't think it's got enough character development even within that to
sustain a novel.
So I think this is very slight.
I think if you like your science fiction to be very slight, then you'll probably
like this quite a lot.
And I definitely liked it more than the clock or the weir, but there's not enough
to it.
I think I will, I think I will say it is really interesting to see.
So I will read this and assume that the previous books have like somehow got loads
of plot in.
No, like the first book is about a ship and it has some people on it and they
talk a lot while some things happen.
And then that's the end of the book, Bloody Love that book.
The second book explores one of those characters and some other characters doing
much the same thing.
The third book explores a different one of the characters from the first book and
some of those characters.
And it doesn't even really explore one of the characters from the first book.
It explores someone who knows one of the characters from the first book.
And the link between the fourth book and the first book is the Ashby, who is the
human with whom one of the characters is in love is one of the characters from
the first book, that is the single tie.
These are not like it's not some big crescendo and this is like a super chill
capstone.
They're all chambers.
His style is very much focusing on character in small, not all that
climatic circumstances.
This is, I think, probably quite typical of her writing is not like unusual in that regard.
Yeah, I have gathered this from my post, post reading analysis.
I really like this book because I really liked the characters and I really
liked watching them interact.
But I completely understand why these books are quite divisive in the community.
I'm definitely going to read all of her others.
Really enjoyed it.
Liz, do you want to talk about division in the community?
Yeah, so I read the first of Becky Chambers's quarter to books and I didn't
really like it.
There's a bunch of characters who have a, you know, they do some talking and
there's some like mild peril and it gets resolved and it's all happy at the end.
And in this one, well, I mean, I think it was almost better than the first one
because in the first one, it felt very much like she felt there had to be
something going on.
And so there were sort of things going on.
And in this one, she's just decided, actually, I don't need anything to be
happening other than there are some characters who are on a planet and they
are, you know, talking to each other and we're learning about their
characters and their species and stuff.
And I mean, it's fine.
If you want some aliens who, you know, described physically as being very
alien, but in fact, you know, all talk like people in Sannevay much like people
and they have some discussions and they clash mildly and then they mostly resolve
them at the end and there's some nice bits.
It's fine.
But I didn't enjoy Chambers first book and I wasn't expecting to enjoy the
fourth one and I didn't enjoy it.
I don't know.
I can't understand the appeal particularly because I think you could do a
lot of this stuff.
I think you can, I think you can tie character and plot together and I prefer
books which do that.
And this one is like, nah, I don't need to do that.
I'm not going to bother.
So very cozy.
I guess if you had a book that did the inter-character stuff as well as this book
and had like a really great plot, I would also very much enjoy this book.
I do find that Chambers's approach to character is really good in a way that I
think very few other writers manage.
Like for instance, in the kind of other books in this category, I think the only
one that gets close to doing the interpersonal stuff as well as this book
does is the Martine is not a coincidence that the Martine is much higher up my
like order of voting because I think it does do that.
Melting plot and character work very, very well.
But like I will say, I'm not sure any of the other books do the character work
anywhere near as well as this novel does.
The tension in this book arises firstly, because two characters get into a
political argument and the book has been so cozy up to that point.
You're shocked when this happens.
And then secondly, they immediately set aside their differences to work on a
common crisis.
So in the Martine, there's a scene very early on where two characters have
actual political differences that matter to the bigger picture story.
And then immediately afterwards, one of them immediately lets that go because
something excites them scientifically and they need to use their scientific
knowledge to solve the problem, which they do, thereby showing scientists working
together to solve something.
And it's just a, I don't think the characterisation is notably worse than in
the chambers, and b, that occupies about two pages of the book.
So I feel that the chambers also has a thing about lack of density in terms of
a science fiction novel, that this is a novel for some, for people who like their
levels to not get, not do very much, or not require very careful reading either.
Because if you read the Martine at the speed at which I read the chambers, you
would, you would miss about 95% of what's going on in it.
The Martine has used amounts of glances and people saying things they don't quite
mean and chambers does this, but it's all much more spread out.
I quite, I, I, I've ranked the, I've ranked the chambers third in my big
list of books for the Hugos.
I did quite enjoy it.
I think I enjoyed it better than three of the others.
What did you say, Liz?
You just said you'd like your books to have some plot in them?
Yeah, pretty much.
I mean, the thing is, I'd like my books to have plot and character.
Ideally, and if it has a little plot of the chambers, I need the character to be
more.
Yeah, it's more that I just can't see what.
Like, it's tricky.
Like, sometimes you can't, it's very difficult to predict the bits of a book
that will work well on the bits that won't.
Well, I went away from this thinking I will read a lot more chambers.
I'm going to read it all.
It's great.
I might read, maybe the sort of books I read in the bath or on airplanes.
I read a long way to a small angry panel on my honeymoon on the beach in
Korsaika, and it was 10 out of 10 for that use case.
But yeah, I will say that the long way, the long way for a small
angry planet did make me want to throw it across the room.
And this one did not make me want to throw it across the room.
I think she has grown as a writer and it feels much more developed as a
novel, whereas the one way to a small angry planet felt incredibly episodic.
That was one thing I really didn't like about it.
It felt like six episodes of a TV show kind of jointed together.
So yeah, the problem is it's clear that she has grown into a writer that I don't
get along with.
So which is like entirely fair.
I could definitely see that this is a very specific style of book.
And I can appreciate why there are people who like it and people who don't.
The interesting thing about it to me is that the two writers on this list,
who are the writers that people come up to me who are not in our community and say,
have you read X because I know you like science fiction, our chambers and we're.
They're the two writers that have really burst out of our community and are working
like with people who do not follow like all the stuff we talk about.
And so clearly they are doing things that like people like, but clearly not.
Because I don't think spoilers this is.
I don't think either of these books are going to win the Hugo.
So yeah, clearly not in the world con kind of niche, clearly not as well received.
But it is interesting.
I bet they're selling a lot of books to non science fiction fans, but not the same
non science fiction fans as well.
I bet the people who are saying, Oh, I love the Becky shabers and not the same
people who say, you know, I love Andy Weir.
That is true.
I think.
Am I be wrong?
I think it is.
They should collaborate.
I'm going to introduce she who became the son.
I was going to say speaking of books I wanted to throw across the room harshly.
Yeah.
Alison Alison didn't get along with this one Liz.
But it ended up as my third.
So she who became the son, she who became the son is a book by Shelley Parker Chan.
It is the first book by an Australian author on the Hugo ballot.
First best novel, the finalist from an Australian.
So therefore it has broken out a little bit in Australia and it's getting read by a
lot of people because of that, which quite not to do.
She who became the son by Shelley Parker Chan is a book, which is about a monk
called Zhu Chongba or are they called that?
Basically, there is a young girl who lives in a village and is a time of famine
and everything is very bad and bandits kill her dad and her brother.
And she assumes the identity of her brother in order to secure her fate.
And she goes on an adventure.
She becomes a monk and then she gets an army and then lots of other things happen.
I've nailed this description.
It's a surprisingly difficult thing to talk about because I enjoyed it.
But from my perspective, not much happened because she was much the same
person at the beginning that she was at the end.
And really, like, no one really changes.
And like it just felt like I was reading the same passage, but about different
battles repeatedly, which I liked and it was well done.
And some of it was like some of the joining bits were very interesting.
But yeah, found it a little bit long and a little bit repetitive.
And it took me the longest of all of the books to read.
I think it's fair to say, which instead didn't like it.
But I liked it less than all the others except the we're.
Liz had it as a pick many episodes ago.
It was a pick.
She did.
And we ignored her like fools.
I was excited to read it there by.
I thought the opening was fantastic.
I've seen this described as misery porn, but I quite liked it.
I was really excited by this book after the first chapter in which terrible things
happen. John said she was trying to fill her fate.
But what she does is adopts her brother's fate as a deliberate thing that her
brother was told by some fortune teller that he was destined for greatness and then
dies. So she decides that greatness is a thing that you can go and get.
And then she goes and gets it.
So I really, really liked that bit.
And then she goes off and has a kind of an absolutely terrible growing up in a
monastery section, which is passing for a boy's section, which is just awful.
It's big in awful in big ways.
It's awful in small ways.
I was like, this book is terrible.
Everything about this book is terrible.
I cannot cope.
And then once it gets out of that bit, she then has the first bits of leadership
where the plot get, you know, she does a thing where she's like, she forces an
avalanche to happen.
And my disbelievers, suspenders went spun at this point.
I was, this is complete, Tosh, that, you know, there has never been so much
Tosh written in a novel as I am reading here right now.
Come on.
And then after that, I kind of got into a bit of more and quite liked it.
When I heard that the author had been inspired by Chinese dramas, I was kind of
like, well, I can see a bit of that because I think they have a lot of this.
Complete nonsense in them.
And, you know, when I kind of got on with that bit a bit, but in fact, there's, there's
actually less of it when she actually gets into the big politic stuff.
It's not as bad, but it's still not good.
And anyway, except that the overall conception of it, I ended up quite liking.
And it's better than the chambers because unlike John, I think stuff does happen
in this novel.
And I think characters do develop, not necessarily her.
I like the B plot quite a lot.
Um, with the, um, with the other, the other side.
And I quite liked it.
But it took a lot of going.
I would never have had I not been doing Hugo reading.
I would not have read.
I would not have picked this up, book up.
I would not have read it, but I definitely wouldn't have finished it.
So, you know, but still quite like some of it, but I had to set aside a big
pile of nonsense.
That's the big reservations.
I think I've said bigger reservations on this one.
So this is a book that some giving it some points for trying to do something
epic and not quite getting there because I like books that try to do epic things.
Yeah, I like to.
I'm not sure.
Yeah, I can't pinpoint exactly why you're saying some bits and nonsense,
them to make sure.
OK, but I mean, what I liked about it is I think one, it is following kind of a
historical, you know, using a historical backdrop that I haven't seen done that often.
And using it in a way which I think does a lot of interesting stuff about gender
and gender roles and especially, you know, when you say you doesn't change,
I think that what she does is kind of it almost feels like she is in some ways
unchanging, but in some ways kind of adjusting what she learned as a child and
realizing kind of like what she has to hide in order to be successful as a man.
And maybe the fact that she has a very strong sense of her own identity and the
fact that she's going to take this fate and she's going to make this fate hers is
kind of interesting thing about her.
And I really liked how that, you know, it contrasts like she feels like she's
never kind of comfortable being a man, but it doesn't feel like she would have
been entirely comfortable in the role of a woman and how much of that is her and
how much of that is the gender roles society she's in.
And then you contrast that kind of with the opposing, opposing general
Aoyang, who has another completely different take on kind of gender roles and sexuality.
And I thought that was like by far the most interesting part about the book.
If that had not been there, then I agree that maybe I would have not really wanted
to read it just as a sort of straight historical fantasy if it was about a peasant
boy, you know, rising to to power and the, you know, the general who opposes it.
But with that put on top of it, I really enjoyed it.
I will say, I think the character development or the character manipulation of
the B plot in the enemy camp was I did enjoy those bits.
I didn't have a problem with the avalanche because I don't think she does it on purpose.
She raised her the gods and then she does a thing and I don't know, it's open to
in separateation, I guess.
But yeah, I didn't, I didn't mind that.
I see all of the points you've made and I recognize that they're probably well done.
But like it did.
I never got excited to read more of this novel, which is why it is towards the bottom of my
do.
And also it is the first in a series and I have no inclination to pick up the second
or the third or the fourth.
So when Park Chan does another series doing something different in a different
place, I'll go and read the first of those, I think.
I think, yeah, and I think it ends pretty well.
Like I didn't feel like the cliffhanger is anywhere near as bad as some other cliffhangers.
I've seen, but also I, and maybe I'm wrong, I assumed its first half of a duology.
I assume in the next book, you will become the emperor.
And I might be wrong, but that's kind of, it felt very much to me like part one of a two-part
story in a way that I can't quite quantify.
But if anyone knows, write in listeners.
It's a duology, apparently.
There you go.
Oh, OK.
Hey, see, I'm good at books.
Trivial Superpower is detecting how long a series is from the first book.
I agree with our listen.
It is a little bit long and it does get a little bit repetitive.
But I wonder if that was partly based on, you know, whatever historical structure is
there that you kind of feel there's a bunch of like historical events you have to
tick through.
One or so, I wonder whether because if it is based in, because I knew it was based,
I know it's like the author wanted to do like a queer Chinese kind of story.
But if it is specifically based on Sea Dramas, maybe part of that comes from kind
of the structure of television and television episodes, because now when, as
soon as I can remember, was it Alison or Liz who said that that was one of the
influences?
I can't remember.
Sorry, listeners.
Sorry, people.
It was me, I think it was Alison, but I would agree with Alison.
It does feel like the Sea Drama influence on it.
So then that really made me think, oh, maybe the repetition I felt was the kind
of influence of a kind of television structure on the novel.
Because I don't, I suspect it wasn't conscious, but I wonder whether that kind
of that style of plot be, if it came from the television, that would make a lot of
sense to me in my head.
Yeah, having that sort of like reversal of fortunes.
I started feeling a lot more charitable about it when I learned that she was
influenced in influence of Sea Drama is trying to bring some of that because I
don't think there is enough of that in SF of fantasy.
So in the end, I like, I ended up liking it a lot more than I had when we went
through.
I think I have a general cross cutting point about the dead hand of plots in
novels, which in, in the weir is in the body of the, what's her name, Stratt,
the woman who jerks the plot around to suit her.
And in this one is the fate that drags the plot around.
And, and authors should hide when they're being authors a bit better than either
of these two novels.
I'm not sure I wholly agree with that because I think it's kind of the other
way round, but I know what you mean.
Light from Uncommon Stars by Rika Yuki.
And this is a book about a violinist getting some violin lessons.
So no, this is a book.
Primarily, I think about what it is to make things and what it is to be part of
a community and what it is to be authentic.
And it is a book about how you balance the pressures of who other people want
you to be with the pressures of who you actually are.
I very much enjoyed it because I really thought the ways it talks about those
themes were things I found really interesting.
And they are things that I care about quite a lot.
Like basically I'm the sort of idiot who like you be like,
where do you want to get dinner, John?
And I'm like, well, I'd all go there.
That's a chain restaurant.
I think a lot of the considerations in here about kind of small community
endeavors versus kind of other approaches really resonate with me as a result.
So I think this book was probably kind of probably pandering to me a little bit.
But I did very much enjoy it.
I also very much enjoyed the description of kind of being trans and how that
intersects with how that intersects with sexuality.
And kind of I really thought that was really interesting because obviously I
don't have that perspective.
And so seeing that perspective kind of on the page was really, I thought was
really kind of nice to see.
So yeah, in general, very much enjoyed this one.
This is the second on my ballot as a result.
I kind of go back and forth on this one because I think it does some things
very well.
Like I agree with John, it's got all those themes and it's got kind of like,
yeah, how do you find your identity and keep your identity, particularly in
immigrant communities in a community of maybe people who are like yourself or
unlike yourself?
I just felt kind of it.
It did that really well at the start.
And then I'm not sure it really expanded upon it into making a satisfying
novel.
I mean, we should say that there is there is some plot going on here, which is
that there is a woman who made a deal with devil to sell the souls of violin
prodigies to them.
And so she is, she finds Katrina that the violinist who is going to be her
seventh soul that she will sell and reclaim herself from damnation.
Yeah, I never did think that would happen, not for one minute.
Spoiler.
No, that's the thing.
She sort of that that's obviously never going to happen because it's in many
ways a very sort of sweet book.
And you can't imagine ever that, you know, Katrina, who has overcome
so much to live the life she wants to live is going to end up having her soul
soul to the devil for all time.
Yeah.
It's not as sweet as the chambers, I should say, if you're considering the
sugar content of novels, then the chambers is definitely top of Alice.
Well, it's absolutely not as sweet as that because before the novel even
starts, she's had a massive amount of trauma and she continues to have that
at the start of the novel and she finds essentially this safe, safe haven, which
is not really a safe haven because it's with the woman who's really looking
for a seventh soul to sell to the devil.
It's just I really liked the first bit and then I felt it just kind of like
kept going and then eventually ended.
And there's some sort of subplots of feel like unsatisfactory resolved, like
the woman becoming the violin repair person that she was always told she
couldn't be and things like that.
Never just sort of never seemed to kind of end up anywhere.
Does that make sense?
I love this book with reservations, which I'll get to.
I I'm interested in John's conception of it because I don't think this book is
quite as sweet as it makes out because it is a great big everything donut of a
novel.
I didn't say it was sweet.
I think I said that.
I didn't entirely get it as being a novel about community in one's place in it.
So much as I thought it was a novel about families, both biological and chosen
families and the sorts of abuse that arises in those families, even when you
don't necessarily intend for it to.
And that that was the thing that over, you know, that seemed overarching to me,
which was not sweet.
I thought it was extremely careful and there were multiple examples of it and
they were all very well done.
And I thought it's great because it's doing this hilarious story about a kind
of demon and violence and space aliens and this and that.
It is a great big everything donut of a book.
Far too many seems have been put into this book and some of them come out right
and some of them don't, but it keeps this lightness of tone while dealing with
some extremely troubling things.
And I really, really liked that, but I have some reservations about it, which I
can go to, but it's still my second choice book by Miles because I thought it
was doing something really different and I liked books that are different.
Little reservations and they are quite small.
At the end of the book, Katrina, who is the violinist, her plot arc gets
wound up substantially before the end of the novel, which then goes off and
talks about her mentor and the space aliens and they get the end of the book.
And I don't think that's entirely deserved.
And there is a bigger problem with it in that it's busy being a feel good
novel about finding your own identity and living with it.
But characters in this book are doomed to health for all eternity.
And the people who do that don't get brought to bear for doing that.
And there's another thing in which two teenagers get murdered and characters
who we left as being who presented us to being positive wholesome characters
clean up the mess and nothing more is done about it.
And in both of those cases, I was like, you can't have that stuff in this book.
So it felt underendated to me because I feel like a reputable editor would have
gone, come on, you've got to sort this out.
And you could perfectly well sort it out.
That's why they're minor reservations.
I go, yeah, no, I can see how you could get around both of those things.
I think you might be right about the violin lady and the mentor and the
aliens getting the end of the book, because I do think it is really Katrina's story.
And one of the things I wanted to say to you, so you said it was unbelievable
that the mentor would sell Katrina's soul.
It is really notable to me that at no point does she actually sell a soul.
She in every case basically says to them, you can sell your soul and you will be.
You will have all the fame you want.
And she is selecting people who want the fame.
When their children as a result of grooming, well, no, they don't.
They make the decision as adults.
As a result of grooming.
Yeah.
But there's a clear thing here, which is that Katrina gets asked the question.
She says, no, initially.
And then she says, yes, when she realized that saying no means that the mentor will be
damned. And she makes that decision because she wants to trade her soul for the mentors.
And then the book kind of engages in a little bit of chicanery and makes it all
okay on both counts, which, you know, I actually quite liked it.
Like I was glad that they resolved it.
It felt like less of a cop up than it might have done.
There was still a little bit of a cop out equally.
I'm not necessarily all that bothered by cop outs in media because return of the Jedi
is my favorite Star Wars movie.
But I do think like, and you're entirely right about the grooming, but I think the book
attempts to kind of distance itself from the horror of what she's doing by by kind
of employing that strategy.
I am not sure the extent to which I think the book really grapples with that.
And I don't know whether, like you said, the thing about the two kids getting murdered,
like the character who does the murder is punished, but like not with anything approaching
due process. So that's a problem.
And so like, yeah, there are bits in this book where I'm like, yeah, maybe you didn't
need that plot beat.
The central thing of the book being like, the problem is that when a civilization
reaches significant enough size, they all just realized that life is entirely pointless
and everything just goes to hell.
I was like, oh, that is an interesting concept.
And I really, really enjoyed that.
And I feel like I want to read a book that is much more about that because that was
an idea.
Well, when I talk about this being a bit of an everything book, there's so much here.
There are so many fizzing ideas that you could have spun a novel off.
Yeah.
And it would have been good if somebody had said to Aiki, well, maybe, maybe you could
just sort of tighten the boundaries of this little bit.
No, very excited by this book, very excited by the possibilities in it.
Enjoyed it a lot.
Yeah, definitely my second choice of these.
Yeah.
So I mean, you have picked up one of the things I had a problem with.
Basically, I think it feels a little uneven kind of the sections where it feels
very little moves on.
And then we do have this segment where, yes, as you say, one of the aliens who is
being bullied by some random teens decides the best way to respond to that is to go
and murder them.
And then like his family responses, oh, we'll clean it up and we'll never tell
anyone what happened and we'll just put you in stasis to deal with later.
And then that's kind of it.
It's kind of an astonishing thing to happen in the middle.
And I had to double check, you know, because I read five pages and I was like, did they
really just do that?
And they did.
Yeah.
So I felt that quite shocking.
And I think like that kind of exemplified what I feel about the book, which is it sort
of drops these nuggets of these nuggets of things like that.
Or like, like as John said, the giant idea about when civilizations will will collapse.
And then I'm not sure it kind of completely follows through with them.
Um, I, so I did enjoy kind of big chunks of it.
And I think it does have some good characters.
And I liked a lot of the setting and, you know, the lot of great descriptions of a
food and the importance of food and the importance of, you know, what, how food
makes you feel.
Oh, I loved all that.
But I think then it's like, actually, maybe it does that one too many times.
They go to about six different restaurants and say, and this restaurant
serves this food and it makes people feel, you know, reminded of their home or
reminded of, I thought Aiki probably writes in noodle bars.
I'm not sure that I thought that because the bit where the bit where the alien
kills the teens is clearly like radicalization thing, right?
Like the, you see the team being radicalized through the novel, like in favor of
this kind of imagined homeland and he like started becoming more and more and
more jingoistic and then eventually culminates with this horrible thing.
And they're basically like, Oh, no, this is a problem.
And they, and they stasis him.
And I did think that was an abrupt end.
And I think, you know, I wonder whether you could have told that same, you had
that same narrative thread, but without quite the abrupt end that it ends up having.
But I will, I think I disagree with the civilization ending nihilism not following
through, because I think one of the interesting things about it is that it
does follow through in the characters, like the conversations that the
head alien and the violin lady have are, I think, exploring that from a very
character focused and carrying that theme through to the end of the book with a
very character focused thing rather than a very plot focused thing.
And I, I actually really enjoyed that, especially because I think the, the
perspective of the violin lady basically comes to his, well, if nothing matters,
then we get to define our own existence.
And this is not a problem for me.
And the aliens like, there.
And I, I really like that.
Because like, I am a nihilist, but not a nihilist who thinks that nihilism is
a reason to give up.
If that makes sense, I've always been like nothing matters.
So everything I do has the meaning I attach to it.
And that means I have to be careful what I do.
And I have to put like things I like into the world because there's nothing else
that will do that for me because there is literally no reason or meaning in the
universe.
And so I've always felt that to be freeing.
And I really enjoyed the way this book talks about it.
I think this book comes very close to explicitly saying that human art and
music and possibly also doughnut making are the things that will, that could not
just cure the, what's it called, the existential plague?
Yeah.
For everybody, not just for humanity.
That's the, the, the point that the book comes to on this.
When I think the book is arguing that making stuff is what makes meaning in the
universe.
And it would be hard to argue with that.
And I think I mostly agree with that as a person who makes a thing.
So yeah.
Yeah.
I think several parts of this book actually resonate with me.
And, and actually I thought a lot of the themes were very similar to everything
everywhere at once.
That's why I mentioned the everything, donut.
Yes, it was a good, it was a good joke.
Liz, do you want to set us on the home run?
Home straight.
OK, so our final book is a designation called Peace by RK Martin, which is the
second book in her takes Kalan series.
I'm not sure if I'm pronouncing that correctly.
Anyway, so what is going on here is we were left at the end of the first book
with an empire where kind of the overthrow of the empire had narrowly been
filed and we have a new emperor in place.
And two of the characters who were heavily involved in that, we have three
seagrass, essentially an information
analyst and Mahit Dismar, who is an ambassador from a space station that is
not part of the Takes Kalan empire, but has a kind of very uneasy piece with it.
They end up as part of a conflict with another alien race, which is lurking on
the edge of their space and no one can communicate with it.
And it's kind of about how this war or conflict unfolds.
And strategically how this conflict is being used by all the different players
in this empire and by this station that isn't part of the empire, but it has its
own agenda, how they're kind of using this war and manipulating information
and manipulating the politics of the situation to each get their own ends and
how essentially three seagrass and Mahit come in and mostly disrupt that by being
themselves. Yeah.
And I really, really liked it.
I think I do just want to say that I have just checked how I pronounce.
And the name of the, the civilisation is Tix Kalan, but given its made up word,
don't think about as much.
Thanks, Kalan. Well, it's between me based on a, on a real language.
But I mean, given how important like linguistics is to this book, I should
probably feel to at least pronounce the name of the empire.
So it is, it is a sequel to a memory called Empire, which won the Hugo.
Yeah, it's just got all the sort of stuff I like, which is it has, it has
politics, it has intrigue, it has characters who are trying to kind of forge
their own relationship in the face of, you know, in the face of their
upbringings in the face of how they feel about people from these different
empires. It has first contact with an alien species.
It has, you know, the use of language and poetry for communication, hidden
information. It has a really good sex scene. It's got lots of good stuff.
Oh, that, that last bit was a spoiler there.
There's a sex scene in it, Alison.
I'm looking forward, I've been looking forward to the sex scene in this novel
ever since about 10, 10 pages into the first one.
So it was pretty good.
Loved the first book.
I have a joke about this episode and this is it, which is that I look at these
six novels and I think what we have here is five petaloes and a swan.
And the Martin is the swan.
This is a book that is just so much better than any of the other books that it's
hard to believe they're in the same book contest.
Because it does all of these things.
I mean, I haven't got to the end of the second one yet.
So, but I was kind of like, can the second one be as good?
And it was like, oh, no, it's actually engaging right there from page one with
the alien, which is the thing that the first book doesn't do.
And I was like, oh, yes, yes, it definitely can.
I'm loving it. I had to tear myself away to come and do the podcast this morning.
Thanks, Halosan.
So having so much fun with this book.
Oh, this is what this is what I read science fiction for.
Doesn't get better than this.
Yeah.
Love it to bits.
Don't really want to criticize it too hard because, you know, it might break if you
look, if you if you apply your critical chisels to it with too much intensity.
It's a fantastic book.
And I'm only halfway through.
So hopefully it doesn't, it doesn't fall apart in the last 200 pages.
Be a bit sad if that happened.
I don't think it does.
I do think the previous year in which the Martin novel was in it.
I also felt that year that the Martin was kind of head and shoulders above its
competition.
I really adore as a writer.
I think she is fantastic.
And yeah, I had heard some people say that the second book was not as good.
And firstly, I think I enjoy the second book as much partly because I really
like first contact stories and kind of conversation where people are trying to
say things to other people that don't really understand them.
And so that again plays very specifically to something I love.
But unlike the we're, which is in sixth place, this book matches that cool idea
with some stonking blonde characters.
And I very much like that too.
And I can see how someone might not like it quite as much as the first book.
But like the first book is sublime and this book is very excellent indeed.
And yeah, I'm kind of very happy to put it at the top of my ballot.
And I'm glad that I enjoyed it as much as the first novel.
Liz.
Yes, I would say that I can see why you wouldn't like it as much as the first
novel because the first the first novel has that wonderful.
I am experiencing this society and learning about this society and it's also great.
And it's hard for a second book in the same universe to live up to that.
But I do think I felt it started a little bit slowly.
And then in the last couple of hundred pages, I really got what it was going to be.
Like what was going to be the theme?
No, not.
I mean, it starts slowly in plot terms, but I think it's really the end of it.
That all the things, the kind of, you know, paths that have been laid through the
first two thirds start to come together and you start to see why a character has to be,
you know, moved from A to B in the first two thirds in order for it to
satisfactorily kind of end up at sea at the end.
Like it all all starts to come together very nicely in a way, in a way that you want.
And therefore in like hindsight, the first section does not seem slow at all.
And I also thought, yeah, as a second book in a series, it manages to add the
extra thing and that the extra thing in this case is kind of even more thinking
about societies where individuals are not necessarily solely individuals,
but are linked or, you know, have access to the thoughts and feelings of other,
other individuals and what that brings to you as a society and how you have kind
of three very different societies that approach this in a different way.
And how they kind of all end up, I think, you know, working out about this in
different ways. It's not very coherent. But obviously, I'm pointing out why I
mean, like there's basically three very different approaches to not being an
individual who is the sole individual in your own, own mind.
And I think you see at the end that these three are going to come together.
And how, especially with, I won't, I won't spoil this to a trial and photo,
especially with 20 Cicada and his eventual decisions and outcome.
I really enjoyed. Oh, I love him as a character already.
Love, love, love, very excited by where that's going.
And also, I know that John talks about, about reading novels,
whilst not thinking too hard about what the author might be doing with particular
characters and where they might be taking them. But I, that the bigger
arm bells have gone off with that character. And I'm very excited about where that
goes. So, and, and again, I just assume that Martine is good enough that nothing
is in her novel, not for a reason, and it will all come out.
But I turned out to be wrong about that about the cats.
Apparently, sometimes a cat is just a cat.
No, a cat is always excellently a cat.
I did. I wanted to say, I wanted to say, actually, I was slightly wrong the year
that the previous Martine won. I also thought the 10,000 doors of January was
very, very good, very different. But I really enjoyed that.
But in fact, the second place novel and the most first place votes was for
Sean and McGuire's middle game.
Middle game is good, but I got slightly, I had good ideas by
don't didn't think it stuck the ending.
Well, I cannot tell you whether the Martine sticks the ending.
And now we're going to discuss some of the themes we think are arising from
these novels as a whole. I did want to say like, it is interesting to me that
two of these books, at least, are clearly highly influenced by lockdown,
because like the galaxy in the ground within and Project Hail Mary both feel
very much like books that were written by someone who was inside and could not
leave. And they are books about being inside and being unable to leave.
And that interested me.
And I thought I thought it was cool kind of, yeah, just thought it was cute and
kind of, I think, expected that that might be a theme of some of the novels
getting nominated for things at the moment. But yeah, I found that kind of
curious, I guess.
I think that's true for the chambers for the weir. I rather less
charated me just think he's not very good at writing two characters together
unless those two characters happen to be the same character in two bodies.
I don't want to spoil the ending, but in the ending, I got a very strong
sense of Dr. Zargle's book of Earthlets, which is a science fiction novel for two
year olds. And in the bit where they were putting the team together for the
spaceship, I got a very strong sense of Hugh Walter's novels in which there's a
kind of global space force that picks stereotypical people from each
character, as a country, and I feel like the Russian in that was better drawn
than the Russian in the weir. So, you know, so that was also aimed at eight year
old. So, so yeah, a little bit of aliens in alien suits in human suits or
humans in alien suits.
Because that was a cross cutting theme of this, the aliens in the Becky chambers
are not quite as alien as I'd like them to be. Give weir some credit, he does
some hard thinking about what sort of world generates life that's like Rocky.
And I feel like we could have chambers could do with doing a little bit more of
that in her world building rather than just assuming that you get, I mean, it
felt like the cantina, right?
I would argue that there is an extent to which all human writing about aliens
is humans in alien suits because we are limited by our own capacity to imagine
as deeply on health or comment. But I've, I think chambers is, I think, very
deliberately trying to imagine like, well, let's not constrain ourselves to what
we can imagine developing, but let's just say why have completely bizarre
creatures evolved like, and I kind of think that's almost kind of a nice way of
trying to get around the problem because then you're not limited by your
imagination of how life could evolve. You're just like, colours maybe. And I did,
I kind of respect that, but I do take your point. And like the Martin does a very
good job. Well, yeah, I think the Martin does a very good job with alien feeling
aliens. So, you know,
Well, I mean, I think the Martin does a very good job with different, different
human societies as well, right? So with all her barbarians.
I mean, that's the thing in, in some ways, it feels that the different human
societies in Martin's book have kind of more kind of communications, difficulties
and barriers between them than the completely alien aliens in Becky
Chambers books do. There's a lot of kind of points of common
allows you from childhood that childhood kind of does some of the same sorts of
things in all these different societies. And, and I think, Martin doesn't fall
into that trap. You know, her, her different human societies are very alien
in the way that actual different human societies can be.
Yeah, I was thinking the difference between like the the takes
clan and the cell station people who are not on a first first contact trajectory.
But it's also easy to do that with only kind of two, you know, really two
societies to play with. And in a reservation about the Aoki, her
aliens are really not very alien even by the standards of these things.
And they are literally wearing human suits. So, you know,
important, you know, that's not one of the things that her demon is not very
demonic and her aliens are not very like that sort of things.
I thought the demon was quite demonic, but maybe, I don't know, there might be
he does demonic, but also familiar in the way that like, you know, all demon
figures in literature kind of like Dr Faust. Yeah. Yeah.
I sort of feel like I sort of feel like part of this is like the same reason that
you never get properly compelling descriptions of hell. Because you can't
imagine like an eternity of suffering because you're only human.
But if there is a God and he has created an eternity of suffering, I believe it
will be an eternity of suffering. And I just can't imagine it.
Yeah. But that's also why having people getting
eternity of suffering needs to be given a little bit more weight in the novel
than it necessarily is in in life from a cover stars.
Well, I mean, let's be honest here.
There's no such thing as hell or aliens.
So there's no point in being too realistic about these things.
It's the sort of the same way that, you know, you can't you never dwell too
much in hell in the good place because like the thought is unimaginable.
You did go on about the sort of book that physicists.
So so the martin is the sort of book that civil servants like because the
politics of the diplomacy in those novels is just it's fantastic.
And despite the fact that Parker Chan has worked as a diplomat,
the diplomacy in that book didn't ring true for me.
And that is because I think I said earlier that human conversations don't often
don't go in the way that either character expects.
And martin does that a lot.
And Parker Chan does that not at all.
So every conversation that anybody has and it comes out the way that one of the
people was expecting to.
And that's not how diplomacy and politics work.
You said, oh, the sort of book physicists like and then proceeded to not at all
talk about that, but going on about diplomacy.
But I do want to bring up because I think you have a point, which is we talked
about cozy escapism when we talked about the chambers.
But from a different point of view, the we're is absolutely also cozy escapism.
Yeah, no 100%.
And so it's weird to think like those two things are definitely both cozy
escapism, even though I think if you told like, you know, fans of fans of Andy
were you are reading something which is cozy escapism in the same way.
I might read a romance novel or you might read the Becky Chambers.
They would absolutely not think that.
Alison just said that even though Parker Chan worked as a diplomat, like she had
problems with the Parker Chan book, because it didn't ring true to her in terms of
diplomacy. And I said, part of the reason the we're is the sort of book physicists
like is because it does a lot of linear extrapolation in ways that don't break
science. And you read as a physicist and awful lot of books that just do banana
things with physics.
I've never really minded that.
But I do have a lot of friends who I think mind it a lot more than me.
And the we're I think one of the reasons why I've got a lot of friends who really
like the we're is because I think that we're doesn't do that for the physicists
who mind it. But equally, there are very few things in SF where I have a
professional problem with because I'm quite happy to suspend my disbelief about
stuff that isn't physically rigorous.
And I think SF expects us to do that more with physics and maybe with biology
that it does with other stuff. But I don't know whether that's actually true,
or whether that's just like a bias I have from understanding one of those
things and not the other.
So the point you actually made when we were having this discussion, not on the
podcast was I got over this thing with physics a long time ago.
So maybe Alice, and it's time for you to get over it in terms of politics of the
stuff you remember from your civil service career and kind of sorts of
organizational structures, because I am very interested in the way that
organizational structures work and humans interacting with them.
And I like science fiction that does that and I like it to get it a bit right.
So yeah, maybe I do need to get over myself.
But I got over the physics thing as well, because I mean, I do know that
science, lots of science fiction doesn't take its starts too seriously,
which I think is to its benefit.
Liz, do you have any comments on how great science fiction is apology?
Nope. It's nearly in a time.
So no.
And then do you want to talk about lesbians?
I mean, I just put that because I realised there's an awful lot of
lesbians in these books.
The prime relationship of the Martin, the Clark, you know, the Parker
Chan, they are all basically centred around lesbian partnerships, which I
thought was interesting.
And even the chambers, which like has a nominally, well, it has a
heterosexual relationship, a human male and a female who is of a different
species who can change gender if she wants to.
And like, I would argue that just the species aspect makes it queer, but
it's also not quite as even if you ignore that aspect, it's not quite as
simple as being like, that is a straight relationship.
So it's an interesting point that a lot of these do explore that as a kind of
thing.
Yeah, I was thinking that it's interesting to me, it's not even just
queer relationships.
It is specifically in those four, like lesbian relationships, and indeed,
you know, and kind of older lesbians in the Ioki way.
I think I wasn't expecting to come up with such a disparate group of books, I
think. It's quite interesting to see.
I mean, there is a lot of it.
And there aren't any positive depictions of human heterosexual
relationships in these books, don't think?
I mean, the Project Hail Mary has no depictions of good relationships,
whatever.
I mean, I guess we've had plenty of years of that.
Yeah, that's it.
But we haven't really, because what we actually had was relationships between
science, dudes, and some effects.
So that doesn't count.
Yeah.
Yeah, I still think like the heterosexuals can, you know, take a back seat for a year.
Fine.
I don't mind.
Didn't mind it, but I would agree that there are a lot of lesbians in these
books.
If that's what you like, then the Hugo reading is for you.
I had another cross-cutting scene that I didn't put in that I'm going to say very
quickly, which is that I have never read all of the books on the Hugo ballot before.
This is like, this is like one of David Lodge's humiliation around, says it is I
haven't ever read all the books on the Hugo ballot before in time to vote.
And it's very interesting reading books, which are some of which it was that you
would never naturally pick up to read and then getting to sort of think, well,
how does the field all fit together at the moment?
Because some of these books are books that I would not normally have chosen.
That's why I like, I really like reading the Hugo shortlist because it forces me to
expand beyond like my kind of default.
And sometimes I am really pleasantly surprised.
And sometimes I'm not, but the amount I've gained from doing it has been far more
than the amount of time I've wasted on stuff I didn't really like.
I think I think in general, the balance is very much towards it being a positive
thing rather than a negative thing in my case.
So yeah, I like it.
I try into it.
If you work out from our votes, what our consensus kind of ballot would be, a
desolation called Peace is in first place, followed by Light from Uncommon Stars,
followed by She Who Became the Sun, followed by the Galaxy and the Ground Within,
followed by a Master of Gin, followed by Project Hail Mary.
So we all agree on our first and last place picks, and there's a little bit
jiggling around in the middle.
I think consensus wise, we all think the Parker Chan, as a consensus, we think
the Parker Chan and Ioki are better than the chambers and the clerk.
I know that Liz likes the clerk better than me and Alison.
Sorry, Liz.
I just want to say that consensus list is the same as my list.
So we should just have had a dictatorial thing where I told you what to believe.
And that would have done.
It seems unlikely.
Yeah, given how much I disagree with the consensus list, I will not be listening to
solely Alison's opinions on books.
What do we think will actually be the order of the books?
On the short list.
I think it might be quite close to our consensus list.
I wonder whether the chambers will do slightly better than we have ranked it.
I think the we're is going to do much better than we ever act it.
I think it's going to get a lot of first place votes from people who are very
sad about what sorts of books have been willing to go recently.
I think it might get a lot of first place votes, but I think it will
it will last first place votes and it will still not come second because the
overwhelming consensus of the community is not that even though there is a strong
minority for whom it is that by my wrong.
I think Martin will win.
Does anyone disagree with me on that?
No, I don't think any of the other books can take it.
I mean, I think it since it's already, you know, the previous one won, I think
in a very similar situation where there was other good stuff on the short list,
but it was probably just above them.
And I think the same thing will happen again.
Yeah, I think the we will get a lot of first place votes.
But then when it gets knocked out, it'll be interesting to see if any of them
actually redistribute to other stuff on the short list or if they kind of all
go into the no award bucket or just no air bucket because it feels like it
appears to appeal to quite different set of people.
What do we think should have been on the ballot that wasn't?
Like if you could take, if we take Project Hail Mary off the ballot,
what sixth book should have been on that ballot?
No offense to anyone who loved Project Hail Mary, but it is our sixth place choice.
So I would assume that is the one we would replace with a different one if we
were there, if we were the monarchs of the Hugo Awards.
I mean, I would put Aidan Tricowski's Shards of Earth on there because it is,
you know, having looked at books which we say, oh, the aliens are all a bit too human
humans in alien suits.
That is a book which really feels like it has some quite alien aliens,
included one who was sort of a distributed, a distributed intelligence.
And it's got all that couple to an actual plot, some good space opera,
a crew being rounded up to a century, a kind of semi-heist,
heist plotline, kind of universe destroying threat.
It's just got loads of stuff in there as well as having a lot of these aliens and also,
you know, some humans who are clearly dealing with some trauma from last time
that aliens came to attack.
So I think it kind of covers a lot of stuff which is in some of the Hugo finalists,
but does it all in one package and does it really well?
So I put that on.
Alison, I will put on Monica Burns, the actual star because I like
massively ambitious books, even if they're a bit flawed.
And I thought it was massively ambitious, more ambitious than anything else.
I read apart from possibly the routine because it ties these
seams of historical fantasy with modern day contemporary SF with far future SF.
And it brings it all together in a kind of twine story.
And it's just like catlit for Alison's.
And it's not perfect, but I would love to see more books like that on the Hugo ballot, please.
I have a dirty secret listeners, which is I haven't read that many books.
It's really 21.
So I'm just going through my good reads to find out which books were from 2021
so I can have an informed opinion and I shall read them out.
Now I read from 2021, The Psychopath Club by Sandra Bond,
The Rising Storm Star Wars, The High Republic by Kevin Scott, The Unraveling by Benjamin Rosenbaum,
The Jasmine Throne by Tasha Sierry,
Leviathan Falls by James S.A. Corey, and Star Wars, The High Republic Into The Dark by Claudia Gray.
Of those books, I'd probably go for The Psychopath Club, but The Jasmine Throne is a close second.
But yeah, of those, I think The Psychopath Club is the best one.
I have already plugged this book, but if you haven't read it, go and get it because it is great,
especially if you like The Wasp Factory by Ian Banks.
It has a lot of kind of, it really reminded me of that in a good way.
I wouldn't have nominated either of Star Wars is, and I didn't nominate Leviathan Falls.
The Expanse always were already won in series, so I don't think it needs any recognition.
Singly, I think they work better as a series anyway.
Did you not read, did you read Redemptor?
Oh, sorry, I should know.
I'm not mentioning ones that are on the load star ballot.
Ooh, OK.
I'm not sure whether I would have nominated any of them for Best Novel, but I did.
The ones I have read are very good, but like, I quite like how different the load star and novel
ballots end up being every year because it gives me a better view of the genre.
Goodness, that sounded one key.
I have a question.
Load Stars not a Hugo.
Do they still redistribute votes?
Oh, no, because like, if you nominate a novella in Best Novel, the votes would get nominated,
like, would get shunted back into novella by the administrators.
I assume they don't do that for load star.
No, you can explicitly know you can explicitly be nominated for both the
load star and Best Novel or Best Novella.
It does slightly surprise me, then, that there hasn't been a little bit more
crossover between the two, but maybe this is why load star was good.
But this is why it took forever to get a young adult category into the Hugo's.
Yeah, I think everyone was very worried about things just being in both because people
were very worried about the exclusivity of it, particularly as as we see, there's so
much stuff that feels quite young adult-like on the getting onto the novel ballot.
We might talk about the load star, not when he's later, sorry, the load
star finalists later in the year, we might not.
Well, apparently we're quite, we could talk, we could bleep on for some time about
science fiction.
Who knew?
It's interesting.
Listeners, we have been recording for four hours.
Now, admittedly, we did record a different episode earlier today.
So that's not all Hugo's, but I joined this Zoom call four hours and 53 seconds ago,
as I speak now.
That is a long session by Octa-Thop standards.
But that was the Octa-Thop podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
[Music]
I mean, I'm also this book, so far I'm at the point where this book has flat cats in
it and I'm like, Oh, Martin is too clever a science fiction writer.
So this is both flat cats in that it's a call out to flat cat and true to the flat
cats, I use the triples, right?
We have a cute species that is taking over the ship.
But clearly that's going to be linked to the overall theme as well.
There's no way those cats are turning up later as either the novel form of something
or an element of something or something that's going to be integrated into a
live mind or something of that kind.
You're making the classic mistake of not understanding people who like cats.
Sometimes a cat is just a cat.
Oh, for fuck's sake, it's a bet.
It's a bet not be just a cat because fuck.
She's Mr. Trick there.
No, she hasn't.
It's a cat that illuminates something about the personality of people on the ship.
Yeah, they've been infected by a parasite that causes them to like cats.
No, that's a cat.
You're your your desire for mentions of cats to be not about cats is shining through here.
But as someone who likes cats, I very much enjoyed the cats.
It had been infected by a parasite.
And we are two thirds of us.
So so Liz has previously volunteered at a cat cafe.
So Liz is also full on board the cat train.
I did yesterday.
It was very nice.
Oh, Jesus.
If we were the Supreme Court, we'd be ruling two to one in favor of cats.
In favor of just having cute cats turn up in your lawn for no good reason on a spaceship.
No, a good reason.
Rather than what would actually happen on any actual spaceship,
which is that they'd have had a massive eradication program.
I think there is good precedent for laying cats on naval ships, right?
Yes, because they because they might because they do actually have massive.
The cats on naval ships are an eradication process program for the mice and rats on naval ships
and no kidding because they will ship store food.
Yeah, I know. I know. I know this.
But I think if you get to a point where your ships are sufficiently well,
like parrots, I think I think probably people on ships.
Ship.
We are having the podcast guys.
We're having a podcast.
No, because a big guy going back cats is not what we want.
There's a reason you can have the cats are there to also eliminate something about how people
change, how people interact with cats.
And it's also very much about like, you know, how do you continue being a person
when you are in space on a warship?
And maybe one of those things is seeing someone unexpectedly petting a cat.
Anyway, I don't have a problem with another alien life form turning up in this book.
And I'm totally up for that.
And clearly there are things I don't know yet because I'm halfway through.
But they're not the cats.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod
and ComaveTech.com.
Used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
beep