Right, people I actually know might be listening to this podcast, John. I think that is over
my rudeness line. Sorry, John. Sorry, Liz. It was quite funny. It is quite funny.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 70th episode of Oxford though, the podcast for science
fiction and science fiction fandom, which is coming to you on the 10th of November 2022.
I'm John Cox and I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty and we have some letters of comments.
That we have two episodes worth of letters of comment because actually we sneakily recorded
69 before you had listened to 68 bonus letters all around. Dude, because Raj says that the correct
response to 69 is dude as per Messers, Preston and Logan and that is fair comment Raj. When there
is a genre call back, we should always do the genre one, right? Yeah, that's fair.
Isn't that like a very gendered biased comment? I think we established quite early on that
chaps was gender neutral. I believe it was an episode title. Yes, so dudes is also gender neutral.
For the purposes of responding to the number 69 in a feminist way, I feel that dudes can be
gender neutral. Write in feminists, all of you. No, no, no, it's okay.
Listeners won't know this but Liz has recently received, recently purchased two new fountain pens
so she can write twice. You can also do that mirror writing where you have a fountain pen in
each hand and and be your chorolean. So Raj also notes there were no graphs and I did forget to do
the graphs. Basically it's just been, I don't know, the world seemed to have been very manic in the
last few months and so I forgot to do the graphs. I'm very sorry, I will do graphs for next time.
Well they're going to be graphs. They were going to be graphs. I'm going to do a graph of the
bimodal distribution of the Hugo voting and I completely forgot. Yeah. So I will do that, I promise.
And then what makes Discovery the worst space shuttle other than being in a big garage?
And that is the only thing. Like I don't have a beef with Discovery's track record as a scientific
vehicle. It is just the way it is displayed. I think if you're going to go and see the space
shuttles there are more exciting space shuttles to see museum-wise. Give us your ranking of space
shuttles which are the most exciting, from most exciting to least exciting museum-wise, please John.
Atlantis is the best space shuttle and then I think Endeavour is the second best space shuttle
and Discovery is the third best. I haven't seen Enterprise yet. I've only just started Voyager
but I'll get there eventually. That was a joke listeners. You can tell from the fact that both
Alison and Liz are studiously ignoring it. Do you have a tumbleweed thing to put on your
stream deck? You know I could get a stream deck and then I could just press the tumbleweed button
every time John makes a joke. Hahaha yep I'm down. And then John will edit them straight out again.
Oh we need to do a guest as it Liz. Problem is that would be work so it's not likely to happen.
Raj wrote to us about episode 68 and says that he disagrees with me listening from number one
was a brilliant experience and says that we're all going to get drinks out of it so recommends
against discouraging it too much and that a naked self-interest is a powerful motivator.
When are we seeing you Raj? I mean presumably Eastercom.
Wow yeah you could definitely pass drinks. I mean and if Liz isn't there we will have Liz's drink
for her and because we're heroes. And we can phone her up. We can drink Liz's drink at her.
There will be no phoning me up while you are drinking my drinks. I will accept one or the other
but not both. Raj also says that there have been a friend of Glasgow since very early and got an
email saying they were being upgraded to full attending without any extra payments so they're
not sure where the £20 that I mentioned comes from. I don't think anyone else knows Glasgow £20
I think it is just me and it's a long story involving a contraceptive and a time machine and we don't
have time to go into it here. That was a reference. I did try and get Eastercom to owe me a penny but
instead of going for a complicated process I just told them that their form was not quite right.
That was great. Thank you for getting in touch Raj. And for continuing to listen now like the
you know the buzz of listening to 90 episodes and two weeks has won off. Esther wrote to us.
Esther did. She wrote us a long email explaining some of the background as to why the Glasgow website
was complicated saying they think they should have sorted that out by now but saying critically
that Badger is the best cat. Badger is the best cat. Basically Esther sent us an email telling us
to shove it up our back end. Only people who have read the email know why that's funny which means
it's us three at Esther because Esther didn't at all say that but it pleases me to lie. She said
you're very welcome to cut it all apart from the bit about Badger being the best cat. You have to
say that on the podcast. I mean that is fine. I would say that every week if necessary.
By quoting Esther out of context John why have just ensured that Esther will send us another email.
I think she's good. I think she's good really it's cool.
Bah, ha, ha, ha, ha. Yeah and it's very nice of Esther to take the time to write to us and explain
things because I imagine she is basically permanently busy for the next two years.
And whose fault is that? We love you Esther. We love Glasgow. It's the best WorldCom and Badger is the best cat.
Glasgow is the best WorldCom. Badger is the best cat. Karen Schafer is the only person to respond to
my exaltation to the listeners to email if you vote for best editor and she emailed to say
that she doesn't. So as far as I could tell literally none of our listenership does
which I think says a lot about the viability of the category in general. Fair. Sorry editors
but it's not editors obviously do a great job and deserve recognition. The hue goes to a terrible
job of providing a mechanism by which that can happen I think is where I'm at on this.
Karen does suggest best editor awards we better given as a nebula judged by a professional audience
which yeah I mean is it going to work in the hue goes because that's not how the hugh goes
work but I think there is maybe some truth to that or you know kind of like how the the Oscars
work of having like specialist vote on particular specialist categories or at least created shortlist
in particular categories you know that might be interesting to have like an editor voted shortlist
of editors for a public vote or something similar. I know this will never happen in the hugh goes
but it's fun to speculate. I'm looking forward to the Batties which is Liz's awards
recognising editors. The Batties. I'm not giving out any awards recognising editors
okay any awards but if I did they'd look. What would you give awards for if you were giving
awards Liz? I don't know don't put me on the spot. Best award trophy. You were going to talk about
my plumbers there Alison. I was Mark Plutmer wrote to correct John's statement about
ISBNs and ISSN's he says he didn't say anything about that in terms of fanzine and
British library deposits because banana wings doesn't have one and they were contacted by the
British library and told they had to deposit copies so I'm like well what did plocked it I mean
presumably at some point the British library decided that banana wings was worthwhile and
plocked it was trivial. I mean it's good to know that the British library has an accurate
impression of the British landscape isn't it? Yeah you only need to deposit copies if there's
a print edition apparently and there were there were online editions of octa-thop so maybe they
just kind of went over the way back machine will do. Did you mean to talk there or or plocked
I probably meant plocked to what did I say did it make any sense does anything make any sense?
You know because you said there are print editions of octa-thop and like we haven't been
talking about putting octa-thop in the British library because that would be weird.
Hey British library would you like octa-thop? To be fair Liz I assumed you knew that every
episode I make I put on a USB stick and mail it straight to the British library I don't know what
they do with them. Well they farted to their big round reading bin so they said they just mail
it straight back. Mark said as our resident fan historian Alison, undoubtedly already know I
did not know this obviously because I am not a fan historian. The new wusswuss memberships are a
reversion to the way that things used to be done. You pay to join the convention and then you paid
an attending supplement if you were planning to go. C1956 where it says of loncon to join the
convention it will cost fans one dollar then it will cost them another dollar if they attend.
How was the first loncon Alison? Fuck off John.
Thank you very much to Mark for writing in. We also heard from Nicholas White on the subject
of Hugo nominations which basically he says Alison is right that works don't include people.
The logic he gives is that people can be eligible in both categories and so moving the wouldn't make
sense. I do kind of feel like if someone's clearly not eligible in one category and is clearly
eligible in the other it would absolutely make sense again. So I still think that's a whole but
but no fair enough. He's good to know that that is how it works.
What if you move some one what if you move nominations to someone who was
definitely not eligible in both but you didn't move nominations for someone who say
you know edited lots and lots of novels and a small amount of short fiction therefore would
be like technically eligible in both but much more likely to be nominated in one it gets tricky.
Now as a good point it is a good point. Chris Zephyr J Garcia he says that he sent
issues of the journey planet to the British Library and also to the Library of Congress the
National Library of Ireland the National Library of Australia and a few universities and other
libraries and apparently the University of California Riverside had asked Chris to send a USB stick of
everything he's ever done to them but he hasn't done yet. UC Riverside have a then they have a huge SF
library or SF collection. Sorry I was just contemplating a USB stick containing everything
Chris Garcia has ever done. It doesn't include the poos. How many terabytes would you need for the
completed works of Chris Garcia? Chris writing and let us know. Yeah we expect you to have done this
by the next time we record and we expect to know exactly how many bites it is to the bite
no rounding. He also says about episode 69 in his letter regarding that he has lots of opinions
about he goes he thinks there should be as many he goes as Oscars. I don't know how many Oscars
there are he also says despite the complete opaqueness of EPH he thinks it's worked and is working
and yeah I agree with that I think anyone else got any opinions? Don't the Oscars have so many
Oscars that they basically present a load of them I think will be less popular to television
audience after a separate ceremony. Yeah so so that's the problem is that if we have very many
more Hugo's some of them get passed out to a different ceremony and guess who gets put into
the different ceremony? Best editor. It should be a continually moving feast based on how many votes
they got the previous year. Oh oh oh this I would be very up for the Hugo's being a lot more like the
Premier League. They could be a playoff. Fiona Moore wrote to us on episode 67 saying that they've
now shut the boat ride at Phantom Peak presumably because of the number of people who got duckings
as the weather got colder. We got very wet on that ride. It turns out that you know how boats have
like sides so that if the boat rocks a bit water doesn't come in. Turns out that was a good innovation.
I thought all boats just were infinite planes. Do you know that boats have sides?
Yeah this boat was a not very infinite plane with with... Do they have corners or do they have
vertices? That's the question. Octoport vertex corner. That's one for anyone who has listened
from the very early days. Should that be Octoport corner vertex? Ah we also had Peter Soderman
wrote in to say that he is listening on Bluetooth enabled hearing aids so he can hear us right in
his ears and Farah Mendelssohn responded to say that Farah also does this. So um hoorah for hearing
aids. I'm very flattered that you choose to basically keep pipers directly into brains. Yep.
What's the news peeps? There isn't really that much news. Yeah! And that was the Octoport
Despite it being a while since we recorded it seemed to have been a unusually quiet season for
science fiction science fiction fandom news. I'm saying that because then I know everyone's
going to write into us tell us which bits of news we missed. What we should do is we should do you
know when there's not much news on the actual news and they do loads of like human interest stories
we could just spend ages talking about Johnny and his new cat. I feel that is more of a visual
story. Very good cat though. It's a good cat. Anyway news there was I mean there was some news.
After we said the most exciting thing on the off-sea clock award shortlist was Deep Wheel
Ocadia by Harry Josephine Giles it duly won the off-sea clock awards so congratulations. Yes. Yes.
And you it turns out you can get it as an audio book narrated by the author so that's probably what
I will do. Oh yes I know the none of us were at the clock award ceremony but I saw photos it
looks like this year I was at the science museum tying in with an exhibit at the science museum
that looks pretty good. A bunch of us are going to the science fiction exhibition at the science
museum on the morning of the 25th of November so do come along if you'd like to just book your
ticket for 11 o'clock and I will see you there. It was curated by Glenn Morgan who has written
a accompanying book or edited in a accompanying book which Rachel Livermore has a chapter in
wow so that was very good and I'm excited to have a look at it but I'm also excited to go to the
exhibition. So I am pretty excited. Are you going to the exhibition as well John? I mean at some point
I haven't made much firm plans. Yes. Running till next year. So well done to Harry Josephine
Drowls. I still haven't read any of the other C o'clock award nominees but I will get around to
it eventually probably. And there were a couple of shortlist reviews I think this one on Strain
Tries and Switch I will pop in the comments. Show notes not the comments. Pop in the show notes.
Don't forget to like and subscribe listeners.
Alison tell us about Pemicon and the emails you have received from them. I am I suppose I'm a
supporting member of Pemicon and they've sent me an email saying you're a supporting member of Pemicon
and here's what you need to do to upgrade to attend and I'm a supporting member of Pemicon because I
accidentally got pissed and spent 60 dollars on a moustache shirt at their party at Chicold which
is why you should never go to parties at Wilcons. The moral of the story is don't party listeners.
And I was pissed because I had been drinking pints and pints of James Bacon's toilet water
and I don't know how much alcohol is in it. Dave O'Neill's toilet water. It was David
Doney's toilet pims earlier in the weekend and then later in the weekend it was toilet water
said James and Dave O'Neill was like oh god he's put passion for, I step aside for one
million and he's put passion fruit in it. And it was repulsive but alcoholic like so many people I know.
But the excellent thing about this is that Alison gets regular emails from Pemicon now
reminding her that she got too drunk and bought a moustache shirt which is amazing.
And that if I would like I could buy another moustache shirt because they have more moustache
shirts for the con. Yes they immediately changed the moustache shirt when they became Pemicon.
Yeah so I bought the moustache shirt and then eight hours later it was it was out of date when
they announced the the convention. Well and given that you're doing Glasgow merch I hope you're
taking copious notes because this is merchandise par excellence. Pretty much yeah. But I have
got a nice moustache shirt. I mean have you bought another moustache shirt now then? Not yet.
Boo. Oh god how drunk was I? You were quite drunk. I don't know I think I'd gone to bed
at the point you purchased this t-shirt this is the problem right?
It seems very likely duffled to it. Yes. Was that the night when you stayed up and drank margaritas?
No different night. Okay oh. No oh no I got very drunk on several lights at Chicago. Sorry guys.
And I stopped using John's excellent app called moderation that tells you how much you've had
to drink and goes nah-ah-ah later in the evening. Have pancakes that have jam on them made by
listener to the podcast Meg. Ooh very good. Anyway do you want to talk about the First Nations fund
which is why we were bringing up Pemicon. So Pemicon have announced their First Nations travel fund
and they have said that they are committed to reserving 10% of their adult attending
memberships or 4000 Canadian dollars which if it is greater to assist Indigenous
science fiction and fantasy fans to travel to Winnipeg this fund will be under the direction of
Indigenous groups who will contact Pemicon to request funds for individuals they believe
should be assisted to travel. Pemicon will not make decisions about who is eligible for funding
and they haven't I don't think they've released more information than that there is a link in the
show notes that's quite neat I like it. I think it's very neat and Alison you could now think of it as
buying a quite nice t-shirt and also making a large donation to the First Nations fund
if that helps with your t-shirt buying. I could write to them and say could you not give me a
supporting membership and instead donate the purchase price of that t-shirt to the First Nations
fund rather than using it for the general convention fund which is presumably what I actually supported.
Yeah but they're not going to you know the more money they get the more they'll have for that
and it's not like you as a sporting member you're going to cost them much money anyway were you?
No don't suppose so I'm an idiot and you might want your sporting membership anyway if you fancy
voting on the NASFIC. Ooh the NASFIC for 24 presumably. Class go. 24 NASFIC which I probably do care
about don't I. Do you? I don't know. I don't feel I should care about but nevertheless. I'm
probably not going. Yeah I mean unless it's in Glasgow but it seems unlikely. Because it was
very convenient if we organised the NASFIC in Glasgow for the week before the world caught it
would be just great because everyone could just do both conventions. I feel this is constitutionally
not allowed. I believe no matter how you read the section of the Wissers Constitution on the
definition of North America it is difficult to put Scotland in it. Yeah okay we will hold it in the
Canadian Embassy in Edinburgh. Canadian Embassy please write in. Also I don't think surely it would
be a consulate. Yeah it's a Canadian Embassy in Edinburgh. Well because there's only one embassy
right and presumably it is in London. I'm presuming. It was just a joke. I mean I understand that it
needed to be micro-analyzed. Look right. If your jokes are not factually accurate jokes about
Canadian international relations are they really jokes?
We were then going to talk about Chengdu. Liz do you want to get started on Chengdu?
Yes so the reason I was going to bring up Chengdu is because I think I went to their website to see
if there was any news about Chengdu and realised that I could now log in to their website. So I
log in and I have an account on their website and it shows me I have a Wissers membership, a 2023
Hugo Award voting rights membership, physical admission, online admission and voting rights for 2025.
I'm not quite sure why they are listed as five different categories but I have caught all the
Chengdu Pokemon. So I assume anyone else who voted at discount can now log in and do the same and
check everything is fine in their account. What I can't work out is if it's actually possible to
buy a new admission. I mean at the risk of your form when you can try and do it but they don't
have credit card payments up and running yet. Can you pay by WeChat? Yeah so you can pay by
WeChat and AliPay I think and there is a thing saying that you can pay by transferring fees
directly to our collaborator but I haven't gone through the whole form to figure out if that actually
works because they have to fill in a whole form and they don't actually want to buy
another membership. Because we're already attending. Yeah I mean I think you know they made
you stand up with a US agent and that would be perfectly sensible and I could three actively
pay by WeChat but I don't think I've set up a credit card with WeChat so but that's on me you
know. I haven't spent a while this week having to get my line account re-verified so that I could
pay because it's a mechanism I use to pay train fares basically. You can set up everything in line
but it won't properly validate your payments stuff until you fully do the know your customer
thing which in my case required me to send them two separate forms of ID like as selfie is next to
my face so I suspect you're going to have a lot of problems. What is line? So line is it's a Japanese
social messaging and everything app you know in the way you have now everything apps it's a Japanese
one but it's very very widely used in Thailand so I can link it up to the where I pay my like
train fares using a card on the train system in Bangkok and use it so I can recharge my train
card through that and it's not working because I hadn't apparently fully verified my identity
and so I have now done that but it took a while but until you actually try and pay for something
you wouldn't know you weren't properly verified so I suspect WeChat is going to be the same but you
can give it a go. I had to do quite a bit of verification to get the chat the account in the
first place but maybe not enough. When I try and click on the login link I've been sent I get
Chinese characters that say incorrect password but I'm not using a password so I am confused by that.
Did you request a login thing and it gives you... Oh no no it worked it worked if I pressed the
link in the second email that just arrived I don't want to tell them why there are two but I'm in.
Ah yeah that sort of thing where if you've got this is the thing I'm finding with like login
emails because I was working with a very rubbish email login system for something if you I
accidentally request two the first one gets automatically cancelled but the second one hasn't arrived
so anyway you're in. Yeah I had to translate this from Chinese listeners. Thank you for
participating in site selection vote of the 2023 World Science Fiction Congress. You have obtained
membership in Chengdu 2023 World Science Fiction Congress and enjoy the corresponding online and
offline participation rights and I've got Wussfuss membership, physical admission, online admission
and about credit card payment. No hang on what this will let me buy how do I get to the one I've
actually got. Hmm purchase history? No look at World Con rights the thing saying World Con rights
tied to this email. Oh yes yes I see it yep I have the same ones that Liz has. Yeah cool cool yes
so I just need to go and do this process but it's probably not that exciting to do it live on the
podcast. You do have to click the big button that says register and then log into their payment page
to get there because you're basically logging into the account you have in their payment portal
which has their product associated with it so it's a little bit counterintuitive but it does
appear to be there and they said on their main website they'd send an email to people who voted
so if you haven't had the email yet presumably there will be one. I have the right to bid in
site selection in 2023 for the 2025 World Con and at the moment there is only one on the docket which
is Seattle so I will be going and pretending to be the Starbucks logo in front of the first Starbucks.
If before we go off the subject of Chandhu though we have to say guest of honor choice still shit.
Yeah yes I mean I'd say problematic but we're beyond problematic aren't we really.
We are we'll be on problematic here this isn't really a this is a mess.
Yeah and Chandhu as far as I can tell just completely silent.
Yeah. On most things since since Chai Khan really. When it reflects poorly on Chengdu
and it reflects poorly on maybe this is unfair but I think if I was a guest of honor on that ballot
I would be saying to Chengdu one of us goes and if it's not them it's me.
I'm so I'm a little bit surprised Robert J. Sawyer is still a Chengdu guest of honor if I'm honest.
It's quite a battle of this yes.
So so yeah I it's just horrible.
I do want to say we don't actually know to be fair we don't actually know whether the other guests
are trying to put pressure on behind the scenes which they may feel is and you know it may
be more effective putting pressure on them while still guests of honor just declaring they won't be a
guest of honor but there probably is a point that we are approaching.
That is a wise and fair commentless.
Can I do a little plug for Glasgow?
Yeah go on.
One of the things that this underlines for me is the importance of engaging with the community
issue as you build your convention and the Glasgow's got a community group on Facebook already
up and running. It has 800 members it has people posting about all sorts of things
that they're two years out they're already getting going with this and I think that's very
commendable.
No I mean Glasgow are doing a phenomenal job of talking to and involving the community
which is largely thanks to the work of the two promotions DH's who are Matt Calvert and
the amazing Meg MacDonald.
World fantasy con are going to be in Birmingham maybe.
I don't know I mean I can't tell I kind of looked on the internet to see at what point the
result is announced but I assume it's basically after they all get up later today and that's why
why we don't know yet but Farrah Mendelssohn and Karen Fishick are in New Orleans at the moment
enjoying New Orleans and also the World Fantasy Convention also bidding to bring it to the Birmingham
hit show. Wait it's Farrah bidding I think so I'm not at all sure Farrah is involved oh
because all I can see is it's kind of wish we can HWS events so picture of them yes doesn't say
that Farrah is bidding for UFC just says that Farrah is there next to the person bidding.
Ah yes and says so stop us and ask about it but doesn't explicitly say Farrah are you involved
in this bit and if you are Harrah and if not also Harrah you do you will we go to World
Fantasy in Birmingham have you ever been to a World Fantasy con before either of you I've never been.
Yeah I went to the one in Brighton I enjoyed my weekend in Brighton I had a nice enough time
but it is very much aimed at professionals and the vibe I got was very much this is a con for
professionals and anyone else who comes along that's nice but we're not really into you I also took
a day out in the middle to go to a wedding so I maybe did not do the full con experience.
I might go to World Fantasy Convention in Birmingham if enough of my pals are going which they might
be but I feel like it's not really a convention for me and my main interests. Yeah that's pretty much
it I went because it was in the UK it's very rarely in the UK I thought it would be fun to go
along and see and I found I got a very cheap early membership and a very cheap hotel room near
Boi in the hotel but the convention explicitly said probably shouldn't stay here because it's
really noisy and it was it was a travel lodge and so I had a perfectly nice time but I wouldn't say
it was such a great convention experience that I feel compelled to go back and it was also the one
where basically didn't really have a code of conduct and their like access was awful the
registration was in I think a room which you could only access via stairs and that kind of thing
so I liked it but nothing about it made me think yes I definitely want to go back but I think this
one is a it looks like a sort of completely different team who've been running UK fantasy
cons and so yeah running a World Fantasy cons sounds like a perfectly sensible step and I'm
sure it'd be very nice but it's probably not something that's going to like draw me back to the UK to
go to if I'm not here. To be fair for you the maths the maths on this works quite a lot differently to
us right because Toyland is a lot further from Birmingham yeah although 2025 is a long way away
The next thing on the show notes is Novocon excitement question mark
What I like about this is that Alison is the one keeping us on topic
Who wrote Novocon excitement question mark on the show note? Me because I didn't know if
anyone was excited is anyone excited? I have I mean I'm obviously excited for Novocon because
by then I will be back using a an app that tells me not to drink too much and so therefore I will
drink moderately throughout good how sensible hmm sance plausible doesn't it I am looking for
to Novocon which is um next weekend it's next weekend oh okay by the time this episode drops I
believe the fishlifters will already be in Buxton yeah we're not going up till the Friday but
we've kind of dithered back and forwards on whether we were going to go buy train our car but I think
we're actually going to go buy car because I think we're worried about train strikes and the fish
lifters are solving this by going the day early I believe the train strikes have been called off
but equally I believe Buxton is a pain in the arse to get to by train anyway um yeah but I much
prefer train to it's not really for conventions for me it's not so much the pain of getting there
it's how much stuff you have to take and then also how much you're going to need a car once
you're there and the answer in Buxton is not at all because that hotel is right by the station and
also right by everywhere else in a way that I really like so I am very much looking forward to
going back to Novocon and having fun and I think I'm trading there you've got a week to sort that
one out yeah I've got about four days I'm a bit worried that by taking holiday this week I've had
a lovely relaxing holiday by essentially putting all the things I had to do before Novocon out of my
mind completely for four five days and I'm not sure that was very healthy but you know it's been
it's been great I had a lovely time what I like about this is that by asking this innocent question
in the show notes I basically caused Alison existential dread so sorry Alison I've made a
note of it for talking to my therapist anyone else on anyone else excited about Novocon writing
people I am not going to Novocon I don't think Liz is going to Novocon either I am not but hello to
all our listeners who are listening doctor on their way to Novocon you can now I'm the very
quickly writer letter about how excited you are or tell us how it was yes indeed I did realize
what I was going to say about Novocon which is that um hello my column is doing the program and
wrote to me and said would you like to be on this item that looks pretty interesting and I was very
excited because nobody ever asked me to be on the program at Novocon so so that was thrilling and
it was a great show that I had to write back and say no because it's at 10 o'clock on Sunday morning
and I have booked a hangover for 10 o'clock on Sunday morning so I won't be at this item hang on
he said no one ever invites you to be on program at Novocon didn't you do recording of this very
podcast at Novocon last year. If I were to know that I wouldn't say we were invited I would say we
we we we forced our way into a room with an iPad and and made Esther buy us drinks we're awful
thank you Esther yeah any listener who likes to buy me a drink at Novocon is is very welcome
because I still have no money um yeah I'm a bit sad I'm not going but equally yep I'm sure everyone
who does go will have a great time and yeah please write in and tell us how good a time you had
it's nice to see Novocon is still going because I was worried they would sort of
get 50 and stop but they have not so it's nice that even though I very rarely actually get to go
that it does give everyone the opportunity to go and have a nice time hanging out in Buxton
actually but my this episode is all pre-show and no content I feel like we've gone through a
lot of important Spanish topics of the day and now we're going to do pics pics we've been so
on topic that to reward ourselves we're going to do pics so my pick is I have gone slightly retro
because at some point in the past when it was uh on sale I bought the complete books of Earthsea
and then decided it was time for a reread and in fact to get through I've got through
the first four and I don't think I ever actually read Tohani before and it's
it's really interesting rereading them they hold it very well but if you read them all in a row
you can also see kind of the development going through the characters especially in
Tohani being written much later on and as Le Guin mentions in the the forward to it
kind of a book she couldn't write until she was much further on in her personal development
tackling the kind of feminist issues that are in that one because there when you read it it just
put into context how sparse the female characters are in the first few books and how much
was missing from like the the point of view of any of the women in this world and then it's kind
of all there in the the fourth book I mean it's there in second book to some extent but around
magic and so on and the division between wizards and witches is all very interestingly explored
anyway they yeah hold up really nicely therefore short fun reads in a really nice world and I
enjoyed visiting it and I've got the the books of earthsea the the collected short fiction to go nice
I need to read earthsea I've got the first book on my iPad but I haven't it hasn't bubbled to the
top of my to read list yet but I know that there's a deficiency in my education that I need to address
yeah I mean there's obviously like there's always lots of discussion around like oh and people
recommend books that people should read and it's like stop recommending books from your youth
because they're not always great maybe we should not be recommending people things written in the
60s and 70s but actually I do think these hold up I'm not sure that you know the first things I
would recommend to someone yeah but I think they really they will reward you reading them no and I
think that's the thing right you've got a you've got a temper recommendations of you don't want to
recommend people not read any science fiction from the old days it's just about whether or not
it's about having a balance I think between the old and the new at earthsea is one of the ones I do
want to read from the old yeah and it's also considering that stuff you actually read
20 30 years ago may read very differently now but having you know read them at I mean I think I
read the first one probably 10 or 15 years ago and as I said I only got the last ones recently
you know there's something where I feel confident recommending them not something where it's like
oh well I read those 20 years ago but I bet they're still great and then if I went back and reread
them maybe they would not be from earthsea to the Northsea yes okay and it's a main
me go first just for that joke I did it's not that much of a joke I went up to Newcastle last
weekend which is where John lives so I got to see John which was nice and did you go to play with
John's lightsaber I he did not let anyone else play with his lightsaber I don't think or if he did
he certainly didn't let me play with his lightsaber I'm not sure I asked I would have been very worried
about dropping it or something did you let anyone else play with your lightsaber job yeah but I
can't remember who was it hug yeah anyway so I was actually staying with friends in quickly bay
which is nearer to Newcastle and I think I'd realize that is it's on the Metro so there is a
service into Newcastle every eight minutes I was very excited by that I was like where else in
Britain has a metropolitan railway and a beach and there's not that many places so I'm going oh oh
I need a city with a beach that would be good so if you live in a city with a beach let me know
and I went swimming with Meg and we had formed this plan this is Meg McDonald excellent
promotion joint division head for Glasgow and we had formed this plan it's her fault because
I was like I'm not going to go swimming when I'm there because it's going to be the end of October
and it will be absolutely perishing and she went I'll come swimming with you it'll be amazing and
then when I got there for our pre-planned arrangement John was also there and I was thought oh John is
also going to come swimming with us but in fact John was just there to point a law which he did
moral support and we got in the sea and on a scale of one to absolutely perishing it was about a 12
it's very very cold and then we swam and it kind of got gradually warmer that's the hypothermia
set in and we were having quite a last time I wasn't feeling all that cold at all and then I
looked at Meg and she looked really quite cold and I looked at John standing on the shore and he had
stopped pointing and laughing and was now shivering and looking very cold and I was like oh maybe it's
time to go out I was not a shivering and looking cold I was doing my duo lingo but so my pick is
swimming in the sea sea swimming is very good for your mental health apparently cold water immersion
and although the place that I'm staying at the moment which is the lake district is very nice it
does not have sea that does have lakes but it's the weather's been a bit crap this week for
for going in the going in the lakes though I will do next year that's my plan but I then all have
done more wild swimming while swimming is good for you I felt marvelous ever since I went for
that wild swim possibly because I've been on holiday almost all the time and all the rest of the time
I've just been telling people nope can't do it going on holiday have to prioritize sorry people
who I owe things to they'll happen eventually well I would like to say is the if Alison is going
to extol the virtues of sea swimming then we'll have no more mocking of me being at the beach
because I'm just going sea swimming for my mental health it doesn't work unless it's cold doesn't
work if your water's a chopper mental health requires painless pain and suffering sorry yeah
that would presumably be one of the quite nice things about Thailand does Thailand have any
cities that also have beaches yes yeah so maybe I should just move to Thailand done do you pick
I was torn on my pick but in the end I am going to pick moon night I would have picked moon
night previously but previously I picked moon night volume oh god I don't even know
a different moon night volume moon volume seven I'm picking volume nine this time which is uh
jib mckay working with Alessandro capuccio and Rochelle Rosenberg and it is very good I very much
liked how weird it is I haven't really a few like superhero stories recently I got bored with the
current run of Ironman it wasn't very interesting um so I stopped reading it but moon night has
kept my interest mainly because it is very very strange I just really like it and it's good
it's got vampires in and also actually another marvel thing I really liked was well for my night
which I watched on the day before Halloween and that was very good and very spooky and I very much
liked that too so I'm kind of enjoying the the horror angle of marvel at the moment it makes me
makes me happy either of you watched well of my night yet no it's horror right yeah and it's
and it's television right no the movie movie movie it is a director Disney plus film right
director Disney plus yep yeah it's like it's 65 minutes it's not a long movie done is volume nine
of moon night like is this like super recent like you're reading actual kind of moon night comics as
they are published or are you still kind of catching up on past issues well I'm reading our Marvel
Unlimited so like I'm not on the bleeding edge because that you can't do on Marvel Unlimited
but um but yeah no it is it launched in 2021 and it is still being published as far as I know
are you saying that Marvel Unlimited is strictly limited no because it has all the Marvel on it
but not up to date it's six months out of date I still think the Marvel Unlimited is a very good
deal if you're going to read a lot of Marvel comics and you don't mind that they're not
bang up to date I think it's great I just found I didn't read enough Marvel comics when I had it
because there's too much entertainment not enough time so moon night came from I think I'm right
and saying moon night came from the original world by night run so so they are connected characters
it does seem like Marvel is going much more into their kind of like mystic magic no not magic like
myth myth myth myth myth mythic in their into their mythic side with phase four and so I'm kind of
excited about that I think that's going to be cool and I'm looking forward to seeing how it all
pans out and for those who are very worried about such things well off by night on Disney Plus
requires literally no other Marvel to understand are you going to watch either are you going to watch
where off by night hmm sora probably not I'm just way behind a lot of stuff and it doesn't
super duper appeal to me so I might get to eventually fair enough so fair positive endorsement I
sound like the Mandalorian John so I a bit it's way better than I had the lorian it's only I
you saying it's only 65 minutes you don't need anything else and it's quite good yeah although
if you don't like horror I don't know how much you'll like it I like some horror that was the
odd thought podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me
right let's move on this is a very boring episode so far well that and that's the after show
sorted I'm glad we're getting all this out the way the theme music for this episode was
fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in competec.com used under a creative Collins attribution 4.0
license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]