Can I suggest that this is extremely tedious podcast content and we should move on?
You should clip that bit. Yeah, and just put it in a sound deck and then you can use it every single fortnight
Even though I have eaten apparently I can still be angry
Hello everyone and welcome to the very
127th episode of Octothorpe a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom
Which is coming to you on the 30th of January 2025. I'm John Coxon
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty and
We have some letters of comment
So we got a couple of comments on blue sky one from Abigail Nussbaum
Who also wrote the letter which we will get back to you later and Abigail reckons that she and John are not easily mistaken for another
So John any comment. I don't remember saying this so I'm deeply confused. I think I said it
It was a joke about how I'm confusing Abigail for me. You see
Your test audience of two says hmm
We also heard from Edmoreland as part of a blue sky thread in which they're talking about how it's nice to see a war
season
Going from like a very broad range of stuff and you know people slowly narrowing it down to the set of nominations
And yeah, I think that is a nice conversation. It's like to be in that conversation. I also
Love the process by which
Everything that happened last year and it starts to turn into well here are some frontrunners that we're thinking about in lots of different spaces
So people's frontrunners very quite a lot as well and Edmoreland also wrote what's on Facebook Liz a double threat
We should say that we said we were getting our hugo chat out of the way early because we want to have it all done before
nominations open but
nominations are not yet open so we're gonna carry on but obviously these are not my recommendations anyway
These are recommendations from our listeners who probably in many cases read quite a lot more than we have watched quite a lot more than we have so
All good recommendations. They're all good recommendations Brent Ed pulls out the West Passeritz by Jared Pesser check
Which I've also heard good things about but I believe is not out in the UK yet
So you'd have to get an input coffee and also private rights by Julia
Enfield which I meant to mention and was one of those things where I forgot to mention it last
episode
Rosanna Pendlebury also pointed out that that was a good one that we didn't mention and there's a bit of a discussion of that on Facebook
But basically I also really like that and just forgot about it. It's basically the story of three sisters and
their relationship with their father
After he dies, but the backdrop is all basically
England that is falling apart due to climate change slowly and it's really kind of all about sort of the the
psychological effects of living with a world that is slowly disintegrating around you
Oh, it's very interesting and I was it's quite different to anything else we mentioned last
Episode so if you like that sort of thing you probably gonna give that a go
It also mentions best game category really enjoyed tactical breach wizards which I saw trailer of and looks amazingly fun
But his window is only so yeah, no, I
Tactical breach ritzes is a game
I would have certainly put bought and played were it available on Mac and
When I spoke the last time about a lot of games being very trivial to play on Mac using whiskey
Which is a port of open source front-end to apples?
Open gaming thing that doesn't really apply to anything. That's got like graphics in it. It's great for you kind of little
Little games that are kind of retro as 80 games and things like that
But but games that actually have a lot of stuff probably won't work that way. Tell me if I'm wrong
I can't remember if I kept that bit in
This is the sort game that I would play the absolute shit out of if it was on switch
Hmm, it does it like a perfect a perfect thing that should be ported to switch assuming that the controls would not be completely
Impossible to to do I want to have it in my pocket
Well, I'm a switch doesn't fit my pockets, but you know, I know I could technically
Buy a PC use steam link to play it on my Apple TV with a controller
But like and I could get steamed egg
I don't really want a steamed egg
I mean a steamed egg seems more likely for that kind of thing
But basically I have succumbed to multiple consoles in the past year, so I'm not getting anymore
Not right now. We also heard as I mentioned from Rosanna Pendlebury who recommends the West Passage and private rights as well
But also 381 by Alia Whiteley
Metal from Heaven by August Clark and in universes by Emmet North and I have at least one of those sitting on my Kindle waiting to be read
So I might get through it in time, but probably not in time to give you opinions on it next week
So I have read some of these
381 I
thought was
quite poor, but I
also
Thought Skywood in by the same author was quite poor and it might just be that I don't gel with that author
Both books
I thought had very interesting ideas that I was keen to see where they went and then they went to the square root of nowhere
And I was a bit peeved that I had
Mmm, I I I would like more coherent books, which is a very me statement
however in universes is the next one on my list and I am absolutely fascinated by it and
I've heard really good things about private rights, which I am
Intrigued at some point to read. I don't know if you like it
But I think it's absolutely the sort of thing that feels like the clock should be thinking about because I don't think it's gonna get nominated
Anything else because it's a small
Second a second book by a like a small British author, but it's also the sort of thing. I think a lot of clutches might like
Anyway, can't be any of that and podcast me if I may be permitted on a tiny tangent, which I'm gonna cause it's my podcast too
There is some discussion in the comments between me and Rosanna about what constitutes like science fiction and what is kind of
Climate fiction and and so there is some discussion of that and what I'm thinking is also
Between reading that and the Ministry of Time quite quickly back to back where the Ministry of Time like climate change is just
It's a background thing that people talk about heat waves and extreme weather events like
If I write a book set two or three years from now where they happen to just be extreme weather events
Is that science fiction now or is that just sort of realistic?
Strapolation and what's the difference?
Right, exactly and if we were a serious science fiction podcast, we might discuss that but actually I think we're gonna go on
Just make more jokes. Someone else wants to do a letter
I want to do one very quickly which is that Fara said please put in a shout in nominations for the eight days of Diana
Win Jones, which is a podcast
about the first nine of Diana's books by Emily Tesh and Rebecca
Fremo and this had not crossed my radar at all and I'm like oh no, I'm gonna listen to this next week
So Fara says it's very good Diana's stuff's very good. So podcasts about it good Emily Tesh is very good
What's not to like haven't actually listened to it yet? I will let you know. I've also had good stuff about Rebecca Fremo's
Novel which let me just get the title up
So so thank you for that recommendation Fara. That's a great shout
Yes, Lady Eve Laskon is Rebecca Fremo's book which I have heard good things about it is basically
It says it is describing a good read as a suffix space sci-fi
It sounds kind of fun and it really doesn't narrow it down these days doesn't know but it sounds a bit like what I wanted
That Mary Robinette Cowell novel to be that was like
Murder mystery on a on a interstellar space cruise line
This sounds like what I wanted that to be except more lesbian. So yeah, I should probably pick that up
Then you can take one for the team fun light-hearted saffron mants. Hey, it's your 99
Yep, I will take that one for the team Johnny Badley says is Keanu Reeves eligible for the astounding award for best new writer
Yes, if you think he is the best new writer if you do not do not nominate him one of the six
What are the five best new writers? What you mean?
I'm not allowed to nominate him just because I think it's hilarious
I mean that I'm worried right because to an actual debut author
It could mean a lot to be nominated for the sounded
The sounding and I am a bit worried that Keanu Reeves name will be there for the memes and then I'm a bit worried
He might win. I really hope that we don't give Keanu Reeves the sounding award because sure he's lovely
But I'm not really sure that's for the good of the genre or so
I didn't like the book of elsewhere
I thought it was deeply misogynistic and unpleasant
So there is also that listeners has he actually written any
SF on his own or is it just in collaboration with China Mayville?
He's done some comics and stuff before I'd actually reasonably say he so it's okay for the to the wuss was
Constitution is it okay to be a lobulated for the astounding award if
If you've written your booking collaboration with a long established award-winning lovelist
It's genuinely good question. I think I think so this I can mention
Someone who is eligible for the astounding and I haven't read their book
So it's a bit cheeky
But Michael Green was great on a panel at Wilcom to the point where I put their book on my like, you know
List of books to be bought and read at some point
So I cannot vouch for the book
But if it's as good as they were in the panel, it'll be good. So give that a give that a go
There's probably people currently shouting at their radios. I'm assuming everyone listens on radio when we
broadcast on the FM saying John you fool
Don't you know that the astounding eligibility isn't in the Constitution and listeners I had forgotten so
I've stopped looking and someone can look it up and write in it's up to a standing is it I assume so also
It's still referred to as the John W Campbell award in at least one place in the Constitution
So that probably ought to be changed go
Where's the nit-spick nit picking of fly-spicking
Exactly right come on guys all right nitpicking I
Cannot find it in the most recent version. So are you definitely on the most recent version? I'm on the
One as of August 12 if I type Campbell it appears in section 3.0. It does final award ballots
She'll listen to the Google was the John W Campbell award for best new writer and the low star award best young adult book
So Glasgow was in contravention of the Constitution because they didn't call it the John W Campbell award on the ballot
This is why this is why going back to last time
I'm not too bothered when call when
Conventions ignore stupid parts of the wuss was called sution because if you rigidly obey the whole thing it doesn't make any sense
Then we also heard from
Ally Baker Brooks who says that she is gonna go through her reading for last year for load star recommendations
Thank you very much to Ali. We also heard on Facebook from Neil
Ottenstein who says I haven't even considered Wallace and Gromit even though it was magnificent
Since it is only 79 minutes long. I believe we'll go on to short form instead of long form and we also got a letter
We also heard from David in Salter who commends the French animated feature Mars Express to us as worthy of nomination for a
Hugo and
Thing is that both of these actually have run times under 90 minutes and so therefore they could go into best dramatic presentation
Short form however, it feels weird in spirit to do that because they both feel like films and so should go in long
form with other films and
There is precedent for this in that according to the wuss was constitution, which obviously I have open you know for
Checking at all times
It does say that you can basically move things between categories if they are within 20% of the
length boundary
So basically if it was like a duck and it quite like a duck and it is within 20% of the length of a duck
You can put it in the category of ducks and the present here is Wallace and Gromit curse of the were Abbott
Which was in best romantic presentation long form in 2006 although there are no details in the detailed notes to say
Whether it just says qualifies for both long form and short form voters placed it in the long form category
So I assume it was only nominated there
Interestingly that was the year when we had nominated Dr
To the empty child and the doctor dances to parta, which is says qualifies as both long form and short form and voters place it in the short form category
So I think that means we had a something in short form which was longer in runtime than something in long form
Which is very confusing anyway, why wasn't Gromit curse of the were Abbott did not win
Which is obviously a travesty even though there were other good stuff there
Yeah, but still in hindsight
Curse of where rabbit and ventures most foul is very good if you haven't had a chance to see it then
Do try and have a look at it before you nominate am I allowed to go and find my
Friends review of curse of the were Abbott, which is the best review ever
Yeah, it's also worth knowing so David asks in his email like when putting these things in the big Hugo spreadsheet of doom
Which tab do you put them in like cuz technically they're in one but you might think they should be in another
My impression is in general the administrators will move votes to the
Category that voters put the most votes in so if everyone nominates it in long form except for like three votes
Those votes will be moved, but if the reverse happens they'd be moved the other way
Like in general Hugo administrators try and respect the will of the voters
So if you think you know it depends what you want to encourage your fellow nominators to do
But if you think it quacks like a duck I would put it in the duck tab
Would be my recommendation that that would be my strong recommendation when nominating is is nominate ducks
In there, but each sort of poultry should go into its individual poultry category
So David mentions Mars Express original release in France in 2023, but North American release in 2024
which
Makes it eligible for the Hugo's in Seattle
But if you are a British listener of which I believe we have some it is coming to the UK in May 2025
So if it ends up on the ballot, it will hopefully be in cinemas just in time for you to make an informed decision
Yeah, I think I totally missed this. I'm not sure ever got a release here
David does say it's a cyberpunk noir detective story that feels a bit like if Mobius a directed Blade Runner
And that is ahead of a logline. So yeah, I am interested in the movie from
The email that you've sent David. So I will be keeping an eye out for it for sure
Yeah, no, I'm gonna watch this when it gets this UK cinema release in May apparently
So I will look out for it and go and see it at the flicks David did also write
Having said all that I will now express an opinion which will probably make you discount everything that's come before at the rambling of a man
Who has clearly no taste and is possibly out of his mind the substance is a no good awful bad highly overrated film
It's over long by more than a bit repetitive pretentious and insufferably didactic
And I should know as I've been accused of being all of those things at one point or another
It doesn't succeed as sf it doesn't succeed as horror and it doesn't succeed as social commentary
I'd say it also doesn't succeed as comedy only a did chuckle a couple of times
But they were half-hearted chuckles at best
It assumes its audience consists solely of simpletons who have no hope of understanding even both basic of thematical plot points
Unless we're bludgeoned over the head would said thematical plot points again and again and again
Until we put our collective hand up to bock the next blow whimpering we collectively get it now. Will you please stop?
Also today
I found out the surest path to mega stardom in 21st century Hollywood is hosting a Jane Fonda style workout show from the 80s
Who knew and then he and then he concludes the email by the way love the podcast except for the bits where you repeatedly praised the substance
Now I I did quite like the substance, but I did
I mean I can I can see this reading of the substance and yes, it was very well put and it made us trough at all
So thank you very much David
I I see where you're coming from but the thing that I think it succeeds that is satire
Which is not any of the things you mentioned but is something I really like in movies and do not get enough of
And I think it's quite a good satire and there we go
I do take the point about the fitness show though. Yeah, no, that's completely right
You're dead all there hadn't occurred to me at all and then you mentioned it and I oh yeah, that doesn't it's there for the body for the stuff about
Body obsession. It makes sense in the context of the movie and for the satire, but yes, no
It's it's a cheap target wait. What's the thing about the submarine arrays of the last arc?
Erwin Hirsch wrote in with a small clarification for us
He says hi octa thought casters that is already a naph. It's the national and Dora fan fun
And then he sent a quick clarification saying no Australia not and Dora and then sent a link
Thank you very much to Owen for it again
I was I was saying I was like I'm sure there's already a naph and I was like I can't think what it would be
But yes the national Australian fan fund which is another example of the national fan funds
We were talking about in reference to cuff so thank you very much for reminding me
Oh, when and a great choice for a national fan phone because as I know now Australia is quite big
You may think it's a long way down the shops to the chemist, but that's just peanuts to Australia listen that we also
Got a letter from Amigail Nussbaum who thanks us for mentioning her book track changes as being on our prospective
Hugo ballots because it very much is and concurring with our praise for Briar Dean books a
Micropress which produces books of long-form SF criticism
You may know them from I was mentioning their books many many times
Briar Dean books this week opened pre-orders for their next book which is color fields writing about writing about science fiction by Paul
Kincaid and I know there have been collections of Paul Kincaid critical works before but this is his collection of critical works
Writing about critical works about science fiction. So he's looking at different histories works and biographies and studies of the field of science fiction
Oh, this is inception, isn't it?
This is getting quite meta. Yes, because if we have enough of these books that are writing about writing about science fiction
We can have writing about writing about writing about science fiction, but it's got a really lovely cover
So it does who did the cover?
Tom joys
And I do very much like how all the Briar Dean books are you know
They have distinctive and original colors, but they all feel like they fit a theme
They're gonna look all very nice on my shelf and I'm not really a collecting books because they look nice on the shelf person
Abia also has an interesting thought about again the best romantic presentation short and long form categories
Which she says reflects a trend of treating those categories as respectively best TV show and best movie
Which does have the effect that sometimes for best short form?
It's not always the single best episode of something but becomes one which is more representative of the show people like as a whole
Which is interesting?
And she's come around to the practice of nominating whole seasons of TV in the long form category
And so she has some recommendations in the long form category
recommends the anime delicious in dungeon and
The only season of chaos the Netflix show a few watch down to those. No, I picked chaos. I think oh, yeah
It wasn't me. Yes. Well, yes neither of you have watched it's likely on the one who picked it
I thought it was very good. We were we were quite sad to hear it to be cancelled because we enjoyed the first series
I would definitely go to watch the second. Yeah, the other problem
It's had is that now I know it only has one series. I'm like oh, I'll get around to it at some point
Rather than being like these ask about the next one
Well, you'll you'll get round to it if it's nominated which it won't be it might be here
It was nominated. I might know watch all 13 of them before the things and it's 13
It's probably 10 or 8 or some weird number of the Netflix I
Feel like it's eight don't quote me Abigail also lists some short form TV episodes
She will be putting into short form which include Doctor Who's dot and bubble
Which I did really like actually and then four things I haven't watched namely Star Trek discos
Whistle speak their body detectives the case is a very long stairway future armour quids game and interview with the vampire
Don't be afraid just start the tape. Yeah, I haven't watched any of them
I'm so behind although to be fair I ground to a halt in Star Trek discovery part way through series four and stopped
I'm here also says ps please update your blue scare can with the latest episodes
So I can repost it and fair cop. I'm in charge of blue scare count
Which means quite often I don't post in your episode for several days if you want to be notified the instant the episode comes out
Please subscribe to our RSS feed. It is more reliable than my brain
Yeah, if you subscribe to it in your favorite podcast listening program, then it'll just turn up
It doesn't solve the problem of people very nicely wanting to me skaters, but it's also another problem
We heard from Louise Hughes who says I stayed in Wolf himself for long-con 3
it was a long way and the tube let me down several times and
Yeah, that that sounds like it would have been quite the commute
Yeah, the tube the tube doesn't actually go to excel. So normally it's DLR that lets you down especially in 2014
It's slightly better now
Raj also wrote in on master don
Basically saying he's going to Belfast because he's an Ulster man and he will support the first not an Irish East Comfer enough
And then he also mentioned he was surprised that we didn't mention Agatha all along which has been getting good reviews
And he liked it and that is true
It has been getting good reviews and Raj did like it
Have you seen it either of you seen it not yet, but it has been I have heard good buzz
So yeah, no people have told us told me it's great
So it's gonna be Disney plus so Liz doesn't have Disney plus the thing with Disney plus is it makes
Someone sent me to buy it a year at a time
So I buy it watch the free year and then leave it lapsed until something comes along that I absolutely have to
Resubscribe for and Agatha all along was not it and all season two will be it
Oh, yeah, that's fine. They're gonna make one. Are they making one? Yes. Yeah, excellent
And spending an enormous amount of money on it
We got a letter from Andrew Openshaw who says I
Love a 99 P Kindle recommendation. So thanks for the tainted cup
I also love 99 P Kindle recommendations, but want to point out that they are also
Generally, kobo recommendations or ebook recommendations in general. So there are other ebook stores apart from Amazon are available
He suggests from bat Hague who we discussed like like I've read the humans
Which is really funny and how to stop time plus the nonfiction books how to stay alive and notes on a nervous planet
I actually saw him speak at Newcastle library a few years ago
Where the two revealed that in the 90s he had a nervous breakdown in Newcastle's very own Eldon Square
Which was the experience that set it on the path to become a novelist
So this is kind of a warning to John really if you're ever anywhere near Eldon Square clearly a dangerous place
Chris Garcia wrote in and he tells us that Bella is very excited with their first fan art
And yes, well done Bella and then he writes mother things and he says that there should be a US Mexican
Fan Fund because there is good fandom in Mexico that US fandom rarely interacts with and yes
That would be great. That should definitely happened and it could it could be called
Muff the Mexico US fan fund and says that he has no 2024 reading to nominate
But he would nominate as long form Tim Travers and the time travelers paradox and Deadpool Wolverine
Thank you very much for bringing Chris
Claire Briarley writes in having listened to our
episode to a podcast for the first time in longer than she wants to admit and she writes
To my amazement I found that you're still referencing my old letters of comment and we to Bix
How did you know I was going to listen this time or are we in a time loop?
I'd like to say that we stopped in the middle and talked about other things
But that's not really true
I very much enjoyed Liz's comment on the new naming channel of Wilcom's wuss was membership as it now relates to attendance at the wuss was business meeting
Maybe they should form a committee to discuss that she also mentions the Australian naff and then she makes some recommendations
one of which yes, she enjoyed reading the Mars house by Natasha pulley and
She also mentions the novel. It's my pick for this episode
So I will talk about it then and she recommends short fiction
Why we why don't we just kill the kid in the Omeles hole by Isabelle J Kim and a catalog of 21st century ghosts by Pat Murphy
She also thinks Sandra Bond's poems are well worth nominating and yes, she recommends time flies
foolish foal and the planetary model or Rutherford was such a bore and between narnia and never where
From Sandra's book. She says she also has her we to bits still has her we to bits no globe, which is good to know
Yeah, I don't think we've talked about we to pick every episode
I like to think that we said we to bits and basically this like sets off some alert
Like it's like a you know quantum butterfly or something which leads to Claire listening to episode the we to bits symbol lights up over croydon
Hmm. She does say that naff might have gone the way of cuff and it may no longer be extant
Hard to tell with Australian funds. Yeah, I think that is
Potentially an issue with poetry is that it is for a poem
And if someone has published a long book full of poems, then there's a lot of potential there
So it might behoove you to uh
See if other people are putting things say on the big hugo spreadsheet so that you can coalesce around something
Otherwise, you're just going to have like 20 poems
None of which quite meets threshold. This is what this is why poems a bit of a daft hugo
But there we go not for podcast. I think it's all right. It's this there's a one-off one. All right. That was like as a client
Jesus Christ we've been recording for an hour and ten minutes
Well, we haven't quite but oh, I'm gonna say I've only got 56 minutes
So either time dilation is occurring between here and your castle. I looked at the zoom rather than my uh recording app
But yeah, um
So let's just go straight to pick and go to bed
We should I think first list discuss the Belfast Easticon Belfast have sent out an email
With the subject wants to be a program participant at reconnect
And so if you want to be a program participant at reconnect
You can visit a link in that email and then you can log in to plan z their program planning system
And fill in your bio indicate you'd like to be on the program and such other things
They say they're aiming to finalize their program in mid-February for release by the end of February
So get your skates on listeners go do that
Yeah, but I assume that is finished for people to say what they would like to be on not finished for putting out onto the internet
And there's always some panels that needs to make sure people
Indeed
Maybe you can sign up and indicate your interest on being on octa thought the podcast
I will do that. I'd love to see who else does that. I know it would be funny
I know they probably won't have it open for sign up, but it would be funny program person mega mc.dodle writes
Belfast is aiming to have three rooms streaming out with playback
If community takes up interest either in volunteering or by online memberships, then
They might try and go to five streams in but they're in the planning stage and looking at the art of the possible
So that is their current plan and they're currently looking for volunteers to be involved with the online side of things
So if you're interested in that do get in touch
with the Belfast Easticon
Email them and let them know that you might want to volunteer
It's exciting that there will be streaming. I hope that means there will also be replay, but I don't know
Well, I mean, I think if you've got three streams then it makes a lot more sense
For people to join virtually than if you just have the ones so you know
Get it out there that there will be quite a lot of program for you to engage with and I know that they're thinking about the social side as well
So the other thing is that if you're doing three streams then
I think probably going from zero to one is more work than going from three to four
So I'm glad that they're doing some because I think it will make it easier to scale up
And honestly like I don't know if I think
Because there are enough um program items at least con that probably don't need streaming
Um, but equally I am glad that they are doing some and I've been banging this drum
I would bang in this drum since sort of I don't know
2011 maybe but like I've wanted Easter cons to do more for supporting memberships and committing generally to do more for supporting members
For a long time. So I am glad that we're kind of keeping the momentum going on that and I'm glad to that belpha star
Taking that board. I think that's really really good. Um, so credit where credit is due. I reckon
We we recorded a lot of the program at folicon in 1988
And then
Somebody lost the real three real tapes
Like, you know, oh no
And you know, we'd spent quite a lot of money on the recordings. It's it's it's
It's just the process after a convention of actually getting all that sorted to a doubt to be too much for the people who had done it
So this this argument's been going on a long time belpha if you're planning to record things unreal to real tape
Well, that was no don't do that. Well, if you're gonna do it don't lose them
Hang on. Do you mean when you say don't do that?
Do you mean if your planning to do it?
Don't tell us or do you mean don't plan to do it?
Don't don't do it on real three or five. They're a better they're a better more appropriate recording media
for modern
Have you heard of a little thing I like to call mp4?
I am relatively sure that no one at uh belpha is
Even vaguely considering real to real tape, but I might be wrong
Anything else we want to say about belphaast. We're excited about belphaast. Oh, I'm really looking forward to belphaast
I've really enjoyed the previous two conventions. I've been to there and I'm very much expecting to enjoy this one a whole lot
And yes, if you're a listener and we don't already know you come and find us
We will almost certainly be in the bar for some or all of the weekend. Do we want to
Have do we not for pod necessarily but closer to the time?
Do we want to say we will be in the bar for this 90 minute period
And this will be the official time
That people can come and chat to us if they'd like to and the three of us can have a drink and whoever else could join
Would that be nice?
Kind of like a table talk except not organized by the convention just organized by us. Yeah
Yeah, let's do it. Yeah, that sounds good
So at belphaast what we are planning to do at some point in the convention is hang out in the bar as a trio and
sort of
Be officially available for listeners to talk to us even more so than the usual available
We are for listeners to talk to us which is very
the whole of the rest of the weekend felt
Without
Explicit consent, please do not talk to me when I'm in my hotel room
And please do not talk to me while I'm on the loo
But if I'm like in the bar
Do talk to me the show art should be the flow chart of how to tell if you can talk to john and allison and liz
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, no. Okay. Yes. That will be good and it could be utterly ridiculous
Though, I mean, I might not be the best person on the pod to do a flow chart
I'm just saying but I probably am really I'm really excited about belphaast
I'm really excited about koflu and belphaast and that whole two week period when
Anytime the time in order to convention of those two week periods and firm about a week either side
There are going to be people staying in my house which sauce pretty exciting. Hey
So that's gonna be good
[Music]
Pics should I go first if you like so so my pick is three men in orbit by sandra bond
I don't think any of us either of you two have picked it. Nope. Nope. I'm ready yet
Okay, so three men in orbit by sandra bond. This is as you might guess from the title a pastiche
of
three men and about by jerem kjorom in which the three men are living in a a universe where
Cavorite is fuel it has fueled a new space age
Cavoritis hg wells is anti-gravity guffin thing not my guff is not quite the right word
you know unexplained technology and
I have been
Chorkeling throughout because I think what's really good about it is that sandra manages to both
do a very good pastiche of jerem kjorom
Whilst also being funny in some of the ways that the original is funny and also some new ways
Whilst also sounding distinctly like sandra who I know but but you know so having her own
authorial voice as well and also bringing a lot of the kind of politics and the way people behave
if not up to date because it's still clearly a victorian steampunk well-sian
sort of a uh science fiction story but but sort of in a way that isn't going to
jar with people reading it now and I'm just really enjoying it it's so funny every page has things
that make me chorple because science fiction comedy is quite difficult right lots of people
write science fiction books that are intended to be funny and aren't so when I read one that's
intended to be funny and is I really like that and so I would recommend it to you all
it's available where ever good books are sold I don't think that's true I think it's available
from sandra or on auson or on e-pub by emailing sandra's publisher and asking for an e-pub copy
and it has a lovely cover by Dan Stefan which is hilarious and perfect and I'd recommend it
and you have to draw a veil over um if three people this incompetent went into space um they'd
all die horribly because space is really difficult but you know I think we it's not that sort of
book really they didn't drown in three men in the boat and they're not and they're not going to
be sucked into the vast horrors of space of this novel either that's fair shall I do
so I do my next all right I am going into one of my occasional forays into romance novels
and I am picking a book called nine rules to break when romancing a rake by sarah mcclean
this is going to be one of those books where I think if you like the idea you'll really like it
and if the idea makes you go then it is pretty much what you think it's going to be and you won't
like it so it's a historical romance the heroine is called lady calpernia heartwell
it's a good name um and she is uh spinster wolflower the type always goes to the balls but never
dances with anyone her younger sister has gone to the ball and made a love match and so now she's
kind of feeling all the stuff she's missed out on and essentially she makes a bunch of rules
of things that ladies should not do that she wants to break and inevitably she finds a dashingly
handsome yet reluctant to commit rake in order to break these rules with and that's pretty much
what it is it's fun it is pretty improbable in that all the rules to break are things which you
know would get you thrown out of polite society but she somehow managed to break them anyway and
has a lot of sex in places where you really would not get away with that I don't think and so kind
of the tension is not there like you're supposed to be like oh will be discovered but you're like no
you won't be discovered because then the ending of the book will be much more depressing but it's
still kind of fun and the characters are great I was totally sort of won over and I sped through
it in a kind of like oh I know what's gonna happen but I won't see them get together so yeah it is
fun one of my biggest complaints is it does this thing that kind of modern modern historical romance
books do where they do a series that are all kind of set in the same universe and so it sets up
during the book the siblings and cousins and so on of the hero and heroine who are going to be
the lead characters of the next book but it means you get plot threads that just never get resolved
because they're going to get resolved in the next book and then you're like okay yeah fine
you were setting up this concept for the next book that's nice why couldn't you do it in the next
book but other than that I did enjoy it doesn't sound like your thing does it John Arson no have
you have you read the Mars House by Natasha pulley because you might really like it but no I would
I'm accepting this in like a fun romance novel which I read in an evening in a way I probably
wouldn't in a book I was supposed to be thinking about seriously for such six awards I would never
I wouldn't give this an award other than being fun okay so so turn your brain off and then
read the Mars House because the romance bitters of it are great I quite like romance I just very
rarely actually get round to reading it much like crime fiction really like crime fiction but
relatively rarely actually managed to read any I read a ton of romance in my 20s before I logged
books on the internet and now I kind of go oh well you know I haven't seen every possible plotter
romance could have and I probably still will read some I can you know I read books that are not far
off in that in genre and I might read some hair because I haven't really read very much
or anything like that but maybe one or two a year and crime similarly lots of good crime novels
that I mostly don't get round to reading yeah I would say this is nowhere near like as kind of
witty as the best hair can be knows it have that social commentary to have a lot more sex so I
do quite enjoy sex that's start the episode isn't it I I remember I remember that that was good that
was a flagrant thirst trap for the listeners yeah I mean if you're going to say what you know romance
published in the last 10 years Elizabeth Red would you want to read I would not put this one at the
top of the pile it's probably like another 15 ahead of it but it's still fun oh what should I read if
I'm going to read a romance book published in the last 15 years what would be the very best one
oh well I think you should probably read some Courtney Milan it can have a lot of sex in it by
the way that is fine they have less sex in it I mean there's nothing wrong with it it's just that
like there's probably a bit too much of it that doesn't advance the plot and also like in
probable locations like in a gentleman's fencing club and so on I have just seen the covers of
this book oh yeah the cover is very classic like hello boobies I've been clicking my pen for five
minutes sorry John you're gonna have to ignore that uh I'm just glad that we've got the episode
title no we can't do that no no I am going to pick a movie I'm going to pick sliding doors which
is a movie from 1998 starring Gwyneth Paltrow and John Hannah so I'm like really finger on pulse here
peeps I thought it was going to be a romantic comedy and it isn't really it's more of a
explanation or a visualization of multiverse theory with a woman who misses a train in one
reality and catches the train in another and it sort of describes how her life diverges from that
point and it's very good Gwyneth Paltrow is very good in it I thought but John Hannah stole the
show for me I thought he was excellent and I think it is probably science fiction I thought it was
very well done I had not seen anything do what it did quite like it does it the ending is a little
bit melancholy and kind of I think explicitly genre in general I thought it was really very good
so I would recommend it to listeners I saw this movie in the cinemas in 1988 in 1998 so yeah
or maybe 1999 you know but that's all the time it's cat lips of Londoners because it it does two
things that Londoners love in movies it has lots of stuff that's kind of London being it's prettiest
and it also has ludicrous geography so that people can mushroom complain about it sometimes I'm very
glad I don't live in London yes I think it's a great movie and I'd say it was science fiction yeah
it's two parallel universes yeah I saw it but probably in about 2000 some things that I have no
memory of it hey I liked it that was good is it on the list of our top 100 science fiction movies of
all time because it probably ought to be no it is not we did also we did continue to go through that
but I don't think I've got any pics from it I think that might be it I feel a bit incoherent but so
listeners if you're feeling the lack of a deep topic that we might get into that we didn't get
into this episode right and tell us what it should be for another time yeah because we have just done
all the stuff around the edges of the deep top of the big topic of the week but haven't done a big
talk with week but we've been kind of plenty long enough so you know please do continue to write in
with your Hugo award recommendations if you haven't already done so or if you read anything that's
eligible between now and the end of nominations we would love to hear about them that would be
great that was the Octothorpe podcast and it's goodbye for me it's goodbye for me and it's goodbye
for me
what's Elden square do you want it's a square with a statue of Elden in it that's not as helpful as
it's I don't know what you want me I mean it's uh it's in Newcastle city center uh there's also a
shopping center named after it but I imagine he was actually in the square he might have been in the
shopping center don't know oh I like this it is bordered by a nando a wagamama a burger place
and a micro pub sometimes it has things in it like stalls of a market it's a short walk away from
monument metro station no I did assume he meant the shopping center um so you know maybe it was just
three yes so like shall I read from the wikipedia page of the shopping center um which says it
Elden square the shopping center now rebranded as uh what she was rebranded as into Elden square and
is now stylized as Elden square apparently was built on site of old Elden square a famous part of
georgia Newcastle this redevelopment which left only the eastern terra stunning has been criticized
with writer calling it the greatest single example of architectural vandalism in britain since the
war sounds splendid oh oh I think there are a few competitors for that has he been to south
ampton yeah I was gonna say the the Grafton centering Cambridge but I don't know what that was built
on top off old Elden square which was a public square no no no the Grafton center oh they demolished
um loads of victorian terra's housing to make it oh it was it was that it was an absolute outrage
oh uston station also yeah uston station is an abomination that is true anyway that was our
olden square corner sorry I didn't realize it was going to spin off like that neither did I or I
would never have gone there listeners right in with your favorite architectural disasters of the
UK hey I have a I have an anecdote about Patrick Nielsen Hayden and UK architecture which you know
he'd be going around beautiful bits of British of British cities and see hideous brutalist buildings
and people would explain oh oh the war you know it's an area that was bombed and he hadn't realized
that the buffer had been in the business of dropping concrete monstrosities all over the country
if you go to the european cities that were bombed you just you do not discover hideous
brutalist buildings in them as a rule but they're kind of knocking down the hideous ones and so
only the good brutalist buildings will be left at some point and then people will go oh I don't know
why everyone was so down on brutalism shall we move on from architecture corner it's not a statue
of lord elton it's a war memorial so that was our factually incorrect architecture corner it's
what you're telling me yeah but apparently it's st george okay who just happens to look a bit like
lord elton i've never really looked at me and didn't really know what lord elton looked like it just
sort of made sense to me that there's a statue in a square named after a bloke probably a statue
of the bloke but no the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud
in compactec.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the
beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]