who would like to do one. You can do one, John.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 86th episode of Octa Thorpe, a podcast for science fiction
and science fiction fandom. This episode is coming to you on the 22nd of June 2023. I'm John Coxin.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty and we have some letters of comments. Abigail Nussbaum wrote
and said that we did a very good job of timing our podcast exactly to fit in with her commute,
so you know glad to be of service. Please write in with the length of your evening
commutes and we'll see what we can do. And she said a great discussion of a face-like glass
and I'm not just saying that because I agreed with all your points. We're very pleased to have made
points that Abigail agreed with because she's one of them clever people who knows a lot of stuff,
so that was lovely. Abigail's like you. She has also given her official Francis Harding ranking
for our future selection or anyone's future selection and that list I'm going to run
through it very quickly is Fly by Night and Twilight Robbery at the top and then Verde
at some point. That's my plan. Thank you very much Abigail. I'm not sure this list is actually in order,
but Abigail writing and tell us if we completely misrepresented it. Oh no, it's not in order.
My dust donsers. I just totally misread it. It's got more nuance than that. Abigail would never
just send us a list in order. It's a nuanced ranking of which ones we should pick to read next.
Like I went and bought a book face on a seat also. It succeeded. Okay, that was completely rubbish.
So actually, Gullstruck Island was her favourite, which is called the Lost Conspiracy of the US
and she says, "hands down my favourite Harding." So that's the one she recommends to anyone who
asks if you were asking. They're just going to take my brownies readers badge away because I clearly
cannot read and comprehend simple English text. We also heard from Christopher J Garcia who pointed
out that they didn't do a Hugo recommendations issue of the drink tank. And I discovered this
while trying to look it up for the show notes and finding that there was not one. And so I
would have mentioned it if you hadn't Chris. What's happened? Look right, I expect a certain level
of service and frankly, hmm, you're never going to win another Hugo with this attitude.
And then, other things. He says he doesn't get many DMs on Insta but he does have a lot of
friends who are porn stars. So, you know, that's data that is. That's good to know. Thanks Chris.
Chris is also fairly certain there's going to be a whole bunch of Chinese stuff on the Hugo
ballot. So agreeing with me there. Foreshadowing. Is it foreshadowing or a segue?
Oh, it could be a segue. A segue. Yes. So, Chengdu posted to their socials to make an announcement
about Hugo Awards. I will read out verbatim. Sorry folks, but due to the amount and complexity
of this year's nominations, we have received the committee still needs some time to work out
the official nomination list. Be assured that we are working very hard to reach the completion line,
maybe one more week to go. And that was posted two days ago. So by the time you listen to this,
it may indeed be out, but we did say that last week as well. So, yes. Also, it should be official
finalist list. And frankly, I think it's appalling that no one from the Waspous Division caught that
before that message was posted. Shame. Shame. But more seriously, I think we all three of us agree
that that message makes us think there's probably going to be some Chinese nominees on the ballot
or at the very least, some Chinese nominees on the long list. I mean, because I guess it's
theoretically possible that they could control the numbers. And then it turns out none of the
Chinese nominees get on the ballot, but it seems unlikely. Yes. So yeah, I assume from that it means
things are complex for one or both of two reasons. One is that the ballots have come in with lots
of stuff on there being represented in multiple ways, which we know is a problem, right? Because
people can write, you know, things with hyphens, things with quote marks, things in funny orders,
like you always have to go through and kind of tidy up the data to make sure you've got the
nominations correct. But then if you're trying to do that, tidying up across two different languages,
that is going to be even more a problem. The other thing I know is that they are using different
software, I think, than previous years, which may be because this software better supports
multilingual nominations. But it may be that kind of things are slightly less smooth because they
are using different software and you've got different teething problems. I'm fine with it. You
know, there's still plenty of time before the actual convention. And they've said, okay, yeah,
it's taking us a little bit longer. Give us a bit of time. Fair enough. Yep. Means I might be right,
though. So obviously good with me. It does mean that. It does. I think that's quite likely.
Better get learning Chinese. Read all the finalists. Like, because, you know, if they're all in Chinese,
how will I meet the Briarly Competence threshold if, if I don't know any Chinese? I do. I will know
in a discussion of this noted critic Nick Clark. She said she thinks she has only once in her
entire history of voting in the hue goes red or watched everything shortlisted in a given category
anyway. So that is a counterpoint to the Briarly Competence threshold, which I enthusiastically endorse.
What in any category? Yes. I think that is a much better use of one's time than trying to read
everything out of a sense of nobility or obligation. Read stuff you like and then do what you want.
I think it's quite nice to do everything in a category. It gives you a kind of feeling of,
I don't know, smug superiority and internet chat. All that topic. I mean, I will say,
I don't think I have ever read, for example, all the nominees in Best Series in a given year.
I have managed Best Novel and I think I've managed the entirety of short fiction ballots and so on.
But yeah, definitely categories I haven't read everything in. I've done all of Best Series before.
I mean, I do tend to read all of the categories I vote in, but I just think you shouldn't. It's not
a stick to beat yourself with or it shouldn't be. It should be a positive, lovely experience,
not a stressful, awful one. Much like life. I can say that I never find you
go voting to be particularly stressful and awful, even if I haven't read anything, read everything
even. To be fair, Liz, you find nothing stressful or awful on account of how you are basically one
of the most laid-back people in the universe. I would describe you as horizontal, especially
because you're knitting in bed right now. I always relax. I just like have a very go with the flow
attitude, which not always the best way to do things, but does lead to a maybe less stressful
life than otherwise. Also, I recommend crochet. Oh, sorry. Liz is crocheting in bed right now.
I always get those mixed up. I can't actually knit so uh. Yeah, I actually,
I actually sell a t-shirt that was suggested to me by Kylie Ding and Robin Stevenson that says
vule vu crochet a vet. That's quite good. We also, so Hugo Administrator Dave McCarty posted to
their Facebook about the venue for Chengdu and and yeah, they've gone from a field to a conference
centre in a year. And you know, I don't know how many people got concussed or severely injured doing
that or or what the human toll was, but it is very impressive. Oh, I don't, you probably don't want
to know the health and safety figures, but if you did, you probably couldn't find them. That's
the thing, right? It's tricky because I see this and all of that is very impressive, but we know how
countries like this do these things this quickly and it's by not giving a crap about the people
who are doing the work. Shall we move on to the much less controversial topic of COVID?
The Smoth News newsletter written by Patreia Mitchell basically is generally a massive list of
conventions with a little bit of commentary at the top and it comes out about once every week.
I think, um, but I just read it for the bit at the top. There is a new guidance from the CDC
in conjunction with the American Society of Heating Refrigerating and Air Conditioning Engineers
or ASHRAE and they have picked a number to aim for in terms of COVID circulation of five air
changes per hour, which is absolutely like, I like this because it's a number that you could be like,
yeah, we can benchmark against the number now and that's nice and it means we can stop talking about,
well, I mean, maybe not immediately, but this is the first step on the way to sort of having
arguments about what the phrase well ventilated means and starting to get towards a more,
um, quantitative discussion of these things, which I think would be quite good. I thought it was
interesting and that I thought I would mention it on the podcast. Yeah, so it's very interesting
because when I've been looking at like air purifiers and things, because I own a home air purifier,
they generally have this value, it calls CADR rating, which is the clean air delivery rate.
So basically it's like kind of the, and it comes in, in for mine, it comes in like meters cubed per
hour. So basically if a thing tells me this clean is like 200 meters cubed per hour, then you can
work out the size of your room and from that workout, like whether this purifier is enough to give you
five complete air changes per hour or whatever. So yeah, it's quite, I think it's quite a good
standard. You have to then work out the size of your room and work out the efficiency of your
purifier, but then you can basically have one of appropriate size in appropriate space,
in appropriate size spaces, which is quite handy. Right, it's just being like, I'm going to buy a
big air purifier and put it in the corner of this room and assume it's all fine. I just like, as a
physicist, what I want is numbers. And so any numbers I view as good, good numbers. So I have
some numbers, um, because I've just been googling furiously. Um, as always, when somebody says,
here's what America is doing, I go, oh, there are other places in the world. So I checked to see if
the Health and Safety Executive has, um, advice on ventilation, which it does. And its advice on
ventilation is, um, five to eight liters of clean air supply per occupant of the space per second.
So you can probably turn that into air changes an hour. Um, I would have thought that was rather
less than, um, five air changes an hour in most workplaces, but I don't know.
Is that, is the Health and Safety Executive? Have you got a link? Could I haven't read that?
I've put a link to its ventilation pages. It's COVID pages when it talks about ventilation in,
in respect of COVID, um, points to the general ventilation pages. It says that ventilation is
just the same as COVID as for everything, all the other reasons why ventilation is important in
workplaces. I think the CDC ones are better because they explicitly say, you know,
they explicitly include, and this is what we are recommending based on COVID being an important
thing, as well as all the other things for clean air changes, things like HEPA filters,
you know, the, the rating of your HEPA filters, uh, you know, and so on. And also suggesting things
like UV inactivation, you know, which is a, not a thing for all, you know, there's reasons for having
air ventilation. Like the reason I know about like clean air delivery changes and so on is because
my air purifier was bought for pollution, where you don't bother with like the germicidal standards.
So I think it is worth, you know, making sure that they have taken COVID specifically into account
and not just gone, you know, for what they had before.
But they have done, but because it's a, this is in fact an outlet of the British government,
I'm sure that John is right when he says it reflects government guidelines. Yeah, I like the CDC one
better. As I said, five to eight liters a second. And the point about that one that's good is that
it's per occupant, whereas the CDC one is per room. And I'll tell you that really puts the
heebie-jeebies in me because the room with no people in it will not develop, you know,
how much you pack the room does matter a lot here. And they, and that, and that recommendation
takes no account of it. Our cinemas were saying when they reopened cinemas, they said they were
changing the air every seven minutes, which is like, I guess, eight times an hour. So it's a bit
more than that, but not a lot. But I do think that the number of people in the room is highly
relevant to this. So I don't, I don't, I'm not just sort of instantly believing the CDC's
recommendation here, any more than anything else. I think there are, like everything here,
there's room for a range of views. It's worth, it's worth noting that the CDC makes it clear that
five air changes an hour is the minimum. And they do note that it's not clear how that scales up for
like extremely large numbers of people. I'm just deeply suspicious of what I don't want,
because like, unless there's evidence that the health and safety executive has updated that
ventilation advice from 2019, I, what I'm interested in is how the science has developed in light of
the fact that we've had a pandemic. And I don't have much interest in pre pandemic opinions on this,
because they don't seem particularly relevant. And so like, if the British government, I mean,
I agree, like, you know, and I'm very sorry that I posted an American thing without
checking whether or not there was a British equivalent. But at the same time, if the British
equivalent is we had guidance on this before and here it is, then I think that's a sign that
they're lagging. So I agree with you. And I think you were right. And that the UK are just using the
same old guidelines and the CDC have actually thought about it and based it on Atlantic Commission
recommendation. So it has a key table, which we're going to link to, which is table one. And what
it basically says is that the it counts by two different mechanisms, which are per volume
volumetric flow for air changes, where it says, good is for better is six and best is better than
six. So the CDC's recommendation of five is kind of firmly there as between good and better. And it
also has a volumetric flow per person, which it recommends. And that is the good is 10 liters per
second per person, which your notice is significantly more than the HSE recommendations. So in conclusion,
what that means is that the health and safety executive has not yet updated its guidelines to
take account of the Lancet Committee. So if you're listening to this HSE, get your figure out.
And thank you for listening. We're thrilled that we have so many people in the civil service as
fans. And all the subject of 2025, Seattle is the only worldcom that has submitted any filing
paperwork. Oh wait, is that when was the deadline? Was it deadline? Did I miss the deadline?
Deadline for site selection. Shit, were you gonna biddlers? I mean, obviously, I wasn't personally
gonna bid, but normally I am on top of all things with this constitution. And I've been slacking
to be fair, but on holiday. I think the deadline must have been a couple of weeks ago. Yeah. Yeah,
because they moved it when they moved the dates, because that's a moveable fee spit.
According to the constitution, bid documents for opposing bids must be filed no later than 180
days beforehand. And no other bids have been filed to Seattle will be the only bid on the ballot.
So so yeah, well done Seattle. I mean, so I like Seattle for two reasons. Firstly, crack in logo.
And secondly, Seattle is a pretty great city. So yeah, I am if it is successful, which I
should expect it will be, but touch would, then then I might go. So I like Seattle, haven't been
for a while. I've never been Seattle. So I like that idea. Oh, it's lovely Liz. Oh, no, we,
Stephen was like Seattle. So I think I think the chances will be at the 25 worldcon and not
nil. It seems nice that it's gone to a bunch of big American cities. Maybe helps grow world
kind of it. If you go to like DC and Chicago and Seattle. Yes. I mean, as well as, you know,
London and Dublin and Helsinki and Chengdu and so on. You mean as opposed to like Reno and Spokane?
Well, Spokane in particular. And I believe this is filed for Seattle. So and I understand, I don't
want to say too much because I'm not like, I don't know these people hugely well, but I believe it
is a completely different con running team that essentially Seattle has two bunches of smoths.
And it's the, you know, Westcon people doing this one. And by and large, Spokane was not.
Though, of course, Wilcons are huge. Lots of people work on them. Everyone works, you know,
most people do some jobs on all of the world cons, but but in terms of who the board are.
No, yeah, yeah, no, that's a good point. I just wondered whether Liz was being sarcastic, like,
wonder whether Liz was being like, well, it's very good that American cities are having a turn
because they're, you know, we need to grow the world, come by getting more Americans into the
Phantom. I realized that's not quite what she was getting at, but I did. I was like, I just wondered
if it was the most straight faced sarcasm Liz has ever delivered on the pod. No, it was sincere.
Like, if it's only going to go to the US, you know, four years out of 10, which is what it has been
for the past decade, then it's nice to have it in big cities where more people can reach them,
basically. I don't know, maybe I'm underestimating the ability of Americans to drive there.
And different big cities. I think it would be quite nice if it went to Los Angeles sometime
quite soon. Or, yeah. I believe there is a Los Angeles bid in the near future. And I have not
prepared to answer this question. But I believe that there is a bid for like, 2029 maybe?
2026, according to Skiffy. That is that sooner than I thought, fair enough. I mean, because I think
if you were going to pick three places to have world cons, you'd pick LA or San Jose, like, well,
you'd pick LA or San Francisco, but sorry, San Jose fans in the absence of being able to do it in
San Francisco, San Jose will do. Or you and then you'd pick Seattle and then you'd pick
like Washington, North Chicago, right? Because they're like the corners and you wouldn't pick Orlando
for reasons. I mean, many reasons, but it is, you know, humid swamp stars. That wasn't that
wasn't the reason I was thinking of, but that is definitely a reason. And let's not go into.
I believe it's an air conditioned humid swamp. Yes. Yes. That is true. I mean, yes, but if I say,
you know, I got on a plane in Bangkok and got off it in Orlando and went, fuck me, this is warm and humid.
That's definitely staying in the podcast, Liz. I mean, yes, obviously, no, no, I do not want
to go to a convention in Florida, in under the current political situation in Florida, which is,
you know, unsafe for many people who would like to go there. But also, I understand other people
do not enjoy Disney World as much as me or human swamps. On the subject of conventions in North
America, should we talk about Permicon? What did we have to say about Permicon? They've announced
their virtual. Yeah. So Permicon, which is the 2023 North American starts fiction convention,
which I have a sort of peculiar affinity for because their symbol is a moose. And as you know, I once
ran an Easter con where our symbol was a moose. Now, as Permicon is in Winnipeg, a place that has
quite a lot of moose. And as a population was in Docklands, which is a place that is not known for
having moose at all, they probably have a slightly better claim to having a moose as their logo.
But anyway, Permicon has announced its virtual rates, if you're in the UK, which is $90 Canadian,
which sounds like a lot for a virtual convention until you realize that the Canadian dollar isn't
really as much as you think it is. But it's a tick that comes out about 60 quid. And they're
planning to have quite a lot of virtual programming. I was very excited by this because I saw their
thing that said, if you voted in site selection, you will have a supporting membership. And of course,
I voted in site selection, but I voted in World Conside selection. I did not vote in
that's fixed selection. If you voted in that's fixed selection, you will have a supporting membership
for the last week. And if you didn't, but you got drunk at Chacon and bought a $65 moose t-shirt
by mistake, it turns out that also gives you a supporting membership, which you can then upgrade
to virtual for, I think, $50 Canadian. And I'm thinking about doing that, even though, obviously,
a lot of it happens in the middle of the night, UK time, because it's in Winnipeg, which six hours
behind. And it's going to be a really good size of convention. They've got 725 attending so far. So,
and I guess it's mid August. So I think it's going to be kind of like a really cool size for
a national convention and way less big than World Cons. So as I like Eastern Consize
conventions, it'll be a bit better than that. Yeah, no, that's awesome. I think that's good.
On, yeah, another Worldcon note this week. Glasgow in 2024 now have the forms up to volunteer to be
on programme or to suggest a programme item to happen. That does go into 2024. And they are
separate forms. And to be on the programme, you will have to, I think, fill in that form, you have
to create a login for the programme system planarama. So we'll link to the page that explains how you
can do this. But that is the best way to suggesting you would like to see at Glasgow, like live
podcasts hint hint. I think we should probably put in a bid for OctaThought Live. What do you think
guys? Yes. Provided we don't have any ding dong arguments that caused us to stop doing the
podcast before then. But you could always have a stunt, a stunt all three of us if necessary.
Honestly, we could be on the programme or I could just be roaming the halls doing guerrilla podcasting
inviting people to eat weird flavours of crisps. Or both.
Do both, yes. No, that's good. I think I would like to do that. If there's anyone who particularly
thinks it would be a bad idea, do write in. I think I think I probably am not supposed to say
this as an official. I'm not supposed to say this as kind of an official pronouncement by Glasgow,
but Esther did say she was hoping to have kind of a room that was going to be set up specifically
with podcasts in mind that was kind of had all the tech that was that was needed to kind of split
our streams for OctaThought and things like that. Because I think they're going to have a few.
I don't think we'll be the only podcast wanting a split off to the work on programme.
Yeah, there may be other superior podcasts that want us to like Hugo Girl. Yes. I mean,
with my Glasgow programme admin helping out on, definitely don't give us a slot because we're
awkward f*ckers. We are pain to wrangle. No, it's a lie. We'll be lovely.
And also, if you do give us a slot, you better have a facility for people who've caught
Covid over the course of the weekend at a pocket. Because you know what I'm like, guys.
The clock award shortlist has been announced. Actually, the entire clock award long list was
announced. And just when I'd finished looking at it and was thinking, oh, maybe I should try and
predict what the shortlist is going to be, they announced shortlist. So that took the window at
myself. It was quite a fast turnaround, wouldn't it? It was very fast. So I didn't get a chance to
kind of pontificate too long. But yes, the shortlist is Venomous Lumpsucker by Ned Bowman,
the red scholar's wake by Alliett DeBodard, Pluto Shine by Lucy Kissick, the anomaly by
Herb Latellier, translated by Adrian Hunter, Coral Bones by E.J. Swift and Metronome by Tom Watson.
Indeed. So it's the usual interesting list. I think they're all new nominees. It's got,
you know, something's published as mainstream. It's got a translated novel on there. It's got
something published by genre publishers. Sounds good, basically. Yes. In the show notes, Liz notes
that she has read one of them. I have. Going to be the Alliett DeBodard. Correct. I have read
the Alliett DeBodard. I have also read one of them. Is it the Coral Bones? No. Is it the Alliett
DeBodard? No. Oh no, it's the anomaly. You said so on Discord this week. I did. The anomaly by
Herb Latellier, translated by Adrian Hunter. So how did you find red scholars wake Liz? I liked it,
but I'm not sure I would have put it on my list of the best of the year. Fair. I think it's got some
really great stuff in there, but it does not really hang together as a novel for me. I mean,
I don't know if we wish to discuss the clock shortlist in more detail, but I would say the
Red Scholars Wake is essentially, it's a space opera about kind of space piracy, but also a lesbian
romance novel between a human and a ship. And I think that's got some really interesting stuff,
but it didn't quite work for me as a romance novel or as a science fiction novel. Well, I like
bits of it. Yeah, kind of it didn't. It didn't go maybe fine off into either one, if that makes
sense. I would say it's still worth reading, so I think it's something that's going to disappoint
anyone who reads it on the Clark list. I'd give it three stars. Okay, fair enough. On the other hand,
a lot of books I've read because they're on the Clark shortlist, and I would give them one star.
So fewer than three stars. Dies Fair. Last year, I had at least one absolute shocker
on it, so there was that. I enjoyed the anomaly. Didn't think it quite stuck the landing, but I did
enjoy the conceit. So yeah, it was also a quite quick read. Was last year the one where one of
the novels was a homage to a novel that you hadn't read that's very famous, but that you hadn't read,
and so therefore you probably didn't get what the author was trying to do at all. That was,
I don't think that was in the "pfft, where am I been?" Jamaica in, so Skywarden or something?
Yeah. So I think there's an issue where you've got something that's trying to resonate with
something that's quite famous, not everyone's going to have read that. Sometimes novels just
of that kind just do not stand alone. I mean, I haven't read it, so I don't know if it's any good
or not, but that might be the reason you didn't like it. I didn't like it because the only
interesting SF-Nolbit was the final chapter, and that would have worked very well as a short story.
I think the thing I'd be very interested in is the transcript of the judges' meetings for the
Arthur C. Clark Award, because I'm sure they're phenomenally interesting. Yes, possibly.
But I mean, I love the process, because what happens is that we end up with these very interesting
shortlist. Oh, but it wasn't the worst book on the ballot last year. The worst book was bloody awful.
No, so like last year's Clark list had two that I really detested, like really, really hated,
and I am curious to know whether this year will be similar, but we will see.
What's the other one you hate, John? A River Called Time by Caution Newland.
I hated it more after I read the afterword. So this year, when they announced the shortlist,
I did not immediately spread this news to my friends. I immediately went to my library's website,
where I managed to download two of them straight away and have another three.
I think one's downloaded as an actual thing, and then a second one that's coming to me by on paper,
and then three of the rest are on my hold list. So I think there's only one that isn't in the
London Library's consortium system. That's a lot better than normal, so I was quite excited by that.
So hopefully I will have read them before the announcement this time. I think I am more likely
to read the Clark Award shortlist this year. If it turns out that the Hugo novel shortlist
is entirely an untranslated Chinese, a language which I cannot read or speak.
Yes, I think that is fair. Entirely reasonable. So yeah, I will look forward to reading them,
and etc.
Alison, talk about your golf trip. Oh yeah, can I get which one about my
golf trip? Right, I'm going to fly out, probably with Stephen as well, on the 26th of September,
it looks like, and I'm going to go straight to Canberra, where I'm going to have a day to kind of
collect my thoughts, because it's a very different time of the day, and then attend Conflux, which is
the Australian NatCon, as well as being the sort of science fiction convention that says it's for
writers, I think writers and artists, let me see what it says. Basically, it actually says it's not
a convention for fans, it's too unusual, but there we go, it is also the Australian NatCon,
so I think it's going to get some fans whether it wants them or not, at least one.
So fans are coming, whether you want them or not. Fan anyway.
I like that. It is, yeah, it's an odd attack.
So I'm going to attend the National Convention, which is in Canberra, and then immediately after that,
it looks like I'm going to go to Melbourne for about a week, and then go to Adelaide, and then
have a couple of days in Sydney with Stephen not doing con things, just kind of celebrating our
25th wedding anniversary, which will be nice. It's actually going to happen, the 25th wedding
anniversary, after Stephen's flown back to the UK. But you know, what does the exact date that
really? And then probably hang around with fans in Sydney, if there are any I can find, and then
go to Perth, well, I'm going to New Zealand, and I might squeeze in a few days in Perth, or we
might decide that it's all too much, and I'll just go to New Zealand and do quite a lot of different
things in New Zealand. It depends how the flights work. But that's the plan. So if you are in any
of those places, and you listen to the podcast, and you would like to put me up or put me in
Stephen up, or take me to do exciting things in Australia, like I quite like to see a cricket game,
for example, let me know. That'd be good. Thank you very much. Gonna be fun.
A variety of guff related merchandise will be available soon. That is very exciting. I hope you
have a great guff trip. I'm trying to think of ways we can invite the listeners to troll Alison on
her guff trip, but nothing has sprung to mine yet. So you're okay. Oh, I was wondering if I should
say to conflicts, do you want to do an episode of Dr Thought Life? No, I know you're going to have
two stunt people. Do you not want to be a go-no because you won't be members? Okay, fine.
How much is the virtual? Won't be member and will be in bed. Will you be in bed?
Why am I not being bad? John probably will. I mean, she's currently a bed Alison, so it seems likely.
Shall we do pics? Who would like to pick first? Do you want me to pick first? Yes.
So I have had a little holiday, and while I was on holiday I did some reading. That's not like you.
You're saying the piss about how much I go to the beach, John? No, I would never. I think I'd
probably go to the beach a lot as well if I were living near to some of the world's best beaches,
rather than living near to South End and also Clackton. Don't make me send you pictures of
absolutely beautiful beaches that you're not at. Ah, send me lots of pictures of beautiful beaches.
Love them. So while I was on holiday I caught up on, I think the latest two full novels in the
Rivers of London series. So when I was on who hasn't read Rivers of London, it is Ben Aranovich's
series of novels about Peter Grant, a Met Police officer who basically works in the branch of the
Met that deals with all things weird and supernatural. It's quite a long-running series now. There's a
bunch of novels, some novellas, some graphic novels that I haven't read at all. Yeah, and I kind of
caught up with the latest two and remembered really why I enjoy reading these. So I actually found the
seventh book in the series. The seventh novel kind of ties up or partly ties up some plot strands
right back from the first book, and I found it a bit satisfying, so I sort of took a big break,
and then the eighth and the ninth are more standalone mysteries, and they're just fun. They're just like
well, well put together, well paced, interesting mystery novels. Peter Grant, the main character,
is really fun to kind of watch him go from new Met Police officer to the person who is now
starting to be the magical expert and mentoring his other colleagues at the stage. These books are
apt. He's also about to become a father for the first time with his girlfriend who is also a river.
Yeah, and I think the one weak point is I don't think they ever end quite as well as I would like
them to. The mysteries kind of always get tied up a bit too quickly or leave a little bit too much
hanging for future novels, but I just really enjoy kind of racing through these two and will
probably pick up the next one whenever it's published. And if I had thought of this and read them earlier,
they probably would have been a Hugo Best Series pick, but I didn't think about it in time.
I thought it was one of the things that came up when we were talking about possible picks for
Best Series in fact. Could have been. But I think I would say, I think next year when the
Worldcon is in the United Kingdom might be a good time to try and encourage all the British fans to
vote there or the good British series onto the Hugo ballot. Yes, and I think there is a qualifying
novella this year to the qualifying volume. Benaranovich was one of the guests of honor at
Reconnect in New Zealand where I was also the guest of honor and he was absolutely delightful.
I listened to his interview and really enjoyed it. I thought it was very good.
So I just want to check the two you read were false value and and lies sleeping. I assume Liz.
No, the two I read were false value and amongst our weapons. Oh, okay. I don't think I've read
amongst our weapons yet, but I have read false value. Yes, so I quite like false value. I think
amongst our weapons is a slightly better one. It also goes back but it also goes back to the
Leslie plot arc, which I thought was a bit not well tied up in lies sleeping but sometimes it's
a Reddit. Okay, having actually like done some live fact checking here, River of London was
nominated for best series in 2017, but it didn't win and has definitely had sufficient volumes to
be eligible again since then. Good. I read most of the first one and then on paper and then put
it down somewhere and never picked it up again, which I mean, I really, really, I was really enjoying
it. It was like, so I don't know why I didn't. I will read them one day. I need to read more books,
guys. Can we read them on a golf trip? They're good kind of books for plowing through when you
might be a bit distracted in transit and so on. Yes, that is fair. It is not a slight
against them just that they're generally told in a fairly linear way and they're pretty easy to
read. They're exactly the sort of books that I think the Hugo Award for Best Series is a good
thing. It means that it's a good thing because I think it is a difficult skill but it does reward
like it means you can write these big long series and it you know you can have these massive stories
and I think that is something that like I would never pick one of these books as like the best
novel of the year by definitely think this series is like a rollicking good read and I would recommend
it to someone who just wants like some lovely books with characters that do interesting things
but aren't like, I don't know, I think there's merit to that. I'm not describing it very well.
Yes, yes. And Mashe's genre is together in an interesting way and also comes from a... Yes.
Comes from a place, you know, the characters in this book are not well represented in
science fiction in general, right? No. Fantasy, I suppose more fantasy, well fantasy mystery than
SF. But I do like the book, you know, I really did enjoy the one I nearly read.
I mean it does feel like they're very much the books about a modern London.
Yeah, that's also true. And we like that if we live in modern London.
God John, have you just convinced me of like a good argument for where we have the best series,
Hugo? God damn it John. Well this is the argument I've always
had in my head about the best series. Hugo, I'm just not sure I've ever been very good at
articulating it. Oh, you've definitely articulated on the podcast. Oh, yeah, you know,
I'd say that. I mean, the problem with the best series Hugo, at least in part, is that that's not
how people vote though. They vote for the series that contains their favourite novel of the year.
Look, right, we can't be grumpy at Hugo categories because people voting them wrong because if we
were, that would just be angry all the time. All the live long day. Very hard being me.
On with the on with the picks because it's bedtime. Shall I go next on the basis that
Alison's pick is even less SF Northern mine. Yeah, go on. I went to a convention listeners.
I went to the UK Games Expo, which was held at the NEC at the start of June. So,
Conventions been running now for 16 years. I think the first one was in 2006, 2007,
2007, I think. And so I remember when it was in a Masonic Hall somewhere in Birmingham and it fit
into a single room. And now it is the entire of the Birmingham NEC Hilton Metropolitan,
plus three full halls of the NEC. It is truly bonkers now. But yes, I went and it was good.
I had a lovely time and I played lots of board games, board games with people who love board games.
So I played an interesting game called Earthborne Rangers, which is really interesting. One of the
one of the key things about this game is that it's fully compostable, which is an odd selling point
for a game. But it means that when you finally like you decided to order play it and slash or
pop your clogs and your next kinder doesn't want to play it, it won't bugger up the earth when it
goes. So that's nice. And it's a game set in a world that's a bit similar to Horizon. It's like
a post-climate catastrophe world where humanity is kind of living more in balance with nature than
at the moment. And it was quite kind of a nice contemplative little kind of questy card game.
And it particularly tickled my fancy because it felt very much like a cross between
Arkham Horror of the card game and Seventh Continent, the board game. And so yeah, I thought it was
really interesting. Well, did I play? My friend bought a game called Solar Sphere, which is a game
about building a Dyson Sphere that was nominated for or won an award. I can't remember which. But
like that sounded like it would be quite fun. And I look forward to playing that. I played a game
called Flick Fleet. Flick Fleet is a very good idea for a game that I would never ever buy. So the way
it works is you get spaceships, which are bits of acrylic, and you put them on an earframe play
map. And then you put asteroids on the near-prem play map. And in order to move your ships about,
you have to flick them. Well, this is by the people who did asteroid dice. Possibly.
So I played that at Dragon Meat and thought it was hilarious and also mad. But you know,
I would never buy it. And I got them to tell me about their Kickstarter for Asteroid Dice,
which has now launched. And Asteroid Dice is a game where you have large dice and you throw
them at people. And I'm never going to buy that. But you know, people seem to like it. Large
like foam dice. So if you want large foam dice, you can buy them on the internet now.
Yes, yes, yes. I am confused because I know about Asteroid Dice, but that's not on the
Flick Fleet website. So I don't know. No, their game is. Okay, so I did not play Flick Fleet.
I played a game called Shape Invaders, where you have a bunch of acrylic space invaders and you flick
them at people. That sounds like quite a similar game, doesn't it? Interesting.
Turn any tabletop into a battleground with Shape Invaders. Aim Flick and eliminate the enemy.
That has not yet been kick-started, but it's coming to Kickstarter, it says. So it looks
less strategic. Yeah, no, it wasn't strategic at all. It was hilarious. Just, you know.
So Flick Fleet is quite strategic. So Flick Fleet reminded me most of the X-Wing
miniatures game. So you have like hit points and shields and like different systems that you can
repair and etc. But it was just, it was a very good idea. I liked it quite a lot, but I was extremely
bad at it. Yeah, so, so I don't really believe in it. That's like saying that Snuka or Pool or
Games of that type are strategic because I know that they are, but they're not when I play them
because I just tried not to foul. Yeah, no, that's fair. Yes. No, and that's like, I appreciate that
Snuka is a very fine game and yes, I would never play it in the pub. And this is in exactly the
same wheelhouse where it's like, Oh, and I would play it in the pub. I love playing these games in
the pub. I'm just very bad at them. I like watching other people play them in the pub. Have either of
you played a game called Catacombs, which was also a Kickstarter and sounds pretty similar?
Ah, yes. Dextarity based dungeon delve. Yeah, it's like a dungeon game and everything is little
wooden discs and you flick them around. Except for the Armadillo, which rolls and I always insist
in getting the Armadillo where possible and you sort of roll it on its side and it goes somewhere
completely unpredictable and it's fun. I have played a game called Dungeon Drop where you hunt for
Treasurish kill monsters having dropped all the pieces onto your coffee table from or gaming table
from a height of about 12 inches. This is a game that you really, really, really want to play on a
tray, which we do because if you don't play it on a tray, then you have an additional game where
you frightified all the little bits off the floor. Catacombs comes with like a side wall to go around
the board. Nice. Sensible. And a Geelat in its cube. Dungeon Drop sells this as an extra,
which is why we play it on a tray. I will attempt to link to all these things in the show notes,
but apologies if I miss one. Octa thought gaming corner. Yes. But no, it was really good and I bought
some games, but none of them are SFNAL. That's a lie. One of them is SFNAL. I bought this
for the listeners who cannot see my camera. I bought Final Girl. So Final Girl is a single player
game which kind of spins off of the hostage negotiator series of games. And it's based on the
Final Girl trope, which is basically a thing that you find a lot in horror movies where you have like
a single woman at the end of the movie who is like the only one left alive and is trying to stay that
way. Notable examples of the genre include Alien and Cabin in the Woods. I bought, they basically do a
lot of off-brand boxes which are kind of horror movies that they don't have the rights to that are
like just generic enough to get away with it. So I bought the set which is the Evamorph, which has a
picture of a woman who looks very likes a guinea weaver on the cover. And that's quite fun. It's
incredibly difficult. I have not won a game yet. But I enjoy it. And that's the main thing. Indeed.
But yeah, it had a lovely time. It was really good. So my pick this week was going to be,
well, I wanted to go last in the picks because I thought there was a fairly good chance
that that would be either at the close of play or after England had got all out. But in fact,
they haven't. So my pick is the cricket I am planning to spend much of the next six weeks listening
to cricket, watching cricket, drinking beer and talking about cricket. Cricket, that's good.
It's not very science fictional though, is it? But yeah, England are playing Australia
and the men, it's the men's turn this week and then it's the women's turn next week. And I'm
going with science fiction fans, so that's science fictional right, to watch the women play in Nottingham.
So one of the great things about the rise, women's cricket is good. Women's sport generally is good.
It's good that it's a lot more represented than it was even when I was like, you know, even 15 years
ago, like it's come on in leaps and bounds, which is great. But it does also give rise to there is a
podcast called the nobles podcast, which if you'd like cricket is quite good. And they have started
a trend of referring to the men's ashes and the women's ashes as the mashes and the washes.
And that makes me very happy. So the mashes are on at the moment and the washes are on soon.
Yeah, starting next week. Yeah, so they've already sold more tickets for the women's
cricket than they did in the whole of 2022. And that included the game that I went to last year,
which was the largest gate for a women's cricket game ever in the United Kingdom.
None of this was really on topic for the podcast. So I did have a plan for what I was going to do
as my pick, but I've had a bit of a mad week that hasn't quite gone according to plan.
So hopefully you'll get that next week, which is a perfectly sensible and realistic pick
of actual books that relate to the topic and everything.
I don't want to, I mean, I don't want to, I'm not going to check, but I suspect you've picked
cricket before. It's possible, I pick cricket every summer. Starting with last summer,
I'm still a new fan of cricket. There are two summers a year because of the joy of hemispheres.
And that was the old thought podcast, and it's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me.
[Music]
God, there's a lot of news this week. There is, isn't there? I'm never getting to bed.
The theme music for this episode was Surf Shimmy by Kevin McLeod and Combertec.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.