The episode title is going to be satisfying meat, and this makes me extraordinarily happy.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 94th episode of Octa Thorpe, a podcast for
science fiction and science fiction fandom. This episode is coming to you on the 12th of October
2023, I'm John Coxon, I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty. And today we are going to discuss
what we voted for in the best novel category in the Hugo's. And when we say what we voted for,
I haven't decided what to vote for yet, I will decide what to vote for following this discussion,
because you may demonstrate to me that novels I have hidden depths that I had not previously
noticed. We're going to kick off at the start, so we're going to read down the best novel category
with one exception. So we're going to start with The Daughter of Dr. Morro by Sylvia Morano-Gassia,
which was published by Del Rey. So this is a book about a house in the Yucatan Peninsula in Mexico,
and it's kind of in conversation with a book by H.G. Wells, which is called The Island of Dr.
Morro. It kind of focuses on the daughter of Dr. Morro, the titular daughter of Dr. Morro, and
one of the people who work in the house for the doctor. So yeah, Colotta and Montgomery.
And that is kind of a potted summary of the book. What do we think? First off, are we going to
do spoilers? No spoilers? Oh, we're definitely doing spoilers. Second, I think that was a good
job, but I don't think you actually basically said anything about what is in the book. So
we might want to see if we can do like very pithy 30-second introverts to the other ones.
Okay, what did I miss out on? Well, just because you didn't mention anything about it,
meaning of the hybrid man animal people. I just keep it. Yeah, so critically, Dr. Morro is uplifting
animals to pick a term from David Brim, but he was doing it in his in their Wells novel as well.
It's patching in some of the things that are just left in the Wells as you didn't need to explain
this sort of stuff when you were writing an adventure novel in the 1890s, but maybe you do
need to do that now. So things like where the money is coming from, and the money is coming from
somebody who believes that uplifted animals might be a good labor force. So obviously, you're then
getting into some very interesting ideas about slavery and colonialism and my general critical
click, which is how is the work getting done. And this book kind of sets some of this stuff up and
then really doesn't answer it as much as I would expect. And it's not a particularly long book,
and it quite spends quite a lot of the book engaged in the daughter's love triangle, which I have to
say is one of the most boring love triangles I have ever read in all of my time reading fiction.
Because there are two men here and they're both terrible. So, you know, but the big problem I
have with this book is that if you are familiar with Wells and familiar about it, then there is
a major reveal about 80% of the way through the book. And if you're remotely familiar with the
Wells, then reading the title might tell you what that reveal is. So this is a problem.
Yeah, I would say when you decided to read the Wells, I thought you were making a mistake,
and I did wonder whether that would come up in our discussion.
Yeah, I think you should have read the Wells four years ago. That would be a good time to
have read it, or when you were a child, something like that.
I don't think you're supposed to not work the twist out, I will say. I think it's like not clear
to the character, and I think it's believably done that the character that is not clear to the
character. But I don't think you're supposed to be like absolutely astounded by the reveal.
I really liked this. I liked the character work. I think the way I described the book at the
beginning really neatly encapsulates the bits I found interesting about it. The hybrids are
kind of interesting, but it is not the plot that appealed to me about this one. It's like their
comment trees on colonialism, capitalism, and the way it blends all that together with stuff
about Mexico, which I was kind of like unaware of. It feels like exactly the sort of novel I think
the Hugo's very good at recognizing in their late stage where it's someone from a different
background exploring the genre from a different set of eyes and having different takes on what's
going on. I liked it for that. Yeah, I think the setting is really interesting, and it's very
complex in how it interrogates it. So it's not kind of a setting where the Europeans bad
the indigenous people's good. There are different aspects to it because there are
kind of the indigenous my own people, but also other people from other areas like South America.
And also one of the lead characters is a British guy who's basically outrunning his pastel trying
to by being in Mexico and around there. But it's not really, it's kind of a more interesting than
just this guy is a colonialist, but obviously he has some kind of privileges and power based on
who he is, but also not because he's heavily indebted to other people. So I thought that was
interesting. The love triangle is maybe a little bit, it's not the most interesting bit, but I kind
of liked Calotta the daughter because she's not quite been raised in solitude and completely taken
in by the you know, shiny young man who appears and she's not unaware of kind of the wider issues,
but he's still someone who's trying to figure out like what would be best for her and still can get
kind of seduced and taken in. So I thought it was a bit more complicated than maybe your average
love triangle between the young women and the two men who are interested in it. Plus she does
kind of at the end is not really with either of them. She is off making her own way.
Yeah, I did like that as the ending of the situation.
Calotta has two hybrid companions who are hybrids who are kind of not quite perfect hybrids,
but they are very interesting characters and I thought they were very well drawn and they
are better drawn than any of Wells' hybrid characters. And the other, I thought this
because it's not just, it's in dialogue with the Wells obviously, but it also has quite a lot to
say, but it's quite like the Tempest with the magician and his daughter and their spirits
on an island and it is also quite like Blade Runner with a madman who is building a working
class and who has a beautiful daughter. And I thought those were also two very interesting
influences. This is one of the most interesting novels on the ballot. It may be the most interesting
novel on the ballot. I just don't think it worked very well. I think that's a, I really liked a lot
of things about it, but I feel like it didn't all pull together to leave me feeling, "Oh yes,
I have read a very satisfying science fiction novel at the end of it." I read it first as well
and I think I probably liked it more if I'd read it last after some of these other novels,
because I think I might have been grading on the wrong curve.
Yeah, it feels like it has lots of interesting components to it that don't quite make 100%
satisfying novel. Also, I've read a couple of reviews of this that say, "Oh, this one's got
onto the ballot, but in fact, Moreno-Gasi has written better books and she's been kind of
bubbling under on the Hugo ballot for a few years." So, so it's definitely worth, I haven't read
anything else by her and I'm definitely going to go away and do that now because I thought this was
very interesting. She'd been on my radar for a while, so I want to read Mexican Gothic, but the one
I'm particularly interested in is she wrote the daughter of Cthulhu, or she edited the daughter
of Cthulhu anthology, which obviously is in my wheelhouse. So, I, you know, I think I agree,
I don't think this comes together quite as well as I think it might have done, but I did,
there were, I thought there was a lot to like in it. And then next up is The Kaidu Preservation
Society by John Scalzi, published by Tor Books. This is a book in which a delivery driver makes
friends with someone because he makes deliveries to him and it turns out that person works for an
organisation that because of nuclear power plants thinning the boundaries between worlds,
works for an ecological preservation society dedicated to Kaidu on a parallel earth.
Hijinks ensue. "Kaidu are Japanese movie monsters, which you probably need to know before you
read this novel because if you don't, they never really describe the Kaidu at all in more than the
most basic forms. So, you have to make them in your mind." "I feel like Kaidu is a term of art
similar to zombies where like you don't have to go into massive detail on zombies either because
everyone knows what a zombie is. Do we think that's wrong?" "I think more people know what a zombie
is than know what a Kaidu is, but two things are left undescribed in this novel and I think it's
quite deliberate. The first is the main character and the second is the Kaidu and I think that's
that's one of the things that is interesting about the novel kind of as a structural thing."
"Scalzy has been fascinated by main characters that go undescribed like was it
lock-in where the main character's gender is unspecified?" "Yeah, main character's gender is
unspecified here as well, which I didn't know until I finished reading the book either.
I read this main character as male, other people read this main character as female,
people have opinions loudly on the internet." "Hey." "I mean, I noted it because there's a few
points where I noticed that everyone was referring to Jamie as Jamie where you would naturally throw
in a pronoun, but only a couple of times did I realize that was happening. So I think it is quite
well done, but it is also a testament to the characters in this novel who are all interchangeable
millennial nerds and gender is basically unimportant because everything is unimportant,
except that they're from millennial nerds." Okay, so this novel is largely the story is
largely told through the medium of "baddens" which is fine, but it does get a little bit
wearing, but I mean I enjoyed it. I read this very quickly, I enjoyed it a whole lot. It doesn't
do a huge amount, you know. It's it's so in the way that the Marana Garcia is an extremely ambitious
novel that doesn't quite pull it off. This is an extremely unambitious novel that does it perfectly.
Yeah, I think that's better. I think like, and the afterward makes it clear that this is indeed
explicitly the case because Scalzi was trying to write an ambitious novel in the pandemic and
they eventually burned out and then this was the novel that he wrote instead. "He's like,
it's a lovely light thing that will distract you from the terror of your know-all life and then
you could read this and then you can just enjoy it and then get on with your life and I'm very
that's fine. We need books like that, but we don't necessarily need them to put them on our
awards shortlist people. What's wrong with you lot? Sorry, anyway."
I think I wanted to pick up on something that Liz said, which is that all of these people are
millennial nerds. This is true, but one of the things that me and España were discussing when
we were both reading it was that it's not just that they're all millennial nerds, they're all
incredibly like sarcastic and quippy millennial nerds and I said to her, "I wish there was one line of
dialogue in this novel that didn't get appended with the word 'droyly'. I'd quite like some wet dialogue,
please. Just one earnest person who doesn't get any jokes would be great because like in real life
there are earnest people who don't get my joke because this world feels very superficial because
it is entirely people who feel like they would be friends with John Scalzi, which is great, but like
it didn't feel particularly plausible to me that the characterizations really
told me out of the book a couple of times. One of the nice things usually if you have characters who
are sarcastic quippy nerds is there's usually a moment where they stop being sarcastic quippy nerds.
Like there's a moment of sincerity or otherwise that kind of then contrasts with it and it didn't
feel like we had that very much. I would say I did find this novel quite funny which given that
there are two novels on here which particularly seldom sells as being funny, I thought it was
interesting that this novel I found funnier than either of those two novels by quite a long way
because they're sarcastic quippy nerds and they do that stuff. I like quite like that stuff because
I like those sorts of people so you know I really enjoyed it. I mean if you have like a couple of
after hours to sit and read a funny novel and amuse yourself then yeah this is for you. It's a
very short novel quite a lot of short novels on this ballot this year. It's 270 pages long. How long?
270 pages. That's short compared to Bloody Nona. Yeah but I don't think it's a short book.
I'm also not convinced that helicopters can do some of the things they do in this book
and there is in fact a line where you know the helicopter does a thing and then another thing
which is fine if it's because you're you know narrating this from your first person millennial
perspective but it kind of covers up that I'm not sure that it would actually work but I mean
that's not really the point of this novel is it? I'm not generally reading science fiction
novels to nitpick the helicopter science either yeah. No but I think if you're doing kind of a
sort of fun adventury novel I shouldn't be imagining like this helicopter bouncing about like Roger
Rabbit or something. Have you seen the movie Mission Impossible Fallout in which Tom Cruise
survives not one not two but three crashes of the same helicopter in sequence?
I have not seen that. Does he survive by driving his motorbike out of any of them?
I'm here. I enjoyed it. I will say coming back to the comedy thing um I find scowsy funniest when
he's not explicitly writing comedy. It's like Red Chirts I found was one of his least funny books
but I really laugh out loud at the Old Man's War series and this was kind of in the middle where
it is clearly like I say I think he is at his funniest when he is not trying to be lighthearted
in a way. Yeah I mean there are plenty of funny lines in this book and I will just come to
Allison's defense so this book is 80,000 words which I do think is on the short side. It is I think
because most I sort of imagine a standard novel to be a hundred and then anything below 90 I think
of is quite short. Three of the books on the short list came up as about 220 pages on my
kobo so roughly the same length and I think of those as short novels yeah and then the
marina gossia is a bit longer and known as a lot longer and the spare man is a lot.
Yeah I mean the advantage of the internet is that you can get you can get facts. Yeah so um
daughter dot tomorrow is bang on a hundred thousand. I think that is normal novel.
Spare man is 108 so I would again say that's normal novel.
Nona is 170 which I would say safely is long novel. Kaiju is short novel.
Nettlin bone is 82 yep so short novel and then the other one which is
legends and lossays. That's the one which I assume is short because it had a short story in it
and that usually means that they didn't quite make word count. Yeah 60k.
That is very short. On the topic of legends and lates shall we discuss legends and lates?
So I'm a small business owner. I'm really up for a novel about somebody setting up a small business
and the trials and tribulations of doing so before you eventually get success. This doesn't
have any of the tribulations and trials really apart from one kind of massive one but in general
everyone in this book is nice. Every supporting character lives their life with no purpose other
than to make the main characters life better which is a kind of weird way for a novel to be
and um oh god and I was a huge fan of Travis Baldry before I started reading this novel so you know
oh yes and it has a fantasy setting but it's not it's about a woman setting up a coffee shop could
be in Seattle could be anywhere. Has no fantasy content. It couldn't be in Seattle. It does have
fantasy content. No one's heard of coffee. Clearly ludicrous. Okay London in 2001 you know.
It could it could be science fiction. There might be less organised crime in Seattle I don't know.
Yeah maybe maybe not I don't know. Seattle fans writing. So this is a world in which there is no
of organised government but there is organised crime. I saw a review of this book that said like
Terry Pratchett without the jokes and that is completely fair without the jokes or political
commentary. Yeah I don't think it's trying at all to be Terry Pratchett so like um yeah but
it's said to Dan Mark Park. I don't think it is. I don't think it's trying to be said to be
Dan Mark Park. It is trying to be a coffee shop AU extended to a novel. I thought it did that
brilliantly. I am not convinced it needs to win a Hugo Award for doing that but like as a cozy book
that I read in an afternoon and made me feel vaguely fuzzy I thought it smashed out the park
and that is I think why people read coffee shop AU's as well. So like I think it does everything
the author wanted it to do and I think the reason it is very popular. What's a coffee shop AU?
Liz do you want to explain what a coffee shop AU is? Yes so Alison there is a genre of fan fiction
in which you take your favourite characters from a tv show or movie or video game and basically
recast them so they're all in a coffee shop and they're all baristas or maybe they're
handsome delivery guy. So like friends? No because in friends they don't actually do any coffee making
like I don't know I haven't actually read any of these things because generally the reason I'm
watching a tv show or movie is not because I want to recast the characters in a coffee shop
but I understand this is a thing. It's perfectly fair this is this is a self-published piece of
fan fiction that got picked up by a publisher but so that is what it is that is perfectly
fine. I don't think Baldry ever really expected to end up where he's got with this.
But I will say so I think the reason it has done the reason I think it has done very well this year
is because it is a cozy book about a queer person doing a thing with not many obstacles.
I think a lot of people needed that in the political and health climate of 2022 and 2023.
So I do understand why it's popular. Yeah, yeah but Bill Mills and Bird exists. I mean I
like I'm not saying this is the world's best science fiction because I do not think it is. I don't
think it's terrible though because I think it does exactly what it wants to do extremely well.
I think that is laudable in its own way. I do not think the author was trying to do anything other
than exactly what he did. I mean but it does set up some things right so it does set up that there
is organized crime and they are coming around to you know get payments from the business owner for
safety and security and the way this is resolved is she goes and chats ahead of crimes and they're
gree she can have some cinnamon buns. Cake. You've read this as organized crime but it's
actually the government. It's taxes it's somebody coming to you in in order to get payment for
public services. Although generally if I don't pay my taxes I don't think they're quite as
menacing people with swords who come round. Yeah I mean very enough but you know this is set up as
like a major obstacle. You've clearly never had the BBC license fee people come over Liz terrifying.
But they it's set up as a major obstacle and it becomes not an obstacle at all because they give
us some cinnamon buns which they have invented. Why even bother setting it up as an obstacle if
you're just going to dismiss it in five seconds and then the lady is now your best friend.
Because the point of this book is for every obstacle you face to be something that can be easily
overcome with application of either cake or friends because again it's trying to be a cozy
A.U. coffee shop story. Like I think all of the things you are describing as bugs are features
which is to say I am going to put this fifth on my ballot or probably fifth or six. I haven't
decided whether I like it more or less than the kaiju book. But I think criticizing it for things
that it is nailing as what it is trying to do is I just think it misses the point a bit.
Well I think it's worthy of recognition if there was an award for best coffee shop A.U.
we'd be right up there right? Yes it would win. It would get if there was a Hugo award for
best cozy book this would smash it. Or coziest book this is very cozy book.
Coziest book. Imagine I read you know if I want something that's cozy I might go and read like
a romance novel because then I kind of know we're going from A to B in it's where the twists are
along the way but even then like it doesn't necessarily have to be that you know you but I think you
have to have like some way of resolving this like maybe we should resolve this by you know a
non-traditional way. I'm not saying she should be paying the protection money/taxes but you know
if there was at least some like small obstacle that she had to talk her way through or that was
resolved by you know talking to her friends about it but it literally just seems to resolve by going
along to this meeting and then it's all sorted right like I don't believe in the romance if this
romance doesn't have any obstacles to it. To be fair they explain later that the the the cinnamon
buns in return for protection thing is because and this is one of the ways that you know that the
madrigal is actually about government not crime is she is drentrifying the area and the madrigal
likes that. That's explicitly said in the book it's it's not you know so I talk a lot about
critical chisels. This book doesn't really you can't really use a critical feather on it because as
soon as you start thinking about anything in the novel it all falls apart like a like a like a
particularly frothy cake that you might get in a coffee shop. I want I want to say I don't think
I've said this loudly or maybe at all. I completely agree with everything Liz and Alison have said
about this novel. I just think that that is the point like every single criticism I think is an
entirely valid thing that is wrong with this book. I have to give my Travis Baldry shout out here
which is that the reason I knew of Travis Baldry was that he took a genre of video game which is
where is dungeon crawling where you go and fight horrible monsters and he made the cutest game
ever made in that in that genre where you are adorable your pet is adorable most of the things
you meet are adorable nothing bad ever happens to you and so I feel like the man has for me here.
I do agree like it is not going to be anywhere near the top of my ballot and hopefully hopefully I
mean if this was the hugo then I don't know I don't know what I'll do. Nothing probably I'll
just rant about it on my podcast I have a podcast. Do that right guys? So anyway yeah I think we're
agreed we disagree on exactly why we're all putting it towards the bottom of our ballot but I think
I don't think any of us are putting this at the top is that fair? I mean yeah but I just I don't
want to think that this is like cozy fantasy has to mean that you can just like make up plot hurdles
and then forget them again. I would also like to point out that if this is supposed to be like
oh the real the real treasure was the friends we made along the way they're all your employees.
Well okay so how are union eyes?
I want to read the sequel to this which is the union.
She makes them partners but they're not really even employees the aspects of her
they because the thing about books about found families and the books where you
even employees books where you kind of work with people to achieve a goal.
That's like quite like that genre. One of the reasons why like one of the reasons about a
podcast is good is because we don't agree all the time. I disagree. We don't automatically do things
to because they'll make John happy right? No I mean that I fully agree with.
You know it's it's it's not that's because when you have a joint enterprise and you bring
something really good together from the joint enterprise it's because you have different opinions
and you work through those different opinions to build the thing that is worthwhile and there's
very little of that in this book. That's the thing that really makes it fail for me is that if she
was telling that sort of story if he was telling that sort of story which I do really like
there's not a disagreement it's just you know everyone just loves it everyone just loves her
it's just being surrounded by people who adore what she's doing.
I'm running out of ways to say I completely agree with your criticism but I don't think it's
what he's trying to do but yes agreed. I would not have read this book if it wasn't on the Hugo
bout and I would not read other things by this author probably. I might if I was in like a really
bad mood and I just wanted something to turn the pages but that's why I have Star Wars
tie-in novels which achieve a very similar thing for me.
This and Clergy Preservation Society both neither of them is going to trouble you very much they
both get read in the after in read a bit of coffee shopping an afternoon with a coffee in a cinnamon
bun. Oh yeah I will say one very concrete boon of this book which might elevate it to fifth on my
ballot is that when it spany made it she did get back onto her cinnamon roll baking kick
and that was a concrete win in this house so thank you to Travis Baldry because I got a lot of
cinnamon buns mmm yeah win fair fair right from a book that tries to do not a lot and is very clear
and doesn't have many obstacles to no another ninth which is different different to that in many ways
so this is the third entry in the locked tomb series this is hard to pray see but it's about
a little girl who likes being the class monitor at her school and then has to go on a school trip
so she's a she's a she's a late teenage girl who has very few memories and so is presenting as a
very younger it's going to be tricky so okay so I've got a thought about this book which is
I enjoyed Gideon the ninth very much I thought it was good I thought to be fair I thought the first
half was a little bit slow but the second half I like thought was great and then I really actually
enjoyed Harrow the ninth as well and I know not everyone did but like I really liked the way it
kind of takes the first book and starts start start playing with the story of that book in a way
that makes you wonder what's going on and then kind of resolves it at the end in a way where you're
pretty sure you know what's going on but you're not 100% and I was looking forward to the third
volume because I thought it would confirm what had happened in the second volume and instead what it
does is it gets way more confusing and for me I'm keen to read the fourth volume still because I do
still want to know what's going on but I do think there is merit to actually explaining what's going
on I wish this book had done more to resolve what was actually going on in Harrow because at the
moment I'm like the starting point of someone reading this book is going to be very divergent
based on exactly how they interpreted the events of Harrow and then this book is going to make that
diverge even more and so I don't think many fans in this series will be on quite the same
wavelength as to what is actually going on and I think that I found frustrating in a way that I
didn't for Harrow so this is my least favorite of the three so far so I would say I enjoyed like
the first half so all the bits about Nona but it did feel like and you know I know that this book
was added to make the trilogy into Quadrilla Jupy Jimmy when the last volume got too big but it does
feel like she got really interested in Nona and wanted to do more about Nona and then at some point
it was like oh but I have to now fit this back into the rest of the story let's go back into the
kind of necromancery necroloid shenanigans side of things and I think it's a little it doesn't quite
fit together and I wonder if I would have just preferred like the bits that are known as this
completely separate book but maybe I need that kind of tension about who Nona actually is to make it
work I did enjoy it I had to go back and look up who half the characters were at the start even though
I had literally read Harrow the ninth the week before it does not even a tiny it's bit of hand
holding it's like do you remember that character who was actually two characters in one and like in
the last 10 pages they changed their name well now they're a main character hope you remembered
who they were and it also has flashbacks although I don't really know when the flashbacks are
happening but anyway sort of retelling the story of the god emperor of this world who essentially
comes from our world and I'm not sure it that fits in um I was necessary to know kind of how it
came about I'd already got the idea from Harrow that he was not a great guy to be the god emperor
but I still enjoyed it because I enjoy everything with like necromancers and ridiculous swordplay
and bone magic and you know people being in different bodies and going into the mysterious
river and living there and coming back out and and so I quite enjoyed it but I also don't really
know what happens at the end yes all of what Liz said I agree with I have a general complaint
about series which is that I don't like books where I feel I'm reading the same book over and over
again which I often do with series even ones that are very well thought of um the locked tomb
doesn't give me that problem okay no that is fair except that structurally it does because I feel
like it's now set up for we basically have a novel where for three quarters of the novel you
have not the faitus fucking idea what's going on and then about fairly close to the end there's
there is a large info dump after which many things become clear and and then about 80% of
everything gets resolved but like the last 20% hopefully she can pull it together on the fourth
book but I am now getting a little bit tired of that structure I also think this book is
far too long for the story it's telling the stuff the bits with Noda was perfectly fine
just go on and on and on and on and we know that in fact not that much of that bill is going to
lead into our eventual plot and there's also some of the stuff later in the novel some of the
flashbacks are longer than they need to be there's quite a lot that just feels flabby in this book
but you're telling a really complicated story deflapping it makes it easier to tell the
the long and complicated story not not harder so I like this one I like Gideon and maybe like
Harold even more than Gideon and I like this one slightly less than all three of them but my
this comes to my other big problem with this book for the best level category which is guys this
is a do-novel this isn't what a novel looks like this is not it anyway it does not have any of
the features of a novel if you looked at it with critical theory you would go oh no that's not
what the novel is yeah it's a it's the third part of a four-part book and it's it should not be on
the best kind of a category and it's an absolute scandal that it is I mean obviously it satisfies
because it's like fiction of more than 40,000 words but it is just like a chunk of fiction out of the
middle of a of a series and series is why we have this best series category and it could go there
and like a bird fruit there which I probably will do because I really like I am curious like
I think it's more of a jam it's more of a jam than a novel yeah like maybe a strawberry jam why
it's not it doesn't it so so a novel tells a story this doesn't tell a story if you pick this up
without having read the previous two books in the series it would make no sense at all this is
basically me saying it's clearly a novel uh it does it does I actually I would actually sincerely
argue that it would make almost as much sense as it does having read the previous two because it's
not like the previous two had a lot of clues readers if if any of you out there have read Noda but
hadn't read the previous two because it's all the Hugo Ballot please write it with your thoughts
does this feel like a level to you I mean I think you could argue it it tells the story of Nona even
if you don't really know what's going on with the rest of the characters that Nona has a sort of
satisfying character arc except I don't really know what happens to her at the end but otherwise
Nona I don't think she does does she well I think she has I don't think she has a happy ending but
I think she has a satisfying character arc we meet her at her birth and then spoilers we leave her
at her death and we encounter her entire life in between so I would actually argue quite strongly
that this is a complete story I might have been more sympathetic to your point with Harrow um but
this one feels much more self-contained than I think Harrow did and I suspect Alexa will again
feel much less self-contained but this one didn't and that's actually why I don't like it because I
I think that's my main problem with it is that it feels like a self-contained story being told in
between like bits of a story I would quite like carry on with like this does not appear to advance
the series in any meaningful way to me so actually I actually almost diametrically disagree with
you on that I want to come back to the um uh point I think Liz made which is this is a book that would
greatly benefit from a proper dramatic personi and the guest list was the most annoying thing
about the novel because it's very cute but I would actually like to know what the fuck is going on
and who all these people are like and that was the other thing which is I did because I have read
Harrow a year ago two years ago a year ago I can't remember now but a while ago I do not remember
the finer details of Harrow in a way that would mean I could pick up anything from the series the
wider series I've got no idea who thingamajig is hecked I vaguely remember her coming up in a
previous book but like yeah so that's that is Camilla one of the original cavaliers from Gideon
the ninth she was in Gideon yeah okay and yes I'd be I'm on and look up now how long it was since
I read the previous installment yeah so I did just read them so maybe it just follows on much more
for me because I've done that and it holds its own as a novel much better but again I think the
pacing is really off for a novel oh yeah I agree like I think I think structurally is a mess
maybe that's unfair but like it and like I'm not I'm not a critic and I'm not a published author so
maybe this is incredibly unfair of me but it feels much less well constructed than the previous two
did to me I mean with the outside knowledge I suspect this was like act one of Alecto the ninth
and the point that we get to at the end which spoiler I think is like Alecto is released and
Harrow's soul goes back into no no but I'm not entirely sure like I presume that's where we're
supposed to get to part of the way through the fourth book to set up the ending and now we'll get
that ending all plot all the time hopefully I am slightly worried that the end book's going to be
more than 200,000 words so that it satisfies the requirements for best series next time please don't
do that this book is too long I mean it really is too long there were multiple times while reading
it that I was like oh no this book is easy to put down and hard to pick up again and you know I had
to go off and read one of the other novels and then come back to it because it's got to be two new
works to be eligible and best series again by the way so one very long book won't do it oh thank you
thank you oh oh I guess I'm getting interested in best series now in a way that I maybe didn't
before I started reading a lot more books so that's quite good yeah and apparently so I just
checked and I read Harrow in February 2021 so it's been like two and a half years and I'm like oh yeah I
also think when we were saying on the best editor and we don't know what editors do we kind of do
know what editors do because the job of editors is to say oh yeah no this is great but this section
in the middle feels like there's some pacing issues what can we do about that and and and I feel like
this is a very successful series and the more successful people get the less editors are inclined
to mess with the thing that they think works so I feel that somebody should have said there's a
great 120,000 word novel in there let's find it because I think that probably it I think if I had
one criticism of the series as a whole it would be that I do think each of the books are a bit
longer than they really need to be it's a mean embarrassing long time to work out that no-no
was was um Harrow and Gideon I mean like 20 pages but still shall we do the next one the spare man
by Mary Robinec Co-Hull this is a story about a wealthy heiress whose spouse is accused of murder
and who takes it upon herself to try and demonstrate that their spouse is not in fact a murderer
also the heiress is chronically ill or has chronic pain sorry and she has a very cute dog
yeah so so this is also a book in dialogue this time with a movie called The Thin Man um unlike
the Wells where unlike you probably should have read us a while ago I recommend not watching
The Thin Man before you read this novel because um because it didn't help at all because The Thin
Man is a very funny movie and this is a relentlessly unfunny novel you know this is the novel I found
least funny of the six on the short list by a mile and considering this it's supposed to be a
humorous novel that's a problem I mean there aren't very many jokes and they don't land very well
and they are mostly instead of coming out of wit and people doing witty things they're kind of set
up as I'm gonna tell a joke now and sometimes they go oh this person said something funny let's talk
for a few paragraphs about how funny the thing they just said was and I'm like well it wasn't
particularly it was just like ordinary an ordinary conversational aside this is not funny this is
the the oh I just read it to the thought Mary Robinette Cowell lovely lovely person she is must be
terribly unfunny I think you are laboring from a misapprehension because I do not think this is
supposed to be funny like the cover does not mention that it's supposed to be funny none of the tags on
goodreads mention being funny the blurb does not mention being funny I don't think this is intended
to be a comedy as I am reluctant to ding it on the basis it isn't one I think it's just supposed
to be a mystery I like hide mystery but I don't think it's supposed to be a comedy mystery I mean
I don't find any of the books on this short list for me anyway but I think it's supposed to have like
a light frothy kind of you know newlyweds sparring tone that I don't think it really gets very well
yeah yeah I think it's supposed to be bands I think the scowlsy book definitely has bands this one
does not particularly have that oh I should know I should know I did have um it's time for a
Españez opinion da da da da dah dah dah dah dah dah dah dah dah dah dah dah dah dah dingle so
Españez found uh no the ninth incredibly frustrated frustrating and really didn't like it uh the
spare man she thought was awful um and the reason she thought it was awful and I suspect Alison will
agree with this take is that she was like I don't understand why this is science fiction this could
have just happened on a cruise ship and I think that is my core I enjoyed it I enjoyed some of the
like world building and I enjoyed some of the things that happened and I thought it was a nice quick
read but I agree with her that I don't think it's a particularly science fictional book and like
I don't think it does anything particularly noteworthy and so like it will probably be towards the
bottom of my ballot because even though I did enjoy the process of reading it I'm not sure it
like excited me in a sort of I'm going to put this on a Hugo ballot kind of a way we should say I
enjoyed it better than the scallowsy and the Baldry but like I definitely think it's less
interesting than the other three um I think there's the and then you might disagree with me you
might both might disagree with me here but I think on this shortlist there are three interesting books
and three kind of potentially well done but not particularly interesting books and I definitely
feel like the the koala is one of the is one of the ones that does not particularly like excite me
on an intellectual level oh oh it excited me on an intellectual level and by that it mean
you know it kind of had me wanting to stamp things on an intellectual level shall we start with
if I'm given a choice between a future where we've dismantled the general the gender binary but
capitalism is alive and well or one where we've dismantled capitalism and the gender binary is
alive and well I'll take the second one thank you very much this is a book where rich people do
rich people things and not only get away with it but use the fact that they're rich endlessly to
push the plot forward and I just wanted to stab them through the eyes all the fucking time sorry
and then they tell me they're funny which they do a lot I really did not like this novel and I
didn't like it because it is all about how if you have privilege you could use it to get your
own way a lot and that's kind of what the plot is yeah I mean I deeply disliked it I think for
part of the same reason I listened it which is if you're going to set up a plot where you know I
think the idea of a mystery where you know a woman has to solve it because her husband has been
wrongfully accused of murder and he's a detective but he can't do any detecting is a great set up
but you can't then also make that woman like the solar system's richest woman and she spends a lot
of the beginning of the book basically going around doing a kind of don't you know who I am
here's my extremely high-powered lawyer on on video call by the way I did think kind of a lot of
the lawyer stuff was supposed to be funny about her the fact that she's continually on time delay
as they get further and further out on the cruise liner in space but it never kind of got particularly
funny it just ended up being a bit sort of like a cagey this lawyer person comes in so I think
the problem there is that by starting off of this premise and then having someone kind of try and
lampshade it by saying I know I shouldn't use my privilege for this but I'm going to just end it
up not working and so then I wasn't rooting for her to solve the mystery I was almost
rooting for all the service people that she's kind of mean to along the way and she just try and
count it at the end by you know being nicer to some of them but when she's you know going oh well
the martini is made by this bartender and not very good I'm like I do not care that you are
getting a substandard martini and while we're talking about um there is a service dog in this
book and they relate they talk repeatedly about how you must not you know the service dog is a
working dog so you shouldn't do things that detract from the fact the service dog is working and then
whenever it suits her the service dog is sent off to do some non-service dog thing and I'm like oh
god you know I really hate it when this happens in the real world you know I don't I it's fine that
you're getting to bring your dog into the cinema because it's a service dog if you then get it to
jump up and down on the seats and eat and eat other people's popcorn that is still annoying
right you know if it's if it's a working dog it has to be working right at least most of the time
and it's not what I like is that we have contrived to have two Hugo novel episodes one in which
Alison runs about cats and the other in which Alison runs about dogs this is very good oh yeah so
I don't talk a lot about the fact that I don't believe in private pet ownership but you know
I agree with that there's a novel for a lot of I will use the dog as a convenient distraction
here and I think it maybe undermines what you know from my non-expert view is a pretty good
portrayal of PTSD and chronic pain and some of the more interesting stuff was about how she can
essentially dial it up or down but there'll be consequences later although I was waiting for
the consequences to really kick in at a key point and they didn't so much you know but that is a
great concept among the more science fictional things about it yeah and I think one of the
things I like about this is the portrayal of of chronic pain and mental health I thought was
very good and something you don't see as often as it would be nice to see in SF. So yeah I agree with
that for sure I have liked everything else I've read by Cole so I think this is just
an aberration really if it's a series I'll probably won't read the next one unless it's all the Hugo
Ballot I don't think it is a series I think it's standalone if this wasn't the Hugo Ballot I would
not pick it up because I've previously put down and closed one of Cole's levels after 100 pages I
know they're not for me but it's on the Hugo Ballot so I'm reading it I do want to say one more thing
which is I also didn't find it very satisfying as a mystery like I didn't find it never had that
kind of oh so that's what was going on kind of oh yes moment it kind of like occasionally
things trickled out but didn't seem to have the right weight okay so I'll trip back to the thin
man one of the things about the thin man that I think probably this book is doing is that the
mystery is not the point of that film and not the point I believe the sequels that the mystery is
something on which the comedy between the main characters the detective couple is placed that
they're they just kind of are funny all of the time every scene they're in is funny and they do a
lot of funny physical comedy and funny verbal comedy and I think that is what she was trying to
catch here so I think that's why I don't I do think it was intended to be a funny novel that is
also a mystery I I was quite surprised by the suggestion that's not the case so I maybe maybe
I'm wrong about this or maybe or maybe it's possible that Cowell didn't notice that the thin man is funny
okay I have a very interesting article about Cowell about what she's taking from the thin man I think
one of the things that strikes me as a binary or not a binary a um parallel between your
description of the thin man on a previous episode and this book is that they are both depictions of
married people who are married where they are just married like and they have affection for one
another and I like that and that's not something again you don't I think obviously not everyone
jives with Cowell's just depictions of these things but I do like that one of the things in the
calculating style as well was like a happily married couple who are happily married and that
I do enjoy in her work so I can see why the thin man might have resonated for her on that level
I wanted more fleshing out of the husband in that case he is a bit of a cipher yeah I one of the
takes I read on this novel was that it's the same husband she always has in all of her books
um which I thought was interesting um I don't know I haven't read enough Cowell to really know whether
that's fair have you read the oh there's one of the calculating styles novels towards the end
which has like a husband who is a senator and he is quite different in a way if I recall correctly
um back on the wood book is a few while since I read them then it is nettle and bone
by Tkingfisher which I picked on the episode one of the episodes leading up to Eastercon so
I pre-seed it there I forgot you picked it sorry do one of you two want to give a summary it is a
fairy tale book in in that it lives in the world of fairy tales it is deeply unsettling in the way
that um a lot of fairy tales are in their original forms but often not in the forms in which they
are now read to children so it's got quite a lot of things pulled out of myth and I think almost the
first page Tkingfisher who is the pen name of Ursula Vernon quotes from an english folk tale
where she is building a dog out of bones and she reflects on the folk song where
somebody is making a harp out of a woman's bones and other part body parts and I I that's
obviously the sort of thing I like and I instantly kind of want oh no it's that sort of here we are
in the world of the world of fairy tales in which people are not necessarily nice and it proceeds
along those lines and people are not necessarily nice and it has something very much in common
with legends and lattes which is that as our heroine goes along trying to complete her task
which is much much less savory than opening a coffee shop she finds a lot of people who help
her but they are deeply difficult and unsettling and strange people who are not necessarily always
aligned with her own needs but they form a group working together in a much more satisfying way
than in the coffee shop book yeah I think I'd agree with that I love this especially after reading
the other five I was like oh god a good book oh that's so nice I really enjoyed it I mean I think
I also like the aspect where so our heroine heroine is kind of the third she's the third child of
the king so she is a princess and her you know she's trying to basically um kill the prince who's
married both of her oldest sisters because he needs to be removed but I liked how there's kind of like
the queen is in there as well and you know there's the inevitability of well all I can do to keep
the kingdom together is to do what I can and use my children sort of as pawns on the board and I
liked you know I don't think she completely forgives them mother for it but she kind of comes around
to understand like the situation she was in and what she had to do because nothing is too light
and fluffy it is just kind of the reality of the world she's drawn I like that I liked all the
different the different witches so I think there's sort of multiple figures who have magic or powers
or witchcraft we've got the dust switch and uh different fairy godmothers or possibly cursing god
mothers and I thought that was an interesting like to have these different ladies of different
personalities all doing magic in different ways I can't say my mind is in like completely blown by
it but I do enjoy it it's a lovely kind of little whimsical dark fairy tale I like the chicken
there's a demonic chicken I love the demonic chicken yeah demonic chicken is great when they
turn this into a movie the demonic chicken will be played by Alan Tudyk no it's really good I can't
I mean I read ages ago but I remember it being good I will say it felt very much like a young
adult novel to me which I think is probably like a lot of kingfishers works have been
um young adult uh novels so that makes sense I think it's really good and I think it's the best
of the novels on the ballot but I don't think it's as good as like previous best novel winners have
been oh there's been some turkeys that have also been some turkeys that's true and it's definitely
better than Wonder Woman I think you're right on the adult thing and the one thing I might
do it for is the main character is you know in her 30s for most of the book and yes she's been very
cloistered and sheltered but she sometimes feels a bit like a young adult teenage protagonist
yeah no I'd agree with that she is she she is played but she's reading very young for somebody
who's supposed to be in their early 30s even if they have been um living in a nunnery for for 15 years
yeah and it means the romance feels a bit weird yes that's fair yeah gotta love me a good strong
silent paladin type though like those and I think that I guess I might be what I mean by
feeling very young adult which is that I think young adult books everyone reads like a kind of
teenager and in this there's not I liked all the characters and they who did all feel different
but there was only like one character who didn't just feel like kind of a teenager to me but maybe
that's unfair oh the mother doesn't the fairy godmother doesn't the dustwife doesn't the demonic
chicken doesn't the demonic chicken could be quite teenage and the bone dog put it this way I was
imagining the main character as being in her teens but I did not pick up on an awkward thing with
paladin because the paladin was also reading like a broody teenager to me and so like they both
felt pretty compatible uh and I know like text you willy they are not teenagers but like that was
very much how I was imagining them and it has to do with the the voice I guess yeah it feels like
you know a princess going off on a quest with the wit and the fairy godmother and then you think
you kind of expect the princess is a teenager not a grown woman and so maybe that expectation also
plays into it you could subvert it a little bit more yes I'm not sure she's learned enough from
her 15 you know she's done quite a she's not got 15 years of experience in that nunnery right
it's not showing in what she does I guess the problem is that I've got
and they've got a fuck all experience of the real world as well but they definitely manifest as
grumpy 50 year olds rather than teenagers yeah but you don't you don't have to be grumpy Sue Mason is a
is a spinster right and a Liz I'm heading for it I'm gonna get some cats but like neither Liz nor Sue
come across as teenagers to me if that makes sense like I think there is a even if you are very
sheltered there is a definite teenagerness to the character in this book that I feel like you do not
have as you age even if you do spend most your life in a very sheltered but it's a very it's a very
minor ding and I think it's mostly to do with the again coming back to like I think a lot of king
fishes books are in the young adult kind of wheelhouse so like I'm not sure it's like something she's
tried to do and failed as much it is just like something I noticed as if that if that makes
sense I mean this is an adult novel not a young adult novel but it feels more like a young adult
novel than a lot of a lot of adult fantasy might yeah it's just not that long it's quite
it I would have thought it was accessible I'd happily give this book to teenagers
which is always one of the things I think about I mean I give books to teenagers that people
wouldn't because I remember what I was reading when I was a teenager so people like you couldn't
give that to a teenager I was like that's fine I think if this was in the load star category I would
not blink an eye at it really if being suitable for a load star as well yeah I mean maybe that's
just because you know YA and Adel cross over a bit more but you know a wizard's guide to defensive
baking was in the you know the load star and had a teenage protagonist and this does not feel
dramatically different I like them both but yeah yeah it's got a lot of hard words here about the
way in which women are treated in fairy tale worlds and indeed often not in fairy tale worlds
that you know you might not want your kids to know about until they grow up and experience
at first hand but there we go I was just going to say that Christian Cushor's books which are also
young Adel in theory have a lot of this about like women's place in the world and you know the
control of women and nobility and things like that so it felt like I came from the same well
I also like those a lot so I've been to know if any experts in kind of children's or young Adel
fiction are listening but I think I've read in general I think I've read that um YA does tend
to deal with more adult themes than adults think it does if that makes sense I would also say I
didn't like it as much as defensive making. Tense of baking is great though so you know that might be
why but it is but it is still very like because I'm like trying to think of interesting things to
say about the thing and it's way more interesting to pick up a pick at like the very minor criticisms
I have than I really liked it so like is tricky. I found this very satisfying I like this better
than a defensive baking I like defensive baking well enough but I thought it was a romp whereas
I felt like this was really getting into the the very very satisfying meat of myth and magic and
and how they work and what the trade-offs they're alike and I like that sort of thing.
And also I quite I did like Bone Dog quite a lot I thought Bone Dog was quite a good dog and
you know having I don't want to you to think that I'm entirely against animals um yeah when
they're kind of magic magic bone dogs that's pretty good and I love the fact they put fur on him later
I thought that was probably a good move. I did like the way it starts in media's res with her
like animating a bone dog. Yes I think also so so legends and lattes and casual preservation
society which both about as long as this book very much tell a story in a very here is the
start of the story and here is the end of the story and here we are going through the story
one beaters of time as you know it was if anything more complicated than that would
overwhelm us so I do quite like this was told in a in a more imaginative way and nevertheless in
quite it's quite a short one. Yeah I think structurally this is more impressive than
several of the other books on the shortlist like in terms of how it is written I think you are right
and I guess I loved it was a great place to start I was I was very into this book as soon as that
dog was made and then it was yeah it's good. Right so then it is time to do our rankings
who wants to do their ranking first? I'm still thinking it's a bit tricky because I've definitely
got a top three in a bottom three years just the ordering within those might change but okay I
shall I start because I think I've got a nailed on order yeah go on them all right so I'm making
a spreadsheet I'm checking it twice gonna find out who's naughty and nice so I'm gonna put
Kaiju in sixth. Oh I see we're going in reverse order. We're going in reverse order I think the
reason I'm putting Legends of Blartes in five is that I have read several uh John Scalzi adventure
books which didn't really tax me very much and had lots of quippy people in them and although it's
not a I'm not on fond of that form it doesn't really feel like I haven't seen it before whereas
Legends of Blartes you know is slightly fresher and then in four I'm going for the spare man I
enjoyed it more than you two by what sounds like a country mile but I did I did quite like it.
In third I am putting Nona the ninth because I wanted it to be about 20% shorter and make roughly
100% more sense then I am putting the daughter of Dr. Moreau because although I didn't necessarily
think it could hear as well as it might have done I thought it tried to do some interesting
things and I did enjoy it in general and then at the top Nettlem Bone the only one that was
previously picked on an episode of Octa Thorb and it was pit by me because I have great taste
boom my picks all right Alison right so in sixth place in sixth place the spare man um I really
did hate this book in fifth place Legends of Blartes because as far as I'm concerned it's not
really a science fiction novel it's a it's a well what would you say alternative universe copy shot
oh no nothing happens it's fine nothing happens in this book and it's fluffy
in fourth known of the ninth it has been bumped down the list because it is not in my view a novel
and also it doesn't make any sense and also it's far too long for what it is in third place
Kaiji Preservation Society because luckily I have not read a John Scalsy novel for about 12 years
so I'd forgotten that they're all alike so as long as I only read one about once every 12 years it'll
be fine I felt that this was a perfectly serviceable science fiction adventure story in which stuff
happens and it it is also a pandemic book that actually uses that fact quite well and use it to
help propel the pot and it is fine it's not great um you'll see we're into not great books here in
second place the daughter of Dr. Moreau because he's just trying to be really interesting and the
fact that it doesn't pull it off really isn't shouldn't be as that much of a um downside and I would
like to see I'm definitely going to read a load more of Moreno-Garcia's books which is not true for
anybody else on this list except probably I will read a lepto and um and then in first place
Nettle and Bone which is a genuinely good book that I enjoyed all the way through and have only
minor reservations about but what I really like in science fiction is like really interesting
science fiction plots that challenge me and do a lot of interesting world-building and I don't feel
any of these six books do this I'm not going to put no award ahead of all of them but you know
honestly guys could do better all right and then Liz so I mean there's not a lot of suspense here
but I will say that I'm putting the spare man in sixth because I don't think it did
successfully any of the things it was trying to do and I would have stopped reading it if it
went on the shortlist and in fifth I'm putting legends and lattes which does at least do most
of what it attempts to do even if what it does is basically you know some orcs invent the cinnamon
bun and the ceiling fan well done um in fourth we are going for the Kaju Preservation Society
because it's fun enough I mean I liked it more than I was expecting to actually because I again
I would not normally read John Scalzi's books unless they're on the shortlist because
I find their hit rate is not great for me but I finished it it was entertaining did you know
tech billionaires and maybe not great guys I did learn that from this book in third I will put
no one other ninth because like I liked it but I don't know what's going on and second it's a
daughter of Dr. Morro by Sylvia Moreno-Gossie which I do think is genuinely really interesting
and I have read other of Moreno-Gossie's books I just don't think this is one that particularly
appeals to me and in first place I'm going to put Netlum-Bong by T. Kingfisher which is pretty good.
So Liz has also described the consensus list. Liz you are the average this year I did not
realize how much Alison liked John Scalzi that is wild to me third crazy that is that is by far
like the Kaju is the one that splits us the most I I apparently thought it was much worse than both
of you third third good lord I should have been meaner about that book in the Kaju section third
but it's yeah it's it's only because it's only because I really don't like voting for books that
instalvers the series third John I didn't say where I was putting no award oh where are you
putting no award yes no so are you putting no award above or below any of these books Liz maybe
I'm I'm thinking about it but if my personal view is you should you should put something to
low no award if you would genuinely prefer that nothing got the prize rather than this book
I think I think I only no award things for philosophical reasons by which I mean either
either stuff like the puppies where I'm like no philosophically I disagree with these people
or the philosophical reason of something not being a novel so like if you know you mentioned the
Clarksworld short story where it's basically a non-fiction piece with lots of footnotes it that
is the sort thing I might put below no award if I'm like well this isn't the short story so what
are you doing but I I very rarely I probably won't just because I feel I wouldn't be appalled if
the spare man won but I'd be quite surprised I feel like writing books is hard history I couldn't
do a bad job so writing books and pandemics is hard we should we should be nice to our authors
we're glad they write books for us I am yes I'm trying to think the last thing I put below no award
and I'm I think I'm much more liberal with the no awarding than you are but I probably won't put
it below anything I just I reserve it for the cases of where I really feel very strongly opposed but
actually if the spare man wins the spare man wins I'm not going to actually be upset do we have a
few minutes for what we would have liked to have seen on this ballot I got how long do you how
long do we have like I could have an entire separate but separate shortlist but we do the
octa thought 2022 awards shortlist I don't have anything to contribute the only one I read was
let let alone a bone that was eligible and that's on it so I just nailed marina oh no you I pretty
sure you read at least one other thing that you have had as a pick which is eligible Tom
oh which one's that see you've lost chances oh you know that's true should just be all aging
Tricovsky sorry what am I talking about right the fact that there are four age of Tricovsky novels
on this ballot is a bloody hour age so you've lost chances it's better than all of the books on
this ballot except possibly nettle and bone um no it's better than all of them by an absolute
country mile um I really didn't like the ending of city of lost chances I thought it fell apart
but apart from that I really really enjoyed it all the way through um so possibly I just didn't
understand the editing it's always a possibility we haven't discussed it in detail um um Sea of
Tranquility is much better than any of the books on this ballot and satisfies my proper science
fiction requirement and also one the good reason why don't understand why it's not on the ballot
those would be my two obvious ones but actually Plutoshine Plutoshine is better than several of
the books on this ballot so oh my god okay that we're definitely going to get letters right in people
um no so actually so yes so I did read it went to the clock uh finalists so that's interesting
I don't so yes so city of last so I think I'd keep the our top three uh is nettle bone daughter
daughter daughter known of the night I think probably the three um replacing a knot those three
so what so I guess if I could put three on here that replaced the kaiju legends and lattes and the
spare man city of last chances um and then probably I really liked the anomaly I know that like that
was a bit of a divisive book but I would like to see that on there um and then probably the Simon
Jimenez because I haven't read it but like I'm sure it's great oh yeah here we are I will say
there is an open question here because there are a couple of books which I was very surprised not
to see on the ballot in a sort of did they decline way rather than a how has that not made the short
list way because I would be astounded if bable wasn't in the top six nominated books and I suspect
that might mean that we find out that it was it got a quang declined the nomination a lot of people
have said this I will be I will be interested to see what the ballot would have looked like without
declined nominations and what would have fallen off and how like our bottom three tallies with that
because I suspect I would dislike bable because I didn't like quangs uh is it the poppy war that
was the first installment of a spare series and I really didn't like that book so unless bable is
very different I suspect I wouldn't like it either um but I was surprised it wasn't on there and
then like you know tomorrow and tomorrow and tomorrow and sea of tranquility are both like names that
you might have expected to see on there as well oh yes I haven't read tomorrow and tomorrow and
tomorrow right like even though when Liz recommended it it totally immediately fell out of my brain
and then Lillian said Alison you must read this book in a very book talk way you know this book
will change your life and so then I decided to read it so but the reason I haven't read it is that I
put my name down on the Libby list on my library and I am number 493 in a queue waiting for one of
three copies so it might be a what this is not quite a fair comparison because I didn't put a hold on
netland bone but when I put holds on all of these books from the library legends of latte's was
by far the most held book it was one I had to wait the longest for um so that was interesting I always
like I was like working out how popular they are with like the library users uh by comparing the
number of holds anything we haven't mentioned that you think should be on this list oh yeah I mean
I mean definitely I didn't even I'm not even as big a fan of bables a lot of people but I
definitely think it should be on this short list above some of the others well should be on there
probably venomous lump sucker from the cloud list I also like the coral bones more I know
John's making the thumbs down at me put both those on there I would put the mountain in the sea by
Ray Layla which I picked a few weeks ago I might put tomorrow and tomorrow and tomorrow on although
it's not like if I'm thinking what I want is books that I think are really good and really
interesting from a sort of science fictional perspective then it's not super interesting from
the SF perspective but I think it's reasonably good um I might put on The Grief of Stones by
Catherine Addison which manages to be a more satisfying mystery than the spare man I think
I've only read one of the Adrian Tchaikovsky's this year and it's very middle book but it's a good
middle book it's just if I was thinking of what what's what science fiction from 2022 would I
give someone as an example of good science fiction yeah there's a lot that I would take off this
Ego list and a lot of things I would put on instead I think if I was using that metric as
opposed to how good the books are and isn't the only one I would keep on here is the marino gossier
and maybe that makes me an absolute mad lad but like netler bones very well done but it doesn't
it doesn't feel interesting in the way that that dr. maro does in what it's trying to do maybe
but I wanted to ask you the middle tricovsky was it as middle as known other night because I feel like
no in that I think it does like I mean I know what's going on boo and I think it reintroduces
you to the characters you need to be reintroduced to much better so it's not it's not quite as
middle book but I think also the thing about another ninth is it's very different from the first two
books and she's obviously going for a different thing with every book in this series whereas
iza void feels more like a space opera book from a space opera trilogy that is building to a great
big space opera finale and I thoroughly enjoy them all but I'm not sure I would pick that one
as the one to give someone all right anything else any other mentions or it's a good year for
science fiction but a terrible year for the hugos oh I think it's a terrible year for both because
like I found the clerk list also extremely underwhelming I think the anomaly and venomous
lump-subcar are the two best ones I've read on that shortlist so far haven't read the coribones yet
but like I didn't think any of them were great so like it feels like slim pickens and I think I
wonder whether that's to do with this is the year where books that should have been written in 2020
in 2021 should have been being published and I wonder whether we are seeing that effect in the
science fiction of 2022 and I wonder if it will return to some sort of form in the next couple
of years that is my suspicion and that was the old thought podcast and it's goodbye for me it's
goodbye for me it's goodbye from me
[Music]
The theme music for this episode was Surf Shimi by Kevin MacLeod and Combertec.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license. This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.