And thus it was, Alison announced her retirement from the podcast.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 143rd episode of Octothorpe,
a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom,
which is going downstairs to get some pizza
and coming back to a room that appears to be on fire on the 11th of September 2025.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And today we have Alison back.
We do, though I'm very troubled by how we had tons of letters of comment saying how marvellous Lori was.
So I'm afraid we're back to your normal not-so-marvellous service.
I mean, Lori can't help being marvellous.
I also do not own any bra tape.
And I was going to write you a letter of comment last time.
I did not write a letter of comment, but had I done, it would have said,
Lori really didn't need to worry about whether I was concerned about what had happened to the roll of ribbon I gave her.
Because when I gave her the ribbon, it went out of my life.
And I no longer felt any responsibility for it or to it.
I did say that. I was like, you can't be worried about Alison following up on these things.
Because, yeah.
100%.
But yes, no, Lori was very good.
And we talked about books and everything.
I really enjoyed listening to the podcast.
I'd like to listen to it every time.
That sounds really good.
We could just have a series of stunt Alisons.
And thus it was.
Alison announced her retirement from the podcast.
No.
Don't retire, Alison.
That would be double plus on good.
Especially don't retire by announcing it on the podcast.
Oh, I feel like if I retire from the podcast,
it's likely to happen while we record.
on past evidence.
Here's another thing I might have written in my lock,
as well as remarking on Lori's dress.
John said a little bit in the last episode
about Randy Shepard commenting on Dune.
And Randy's done this before.
A couple of years ago, I saw him
allegedly accept Hugo on behalf of a studio,
but in practice use that to have a diatribe about the studios who don't respond.
Now there's two things.
The first is that the vast majority of studios for game and for best long-form and short-form dramatic presentation do respond.
And we've been working with them as finalist liaisons.
And they are just as happy and delighted to be finalists as anybody else would be.
There are exceptions.
And in those cases, it's almost certainly that our email isn't getting to the right desk,
which is a problem in a big studio and in a big environment.
That's not really a problem with the studios.
And I feel like we really shouldn't be saying this sort of thing on stage.
It's unfortunate that not everybody responds,
but it's not something that we should be making big public pronouncements about.
And I think it's unprofessional of the ceremony director to use that platform to say things like that.
And I think you're right. I'm going to say one exception is Nintendo. I think they just have a policy of ignoring everything.
Oh, yeah. No, Nintendo could get it as son.
But yeah, I think it is tricky. Like we did it. We managed to make contact with someone on the Mad Max Furiosa team.
But it was like two weeks before the ceremony, before we finally got a lead in.
And it was because one of the other finalists had a friend who'd worked on it.
And I do think it is, I don't know whether the ceremony directors are aware of how difficult it is to contact some of these people.
Because we, like, it was Nicholas doing the emailing at this point because he had not yet resigned.
He sent multiple emails trying to contact various of the BDP finalists.
And sometimes it worked, but sometimes you sent like six emails and you don't get the person that you need.
and with Dragon Age the Veilguard the person we were in touch with at EA got made redundant between
making contact and the ceremony so like I think if that had won I don't know if there would have been
a speech but that was because EA that was because EA made someone redundant and it's like I don't
think it's because the people who worked on the game didn't care I believe the venture capitalists
in charge of EA might not care it's really tricky capitalism's hard I think the people making the
art might care more than the people counting the beans and um i think randy's anger might be better
directed at the beans hariko i'm just gonna say beans are hard too it's not surprising that teams
get broken up when projects are completed if your beans are hard you should boil them longer awards
management is probably something that studios should have a greater awareness of and have a
plan for i think we're at the point now with the hugos where the vast majority of people directing
science fiction films read science fiction in their youth and knew about the hugos and we are seeing
that in the comments that they make when when they write to us and how excited they are to come to the
world con and be at the ceremony so this episode marks the return of an important person to octothorpe
and that person is a luminary in the field,
a Hugo Award winner,
and wears excellent t-shirts.
I speak, of course, of Christopher J. Garcia,
who has written us a letter.
Yay!
And he has lots of things to say.
The number of Hugo trophies vary every year
between three and as many as you need.
When we won and we were a five-person team,
we got five.
And I guess that's the other thing,
which is the convention will make
a certain number of trophies,
And I guess there's no reason that that number of trophies is the number of winners.
So if you have more, if you have fewer trophies, you might have to charge to get more made.
But if you have more, then some teams might get, you know, more than three.
So that's actually good feedback, but couched in a very Garcia way.
So I appreciated it on two levels, Chris.
We're going to come back to this later, but he says,
On the other hand, I've mispronounced names during a Worldcon masquerade for MetaHead
and someone whose name I have said hundreds of times and can say today.
that said there's a level of mistake that's acceptable on stage john's mispronunciation
of claire's name is a great example but this clearly went beyond that he says i'm complete
i'm absolutely full of hate that seattle hasn't seemed to have apologized for the problems
um looking at la cons blow up they got their apology out in a few hours
and well yeah we're going to come back to that chris but you foreshadow some of our sentiment
he does indeed it's almost like chris is very in vibe with this podcast and he also says that
Edmonton has phenomenal Ukrainian food and I'm looking forward to phenomenal Ukrainian food.
That sounds really good. We heard from Alan Fleming and David Bamford.
That's interesting. It's from both of them but it uses the single person first person singular.
As long as I've been in fandom this must be Alan. It seems that conventions have consistently been
terrible at advertising both what conventions are and advertising that to the widest potential
market in advance. I can't say we'll do any better, but as co-chairs of the 2027 Eastercon,
it's called Unconfined and we'll put the URL in the show notes. It's something of which we are
acutely aware. People volunteer when they learn about conventions and fandom, but we need to
advertise away from our traditional avenues in order to recruit the next generation of convention
lovers. That has to be online and creating campaigns using tools and platforms with which
few of us are familiar because that's where the potential new audience is at. I think one of the
reasons why we have embraced Discord to some extent is that that's one of the places our audience is
at but I agree they have to find Discord first and also saying as people who are helping running
conventions you can't volunteer all of the time at a senior level burnout is and has always been
real and they're taking a step back for the conventions in advance of their Eastercon which
I think is probably quite sensible. I believe in other roles having a great pool of volunteers and
area heads and maybe even future chairs is to make sure that there are strong local and national
conventions um and that's definitely true and that is why the fact that a lot of these conventions
are disappearing in the u.s is is such a problem one of the things that made us want to start a
local group in newcastle was that it seemed like the through route of like local groups into fandom
was was faltering um because that's how i got into fandom mostly was the p of a group um but
if that doesn't exist then you're going to struggle we heard from jake seller brookins and i'm going
to take his uh letter and facebook comment because he says the thank you diagrams and the hugo stats
release are great thank you um i think casella did them last year maybe for an artillery review of
books or possibly the year before basically various people have done them before and i like them and so
i decided we should just do them automatically and spent quite a long time figuring out the code in
order to do that and it was probably more effort than it was worth but I still quite like them so
thank you everyone who has enjoyed the figures but will it work automatically every year now Liz
yes if they have my code and can run it because it's not particularly like it's not documented
it's like it takes the dump from something and you run this and then you run that and also it has
some tweaks because I didn't properly account for things like it doesn't properly calculate things
like how many rounds of eliminations there were I just sort of hardcoded it as six and then had to go
oh no wait there are only five in that one so it doesn't really do the it's not kind of just turn
the handle but it's fairly turn the handle so no then well yes and no right like it is not a piece
of code where you push one button and the graphs come out but it's a piece of code where you might
have to tweak half a dozen things and then the graphs come out yeah it's it's it's the it's it's
up to it's academic code yeah like if you want to run it and you've got the email address of the
person who wrote it it will take you maybe half an hour to get it working yeah that's fair because
Stella also says, how dare you impugn June 2?
Sarcasm.
Villeneuve is a generational talent when it comes to filming sand,
not actually sarcasm.
Yeah.
He is.
That is true.
That is a good point.
The sand does look good.
And it's much better use of sand than, say, you know,
the discussions of sand in Star Wars.
How dare you?
Not Phantom Menace.
What's the next one, John?
Attack of the Clones.
Yeah, Star Wars Attack of the Clones,
which is the other notable sand discussion I can think of.
Compared to Lawrence of Arabia.
I think we should talk about Lawrence of Arabia here.
Attack of the Clones has attained memetic dominance
and Villeneuve's films have not made an impact
on the cultural discussion of sand at all.
George Lucas, preeminent sand discusser.
I mean, there is a lot of sand in the Dune films.
Yeah, which makes it all the more remarkable
that not any of it has reached GIF status.
Look, right, Lucas didn't do much good with the prequels,
but that scene was very GIF-able.
I'm not sure I recognise the GIF.
Well, it's not. It's actually a meme, isn't it?
I don't care about Lawrence of Arabia.
Lawrence of Arabia is not a genre movie.
Well, I mean, it's a major movie in the sand genre, really.
And it does have aliens in it.
Sari Polvinen writes in.
I'm very sorry if I've pronounced that incorrectly.
Sorry, please let us know.
I talked a little bit about Finland and FinCon,
and I said Finnish fandom right in, and Sari did.
So thank you very much.
So Finland's con culture is very different from the Anglo-American one,
And it's one of the reasons why there won't be another world con bid from Finland anytime soon.
There's no culture of bidding for Fincons.
Fincon is a con that is basically organized in rotation in four cities.
Helsinki, Tampere, Turku and Ivaskela.
And when Findom, which is a great word, is organizing another big event like Archipelagon,
it usually means that Fincon sits out.
And there was also no Fincon in 2017.
So like the 2025 thing was not part of a global trend.
It's part of a Finnish trend.
Interestingly, although the influx of volunteers at Worldcon brings that you mentioned did happen in Finland after 2017,
and it did bring volunteers to the national fandom,
it also inspired proportionally even more people to go to and volunteer in European Worldcons.
So maybe there is a new generation of Finnish fans who are more at home with Worldcon culture.
And then, yes, thank you very much.
That is a very good comment, and that is useful to know.
And, yeah, thank you for writing in.
Information knowledge.
All knowledge is contained in the listeners.
Yeah, and I think it just shows that when we do try and draw generalisations
between different countries, they can only go so far
because the cultures are just different.
And we don't know the ins and outs of all of them.
Yes.
So, Doug Faunt wrote in to say,
I'm at Worldcon and John Hertz is sharing my room.
I'll tell him he was mentioned.
Please tell us what John said, Doug.
But thank you very much for letting him know.
And Jesse Lip wrote in,
I was correct, shocking,
The whispers is appointed two managers or prosecutors.
They use the word manager to avoid the term from the criminal justice system.
And those managers will make the whispers case to the members of the trial committee who will act as the jury and judge.
So like the equivalent of the jury and judge.
And Warren Buff and Randy Shepard are the two managers.
The trial committee reports back to the LA meeting with findings and recommendations.
And then there is a majority vote to either adopt or reject their findings.
so that is how it will work thank you very much for writing in jesse i also wanted to pick out a
comment that frederick colter made seattle was his first world con since 1992 and his fourth
world con overall poverty followed by children put a big cramp on his vanish activities that
seems like a double whammy that would do that given the length of the agenda of the business meeting
virtual pre-convention meetings are essential because there's just not enough time and i did
not do this um he says second we did manage to address one additional item at the convention
um so there was they did take up the rest of the agenda after site selection and they considered
the artist hugo reform proposal but i have not read the minutes he's like you might want to read
the minutes before the next episode i did not do that so we should do that for next time i haven't
seen them and i did look for them but i haven't seen them so if someone's got the minutes can
they point us at them listen have you seen the minutes for the hugo bit for the artist bit no i
haven't looked at official minutes i mean i think they did take up that one and then i think vote
send everything else to committee which is basically a way of say it'll come back next time but we will
look when the actual minutes are here oh we've been around this loop a few times with artist
yeah keep sending it to committee i don't know if we sent artists to committee i think we sent the
other things on the agenda to committee uh okay interesting oh that would make more sense yes okay
frederick also makes a point um which is basically on the subject of conventions going away um
Since he retired a month or three ago, he has more time to go to conventions, but the number of local cons has plummeted.
As far as he can tell, there's only one left in Florida, which I presume is where he lives.
And that is not great because there should, yeah, a country that size, you'd expect there to be more.
But the one thing that retirement has done for him is open up his time.
he basically says it in addition to trying to get younger fans involved it might also be productive
to get old geezers who had life getting in the way of fan-ish activities to get back into convention
and like i know for instance like i think there are some com runners at high levels um who are
basically people who used to have full-time jobs who have now retired and are bringing their expertise
to bear me and some other people are exploring taking on ownership of the northeast tabletop
Expo because it has been relinquished by its current runners and one of the considerations
the rest of the committee is very keen on and they're like if this becomes a full-time job we
want to be able to draw a part of a salary because it will be a full-time job and I'm like this is
very different to the Worldcon where people do the full-time job but it would be laughed out of court
if you tried to suggest they get paid for it but it might not be tenable to expect people who have
jobs to do that like to do a second full-time job that does limit the pool quite a lot but yeah
thank you frederick there was a lot of food for thought in your lot i mean i think that's very
reasonable but it seems to me that you'll have to be running a very big expo to get anywhere near
the amount of money needed to pay even a part-time salary to someone i don't think that's necessarily
true i think game convention finances work quite a bit differently to science fiction convention
conventions but like air con's only been running a decade and like admittedly it's big but it's in
harrogate convention center so it maybe gets for a games convention it's not that big and it has
someone working uh two days a week on it as salaried stuff yeah the um i always look at
folk festivals and the way they have moved from being um committee-run volunteer events to
largely company they vary a lot but companies limited by guarantee where at least one person
is getting paid for admin work and it's the same sort of thing that the amount of admin work has
become too large to have it operate on a voluntary basis and i don't really have a problem with the
idea of having someone paid to do that stuff i think that is probably sensible from the perspective
of from the perspective of not burning volunteers out like if you can have one or two people doing
work in that way that is probably something that will lighten your volunteer load in a good way
so i don't know and it's tricky right because there was a good discussion in anonymous claire
about how people feel about volunteering for kind of corporations and like you know there's a
consideration there where you don't want to give your voluntary time to a for-profit company to
help them make a bigger profit but you you know if if worldcon had paid for a day a week of like
the chair's time would that have meant the worldcon went smoothly for any given world more smoothly
for any given worldcon maybe it would have done and like i don't know whether there's the money
to do that but there might be it's an interesting thought experiment i think yeah and i wouldn't be
against it i just think you know if you think let's say let's say we try and employ you try
apply someone for two days a week in the uk minimum wage whatever you probably need about
10 grand which is yeah not insurmountable um but it means whatever you're doing needs to get
like 10 grand basically of surplus assuming that person is happy to be paid the minimum yeah yeah
i think you're probably right i think that's the absolute benefit but yeah i mean and it's a
consideration i don't know if it would work for easter cons because i don't but i think that
partly because we don't charge enough for easter con which is a conversation we keep coming back
to. I think the membership for East Con is stupidly cheap. Maybe we'll come back to it when you hire
someone. And of course there are many corporate structures in the UK for operating with a mixed
economy of paid staff and volunteers and indeed Mike Scott wrote to us to point out that two of
our emergency services, the lifeboats and mountain rescue, are almost entirely staffed by volunteers
Of course, both of those will have paid stuff as well and probably all be incorporated as charities.
But I do not know.
RNLI is a charity because they have charity shops.
Yeah, there's a lot of lifeboats that aren't RNLI though, which is something I only just discovered.
I bought something that was, this is raising funds for the Independent Lifeboat Association.
I was like, the what?
And there's hundreds of independent lifeboats.
I had no idea.
Interesting.
mountain rescue is a charitable incorporated organization listeners right in because i don't
know what the difference between that and charity is but the fact it doesn't say charity makes me
think there is one and let's move on from discussions of charities to the facebook
comments on 142 liz do you want to take the lead on those we also got some facebook comments on
our last episode thank you to everyone who was very nice about our stunt allison lorry um
Meg McDonald points out that Glasgow 2024 did have to issue an apology for the Hugo ceremony,
which I'd forgotten about, which was because there were mistakes in the Chinese captions on the slides,
which obviously I didn't notice at the time.
Meg says they had a crisis com plan and a complex coms triage and management process
for the number of issues that they had to communicate with members and the wider public,
which sounds very good.
Yes.
We also heard from Sheila La, who enjoyed Lori's ribbon story.
We got a comment from Lori Anderson, who likes the title of her episode.
We also heard from Ali Baker Brooks and Farrah Mendelsohn.
Mike Scott says, John, there were seven seasons of Deep Space Nine.
A message I know has been relayed to John through multiple channels.
But John, there were seven seasons of Deep Space Nine.
I didn't correct you at the time because I thought, no, I'll leave it for our listeners to write in.
And they did.
It's still too many.
That's like more than The Expanse, isn't it?
The Expanse is too many.
Just throw it up and finish The Expanse, Alison.
We are going to finish The Expanse.
you will
just not necessarily a 2025
I mean at some point you should just admit you don't like it and stop watching
oh hello
if it was just me I would have done that
alright anyway
there are seven series of Deep Space Nine
Roger Coulter wrote us another
letter of comment on the latest episode
to say that a follow up
he reached out to both LA and Montreal about volunteering
yay excellent
and that yes the pronunciation guide
for the Hugo should have been prepared
i have some guidelines from toastmasters about how you actually lay out uh a script so that you don't
end up missing anything you know you don't end up anything trailing over onto another page you don't
end up missing anything and that you should have it all in a binder which all sounds very sensible
yes i mean that's sort of what we talked about last time like but yeah you there's there's errors
that you can make there's errors that you can prevent in the layout process that will make
these things less likely to happen they won't make them impossible but they will make them less likely
what you want do we want to do the skeets as well got some skeets paul wemer skeeted to say he also
heard hugo road in the sound of the train bells on the way to the airport so it's clearly a thing
yes that's good i like that thank you for writing in paul we also sort of got a lot from gotham
butier to say that uh there is going to be a book set in the same world as the sentence and he is
working on it right now and that's very exciting um so yes looking forward to that and raj bought
the wrong book called the sentence um so yeah that is that is distressing i mean maybe that
one was good too right in raj let us know sorry raj
so listeners uh we think we probably can't record an episode next time so we have pre-recorded
a bonus episode for your enjoyment
and it is on the movie Dread.
So if you would like to watch
the movie Dread, then you will be well
prepared for our bonus episode.
And optionally, you can also
listen to Tansy Gardam's podcast
on Dread, which she released
slightly before our podcast on Dread
and is much better. But anyway, listen to us.
It's only, it's much better
in some ways, but she does prefer The Raid,
so she is wrong. Oh, I like The Raid though.
I haven't seen The Raid. Unfortunately,
Dread is not available for free streaming anywhere in the UK,
but you can rent it for £3.50 on the internet.
And it may be available in other territories for free.
It's available in my house for free because I have it on Blu-ray.
So everyone just come to my house.
Open invitation.
The art this time is an illustration by Arthur Thompson,
which has not previously been published.
It was the art for the column head of a Walt Willis column
in the issue of Hyphen that would have been the next one
if there had been another one, but there wasn't.
And I'm very glad that we have the opportunity to publish it now.
And it means that it will be eligible for best fanzine cover
in the fan awards,
were it not for the fact that we're not a fanzine, so it isn't.
But, you know, thank you very much, Adam,
for inadvertently doing us an Octothorpe cover.
Yes, hurrah.
And I've been meaning to use it for months,
so, you know, because I bought it to the Corflux auction.
It's a good bit of art. I like it.
One of the things that I missed as a result of not being here last week and you having to have a stunt Alison was that I missed being apoplectically angry about the Hugos and the result of it.
And now I've been in Germany for a few days chilling and drinking local beer and I'm not apoplectically angry anymore.
So, but at the time of recording, we still do not have any sort of apology for the mispronunciations.
I did draw a cover for you, though.
Yes, it was very good.
It had a Iron Throne made of Hugo Award, which was lovely.
I'm glad you knew what it was, because Stephen was like, I don't know what that is meant to be.
And I said, really?
Come on, Stephen.
Maybe I should draw better.
Maybe if I could draw better.
Listeners who look at the show notes will know that I put the alt text for the image in the show notes.
and so if you don't understand a reference it is often explained in the alt text in the show notes
so that is the the the way to find out if you're unsure fun fact sometimes john explains references
i didn't put in the picture oh what do you mean when what how does that work
you've said oh this is very funny because of x and i was like oh i had not realized i did x
i think that i am not it is a problem when the hosts mispronounce names on stage but accidents
happen mistakes are made and honestly the thing that affects my reaction much more is how quickly
you apologize and how sincere apology happens to or how sincere your apology appears to be
and if there had been a full apology on the sunday or the monday saying we are really sorry for the
people whose names were mispronounced and didn't read out on stage it was because of process errors
in the ceremony that we're going to address by talking to LA and Montreal about what they could
do differently and again we are really really sorry I'd be completely unfazed by this and sitting
here in a state of complete peace and calm but the fact that at the time of the recording it's now
been over two weeks since they made the mistake and that's what's making me really angry at this
point like say sorry you did you did wrong thing and you say sorry and the saying sorry is important
and it reflects onto the sort of person you are if you don't or the sort of organization you are
if you don't and i think that reflects badly on the hosts and on seattle at this point so i'm a
bit cross listeners but yeah that's basically the only update i have they'll probably have apologized
by the time this episode comes out though i swear to i hope they have yeah i think the reason i was
angry was because i knew because i'd worked on it that the um wussford's administration the
WSFUs division had collected all the pronunciation information and had passed that information to
events and the process of generating a ceremony had failed to generate the sort of scripts that
Frederick Coulter mentioned earlier with all the names embedded in it which seems to me to be
a key part of the job that you wouldn't not do that bit that's why I was angry so I'm still
channeling kind of leftover anger there i don't think we have anything else on seattle's apology
and stuff like another thing at seattle that caused consternation was so the chair of the
mark protection committee donald eastlake the third attended a mark protection committee meeting
at seattle um having tested positive for covid and proceeded to take his mask off in the meeting
and was then asked to leave the convention.
File 770 has a post about this where Donald answers questions.
He says, I'm not sure this was a code of conduct violation.
There is a separate health policy that I had not read.
The health policy says, even if you do not feel sick, which I did not,
if you have tested positive for COVID, please do not attend.
It is my fault for not reading the health policy in advance
or otherwise really realizing the error in what I did.
So I'm going to say that I don't think, maybe I'm off base here,
but if you've tested positive for COVID or flu,
or you strongly suspect you have norovirus,
and you go to a convention in that knowledge,
then you, that's bad.
And I feel like I'm insane, because I'm like,
I thought we knew that was bad.
Did we not know that was bad?
This did a giggle, which is why I've like my voice has gone up.
But yeah, like if you've got COVID.
Yeah, I'm trying to think of like,
apparently we need to put in the code of conduct
that violating the health policy and coming in.
Well, you know, you have COVID.
It's a violation of the code of conduct.
But it's like if I was projectile vomiting
and decided to come into the convention,
then I think that would be a code of conduct violation.
Like even if it wasn't explicitly written in the code of conduct.
If you have mumps, if you have measles, if you have whooping cough, also don't go to the convention.
Like, this isn't a COVID thing.
It's like, it's a disease.
Like, if you are confirmed diseased.
Diphtheria, tuberculosis, leprosy.
Oh, God.
Like, I don't want to disenfranchise people, but I think discriminating on the basis of disease vector is reasonable.
yeah and i mean we've had loads of conversations about in this current era there are some discussion
about whether people with symptoms which could be the symptoms of an infectious disease but are not
necessarily and they don't appear to have an infectious disease whether you should come to
the con or not but we're not even in that territory we're in the territory of you definitely have it
and you thought i'll come to a meeting and take my mask off it's just weird don't understand it
I'm so cross, but I'm also so confused that it's undercutting my crossness.
I can't understand it to such an extent it makes me laugh rather than making me want to yell.
Well, I think the thing that I find strange is why would somebody...
If you want to carry on attending the convention despite the fact that you might have COVID,
the thing to do is to not test, right?
Why would somebody test and then go, oh, I've had a positive test,
but I'll carry on doing just what I was going to do anyway?
what was it was it in the covid was it 2021 where it was it was it was reporter six at an american
convention who tested positive on the thursday and then there was a massive list of all the places
they had been after testing positive i can't remember which convention it was i remember we
talked about it on the pod there was there was a us convention i think it i don't know if it was
discord or maybe it was like one of the other cons um that was reported these but yeah it was like
person well they were positive and they went to all these things and then thought they'd mention
it later oh i was positive i better report that uh but yeah yeah anyway john i think you are missing
out i think you've missed out the best part uh which is that donald eastlake was re-elected as
the chair of the moral protection committee i want to know from the minutes who voted to re-elect him
because i think someone with that level of i have worked with donald eastlake and i have thought
that he was not a particularly switched on person for a while but i think if you voted to confirm
of his chair after this like you need your head examined for covid well if you were there and
you re-elected him you should probably at the least go and take a rapid test yeah
it was noted on blue sky and this was actually long enough ago at 13 27 on the 21st of august
2025 wayo de old bear did a post on blue sky basically pointing out that the los angeles world
con had some theming on its website which was reminiscent of westward expansion and manifest
destiny um so they were referring to their guests as pioneers they were referring to their venue as
the frontier um the con newsletter was called the telegram and they had like a picture of a mission
in one of the icons on their menu um and i don't i don't i don't think that's a completely exhaustive
list but i do think it's it's it's kind of it gets most of the problems that were noted um later that
day there was a statement from the la con 5 chair joyce lloyd which um basically said it starts with
la con 5 apologizes for using words and icons that connote western expansion and the displacement
and colonization of indigenous peoples this does not reflect the vision or values of the convention
and at the point that statement was made which i think was about 12 hours after the original skeet
la had completely removed those things from their website it was it was incredibly fast reaction
and then actually um weo the old bear who had been the person who originally noted it skeet is saying
that they were genuinely happy and surprised to see a change in an apology and they tweeted
or sorry they skeeted that on the 21st of august at 1944 so the original skeet was 13 27 and the
follow-up was 1944 which is a six-hour turnaround so i'd done them dirty i'd said it took them twice
as long to respond as it had compare and contrast listeners um six hours versus the 14 times 24
336 hours it has taken seattle to apologize uh for their fuck up and i wanted to talk about this
a little bit because it wasn't good that la con did this and i don't think i think one thing i
want to say is like this website had been up for over a year at the point that this was noticed and
no one else had picked up on it and there must have been lots of fans who visited that website
who did not notice that this was a problem but as soon as it was pointed out that it was a problem
la con made damn sure it stopped being a problem and apologized for the fact that they had screwed
up very quickly very thoroughly very comprehensively and i think this reflects really well on la con
because you can't not make mistakes but the kind of convention you are comes out in how you react
and la con has done itself proud here i think yeah i mean i think this is right because you do kind
of go well how did they decide to use that theming in the first place because there's been problems
with Westercons in the past using that sort of theming and getting not unreasonably hammered for
it. So you'd have thought it would still be in the memory, but fair do. So basically, they saw the
problem, they sorted it out straight away, and that's great. Well done, Eloicon. So they clearly
have a good system for managing escalation and apology, which, you know, if you're a newly seated
Worldcon, I'm looking at you, Montreal, you need, is the sort of thing that you need to be setting
in place quite early because you never know when something's going to go wrong but something will
go wrong yeah i mean i don't i don't want to make it sound you know i think we're complimenting a
lake on on their fast reaction but you know we should be clear that they did do this and one of
the issues with the fact that someone reported it in a skeet is that it that is still going to spread
even after you have corrected the problem right like i'm sure that initial skeet probably went on
being re-skeeted and passed around the internet for quite some time even after the person who
it would have you know noted that they'd apologize because that's just how the internet happens so
you know you're better off not doing it but yeah well done on like very quickly taking it down
because i think it was down even even before the apology i think i went to look and it's like oh
those those bits of the page have gone no i mean you're certainly right that it would have been
better had it not happened and um i think you are also right that people did continue to talk about
it after it had been apologized for but i will say that like it's been a week and most people
have completely moved on whereas the anger over seattle has just sort of grown and grown and grown
um so i do think apologizing quickly does help but also like yeah you can't choose you also can't
choose how people will continue to discuss it but you can just make sure that you do all you can to
do the right thing it's tricky because i understand i do understand how that happened because it is
the the history of california if you are celebrating california's history um then it is very wrapped up
in those things so i understand how if you are focusing on that and not the cultural aspect you
might make this mistake but i'm glad they unmade it it is not a coincidence that british world cons
tend not to celebrate british history because ho ho there are some minefields in there better better
to avoid that uh yeah i spent some time in australia and in particular and at australian
historical sites where they've had to do an incredible amount of work to end up with a site
that is really respectful of all of the people involved in the in what was going on in historical
times and and doing it in a way that has made everybody mostly content largely content i think
i mean i will say and i've just checked and i was right about this that the the 2005 world con in the
uk did have an entire academic thread which was called the matter of britain about the kind of
portrayal of britain in science fiction fantasy yeah but twitter and facebook were both founded
after that so i mean yeah but you can obviously it can be done and it can be done carefully and well
but i guess the most recent ones have strayed away from that probably can be done not sure it's worth
The risk.
So, as expected, since they were the only bid,
the 2027 Worldcon has been awarded to Montreal.
They have put up some minimal information on their website,
including the guests of honour,
who are Joel Walton, Eve Maynard, Chris Barkley,
and they said more,
but I think they've already announced Jeff Jack
as their guest of honour.
That all seems good.
Their website is still a bit rubbish
and I don't know who is actually in the committee
or anything like that.
But they do have a website
and you can register for a membership.
And yeah, their guests of honour, I think, are pretty good.
You're in Montreal.
Having an author who writes in French
is a good thing to have.
I'm excited by Jo Walton.
She does good science fiction.
But I'm very excited by Geoff Jakes.
I think that's how you pronounce it
because the subtitling rendered it Jakes,
like J-A-K-E-S.
And I was initially like, who on earth?
And it spelt Jeff with a double F.
So I was like, who is Jeff Jakes?
And then I worked out what must have happened.
I've always assumed it was Jakes.
No, because I just don't know.
So maybe I assume it's Jakes then.
I think it's Jeff Jakes.
I might be wrong, but I thought it was Jeff Jakes.
And I don't know why I think that.
I've been a fan of Jeff Jakes' work for a long time.
I read all of Alice Grove as it was coming out and questionable content is effectively the only
webcomic that I've been reading I mean at this point I must have been reading it for over 2000
days right because I think I came in at about strip 100 and I think he's on about strip 2500 now
but I've always been a huge QC fan and so I am I'm really excited by this because QC is definitely
science fiction and um i think it's a really imaginative choice and a very canadian choice
so i'm i'm well i'm well enthused it's a great great pick i think we should have a sweepstakes
on the number of days of questionable content they have been oh is it oh no is it like 5 000
5 646 john oh so i've been reading it for how many how many years is that a long time yeah no
I've been reading it for 15 years, listeners.
About 23 days in strip time.
I mean, I think it's been at least a year.
Yeah, it has.
Questionable content doesn't move very fast,
but it has become much more science fictional lately.
I think early in the strip,
it wasn't very obvious what the SF elements were,
but now, of course, it is completely.
The main character lives with an AI, Allison.
Clearly science fiction.
Don't we all?
I'm going to say I am also very excited about Jeff Jakes
and I am very excited about Joe Walton,
who, of course, has been a friend for a long time.
So that's lovely.
And I'm sure the other two guests are lovely too.
Are you excited about any of these guests, Liz?
Yes, but I want us to get to picks.
Sorry.
Liz, do you want to pick first?
Yes, why don't I pick first?
I am going to pick a book.
I am going to pick the book Luminous by Sylvia Park,
which is a debut science fiction novel.
It is about three siblings in Korea.
This is a Korea which has been unified between North and South Korea
and also a Korea where they have highly advanced robots,
which in many ways may be indistinguishable from humans, or are they not?
It's basically all about sibling relationships and family relationships.
And apparently I keep picking books about family relationships,
but it is also about the idea of robots and what it means to be human and what it means to be a
robot. I think it has a very nice aspect here where Jun, who is one of the siblings, is a trans man
and Jun was injured during the reunification war between North and South Korea and as part of that
has many kind of constructed parts which also act in a way as giving Jun like the body he always
wanted to have and so that I thought was a really interesting kind of modern twist on what is maybe
not the most maybe not the most modern of stories you know there's many many stories about you know
robots and humanity and what it means to be a robot but I thought it had a really good setting
and kind of definitely had some interesting aspects to it that I hadn't seen before so I enjoyed it
um I think Sylvia Park is probably a candidate for the astounding award unless they've published
too many short stories before which is possible but i think it's a great debut novel i really
enjoyed it that sounds that sounds really interesting i think that's on my big list of
things to read i suspect it will be submitted for the clark award i think so yeah has been published
in britain yeah so i will probably read it when it gets submitted yeah okay now i think i think uh
Sylvia Park has two previous short stories and so is therefore not eligible for the standing award
which unfortunately I think it's a solid choice it looks like Sylvia Park also wrote a short story
for Tor.com which is in the same uh universe so you might want to uh you can probably read that
oh hello what's that called so this is a 2019 story called more real than him which I think
you could give that a read and yet it is certainly similar to the world and the setting of the the
novels if you like that you might like the novel i'll put it in the show notes alison do you want
to do a pick i'm struggling here so a couple of weeks ago my daughter said i said to my daughter
what have you been doing and she was like well i've been playing a lot of slay the spire and
obviously i played a lot of slay the spire a long time ago but i appear to have fallen back into a
slay the spire hole for no particularly good reason so i'm going to pick slay the spire which i'm
I haven't picked before but somebody else might check for me which is an iOS game and many other
things game PC game Steam game everywhere game that lots of people have already played but
apparently it's one of those games that you can keep playing a lot even after you think you've
finished it because there's more and it is a card-based deck building roguelike so you know
I apparently I do these things where every so often I fall down a rabbit hole of one of these
and just play it until it's played out.
You are trying to explore a spire,
but really you're just hitting things and doing damage.
I mean, you know, stuff like that.
Trying not to die.
Dying, starting again.
That's not much of a pick, is it?
But otherwise, I've just been in Germany doing German things.
I don't know.
Continuing to be addicted to slay the spire seems good.
Yeah, yeah.
No, no, but I stopped being addicted to slay the spire
for months and years.
Years.
It's been years.
but apparently you could fall off the wagon and and just just you know go oh i'll just play one
game for old time's sake we had a lot of travel on thursday like our many many many hours of travel
so it was quite nice for that but the rest of the time i'm like no i could be reading new things and
doing new things and playing new games why am i playing old games why am i playing old games
readers write in i am going to pick a game but i'm going to pick a tabletop game
And I'm going to pick a game called Flick Fleet.
So Flick Fleet is a science fiction game.
It is published by Eurydice Games, although it is very funny to listen to a lot of people call it Eurydice Games.
So, yeah, and it's designed by Jackson Pope and Paul Wilcox.
I shall disclaim that I was provided with a review copy of the deluxe based game.
But I bought the first expansion with my own cash because it had asteroids.
And so FlickFly is a game where you play the Imperium or the Uprising, which are, you know, legally distinct terms.
And you build lists of ships.
Each ship costs some points.
You build a list with a certain number of points.
And then you do battle.
So far, so space war game.
The interesting thing about Flick Fleet is that instead of rolling dice to see how well you shoot,
you put a dice on your ship and you flick it towards the enemy.
And if it hits the enemy, do damage based on what the dice rolled.
And the other interesting thing is that you move your ships by flicking them as well.
So it's a dexterity game.
But it's a very well thought out dexterity game.
It's made by a man called Paul in his garage in Leeds on his laser cutter.
And it's just really good.
It's been out for a while, but it's sort of been getting more and more kind of word of mouth and traction.
It's been given a must play by Tabletop Gaming Magazine.
And it's really interesting.
It's not quite like anything else I've ever played.
And so I do like it.
And you can play a game in like 20 minutes.
So yeah, it's really cool.
I highly recommend looking it up, listeners.
We will put a link in the show notes.
Sounds good.
So is it literally a man cutting all the bits up in his garage and posting to you?
Yeah.
Wow.
And each box you buy has a handwritten note from him in the lid of the box
saying that he hopes your battle against the Imperium goes well
and has a number out of the number that they made.
Oh.
Oh, that's great.
Yeah.
It's very...
I mean, and I will also say,
Even if you have no desire to ever play the game, listeners,
you should go and check out the box art on BoardGameGeek
because if you ever wanted to see Chris Foss-esque illustrations
of giant ghostly hands flicking dice into spaceships,
then the box art of this series of games is the box art for you.
I've often thought my life is lacking in Chris Foss-esque spaceships
being flicked around by giant otherworldly hands.
I do often say that, don't I, John?
You do. You do indeed, Liz.
It's one of your catchphrases.
Hmm.
And that was the Octothaw Podcast.
And it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
Did I ever tell you about the time that Chris and I had two dinners?
Has there really only been one time like that?
Yeah, I think so.
Chris took me for Chinese food.
I mean, you haven't explicitly said this, but it's not sounding particularly surprising.
I thought it was going to be an amusing anecdote, but you guys are just like,
that sounds like the sort of thing that would just happen any dinner.
And I'm like, well, fair enough.
No, no, no.
Any dinner involving you and Chris Garcia.
Therefore, it is an amusing anecdote.
Go on, carry on.
It's not.
It's just they used to be this Chinese place near Chris's old house that did like an amazing peanut oil on their dumplings, which you can sort of replicate by frying peanut butter in olive oil, but not quite.
But we went there for dinner and then he was like, we should go somewhere else and have steak sandwiches now.
And so we immediately after a full Chinese meal got in his car and drove and ate steak sandwiches.
And I'll be honest, that was a struggle.
It was a struggle I was willing to endure, but it was a struggle nonetheless.
Witness my hardship, listeners, and despair.
Ah, yeah.
The theme music for this episode was Surf Shimmy by Kevin MacLeod and Combatech.com,
used under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.