Can you turn off your virtual background just because I like to see the cat?
One, two, three.
Okay, that'll do.
Right.
John, the cat behind you, whichever one it is, like when you did the clap, the little head came up.
And then they were like, oh, nothing's going on. I'll put my head back down again.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to the ninth episode of the Octothorpe podcast, a podcast about science fiction and SF fandom.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And this week we have letters of comment that have arrived since the previous episode.
And we actually have three letters of comment, a comment of comment and a reciprocal letter of comment, sort of.
So, firstly, Helena McCallum writes in to say that you can send locks if you're not called Mark or Andrew.
I like this is a sort of meta letter of comment in that it's telling us a thing and also doing that thing at the same time.
So I approve.
But we had, in fact, already had letters of comment from Claire.
Yes, that is true.
Who is not called Andrew or Mark.
But we had a lot of Marks and a lot of Andrews.
I think there are now an equal number of letters of comment from people called Mark, people called Andrew and women.
And that may be something we want to address at some point.
Maybe we need to be diversifying our listenership.
We're like the board of directors of a company, aren't we?
Yeah.
Graham Charnock used to berate his female readers every episode about their inability to write letters of comment to his fanzine vibrator.
Yeah, that seems...
I tell you what, there are some coolest people out there in the world.
I think we will be coming on to that later.
Mark, someone called Mark, did also send us a letter of comment to keep us in letters of comment from people called Mark.
And he says that he is most disappointed that we had omitted letters of comment from people called Mark.
And he accuses me of having transitioned from the Mark Protection Committee to the Mark Neglection League.
So I would like to publicly apologise to all Marks and to admit that I have not done a good enough job of protecting their feelings and their opinions.
And I will rededicate myself to the Mark Protection Committee from this day forth.
Well said.
He also says that he thinks I'm wrong about the Worcester's business meeting and perhaps a bare minimum business meeting is the right way to go,
given the state of the world at the moment and the amount of work the Con Zealand Committee are probably doing to make Con Zealand happen.
And that is a good point.
Yes.
So basically he agrees with me on that.
He says,
Alison and Liz,
I don't mean to neglect you,
but you seemed pretty clear that you're holding.
Dr.
Hugo Award finalist Mark neglecting the boy coxswain responsible here.
Keep on casting.
So props to you two.
All of the criticism directed in my direction.
Correctly.
Yes.
I mean,
I can't say it.
I can't say it's not reasonable.
However,
I had some vitriolic criticism directed this my way this fortnight from one Lillian Edwards,
who accused me of accused all three of us of not mentioning her new podcast.
This never happens,
which she is doing with Christina Laker and Ian Sorenson.
And there will be a link in the show notes.
It's very good.
You should go and listen to it.
And we are not.
We are completely unapologetic about the fact that we did not mention this podcast last time because we recorded our previous episode on the 17th of June.
And she released the podcast to the world on the 18th of June.
So we would have to have been more than usually prescient to have mentioned it.
So Lillian,
tough.
We are mentioning it now.
Is that good enough?
I claim my five pounds.
I mean,
what I like about that is that you addressed her criticism with tact and kindness in a way that definitely won't stoke any fires.
So that's good.
Isn't stoking fires what it's all about?
It could well be.
So and also,
I think the other Mark asked us to say when we're recording and we're recording this one on Sunday,
the 5th of July,
and it'll go out on Wednesday,
the 8th of July.
Unless it doesn't.
Yes.
All being well.
Unless it doesn't.
Why this podcast is not late.
It turns out to be easier to get podcasts out on time than fanzines,
which is something I had not realised.
I mean,
so I'm just going to say,
and obviously this comes from a place of love,
but I suspect it is also easier to get podcasts out when you have your co-host do the editing of the podcast.
On time.
Yes.
How many podcasts,
how many fanzines have you done,
Professor the Boycoxon?
Me?
A few.
Off the top of my head.
On time.
What is time?
Time is an illusion.
Fanzines doubly so.
Time is fleeting.
So Claire wrote us a letter of comment.
Claire Briarley wrote us a letter of comment to commend us for pronouncing her surname correctly,
and said she was going to be quieter this week also.
So, yes.
Thank you, Claire.
Please send your Clara Hughes on the topic of Claire Briarley to octothorpecast at gmail.com.
Oh, no.
That's such a terrible joke.
Or, in fact, any other regular correspondent.
Finally, two of us were at the first Thursday meeting on the first Thursday,
and Crazy Dave told us that he listens to this podcast at two and a half times speed.
So, we are curious to know whether he is the fastest podcast listener in our audience.
So, if you are listening at greater than two and a half times speed,
please write in and let us know.
And also tell us how on earth you managed to make sense of what's going on,
because I tried it.
I just, I know what we're saying, and I can't hear it.
So.
Whenever I listen to podcasts, I listen at normal speed, or sometimes 1.1,
but normally normal speed, because I feel that podcasts are designed to entertain,
and if they're not entertaining at regular speed, I'll go off and find one that is.
Don't tell people that.
They'll stop listening to our podcast, Alison.
They can listen.
You're very welcome to listen to this podcast.
It's good, though.
Imagine if you could listen to, like, rambling chats in the bar at 2.5 times speed.
There would no longer be sort of, like, four hours of rambling chat over a pint.
It would be like a breezy one-hour discussion.
Yes, and you would be taking shots of vodka to replicate.
I feel that Zoom has missed a trick here.
What, because it doesn't come with vodka?
No, no, Zoom needs smart speed.
I'm in this Zoom chat, but it's really a bit boring.
Let's speed it up a bit.
The details for my guff trip are all taking shape,
and I will be on it next time,
so we may have to organise when to record
in a way that ties in with my virtually swimming off the Great Barrier Reef
or something like that.
I've got lots of plans to go spend time in bars
with people who are not required to social distance,
though I don't know to what extent things are really back to normal
in Australia and New Zealand.
I think they are more back to normal, except in Melbourne,
which is one of the main places I'm going,
which has had another outbreak,
so who knows what's going to happen.
And anyway, so you will get my next report from not Australia,
but virtually Australia.
And I will tell you all about the exciting things I'm doing there
as part of the first part of reporting on a virtual guff trip.
So when does your virtual guff trip begin, Alison?
It starts on the 11th, which is really not very long.
Oh, wow, less than a week.
I've got, yeah, less than a week.
And normally I'd be like panicking and packing at this point,
but in fact I'm actually doing all the stuff I didn't get around to earlier
because as it's virtual it's easier, I hope, to get it all sorted.
Fair enough.
And on your, so when, so you're starting on the 11th,
when does your virtual trip come to a close?
Well, I'm, I finish with Con Zealand and then I will be not flying home.
And I think that's, that's the time we actually have to sort out a recording
because I think I'm, I'm going to not stay with Liz on my way home
and we're going to not, we're going to record Octothorpe
as if I was in Liz's living room.
So that won't be the next one.
It'll be the one after, I think, after Con Zealand.
And you'll be going, how, what was your,
what were your impressions of virtual Con Zealand?
And I'll be going, I am completely knackered and my eyes are square now.
Yes, that's fair.
So there will be more firm details about our live from Alison's trip home recording
in the next episode.
So keep your eyes peeled for that.
Shall we talk about Con Zealand?
We often do, but yes, let's do it again.
I saw a tweet several weeks ago, which I have now lost,
but it was that Con Zealand were looking for people to help with access
and specifically the issues of access,
which would come up when you are a virtual convention,
which I think is quite interesting because it feels like we're starting to get a handle
on what conventions can do to make themselves more accessible to people who are actually at the convention.
But obviously moving online is going to bring a whole new set of issues.
And I'd be interested to know if you have any thoughts on them,
if you've been to any virtual conventions or meetups,
which did think about ways to make them more accessible to people who find it difficult
to access virtual conventions.
And any other thoughts on the matter?
Well, it's funny you should say this.
So I've been doing First Thursday meetups for London fans.
When we started, we very quickly noticed that we were getting quite a lot of people attending
who could not attend the first Thursday in person,
sometimes for reasons of distance,
which is not actually a primary accessibility issue for what we think of as being a local London pub meeting.
So it's nice that these people can now come,
but it's not what I think of as the most important accessibility issue for the thing.
But we also have had people visiting who cannot normally attend the meeting,
either because they do not like crowded pubs or they cannot get up the stairs.
And so that is so having those people there is very welcome.
We have then since then been trying to do outreach.
And we've done this on a very individual basis.
And we are and we've done outreach to the people who we know normally attend the first Thursday meetings,
but have not been attending the Zoom meetings.
We've had a range of responses.
So some of them have come and tried it and some of them quite like it.
Some of them have tried Zoom,
but concluded that they don't like large Zooms,
even if we do the breakout room thing,
that they are preferring their,
even though they might quite enjoy conventions,
they are preferring to do the interactive meetups in smaller groups.
Some people are still struggling with the technology.
People who are deaf are highly disenfranchised from most of this virtual life that we are living now.
It is much worse than a regular pub meeting would be.
And often also than the formal panels and presentations at conventions.
They are finding it harder.
It is harder to lip read.
It is harder to manage the complexity of conversation where several people are in a room.
And that's about all I have on it.
So some people don't like Zoom.
Some people can't manage Zoom.
Some people have disabilities that are more or differently disabling in a Zoom environment.
But, you know, it's something that we've given some thought to.
And actually, for a lot of the older people,
just helping them individually get into this way of working is the thing that's most useful.
So, yeah.
So the thing that popped into my head immediately was the problem that you'd have if you were hard of hearing with this kind of technology.
And I think one of the reasons I got quite annoyed at the Hugo ceremony in Dublin because they had the automatic subtitles.
People were laughing when they got it wrong.
But the problem with that is that it means that they said, oh, we should not have used automatic subtitles because they were inviting people to find them funny.
And I kind of thought that maybe when we see automatic subtitles that are inadvertently saying the wrong things,
we need to shut the hell up and remember that these subtitles are there as an accessibility feature for deaf people
and not laugh in a way that means that convention committees want to take that away for the deaf community.
So my thought, Susan, is that one, you are quite right that if we see something on automatic subtitles,
we do need to remember, look, these are here for a purpose.
It's there to help people.
And we shouldn't, you know, we should try not to react in that way because it's not helpful.
And that I can see that when you're doing an all online convention, there are auto subtitling options that might help.
But my second thought is that for big events like the Hugos, you should really be paying for a live captioner because these problems will not happen.
And we know that is possible.
It takes money, but it doesn't take enormous, vast amounts of money that WorldCom's cannot allocate to it.
And that would have solved that particular problem.
I think in smaller groups, that is less of a problem because I think the problem with the Hugos is one person finds it a bit funny
and then everyone around them starts to realise what they're laughing about and that spreads.
So maybe that's not a problem if it's only 30 people watching live captioning of a panel or so on.
But I was slightly surprised that they used the auto subtitling option for the Hugos instead of going with a person in the auditorium or elsewhere doing it for them.
That's fair.
I think that's a good point.
I think that's less relevant to a virtual thing because the people who need automatic subtitling will use it.
I also feel that laughing at automatic subtitling is the equivalent of laughing at a presenter whose first language is not English or who has a spasticity that means that they can't form words or move in a normal way.
And it's completely reprehensible.
communicating.
You're clearly laughing at someone who has feelings, whereas laughing at an automatic transcription doesn't have a victim in quite the way.
It doesn't have as obvious a victim.
And so I think it is much easier to laugh at that because it doesn't feel like you're being cruel.
So I see why people might laugh at one and not the other.
But yeah, I think Liz's point about the Hugos, especially being able to afford a person to do it, which would not necessarily run into the same problems.
Especially as award ceremonies often have a lot of text, which is pre-written and can just be spewed out.
You don't have to live caption anything except the acceptance speeches.
Yes, and it means you can send them the names of all the finalists in advance.
They could have put that into the automatic transcription software too, just saying.
I actually had another subsidiary point about the other thing Alison said.
I was just going to say that obviously the first Thursday mechanism of individually contacting members who are having trouble and helping them in a one-to-one setting scales poorly to Worldcon levels of attendance.
OK, here's how you do it.
You ask people to talk to their friends who are having trouble and you also encourage local things like the first Thursday to happen because if those things are happening in lots of different places, that is a way to preload lots of people.
So you encourage the grassroots activity that's required.
In fact, Con Zealand, I think, are doing training sessions to get people familiar with their platforms before the con, which I think is a great way of doing it.
And that is also going to open up access.
So you can log in.
You'll be able to log in, I think, to their Discord and things and check them out ahead of time to make sure your chosen device is going to work nicely with everything.
And so you don't spend the first day of your convention trying to fiddle with Zoom, I guess.
Have they announced this?
Or have they just, is this just one of these, we are intending to do this stuff?
Because I've just, I finally got around to filling in my programme participant form.
Sorry, Jenny.
You had sent it to me and I am just terrible.
You are the bane of programme.
You are the bane of programme heads everywhere, Alison.
And it has a thing saying, would you like to moderate a panel?
And I said, if you insist, because I know that although I'm not the world's best moderator, there's always a shortage of female moderators.
And I think that it is better to have less good female moderators than better male moderators.
Controversial opinion.
And so and then they said, would you be happy to attend a training session?
And I was kind of like, yes, of course.
But they do have to fit that training session in around my virtual guff trip.
And so time is getting tight.
Tighter than usual, I feel, for the Worldcon.
There are a few things where I'm kind of like, oh, you're cutting it a bit fine now.
I thought they had said this, but now I mention it.
Of course, I cannot actually find any of the information on it.
Or did they email it to me?
That might be it.
It is interesting.
Since we have started podcasting, I have become much more interested in conventions, official lines of communication,
because that is how I try and find out what conventions are doing.
And so whenever there is something I know about a convention that is not in their official line of communication,
I'm like, why have you not put this on your website in a place that it is easy to find?
Conventions often put quite a lot of control over their official communication routes in a way that makes it hard for, say,
area heads to actually get in there and amend the things for their own area rapidly.
So you can often have area heads who are very happy to keep the information for their area up to date,
who are prevented from doing so by the broader controls over what goes on the website.
And it is not a stupid thing to do.
There are arguments on both sides of this.
But my view is that if you trust somebody to be an area head,
you should probably trust them to update their web page too.
I have now found the announcement and it was in my email.
And it probably says something about me that I immediately tried to find it on Facebook and Twitter
and their official page before I just went and read the email, which I read this afternoon.
But yes, it does say you can ask if there's a form to fill in if you would like to have some live training on Discord,
which I think is a great initiative.
I think it is a great initiative.
I will point out that anyone who has not joined New Zealand because they feel they cannot use the technology
is perhaps in need of this being announced more widely than emails to people who have joined God Zealand.
I'm not technically a God Zealand member.
I'm just on their mailing list of people who have expressed interest at some point.
So it maybe is going to a wider group there.
Yeah, and point well taken.
Actually, interestingly, as a Con Zealand member, I did not get this email.
So, you know, I think that all of these things make sense in terms of how Worldcon divisions are put together.
And they are all volunteers doing these jobs.
And like it all I completely see how all of this has happened.
But I do think at some point there needs to be a little bit of a thought about whether or not these are sensible structures
and whether or not there is a better way to structure these things.
I realise that as someone who is identifying this problem and not volunteering for a Worldcon,
not that I'm definitely part of the precipitate in this regard in that I am not part of the solution.
But.
Shall we talk about Hugo voting?
Yeah, it hasn't started yet.
I have had informal conversations with people who may not may or may not be connected with the people who have to actually count up the Hugos who are like,
we think the time is now getting quite tight for for the management of the Hugo voting.
So this is my question, because I well, I agree that the time is getting very tight for the Hugo voting since it is not open yet.
And they're going to present them at the end of the month.
But also, I do not know how many people actually vote throughout the voting process and how many people try and log in 10 minutes before the end of voting and frantically vote for everything.
So I don't know whether this delay will actually be, you know,
lowering the number of Hugo votes or just compressing everything into a two week window when it would probably be compressed into anyway.
This is this is my question, because when people were discussing this, I was like,
I can see that having fewer votes is a problem, but it was less clear to me whether or not this would end up in there being less votes, if that makes sense.
So, yeah, I completely see your point.
It also prevents you from doing neat little things like having the best Hugo, best novel Hugo presented by a female astronaut and other tricks like this.
It's quite useful to have the Hugos in the bag well before the World Cup.
It used to be that this would have been completely impossible because the process of Hugo voting involved a voting phase and then a counting phase that was long and extremely complicated.
And I believe that now that we have very few postal votes, the counting phase is very quick.
But people are still entitled to vote by post and they cannot do that.
So they can.
They can.
The paper ballots have been up since the nominees were announced.
It is only the online voting that is not available.
Sorry that that ruins the rant.
In that case, ignore me.
I'm talking rot, but it's still impossible because you can't actually post anything to New Zealand with any confidence it will arrive at the moment.
So, you know.
Oh, yeah.
I do.
I do sort of think that if you're casting a postal vote across the Pacific Ocean during COVID-19, that may not be the most reliable mechanism.
But yes.
I like that COVID-19 is quite like the 2019 Hugos and that it's voted and awarded in 2020.
Tim, this is an interesting, this is an ecumenical matter.
The 2020 Hugos are awarded in 2020 for works in 2019.
That's right.
Sorry, these things vary quite a lot.
I think it's the 2019 Oscars, isn't it?
I never know these things.
Everyone does it differently.
There is no consensus.
It is quite interesting in that it is clear that they will get it together, we think.
But if they don't get it together, it's going to be spectacular.
I think there's quite a big risk that they get it together in between when we record this and when the show is released.
So, well done, guys.
That was well-timed to mess up our podcast.
They have announced that voting will open no later than Wednesday, the 8th of July.
So, it should be open by the time this podcast is released.
I'm not sure it's going to be a problem in practice because I don't think really you need a voting period that's longer than a week.
It'll be fine.
They'll award the Hugos.
I do feel a bit sorry for the guys who have to engrave the names on the bases as well.
But they're probably used to this sort of thing.
But that's actually fine because all the Hugos will be being shipped around the world.
And so, they don't necessarily have to be ready and engraved on the day of the Hugo ceremony.
The introduction of the E Pluribus Hugo, let's make the Hugo voting quite complicated amendment,
also means that you absolutely have to do the whole thing digitally anyway and have software that you've run seven or eight times to check it actually works.
So, I assume that when you just close Hugo voting and then you push a button and then ten minutes later you have the results.
But maybe that's hopefully optimistic.
Fingers crossed.
That also perceivably means that the paper votes are transmitted, are data entried into the digital system.
I'm pretty sure.
That's certainly how I would do it if I were a group of Hugo administrators.
And that is not in any way a job application, guys.
I've now listened to all the best fancasts so that I can write an article for the Glasgow 2024 bid is running some articles on Hugo slates.
And one of them is best fancast and I'm writing about it.
So, we can talk about that next time if you like.
A crossover.
But I will be plugging this podcast there, obviously.
And I can plug Glasgow 2024.
They're going to be a great convention.
Glasgow is a wonderful place to go to for the Worldcon.
You should vote for them.
Does that mean I should listen to all the best fancasts?
At 2.5 speed, obviously.
Yes, it does make me laugh that next episode will be the only episode we record other than this one before the close of voting.
So, we gave an hour to Best Dramatical Log Form.
And then we're going to give an hour to all other Hugo categories, which is...
Yes, that's our topic for next time.
All the Hugos in an hour.
Starting from here.
Yeah.
All of them.
We could probably do it.
We just do like a minute per category instead of a minute per finalist.
Or we could have like an extra...
Or we could have an extra long episode where we talk about all of the categories.
And people have to...
And Crazy Dave has to run it at 4.6 speed.
How much of our, like, Star Wars, Marvel debate did you cut out of that episode, John?
Because if you think about it...
I don't think the rest will be as contentious.
I think we all agree.
No, I'm not going to start the argument.
If you can find a topic on which we all agree we have failed in our podcast setting up arrangements.
The other thing we need to talk about with regard to New Zealand is the colonised, marginalised and historically underrepresented people inclusion initiative, which Liz knows about.
So Con Zealand had a previous scholarship, which was for people from marginalised communities to attend Con Zealand in person.
And so it was aimed at people who were in New Zealand, particularly those who identified as Maori, Pacifica, people of Kura, LGBTQI or disabled.
And I'm wondering if this is now an initiative to expand that, given that they're now an online convention where you don't need to be there in person.
So presumably adding people to the virtual convention is less of an issue because you don't have limits on your venue capacity.
And also your kind of marginal costs are minimal.
It's just kind of expanding your online activities and making sure you have the people support for them.
And so they have a new membership upgrade initiative to support the inclusion of colonised, marginalised and historically underrepresented people at Wellcome, which I think is great because that will hopefully allow a lot more people to attend virtually from a lot more different places.
Even more so than when it was actually going to be physically in New Zealand.
So I think this is a great initiative.
It sounds like a good initiative.
Like, obviously, I think inclusion in conventions is a thing that is really important.
And we've talked before about how virtual conventions can be a way to achieve that.
And it sounds like this initiative is kind of putting that into practice in a way, which I think is really good.
It's pretty exciting, actually.
And as I've had numerous conversations with people who are unable to attend Con Zealand because of the cost of doing it, some of those people are marginalised or from groups that will probably be represented by this.
And we should put a link in the show notes and we should also let everyone know that it's happening because this might be you.
Is there a deadline for applying for these scholarships?
Nope.
They're going to say at least weekly as long as upgrades last.
I don't know how long upgrades last, but there you go.
Recently, there has been a new wave of stories concerning abuse and harassment in the community.
And a common thread between many of these is the need to be aware of two factors.
Firstly, the power dynamic that can exist between more established and less established members of the community.
And secondly, the fact that conventions are professional environments for professional members of the community.
And there needs to be more awareness of that.
So this has been on Twitter, I think, mostly, although obviously it has bled into other discussion venues.
And I don't think we're going to try and link to much because it's very widely distributed and it's very difficult to keep track of.
But we have thoughts.
I thought this was interesting because I don't have this mindset of thinking about conventions as professional spaces,
because for me, the conventions are not professional spaces.
And I do have, you know, I do, there are professional spaces that I go into that are conferences in my own field.
And for me, they feel sufficiently different from science fiction conventions that I don't really think of conventions in that professional way.
And so I've been thinking about where this might give me blind spots.
In particular, I think because I don't think of them as being professional events for me,
I don't think of myself as really having any power in them.
When maybe I should, because if I am, say, working on program convention and I have a lot of power over who does and who doesn't get slots for panels,
slots for readings, slots for cafe clutches,
how much am I projecting my own biases on there and kind of rewarding professional names I know
and not rewarding professional names I don't know?
Things like that.
Is what I think of as just being a hobby of setting these things up,
actually something which can make a difference to maybe to the careers of quite junior people
who would really like the platform that they can get at a convention to try and develop their professional careers.
And also in that a lot of the issues that have been talked about seem to involve interactions in convention bars.
This gets us back to the, I think, well discussed previously problem that a lot of interaction does take places in bars and in particular places with alcohol consumption,
which obviously is fun for a lot of us,
but may lead to extra problems of how do you keep things professional if you are drinking in the bar with people who may have the power to help or hinder your career.
That seems remarkably reasonable.
I think I want to go slightly further.
Obviously conventions are for some people a professional space.
They are not, I think, primarily a professional space.
I think we would probably most say that the most, most of us would agree that the most successful conventions,
certainly the most successful larger conventions, are a weird hybrid between personal and professional space in that,
although they were originally set up by fans as a way to spend social time,
and they are almost exclusively run by fans volunteering to do the organising.
It is certainly true that professionals who are attending the convention professionally enhance the convention in many ways.
And as I've just kind of started in a tiny little way,
attending conventions professionally as well as personally,
that I do feel that kind of strange,
the edge of, well,
I would do this,
but I will not do this because it is a,
it is a professional barrier for me.
Or here is this thing that I can,
I may be able to provide a professional service to a convention,
but is it right for me to provide a professional service to that convention?
While I am also a fan attending the convention.
I feel that it is not reasonable to expect everybody in a convention bar in the evening to behave as if they were at a professional event.
And,
and you would not necessarily want that to happen.
I think that I've seen some calls for alcohol and bars at conventions to be banned or relegated.
And I,
I do feel that,
that those people are missing the point or certainly the point for me,
because I am,
although I do do some professional work at cons,
I am primarily there to have fun with my mates.
I feel that at least one of the stories that I've read has arisen out of somebody believing that they were engaging in a professional relationship where it's quite possible that the other people involved in this primarily saw the relationship as a personal relationship.
one that didn't contain a professional component.
And I think there is the issue,
the one where the issue of how much power as a,
as a,
and a very established writer or indeed even as a quote,
big name fan.
I am putting big name fan in actual scarecoats because these things do not actually exist.
And,
and it has always been a joke,
I think,
except obviously it isn't a joke in some ways.
So,
and whether people like that do have more power than they realize.
You say about big name fans being a joke and,
and,
and I see where you're coming from.
I,
I don't feel,
um,
I don't feel that the fact that I have been in fandom for longer than some people gives me any power,
but it might be that that's because I haven't thought properly about it.
What?
Professor Hugo nominated,
Mark Protector or Neglector,
um,
the boy,
major podcast editor,
the coxswain,
yes.
This,
this neatly encapsulates the problem,
which is if you asked me,
are you powerful?
I would probably not immediately rush to say yes.
And I think that means that I haven't thought properly about it because I think I do have a,
I,
I am obviously acutely aware of many of my axes of privilege.
Um,
but I think that is an axis of privilege.
I have not properly thought about,
and I think the problem with saying,
oh,
you know,
there's not really any such thing as a big name fan.
Like,
I do completely understand where you're coming from,
but I do wonder whether that is because we don't properly think about how those power dynamics are actually,
um,
in effect in fandom.
Um,
because I think if you meet someone,
I remember the first time,
you know,
meeting some fans I'd only heard about,
you do.
I remember being scared to meet Greg Pickersgill.
You were right.
I'm not necessarily saying he is powerful.
Uh,
but in some ways he definitely is.
He had a power over me when I was a new fan.
And it's also very easy for me to forget that I've been in fandom for 15 years now.
So I'm not new anymore.
And I think it's double easy to forget that because there are people who have been in fandom a lot longer than me who think I am still new.
So these are all really interesting,
um,
overlapping power dynamics,
which are,
I think,
quite easy not to think about.
which is bad.
But,
you know,
but there are people there,
but there are people,
there are quite a lot of people at the Eastercon who are not very established in their careers,
who believe very strongly that it's very important to be there.
And I've been on panels with people who I,
I think were very introverted writers who almost certainly write very well,
but who,
who honestly,
I think would rather have been in a bucket of,
of live crabs for an hour than on an Eastercon panel having to say things about things.
And I did feel very sorry for these people.
And then again,
who felt that that was part of professional development for a writer.
Yes.
I mean,
what I would hope actually is that going to Eastercons and other conventions is fun,
but I would like it if it didn't have that much impact on careers.
Yes,
I would agree with that.
Because I do think it,
I think it,
it is advantageous that underrepresented people even further,
because they're not the people who may feel that they are able or feel safe in going into a convention bar and,
you know,
having a few pints and trying to schmooze with publishing professionals.
Because also,
as we've seen,
it's those people who are taking the bulk of the harassment in situations where it does go wrong.
And it is not all kind of nice fun and games.
And there are power imbalances.
And the question there is whether the harassment,
not necessarily harassment,
but whether the unfortunate,
some of the unfortunate outcomes arise from a situation where people who are marginalized to begin with,
feel that they have to go outside their comfort zone in order to gain acceptance in the community.
And as a result,
do things that they probably wouldn't do if they weren't doing them for professional reasons.
And at that point,
you're into a very difficult situation,
very difficult situations that,
you know,
as we know from other industries,
lead to terrible abuses.
I think it's,
we should be clear that convention should be aware of the potential for problems and try and have good codes of conduct,
good harassment policies and things to try and mitigate against all these problems.
And obviously listener services and systems so that people who are finding something is amiss.
But at least one of these things that's come out,
the incident may happen now,
and it may only be years down the line that the ramifications of that come to light.
I think that's the sort of thing.
And there's only so much that conventions can do there.
You know,
if you're in a position of power,
try not to abuse it.
Try to realize that the person may be talking to you,
not because they like you and think you're marvelous,
but because they think you may be able to help their career and act accordingly.
That has been the ninth episode of Octothorpe.
Thank you very much for listening.
And it is goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod at incompetech.com.
Used under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 license.
So, before we leave you,
we're going to talk a little bit about staying sane in the apocalypse.
So, Alison, what have you been doing to stay sane in the apocalypse?
The country seems to have decided that we all have to go out to pubs and restaurants,
and I have not been doing that,
but I have come to visit my parents,
which is legal as of yesterday.
So, we're here for two nights, which I believe is allowed within the law.
And, obviously, they are getting on,
so it's quite nice to be able to come up and help them with symptoms,
most of which involve operating systems.
And I feel like it's back to being...
It's the first time I've felt that I've done anything
that's felt like my normal life for months on end.
So, that's quite nice.
But I still think, in general,
I'm not that sane,
and we are still in an apocalypse.
Oh, and greetings to all our American listeners,
who are really just kind of at the beginning of an apocalypse right now.
So, I'm very worried for America.
I mean, I think we're actually in several apocalypses simultaneously,
but there is one main one.
But, personally, this week, I went to work for two days.
I worked from a coffee shop one day
because all the power was going off
for the annual electrical check in my apartment,
and I forgot about this until the air conditioning went off one morning.
I have also been to a bar,
although all the bars here are already, like, table service
and someone brings you your drinks.
So, I did not, like, have to go and cram up at the bar
trying to retrieve my pints.
They bring them to you.
It's all very civilised.
So, it does feel more like I am doing the normal, everyday things
I would do than before,
but I am doing them all while wearing a mask.
So, that's obviously a kind of reminder of what's going on.
Oh, my other thing is that
I happened to be reading the anthology
New Suns, original speculative fiction by people of colour,
edited by Nisi Scholl.
I happened to be reading that this week
and it is very good.
It's not a themed anthology.
It's just an anthology of, like, excellent speculative fiction
and it's got a very high hit rate for me.
And while I was reading it,
I happened to win the Locus Award for Best Anthology.
So, you should go out and get that.
I have this day, say, in the apocalypse
by, it will not surprise anyone to learn,
playing board games.
I recently discovered the joys of print and play board games.
I have found a website called docsdirect.com.
You could put your beautiful game cards in the show notes, John,
because they really are a thing of beauty.
I was very impressed.
I purchased several 300 GSM satin prints
of various board game print and play stuff
and I bought a corner cutter,
which makes square corners round
and I got my craft knife and my,
I was about to say cutting board,
but I actually use a cardboard envelope
because I am pro.
And I got on with it
and now I have print-to-play board games to play.
Even more board games.
Also went to Ikea.
Ikea's still there.
Had to queue to get in.
Wasn't that bad.
Social distancing was fine.
Mostly very good.
Well, Ikea's always had you go all the way around the shop
on a one-way system, hasn't it?
Yes.
Actually, this is one of the things that really made it difficult,
which is the bit immediately upon getting in was very crowded,
but as soon as you got through that bit, it was all fine.
And the other thing is that my parents are coming to visit next week,
which I'm very much looking forward to.
They're staying in a hotel.
They're not staying with us because our house is small enough
that it might be difficult to do social distancing in our house.
But yes, looking forward to that very much.
Hurrah for people.
I haven't seen people in so long.
I'm still not going as far as going to Ikea.
Ikea can still bring stuff to me in a truck, as far as I'm concerned.
Yeah, I'm only going into shops when it's absolutely essential,
which means when they sell almond croissants.
That's fair.
No, I mean, so I would have gotten...
We have been mostly getting delivery, I will say.
The problem is that Ikea's delivery is not priced.
If you're just buying a couple of odd lens for your bathroom,
the delivery costs are exorbitant.
If we had been getting several bits of furniture,
I probably would have done that,
but I just needed a toilet roll holder and a mirror
and other things like that.
So, yeah.
It's a good point,
because Ikea here will deliver minor bits and pieces
for about three quid.
Yeah, they just put them in the post.
I've certainly got odd things delivered from Ikea without...
I think there was one thing we tried
that they wanted to deliver for the full whack.
That's the problem.
It's if you're bigger than whatever could go...
It'll have been your towel rail or something.
Yeah, or, like, it might have been the bin.
Oh, yeah, bins will get you.
The bin might have been too big.
But, yeah, like, it was fine.
I wore my mask.
I walked.
Didn't use public transport.
So, yeah, it was fine.
I am not symptomatic.
Oh, and I'm taking part in a University of Southampton,
Southampton NHS,
COVID-19 testing pilot program,
where I spit in a small vial,
and they tell me if I have coronavirus.
They don't tell me if I have had coronavirus.
They tell me if I currently have coronavirus.
I think this is part of them trying to get set up for citywide testing and kind of instantaneous timescales,
or as near as you can get when you're doing this kind of thing.
So, yeah, I'm helping.
Yeah, we cannot tell you if you have had coronavirus from your saliva.
We need your blood for that, John.
So, we can actually...
I can't do blood tests at home.
I pass out.
So, a spit test is good enough, then?
Because an awful lot of people have been stuffing things up their noses,
and it seems like if a spit test was adequate for this,
wouldn't they just have been spitting?
So, there are various papers comparing the utility of an asopharyngeal swab to saliva,
and saliva does seem to come out quite well,
but I think there's some slightly contradictory results.
The other problem is that I think trying to get people to swab their own noses and throats
successfully at home is quite difficult,
because when you need to swab your nose,
you need to swab your tonsils without touching the rest of your mouth,
which is quite complicated,
and possibly just spitting in a tube is better.
I can spit in a tube successfully,
but I cannot do any of the other things.
And I got a blood test at home once,
and it was like, prick your thumb and put blood in the thing.
And I have a phobia of blood,
but I was like, I could just prick my thumb.
I can't.
As it turns out,
much easier to get the train to a different city
to have the blood test than it is to do at home for John.
I'll just come around with, like, a diamond pen
and write blue on it for you, John,
and I will charge you only 20 quid.
I didn't say, like, in what time slot I would come and visit you, John.
Yeah, in fact, John,
if I promise to do that,
will you quarantine me for 14 days in your house?
Oh, hello.
Hello.
Why is she unhappy?