uh i'm gonna do this again because i don't know how editable any of what we just did was so
hello everyone and welcome to the very 131st episode of Octothorpe a podcast for science
fiction and science fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 27th of March 2025. I'm
John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott. And I'm Liz Batty. And this morning with your cup of morning life
juice we bring you some letters of comment so we heard from many of you because last week's episode
show art was handwriting samples from the three of us and we gave you a hint and the hint was that
john has the nicest handwriting and so many of you tried to guess the order of our handwriting
tami guessed it when allison liz john and then liz john allison liz allison john was guessed by
anginaeel allison john liz was chris karsia's guess rosana said john was in the middle mike
scott said allison was in the middle although we think he might be cheating because he probably
should know what allison's handwriting looks like uh bidget said mine was the top one and then
they're all handwriting fonts and malcom hutchis and also guess that we were using handwriting fonts
handwriting fonts are not as good as you think they are guys uh shilah lah said we all have
nice handwriting so thank you very much but the winner is the one person to guess correctly uh
which is ed mauland who correctly guessed that the order was john allison liz and there was a second
hint which is whenever we do anything in order on this podcast we're doing the order john allison
liz so well done ed uh will buy you a point of the beverage of your choice uh easter con awesome
other convenient time not if it's whiskey we won't okay yes not the pint whiskey but i was you know
entertaining non-alcoholic options rather than the pint of vintage champagne option
might as a pint of vintage champagne we have checked and ed is down as attending the easter con so
we are confident that we will be able to procure him a beverage i will also say one other person
correctly guessed mine but didn't guess the other two cushila lah said that we all had nice handwriting
but said the top one was the nicest hmm so i think that counts so shilah you can have half a pint
uh at a future convention of your choice the other person who didn't guess all three of us
correctly but guessed me correctly was dug font who basically just said john's at the top and i was
like i am so yes thank you dug thank you i was deeply entertained it was very fun to watch the
guessing neil harrison was outraged to discover he had no samples of mine nor liz's handwriting
and i was like well we wrote your christmas card in 2023 so it's not my fault you didn't keep it uh
but yeah hey a christmas cards could be written by a spannier of course no yeah what what i didn't
say to neil was but john and a spannier sent me a christmas card this year
we wrote neil and nick a christmas card and i was going to cycle over to theirs on the
i come over the 23rd or 24th of december to drop it off but i messaged them and they were like oh
we've already left for christmas and i'm like ah so that christmas cards sat on our window
sill for a while before it became clear that it was never going to actually reach near the nick and
it went in the recycling but near the nick there was a christmas card. Tainingly speaking i suppose
we could have saved it for 2025 but that is a level of organization we do not possess we might
have digressed but yeah no no i um john occasionally sends me things in the post like random bits of
ballgames and and he has handwriting that is sufficiently beautiful but when i get it to the
post i go oh someone with beautiful handwriting has sent me a package and i have always by then
forget forgot that john said he was going to send me a bunch of leftover bits of video of ballgames
so you know i open it to go oh yeah no i know what this is now. The thing i've meant to say about
this but forgot is that i may have been grading on a curve because when i said john has lovely
handwriting it is possible that there was a silent for a person of his age and gender hidden in that
i do think that the reason a lot of people assumed it was not in the show order is because a lot of
people looked at the top handwriting and thought there is no way that is a man's handwriting and i
i suspect that compounded a great number of people because the only person who guessed john first was
the person who guessed all of them correctly yeah and and no one else guessed i was the top
handwriting and i think i think i have very nice handwriting but uh but i think there is a i think
you are right that most people assume men do not we are going to be at east con we were going to
segue from buying a drink uh but that went madly wrong we are planning to have a uh meetup for oct
thought fans and for people who quite like us but detest walked thought uh and that will be at nine
p.m. in the bar on friday unless something changes in which case we will publicize it in the east
con discord and east con newsletter and on our blue sky and facebook meetup also open to people
who love octa thought but detest us i don't know how big that quadrant in the graph is but listeners
if you think we're all absolute pricks but quite like the audio we make do write in was that another
gender term of abuse what did i say quite possibly pricks it's all right i can get behind that one
liz uh we will wear our ox thought t-shirts uh i i will wear my octa thought t-shirt i can't
remember if the other two have an octa thought t-shirt i do not have an octa thought t-shirt but i probably
can sort something along those lines out before easter now that i think about it when it might be
that we could in this episode say that easter got octa thought t-shirts are available for sale
okay god i know who wants to mule me an octa thought t-shirt to beau fast
what size are you liz uh don't know well it depends on what like t-shirt purchasing system
you're using right yeah yeah yeah no i completely get it do you do you have a favorite t-shirt blank
no okay so because that would make it easy you could say oh i want to bellow in canvas 3000
i'm a larger than bellow in canvas 3000 i'd go right that's great i do not know to that detail
my t-shirt blanks i do know that i have a double in 2019 bid shirt that's quite nice did you make
those no that will that that'll have been um offworld won't it did you make foley con shirts
my foley con shirt still fits i can dig it out and look at the size yep that sounds good all right
i mean i won't necessarily use that shirt blank no because it might not come in purple
so you want them to be purple and should i put the space people on it because i've really to do
a shirt with the little space people for a long time and i haven't ever done it i reckon we get
the actual logo shirts that lori asked for in august and we make those available and then we do
stretch goals and explore those after i reckon minimum viable product first stretch goals later
you are you are basically putting work in my diary before easter which is not great because i have
like in my defense i did put this work in your diary six months ago i am just now nagging i
this is what i'm like now no i mean i in um yes oh in my defense um let me wait till we get to the
e-base section because jesus fucking christ on the stick oh my god rizanna has written us a letter
which she says is more of a question than a comment it's very good this is too late for 2025 but i've
been seeing people talk about nominating tiktoks for the he goes specifically tiktoks not on any sort
of regular schedule where it's one person and they review and discuss books um i had originally
assumed these will be fan writer but have been told they ought to be a fan cast because video
which made sense to me um being kind of like booktube but but on your phone i've now seen tiktokas
talking themselves talking about it and putting themselves as fan writer however looking at the
rules they don't really fit in either categories i understand them i may be calling on liz in a
minute in your collective opinion where would tiktok review folks be nominatable in the he goes and
where should they be nominatable or see do they just kind of not fit at all um i think as long as
you've done it at least four times um it's fan cast and it should fit squelient fan cast and if i'm
wrong liz will tell me because she has a much better understanding of the wiswers constitution
than me um i am a very old person and i am not entirely persuaded that anyone's
unformed ramblings on video or podcasts really qualify them for fan writer but i accept this
as me being old and you may have a perfect script and be amazing and at that point maybe
maybe fan writer would be fine i think it's fair to say that the podcasts i enjoy are definitely
not written or in general but like shut up and sit down do have like scripts for all their videos
but i would also say we never nominate dramatic presentations in novel because they have screen
plays so i am not sure the presence of a script even if it's a very beautifully written script
mmm means that it's fan writing instead of fan casting i mean i i it is possible that i am under
estimating the quality of writing in these book review um tiktoks in which case i am very sorry guys
um i mean as you may or may not have realized from the last hundred and thirty-one episodes i
would never personally nominate somebody who's primarily a book reviewer for fan writer because
that's not what i think fan writing is all about but i understand that i am in arcane arcane
prehistoric creature in this regard do you mean arcane or archaic archaic by being archaic i'm
also archaic yeah i mean i wasn't that's why i was like she could mean either plausibly yeah i think
i think we have to distinguish the actual constitution from vibes so the actual constitution says that
fan cast is any generally available non-professional audio video periodical devoted to science fiction
fanciore-related subjects that's had at least one thing in the last kind of D.A. blah blah and that
seems to me to be tiktoks they say periodical we have it's is well established that periodical
for the purposes of fan cast and fanzine does not require a regular schedule um because many many
many successful fanzines in particular have have only been periodical in the sense that they've
put a number on the front yeah well i mean that's getting very arcane i mean the same thing is do is
you know the same thing is true of semi-prozine um and there's semi-prozines that do not appear
in a regular schedule and to be honest with prosines that do not currently appear on a
uh regular schedule like you know fanzine science fiction has gone to a very irregular schedule so
i think periodical does not necessarily ever imply it has to be a regular schedule i mean i'd also say
that fanzine is basically the same as fan cast except we haven't it doesn't say audio video and
you have to not be a fan cast basically we sort of define fanzine as not being a fan cast in some
ways yeah and for fan writer it says has to be appeared in semi-prozines or fanzines are in
generally available electronic media so you would have to classify tiktok as electronic media
which also doesn't seem like much of a stretch so fan cast but your your actual tiktok is a fan
cast and it seems exactly the same as the booktubers to me and we've had booktubers on the ballot before
yeah i stick it in fan cast vibes i'm always going to go for vibes because if we get if
somebody is a finalist and they and they jib too hard with the vibes of the hugos then
then a thousand amendments have brought the following year to to get them out again so you know i
agree it's probably a fan cast we heard from far remendelson so just to so far i wrote to us about
the BSFAS charity status and um fower writes in I just want to pick out a couple of things
from this so basically Fower points out that they won't have to do accruals anymore and I think
we noted that last time but basically Martin Potts got stuck with the Treasure a role for 16 years
and now it can be a lot easier and that does seem pretty compelling so Fours says "becoming a
charitable incorporated organization gives BSFAY members the oversight of the charity commission
so they can report the BSFAY if they think something's gone seriously wrong" and basically says
charities you know make surpluses that stay in the charity and it's clear that BSFay is really a
charity it's just not registered as one um for a notice noted that it means that the organization
of the BSFAY will be regularized so Fours says "thank you for your kind words assuming this won't
make much difference but while things are ticking along very nicely at the moment there have been
moments where the BSFAY has not been so secure the result is we don't have recorded past decisions
and meetings it's a shame that no one is around in fandom that could advise on the BSFAY's history
in a sort of committee role um I've always thought that would be a good idea um but yes this is
definitely one way to try and make sure that that history is preserved then finally and I think
this is actually the one I we had not mentioned at all by these probably the best one which is
if you want to apply for grants being a charity means there are way more grants you can apply for
and that is oh we had not considered that and that is a that is a smashing point so thank you very
much FARA. On the subject of FARA's email we heard from listener Alison Scott who pointed out
camera is not in fact a charity and I regret the error I thought I'd checked but apparently not
closely enough. I thought it was a membership organization and it used to be but now it's a
company limited by guarantee because membership being an unincorporated member society is not a
particularly good long-term strategy for your organization in the UK um and they decided
that and they were really far too big for it they are a very big campaigning organization but they
are yes that's absolutely key point that I had not thought of there is a whole world of stuff that
you might be able to apply for uh which we've probably never in well I don't know if the BSFAY
was really investigated because they maybe could not. We heard from Christopher J. Garcia who wrote
in with an appreciation for Robert Pattinson um he says he's a fine though vindictive actor
and which I like he says basically he he takes roles at a garbage in big films and
punishes those films by being incredibly dull and annoying and then takes on good roles he cares
about and does excellent efforts yeah which could be true I mean there's a lot of actors who are like
I'm gonna do one for my finances and my beach house and then one for the you know the stuff I really
want to do but I don't think I've actually seen many of the big films that Robin Pattinson is
possibly dull and annoying and so I will have to hold my judgment on that but I didn't think it was
great in Mickey 17 which I have now also seen so yeah Chris does say uh that he's the performance
equivalent of hold music which I thought was a statement I've seen Twilight and I thought he was
all right in it but yeah I think I think Chris might be right about this I do like whenever he
like doesn't utterly wacky interview because he's presumably bored of being asked the same three
questions over and over again and just comes up with the whatever stuff he likes I like those uh
Chris also says he really wants to see Mickey 17 but all his tensions far as films go is
directed towards time travel is dangerous playing at cinequest tomorrow and I am going to go and
look up time travel is dangerous and see what it is yay I mean it's a film which we know um
it's apparently a 24 British comedy mockumentary film which sounds quite good yeah coming to
cinemas next week apparently hmm UK cinemas on the 28th of March so by the time you get this
you'll be able to book into it for next weekend for the for the weekend immediate. It does start
Johnny Vegas who I feel very marmighty about. I even cinero in saying he's very disappointed we
missed the opportunity to refer to the title change from book to film as taking the mickey
thank you Ivan correct thank you I taught all. And then we heard from Renee who runs the giant
Hugo spreadsheet of doom along with the lady business people and Renee is letting us know that
the 2026 Hugo spreadsheet is open which is great because um means you can go through through the
year as you read watch listen play good things you can go and put them in the spreadsheet you can
also go and see things that other people may have thought are good and eligible and read what to play
them. It will also give you hints if you're not quite sure what category something should go in if
you put it in there people will generally like leave a message if they think it's in the wrong
category and so that will help put that in there and yeah the Renee and pals do a great job of
you know keeping this running and moderating it year after year so I'm very pleased it is open I've
gone and put a few things in already and I encourage you all to do so not least because if there's
a thing you really like and you put it in the spreadsheet now when there's like six things
then I think there's more chance that people might actually see it and read it before nominations
open for 2026. We also heard from Lillian Edwards and Frederick Coulter who I think is a first time
writer apologies for one Frederick posted on our Facebook group to say he was listening to our
latest episode and got a message from one of his Canadian friends that they're skipping this
year for Worldcon because of Trump he was looking forward to meeting them in first in person at his
first Worldcon in 30 years he wonders if this is going to spread and how it will affect the LA
Worldcon so Ivan Kurt Phillips, Pharah and Doug all posted sort of saying similar things like either
they know people who were giving a miss or they themselves are giving a miss so and I should say
here that I have obtained a refund from my attending membership so I we are no longer planning to
attend either and that is yeah it's sad. So there's also been a statement this week from the Seattle
Worldcon chair and I think this has been building for a while I've seen other statements other people
saying elsewhere on blue sky and elsewhere that they think Seattle needs to put out a statement and
they have and it's basically a statement about how the convention respond to orders and actions of
the US government that they condemn that create hostile conditions and travel barriers for
international members and also overall LGBTQ+ members. Basically they're saying that they are
going to try their best they're listening to everyone they don't have a set of concrete steps
they're going to take now because probably because there's like not really a satisfactory answer they
can give I don't think to what they will be able to do and also it's obviously a very fast-moving
area anything they put down may actually be completely different the situation may be completely
different in a few months time by the time people are actually thinking of entering for the
Seattle Worldcon and but they do have a few concrete things they can do which is to recommit to the
codes of conduct and diversity and anti-racism statements that they do have virtual memberships
and it sounds like you can done did you downgrade or attending to a virtual? Yeah that isn't mentioned
in the statement explicitly but I wrote in to see if it was possible and it turned out it was.
I don't know whether that is I just got lucky or whether that's an official policy or what
but if you're in a similar position it is worth emailing to find out. I am I'm good to say what I
always say which is that if you are someone for whom the downgrade from a attending to a virtual is
not a significant expense for you then you might want to consider retaining your attending membership
to help the Worldcon which is almost certainly going to find all of this very difficult or of
course transferring it to somebody else. They've got all of the Chengdu pass along which is loads.
Yes it's $40,000 so I'm sure it'll help but that's still a relatively small proportion of the
Worldcon attending and they may they may of course be on the hook for room blocks that they are
but they've said that they've sold their entire room block already so I think they're probably
okay yeah room blocks are full room blocks are full and they can't extend them they are having
trouble like I think there are many things that Seattle Worldcon is struggling with.
My impression is finance is not one of them but I might be wrong and I don't.
And they've also put together you know guides to your rights um you know during immigration
and some non-profit organizations that they are sporting and also end by saying a lot of the Seattle
staff are also going to be impacted by this and they're also dealing with the impact of other
buyers natural disasters and you know they're trying and they think it's the start of their
response and yeah you can email the chair if you have any queries.
I think there was a statement they really had to put out even though they can't make
big concrete statements but I think they can say look we're looking at this we're thinking
about this we are trying to support you through it but I think they are going to be
quite heavily affected by people changing plans maybe not so much by kind of international
visitors from Europe and so on but I would bet that there would have been quite a lot of
Canadian visitors going to Seattle who will now not be willing to enter the US and it
remains to be seen like how much of an effect does this have on your membership curves do they
pick up extra virtual members how deeply financially committed are they or do they have a lot of
wiggle room to to move things around to you know cancel expensive things and so on.
We do think that the room blocks are filled so if they were on the hook for a certain number of
room nights they've filled them but I didn't check what like the cancellation policies are on
whether they could be hit by a potential late cancellation say if things change in a couple of
months. I thought this was a very good statement very very measured very clear in in its condemnation
of the place we find ourselves in but but but not so clear about what Seattle is going to do better
but you know there is only so much you can do. To some extent I think conventions especially when
they are bringing in volunteers who are basically doing things to volunteer for the convention which
could be otherwise paid work done by people in that country we may have been skating on thin ice
in some ways for a few years on this and it may just be there now enforcing more strictly
something which was kind of policy before. Yeah it is unclear if I was going to a US world con I
would not be volunteering because I would be worried that that would be a problem. I think
you're probably fine to volunteer once you get there but don't say don't take my word for it.
For people who are out there saying it's always been like this please note that multiple European
countries have issued travel advisories to the US now and the UK while it hasn't issued a travel
advisory has changed the long-standing wording in in advice for travelers to the US for basically
you should expect to meet all entry requirements to the US is enforcing entry requirements strictly
which is a change and they think there is so clearly our foreign office thinks there's a change
because there is and I think the best hot take I've seen on this said well of course
all countries have the right to refuse entry and will refuse entry to anyone who they
who they think shouldn't enter but there is a very big distinction between refusing entry and
detaining indefinitely without charge. That's the other that's the terrifying thing and they do not
have the right under international to do the law to do the second and they are definitely doing it
in multiple well-documented individual cases where the people while they probably haven't followed
the letter of the of their entry requirements have not made very major errors you could easily do this
and and there's at least one case where literally the only reason given for detaining a person is
what they've said on their socials. It's not just people immigrating either there are
advantage of examples of citizens who had have had visitors visits from the secret service because
of social media posts that were only you know weren't like storm the White House but were mildly
inflammatory and this is this is a lot right it's obviously a developing situation we are none of
us are experts we are just doing the sort of talk we might have in the pub but also I'm not going to
the US anytime soon sorry guys love you all. After our last recording we got the little email through
saying what our schedules were going to be like for reconnect to the Belfast Eastacon which is
rapidly approaching and I think we all have schedules we are very pleased with you should say these
are all preliminary and may change because we've just seen kind of our initial program assignments
but I have clicked yes I'll be on this session to all of them so hopefully I'll be on all of them
yeah no I'm excited. Killy the most important one is up to top live which will be as traditional
on Monday at 1230 we are down as fan interest and performance guess we're a performance
be like the last legs are being in the bar before you're to dead dog I think we're a performance
you're a performance with fan interest I think yeah I think I'd say we're performance before we're
interest. Silly are our live podcasts sir oh that is a hundred percent true well they're live that's
as much as we can say about him they are definitely live yeah and they are plausibly podcasts but no
yeah this will be good so Monday at the time list said 1230 I was a little bit short of time
and one of the things that happened as I was a little bit short of time was that I unaccountably
forgot to fill in the programming questionnaire with the list of all the panels and then I realized
that and I thought oh I could I could kind of send them an email saying please please please
include me despite the fact that I'm a little bit later than I thought on the other hand I could
just have an Easter card where the only program items I'm on are the fan funds auction which is
going to be on Sunday evening and then also I'm on opt to thought live along with you guys I guess
the things I am on at Eastercon I am on a little thing called octor blive with allison and liz at
1230 on Monday I'm on fandom politics and boycotts whereas the line in how do we draw it with Liz
batty brine is bit and cat cobetti as panelists and tami cox and as moderator when is that
Sunday 5 p.m oh yeah no I'm gonna be I'm gonna be in the third row for that and then I am going
to be moderating two other panels on the sunday so I have is the force with you at 1230 on sunday
I'm moderating that with a pretty great selection of panelists so I got Rebecca Rowanhorse Russell
Smith Jonathan Laidlow and David Green and then I've got what does this card really mean history
in board games which is Russell Smith Tim Kirk Estemma Callum Stewart and Ian Moore so I those are
both things I think I've said everything I want to say about Star Wars at Eastercons for the
civil future but I'm very happy to encourage other people to say interesting things about Star Wars
and I don't know much about history in board games but by jov I know about board games and I will
be asking insightful questions of an insightful panel so I'm looking forward to that too I'm on
the aforementioned Oxford Up Live on Monday and on Sunday I'm on fandom politics and boycotts as
mentioned previously with one jion cox and some other great panelists and also on Saturday afternoon
I will be giving the hey lecture yeah whoa oh that's fabulous yes I am very excited and also very
nervous and I don't know why so come along and smile and make reassuring faces at me oh that's
so good no richly deserved and I'm excited to attend but yeah it was good be great very excited
also there's anything you particularly want to know I mean in my specialist field of like holding
up sequencing of pathogens then let me know and I might put it in the talk because I haven't written
it yet bae I assume you're gonna write it on the plane to Belfast in the accepted manner of academics
no I'm gonna write it well in advance because that's how I roll hey no it is strange if I was
giving an academic talk then yeah I might write it like two or three days ahead unless they were
doing that thing where they like your slides 10 days ahead or whatever in which case I'd write
it 10 days ahead if I'm just on a panel you know fine I will just prep the panel but for some reason
doing an academic talk to Eastacom people means I'm gonna be like preparing way way in advance yeah
it's weird it's a particular thing isn't it condensing your academic expertise in a way that is
understandable to non-expert but generally bright and extremely picky people not not wanting to
trouble you yeah but I'm not I'm not that nervous about explaining it to like non-experts usually
but for some reason specifically Eastacom experts or efficient convention non-expert is
more nerve-racking than a while it's terrifying it's fair thanks John I think it's because I've
seen like 20 years of hay lectures and they've all been really good so you will not be the one
to break the duck do not um no you'll be great I'm very excited about this so if anyone's
disappointed by my saying I will not be available on panels at Eastacom I it gives me more time to
be available in the bar so I will see you all there I don't know which bar there may be more than one
bar we may have to specify which bar we're gonna be in okay that's the point okay and then um
I'm looking forward to Eastacom it's gonna be great I'm looking forward to Liz's hay lecture
those items do all sound great so if every world's items are as good as that it's going to be a
fabulous program well I think they're all going to be good and I know that because I signed in and
clicked on the ones I'd like to be part of and so I looked at them all so yeah relatively little
where I felt like I had like one of the reasons I'm moderating to is because I was like well that's
a very interesting topic which I think I could moderate but I'm not sure I have anything interesting
to say about congratulations to Meg and David who are the co-leads of program and I've done a
cracking job ably assisted I believe by a couple in sharp and D Franklin well do you want to talk
about so the other thing that none of us are officially on but which we will probably be trying to
attend is the launch of color fields writing about writing about science fiction by pork and
cade and yeah I am excited about about this I'm excited sounds great that does also sound like
a good thing to go to I mean I'm sure there's gonna be lots of lovely things to go to Eastacom
I'm really looking forward to it at this point I have a I have a kind of three-week spell in my life
which has is continuing continually has house guests fleeing America sorry house guests from
America and core flu and then different house guests from America and then Eastacom in it and
I'm very much looking forward to all of this but my um but I'm slightly worried about my health
and and deliver in particular so I have a lot of things that I have to have done before that
first house gets to arrive so yay yeah you got makeup to look t-shirts yes I do have to make
optical t-shirts available for sale which I will definitely
we've just heard in the last couple of days that the person who for many years was Britain's oldest
active science fiction fan Peter maybe passed away peacefully in his sleep a couple of weeks ago
there's a post from his great niece on his facebook feed um Peter was the first winner of
the Doc Wear award in 1963 and I think when we talk about the sorts of people we think win the
Doc Wear award um um Peter really exemplified that because all of his work on fan on
fanish things was well behind the scenes and also really quite a long time ago because you know
he was he was quite old he was 98 he was one of the first members of the Cheltenham Circle and the BSA
um he acted as the librarian of the BSA lending library and then was a BSA committee member
it was also one of the founders of the Order of St. Fantany which is something that we don't talk
about very much um on the podcast because it doesn't exist it doesn't really exist anymore
he was presented in his absence with the first Doc Wear award at the 1963 EasterCon
bull con and was a member of the organizing committee for long con 2 and was responsible for
the long con 2 publications he carried on going to EasterCon and Novacons well into his 90s and I
used to chat with him there I found him very good company um I missed those conversations
yeah I didn't have anything to add because I didn't I did really chat to him
neither of you actually knew him right I mean I knew him by sight but I don't think we'd really
had many conversations before he stopped being able to attend conventions yeah fair
the BSA award finalists were announced a few weeks ago we covered the long lists and they have
now been narrowed down to shortlist by members of the BSA and members of the BSA and members of
EasterCon will be able to vote on the winners so we're going to put a link in the show notes to
all the different finalists you remember that the BSA awards now has quite a lot more categories
than it used to I mean there we used when we've had like three categories but now it is up to
nine I feel like it was four for a very long time yeah but they do look like pretty
great short lists especially in the the nonfiction so they split nonfiction into short nonfiction
and long nonfiction and so the long nonfiction is basically a set of interesting looking books
including ones by Paul King Cade on Prevent by Keith Roberts by Paul Marshall on J.D. Ballard's
Crash John Clute's book The Book Blinders which is what he gave his lecture on last year at
EasterCon uh spec for Nuby's volume two I think Effect Effect VNuby's volume one did it win a
BSA award or was nominated for one and of course Track Changes by Abigail Nussbaum from Bridene
Books yeah so that's a really good shortlist and then the short nonfiction has like seven
interesting interesting essays not all of which I have read yet but includes the one by Ted Chiang
on AI that was going around a lot last year on Bailie's book about considering Cozy science
fiction fantasy ones by Eugene Bacon and Estee Grunavagan and the Hugo Award Report from
Chris Bowerclay and Jason Sanford so yeah they're all basically pretty solid
shortlist I will not read them all out but you can now go and take a look and a lot of the short
fiction and shorter fiction is online and so you can have a read of those as well I will say
that a lot of the categories have not the five nominees as specified in the Constitution but
they have gone to either four nominees or you know six or seven presumably because of ties in
the voting for the shortlist which does suggest there might have been like a very
widespread of votes across you know from maybe a fairly small voting pool across a wide number of
items which may indicate that not a lot of BSA members voted so I guess we have to see maybe
having this many categories meant the people didn't feel they were qualified to vote on some
of them and so didn't but also we always know that if you have short fiction then you get like a
very long tale of you know if you look at the Hugo Short story you always get a very long tale of
nominees and that occasion has gone down to different numbers as well so there's a big thing that
happens it's strange that they have only four novels there well presumably because it was either
four or eighteen so we have unfortunately the BSA Awards are not yet listed on the BSA website
so we've linked to the file 770 summary of the awards and we will let everyone know when it's
on the BSA's website. Do we want to talk about F now? Yes. Who wants to introduce that?
So the European Fan Fund transports European SF fans to conventions and there is going to be a
race to send a fan to Archipelicon which is Euricon 2025 in Mariam in the Aland Islands in June.
Open to any European fan living outside Finland, Bulgaria and Poland.
Nominations for the EFF have been extended and they now close on the 30th of March so if you're
thinking about standing or know someone who you think should stand then do nominate them.
Yeah we think the European Fan Fund does a good thing and we recommend that you will vote in it.
Hmm I shall vote enthusiastically. I'm very excited about going to Archipelicon so this seems
like a good thing to win. There is also going to be a Fan Fund auction at Eastercon and that is
currently scheduled for Sunday at 8pm. If you were thinking of bringing something lovely to auction
in the fan funds then we have made a statement about this in the progress report which is basically
please only bring small light things and please tell us in advance if you're bringing them
because we are all flying and we don't really want to end up with somebody bringing in 30 kilos of
un-unfor-sorted paperback science fiction books or anything like that because we will not be able to
sell them or indeed give them away. We don't have a table, just small light valuable things
and let us know that you're planning to bring them so that we can say oh that's lovely please
save it for next year. So our only action this year is that we're going to have an auction,
we're going to have about 50 things in it, we already know about what 30 or 35 of them are so
there's not that much space but you know if you have something amazing do absolutely let us know.
So basically please bring small light valuable items to Eastercon and hand them all to Alison.
Yeah yeah if you've got any emeralds Alison has said she collects emeralds as well.
If you've got first edition boxes of Dungeons and Dragons do let me know
which is like emeralds in terms of their size to weight to value ratio.
Alison teased me by saying she might have a lot of white dwarfs she couldn't sell because they'd
had the Dave Langford's columns clipped out and would I like them for free and I was like well
yes I would but I suspect they're still worth things so maybe that's a bit cheeky and then it
turned out that they hadn't had the columns clipped out so they are still worth massive
longer and therefore I am not having them for free because I don't think those ones are I mean
the very first issues which I do have to sell them will be going on to Facebook,
can't be a quite soon, are worth massive amounts of longer but by the time you get to the one's
with Dave Langford's columns in they're down to about 10 on issue which you know isn't that
amount of money but you know four old magazines is pretty solid let me tell you.
And just because Alison didn't mention it those eBay auctions are for the fan funds with the proceeds
going to Guff F and the Corfloo fan fund. Also one of my buyers has got his stuff and wrote to be
saying one of the things you sold me used to belong to Dave Langford, can I ask how you came by it
in a kind of are you thieving where I'm like oh shit maybe I should have been putting this in the
listings which I did think about but oh that's actually a good point because Dave is famous
and not everyone knows he goes to the pub. Yeah he's famous to the exact people who are buying
this stuff so maybe that would have been an idea but it feels a bit odd to say I'm here selling
Dave Langford's file copies you know even though that is what I'm doing. I think you could put a
little label on I'm saying from the library of Dave Langford on your eBay auctions and you might
get an extra quid. Well and also you might what you might also not get is people assuming you've
nicked him so in my make your life a lot easier in the long run anyway. Indeed I mean I have been
kind of telling people what they're for but not obviously I don't put in the listings that the
money's going to things that aren't charities that are like charities for lots of reasons.
Another reason if we if the fanfons were charity or if the science fiction is like a pedia is a
charity we could actually be managing that through eBay in a way that would almost certainly increase
the amount but I'm not I'm not taking bids anywhere they're all on buy it now for what I think they're
probably so full and I'm being careful here to say to not say what I think they're worth because you
know some people have more bodies in the sense. I'm mentioning it on the podcast as well because
you might be if you're one of our older listeners you might have a box of elderly
Dungeons and Dragons stuff in your attic. It was a very it was a big craze in British science fiction
fandom in 1975 and 1976 probably also an American science fiction fandom in 1975 and 1996 and that
was a very good time to have got into something lost interest and then put it away in a box for 50
years let me tell you. So if you have those things either use them or give them somebody who'll use
them or sell them or if you're going to do none of those things write a note on the box in a sharp
you're saying do not throw this away when I die without checking the solve process first.
And then then picks I think we're pivoting to a Rosanna Pendelbury fan podcast and we will see
why that is over the course of these picks but I am going to pick The Power Fantasy by Kieran Gillan
Casper-Wynyard Clayton Cowles and Brian Hughes that's it's really good. So I haven't been talking
about this because I wasn't sure whether it was technically eligible for a Hugo last year or this
year but the trade paperback came out at the start of this year and I think I think therefore
it will be eligible next year but I will be enthusiastically nominating it when that comes up.
This is kind of there's a couple of different ways you can think about it it's kind of an
exploration of what the X-Men would be like in a more realistic setting or it's what watchmen would
be like if there were six Doctor Man Hattens instead of just one and all of them were angry at each other
in that way that families often are. It is very powerful it's very intriguing I don't know what's
going to happen it's kind of about Brinksmanship and about how difficult it is for entities with
extreme power to interact with one another without destroying each other and it's just really good.
The art is amazing the writing is excellent and yeah just really really enjoying it and it's
as I say the first trade is out now it collects the first five issues I think you can get it
of like a tenor which is ridiculously cheap but I've been reading it in singles and it's just
it's amazing so so yeah I would enthusiastically recommend going and looking that up and jumping
on the individual issues because the backs of the issues are very funny and I don't think they're
going to be collected in the trades so yeah. Please send me screenshots. I like that you think I
don't buy them as like physical comics one of course I do buy them as physical comics. Please send me
photos which are just like you know generalised screenshots. Hmm right and Rosanna Pendlebury
has written a lovely review of this at Nerds of a Feather which I have linked in the show notes and
it's very good she describes it as what if your cold world was six people each with superpowers
the equivalent to a nuclear arsenal and what if each of them was a total mess of a person? So my pick
this week is The Tomb of Dragons by Katherine Addison which is the final installment for now
of the Cemeteries of Amalot Religee. I think I've picked the second one on this podcast before
so it is another kind of mystery novel with Farah Salahar a priest who can speak with the dead
although at the start of this book, spoiler said previous book, he has lost that power and is
essentially just kind of a very it's not cozy well it kind of is cozy in that solving these
problems tends to involve Salahar going around and drinking a lot of tea and walking around places
and many times having to have someone show him where to walk around places and then having some
more tea and then having some more conversations and in that way it's very cozy but kind of the
background world is a little less cozy and you know it's it's clear that a lot of the time he is
trying to you know work against the wrongs of society and so the first two I greatly enjoyed
the third one I did enjoy maybe not quite as much though and that's partly because of the way it
intersects with Addison's previous book The Goblin Emperor in that The Goblin Emperor,
the Emperor does reappear in this book and so it feels a bit too much like a sort of the Emperor
comes in and by fiat can do things because he is the Emperor and it sort of reminds you that
this is what happens in worlds where you have an Emperor this is just that we happen to have a
good Emperor in this world at the moment and so like when he turns up it feels a bit like the
super powered character from somewhere else coming in to fix things so there's some aspects of like
how that is resolved that I didn't quite enjoy and I do think it was getting a little repetitive
with the second book like there is still a lot of tea drinking in all the books and a lot of
wandering around but there is like a scene which is unfortunately almost kind of word for word the
same as from a previous book but where they're trying to kind of persuade Salahah that actually
he does have friends and he can lean on them and they would like to be his friends and he needs to
kind of accept that he can sometimes have friends and lean on them I think one of the
main relationships comes to a very nice conclusion around that I don't want to give too much away
but I felt that worked and quite a lot of it works it's just I feel that some of the some of the
kind of how things get resolved is less satisfactory than it could be. Volimately I think it's very
satisfying trilogy and so it's probably an early front one of one of my best series nominations in
2026 and much like John references a very nice review of The Power Fantasy by Rosanna Pendleberry
at Nozefether I'm going to reference a very nice review of The Tomb of Dragons by Rosanna
Pendleberry at Nozefether which also manages to capture most of the things I felt about this book
so I think what we're saying is we should maybe just give up on picks and you should just go and
read Nozefether. Yep I believe Rosanna has also done some writing for Strange Horizons so you could
go and check them out too. I'm just checking that Rosanna hasn't reviewed my pick which I do not
think she has Rosanna if you're listening to this and you have reviewed my pick. How dare you Alison?
Please send us a link. I am picking The Death of Stalin which is a film by Amanda Inuchy which is
remarkably accurate on the actual events surrounding Stalin's death and remarkably inaccurate
on the dialogue which we cannot of course know that people spoke around that death but it is the
blackest black comedy of all time and it's currently on BBC iPlay you'd almost think that
they thought it was timely because it's what happens if you have an aging extremely powerful
and completely mad ruler who has been having purges and what happens when that person dies
and the people who have surrounded him who have all changed their behaviour to support him in his
madness have to decide what to do and it is extremely funny but it is much darker than Inuchy's
other work which if you've seen some of Inuchy's other work you might think there wasn't really
very much darker for it to get so yeah it's fantastic everyone should watch it and if you're
in the UK you can watch it at the moment because it's on BBC iPlay, fantastic film and Jason Isaacs
who is in general a very very very fine actor is it absolutely knocks this one out of the park
and if you had to criticise the film which is quite hard to do the big criticism would be as a
result of historical events Jason Isaacs does not turn up until halfway through the film which is
a great shame Jason Isaacs is the only actor to have ever played Tobes which could leave that
there without further explanation oh no no no no no no no no you are not leaving that there with
that further explanation no you know you know you know you cannot i believe i'm Tobes did explain
this to me so basically Tobes was used as a character in a Robert Rankin novel and Jason Isaacs
played that character in the dramatisation of the novel oh like an audio dramatisation
yeah like they did like a dramatised reading of it for the audiobook and he really has Tobes
to Valwa yep oh my god right well that's gonna be my pick next time wow i know right
the Brighton Lomicon in he is in episode e12 d13 of the Brighton Lomicon playing Tobes to Valwa
Tobes i mean i think this is like amazing right absolutely amazing yeah Tobes is justifiably
extremely proud of this as he should be i mean that is that is the best you know because who wouldn't
want to be portrayed by Jason Isaacs really yep oh my god okay we need we need to find a clip of
this because i need to see if Jason Isaacs really catches the essence of Tobes in his portrayal
is at the end of the episode i feel like i felt like that was a bit of a show stopper wasn't it
and that was the Octothorpe podcast and it's goodbye for me it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me
Friday would work because then people know what we look like for the rest of the con and have met
us i feel like Friday's a good time all right Friday the mum all right so there is a risk that
there'll be something amazing on the program and we'll find ourselves up against a life-changing
program item should we say nine o'clock there won't be a life-changing program item at nine o'clock
on Friday will there i'm not in Belfast until like nine thirty so on Friday yeah oh okay so maybe
Friday evening is Friday evening really difficult then are you gonna want to get to the con oh well
you didn't specify the am or the pm oh no i'm not meeting people at about nine am john god nine p.m
idiot boy honestly hook line and singer okay uh yeah nine pm on friday sounds like a lovely idea
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in competetec.com
used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
them up.