Actually, I'm just going to pause and look one thing up on the internet if that's all right.
On the internet!
Yes.
Disgusting.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 69th episode of Octathor.
Nice!
But this episode is coming to you on the 27th of October 2022.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
An ominous batty and I don't know these people.
And that was the best interruption you've ever done in the history of the pod.
This is a unusual episode of Octathor because we can't record this week listeners
and so you're going to get some audio of me, Alison and Christopher J Garcia chatting in
the fanzied lounge at Tricon 8 and we're also going to talk about Hugo Stats because Hugo
Stats are timeless.
Liz as our Chief Statistician in Chief has read the Hugo Stats.
Yeah, every single word.
No, that's a lie.
Have a new?
No.
I mean, I've skidned every single word.
I haven't read like every single column of EP8 votes for, you know,
best short story or anything like that.
But hopefully Nicholas White and his team who did the Hugo Stats document have in fact put
some helpful notes on things that might be of interest on some of the pages.
So and put some very interesting final charts in there.
So thank you very much, Nicholas and Kat.
I understand this was a joint effort between Nicholas White and Kat Jones.
So they argued quite a lot about which things should be included and eventually included both
of their favourites.
So that's why it's so long this year.
We appreciate your efforts, guys.
So I think one thing that I thought would be interesting to look at is E-Proibis Hugo.
This year, the business meeting confirmed E-Proibis Hugo as the nomination counting system
for the foreseeable future unless the business meeting decides to change that.
So I thought it would be interesting to see where this actually made any difference either
E-Proibis Hugo to make a difference or just the top six within the top six number of nominations
were the top six nominees.
And I think it made a difference in four categories.
Possibly the most significant of these is in Best Novella where Agent Tricoski's elder race was
actually, oh, I've got to count.
It's one, two, three, four, four.
It was actually nine in number of nominations if you just counted by number.
But it got on the ballot because the top nominee was by Martha Wells and she declined to take the
nomination.
And then Elder Race beat out another Catherine Valente Novella as well as actually an Eddy
of Corifor Novella which both had more kind of nomination, but on E-P-H Elder Race won out.
Which is quite interesting, but I mean it's kind of predictable that if you nominated
one Catherine Valente Novella you might have also liked another Catherine Valente Novella.
So I think you can see there where E-P-H has helped Agent Tricoski who might have a slightly
different set of voters get onto the ballot.
So this is actually, I think it might have crystallized something I already thought,
but I didn't know I thought if that makes any sense.
Which is that E-P-R-S Hugo may well mean that especially as the world con attract more diverse
groups of fans in terms of nationality, E-P-R-S Hugo might make sure that like any given block of
one nationality gets a nomination onto the ballot.
And so it might be that sort of if Adrian Tricoski leads in terms of like the people voting and
nominating in the UK, he gets on the ballot and that reduces how many of the people on the ballot
are American authors because obviously the American pool will be bigger, but from the E-P-H
perspective it will look like slave voting.
And so that's really interesting and might actually make the Hugo awards much more international
over time, especially as we see other communities come in, which is I think perhaps really really
really positive.
One thing that somebody who probably doesn't want the name attached to this quote on a podcast
said is that you are correct that E-P-R-S Hugo does tend to favor people with smaller minority
groups of voters and therefore makes the Hugo final ballot more diverse.
But the effect this is having is it's getting quite men onto the ballot because in the context
of the major block of Hugo voters now they're the minority.
And I thought that was very weird and strange, but this is an example of where it happened.
And as Elder Race was in fact my favourite of the novellas.
I'm quite glad to see that.
Because there hasn't been a male winner of one of the big four since 2016, 2017,
which is obviously like really positive in many ways, but does mean that at the moment
a lot of these mechanisms try and make sure that the less recognised get onto the ballot might be
working in the opposite way to how you might expect them to.
I think that's a lot about how strong the Hugo is as an award at the moment.
We go say Elder Race actually came in second, so it clearly was a popular finalist.
Well that's the other thing, right? Like I think it would have been a weaker ballot without Elder
Race on it. And I think that was the argument because I think last year one of the EPH,
one of the finalists that got onto the ballot because of EPH ended up winning that category.
And my argument last year I think was if EPH is putting the eventual winner onto the ballot,
EPH is clearly acting for the good of the award.
Elsa, Siennasson?
Siennasson, yeah.
Who I met at will come for the first time.
And was obviously very deserving, so hurrah.
So that's good, good knowledge Liz, thank you.
What else did EPH do?
So it made a difference in fan writer where if we just took the straight nomination count,
we would have had Alice's duet instead of Bitter Corella.
Great to have Bitter Corella and also they were very, very thrilled.
And yeah I think in that case it kind of got as a first time nominee.
First time finalist onto the ballot.
And also Dufit's just one of the things where Bitter Corella was writing a very different
style of thing than Alice's duet rights.
So you can kind of see how people may have voted for the similar types of fan writing that they like.
And some people obviously voted in a slightly different way, a slightly different constituency
and it got on there.
The other place it made a difference is there would have been a tie for sixth place,
sort of trying for fifth and sixth place actually, a three-way tie on fan artist.
But actually what happened is that Richard Mann had the lost out in EPH.
And there I think that is a bit of a shame.
Who got on instead?
Well no one got on instead.
The thing is I think because there was a three-way tie essentially for fifth,
sixth and seventh on that ballot under number of nominations.
Oh.
You know they would have all three of them been on there.
But because you can break ties with EPH to end up with two of the people who were nominated by
15 people getting on there and the third one not which just feels a little bit harsh.
Yeah no we can see that.
And then the last place it made a difference was best editor long form.
But let's just talk a little bit about best editor long form.
So EPH did make a difference in that, I mean it's hard to work out what would have happened
with that EPH because there were five people who would have been fine lists who formed the
administrators. Well there were four people in four the administrators that they were not
eligible in this category and then Tony Viscof declined nomination as she has in the past.
So essentially the people who came third, sixth, seventh and then tenth on the ballot were not
actually eligible. And then so when you remove them all I find it quite difficult to work out what
would be maybe going on with the EPH. But certainly Olivia Evans got 13 nominations and
went out under EPH. But Oliver Johnson for instance also had 13 people not make them and was not in
the ballot. I've also had a conversation with another finalist in this category where they
had a conversation with the administrators to go am I eligible in this category or not and
eventually after some discussion concluded that they were and so is on the ballot. But this I
think demonstrates that this is an extremely problematic category. I think when it was
created I think people hoped that it would make the work of long-form editors and the process of
long-form editing more visible to Hugo voters and to the community more generally and I'm not sure
that has worked. I mean there's also the 25% threshold which we haven't discussed much yet but the
business meeting has removed that so it no one accounts but I bet that long form was the closest
to not being awarded under 25% rule. So you said that in fan writer Bitter Carrera got on?
Yep. You said that in best editor long-form Nivia Evans got on in Novolettes the Adrian
Tricoffs sorry in Novella the Adrian Tricoffs killed us on. What was the fourth one sorry?
It was fan artists it was fan artists there was a tie and in fact in Beth's editor I think there
would have been a tie but I find it a bit confusing because there's somebody missing.
EPH got two black women on took one white man off and put one white man on so I think in balance
Alison's point about EPH favoring white men is probably wrong. This is this is um data over
several years that have been crunched for for that quote not not just this year. There is data
over several years yeah I mean it's for a future discussion but I mean it's not it's
but it doesn't seem like an overwhelming effect indeed no but it's kind of like EPH is only having
small effect I mean it's having kind of effects here on only four categories and in some case
a couple of cases it's just breaking a tie for sixth position but as we said you know it remains
out there is a challenge. Interestingly last year Octa Thorpe would have Octa Thorpe was seventh
under EPH but only because of EPH we were quite a long way downstream without EPH but this year
we were in the top six even without EPH so that was kind of interesting and kind of nice so thank
you everyone who nominated us. We were second under EPH and we were third I think under yeah
nominations which is pretty good but Liz you were going to talk about the 25 percent rule and I
interrupted so please go ahead. I mean the 25 percent rule I you know it has been removed it will
not be there in future really I'm talking about best editor long form because I think a category
in which people are nominating a bunch of people who are ineligible is a problem I mean you always
get people a casual person who's nominated who is ineligible especially in things like fan artists
and pro artists where they have to have done a qualifying piece of work but there's a lot of
people being nominated who you know just inform the administrators that they are not eligible so
they're not declining it they're really not eligible it had the lowest number of votes in that category
so it was had 635 votes and you needed 559 to get 25 percent so it was it was well above but it's
still a low number it also had kind of the lowest number of people nominating in that category I think
yeah the finalist range was 12 to 44 which I think is lower than any of the the lower end of
that is lower than any of the other categories I can see on the finalist list yeah and there's also a
new table thank you to Nicholas and Kat saying how many nominations people made in each category
and so you can see that actually only 33 people even nominated five editors invested in long form
and the same is true in fan writer where that was low but only 72 people 72 people nominated
only one editor so I think there is a real problem here in that people are not really
nominating for this category when they do nominate they're nominating people ineligible because they
don't have the information to know who is eligible and then the number of people actually voting is
low so it's kind of doing quite poorly in all three categories well and it is striking that that
that distribution is by modal because you've got 72 people who nominate one and then you've got 34
people nominate two and then it goes down to 26 and then down to 17 by the time you're nominating
four and then there are 33 people who nominate five so what that says to me is that most people
know one or two editors and then there is a group of people who know lots of editors and the sort of
people who know quite a few editors they're not really big and so you presumably got incredibly
incredibly engaged people at one end and not so engaged people at the other and actually I hadn't
noticed but this repeats in most of the categories which I find really interesting and I'd never
noticed before it's fascinating yeah they're all by modal basically yeah I don't think we ever had
these I don't think we ever had these actual numbers before but yeah you get all these by
modal distributions people I then nominate one work or they nominate five works in a lot of categories
yeah nice really nice that really really cool yes thanks to the people who put it together
on the subject of long-form editor the problem is obviously editors have a huge huge impact on the
field and we should recognize that impact somehow because it is much more the the sort of the editors
of science fiction are much more important especially to the Hugo electorate than for instance podcasters
and so like I do think there needs to be recognition of editors but I just I don't think this is how
because you like you say Liz it's abundantly clear that people don't really know
who's doing what work who's doing eligible work etc I'd much rather and I think I've said this on
the podcast before I I've always thought it'd be more sensible to just give the editor of things
that win a Hugo as well as the author there's probably problems with that but like it seems to me a
more elegant way of doing it but certainly I never vote invested in long-form because I have no idea
what how you would judge I never feel like I can give a informed opinion and I don't know how
if you if you are listening and you do vote in best editor and you don't just vote for editors
who took you to dinner one time please let me know how you decide because I I would I would be very
interested to know how people do yeah I found an extra thought here as well on best editor long
form if you look at the constitution best of the long form is the editor of at least four novel
length works that's quite a lot isn't it yes but the crucial thing is the person who came in third
on nominations was Lee Harris who is a senior editor at tour.com so he will be acquiring a lot of
novellas so that's the thing is possibly people have been looking at you know if you publish a
lot of novellas which are all published kind of as standalone books then maybe people start to
nominate you in long form when really they should be nominating you in short form he also did quite
well in short form but that is a possibility that is interesting I feel like there was a year when
Lee came six in both and was eligible for both yeah and what you know five things on the ballot
and he was six in both categories and I thought that was a bit hard yeah so possibly in some years
he is eligible in both categories but it would be a shame if the fact that it's got to be novel
length and a lot of these a lot of these ton of allas are quite long and because they're published
just downloads you might think they might be novels and it should go in long form but your
nomination should go in short form. I think I am right in saying and I'm sure that one of our
listeners will write in if I am wrong in saying but I believe I'm right in saying that if if a lot
of people have nominated someone in the wrong category their votes are moved to the right category
so I think if like a hundred people nominate Lee Harris in long form editor and Lee Harris is
actually eligible in short form editor those hundred nomination would be moved. I'm gonna say that's
works I think that's works I don't think if you get a load of votes in pro artists but you're
actually a fan artist they're gonna ship them I think it's I think that's only the case for works
that works get shifted around categories but votes don't. Off to the wussfus constitution liz
I in fact have it open right now because I was checking the wording of the editor category
okay so the committee shall move a nomination on an individual ballot from another category to
the works default category only if the member has made three of them five nominations in the final
category. That doesn't say they come but work yeah because the interesting thing is that Lee Harris
got 33 nominations in in short form and 30 nominations in long form and if you combine them
I mean can't predict what the UBH effects would be but that would have got him on the ballot in
short form. This year he would have been he would have been eligible in both. My guess is there's some
overlap there that the people who nominated him in long form will also have nominated him in short
form but anyway Cat Jones, Nicholas White if you're listening to this please write in and tell us
what you do for categories where it's not a work but a person do you shift them or not?
Yeah. Inquiring minds what to know. Does the constitution, does the constitution define work
and person like very rigidly or is it one of those things where there's a dry and whole?
It's just a little hole John. Waff a thin hole. Enough about holes.
But yes that is also very interesting. I do not want to be at the business meeting that tries to
write a definition of person. Me neither. This is a live issue in the artist arguments there's a
whole thing going on about corporations and whether they're eligible so it's not this isn't this is
a live issue this isn't something that's just um yeah can I can can I nominate an AI as best
fan artist? Oh this is going to be a big issue for next year so yeah I've asked to be on Sarah
Sarah Felix's committee but I haven't heard anything yet. Listen as if you could all please nominate
mid-journey in best pro-artist or stable diffusion or darly. It doesn't matter which one I just picked
one. The important thing is we nominate one with enough votes that it would get on the ballot and
then we have a precedent and we all love a precedent and I'm sure whoever is doing the Hugo's next
year will thank us for starting this campaign. In Chengdu. News whose head of wussfuss division
for Chengdu? No one knows. Um I mean I think we do but I think it's someone from China with a
deputy from the US. Do you suppose they listen? I think it's Dave McCarty. Oh Dave McCarty. So if
you know Dave McCarty tell him that the fix is in for AI artists tell him that John put the fix in
for AI artists. Yeah I mean I think it is particularly funny probably not it's funny to me because I'm
not an artist I suspect it is not so much funny if you are an artist so no. I'm an artist and I
think it's pretty funny. I think it's funny okay. Well and also I will say that if the precedent
came out that mid-journey got on the ballot I would be fucking outraged so there is that. I was
very much hoping that the people who made this decision would be rightens and not wrongens.
But it's a tool right? You're a tool. All of these things are tools that artists use.
Good interruption John. I'm so sorry. There's but the Hugo Committee is
Genyu Zhang and Dave McCarty for 2023. Do you want one more little bit of Hugo stats? Yes Liz
obviously we want one more little bit of Hugo stats. Oh the Hugo stats. I went and looked for
categories in which single transferable vote makes difference. So essentially in what categories does
the person with the most first the most first preferences on the first round not win and there
are three. Oh interesting. So one of these is best related work so basically being seen by
Elsa Shunison had the most first preferences and it's not until quite late on in the vote
redistribution that the votes go to never say you can't survive by Charlie Jane Anders which one.
So that's one case and the other case is again are the editor categories where Neil Clark does
not take the lead, invested in his short from from Ogunna Tovri Donald-Eckpecky until the third round
and again in best editor long form it's not until the third round that Roxie Chen takes the lead
from Mavowulf. So those are the three categories in which I saw the lead shift but it only ever shifts
from the person with the second most first preferences to the ending up with the most at the end.
Basically. Okay. I'm going to say performing as expected there that's doing what we want it to do
it's fine. Yeah it's fine I mean it's just it's interesting to me that actually doesn't make
us as big a difference like there are is generally like a front runner or even only two front runners
and one of them wins out. It's not that people are you know putting their first preferences
to something which ends up coming in fifth and has no chance of winning a lot of the time without
having the single transferable vote. I guess people would not vote the same under ST if it wasn't under
STV so it's hard to predict but yeah. The reason you have STV is that without it you get weird
anomalies caused by first-past-and-past systems. Yeah. So so you want to have it to prevent to
prevent voting anomalies rather than to get the right result. I don't think there's a right result
in awards. That is not what you said in the pub last time we discussed awards.
No but it would be interesting is something which had very few first preferences you know when people
had a choice of all the options ended up winning. Yup. You know basically when in a case it was sort
of everyone's second third fourth preference. It seems to be a lot of things people put down as
first preference. For instance "A Way With Children" series by Sean McQuire which won. On the first round
it had 476 first preference votes which was about 220 ahead of anyone else. Interesting.
Thank you very much Liz. And that ends Hugo's Dats Corner for now. And listeners if your podcast
app supports chapter arts there will be a graph and if it doesn't there will be a graph in the
show notes and the graph is the bimodal distribution I got very excited about earlier. You've already
done it. It's a graph. The work will be to make it in map plot live and make it actually look good.
This is a very quick and dirty numbers graph but it is really interesting. You're going to do an
elegant graph. I normalized it by number of ballots that had one nomination. I love that both my co-hosts
are really into analyzing large data sets professionally. Yeah. But you can see that like it is bimodal but
it's really interesting in novel that there's almost twice as many ballots that nominate
five as there are that nominate one. So most people, the mode is that people nominate five
novels which is interesting. And then the one where the bimodal distribution is least apparent I
think is load star but this is going to be part of making this nicer is that the color key is not
very difficult. No sorry best fan artist, best fan artist. Yeah because you've only used six colors
and there's like 20 categories so we might need to work on that. Best podcast is not very bimodal.
It's one five four seven six fifty seven twenty five seventy one so it just is low in four.
Most people who nominate four and this is true in most categories. Most people who nominate four
you know a lot more people nominate five because once you've won't you double age four,
finding a fifth is often is not as hard as as nominated your favorite thing and then finding a second.
Well it's percentage isn't it? Finding twice as many is way harder than finding 25% as many
one hundred and twenty five percent as many I should say. Anyway spinning off from the discussion
of the Hugo statistics one of the things that happened at the business meeting at Tricon 8
was that the best interactive experience slash best game Hugo was passed. This is very good and has
widely been accepted by everyone as a good move and it means that after it's ratified in Chengdu
you'll start to see best games appearing in these Hugo stats which is very exciting. Congratulations
to Ira Alexandra for getting it passed and for showing the exemplar of how you get stuff done
in the business meeting which is you spend five years debating it hashing out the details and
everything outside the Worldcon in people's leisure time and then at the Worldcon you spend
literally two minutes being like well we all think this is a good idea don't we and winning 70 votes
to 15. That is how all business being a moment should be done in my home but very good news in
this particular case. I love that I was like I really really want to congratulate Ira and then
John said everything I was going to say sorry it's really good it is amazing we're very very pleased
for Ira for everyone who's done so much work on making best game happen and yeah we have a new
Hugo hopefully that won't happen too often because I think people are like oh here's eight more
hugas we could have and no don't do this is the last new Hugo yeah it's finished yeah we're pulling
up the drawbridge now guys if you want another Hugo you have to you have to overtake games as
the largest part of the genre and then we'll have a think about it that would be a really how would
you put that in the Constitution the last that last added category you have to demonstrate that
you're better than that one and then you get on we need some kind of Hugo Thunderdome Thunder
Hugo there's got to be a pun in here somewhere one in one out in order to get a new Hugo you have
to recommend fun for actual slaughtering I do think like generally speaking I mean because I am
in general opposed to Hugo proliferation because like I don't want there to be infinite hugos but I
am very strongly in favor of this particular Hugo and I do I'm very very excited that it is on
especially after it had such a great showing when we did the trial Hugo which I think just went really
really well it's true I'm usually like no more Hugo's too many Hugo's no more Hugo's and then I'm
like oh but we can have best game yeah maybe maybe one more Hugo maybe a wafer thin Hugo
wafer thin yeah is it that the category gets added when it's ratified or is it added now
for Chengdu so it is going to be the first one's going to be in Glasgow okay so UK video game
studios this is your chance to yep but also listeners listeners please write in with the games
that are scheduled for release in 2023 that we should be playing that would be very good for a
future episode I think that was the arc to thought podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye for me
it's goodbye from me
hello everyone it is the the Friday I'm reliably informed
allegedly it is the Friday I welcome and I have a question for you
why we have not previously heard the wittish expression hanging out my arse
how how would you not heard that happened I had to look it up on the I knew what it meant
from politics fair enough we are here with Hugo award-winning fans in editor
and all about man about town man with the beards man with a mask man with a plan Mexican wrestler
Christopher J Garcia that's so reductive of all the things that I do but I admit the most
important of them is human being the most important thing you've ever done is the hard
copy podcast that's correct actually which we brought up at our podcasting apple yeah and is
coming back next year because I finally got another tape deck hey all right so I have to have I have
to have tape split you will have tapes there is no question yeah so when you get me tapes can you
do me now can play please yeah so last time christ did hard copy podcast I immediately ripped them
all to my computer I don't know if I can still do that I got I used to get a hard copy podcast from
Jim moat Jim track yeah yes he did a couple I think and apparently in the 50s fans did this all
the time they sent all your time yep audio tape audio recording of material happened at a lot of
world content lugging around the reporters would have been insane um but they're also from 46 I
47 someone has wire recordings of panels from the world column that's cool and that's the one
that it survives insane because it's basically made out of wire made out of a combination of toilet
paper and dreams you know audio recording and fandom goes way way back including there was a
group that did something more along the lines of an app amateur press association that would
pass around these tapes and then they would put your own with them and would go around around
table I cannot remember what they called it I'm gonna say tape thingy and those some of those
exist I would have called it tapper leave this pause in because it's important
Chrissy's staring deeply into my soul with the expression the only a father can have
how how do you realize that yeah resemblance is uncanny yes uncanny now you were in the room
where famous community body the Hugo was study committee was abolished yes can you give us your
live reaction sorry can I give you my life reaction were you in the room as well no I read
a taut disc golf i have a live reaction from that oh no oh no okay
that's fat i'll give you i'll give you my reaction that this is literally exactly what it was
as far as i can tell the the ex chair of the committee and i got the other committee members
decided to fuck around and then they found out yeah i don't i've read the i've read live
blog but what happened i'm like i don't understand what they were trying to achieve i think it was
entirely predictable the world they did achieve was pissing the room off and yeah now it is no more
well yes and i think one of the things we have studied the hugos in multiple dimensions
and time wine yep um and what we have learned is nothing and i think that is actually very
important that there may be nothing to the hugos and we may just have to keep going forward
except for we need an audio you know oh no surely oh god oh my personal preference would be
that we split raspromatic presentation in a way that splits out an audio
audio presentation category but i don't know i am broadly opposed to an audio category i'm sorry
rigorous yeah i'm narrowly but also i think it's something that's at the very early stages of
thinking about it and it needs somebody in the community who cares quite a bit to do some actual
work and that's probably not me for itself it's and i've decided in 2024 it will be the one thing i do
is bringing that forward i think we do need we don't necessarily need the category now i wish
one of the world pound of a few now and then we'll take it on as their uh discretionary
but uh john is also completely wrong wrong uh as usual because we do need a category because the
number of podcasts in our space if you count fiction nonfiction exceed the number of feature
films in our space yet we have a category for future films yes yeah but the number of terrible
fanfics about Harry Potter exceeds the number of feature films we don't have a category for
terrible fanfics about Harry Potter best related work maybe you've heard of uh archive of our own
well best related work can have all the audio and this is not fun theoretically
maybe should it sure will it no anyway it is it's a day of 2020 something 20
so in a year in a year that was in the past after Brandon Sanderson made a podcast with
Mary Robinette and some other people who i temporarily forgotten they won the best related work you go
i believe voice up in a year that began with 20 so were you in the room where it happened
when it happened no that's that's why i asked the chris for his rewe were in the room where i
had i read i was in the room where it happened because you left this fancy land with a mission to go
and be in the room where it happened yes and as i was in the room where it happened and they didn't
get to Ukraine they didn't get to Ukraine because they were too busy pissing around with the Hugo
War study committee yeah and to be fair i don't think they were going to solve Ukraine so i don't
really mind everything no they would have told i i guarantee you a resolution non-binding would
have solved the entire piece yeah non-binding resolutions are you know as we know a fine fine
yeah a long history from the past to today but i think actually it was a strange business meeting
even by business meeting it does sound weird there was a point where someone rambled for like
five minutes and then someone said so what are you actually saying and her response was i don't know
and me chris or this James Bacon and Dave McCarty were all sitting in the back Dave
wheels with laughter it's it's open there i mean especially on a Hugo War nominated
podcast you start talking you realize you don't know where you're going and you're like i don't
think any of this had a point um it's like life the point of all things is the same pancakes
oh well i'm see i'm not needed here but by the way let me say this actually to all the listeners
of this there are gluten-free pancakes available at wildberries and i know this isn't an ad for
better best fiends or purple mattresses but all podcasts need to have a plug and wildberries is
the plug for this podcast yeah i love to i think it's my favorite breakfast so far yeah just saying
something the breakfast here the hotel is great too i was shocked um but wildberries was so good
and sitting next to one of my favorite people on earth the john the rocket coxin yeah because
he's going to have a Hugo come this time sunday night that is the first lead not over long
and secondly it's not night now it's night like god that's me it's night all right all right
all right burn up burn up no burn up all right my favorite breakfast so far this week has been our
capisito which was amazing little Cuban place and i had a plantain omelette which was gorgeous
all plantains are my literal they also had a carafe of uh Cuban espresso to myself oh which was
enough coffee what what yeah hold on i had more coffee since then your people found trade routes
enabled to get coffee yeah that was enough coffee for you yeah yeah with a princely sum of four
dollars and 95 cents plus tax your princes are not as well healed as they used to be apparently
that is reasonable yeah is reasonable no Chicago food is fantastic i haven't yet we have the
minor problem that we have my wife is gluten free so i tend to eat gluten free but we are doing
did you ask these girls to come in oh hello hello i like your get up so for the recording
kevin and Andy have arrived kevin the fast will concert of san jose in uh 2018 and Andy his husband
who is mid chair who is mid chair and who is a man in his own right damn it
dressed as a violent or petty peckettess yes i'm dressed as rainbow dash it's very so dash and yes
i that's very silly it's very good it's very nice it's bright and it's colorful so i have a question
because i saw i saw on whatever day was i passed from the t-weds day i guess that you had redone your
uh mohawk uh as as a rainbow so was that for this cosplay or did you just fancy it's for it was
i was toying with the idea in double all right uh double and i still have the zebra stripes
yeah um but it was too blustery to put the blade up all right yeah and windy so the without the
bangs the front of that four lock was platinum so i can sponge in color so the way bangs were
different color every day in double and the last couple days i actually striped
that for like a rainbow and i was toying the day did going to the phone and then i found this very
silly christmas or which featured a rainbow mohawk unicorn mermaid excellent carrying a cosmopolitan
so how how how did you get how did you commission that christmas ornament i did not i did buy it
and then i made the costume which will be in the masquerade tomorrow absolutely excellent i'm
looking forward to the best so this is like a like an extra extra bonus it's a bonus for your
last grade so what's the what's the best angles in this costume darling um probably about like
probably three quarters you got to get the ass this is exciting audio content yeah christopher yes
have you heard of a fantasy called journey planet you know i have worked on at least two journey
planets as time goes through how do you respond to accusations that we have done more octopus and
you have done journey planets i know sure um they are true they are true actually yeah really
yeah as well yesterday no we only got sixty four yeah we overtook yesterday yeah we just we also
had a discussion about this yesterday i'm pretty sure we're drunk and i've been as a recording
of you and me and drug discussing it so like i'm pretty sure that i can put that before this
yes i know it'll be very funny so that yeah he's like flash back town
i think we did i'm pretty sure i think it's possible i wasn't paying attention
but yes we've done sixty four issues in 15 years yep yeah you know 14 years that's a pretty
good going because they're big undertaking they are big undertakes and a certain john the rocket
coxin has done three with us yes uh two star wars one the matrix the matrix i'm smart yes yes
but it's yeah no it if you haven't read journey planet uh there is guaranteed at least one that
you will enjoy that is true that is absolutely true yes um the most one of the reason was on
like jillipino culture and stuff right yeah jillipino alamat which is sort of the overall term for
urban legend myth uh tradition all put in the sort of one overarching concept and jine martin was the
co-editor and uh we had i think every contributor except for james and me were
philipino or philipina the stories we got were fantastic the art is phenomenal i got to play
with dolly too my favorite ai generator uh it's just it's one of the it when we finished it we
don't always print issues and i decided we're gonna print this issue because i found a place that
would do it inexpensively in color hey that's good i got to print my uh i got to print my um
worth um alison's gonna charge me bad dollar i'm not i don't how many companies you find
to print you know it's black you know i print it black and white right oh i did tell you
our beautiful color images readers pdf mine's also going to have a load of pieces of color
images um you could also run to the fedex and do the printing there but it's real expensive
i'm not running anywhere christ but there's a reason why i printed black
so that we can do printing but that if people watch this look amazing they're gonna have to
yeah i just sneak away to progar ox so they have color print air no chills no there's not a single
color they do have it i blame you for this most people don't have print them damn you liz um
the weird thing is had when i did the fancy lams here last time i did have a color printer i was
actually they gave me a color printer and every it's every division at one point or another
came and printed something on our our printer yeah i see that i could have generated a color
printer probably if i be special at my job no that means you're the best at your job i didn't
really work so i mean i kind of wanted to do it yeah and honestly black and white printer is
it's worth everything it's there's reflecting the primacy of the text the immutable object of
wolf will be more likely the pdf version which will be in full color yeah so i would i would
definitely send your when you're PDF yeah we're not all librarians we're like but you're not a
wash i'm an archivist technically oh you didn't know this that's the guy from the end of the second
matrix here yes which i've never seen uh kind of yeah well it really depends on your point of view
he is very good at saying ergot and that's you know that's a skill i know you said ergot but i heard
ergot and i'm thinking wheat rust is one of my favorite elements i want you to say niche again
niche you mean niche i mean niche no niche yeah it's a niche interest
we're a niche podcast we are an inch podcast see told you i mean and to that i say Chris
to to fire fire uh but we're in the shape of a coaster oh well that's how uh when we're
going to get pancakes from the Cuban place obviously the spanish for pancake is pancake
that's just that's real that's like genuine that's how is that actually yeah because it's like a
loan word yeah there's a loan word but obviously they pronounce it like the spanish for pancake
so parquet oh and see i've around my my grandparents house it's uh well it's either pancakes because
half the kids don't speak spanish uh or it was uh oh i know it translated as pan flat uh
because pon of course bread and flat of course uh a description of a thing that is not flan
yes it's spanish has uh it's spanish this morning had trislet chase pancakes which were
really pretty much so good she's doing a little dance where did you have the truth let's say
pancakes gafafita it's not the same is that the same Cuban yeah i gotta go there how far
ten blocks north maybe like so you've got the not the you cross the bridge left of a hotel and
you walk until you get to a church so it's lift distance not uber distance it's it's ten gaseous
i'm like can i catch a bus it's 38 carcios miles yes so on my tap trip gaseous it we were going to
go get breakfast he said it was about a mile away and he pulled out of the hotel turned right and
then when it's that and then immediately he said right again on the next block and we definitely
could have looked but you were like you genuinely thought it was a mile away and that's why gaseous
a mile is a block because it's 64 garcia miles one mile for every turny planet yes
which by the way 64 64 issues is a long run for an inter planet jennep fancy
true hi inter-demit you think galaxy girl do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do do
hold on work i might go to the vanishing position later always i want to know if the l.a. bit still
exists i believe so i hope so um so i want to go away yes i like that and a spaceship and the
star wolf they're the only right weirdly two of the space shuttle's also have star wars that's true
yeah washington dc is the odd one out but it's also the worst space shuttle they'll go to that one
not the best space shuttle incorrect wait that that that enterprise no enterprise new york is new york
okay so enterprise new york and devver is l.a yeah and discovery is in washington but they've
just pumped it in the middle of a massive garage so like oh at the okay pulling it a massive garage
is so lazily just it is a freaking so as a museum nerd
the technique they're using in that is called visible story yeah and the idea is to make visible
because museums we're recording i don't know if you know museums are unable to show more than a
percentage of their collection yeah what they chose to do was to show their high value if we
don't show this we can't be a museum things as a guy gets a really a mandate to be able to see
the things yeah so instead of having to worry oh is it going to be on display at this time you always
know it's there now their techniques aren't the best but the idea of virtual of visible storage is
you know it's fundamental fundamental yeah but the one at Kennedy is displayed suspended as if
it's like in midlife and the one in a is suspended on the full launch stack and the one in washington
is in a garage but it's a really nice garage oh it's a great garage it's a they had great fridge moments
oh okay really good massive fridge package which garage is this the advisee center the uh
washington dollars yeah they're no wait the dollar source at national and what is it a museum it's
there it's it's only an air and space museums like it is of display oh it's like they're shed it's
like their um well like the imperial war museum at doxford exactly yeah it's not as imaginatively
laid out as the imperial war museum it's good the imperial war museum at doxford is a shed full of
planes too it's several sheds full of planes and they add them to decide which sheds and which
planes that has not happened to the one who just met their real birds okay yeah and like because
you can go from the sr-71 blackbird over to the uh they moved some of the like super old like
late 19th century stuff over there too they have a lot of really cool blanks yeah i guess
as the spritsonian air and space museum like the the part of it that's in washington is also great
so i like that museum when i went but yes you would not be surprised to that it was a very very
long time because it probably changed a bit since then so the last time i was there was when i
worked at the smithsonian was 93 i was at one of the art museums and i've been behind the scenes at
all the things i did not get to go into the spirit of st louis and rude around in the uh
glove box but i know i should have but i did so if you have a badge at the smithsonian you can get
into literally anywhere it will open almost every door and i've done this many times yeah and so
one night me and a bunch of my hootlem friends who were all in terms went and we went into the
national museum american history and there was things like faunsie's jacket are on display and such
we found a staunch of 1940s clothing um one of which was this amazing jacket that fit me perfectly
it had shoulder pads it was great it was an ss jacket oh no and i didn't find this
i'll tell you later oh no are you the bunnies yes yes chris is the bunnies the bunnies but uh no i've
been uh we also found uh two of us had our partner in american and so we went we found the bones of
our people all in the back that's like sitting around and one of what said waiting to be repatriated
and i'll guarantee you they're still waiting to be repatriated yeah yeah no that's bad these things
happen i need to go i haven't seen the enterprise yet do you need to get to the york i have that's the
that's the only one i've seen the other three i have seen enterprise when it was still
in service and when they were sending and devor i saw it fly over mofford field on the 747
uh those are the oh and i thought columbia once on the path uh but those are the only ones
[Music]
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in comfatec.com
used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]