Please note, we have recused ourselves from consideration for the 2025 Hugos in the
category of Best Fancast. I don't think we ever admit anything illegal on the podcast.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 130th episode of Octothorpe, a podcast of Science
Fiction and Science Fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 13th of March 2025. I'm John
Coxon. I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty. And on this incredibly incandescent Saturday
filled with sun, we have some letters of comment. We do. We got a letter of comment from Simon
Bub who said there was a panel on the subject of cookbooks at Glasgow 2024 and the last question was
which cookbooks would be recommended and they recommended the Game of Thrones cookbook,
a feast device and fire which predates the TV show which apparently takes quite a lot of
inspiration from medieval cooking and is very good. I have nothing to add to that except obviously
for you me there's lots of hand pie recipes. We also heard from DC who says they enjoyed our
episode of Watchdog. This is a joke which will only make sense to British people of a certain age.
I'm not sure if that even includes John. No, today I learned that I am of a certain age.
Yay, okay so John is old enough for this one. That gets worse and worse I can tell you.
There was a clip going around of an interview with the actress who plays Miss Wong on severance
because spoiler severance but being in severance was the first time she's ever used like
an acoustic telephone. She was like how does it work? Do I just pick it up and they're on the
other end? It's amazing. I put link buttons on it. Amazing, excellent stuff. Oh my goodness.
Yeah, severance still good. Dave Langford wrote to us to say that he is one of several people who
are following the podcast by reading our transcript. He said it can be a bit of a struggle. What did
it lose to? Okay, it lost to standards and Z bar. Sorry Dave, the transcript isn't going to pick
that one up properly either but obviously if you are hard of hearing it's the only game in town.
If you are one of our listeners who reads the transcript and you can't figure out what we
meant from the transcript then just write to us and we will let you know what we said if we can
remember. Just as a general thing we will listen to the episode, work out what we said and update
the transcript so that future people do not have the same problem. That probably makes a lot of sense.
We won't just search our memories and be like oh no, I don't know and there's no way to find out.
So did you buy any chance do that for stand on Zanzibar? Yes. Good call. I feel like for a lot of
these if you vocalize the thing that the transcript has told you you might be able to work it out from
your great knowledge of science fiction. I'm also quite surprised that the transcripting software
can't manage stand on Zanzibar it will manage at that time because those are three perfectly
ordinary English words so you know. I think also the other this is a bit off topic sorry but the
other thing is that when I used to do data input for a company that was basically putting paper
forms into an online system the other thing you can do when you're trying to work out what someone's
written is if you write the same thing that's on the paper it will very often mean that you are
making the shapes and then you'll be like oh they meant to write this because that's what the shapes
are doing in my handwriting. So whenever I had a particularly difficult form I would just write
it out in my own handwriting to see if that helped. Fun fact people John has lovely handwriting this
might not work if your handwriting is like mine and handwriting is another thing like payphones
that I am not nostalgic for at all. John do you have lovely handwriting? Yeah John has lovely handwriting.
I have been told that I have by partners and friends but Alison but yeah all right so when we
have no show art we'll just get John to write the words octa-thop in nice handwriting. Okay you're
on for this episode. Okay all right thanks for volunteering with beeps. Oh we can all write octa-thop
and you can guess which one is John. Oh that's a good idea. That is a good idea. You'll know
which one's Alison because it's her handwriting on most of the cartoony art. Oh no. Never. I mean
very occasionally but generally speaking no it's almost always a handwriting font of some kind.
Last episode that was definitely not a font was it? Hang on which bit of it? The yup question
mark question mark question mark 100%. Oh no that might be actually that might have been my actual
handwriting. I mean the flow chart I take the point is not your handwriting but your handwriting
has appeared on previous show arts. Yeah I do also have a handwriting font from a used to be able to buy
a software product that would allow you to make your own font and I have a handwriting font
derived from that that I do still use quite often for things because it's kind of like my
handwriting but toidia. Anyway that was probably a digression. Dave also says that we mentioned
the Brunner Appreciation by John Nielsen Hall and Ian Watson and if you want ebooks or your actual
print these also appear in the Taffree Library books Motowaid Reamer which is John and Watters
Wisdom Ian. They're both available there and we did put the link to Motowaid Dreams in the show
notes last time but I don't think we linked to Watters Wisdom so I'm quite glad to be mentioning
it again now. Thank you Dave. We also heard from Christopher Jay Garcia,
hi Chris. Chris compliments our little dramatic reading of his letter although Bella said you
didn't sound enough like us so sorry Bella we will try and do better. We might be the wrong
podcast to sound like your family though Chris I'm sorry or Bella. I think we can capture the spirit
if not the accent. I would like on the record that I try to sound like Chris most of the time and
when engaging with any issue I think what would Christopher Jay Garcia think? Well apparently he
thinks slime pods are great which was from John's cookbook pick and he made a close version of it
when they did the science fiction food episode of Journey Planet. He also is looking forward to
the virtual meeting and says Lumi is an interesting platform there are some US groups that use it
I believe it is used by the American Historical Society so that's interesting if there are like
other non-profit groups already already using it. Chris also says he knows way too much about
seating for the Oscars. This does not surprise me in hindsight. No I mean in hindsight no but I mean
there's basically no topic we can talk about that I would be surprised if Chris popped up and said
actually I know way too much about that. He says that the seating is a result of extreme legal
wrangling and that they even start before the nominations are announced and expected winners
are often in good positions because they have good lawyers. I'm just now imagining like a bunch of
lawyers sitting around in a room trying to argue about whether a certain actor should have to sit
two rows further back than they really want to. That sounds like a lot of hassle. I think there's
a bit of and Mr De Niro won't be attending the Oscars unless he is in a sufficiently good position.
Can't imagine if we have that for the Hugos we like no I will only attend the Hugos if I get to
sit in the aisle seat of Row E. Surely Row C Liz that's the third row. I don't look like I'm too
optimistic about my chances of winning. You want to look like you have the right level of humility
John. So I was saying this to España when we went to an agent track off-ski reading which
I'm foreshadowing for later but I was like one of the things I like about being in third row is
it means I never have to decide when to sit because I always just sit in the third row. But there are
some members of third row that treat this as if it's not some sort of moral obligation. I find this
absolutely baffling. Some have said that whatever row they choose is the third row which I think is
a schism in third row doctrine that I thoroughly reject. So just you know putting that out there.
Do you want to do you want to know a secret? Well I'm not in the third row and have no desire
to be but if I go somewhere now and I think where where should I sit and it's not already
obvious where should I sit. I sit in the third row on the grounds that that's a
crumbular place to sit. See there are there are non-third rowers that are more aligned with
third row doctrine. This is an outrage we should we should be better. I don't know which third rowers
who listen to this are of which schools of thought but schism schism schism is all I'm saying.
Thank you to everyone who commented on Facebook and I am going to pick out from this Pat McMurry
who said who looked at cover art and said before I looked at the title I thought that's a wildly
inaccurate map of Southeast Asia. So I was quite pleased about that because I was worried that
that my artwork which was obviously a deterred clip art I didn't draw the entire world
might not be obvious so I was pleased that at least Pat spotted it and Liz thought it was obvious
if you lived in Thailand. Yeah I think that's fair. Yeah I mean it's a bit like if you drew a map of
the UK and left off Wales do you think you would notice? I would. Yeah it's a similar thing.
But that did happen in an EU map and whoever drew the EU map didn't. So yes take your point Liz
it's a very fair point. I don't know how that happened anyway. Also on Facebook we heard from
Sheila La who said that she wanted to write to us because we didn't get many locks last episode.
Thank you. And isn't going to make it to Eastcon this year but says listening, listening helps
her stay feeling connected to the community and she is going to read the Ministry of Time.
So yes I'm glad about that. Thank you very much for being in. And we also heard from a couple of
people on flexibility and cancellations. So far I'm interested in comments saying
trains have their own legislation that takes them out of consumer protections and I'll put a link
in the show notes and Ivan said he has used different options of flexibility at the premier
in travel or depending on calculations of risk and the ward and he would find it quite frustrating
to find out that he paid more than someone who booked the non-cancelable room and then didn't
actually get anything for the paying more. And that is an interesting part of the discussion
I think which is you know if you have paid because you do want the flexibility is it fair to you.
Does that imply that if that's illegal there should be a some sort of lawsuit to get refunds
for the differences I don't know. Right in if you sue anyone Ivan. Ivan also said your tale carries
the same tone as the weekly stories in local newspapers about people who haven't bought travel
insurance asking for sympathy for those who take fewer holidays. That should get us some locks.
I was going to say I feel the same way I feel a bit about like delay repay and like flight
compensation which is that it seems like this is basically a bonus for people who are aware of it
and able to go and find the right forms and write in and claim it and therefore a penalty to people
who don't know about it. So I feel if the you know if train companies are starting to say okay
you can claim delay repay and tell you about it and announcements maybe hotels should have in
their fine print. This is a non-refundable rate except maybe you can refund it if you write as a
particular letter. Now I do think you might be right there Liz I think if this is actually illegal
the government should probably stop it happening. And so you know here if you're listening
get us sorted. Whether that's Kia Starmer or Kia Egan I don't know but one of you sort it out.
I'm never going to ask Kia Egan to sort anything out. Are we also heard from
Ali Baker Brooks and and Rosin? So thank you very much for writing in everyone. We also have
some follow-up from Liz going to Tokyo. Yes so if you remember last year I went to Japan and it
was great and I saw a really good Peppers ghost effect and we're all very excited including Alison
because Alison loves a good Peppers ghost. Oh I do. Oh yes and as a follow-up I found a YouTube
video which is called Disney's Best Illusion Explained and it's essentially someone called Zach Wally
who I hadn't seen the videos before but I can tell they are a big Disney fan because they're in
like a massive haunted mansion themed room when they're doing their video. But anyway Zach has
basically spent a lot of time looking at little videos of this Peppers ghost and made his own
miniature version of the Peppers ghost and it's really cool and very cute and so you should go and
take a look. It will thoroughly spoil how the solution is done but unless you are likely to go
to Tokyo Disneyland right this minute and see it then I think it's worth spoiling. Yeah I since the
last, since the episode where Liz picked that I have been to Anna and Hogg's house and I have seen
the holiday pictures of which there were lots and lots and lots and I was distressed to see
that Liz was not wearing her who wants to be a millionaire baseball cap which I assume she wore
to all Disney based enterprises but she is wearing ears and then I got to see Anna's collection of
ears which is more ears than any one person needs. Oh god I need to go and Anna and Hogg might be
over I want to see all these pictures. I should explain here that I was basically firmly a non-ear
wearing person on the grounds that at least in Florida they are incredibly expensive and quite
uncomfortable and then in Tokyo basically some people are dressed up but not a lot of people
are wearing like themed t-shirts but everyone is wearing some kind of themed ears and or hat
and they have an amazing range and I found what I referred to as classy mini ears and bought them
and did in fact wear them. Okay can we have a photo for the chapter art please?
Maybe if I can find them they are quite classy they're like blue velvet. Ooh a photo of you wearing
the ears obviously not a photo of you without the ears or a photo of the ears without you.
But yes no it was good to see I would quite like to go and see the um I would quite like to go to
Tokyo Disneyland it looked pleasantly mad in the way that the others do as well.
One of the best things about that YouTube video is that the Imagineer who designed the original
effect was gets in the comments and they have a bit of a love fest where he says how impressed
he is with the guys model of it and the guy says oh my god I can't believe your commenting on my
YouTube video and it's all very sweet. It's very wholesome and it's like oh what YouTube is perfect
for.
BSFA. No I got a newsletter from the BSFA telling me that they had unanimously voted to
pursue charitable status so they're going to do that. Am I allowed to editorialise here?
I mean it's never stopped you before. So they said we can get gift aid on donations which they say
oh well that might earn us a certain amount of year but it also might increase donations so that's
probably quite good. In return for which they do have to submit accounts accounts to the Charity
Commission and a trustees report which might be more volunteer effort than the benefit they get
from the gift aid I'm going to suggest. That's my that's my weak editorialising here that
those those former requirements are quite a lot of work and deciding what you want to do is
constrain your organisation to do a ton of extra volunteer work in perpetuity is not necessarily
the best possible option but there we go. They've decided to unanimously that's fine.
Presumably the gift aid is not the only benefit from charitable status. They note that oversight is
both a pro-andercon because basically you know there's extra volunteer effort but also it's good to
be accountable I think is basically the summary. One of the pros is that directors become trustees
and regular miniatures meetings command entry and trustees become legally responsible and I
think this is a funny definition of the word pro with which I was previously unaware.
Yeah I mean you know I remember when Tony Blair was and became prime minister and the
black government was elected and one of the first things they did was increase a whole range of
government oversight i.e oversight for the things they were doing and I'm like you've you may have
forgotten that you're in power now and it's the job of the opposition to call it to account not
you to hold yourselves to account but there we go. It's not obvious to me that a member
organisation needs more accountability but if that's what they feel they need that's okay.
From my perspective as someone who has been on committee of both the Biersevay and the
SFF one of which is the charity of which is the Coenie Company they're both doing accounts
it's not that the Biersevay are not doing accounts they just now have to do them and submit them
to the charity commission rather than submitting them to not sure if they go on company's house
but wherever so that doesn't seem like much extra regulation. The Biersevay directors would have
responsibility for the company anyway and then they become trustees which gives them a slightly
different set of responsibilities but it's not again not the whole committee it's just
the directors so I don't I don't see this as particularly being that different
and I can see how if you are a member of the Biersevay it might seem better that actually now
there are going to be regular minited meetings because that probably should be happening anyway.
Oh yes so the last line there which is we will be able to use receipts and payments which
probably means as opposed to accruals which is much better suited to our activities and will
make it much easier for us to recruit treasurers that's 100% true. Yeah and the bit I was likely
surprised about is they say gift aid we can claim 25p for every £1 donated this could amount
to as much as £250 an year they're simply saying that the Biersevay can only collect
gift aid on donations can they not collect gift aid on memberships? They probably can't
the membership is primarily paying for physical paper to be posted to people so no that's a service
what if I have a digital membership that doesn't have anything posted to me?
Good question but you are still benefiting from the magazine so they can have that
argument with the charities commission but probably not but this is something that all
membership organisations go through but if you give people benefits for memberships then that's
not then that's not a charitable part of your work right. For example I have been in membership
based charitable organisations where they ended up splitting it deciding which bit is kind of
benefits to members and which bit is benefits to the charity and then being able to claim back
gift aid on so I wonder if there is actually more financial benefits although there will be the
issue of having to collect gift aid registration from everyone and obviously not everyone who's a
member of the Biersevay can sign up for gift aid. So I'm obviously a member of camera and camera
is obviously a charity and camera has never asked if they can claim gift aid from my membership
dues so yeah like I said I can also have been in one organisation which did do this and
they did quite a bit of diligence to make sure they were getting it right and it was some hassle
but it did you know give them quite a big bonus. I do think this thing about them getting more
donations I had a number of times when I was working that obviously I wasn't going to take a
benefit from somebody speaking but you could take a donation to charity right and so they would say
go come along and we will make a donation to a charity of your choice and I always pick the
science fiction foundation and one of the things about the Biersevay being a charity is that there
are certain times like that there are also things like people leaving money in their will to a charity
where if you're making a will you might consider making a donation to a science fiction related
charity that's an option so they may find they get more donations from all of this.
Yeah I mean it's also things like I'm not I mean I know the Biersevay are not going to get into the
app to being booksellers but for example when I donated load books to Oxfam they took my details
so they can get gift aid on the sales of those so if someone you know someone sells a load of books
and then don't want to donate the money the proceeds to the Biersevay I mean they can get
gift aid on that. Yeah they can. It's actually really mad how it works for charities I don't
know if listeners are aware of this but technically speaking they have to offer you the money before
they can treat it as a donation because otherwise it's not eligible for gift aid so I get emails from
my local hospice being like we sold your books for £11.24. Do you want us to send you the £11.24
or please may we have it and I'm like yes obviously you can have it and I do think that's one thing
where I sort of understand why the law ended up like this but I think letting charity shops claim
gift aid on I think maybe that could just be a legal loophole that gets close to some point
that saves all the charities a lot of work because that just seems like make work which is good for
no one. So they don't say right back and tell us if you want the money they say if we do not
hear from you within 28 days we will assume it's a donation. I quite like this process though
because I really do like knowing how much money the British Heart Foundation has made from selling
our old crap which is a lot. I mean I'm not saying charities shouldn't be able to choose to let
their donors know I just think as a legal requirement it's it can't be a good use of volunteer hours
you would think. Yeah it's all done with barcodes. Yeah I mean for the BHF maybe for like a small
charity shop that supports a local hospice maybe not like for Oxfam. Yeah maybe there should be some
scale thing right Oxfam can do it automatically. If you have opinions on charities in the UK
listeners write in. And if you're the BSFA and you're thinking of opening a second-hand bookshop
let me know what about the tumbola do you think that donations at the tumbola are now gift-atable
and do that in that case they have to get a form every time I give them a pound for the tumbola.
Isn't tumbolaing technically illegal and so they probably don't want to make it paperwork?
If that's the case then yeah they're probably not going to be kidding me on that.
You could definitely do a tumbola in a legal way. It's just that for various reasons most of them
don't quite fit the rules for tumbolas but I don't think anybody's paying a lot of attention.
No this is one of those things where I have a confidently asserted we never talk about
legal things on the pod and then I'm like I've finished tumbolas. That hive of scum and villainy.
That hive of scum and villainy which I can tell you raises a ton of money. The fanfans of course
have looked very vaguely into the possibility of whether the fanfans could have charitable status
which would benefit us in a couple of ways and decided it's far too much like hard work.
But the fanfans are not anything formally right now are they? No they are just they are just
well it's complicated because the League of Fads they all have bank accounts right and the League
of Fanfans has a bank account now and has a whole pile of and now has a constitution and officers
and things of that kind because we needed to move our bank account away from Lloyds and the
new bank account requires us to have those things so we have those things.
If you're an unincorporated member society in Britain and you bank with Lloyds which a lot of
people do we are all moving our accounts because they're charging us lots of money.
Another thing I can report from the BSFA AGM is that there is going to be a working group
for the Best Translation Award and that working group involves Farah Mendelssohn, Kevin McVay
and Neil Harrison who are clever people with opinions and I might also involve other people
because I confess I found this out by vaguely listening to Neil in the pub and may not have been
paying as much attention as I could at unreaders but yes so there's going to be a working group
and they're going to sort it out probably. I feel it would be good to have a non-English native on
that group or somebody who was familiar with the business of translation. Maybe I mean I mean do you
know who was at the BSFA AGM who was there to volunteer? It might be that this is opinions from
those people. It might be the plan to put out I think a call for people to send them their opinions
anyway so thanks quite preliminary. John and Allison are you on any working groups of any kind?
Yes I'm on the business meeting operations what is it called? Business meeting operating systems
Discord which is part of a subcommittee the name of which I don't know which is looking at the
business meeting and holding it remotely. It's being chaired in what I would characterize as a
quite hands-off way by Farah Mendelssohn who is basically dumped us all in a Discord and just sort
of let us get on with it. I have pointed out in the Discord that I saw with ADHD don't do well with
free form and more do well with structure and deadlines but yeah it's going well. Most people
are very concerned about how we have meetings with Roberts Rules in remote spaces and I'm like I
fundamentally don't think that's the answer and last episode I talked about my opinions based on
the Python community and I've worked that up a bit more now and I've called it Wepps which stand
for Worldcon or WUSFS enhancement proposals after the PEPs which are Python enhancement proposals
listeners and that started some discussion which sort of peated off but I think once we make it into
I think the plan is for the next stage to be done more in terms of Zoom meetings and with more
focused questions so I think that might be the sort of thing my brain can latch on to more
and hopefully I'll be a bit more able to contribute in that mode but yeah it's fun so far and I
disagree with a lot of the people on the Discord but that's all right that's that's all good and
healthy probably I hope I hope none of them hate me. I've volunteered to help far a little bit with
the process and we are meeting tomorrow in fact to talk about next stages and indeed we're going
to break into a number of small subgroups and the plan is to have some Zoom meetings and hopefully
if there are people out there who are on this group but have been put off by Discord they'll get
engaged with Zoom so it should get a range of voices in there and hopefully some good stuff will come
out of it it's quite hard to see how it's going to all come together at the moment and I think
that's one of the things I'm going to be talking to far about. I like structure a lot more than
many people do which is I recognize because of my neurodivergence. Because there aren't any other
neurodivergent people A in fandom generally or B on this subgroup. Well but I think it's important
to say that I guess I recognize it is I don't mean it's because of neurodivergence I mean it's because
of my neurodivergence and I'm being very specific that I mean my neurodivergent in this case because
not all neurodivergent people need the same adjustments. So I think one of the crucial things
in this committee is that it does report back with something even if the something is we have had
these discussions so far and we're going to keep at it for another year because I think there is a
bit of committees are where things go to die if the business meeting doesn't want to discuss them
I'm going to need to kind of get over that and so having a committee that actually comes back
with proposals and stuff would be good although I think there have been a few recently that have
come back with them so it might be I've got like a an out of date impression but certainly I
remember some kind of like it's a report from this committee yes this committee exists will come
back next year. I don't know whether it will become one of the recommendations of this committee
but I'm going to keep talking about trying to conduct the business of WUSPUS in a way that does
not require why would synchronous meetings. I think I think we don't need to handle most of our
business in a way that is a synchronous way and we can do it asynchronously i.e it can be taken
away and done online with text in ways that don't require everyone to make a specific meeting at a
specific time and I think that would be a huge win for the international part of the community
and I think it would be good and I think it can work because we see it work in other
organizations and I think so I will not be letting that lie Liz so even if the committee doesn't
report John will report but I suspect the committee will report. I obviously joined this group a
little bit late but one of the things I've noticed is that quite a lot of the proposals that have
come forward so far involve more work so that may be because of the people that they come from
but what they what we're seeming to get is a lot of people suggesting things where we do a load of
work asynchronously and then we do all the same work we're doing now synchronously and I think we
need to have some stronger support for ideas that actually reduce the amount of work overall and in
particular reduce the amount of work that has to be done all in one place at all in one time
because those are the things that people find hard and and you know boards boards of international
organizations manage to have board meetings that last an hour and there is absolutely no reason
why WUSFUS should have to have 12 hours of meetings once a year. I think yeah I hope I am not one of
the people who is coming up with ideas that are more work but not unless your proposals involve
doing everything asynchronously and then taking it all back to a synchronous business meeting where
people debate and vote in exactly the manner they do at the moment. No because I think we had a
we had a non-binding vote for the entire community and I think actually having some more direct
democracy in WUSFUS where things get decided by a vote of all members is a great idea
and doesn't require any sort of synchronous activity. Sorry that probably all sounded a little
stoner than I am. Nominations for the hue awards are still open if you have things you wish to
nominate go nominate them and relatively quickly because this issue this episode is going to come
out on the 13th and hue-go nominations will close on the 14th so if you are listening to it on
Thursday the 13th nominations will close on Friday the 14th or technically Saturday the 15th
depending on what times you are in so you don't have long go and nominate things yes but not us yes
not us because we've recused and as previously mentioned I cannot talk about anything from 2024
until hue-go nominations are completely closed neither can I and honestly it's actually quite
tricky I keep thinking about retweeting things and being like oh no I can't retweet that it's
tricky. The Locust Awards that bastion of true democracy the biggest science fiction
democratically elected award the most famous the most important the Locust Award the 55th annual
Locust Award yeah so if you care about that go do that I guess you need to be a member of Locust
or something no if you're a member of Locust your vote counts twice because it's democracy oh yeah
no I think we've made that joke before haven't we we have John is in a callback I'll make it every
time it comes up but because presumably if you're not a member of Locust but you have more than one
email address your vote can count what's for each of them oh no I know I say never do anything
illegal I'm not even sure that's illegal so there we go unclear immoral unethical but but don't
don't be like yes I am Alice and Scott and I am Skalison art I am Malison Dot like because
they're gonna spot that one I am Alice and Scott with a random Cantonese numeral that will repeat
I saw a an advert or mention of something called the Oxford Bloomsbury fantasy summer school
which I had never heard of but it is it is what it says in the tin basically it is a joint thing
where Blooms republishing support a summer school that takes place in Oxford in extra college it is
three days of lectures and talks and it says it is aimed at anyone with an interest in fantasy
literature aimed 16 age 16 or over and I thought it sounds quite academic but when you look at the
frequently asked questions it says it's not an academic conference and is aimed at members of
the public and A-level students interested in this important genre yeah and it sounds quite cool
you can go and check on the uh lectures and talks that they have planned I mean there's not a specific
thing but there is a long list of excellent sounding speakers including Professor Adam Roberts
and there's like an afternoon where you get to talk with Bloomsbury publishing about like the
landscape of fantasy fiction publishing and it sounds quite cool and if you want to go you have to
basically it's free but you have to apply so there's a form where you can put your interest in
express interest in it and why you would like to go and then they'll let you know in May if you
have been selected it looked to me like if you want to just go online that is also an option and
presumably that will not be limited in terms of places but I don't know yeah it does say we plan
to livestream the school so anyone who can't come can listen to talk remotely which I would
infer means yep it's all going to be streamed online but if you yeah if you want to go it's
basically you have to pay for your travel and hotel whatever but it's free to attend which is very
nice so it might be a nice opportunity for someone who wants to spend three days thinking deeply about
fantasy literature and hanging around Oxford the thing you just quoted about streaming um that's
not on the page that I'm on I did a control F for stream and the word stream doesn't appear on this
page so what page do you want this on the FAQ uh nice okay cool like just just just good just very
good and I think having it be in person but like streaming all the talks for anyone who wants to
just watch the talks is very good idea nice and I would not have found this out if it was not for
my glorious co-host Liz and I found out because someone put it on Facebook hey it works sometimes
you're fine good stuff on Facebook very occasionally
I want to plug a thing and the thing is a guff free ebook and in the manner of quite a lot of
free things it says if you enjoy this free ebook a donation to guff is a fine way to express your
appreciation for this free thing um so it is free but obviously we like donations because guff thrives
on your donations um the this is the incomplete chronicles and I think big thanks to Dave Langford
who's done the editing of this volume and he has brought together the known segments of unfinished
guff going under fan fund or get up and over fan fund trip reports so obviously there's quite a
lot of completed trip reports and where we've got them I think we've got 10 now for download on the
free guff ebook site um but we also have incomplete ones for various reasons there'll be a link in
the show notes um the people represented are Joseph Nicholas, Justin Ackroyd, Irwin Hirsch,
Roman Alsadsky, Eva Houser, Paul Kincaid, Damian Worman and Juliet Woods and and Rosin and there's
various reasons why the reports of these people haven't been completed but there's still chapters
and there's lots of good reading in here and I strongly recommend everyone download it and
and have a look at what we've got but thanks to Dave for putting it together and
yeah thanks to all the guff winners who made this stuff available um none of my stuff appears here
because I am in the process of writing my guff report and it is appearing in fanzines um and I don't
think any of it has actually appeared yet but one of the pieces go to appear very shortly on
octa thought and one of the pieces will appear shortly in idea and I am working on two more so
it's good I thought and Rosin had a complete guff report it's just that it was in the medium of
interpretive dabs she did yes so technically there is a complete a complete report but there
are also segments in the incomplete chronicles one like I will note that the taff equivalent of
this document is about to be updated to remove bits of my report from it since my report is now
up but like the report I published was was basically in its entirety available you just had to go
to the fanzines to read it and the bit I hadn't done was put it in one pdf yeah there are times
when most of the writing has been done and it's the case of layout which is taking the time and
then there are times when that is not the case and then there are times of interpretive dance
as Anne showed us quite an episode title times of interpretive dance yes I and to follow up from
previous episodes I think it's also a good time to remind people that taff voting is still open and
you can go and vote for taff we had a brief discussion of this in a previous episode which
I can't remember which one it was but there are some very worthy nominees for taff this year and
you should go and look at their uh what do you call them not manifestos platforms yes you go and
look at their platforms and vote and don't forget to also donate staff
and then shall we do pics ah listen do you want to go first yes shall I go first so
so one thing that Stephen and I like to do is go and see a movie sometimes shocking yes well we
went to see Mickey 17 um which we've seen posters for a couple of weeks ago and Stephen was like oh
oh it's a movie about Wolfenstein and I said what he said Mickey 17 and I was like oh god
so I I thought all of you should now share that pain mhm thanks so we went to the kind of lunchtime
showing yesterday and only afterwards we realized that nobody else has seen it yet I mean it's
it's got reviews but it premiered yesterday so unless you manage to see one of those like
Thursday night shows this was the first this was the first show in in our cinema um so this is the
new film from Bonjourne Ho whose last film was Parasite which won everything um and it is based
on a novel by Edward Ashton called Mickey 7 so there are 10 extra mikis in this one um I hadn't
heard of the book or of Edward Ashton um and having read a couple of people writing about the book I
think that might be because um Bonjourne Ho considerably amended the book when writing the
script for the movie so he so there's a lot of changes from the book Robert Pattinson plays Mickey
17 who is an expendable he he's he accidentally not quite accidentally but he needs to get off
earth for reasons and he actually accidentally signs up to be an expendable spacefarer who is
somebody who gets killed and then reprinted you know dies in the horrors of space because
doesn't be no guys space is very dangerous um and then they just reprint him like on an inkjet
printer and reload his memories from the last time they backed him up and he's good to go again
and it's it's really good um I mean I think this is a very good film that everyone should watch
I can't imagine there's going to be um five better films of this for my 2020 for my this year's
Hugo nominations but we will see I thought Robert Pattinson was not all that good at acting but he
does a really good job of this um the space trip he finds himself on is being run by a charismatic
politician not very good charismatic politician played with great enthusiasm by Mark Ruffalo
so if you like Mark Ruffalo being massively over the top then this is a film for you as well
he has a equally over the top wife called Tony Collette and there's kind of busy
see you stealing the scenes but it's hot this is kind of an anti-capitalist fantasy that talks
about the way in which the capitalist regime uses people up without regard for their personal
rights I liked it a lot I think it's very very good I didn't read any reviews I kind of I started
listening to one review and then went oh about a minute in and went oh no Steven we should just go
see this film rather than reading reviews first about half the reviews spoil the first major review
of reveal of the film it's not a reveal it's going to be a huge surprise to anyone who's ever read
a science fiction book um but there you go so Mickey 17 because he's the 17th version of Mickey
because he's died horribly 16 times most of which you get shown it is a bong doing home film so it's
got some it's got some fairly violent bits in it but it's also quite funny and it's got some good
science fiction and I liked it a lot I suspect the spoiler you're talking about is that also spoiled
in the trailer and posters so almost certainly so don't read don't look at the posters don't
read the trailer so I I very much enjoyed this I'll push back a little bit on Robert Pattinson
not be a good actor I think Robert Pattinson is a very good actor and has done some very interesting
things yeah no he's really really good at this and I was like oh apparently he's better than I thought
I mean I watched high life I mean I say I watched high life I watched the beginning of high life
which I thought was an ex excribble movie but I did not find him the bad thing about it
but yeah Mickey 17 is great it's very funny and when Alison said that they're printed out like an
inkjet printer there's a visual gag there which is very very good several very funny visual gags
but yeah and it's just it's much funnier than parasite and much less stressful but I do now
want a tardigrade and I want a tiny little tardigrade and I want it to gamble I mean they're basically
wood lice they're surveillance I've always thought wood lice were cute so so I I was trying not to
listen to you hard you because I was thinking of going to see this tomorrow hey I don't think
we've spilt heard a thing no I don't think you have I think it's because mostly because it's
honored at a reasonable time and the other option was the brutalist starting at 10 30 a.m. and I
think that might be too much if the brutalist is about to leave cinemas for you then what shit
because you'll probably be able to go to bikki 17 next week but mikki 17 is kind of much easier
to watch than the brutalist everything is probably about to leave cinemas or I don't know to be
honest because it's hard to know when things actually come out and how long they'll stay out for so
but I think mikki 17 sounds more fun than four hours of the brutalist so also for john have you
heard of a thing called a pill millipede well I've heard of pill bugs but that's just the American
word for a wood lice so a pill millipede I assume is like a very long woodhouse yeah nice thank you
oh they're big though it reminded me this film basically is a cross between
arrival parasite and how to train your dragon and it was good I liked it I don't know yeah I don't
know if it'll be on my ballot we will see but I did enjoy it very much and um and also I will say
mikki 17 is a better name than mikki 7 yeah I so the only person I know who's
read this book and had you heard of Edward Ashland ever anyone I was vaguely aware of this book
because it kept him up in amazon 99 p sales and then I saw it had been optioned by mong june
hoe and was like oh that sounds interesting but I didn't know if it was like this is a great book
which is optioned or if it was like the Martian I think it's a little bit like the Martian and
it's suffered so I'm gonna say once again um I understand that there is a proportion of
everybody on this planet who is a young beautiful straight white male able bodied man
and nevertheless do you have to make if you're making a close first person
movie where everything's going to be about this one character and what happens to him
do you have to always pick that segment of humanity to make it about and I think that is
probably also criticism of the novel but yeah Nicholas white has read and reviewed the novel and he's
the only one of my friends who has I think but other reports of it say oh there's a problem with
this novel because not that much happens and I have to say I do not think this was a problem with
the movie I thought the movie had plenty of plot about the right amount of plot for a movie
and it also had plenty of kind of satire and philosophy and all those sorts of good things
that I wanted my science fiction movies I have heard of Edward Ashton because he's written a
couple of short stories for a skate pod in the time when I was avidly listening to a skate pod
so the name does ring a bell and I went on a skate pod to check and I just want to say his
author bio is brilliant um Edward Ashton lives with his adorably mopie dog his inordinately
patient wife and a steadily diminishing number of daughters oh which is a hell of a way to describe
your daughters is like becoming adults and moving out I'm just like I just I might have to steal
that my parents live with a steadily diminishing number of sons um so yes I like that very much
it so he did a he did a tweet that really endeared me to him which was good news
obsessing over every review of your new movie is excellent distraction from obsessing over
every review of your new book yeah he sold the rights before the book came out which is
quite unusual it's probably it's more unusual for newer authors uh shall I go next yes so I've
been finding it hard to find things to pick because I can't pick anything from 2024 and I'm
still trying to my own go reading yes so I'm really sorry for picking something from 2025 guys
yes no go and pick things in 2024 we can't do it anymore or at least not for another couple
weeks and even then probably not anyway so I'm picking something which is completely non-science
fictional so forgive me but I am picking the tv show hacks which is a comedy show um about uh
Deborah Vance who is a legendary comedian who's in the middle of a long long run on uh Las Vegas
and her interactions with Ava Daniels who is a much younger female comedy writer and the kind of
premises that Deborah is Deborah's act is a little stale but she is still a comedy legend
whereas Ava is new and basically pretty arrogant and loses her current job because she makes a
terribly insensitive tweet but it is a terribly insensitive tweet and so the idea is that she gets
sent out to work with Deborah to try and make up new material for her show and I kind of avoid
it because I knew I had good reviews but it didn't sound particularly appealing but it is actually
pretty great one of the people behind it was the writer on like the good place in parks and rec
so it's kind of from that sensibility and it's just it's pretty funny Deborah and Ava are both
terrible people in some ways and can bring out the worst feature but sometimes bring out the
best of each other I think it's main it's main selling point is that they got Jean Smart in to
play Deborah Vance and Jean Smart is she was in uh Legion and Watchmen and Fargo and she's great
basically so she would be worth watching anyway but they do surround her with an interesting cast
and yeah I am really enjoying it I've finished watching series one there is two and three and
then probably four and fives I think it got a lot of awards and it is surprising entertaining nice
if you're in the UK this is on Amazon Prime I'm quite excited about this because I need a continuous
stream of things to binge watch when Stephen doesn't watch me on to watch Telly and I've just
finished drinking series too so this will be great probably go quite well after that.
John Doppick what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna drop in some audio here of me and España drinking
the thing I'm gonna pick so this is John and España Try Shrout by Gravitywell X Adrian Tchaikovsky
X X there's an X look there's an X yes this is España hello that's the beer oh it's quite good
sorry did it make you laugh while you were drinking yep that's actually quite good yeah sort of
yeah sort of got that soft dank juiciness to it that I like in a pale ale yeah sort of sweet a
little honey maybe maybe oh is that maybe that multi flavor that I think of as honey sometimes
yeah yeah there's some more in there it's mellow yeah it has a cool label art with a spaceship
oh it's the cover up for the book as a number yes it is yeah but yes there's a hazy pale ale
and it tastes like it yep it does this was John and España Drink Trout by Gravitywell
X Adrian Tchaikovsky so we went to Waltham Stowe the weekend just gone to hang out with the
esteemed Kleberailey and Mark Plummer and the somewhat less esteemed but still fairly esteemed
Alison Scott and Stephen came and drink beers a great many beers we were nearly thwarted by British
trains so we went to London and we went drinking and the last venue was Gravitywell Brewing which is
in Layton yeah it's a Layton middling but it's it's in one of the arches on to Layton midden railway
station and they have made a beer in collaboration with Adrian Tchaikovsky so we bought some of the
beers and then the next day we went to see Adrian Tchaikovsky launched the book for which this is a
collab and he was in conversation with Oliver K Langmeade and Oliver K Langmeade wrote a book
called Calypso and I have no editorial commentary on the book so Shroud is a 2025 release and so if
I had read it in the last week I could have editorial commentary on that but I haven't but it is on my
it is on my calax and also it is Adrian doing hard weird what happens if you put humans in this
strange environment science fiction and the bit he read was very atmospheric and very good
the beer itself has a QR code on it which links to a PDF of a short story that you can get
if you sign up for the pamakmilla newsletter or you can go and read it on asterisk magazine's website
where it was first published and where there are pictures and where you don't have to sign up for
a newsletter so I've put that link in the show notes listeners because I am kind and nice and I
think we talked about that on a previous episode and again I have no editorial comment on the short
story and Adrian's interview was very good and we went to get hot chocolate afterwards but it does
occur to me that this makes Adrian the quadruple threat because the novel is eligible in best
novel the short story is eligible in best short story the interview is eligible in best dramatic
presentation and the beer is eligible in best related work so I have some I have a sort of personal
I don't which is the one I discovered this beer was available I phoned gravity well to say we will
be door stopping your bar at two o'clock on sunday which is when you open on a sunday and please have
some cans on this available for us to buy because it would be absolutely tragic if john didn't get
one and the rest of us also wanted ones to take her we ended up buying most of the cans that they
hadn't hidden the bar well actually what I will say is it turns out that if you went to the signing
with Adrian and the reading when we got there they were like do you want a drink and they were
like do you want coke lemonade wine and I was like do you have beer and they went yes and pulled out
an entire can of shroud so it was like you can have some bad red wine in a little paper cup
or you can have an entire can of great beer and I was like this is surely a non
no brainer you were wondering on the sunday if they'd have beer at the signing and that was
going to be my next question I want to just big up gravity well a bit because you can probably
get gravity well beers from a good beer shop near you or from their website which is linked in the
show notes their beers are all amazing they are absolute science fiction nerds
so I think this is the first collab they've done with an author if your gravity well right in
improved be wrong but I'd like to see much more of that if you're a science fiction author why
don't you get in touch with gravity well and see if they'll do a collab with you because that sounds
great too 10 out of 10 would drink more and their beers are absolutely lovely some of the gravity
wells probably my favorite beer from available from a small brewery within one and a half miles
of my house and that might not sound like much but we went to 11 tap rooms last weekend and
and they're all one and a half miles from my house or less so go gravity well you're great
keep doing what you do that was the Octothorpe podcast and it's goodbye for me it's goodbye for me
and it's goodbye for me
we should move on to the next bit which is there's no Hugo category for sweet pastries
yeah John do you want to explain why you wrote that in the show notes uh because it means that
we can still pick sweet pastries and Alison can do her croissant story all right so this is where
we're putting the croissants is it is it in this episode or is it going to be a special I thought
it was a bonus special yeah I mean to be honest I can't remember why I wrote it in but I think that
might have been it you just maybe you just thought it was funny maybe do you have that tumbleweed
thing on your cup wall I mean I think it probably was funny at the time often true I mean I feel
like there could be a hugo category for sweet pastries right so as long as they're genre related
I'm like how could there be hugus for beers that's not hugo for sweet pastry yeah I mean
anyway is this a point are we going to keep that in all or or remove it entirely should I segue
from it or just pretend that it never happened the theme music for this episode was fanfare for
space by kevin mccloud in competetec.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license
this podcast will end at the beep beep