So, content. Shall we do some topics?
Topics. Content. Yes. Yes.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 136th episode of Octothorpe, a podcast for Science
Fiction and Science Fiction fandom, which is landing in your back garden and staggering around a bit
on the 5th of June 2025. I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty and the 5th of
June 2025 is a very, hopefully a very auspicious day for me because my daughter is getting married
that day. Oh, congratulations Marianne and Kirsty. Yes, so I am. If she listens to this, she'll be
very annoyed because it's super small. It's a super small wedding. So if you're listening to
this early enough listeners, you can go and gate crash the wedding. Yeah, please don't drop the
podcast until after 11 o'clock. I'm going to schedule it for midnight. Go, go, crash the wedding listeners.
Yeah, don't do that. Just be properly Vince Vaughn about it.
And he says, "A tiny bit worried. I like it." I don't think you can actually do that unless it's
in a church, but if it's in a church, you definitely can. This one is not a church. It depends if you've
got a set of lock picks and a real desire. It's a yellows giving us more clues. It's not in a church.
Not in a church. It's just a building in the United Kingdom that's not a church. I feel like
that's really narrowed it down so often you go. Well, all right, I'm going to narrow it down to
more. It's not in my house. It may not be an Allison's house either. I don't know. Yeah, no,
we're having one of those things in the back garden with like a marquee and you see Don American TV
shows. Having seen Allison's back garden, I'm going to hit the doubt button. Press X to doubt.
Yep, that. For some reason, there are very few outside weddings in the UK.
Right. Congratulations again, peeps. And we got some letters of a comment. Would you like to start
with Chris's letter of comment on croissant's Allison? So we just have the one letter on the
almond croissant episode, I believe, but it was a very good one. It was from Christopher J. Garcia,
who writes everywhere else is weird, but coffee shops in Santa Cruz County are correct.
Here an almond croissant is a croissant made of almond flour. My brain is exploded at this point.
They're also delightful. This is true. Cakes made of almond flour are very good. So
like seriously great. The exterior is perfect. And I very much hope at some point in the future,
I will be able to come to Santa Cruz County and test this theory for myself. I think he also says
that quasins are as limited to Facebook, go easier than elephant ears and as quasins turn out better
with less attention, elephant ears go from delightful to weaponized in less than three seconds.
Where elephants ears are a shoe bun. So yes, I think that's pretty likely. Thank you very much,
Chris. Your letter made my mouth water. So there we go.
We heard from Faro Mendelssohn. Actually we heard from Faro a little while ago, but we've just
got round to doing this. Notice, Faro writes that the Carol Goldman Fund administered by Dream
Foundry has funds to support the tenets of Palestinian fans, writers, artists, etc.
The money has been disbursed for 2025, but in 2026 it will be directed to support Palestinian
fans, writers and artists to attend Urecon in Berlin, which is Metropole Com. You should contact Dream
Foundry for details if you are eligible or that's the link to spread if you would like to spread the
word further and it is in our show notes. Thank you very much, Faro. We'll put a link to Metropole
Com in the show notes as well. Thank you very much to Ming-Lui for writing in and now I know how to
pronounce his surname and I'll put a link in the show notes so everyone else can learn to.
We heard from Raj on the subject of our live episode from Reconnect and we didn't come to this
last time. He says that he was almost disappointed with how coherent the live episode was and so
clearly the solution here is more beer. Raj doesn't suggest the more beer. I'm editorialising
that on the end. Raj just opined. I mean we could say that the solutions are clearly more beer
or having Covid. So I think we should try more beer first. That's a noted biostatistician
no bioinformatician Liz Batty with her medical knowledge. Correlation is not causation obviously.
We also heard from Tammy Coxon on Blue Sky. Thank you for thank you to Tammy for writing
us in and thank you for our nuanced discussion of the whole worldcon AI thing on the previous
episode. We got very few letters on that which makes me believe that we maybe...
Will we... Will we two nuanced? Do you want more hot takes? Let us know. Same number of takes
but hotter presumably. Spicy takes. Spicy. I've only got so many takes in me. But then we have a
pre-show because we have a pre-show where we start doing the spicy thing and Liz tells us to stop
having a log. You wouldn't take off our headphones and go away. There was a very specific situation
where I wouldn't do that. Which this is linked to yeah. Yes I mean I think I said Alice and John
if you're going to have a big Barney about AI I'm going to take my headphones and wander off for 10
minutes. Seems perfectly reasonable. On Facebook we heard from Jan Harley who you know noticed that
our last episode was a little bit late but she hadn't missed our lovely voices because they're
catching up on the back catalog and just got to the end of number 73. I do hope the concerns about
the 2023 Worldcon at that time weren't justified. Mmm spoilers. Yeah I mean I think this is time for
our regular disclaimer that we do not recommend starting for the beginning not least because we
may have been completely wrong about something and had it all come back to bite us. If that's the
case please don't tell us. Don't write. No tell us that'll be funny. Okay. Yes agreed. And we heard
from Christopher Jay Garcia. This isn't Stajavu because he also wrote in on episode 134 and he says
the conclave was delightful and ended up with Chicago winning unlike at the 2006 Worldcon.
Do you know anything about the 2006 Worldcon? It was Worldcon held in 2006.
Do you know this is a deep cut about site selection? I assume so. Probably. We should look it up.
He also says that the Arthur C. Clark shortlist is pretty good and says I've earned a cookie. Brilliant.
Yeah so so I am going to be very distressed if we discover that the Arthur C. Clark shortlist for
the first time in living memory does not have at least one book that causes everyone to go
what on earth is that doing there? I think it does have that book but that book might differ for
different commentate. Which is actually always the case so that's quite good. Yes. Demonstrating
this is a jury award and has scope for a jury with a range of views. Yes. Oh I'm sorry I've just
gone back and looked up the 2008 Worldcon site selection so the one that was held in 2006 when I
think I was not really paying attention to site selection so I did not remember that Denver won
by 12 votes. Oh wow. Wow. So I've got a follow up question Liz. Yeah. Was the 2008 Worldcon in
Denver? Yes. Intrifying. I honestly don't know if that's a trick question. Yes. It wasn't.
Just didn't know that. I did not go. I hear it was good but uh Mile Highcon? No it's called
Denvention I think. Denvention. Okay. I've heard of Denvention but it was very high up.
It's all I remember that there were people who went and said actually the altitude was quite
more of a thing than they expected. Who knew? Anyway I'll pop that on the show notes.
We also had a lock from Ali Baker Brooks who wrote in on Reconnect which was the 2025
Eastcon in Belfast. Great pro black great con amazing program and wonderful to meet so many
newer con people energized by Glasgow in 2024. Um CSI agree with all of those things. Um I think
she says two things she says the con food was very good and very difficult for food restrictions
and number two it was a great venue for many things but socially there wasn't a central hangout.
And we were going to talk about Eastcon anyway but we are going to springboard into it with this.
What do we think on those two criticisms? Well she's not wrong on the food. People who
attend the hotel restaurant I think thought it was quite good and quite good value but there was
an issue around cheaper food such as you know you might like to pick up a baguette or a snack.
I feel like for the hours when it was open there was a cafe near very close to the
hotel and that was quite a good source of you know the sort of things they sell at cafe near
but when you're kind of saying well cafe near is a great choice for con food. Um I think that's
an indication that there's a problem there and if you had a little bit more time to spend
then for some of the times that George's market was open it had fabulous food of many tools
and for some of the time there was a chip shop and apparently that was very good if what you
wanted to eat was a fish and chips which I personally often do but other people might not.
But so it was pretty limited that was an issue. I didn't really notice this because we had
amazing breakfast at our hotel and then we didn't eat again until going out to dinner every night so
I understand the time speaking from a place of privilege here. Um but I therefore didn't notice
that there weren't very many cheap con food options. I think there was a lack of like stuff you could
pick up and take away. Did eat in the hotel restaurant and I had some very nice like
vegetable soup in a baguette which was reasonably priced but then you had to have half an hour
free to queue up to order it and then sit down and wave at someone and hope they remembered
where you were sitting to get it. There wasn't sort of a oh I'll go and pick up like a sizable baguette
option apart from a very few that were in the in the convention center. Uh I mean I thought
having said George's market was amazing. The food there was so good and tasty and pretty cheap and
you know you didn't need that long to go and go and snag some but there are people who can't get
out of the hotel and convention center at convenient times and St. George's market is not open on a
Sunday or bank holidays so yeah I went to the Nero a few times and I very rarely saw anyone from the
con in it so maybe we needed a big sign saying there is a Nero over here if you need a panini.
Yeah I mean obviously a cafe Nero panini was a much better option than not being able to get a
sandwich in the hotel but again it's only open in the daytime and and convention workers in
particular tend to need food at quite a variety of times of day so yes Belfast was great for food
generally but the con food was not always the best. I want to say I think these are reasonable
comments. I am curious as to the extent to which this is worse or better than other
Eastcom venues that we've been at previously. I think it's tricky right because Belfast in some
ways was much better from a food perspective because it was in Belfast and especially like if you're
at the NEC your options to go and find other food might be more limited than it is in a city
that's a capital city and so yes I don't know I think that's got to be part of the consideration
because like the NEC food venues get very busy in the evenings much more than the Belfast ones
would do it as far as I could tell anyway from my experience of waiting in both places
and so it's probably true that the bit act of venue stuff was not very good but the fact that
you have it in a capital city I think changes the the conversation a little bit I would say.
I did think that being five minutes walk from the centre of a capital city was pretty good
generally and and that's actually something that that is is a benefit for Eastcoms it would be nice
if we could hold more of them in cities I know it's difficult. Yeah I think it's a trade-off I mean I
think we've certainly had better and worse cons food-wise I did like the last NEC one where they got
the food trucks the food trucks are good. The food trucks make a big difference too. I don't think
it was logistically possible to park one is a problem but I think a lot of the complaints on
this one would have been solved by one food truck doing like flatbreads with hummus in
and kibabs basically and that seems like yeah we are making trade-offs but there might be room
to solve those whereas there are some places where like if you're so far out of town that you can't
go anywhere and get any decent food in the evening then you can't really solve that as easily.
I did think that Belfast shuts down more over the Easter weekend than a lot of places we've been.
There are a lot more places that seem to close very early on Sundays or were kind of closed on the
bank holiday. It is a long time since we've been to Liverpool for an Easter con but one of
things about Liverpool for the Easter con was that we would we would spend some energy in trying to
persuade local bars and restaurants to stay open. I mean before the weekend we would go in and say
we are doing this people will want to eat if you are open on good Friday and Easter Monday and Easter
Sunday then things will be better for you. I think things have changed a bit people say Belfast is
a lot more open over the weekend than it was 10 or 20 years ago and I well believe that.
Well when we were sort of discussing in committee one of the committee members was like
remember everything will be shut on Sunday it will be a nightmare and then I went out and ate
and drank on Sunday and I was like this seems to be a very pleasant nightmare which I'm quite
enjoying really and so I think you're probably right. I think my impression and especially my
impression from talking to people in Belfast is that it's changed quite a lot since Covid
and I wonder whether the shock of everything forcibly going away for a while made the restaurants
think well if we open on Sundays we'd get we'd might be able to get some more money and that might
be quite helpful and then other people are like oh going out on Sundays it's quite nice isn't it?
I believe Belfast City Council also changed some possibly possibly some rules they made they definitely
made it easier for people to open over the Easter weekend. Well that's the other thing having been
in Vienna a week later on a on May Day or May Day supermarkets don't open in Austria and on
Sundays supermarkets don't open in Austria so like Belfast is very open compared to some places in
Europe. So Ali also talks about social hubs what were our thoughts on that? I was quite surprised to
see this because and I understand that I like bars but I thought that the Hilton bar was placed
almost exactly equidistant from both chunks of programme space so it was in fact a central location
and you could either walk one way through to the conference centre or the other way up to the
Hilton's programme spaces and it kind of seemed fine to me and I spent quite a lot of time there
maybe not quite as much as I like because some of the time it was a bit kind of noisy and full
but most of the time it was great as a central space there was also kind of there were kind of
rather impersonal lobbies for both of the for both of the sets of conference space but I'm not
sure either of those are really great hangout spaces they were good places sort of rest for a
little while between items. So I think yeah I agree with Alison in part I don't think the space was
quite equidistant from the two sides of the convention because I think it probably was closer to the
Hilton than the ICC but it was relatively marginal and I think in general it had quite a good central
space for that but I will also say I'm not sure I'm I've never been a huge fan of conventions that
only have one obvious social area I quite like having a mixture of places to hang out and catch
up with people. Yeah I think it felt like the Hilton social space was good but it was probably a bit
far from the convention centre to be the obvious social space if you wanted to hang out there and
the convention centre social spaces were a bit not we're a bit sort of sterile and convention
and century there was only that really that warm area outside the art show that it had sort of
table and chairs could hang out in then there were some other kind of scattered sofas which I did
like but then downstairs at registration where there were some you know there were some kind of
displays and stuff on I think blood on the clock tower was played down there it's a shame there
wasn't a bit more sort of like social space hang outy stuff that you could do down there.
I think that's obviously going to be a problem with any site that's a convention centre hotel
split but in general I thought the ICC worked really the ICC Hilton worked really well as a
convention site obviously I suspect if stairs are a problem for you as an access thing then having
to get the lift from once the other was probably a bit of pain in the neck but I don't know if
anyone listening has opinions on that please do write in because I'd be interested to learn
well I have some opinions on this because I use the lifts all weekend which is I think the first
first time at Nista Khan I've really felt oh yeah that that's going to make it a little easier for me
and they were fine and that's maybe why I think it's a bit more equidistant because there was
just one little lift to get down to the conference centre or up I'm not quite sure there was one
one lift that took you one floor to get from the Hilton to the conference centre that was
normally empty and there was the main Hilton lifts there was normally a not very long
queue for so it was fine but they were quite slow because as well as serving the Metcenine
I mean that felt like a hotel that really needed escalators up to the Metcenine which would
certainly have it but was built now or made in America yeah rather than that big staircase in
the lobby so you were reliant on the Hilton lifts and they were kind of if you were trying to get
up to a programme item at a point when there were like a lot of people going back and forth to their
rooms it could take quite a long time nowadays hotels like that are built with escalators up to
the Metcenine and then lifts that take you to the bedroom floor because of this exact problem
especially if they've got a lot of conference space but if they had escalators then you
couldn't use the stairs for photoshoot as I did see one day okay I mean you know I can't
think of both stairs and escalators have been primarily to move people around building rather
than to provide Instagram backdrops but what do I know oh the other thing I know the other thing
I wanted to say about the layout which is in general it was all fine except there were programmed
rooms called the board room in both the Hilton and the conference center and nothing was done to
distinguish these so I turned up for at least one program item in the wrong one and went oh no
and of course by the time I got over to the other one which took quite a long time it was full so
boo yeah so I thought the commission would quite well from a flow perspective so yeah it was nice
to look round look round nice to walk round I also really liked that the art show and the
fan tables were next to each other and there was like a place you could hang out there I think
that felt very good and I think part of the problem here is that like it's tricky right because on
this podcast we do a lot of critiquing conventions and I think it's good and wise to critique
conventions but honestly I'm just absolutely thrilled when we get a new venue for EasterCon
that looks like it works even 60% well because it's not like we're drowning in great candidate sites
so the food thing I think like that's an access issue and needs to be taken seriously but
yeah if the bar's in slightly the wrong place it's also a thing you it's also something you can
work on right like you if we went back to site we said hey you know how you sold approximately
3000 baguettes or something you know because I think we do tend to eat on site quite a lot you
know how you sold all these baguettes if you did it again would you mind putting a vegan one on
that you'll sell another 200 then that's a good starting point for negotiation yeah true and you
can't ask them to move the bar around because that would evolve like jcb's and stuff yeah I did
wonder if where we heard in the bar is because it was a bit of a thoroughfare for getting between
places and was sometimes very crowded maybe we needed to keep a bit of a channel there so people
could actually get through because I'm sure I inadvertently stood in front of people and probably
inadvertently stood in front of people in scooters who were trying to get around without going outside
so that's another possible issue but yeah generally like would we go back to Belfast oh god yes in a
heartbeat yeah if it if it was a if it was a viable place to go I would quite happily go back to that
venue on an Easter weekend it was I think generally very good freescon and do you think it ended up
being more expensive significantly more expensive than a mainland UK one or not so much you mean
from the perspective of me going or from the perspective of the committee running it I mean I
mean for the perspective of attendees but it's it's completely you know the comparison doesn't work
for me because I just flew to Ireland so I'm such an outlier it doesn't matter but basically other
people from this was a financial drag for me it was one of the most expensive Easter cons I have
been to baby ever can I just say can you if you subtract the cocktails at the rattle bag from the
cost of your weekend it is funny you should mention a cocktail rattle bag but I had five I think
excellent meals out and a whole bunch of cocktails that and a normal Easter con I probably eat out
once or twice so that's the difference of being in a big city you know top scale restaurants so
so that's that that's what being in a capital city gets so I felt like I had a bit of a Belfast
city break and also I'd spent you know a small fortune in a cocktail bar which I have never
previously done at least a con I don't think so apart from that I think I think it was law
price no no neither the NEC doesn't seem to have any amazing bougie cocktail bars I'm not sure why
that is yeah because it's not you know Belfast's a capital city and you could tell and neither does
he throw strangely no so it's interesting right I think probably the cost of getting to Belfast
by plane was more for me in a spannier than it would have been to get the train down to most
like places that hold east cons the cost of the hotel I would say probably a little bit dear but
it's very difficult to tell because the insane things that have happened to hotel prices since
covid like is that just what it would have it's hard to work out in terms of like eating a drinking
in Belfast probably a little bit more expensive but I think the other thing is that because it
was a capital city we probably could if we'd needed to eat in quite a lot cheaper than we did
because you've got so many options and also the cocktails were delicious but not cheap
but I certainly don't it doesn't stick out as significantly more expensive to me certainly
I don't think it was cheaper but it didn't seem extortionate compared to anywhere else you're in
Newcastle I thought those cocktails were phenomenal value and I think quite a lot of the food that
we at was pretty good value as well sure but I could I could easily have spent 100 pounds on
drinks in that bar over two nights and that is rather more than my usual alcohol budget in East
con and so although I'm not saying it was bad value it was definitely higher outlay of money
yes so the convention was expensive for me but I think every single individual thing I purchased
was good value for money yeah that's good way of putting it I think that's that's the point
so so I just had I just s drank far better than I normally do it and also I saved all my
lunches so I didn't have to spend any better on lunches I think you had a it sounds like there
was a much higher discretionary spend but in terms of travel and hotels which are the kind of non-negotiable
bit it's not actually too much different than many bits of the UK if I wasn't staying in the
main con hotel and that's pretty unusual for me so it would have been 40 quid a night more in the
convention hotel though I think we probably have got about 40 quids less worth of breakfast so
that seems fine um not quite 40 but again like it's a lot easier not to be in the con hotel in
Belfast than it is at for instance I mean Heathrow is actually pretty easy but like there are some
venues where it's very difficult fewer than they used to be because most of these airport and
off-center sites have got clusters of budget hotels around them now in a way that again they
maybe didn't 20 years ago so I mean I think we're going to Glasgow in 27 we're based to the crowd
plaza the first time I went to the crowd plaza there was one budget hotel within walking distance
whereas now I think there are dozens fair yeah I mean there's there's not quite dozens but there's
you know there are there are a sufficient number and then if you can't walking into the town center
as walking distance which is a bit further than it wasn't Belfast then they can as well so that that's
the thing like when is the last time we went to a really truly isolated Eastacon venue I don't
think we have for quite a while hinkley it went hinkley for like 20 years yeah before my time I'm
going to look up the Eastacon venues and find out Bradford in 2013 yeah all right would be the last
properly isolated one I think which one is that and even then like Bradford does he do court yeah
no the Cedar the Cedar Court has some fabulous curry houses with an easy walking just if you
want to be food that's not curry it's a bit harder yeah but it doesn't have hotel it doesn't have any
hotels in walking distance yeah and so they they basically had to put on a bus for that to make other
other things viable I mean I stayed in the fabulous Bradford hotel I remember it was incredibly cheap
but yeah that that hotel is really truly if you don't stay there you are getting a bus or a taxi
or walking very long way but that is kind of the last one right like Harrogate there are a few in
in walking distance including one in the car park basically they've been Heathrow
Talford had some Belfast had them Birmingham has them yeah I mean and that that that changes that
changes your access and your cost conversation right because it means that you've got more options
to suit what it is you need in an ideal world and obviously like most conventions I hesitate to say
all conventions although I think the vast vast majority will set rooms aside in the main con
hotel for people with access needs but obviously there is a conversation there about if those rooms
cost more you also have to make sure you've got like a bursaries program or something to make that
work because people may not be able to afford it otherwise but you know we do do bursary schemes
and stuff so that is that is something we are doing I think else on Easter come if you're listening
to this then the Easter can't catch up has closed I hope many of you listened to them because I
totally forgot and did not I did this Dwellie catch up so after last year I my life is going
through one of its periodic busy times at the moment so I don't know it's complicated it is yeah
so like I probably would have done if it wasn't for the fact that Easter was directly before one of
the big conferences in my field so my my time immediately afterwards has been extremely busy and
that is a typical it's usually quite busy but it's not usually quite as full on as it was this year
so we can only speak for three of us I would be interested to hear from anyone involved with Belfast
how they how their catch up went yeah like did they actually get as many people logging in and
watching stuff as before because it seemed it seemed quite and also the the con discord usually has
kind of trickles of conversation after the con although admittedly some of the time that is due to
everyone reporting positive covid tests and there was a bit less of that this year but it went very
quiet very quickly and it didn't seem like there was also much discussion of stuff people
people watching or if there is a thing where you could you know almost plan to have people posting
in the discord occasionally after the con saying oh I've just watched this and it was great and
encourage that because then more people remember that the catch up is there and also what are we
doing with all these catch ups are we didn't tell for save them to be conversation sent them to
be archived with places that Alison will now take as she was involved the science fiction
foundation fan act org both with sort of statements saying available for researchers but please don't
stick up all the internet and yeah so I think that's about as best you could I do want this stuff to be
systematically saved but it is quite hard unless you said that to your people when you started
which I think we did yes and when if we should be all right it's just just occurred to me
should we be trying to identify a few items before the con where we would like to not only save them
but maybe put them up publicly later on as a sort of taster of if you like this program item why
don't you come to next year's Easter con there'll be another hundred of them yeah so I think I think
you could like I've not really thought about this and like you know this is definitely a
spectacle for future conventions but there's no reason you couldn't say to people are you happy
to be streamed are you happy to be on the catch up for members only are you happy to be on the
internet publicly and separate that out as a separate thing and then you know if you do have
panels where people are happy to where everyone was happy to be on the internet publicly you could
consider those as tasters if you wanted to the only thing I worry is if you have that tick box
does it make people more reluctant to tick the other tick boxes because psychology is a funny
old thing yeah I think maybe you do it kind of preemptively uh you in fact contact all the people
you know you identify some lucky candidates or maybe you look at like the guest of honor interviews
or something and and talk to people on them and say actually would you be happy to do this
totally optional no problem if you say no but just it occurs me it's like it's uh it's a nice thing
and we might be able to use it to be a sort of you know little bit of publicity for us and also
give people on the internet some more content but not give away the whole thing so that people have
to join and watch it there you go idea for you for free future Easter cons which I'm not going to do
any work for have fun yeah no I feel this is all part of future Easter cons take note because I'm
not sure I'm ever going to run another one so do we have anything else on Easter con so one of the
reasons I had a very expensive Easter con was that I spent an enormous amount of money in the cocktail
bar in our hotel um and that cocktail bar rattle bag has just won an award for best bar in northern
Ireland so you see it's not just us who liked it yeah it was phenomenal worth going to Belfast
for I'd say if you like cocktails I will yeah I would say if I ever went to Belfast again I would
be making a trip specifically there there were other places I'd go as well I'd go to region ramen
again because that was great but but yeah no I would I would consider it uh to be a place you
should visit if you go since Easter I have twice been out with people and they have called out a
cocktail bar to me and said I used to really like that one but now it just seems to be so you know
it might spoil you rattle bag might spoil you for Commodore garden cocktail bars I I had a
chilli mango frozen margarita for two dollars fifty so I have not been spoiled there is a place
in Newcastle called Little Robo and they were doing chilli margaritas and they were fucking excellent
so you know other cocktail bars are available I've never had a I've never had a martini as good
as the one I had at rattle bag though so like you know it is it's very good oh the cacao infused
boulevardier that wasn't on the menu because we got to the point where we drunk all the cocktails
on the menu so they had to suggest other things to us yes we did that when we went with tami
cox and we did the words I think we mentioned that in the live episode something we did mention
in the live episode because it hadn't happened yet is that tommy and james commissioned some lovely
sort of spirits glasses with the reconnect logo etched into the sides for the committee and I
christened mine with poutine and ginger ale which was very lovely thank you very much to tommy and
james for that gift and it goes in the dishwasher because it's etched so just fantastic choices
all around and I don't know if we talked about this on my live episode but I wanted to talk about
games when do you not want to talk about games games at the east corner games generally games
at the east con so I this east con is the first east con I remember having role playing games and
social deduction games on the program as actual programmed items and I thought that was wonderful
I think when I think it worked really well I think I thought the games room was pretty good it was
run for them by a local game shop with volunteers yes I think this is a very good wheeze and I think
that is a good wheeze but I think kind of my family walked in and they immediately suggested a
a stupid party game for us to play which probably wouldn't be a likely choice for any family at
the east con but certainly wasn't really a very good choice for us and then we found our kind of
head banging number game and so I did I did play a stupid party game the other day that I liked
but but no so I thought it was a really good idea and I think that probably is a good a model that
works quite well if you can get a game shop that is attached to a games club who will all come in
and volunteer and in return for their badges and wouldn't otherwise be at the con it's like a good
bet to me it ran on weekend it was pretty good they had quite a lot of games including you know
I mean I like games rooms generally so you know I thought it was almost fine I think having a
games club run the games room was very good because I think it divorced the games room from the
culture of games rooms at east cons and I think that was good because as someone who very much likes
games but finds the games room at east con has been sometimes extremely insular and not very
welcoming I think having a company come in that didn't have that baggage but did love games
who was like just happy to run games and be gamers that was very nice yeah I thought the games
room worked very well and it was interesting to me in the light of like the zu con run we did at
Glasgow where that's one of the scenarios like I actually thought having the dealer in the
dealers room who were selling games be the same people that were running the games room was nice
because like obviously that means that if you play games in the game room they might be able to
able to sell it to you in the dealers room and yeah there's there's some interesting
thought being able to sell them to you straight there in the game room was perfectly good idea it
also works yeah yeah yeah because Glasgow did this west end games which is based in Glasgow ran a
bunch of the gaming at the Glasgow Worldcon and I would quite like to see east cons pursue this
more vigorously because I think it might be an absolutely fantastic idea but I also think it might
mean that you introduced the gaming communities in various cities to east con and then they might
tell people about east con so they can might also be advertising listeners it has an issue which is
that we have a bunch of other areas of the convention where it would be possible to give people
privileged access to sell to our members in return for them doing something for the con and we tend
to not do that because we've had bad experiences obviously in the past um but probably a very long
time ago so this might not matter when also I think part of the thing is that to run a good
games room you need a good games library and asking a member to bring a good games library and
stay in the games room all weekend is very different to asking like a local games cafe to do it so I
think that's another element but this is all because this is also largely how games conventions do it
not entirely but you'll often see at games conventions that you'll obviously at games conventions that
like shops run or not shop necessarily but cafes run the board game library yeah yeah yeah I mean I
think the thing we are that specifically having a Belfast is that it wouldn't be feasible really for
the people who normally do the provide a library of games to do it because it was in Belfast and so
that might have meant by necessity we have to go and talk to someone who doesn't need to bring
them across the ocean um I noticed there are also uh snag tights were dealing at Belfast which is a
very nice idea but I don't think they actually had much stock there was sort of there in a sort of
more promotional way and talk to people and to come back next year um because it wasn't really
feasible for them to bring a whole load of tights in different sizes over 12 fast and that might
also be the case actually that selling may not be the solution for them for for east come but they
did have a lovely time so yeah so it's interesting so I would be I mean I have a feeling that we've
done this with a games shop before but can't remember but I think what what it sold was presumably
the games company well I hope they did well out of it because what I wonder is whether we've talked
to them to games shops and cafes before but they haven't known if it would actually be a viable
thing for them to do because they don't know like what the arrangements are between to be guaranteed
themselves did they just come along knowing they'd sell some games on a quiet weekend for them etc
um yeah I went in the game dream we played some games I think they made pretty reasonable
suggestions for us although I think yeah maybe they were uh occasionally pitching it at like a
slightly lower level than they might have if it was a games convention and there were people who
were happy to play reasonably serious games quite late at night but we played some good games
probably depended who you got I think it very much depends because like yeah if they'd
suggested stupid party games to me I'd have been like yes please um and like I play crunchy games
but I also like stupid party games like it's not so much uh only I always want to play super complex
games at conventions neither do I always want to play super uncomplex games at conventions so like
my my taste expresses multitudes oh yeah like sometimes I'm totally happy to play silly games
as long as I can cast a fireball in a game at some point I think it's more just making sure
yeah maybe they get just making sure they pitch it correctly we played the flow board game is that
good I still haven't seen the film but I am informed it is as tense as the film because basically at
any time um you're trying to build like little workways for your animals and anytime away from
come and sweep them away and you have to start all over again and it is timed oh that sounds very
that sounds very stressful yes that sounds much more stressful than I found the film have you played
magic maze have I played magic maze no magic maze is a real-time timed game where you're like a
group of magic users trying to get through a maze which is set in a shopping center for some reason
but you're not allowed to talk you can only use gestures and each of you can only move the characters
in certain directions and so you've got to do it all in real time just by like staring at each other
meaningfully and it's very stressful but it's very good and I very much like it so maybe I would
very much like flow too so it's basically the opposite of space team in that it's individuals
on the ground now in that it's silent rather than space team which is basically the loudest game
it is possible to play yes yes all the stress of space team with none of the noise yeah oh that
sounds good it is it's it's good not everyone likes it some people find it extremely stressful
I have added it to my wishlist oh you're wishlist
Seattle 2025 is on the horizon and we're going to talk a little bit about some things about that
one of the things we're going to talk about is the consultative vote on issues pertaining to
Waspous so there are two consultative votes this year there's a consultative vote on
ratifying the amendment to abolish the retro Hugo Awards and there's a consultative vote on
ratifying proposed revisions of Hugo Award categories for best pro and best fan artist
what do we think about these by the way you've missed the deadline listeners it was at the end of
May the the thing opened for May and May was really busy so we didn't talk about it I'm not
clear why it needed to stop at the end of May and maybe we could discuss that a little bit
because the first business meeting is on July the 4th yep so why does it need to stop by me if
that whole thing is just to get an indication of where members are at it seems like you could
wrap it up basically anytime before that first meeting and it'd be fine but I don't know whether
you two agree I think they still format agendas in extremely old-fashioned ways and they'd wake
some weeks to do it ready for printing but the consultative won't won't be in the agendas
okay no okay that may make no sense then um I do have a strong opinion on the um division of
artist one which is that it is possible that artist does need some revision but this is definitely
not the way to do it and I thought um I think we know the no explanation was given by Richard
Mann and I agree with almost every word of that I basically agree I think I can see why this was
introduced I mean I will note it was struck down in Chicago and a very similar thing was brought to
Glasgow and I guess they're going to keep going until they get it through but I am not sure that
this is how it needs to be changed if it needs to be changed which I agree it might well need to be
changed but um I'm not convinced this is it well I mean they're basically saying that
work in fan artists cannot be sold which seems outrageous just outrageous you know it's it's
tricky isn't it because like if we sold episodes of the fat the podcast that would that would be
disqualifying and that's fair but art is a bit different for historic reasons no but isn't there
a one quarter of your income thing for the fan categories which is is problematic in itself but
differently problematic so they're not so so but saying it cannot provide more than one quarter of
your income would be a start which would be fine for fan artists because I'm sure there aren't any
fan artists who are making yeah yeah there's not much money in it guys no I think I agree I think
I think um there are probably things that might want to be tweaked but I'm not sure this is how
you tweak them um Liz what do you reckon I mean I don't have strong feelings about the art category
because they don't do any art I do see I think what they're trying to do is you know um I think
they're trying to clarify things a bit other than like you know fan art is vibes or whatever
which I do agree with but I don't really personally have an opinion on where you should
draw the line because I'm not drawing the line basically I think what it knocks out of fan
artist is the sort of fan artist who will do you a you know do you a headshot of your d&d character
for 25 dollars or whatever which arguably yeah if you did it by an income threshold instead would
be in fan artist rather than pro artist seems like a benefit but I'm not sure we're nominating those
those people who fall into that category are not really getting nominated for best fan artists
at the moment anyway I'm not sure so yeah I will point out that the things in the consulted
vote I think that were passed by 2024 and are being ratified by 2025 so they've already passed one
hurdle and this is just the second hurdle do you think that consultative consultative votes should
be used primarily for ratifications or do you think they should be used before that because so
far the ones we've done have been for the best indie film Hugo for these two and I'm sure there was
another one that I'm forgetting and that has all been ratification as far as I remember so do we
think that's how this tool should be deployed or or what we reckon I think that's the only way you
can deploy it realistically because the timeline like so the deadline for submitting
motions of business meetings always a month before and then you would have to look at those
select some for consultative votes and run the consultative vote in that month which is a pretty
busy month if you are following the normal schedule of the business meeting is actually at the
WorldCom so it seems like it's something that they can do a kind of consultation on and you can sort
of view it as well the business meeting has passed this let us also take the temperature of this
year's membership as a whole on it and you can do it early enough that it doesn't interfere in a
very very busy time for the Hugo's sorry for the other Wussfuss division having said that this one
I'm not sure why this one needs to cut off in May as we said because it the results won't be out
in time to and the other consultative vote is on just basically abolishing the retro Hugo's so
I say yes let's abolish the retro Hugo's it's time I was persuaded by Fiona Moore's counter
argument on that which is basically we're only to do seven more and then it goes away anyway so
let's just carry on and I was like yeah fair I thought that was not a bad counter argument but
I was also worried that if it wasn't killed then people would start inventing new reasons to give
out new new old awards and it's just so yeah no get rid of them so we were split we were split
I mean if we don't get with a bit of them I will therefore are in complaint in seven more years I
guess at the issue being that if we only have to do them seven more times but if one of the current
cons chooses not to run the retros then we'll come back around in 25 years yeah and when we're
doing the episode of rock 4 in 25 years this it will give us a way to talk about that's fair I
mean I I was torn on it um and I I think I actually might not have cast a vote because I was like
I'm not sure I care enough either way I would like to say that on the Seattle website it says that
Wussfuss is pronounced Wizzfuss yeah so I've just noticed this if you go to the Wussfuss page on
Seattle it says it's known as Wussfuss and then in brackets it says open quotation marks Wizz
spelled W-I-Z hyphen fizz spelled as in fizzy drink close quotation marks and I'm like no it's
Wussfuss as in Wussw-U-ss fuss f-u-ss but not Wussfuss not Wussfuss that would be silly Wussfuss
Wussfuss not Wussfuss or Wizzfuss Wizzfuss yeah does anyone pronounce it Wizzfizz all right I'm
outraged is there something about weird about American the lack of vowels in American English
again where where distinctions just don't happen in some sub-dialects but I'm not sure this is one
of them the problem with saying about American English is obviously that there's quite a lot
of different vowel sounds in American English absolutely yeah but there are sub-dialects of
American English that have fewer distinctions between vowel sounds than you would normally expect
what I would now like to do is ask Andy Openshaw to record himself saying this and send it in so
I can splice it in next episode so we can get the Jordi dialect because I think that might be
quite fun sure what Wussfuss yeah Y-I-F-I-I that's why I think it's pronounced oh I think we should
just please everyone who listens to us please send please send a short mp3 of you saying the word
Wussfuss in the way that you pronounce it yes everyone every listener every listener right in
and then we'll put it together in a big schmorgas board yes please yes and I've been studying Swedish
because I've go to archipelachon next month sorry I had some jam here's what's your non-sequitur
and and it turns out that schmorgas board means sandwich table which is way less exciting than
my concept of what schmorgas board means oh I mean I think that if I showed you a big pile of gold or
a big pile of sandwiches one of those would excite you more than the other I think the only way to
settle this is for a consultative vote on the pronunciation of Wussfuss
Graham if you're listening if you want to do some good versus bad polls on this podcast do
write in yeah look but if you want to do if if I didn't want to volunteer John to splice all the
all the mp3s of Wussfuss together into a into a lovely um celebration of our um
linguistic diversity but actually it does have very good especially if you're
you're listening from somewhere far flung like you know Finland or Newcastle
Jersey Australia Seattle the moon we know it's we know it's Wussfuss is Seattle we don't really
need one of those can I just say I'm looking at pictures of schmorgas boards on um a well-known
internet image search and I can confirm that they excite me very much yes I do but that
oh nom nom nom nom nom nom nom oh yeah are you feeling hungry John ha ha ha right then listeners
that's the Liz signal that we need to progress quicker to picks um so there's one other thing
which is erin underwood wrote an excellent opinion it's uh what does our pet stand for opinion
editorial is an editorial not always an opinion anyway erin underwood wrote an article on
Faztev's Everny about selecting program participants for world cons it is very excellent one of the
things she calls for is a bit more grace and understanding I think one of the reasons why we
didn't get a lot of outraged comments on our last episode is that we are um largely at a chord that
you know it's not too helpful to be very very shouty and angry about some of this stuff and so
yeah we recommend you go read that I would also point out we should link to Jason Sanford who dropped
an investigation into Seattle and it turns out that um his reporting indicates that all of this
was triggered by a single person who had used chat gbt in the process uh and that's what caused
everything that stemmed from there so it's just one volunteer who who used this tool and I'll link
to that in the show notes as well worth worth having a read of both of those I think but we won't
go into detail and I don't have a lot to say about them I just think they're interesting
perspectives I don't know if I threw oh so if it was one volunteer using the tool once
then one of the ways to spun is that um people were in a hole and started digging
there's definitely a point there about volunteers and the lack thereof I'm not sure that big internet
flame wars increase the uptake of volunteers for world cons and so if we want to have more
volunteers to avoid using these tools we might want to consider how we treat those volunteers
when we think that they've done goofed and obviously most of the outrage landed on the chair and the
division head which probably as it should be really but even so it's still not ideal I have no idea
who the volunteer was no I don't think I don't think that is known no and I think that's exactly
correct really there's no point dropping the internet on the head of a person who did this in
good faith probably who never occurred to them probably someone who was pushed for time and
trying to speed things up and didn't think it would be a big issue and yeah you kind of have to
protect your volunteers by saying okay the people higher up who could have potentially
stopped this by being a bit more explicit in their in their instructions or whatever I think
it's fair enough that they end up being the kind of public face of it yeah I agree and you know in
sales defense that's exactly what they did all right let's do picks so that Liz can go and eat
some food yes yeah can we have one day today today I want Hulk Liz at a smorgasbord because she's
angry can we do that for art does that work please that would be great so yeah Hulk Liz at a smorgasbord
yeah that's a nice simple hunt prompt right you and I can be sandwiches and Liz can be eating us
um no too weird too weird all right the rest the idea was good oh I might just do it
I would it's not often you get to see Alice and speechless uh so quite happy with this um right
should we do picks sorry I'm not sure how a smorgasbord differs from a shark kuchibord
more pickled herrings oh yeah maybe convey that in art oh I'm so I am really looking forward to
going to the order dialers of Stockholm now yep good picks who's picking first I haven't picked yet
so I'm not picking first right so I am being the least original and most unsurprising pick in the
history of picks in that I am picking Andor either the second series of Andor or the entire thing
because I have now watched it all um and can confirm it's very good I mean it's good enough that
even if you have always hated Star Wars and think the whole thing is drivel it is probably
worth watching Andor it is that good um it's such a good show yeah it's it's it's great tv is not just
great for Star Wars no it's it is it is magnificent it is so good at as a mass market product
writing a piece of television about what it is like to live in an oppressive empire how that affects
lots of different ordinary people going about that or everyday lives and in particular how
very ordinary people get radicalized and we saw that in the first series and we're seeing it we
see it again quite a lot in the second series um towards so so for people who don't know Andor is
a prequel to the Star Wars movie Rogue One which itself is expanded from a single line in the
opening crawl of Star Wars so they took the single line that said the the rebel alliance had won
its first battle and acquired plans to the death star and they made a movie Rogue One all about that
and then Andor is a um two two series now finished you can watch the whole thing television series
that explains how some of the characters in Rogue One got to where they are at the start of that
movie and there are other characters a well who do not appear um and the whole thing is just
immense in lots of ways and one of the ways it's immense is that the implication in there is that
any other single line of Star Wars could be might be appropriate to be developed into an entire world
that there is a universe of stories out here and including some quite good ones you wouldn't
necessarily know this from watching all of the output of the Star Wars universe at the moment
but it's not all being made for me um Andor definitely is though um it it's not the very end of it
it kind of drifts a little bit it's still great it never gets less than absolutely great but there
are some points in the last few episodes where they're clearly inserting hooks that are going to be
part of the story in Rogue One and so that makes it as a standalone product just a tiny bit less good
we had I'd seen Rogue One once when it was fairly new I don't think I saw it in the cinema but I
think I saw it on television shortly after and um I hadn't watched again and it didn't
really didn't watch it again until Andor was finished but now I have watched it um again and
can confirm that it does the job of knitting it all together very well and also it stands up
very well and now of course I want to watch Star Wars the the one true the one true Star Wars movie
so yeah it's great go watch it fabulous stuff and buoyed up by that I've started we've started
season four of the expanse so you know uh everyone take a drink only three more seasons to go
and the season two gets shorter so you know you're within the finishing line oh are they
yeah the last series only six episodes I got to the end of season three and I thought well they've
kind of wrapped it up here as if there may not be any more so so season four they have to kind of
start a whole new story off which is quite interesting yes so in the in the books the books are
nine books and basically each three books kind of teller loosely like a l'alac I think they're
eight books four to six and by extension seasons the latter seasons of the tv show tell a very
interesting very very good kind of solar system politics story which I really enjoyed so yeah
and then you know books haven't got weird and those good listeners I recommend it too
oonnie i'm behind with it and I don't think it's quite as good as severance but that is sort of
you know it's it's it's a it's a hell of a comparator right like it's not quite as good as
what I would argue is one of the best science fiction series is of the 21st century are we
blessed to have amazing shows like this on television is doing science fiction we really are that we
no longer have to say has there been any good science fiction tv well holo and as a Russian
episode of Star Trek once yep Liz do you want to go or do you want me to go now i'm trying to
decide if I want to start an argument with Alison about televisual sf and fantasy of the 2000s but
I think I will save that for another episode oh yeah no we could put it in as a sort of plot for
yeah I need to you know have a bit more brain and not be quite so wasn't really thinking of the
2000s you see here I was kind of thinking of the 1980s possibly the 1980s that was true but I
think we should not overlook the contribution of stuff from the past 25 30 years because there's
some good stuff there although Alison will probably get to in about 2040 so uh on the subject of
j my course jdinsky uh and bowel on five and good tv from the 90s uh he's moved to the UK I saw
yeah yeah it's quite a big step just to run doctor who
I'm gonna pick a book listeners hey I know right I am going to pick welcome to forever by Nathan
Tavares um so this is a novel from last year it is a novel about a man called fox and fox is having
a very recuperative time and then someone makes him a tiny little clone of his dead ex husband
and he very much enjoys that ex husband because of the death but also ex husband because of various
other things it's interesting I think it's really good I really enjoyed it it's kind of cyberpunki
it's about a great many things and it uses the metaphor that it employs very deftly to talk
about many of them um there is a particularly brilliant scene where some of the characters are
walking through a city and then there is a glitch in their neural interfaces that means the beautiful
lovely city that they are surrounded by kind of fades out and is replaced by the actuality of
what surrounds them which is much much less savory and it kind of comes back to that central
metaphor and uses it to talk about things like anxiety and masking but also talk about queerness
and about what it is to be queer and what it is to be out it talks about protests it talks about
the role of capitalism and technology in our lives and it talks about duties of care and
it's just very good I really enjoyed it it spoke to me on many levels and its ruminations on
unfettered capitalism and on the cult of personality that tends to lead those companies and on
mental health issues all really resonated with me I would very much recommend people read it
it yeah it's really stuck with me and I really really enjoyed it right I haven't read that yet so
sounds really good so good I liked it I'm gonna pick a pick which I honestly don't need to pick
because I'm pretty sure everyone on this podcast or listening to this podcast has either read it
or he's going to read it but I'm going to pick the incandescent biomly tesh anyway you all know
emlietesh won a Hugo for some desperate glory um and the incandescent is the follow up it is
totally different in that it is I mean I would call it dark academia although the good reads
pages full of people arguing about whether this is really dark academia so yeah but basically it's
about magic school if the magic school was basically a private sixth form in the UK and can only teach
magic because magic is basically like Latin it's this super niche subject the only a few rich
schools can teach and it might get you into a good university to study study magic which you're
probably not gonna actually do magic but you might go into another another career like and it is
one reason I like it is it's very explicitly it's a very english school story but updated
to the present day so there is a lot of teaching observations and lesson plans and you know working
out sources of risk and pastoral care of your students and not enough time to fit everything in
the day and I really like that I mean I'm not a teacher but I know enough to recognize what seems
to be a pretty good portrayal of teaching in the modern system I also I do like the kind of the
world building and the magic system that the leaker it is dr saffi walden and that is explained
it is a joke hey yeah I spent a bit time going is that really a joke yeah okay so I really enjoyed
it I found a pretty fast read I found it interesting I mostly like the central romance although there's
kind of a you know a red herring that goes on which is a bit too obviously a red herring and in fact
that would be my main criticism is sometimes bits of the plot were really obvious and I'm not sure
if they were supposed to be really obvious and it's because the narrator cannot see like her
her blind spots and flaws in not spotting them or if they're actually supposed to be a surprise
to me which they were not but even kind of figuring out what was going to happen I still enjoyed it
and what I really liked about it is that saffi is a middle-aged woman and I think you really get
the sense of sort of reflecting on her life and reflecting on her past relationships you know at
one point like she meets her ex-girlfriend and you can really kind of see us seeing like the path
not taken and deciding like where she gets satisfaction from the path she has taken I mean I think
you're all going to read it anyway but it is good it's not quite as good as some desperate
worry but it's still very solid I would not be surprised to see it on lots of award shortlist
next year is that one of the books is that a 2025 novel probably yes yes just come out I think
that sounds very good my opinion people probably know but obviously not quite as good as some
desperate glory is still incredibly high praise right that was such a good book even a book that is
only 90% or 80% or even 70% is good it's still going to be entirely my jam so I'm looking forward
to reading it I am also looking forward to her appearing at NovaCon I mean it's it's part of
expectations right sometimes but glory I kind of went in with people saying oh this is good but not
really many pre-made expectations whereas I went into the incandescent going oh this is going to
be good it's a new aminitesh and so it's got very high bar to live up to so when I say not quite as
good I might be marking it a little harshly but it doesn't have some of the kind of jaw-dropping
moments I think it's deliberately a little bit more internal like a little bit less like the giant
space opera ideas it's just a different book I'll probably get it in hard back and take it to
NovaCon to get it signed all right in that case that was the Octothorpe podcast and it's goodbye
from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
so
so I have a new hobby which really doesn't have anything to do with the podcast but I'm so excited
about it I want to talk about it is it playing games no it's buying games and charity chups
buying games and charity shops because it turns out that I need to go to a for a walk every day
for my health but I hate you know stupid little walk for my stupid mental and physical help and
I hate going for walks absolutely hate it but it turns out that if you say to me would you like to
go for a walk that takes in two or three charity shops and you can buy games I'm like oh yeah no
I'm up for that I come home with sax full and some of them are terrible but some of them are great
so you know it's good and I was gonna mention it in terms of stupid party games we played
that show stack which I paid three pounds for in the in the British Heart Foundation and it
involves you stacking that shows and then removing that shows it is a it is an extremely close
simulation much closer than many video games managed the big video games it's a much closer
simulation than many board games managed and I've picked up all sorts of interesting things
and some absolute junk oh god but I'm getting better I would dare say that's a dangerous hobby
oh fab there's so many there's so many games and charity shops you have no idea and it's good
for the planet right because it stops all of these games being I don't know if it does stop all these
games going into landfill a lot of the better of the landfill anyway because I get them home
inventory them and there's loads of bits missing and I go oh no that is junk every game will on an
infinite timescale end up in the ground you should burn them if I put them in I mean yeah there's
not get burnt bits that can't be recycled will get burnt in London ah because we have we have
incinerator but this is one of the things with um this is one of the things with a card game
called earthborne rangers is is entirely compostable quite more and more are I get more and more games
that have no no non-couple parts yes and then I get I get games from the 70s that are like
giant plastic monstrosities yep they have plastic boards and plastic pieces and plastic
balls and it's amazing sorry that was way off topic but I just it will wear off in a bit guys
shall we do the rest of the show notes oh also I am playing blueprints a lot
excellent for those who don't know um this was actually the reason Liz thought to pick it was
because the art for the subsequent episode we already knew in advanced listeners was going to be a
blueprint of an almond croissant so that was that was uh Liz's inspiration for picking it I think
is that right Liz yeah that reminded me that I could pick it and ruin Alison's life when I was
like shall I not pick it because it might ruin Alison's life oh no I'll pick anyway it is good though
well it didn't so so what happened was that we recorded that episode about two minutes before I
got to the car and went off for holiday on the north north coast where I did not you know I
hardly got onto the internet at all I certainly didn't play any video games and then I got home
and John sent us the podcast to listen to and I got to Liz's pick and I went oh I have not yet
bought that game I should see if it will run on my back and it does and so I have played it quite
a lot but at the moment I'm mostly playing games with my family because it's back on a day weekend so
I'm going to say that I have been playing this is massively massively off-topic now I've been
playing the Zelda game haven't finished yet it's all right oh echoes of wisdom yes yeah I picked it
and I think Liz has played it as well no not yet although I do want to switch though I have I've
played up to about 90% of it and then stopped and this is something I do with a lot of games so I'm
kind of like is this me because you have ADHD no I don't think it is I think I I kind of don't want
just like I did it with Horizon Zero drawn and with dredge I kind of get to a certain point
and go oh if I carry on much further they won't be any game left so I'll just place up the
else for a bit and then come back to it except that I don't it's fair that's been Sadie HD
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod in Competech.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beat
beep
as you can see that you're on the right side.