I am very sleepy, sorry guys. I'll probably wake up while we pod and I've got loads of coffee.
Aye.
But there's no more coffee coming once it, because you know, abandoned.
Witness my intensity for people not being brought coffee,
during pods. This is fair.
I don't know how little man who like, comes all the way to the house with your coffee and quests on.
I mean, I can get a man on a motorbike to bring me coffee from a shop, but I have to go now and collect it.
Hey, I'm the subject of being coffee, bringing coffee during pods.
Thank you. This is of the opinion our diamond slippers are pinching.
It's just fair.
Yeah, if I find there's probably my coffee machine before the pod or something, I don't get coffee.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 122nd episode of Octothorpe.
This episode is coming to you on the 7th of November 2024.
I'm John Coxson.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
And as we record, it is the weekend before Halloween.
Does anyone have any Halloween plans?
I am going to carve a pumpkin and it is going to have the face of beetle juice on it.
That's as far as I've got really.
But I'd like to do a fairly topical pumpkin and that seems like the topical pumpkin for the moment.
We've got a pumpkin.
I don't think we've made a decision on what to carve into it yet.
But I will put a link in the show notes even though it'll be a bit late because it'll be carved by the time you listen to this.
Yes, and then Liz.
How big's Halloween in Toyland, Liz?
Kind of surprisingly big, but mostly as a marketing thing.
Like, I don't think most kids will go out like trick or treating or something,
but there are like Halloween parties and I went for a pedicure this morning
and they'd put up loads of plastic spiders.
I am going to sit in my house and give lots of sweeties to small children
and pretend that I'm scared by their costumes.
Yay!
So, Ispania and I had a party last night, which was folk horror themed
and I will endeavour to put some photos in the show notes, listeners.
But Ispania made like a big round shroud with like a face in the middle
and put bunting all over the house and made flowery wreaths and decorated all of the banisters with flowers.
And it all looked very summer-aisle and I costumed as Christopher Lee's character from the Wicomann.
And then she's like, "Kids won't get this, so I'm going to need to completely redecorate the house before the night itself."
And I'm like, "Or, or we could just give them sweets because that's what they really want."
So I don't know. I don't know how that will pan out.
They don't care what your house looks like as long as there's a pumpkin outside it.
Yeah, one or so. I think it's creepy enough. It's fairly creepy.
But yeah, it was good. And we had a lot of candles, like a lot.
For the small children, I think it will be creepier if they don't really understand what's going on,
but knowing your house looks like you're in mid-tomour or the Wicomann.
I think it'll be creepier if you have like a small wicomann in your house
and you measure them up with a tape measure as they come to the door.
[
For the listener, this pause was intentional.
When we were still in Southampton,
ispan your dressed as like a woman in a white dress and like put blood all over her hands.
And they were kids who were like genuinely like very freaked out by it.
So I do think the other thing is, I think you've got to go a little bit easy on the little ones.
We've got some letters of comment listeners.
We have a letter of comment from Christopher Degas here.
And the first thing to say is happy 50th birthday Chris.
Brilliant. He says on Alison's pick, as Alison was first described with the UFO 50,
and mentioned the Alex, he was searching his game historian brain to figure out what she was
talking about, only for her to reveal it as an alternate history thing.
Tiny fists of rage. So yes.
That is the effect I was going for. I am very glad it's worked for at least one person.
He says that the next one he listens to will likely be listened to on the road to a
lucha libra wrestling show with the kids as part of my ongoing birthday celebration.
Octa thought the gift that keeps on giving.
Now I am a bit worried that that's the episode on grass,
which we did not record with Chris's kids in mind.
Oh, no, that's a lot of discussion of feminism and horses.
So sorry Chris.
We did actually, to be fair, you did put lots of trigger warnings on the thing.
People should check out trigger warnings before plague a podcast to children,
because it might talk about interspecies sex.
Spoiler.
Yes. He also says that he met someone, he was in a Starbucks,
and there was a woman reading alien clay.
Good. I have alien clay on my shelf.
Megas lent me her copy, so I'm going to read it.
We also heard from Jake Sellebrücken's editor of the Ancillary Review of Books,
next in publication. He points out that actually some Hugo Sanquis were made by the Ancillary Review
of Books in 2021 for the discussion of the Hugo results,
so they may be the first Hugo Sanquis.
And they are very nice.
Thank you.
So we will link to those in the show notes.
And we also heard from Zoya Connell,
maker of the Sanquis diagrams, referred to in the last podcast,
suggesting that yes, it would be great if all the data came as CSV rather than PDF,
because that's basically what takes most time in making the graphs.
Always, the data cleaning takes more time than making the graphs.
Transatlantic Bestie Laurie from Hugo Girl said,
"This morning I heard the term 'Sanqui diagram' for the first time in my life,
and then the second time, the third time, and so on until about the 25th time."
Yes.
I mean, we're good. We help people with graphs.
On that note, I listened to a recent episode of Hugo Girl,
and I can confirm that the X axis is the one that's horizontal,
and the Y axis is the one that's vertical.
Graph chat.
Are they a data challenge podcast?
I think we are significantly to the right of the mean on how much we know about graphs.
I am the least data forward of the three of us, and I cannot believe.
I mean, I think if you kind of picked three humans from all humans,
and I was the least data forward of them, that would be very surprising.
Yes.
Because I am in the top 0.01% of the population in terms of my data enthusiasm, so, you know.
I think that's right.
What you've got to remember is that X is a cross, and so the X axis goes across.
Science fact.
I think X axis goes across, and the Y axis goes up, but which way does the Z axis go?
Into the plane of the board.
It goes nowhere because if you've got a Z axis making a 3D bar plot,
and they are nominations, so.
Well, I mean, Liz, I do physics.
We do actually have to consider all three dimensions quite commonly.
Four shadowing.
But do you plot them all on the same figure?
We usually, yes, we do.
I mean, this could be a very long digression.
And maybe it's better because I find isometric plots are the domination,
because what you're basically doing is condensing your three dimensions into two dimensions,
but being super fuzzy about which two dimensions you've picked,
which I find very infuriating.
I strongly recommend Hades and also Bastion.
I recommend Grand Theft Auto 2, which was the correct view.
I was in the XY plane.
And which is on Netflix, and which is on a free on Netflix, I think.
I recommend watching the Twitch streamer who's playing Grand Theft Auto 4 all the way through
with the speed of all the other cars set to maximum.
Anyway, we might have digressed.
It's just possible.
Roman Ozansky wrote in about PDFs.
He basically went through a bunch of different examples in his email of e-pubs and HTML and
whatnot, and what they display us on various different screens.
Later in the episode, we're going to talk about,
"I'm going to try by Donald O'Dekpeki."
And a reporter heard from a friend was that they hadn't read the report yet,
because it was a PDF and they were on their phone.
And they were like, "I don't know what it says,
because it's too small to read.
So I'm going to have to wait until later when I'm on my computer."
And I was like, "Yes, this is back to that same discussion point."
Thank you very much for writing in Roman.
I suppose only old people get to say,
"Trying to read long documents on your phone and then giving up is what's
addling your mind and get off your phones and spend more time on big computers,
ideally ones that are fixed to the wall."
I just don't think that's helpful, is it?
Is your computer fixed to the wall?
Probably not, though.
I mean, I think I'll just be over here shouting at clouds.
Well, and also, is that what's addling people's minds?
Ah, yes, no, I don't know.
Yeah, no, it is.
It's 100% it's that people are interacting with content
through a tiny, tiny screen, which is not well-optimized for it.
So they therefore veer to less thoughtful content,
even more than they would anyway,
because the less thoughtful comment is often monetized to make it more attractive to you.
It's complicated.
I mean, I think we've got to accept that there are millions and millions of people
who do not own computers and will never own computers but own phones.
That's completely fair, but actually that's not mostly the people
who we're talking about here.
But yeah.
But also, I think we have to bear in mind that people who are very good at psychological
manipulation are very good at it at all screen sizes.
And my mother primarily consumes all of her gamification on Facebook through an iPad,
which is a big screen and yet still has all of those traits.
So I would put it to you.
The problem is capitalism not screen size.
And I'm fully up for dismantling capitalism, but this may be a digression.
So I segue into an email received from Emily January, I think literally...
Was it about capitalism Liz?
No, it's about PDFs again.
Emily, if you want to write in with thoughts about dismantling capitalism, feel free.
But Emily does basically discuss some of the things we talked about about publications
last time.
And that like what she appreciated from the newsletter team at Glasgow is that the updates
went on a blog as well as a PDF.
So it would be something which would dynamically resize, whereas all the PIs and so on were
formatted for printing.
And so they look beautiful, but do not resize.
And they say this isn't a Glasgow Worldcon specific program.
A lot of UK fandom is very attached to PDFs.
Yes.
I mean, I do see the point, especially for progress reports where I look at Belfast's
beautiful progress reports and I go, this is a work of art.
These are absolutely lovely, but probably people want a bunch of information they can
read on their phone, where make sure you have all of that information in a phone-readable
way, e.g. on your website, as well as in your beautiful PDF.
Well, in general, I just find people who construct...
Because the other thing that you find very commonly is someone's like,
"Oh, I've done this.
I've made it a Google Doc."
And I'm like, "I do not want it to be a Google Doc.
I want it to be a web page."
And that also, like, because again, that doesn't render well on my phone.
And I don't want to spend my entire life at my computer.
Sorry.
Are you just arguing that you don't want to spend your life on your computer,
so you want to use your phone to do things that are better done on a computer, John?
No.
I think I fundamentally disagree with you that these things are better done on a computer.
I think this is once again an example of where we cannot assume everyone feels the same way
as we do.
And also, I spend a lot of time in their computer.
I spend a lot of time on, you know, trains and public transport and things,
where I'm not going to get my laptop out and read a PDF.
That's the thing, right?
Like, I'm not saying I want to spend my entire time glued to my phone,
but I am saying is that if someone's released some news and I've got five minutes in the queue
for a sandwich, I might read the news on my phone while queuing for a sandwich.
And if you've put it in a format where I can't do that,
I might instead go on Instagram.
It's not that you're competing with me going home and being on my computer to read it.
You're competing with the other things which are on my phone.
Which are much more compelling than trying to scroll in on a tiny PDF.
And I read Instagram more on my phone than fanzines on my phone.
Is that good?
Maybe not.
If fanzines were better to read on my phone, would I read more fanzines?
Maybe.
Would that be better?
Should fanzine fans like pay attention to that?
Maybe, but it's not up to me to say because whenever I do, people get very happy about it.
So are the web-based fanzines that you love so much?
Good to read on your phone, John, and do you read them?
Yeah, because I read most of my RSS feeds on my phone.
Not exclusively because it syncs to my computer, but largely.
My phone might have a bigger screen because, yeah, I do find I do more things on my phone than
I used to because more things are phone first.
There's a great tweet about buying flights on our phone and this is not a phone job.
This is a laptop job or something.
I'm going to have to find it because it's quite funny.
Shall we move onwards?
Maybe.
So we've had a Facebook group for OctaThought for a couple of years now and
anyone who's in the group, oh, you're very welcome if you're on Facebook,
then do join the group.
Anyone who's in the group is welcome to post, but nobody except us ever does,
except that Ali posted a post to the group to say, "Tell us two things."
The first one was, as your intermittent SF for younger readers correspondent,
I have recently become a huge fan of Patrick Kenny.
I've just finished Monsters of Rookhaven,
which is a beautifully illustrated story about the true nature of monstrosity, family and friendship.
And his latest book is Stitch and she thinks he's up there with Francis Harding and Patrick Ness.
So, yeah, go read that chaps and she also recommends the podcast.
I'm a fan of that having by Ollie and I don't know who else.
We met Ollie at Wollcon.
So I have not actually checked out that podcast yet, but it is Ali's recommendation,
so go and do that.
There we go.
And more people should post to our group if you have interesting things to tell us.
This is good.
Thank you.
Having just looked it up, I believe that I'm a fan of that.
It's hosted by Vivian Asimoz and Ollie Rose,
and we will put a link to their Instagram and the show notes,
which has their link tree so you can find out where you can listen to it.
So we also heard from Kat Kobetty, who says, "Let's recommend more of an announcement."
We just launched a new podcast project titled "S8.25,"
which is celebrating 25 years of Strange Horizons.
And we like Strange Horizons.
They are good eggs.
And I also like this podcast because, I mean, it's a good podcast,
but also the sound is beautiful.
It sounds like BBC radio hosts speaking into my headphones.
So we do recommend that you go and check that out.
And also 25 years of Strange Horizons.
That is a lot of Strange Horizons.
It is.
Makes me feel old.
Caroline wrote to us and said, "You may have a discussion in this episode 120
that rather assumed future Wilcons would be hybrid,
and that con runners would be learning better how to embed the online convention into the event."
Smofcon has announced that it is de-hybridting for this year.
And we're going to talk about that in a bit.
And she, Caroline says, "This feels like a bad sign for future hybrid Wilcons."
I'll be interested in your take.
I do think it's a bad sign.
We're going to talk about Smofcon specifically,
but I think the argument is slightly different from a tiny convention like Smofcon than it is
for a huge convention like Worldcon, which has the word "world" in its name.
And therefore, I think has something of a responsibility to try and draw in voices from around the world,
which is also something we will talk about a bit later in the pod.
As for Smofcon, I think it's fascinating that Smofcon has decided that pulling in its
reach and concentrating exclusively on the fans who can afford to fly to Smofcon
is an interesting take.
And I would contrast with Corflu, which has been hybrid for longer than any other con,
and is probably going to continue to be hybrid forever,
because it's a small global community that does not have very much money,
and is therefore contrasting with Smofs.
So when you sign it for Corflu, do you sign it for like a hybrid membership or an in-person membership,
or is it just kind of membership?
Three memberships which are attending, which gets you the attending and the banquet and all the
publications, supporting which gets you the virtual and the publications, which are still huge
chunks of trees being shipped around the planet, sorry guys, and virtual, which is just attending
the online con. And I think they're trying to persuade them to put the PDFs in that, but I don't
know if I'll get that far. If you're Corflu, reach out and tell us what you're doing.
Yeah, I mean, it sounds very much like they offered a hybrid virtual membership,
and very few people bought them. And I guess there is a point where you have to say, okay,
we have very few people who are going to be benefiting from this, is it worth putting our time
and effort in? It is a bit of a problem because you might sign up for virtual very late.
Like, there's no real reason to sign up for virtual, it's not really incentive to sign up for
virtual like a year in advance, unless you really, really know you won't be able to make it,
and you want to support the con. If you're still thinking you might be able to make it,
then you'll just kind of hang on and then buy a virtual membership at the last minute.
So maybe there needs to be like a kind of a cut-off date for virtual or a please sign up early,
even if you're virtual, then we know they're coming. It'd be interesting to know if like
after Smofcon said this, have they received messages from a bunch of people saying,
"Oh, actually, we're going to join virtual," or is it that there really really was low demand?
It'd be interesting to see if they discussed that at any point.
Yeah, I can also say if you're a small con and you have very limited people power,
then that is one thing you can drop if you think it's not really going to be used.
I am going to say two things. Firstly, there's a difference, isn't there, between?
I find hybrid conferences in my day job completely useless because the whole point of going to a
conference in my day job is to have chats with people after their talks about what it is they're
doing and that's very difficult to do in hybrid. And that says to me that the more that your
proportion of the event is about the networking you get in the bar afterwards, the less it is
useful to have it hybrid. And so in that case, I think a lot of what Smofcon offers as a convention
is probably building links between smoughs in the bar afterwards. And I think that's very hard to
do hybrid. And so I suspect there is an angle here where Worldcon, I mean, I know that this is not the
way we think of it necessarily as a trio, but I think there are some people who see Worldcon
basically as a thousand program items that they will go and enjoy and then go home once the program
is finished and then come back the next day and repeat. And that's the thing you can do. If you're
all you're doing is watching panels, you can watch panels from your sofa and you can have an almost
identical experience. That says to me that I'm not sure whether Smofcon doing this is a bad sign
for Worldcons generally because I think that mixture of the reasons people want to attend is
very different for the two. But equally, I do see the point that Smofcon should probably be modeling
best behavior for con running. And this doesn't seem like that. I agree with a lot of that,
particularly the first one, because Smofcon is more than any other convention I've been to,
all about the networking and contrasting with Corflu again, Corflu is all about meeting your
old friends, including friendships made over many decades in some cases. So it's a very different
vibe, even though the bar is still the most important thing. But there's also a thing
like I suppose Smofcon thinks if we're going to do virtual, we have to demonstrate best practice,
whereas Corflu's always done virtual by just sticking a webcam in the corner of the program
to whatever effect that generates, which is about cheaper offering. And that's why they've been
doing it for 20 years before anybody else was because there was a thing called Ustream, I think it was,
and they could just have a Ustream. I think that's the it's it's going for a different thing. It's
trying to attract a different thing. And I think you're completely correct about about Smofcon being
all about the networking afterwards. I went to almost none of the program when I went to Smofcon,
I still had a fabulous time and met a lot of people and learned a lot about com running,
much of which could not have taken place on the formal program. And then in terms of your second
point Glasgow had, I think, 600 virtual members, which is really quite a lot. So there's, if you,
if you build it, they will come for the Worldcon, I think there will probably won't be quite so many
for US Worldcons. There's a time zone thing where it's much easier for North American fans to attend
European conventions virtually than it is for European fans to attend North American conventions
virtually. Yeah. And this goes into a discussion of privilege in con running and a sense of,
I think there's a sense of there can be, I think, a sense of us versus them between con runners and
people who come to cotton. I think that's kind of exacerbated by the fact that if you want to be on
the inside of that loop to do it properly, you have to go to Smofcon, which is a hell of a time and
money investment. And that is tricky. And they're a bursaries. And I don't know how you, and we're
having the same problem in academic conferences, because people are like, well, if you make them
hybrid, you solve the problem. And it's like, you don't really, because again, the primary thing
about academic conferences is the networking. And by saying we can make it hybrid and have people
come from less well off countries or the global south or wherever, you're basically saying,
well, they can just watch the talks, but they don't get any of the networking. And we don't have to
try and make the networking more accessible, because we've done this thing for them and it's fixed.
And it's like, but it isn't fixed. And this really complicated. So there's like a really
complicated discussion of privilege and of wealth here. And I don't know how you square any of
these circles. And it's something I've been thinking about for like four years, and I haven't reached
any answers. So I'm not sure I'm going to solve it soon. Some of the solution is designing good
virtual social spaces, which is something that I have been bleeding on about for four and a half
years and feel like it's never nobody cares. It's only me. I'm the only person who cares.
Yeah. But I'm going to ask, I'm going to, I'm going to ask a provocative question,
which is how much time at Glasgow did you spend in the virtual social spaces versus how much time
did you spend in the physical ones? Yeah, so none of it. So that's the thing. You could design the
best system in the entire world and people in the room still aren't going to want to use it.
And I don't know how you fix that. You have a dedicated online smothcon as well, because that
way you could bring in the voices, but nobody cares enough to make that happen. I mean,
I think you made me slightly talking across purposes, because I think John is also partly
talking about academic conferences. I'm using it as an example, but I think it's very similar.
I think it's similar, but I think there is a bit of a difference when there's kind of people's
professional goals are in there as well. Also, there are definitely some academic online conferences,
quite a few. And it's exactly the thing that you'd expect it to be, which is where it's a
relatively poor bit of academia that has a small global community and online convention. They
have embraced online conferences. They exist. It gets me examples, because I think the vast
majority of conferences have gone back to being in person. Oh, very skeptical, both sides just though.
We're speaking specifically from the scientific perspective.
Specifically, I have been doing a number of conferences where they make the talks available
online, and there are discussions and stuff, and yeah, you're not getting the networking,
but it's way better than not having them online, because it's not a choice between online or
in person. It's a choice between online and not going. I guess what I want to be careful of is
I want to be careful of viewing, putting the talks online as fixing the problem, but I do want
them to put the talks online. Yeah, that's fair enough. Like, I'm giving a talk there. I was invited
to Rome with three weeks notice. I was invited to a plasma observatory meeting in Rome to talk,
and unfortunately, I'm annual leave. So I'm going to deliver the talk remotely, which will be much
worse than going to Rome, but I equally can't go to Rome. So yeah, I mean, it's much worse, but
my students have been to a number of conferences and watch the talks that they would not otherwise
be able to go to, and that's like immeasurably beneficial for them, even if it's not quite as good
as getting to actually go there in person. Trying to look at some of Connor's at Bellweather for
Wilcons doesn't really work, because Smofcon is like 100 people and almost always in the US,
and in US time zones and Wilcons are quite often in the US, but not 100 people.
So I actually think it has not progressed as much as you think, Liz, because I think I've changed
my mind, which is I do think that Smofcon should be doing what it can to put sessions online,
even if people will miss out on the networking, because it's still better to be inclusive as
inclusive as you can, even if it doesn't fix everything, you can make it better. And air
perfect is the enemy of good. And particularly free play. Yes. Well, yeah, and that's the other
thing. So replay for the people, because one of the things I am doing when I'm in person
conventions is not going to the program, but I bet I've seen more of the Glasgow program than the
average person who went to Glasgow at this point. Oh, I mean, I think that probably depends which
average you're using, but that definitely gets into the weeds. So shall we move on?
This episode is brought to you by people who think a lot about very, very niche things.
We can go back to Sankey diagram if you want, John. No, this is I love it.
The previous 121 episodes were also brought to you by people who think a lot about very niche things.
World FantasyCon was held last week in Niagara Falls, New York. It looked very nice,
mostly because I've seen pictures of Niagara Falls a lot, unlike Facebook and Blue Sky.
I haven't seen any pictures. I don't think of the actual conference, but I'm sure it was very nice.
Anyway, I just want to say that they announced the World Fantasy Awards there,
and I just wanted to pull out that the winner of Best Novel was The Reformetry by Tana Rivedo,
which I had as a pick quite a while back, and I was very glad to see that it won an award.
I quite like it when like major awards are sort of kind of apportioned out between different books.
Yeah, sometimes it's something that comes along and means everything, but actually I think it's
quite interesting that we have something that Windsor World Fantasy Awards that wasn't, say,
even on the Hugo shortlist, and also in this case I like it because it's a good book.
So yeah. Does it have dragons in it, Liz? There are zero dragons, I recall.
Okay, cool. Just checking. Do you only read books with dragons in now, John?
No, but it's one an award for Fantasy, and in my head, Fantasy is either Wizards or Dragons.
Ah. This might be quite a limited view of the genre. Yeah, I mean, given that the winner of
the valor is called Half the House is Haunted, one of short victims called Silkencott and Linen
and Blood, and the anthology that wins is The Book of Witches. I think that maybe a certain degree of
horror crossover here. Interesting, interesting. Are you saying that none of those books have dragons
in either? I haven't read them, so I can't rule out the fact that there might be dragons in some of
those. Okay, no, so the Reformetry, I think, was the first pick you made this year because it was,
it is still on my, I've bought it, and I haven't listened to it yet. Listen to it, I'm ready yet.
Oh, was that when you were going to go through all of my picks for the year, and that lasted like
a whole zero episode? No, I'm still going to do it. I just haven't done it yet. Oh, I see. It's got loads
of time. It's October. Yeah, yeah. But this Four Shadows are Complaint, which will come later in the
episode. And Liz, I think has now twigged what the complaint might be. No, I do want to say,
I agree with you. I think it's good when good books get awards, and I think it's good when that love is
spread. I think it's better for the community generally. And the World Fantasy Awards are one of
those awards where there's sort of some public voting and a jury, and I come and I'm how they fit
together. But it does have some jury aspects, which say the he goes do not at all. So it's always
interesting to get that kind of perspective of people who maybe read specifically and very widely
for one particular award, much like, you know, judge science fiction awards, which there may be one
in the UK. And then do we want to talk about other awards? Yeah, I was just going to mention
the Kitchis, which an award that we possibly don't mention very often on here. But there's a nice
piece in the bookseller because they have revealed their final shortlist in that they have decided to
close down the awards after 15 years, which I found quite interesting. Basically, they have
decided that it's becoming a lot of work. And so instead of keep going, they are going to, you know,
go out on their own terms after 15 years with a final shortlist. And I thought that was a very
interesting way of doing it rather than kind of keep going on until there's no interest or until
you are forced to cancel them one year to say, okay, this is the last year. Let's make a success
of it and we'll be done. I think they do also usually have interesting shortlists, although I
confess I've read two books, I think, on this year's shortlist. So yeah, what's on the shortlist?
Well, they've got my which Your Wishes My Command by Dean of Mohammed, right? So that was on the
a graphic story. Yeah, that's also the interesting about the Kitchis is that, you know, they just
have like a graphic novel in the debut novel category alongside non graphic novels. And yeah,
why not? I've read, I've read Your Wishes My Command and I've read In Ascension. I thought In
Ascension was pretty good. That's the one I've read. Yeah, I thought it was, you've read all of
the clock shortlist from last year, right? Um, maybe? Did I say I had? I can't remember.
Basically, I've read In Ascension and I think it's not the best one. So, you know, but it was all
right. It just, I don't know, I don't know, judges, eh? I'm deeply aware that this is coming for me.
So yeah, let's return to this in a year and see. Oh, I will have no comment. No, I've read three
of six on last year's clock shortlist and I would, I would have founded a tough choice. So I can
see how you also might get into, oh, we have to come up with a consensus winner. I mean, I probably
would have given it to some Dashbook Glory, but still, I also really like Jane Gang All-Stars.
I haven't read that one. So the Ursula K. Le Guin Prize has been announced and it's gone to
It Last Forever and Then It's Over by Anne de Marcan. This is interesting because that book
beat out both some Desperate Glory and The Saint and Prey Glor doors to win the award and that kind
of echoes what we were saying earlier about it being good when the love is spread around the field
and certainly I will have to pick this book up and read it because I haven't read it. It sounds
interesting. Yeah, it also must be a weird eligibility period, I think. Well, I think those
be on the wall by Mackayre Johnson is a 2024 book. Let me just look up the Ursula Gwynn Awards
prize overview. We could say also there's a strange rise in view of all the books on the shortlist,
which is interesting. Okay, so yes, it is a slightly weird, this year was slightly weird in the books
published January through March of 2024, what eligible for the 2024 prize, then for 2025,
it will be books published April 2024 through December 2024 to get them onto a calendar year.
So that makes it interesting because it's a set of books that would otherwise not all be competing
against each other. Yeah, because I think like the Siege of Burning Grass is also a 2024 book.
So that's something which is potentially Hugo, eligible, etc. And it's quite good. So yeah.
Having realised that, that's interesting because this might give a little bit of a preview of what
will come up in the next few months for the nebulas and the Hugos, as you say. Also,
Numi-Kare Johnson, always exciting. Yes, I haven't got to that yet, on my list.
This is a Pro Mackayre Johnson podcast. I have a very guilty seat. I was reading lots of books
and then I haven't picked up a science fiction book since Glasgow. I'm still reading the same
one I was reading then. Something has happened in my life. I don't know what. Which book were you
reading? It is the second part of architects, Adrian Tchaikovsky. And it wasn't the trouble
of liking it. I was loving it. That's why I haven't just, because normally I just go, "Oh no,
I'll start to own another book and then come back." That's great. Well, that was what I was going
to recommend. And then you said it was Adrian Tchaikovsky and I was like, "You must read it."
So that tells you where my head's at. Really enjoying it. And also, I want to read it because
for I've forgotten the whole of the stuff that I have read, because I'm old now and I
honestly need charts for novels where it shows me who everyone is and how they interrelate with
everybody else and not in a dramatic persona at the beginning of the book. And a big chart into the
wall. Look, all you need to remember is there's some weird, clam-style alien gangsters who all have
names like The Unspeakable, Aclu, The Raised and The Hook, and then there's some crabs and it's great.
There's some weird things in space. There's definitely weird things in space. There's many
weird things in space. That's really the whole point of the book. And when there's a bunch of
lovable rogues who are forming a motley crew of heroes in a family that doesn't like each other
very much. Yes, I mean, I'm not sure they're all lovable. That's why it's great. No, I mean,
this, this, have I mentioned before that this series of novels reminds me a lot of Blake 7.
Anyway, we are probably off the topic. Yes, because we're procrastinating because we don't
want to do the next bit. Am I going to have to get serious for a minute? Yeah.
Bearing in mind that we are recording quite early for this episode, and so it's currently the 27th
of October, and this news really only came out yesterday, and we wanted to discuss a little bit
some of the discussion that's happening around a report about the author and editor,
I'm going to show if we Donald Ekpeki. There is a report from a writer, Aaron Kens,
that essentially they became friends on the internet and had lots of discussions. And it ended
up basically with what seems to be Ekpeki saying that they would co-author a story,
which is I think Kens is originally, and then Ekpeki made some edits to it, and that they would
jointly submit it to magazines, and then it ends up basically that he submitted it just under his
own name and is very unclear about what is going on and does not reply to our questions and seems
to say, well, this is just what happens in publishing. But I think it's actually less interesting to
me, this one particular incident, as much as what happened when Kens posted this report on Blue Sky,
which is within a day, there were many, many other people replying to the tweet and
quoting this tweet saying essentially that they had also had poor experiences with Ekpeki and
that the whole thing made them very uncomfortable. And it just seemed like one of these things
where someone being willing to talk about one incident made the floodgates break, and then everyone
started discussing other incidents that had happened. And so what I found most interesting,
I think, was probably a thread from Gotten Batya, which is safe for those who don't know Ekpeki
that he is a writer from Nigeria, who's been nominated for multiple awards and edited multiple
anthologies, and Batya is a writer from India, and that Batya's thread basically says, you know,
he doesn't want to talk about one individual, but talk about kind of the industry climate that
enabled it, and I think that is very interesting, and maybe there are reflections and lessons for
us as basically a bunch of white British people. One of Batya's points is that when we value
diversity andclusiveness, is our kind of white guilt getting in the way, and is that being leveraged,
especially by people who can take advantage of the situation? And the things he particularly
picks out are that Ekpeki had a lot of fundraisers repeatedly for coming to Wilcon and to other
conventions, especially when he'd been nominated for awards, and is some of your white guilt
basically saying, okay, we should give to this person's fundraiser, which really benefits only
them, and is there a better way for us to kind of direct our efforts and funding into trying to
break down some of these structural barriers that exist? I'm not sure I have personally a huge amount
to add other than like there are obviously people discussing this that are worth listening to,
but I do wonder if we should really be kind of rethinking what fundraisers we boost, what we promote,
what we give to, and whether that is actually helping kind of the structural structural issues
that need to be addressed, whether we're sort of making ourselves feel better by saying yes,
this person can have a trip to a convention, and it's not to say you shouldn't give to people's
fundraisers, but really think about kind of, are you doing this because you get some kind of warm
fuzzy feelings for having helped someone travel to a convention they would not otherwise be able
to attend? I want to give some props to Erin Kairns, who is the person who blew the whistle here,
because she posted a tweet in June saying this is a thing that's going on, and it kind of sank
without trace, and rather than just going oh well it just must be me then, she then went off and
wrote a dossier which is what we've got now, and that has actually triggered the discussion,
and I think actually getting into the bigger part of it, I stopped contributing to one
global fund, because I observed that the same people were getting repeated trips, and I really,
I'm a big fan of that not happening, when you see the same person getting trips to multiple
conventions, you start going hmm, and and, and, pecky's not the first example of that,
and not the first example of that where I've seen people getting multiple
trips to conventions and gone well why, why this person, why not more people, and, and obviously
there it's very complicated, because there are people who are extremely valuable members of
community whose engagement is predicated on repeated fundraising and repeated bursaries, so
it's incredibly complicated. Batty does mention in his thread that most of the people in the global
south who are involved in writing and reading science fiction are part of the privileged part
of their own communities as well, which I think is, is a fair point. I can't solve structural
inequality in the world individually, I don't know what to do. Yeah, and the other thing is that
there have been trolls for a while basically saying like oh you know he doesn't write his own staff,
and it's always awkward when you, you end up like saying the same stuff as people who are
saying it because they're massive racists, right? It's very frustrating because firstly I think
what he's done is noticed that our community is very vulnerable to this kind of thing because we
want to lift people up who are from marginalised background, which I think is something that is
to our credit, but he has noticed that you can get quite a lot of personal benefit out of that
and has exploited that. And secondly he, I think next time someone like this is coming up who is
from the global south and who is a very talented editor and who is not doing this in a negative way,
those racist trolls are going to be twice as loud and that is very annoying, just very heartbreaking.
Yeah, no, but whenever you, whenever you find that you're on the side of the racist trolls,
you have to remember that a stop clock is right twice a day. Still never, still never feels good
though, yeah. You know, they're still wrong, right? It's not a good feeling. Yeah, and I think,
I want to say additionally a lot of the stuff which has come out, so Aaron Kairns' story is about
him submitting something to an anthology that was essentially their joint work under his own name,
but a lot of the other things that people have mentioned are just, they're not things which are
like completely unethical, they're just things which feel a bit like, oh this person is definitely
trying to use my goodwill purely to further their own career. They're not things that you might call
out as being specific or ethical things, but the things like pushing people to nominate you for awards
or these things where you might not call them out as isolated incidents, but now they kind of go
into a pattern of, okay, this person was definitely aware of how they could best get themselves
award nominations, and then if you have award nominations, then that's the reason why you should
be running a fundraiser to go to a convention, and then once you do that, maybe you'll become the
guest runner at a convention, and you know, it's snowballing to boost your own career, and I'm sure
there's tons of people who have done this in the science fiction world who have taken a
advantage of connections, and you want to have connections with people, and it's just kind of
pushing that a step too far, but then to submit something to a magazine under your own name,
which is not your own work, is over the line, and that's where it came out.
Yeah, yes, and there are other examples of just slightly off behavior, like I have a personal
interaction with Ickpecky, which might be a good one, and there's lots of little things like that.
Sorry, just be clear, are you saying you had one, or are the people saying they had one?
No, I had one. Oh, okay, I had a very classic conversation with Ickpecky, a very classic sort
of conversation that people have. If you are a Hugo finalist for a podcast, and you say,
"Hi, great to meet you, really, and by your stuff, I'm Alison from Oxford, and they look at you as if
they are a piece of chopped liver and they walk away." And that is not unique to one, this one person,
but it is a conversation, it is the only conversation I have ever had with that person.
I want to highlight something really quickly here, which this goes back, I think, there are
parallels with this and the discussion we're having about some off-con, which the other thing is,
our field is so much about who you know, and if you can get into a bubble or multiple bubbles,
you have a significantly different time in fandom than you do if you don't.
It's not wrong to do things that will attract attention to do things that get awards,
that do things that network effectively with people who are influential in your area.
I think this is something that we'd hope that a lot more creators from the Global South would
be able to do now and in the future. I think what is wrong is not bringing your mates along with you
when you do this. What I want to say is because that kind of networking relies on you don't go
to a single convention and build that network, you go to many conventions over years and build
that network. And so it's tricky, right? Because Egepeke got lots of funding to come to
conventions repeatedly, but if we don't bring people to conventions repeatedly,
we're also not bringing them into the network. And so I don't know how you square that circle,
because I agree with you from what you said earlier, I agree that we want to make sure that
this is lots of people and we're bringing lots of people over. But the other thing is if we bring
lots of people over, we bring them once each, that's also not going to bring them into the
community. I don't know how you answer these questions. I think they're hard questions.
And they're all tied up in privilege. And I think it's very difficult to dismantle.
You have fanzines, you have good online forums where people have good and ongoing discussions
about conventions, about sorry, about science fiction. You have online conventions that can be
attended for very small amounts of money globally. You have these networks. I'm part of a community
in SF where the network has been created over many decades through these interpersonal engagements
that do not cost a lot of money. And it's actually very easy to get it to that. You just have to
read a few fanzines and write some letters. But that's not the, that's really not the network
we're talking about here. We're talking about publishing. We're talking about, you know,
selling your work and networking with editors. I will also say, even if you're talking about
con running, that's not how you get into the con running. You go to smothcon, you go to worldcon,
you go to the parties, because the con runners aren't reading and writing articles, or I mean,
they are. But that's not the primary way you get into that bubble. That's kind of what I mean.
Like, I think there are bubbles you can get into. But speaking of someone who can't afford to go
to very many US conventions, and I know who goes to more US conventions than many people,
I am on the outside of a lot of these bubbles because I do not have the networks that allow me
to get into the middle of them. I am quite connected. So how the hell you do that if you're from the
global south? I have no idea. But I don't think the answer is reading discussion forums, because I
do that and I still feel like I'm on the outside. I run a Hugo award winning podcast,
which explores these issues and I still feel like I'm on the outside. So like, I don't
know how you bridge those gaps, but I don't think it's as simple as writing letters to fanzines. I
think that's a very reductive answer that I think pretends that the issue is much less difficult than
it is. No, sorry, it is fair. Certainly. But it's hard. It's hard. I do think it's not fanzines,
though. I do think online communities are part of what can make this easier. Oh, yeah, 100%.
It is you do not have to go to a lot of conventions if when you're not going to a convention,
you're actually spending a lot of time in the space, in spaces where the people that you want
to influence are that are not the convention spaces. Once every because people can all know who you
are, despite the fact that they haven't met you, it is still possible to do that.
I think we are unfortunately, sorry, I just want to say, I think the part of the problem here is
that we are talking about a network people want to get in that we are not in, which is the network
of publishing specifically and how you get your stuff in front of authors, how you get that
invitation to like edit anthologies, how you find publishers to propose anthologies to. And I
think maybe, I mean, I don't really quite understand how you become part of that because it's not
something I've tried. So maybe, you know, we can only talk about our own networks, but not particularly
that specific network that the aspiring writers trying to get into that in crowd.
Well, that's why I'm talking about com running and not publishing because I do understand the
com running network. I do understand where I sit in it and I do understand the barriers and I
think they're very similar barriers. Yes. But I am trying to find analogies that allow me to say
sort of anything useful. But because the other thing that like with getting into fandom at all
in the UK, the other thing is not just wealth privilege. It's like time privilege. Because the
other thing is like we always have our conventions in the UK at Easter and that makes things difficult
for sort of people with various religious observances. And the thing I find difficult with
smofcon is it's always in December, which is firstly always my birthday, but secondly always a
giant international academic conference that I usually attend. So I even if I had the money to
attend smofcon, I couldn't. And so like that's another consideration where I don't know those are
extra barriers, which can be thrown up. But I do I take your point about for the publishing. I know
nothing about those networks by also by I think I know enough about feeling on the outside of networks
I would like to be in that I can say things about how that works. And I'm assuming full disclosure
that that transfers and there might be nuances where it doesn't. That's a fair point. I think
there are a bunch of of podcasts in our space that are talking about the exact thing of getting
into the public getting into publishing. It might even be a preponderance of podcasts in the space
that we are in that talk about that. So you know, if if that's an issue for you, go and listen to
all of them. That's a good point. Can you name any specifically? Just because it feels like we're
saying listen to some podcasts and that will help. Oh, well, I mean, if you look at if you look at
podcasts that are traditionally nominated for the Hugo, then a bunch of them are about what it is
like to be they are they are three writers who are trying to improve their networks by running a
podcast. And they talk about this stuff a lot. They talk about their submissions, they talk about
their writing, they talk about the sorts of things they are doing, the sorts of people they're meeting
and the sorts of conventions they are going to. But I think they're I think you're right that
there are a lot of podcasts by science fiction writers that talk about the craft. But I'm not
sure how many of them focus on the because we're focused on science fiction fandom, right? So we
talk about the kind of the community and we talk about how we interface with the community. We talk
about how you get into that community and what that community is doing. I don't know if there's an
octothorpe equivalent in the writing space where people are doing stuff like going deep in the latest
sifwa news or talking about what sort of more professional geared conferences are coming up.
I don't know if that actually exists. Readers write in. Have we got anything else on
Ickpecky? Just to remind people we did say this at the beginning of the segment, but
this is a rapidly moving story and it will probably be totally different by the time you listen to
this podcast in 10 days time. We recorded this episode quite a while before it was released.
And so we want to highlight that. Since we had this discussion, there's been a lot more conversation
about this online and in particular, Ickpecky has responded to the allegations in a long PDF.
We're going to post a link to that and to Jason Sanford's write-ups in the show notes so you can
read those as well. Who wants to do their pick first? Liz, do yours first? Yes, so I believe this
is going to be followed by John registering a formal complaint. But I have picked Japan.
Because the reason this is that you got the episode on grass last week is that I was on holiday in Japan
and it was great because I know Alison loves a good Peppers ghost effect. I was going to pull out
that I went to Tokyo Disneyland and Tokyo Disneyland is great, but also it had what is
absolutely the most jaw-dropping Peppers ghost I've ever seen. I literally sat there and my jaw
dropped and kind of how on earth did they just do that effect way? It is a spoiler if you're
planning to go to Tokyo Disneyland because it will tell you something that is jaw-dropping
is a Peppers ghost and then you'll start going, "Oh, can I see if it's a Peppers ghost?" But it's not
really spoiler in that the effect is of the beast imputing the beast transforming from the beast
into the prince. So you all know that's going to happen anyway, but it does it just amazingly well.
I've just watched the video. Firstly, I would like to say that it is appropriate that it is on a
subreddit called Blackmagic Fuckery, the book which is editing that clearly has no other
explanation but no good Blackmagic Fuckery. But secondly, what the fuck Liz? How how how like I
don't what? That is my reaction. I really want a 3D video for that. I think it's probably a lot
better in 3D than it is. That's because the thing that Peppers ghost does is 3D. It's pretty damn
good in 2D, but sorry Liz, continue. It is amazing is the point. It's great and also also bear in
mind that I think one of the neat things about it is that this is being viewed from many many
angles because you're you're starting giant whirling teacups. And so there's quite a lot of people
looking at this at once from different angles. So they had to make sure kind of that the effect
was seamless for everyone on the ride. And yeah, just that is but it's just kind of one thing of
Tokyo Disneyland was great and partly it's because they are really I think pushing what you can do
with people in a in a theme park and what effects you can do in front of people. And they obviously
put an awful lot of thought and care into it and it was just generally fun. And I think it's also
quite a bit cheaper than the US ones if you have to get to Japan. Yeah, yes, which you know for me
not too bad. But if you are thinking oh that's so far away I will never go. If you ever go to Japan
I would recommend it as well as I would recommend just going to Japan. It was fun.
Yes and this brings me to my formal complaint which is I was going to read, listen to, play or
interact with all of your picks this year both view and when you pick things like Japan that gets
quite a lot harder. Because I've been doing my best. Do you have anything else on Japan? Sorry Liz.
I was just going to pick another I mean I'm going to find a video now of the other really
cool effect which is so I went on the Tower of Terror ride. The Tower of Terror ride is not my
favorite ride on account of it just like throws you up and down vertically and that is not my
favorite effect. If you would like to know how much this is not my favorite effect you can ask
Andrew and Anna who are my traveling companions on this trip and the photo of me on this ride was
so bad and so funny that Andrew went to buy it. He never got to pick it up but he went to buy it
because my expression was so bad. But I went on it basically because I knew the effects at the
start would be so amazing and I've got to now I'll find and send you the effect of essentially
there's a little kind of statue that wakes up and speaks and then disappears and it's probably a
very simple effect but again it's just one of these things where it has to work for everyone in the
room and just kind of wow you and also it still wows you even when you kind of expecting it.
It's just very cool. Sorry John so maybe John you can just watch these YouTube videos of
uh little cool special effects and consider that as good as a trip.
Thanks Liz. Hybrid. Yeah.
I have no further comments. Shall I move on to my London based immersive? Yes. We've been getting
PR pictures for all sorts of things for a couple of years now and somebody said do you want to go
through this thing and we ignored it because we had all our PR pictures and then the PR came back
to us and said oh please come on you can do one if you could maybe do this and I was like well
I'm in London and I quite like immersive so maybe I should go. It's bridge command. It is under the
arches at Foxhall station in London and it is right by the station which if you've ever done
immersives where you've had to walk for 20 minutes to some industrial estate somewhere it is not one
of those. Being under the arches is quite good because you get a sort of rumble continuously
through the thing which is very would be very expensive if they had to pay for it but but really
makes you feel like you're in a spaceship. You and between four and 14 of your friends or
random people you met or you meet at the event are the crew of a spaceship and you were given
things to do and you're given different roles in the spaceship so I was the engineer and I had to
deal with a fire in our nuclear reactor which was very exciting and also do a lot of things which
are actually playing video games because you have little screens where your job is and it shows you
how different systems are heating up while other people are firing the phases or whatever and
it's kind of great and we really had a good time. It's very immersive they give you boiler suits to
where I did not wear a boiler suit I wore a flight jacket instead because there is never
been a boiler suit in the world made that would fit me and and you go on and we were a spaceship
escorting a cargo ship to meet up with a group and obviously stuff happens that's how battles
in space work but you know I would have thought that it was if you like immersives it's kind of
pitch perfect for the sort of people who who read science fiction because they like big space
battles so yeah there was a lot of fun really enjoyed it it is fairly expensive but I mean
immersives are fairly expensive it's kind of it's not expensive compared to theater shows
and obviously there are there are actors as well as you the actors were very good you're in
there's a spaceport bar which I which I quite liked I like being in a spaceport bar I'm very
easily amused. I think that's fair. But it is and it's obviously a labor of love it's clearly
they did a kind of small version of it which apparently had um had had like cardboard sets
and and a lot of the people who go to this a lot of people who were there when we were there
have gone loads and loads of times because they love it so and all the stories different and
the story is ongoing and stuff like that so it is not just a thing that you do once and then you've
done it really enjoyed it and thank you for thank you for freebie. This it has echoes of when
we went to Galaxy's Edge and you went to Phantom Peak whenever all of us go to Disney you go to a
London based immersive this is a pleasing pattern. I will get to Disney in 2026 yeah and I will do
Galaxy's Edge extensively. I think you find that if you messed upon the Millennium Falcon ride and
if you messed up the Millennium Falcon got destroyed it might cause some continuity problems.
All right I'm going to pick a book and it is a book that I read as a result of the clock award but
it is not one of the clock award books from this year it is one of the short lists from last year
which was Chain Gang All Stars by Nanakwame Adjibrenya which is very very good. I'm coming to realize
that the thing I value most in science fiction at the moment is anger and it is an incredibly
angry book it is very raw and it's about a future United States in which the penal system has gotten
to the point where they've effectively recreated Roman gladiatorial combat as a form of justice
and it follows a few characters over the course of the novel and sort of explores how they came to
be incarcerated and how that works for them and the author has footnotes through the book which
kind of explore the the various systemic prejudices against the type of people who end up in the
justice system in the states and I found the mixture of and it's not a subtle book it's not
trying to be a subtle book it's an angry howl that is taking everything to 12 in order to
make it impossible for you to misinterpret what it wants to say to you and I valued that a great
deal I thought that was very good and I don't think it would land for everyone but I loved it I
just and it made me so angry and so sad and there's a couple of scenes which I was like Christ that
is a scene and I really really enjoyed it so I'd highly recommend it to everyone um listening and
I'm really glad I read it and I'm really glad it was on the shortlist go with that listeners
that's my recommendation that's my pick I don't think either Liz or Alison have read it it's very
much on my to be read list and that was the Octothorpe podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye
from me and it's goodbye from me
[Music]
hang on no I did read something that I can pick we're saved we're saved otherwise John wouldn't
have an opinion this week and it would be very sad there is no shots of John Dottie we're gonna
opinion this week that's that's the art prompt sacks of opinions I mean guys guys like you
you're coming for me hard this week guys like I don't know what I did I don't know
was it the extra eggs this week like oh good good you're looking faintly hung over John and I can't
resist uh you're just sticking the knife in the theme music for this episode was fanfare for
space by kevin mccloud in competec.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license
this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]