What's talking about science fiction? Anyway, shall we talk about the Hugo
Vollist? We want to talk about science fiction, John.
Hello everyone. Welcome to episode six of the OctaThorp podcast, a podcast about science
fiction and SF fandom. I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
And we have a letter of comment from Ispania Sheriff, my wife, who attended a one-day
convention called Wifi Sci-Fi, which was hosted by Anne Colette and it was a
minicon consisting of a single Zoom panel in two parts followed by breakout
room cabbie clutches. The panel had the topic SF and the pandemic tackled by
five panelists and then the second half of the panel was on the same topic but
with different panelists and then afterwards you were assigned randomly
to a breakout room with one of the panelists and in Ispania's case she
talked to Corey L. Lee who was charming and then suddenly switched out to Adrian
J. Walker who was also lots of fun. This is the second Wifi Sci-Fi event that has
been run and you can find more details at ancolettes.co.uk/wificell
I did not go but I heard Ispania having a lot of fun. I believe I was playing
board games on the internet while that was happening. Is that because you are
playing board games on the internet roughly 50% of the time you are awake?
No that is a that is a vicious lie. At least 25th of the time that I am awake I
am playing them in real life so there you go. I think this is the second Wifi
Sci-Fi event isn't it? Yes. Clearly the first one went well if they've done a
second one and it seems like a kind of nice way to spend three hours on a
Saturday afternoon. And it sounds like they've got the social aspects down a bit
by just like randomly allocating you to a room and you have a chat which is
yeah. Yeah I am wondering whether this kind of mini convention will turn out to
be a really viable way of doing programming in the kind of current
virtual age because it means you can really pick and choose what panels you
want to go to. If like three people a weekend run a panel with some socialising
afterwards you can massively split the amount of effort between a lot of
different people you don't have to have a centralised effort and you can pick
and choose what events you want to go to which is potentially very cool. I've
done a lot of Zoom parties now and I'm coming to the conclusion that for kind
of just having a good time a number at around 30 to 40 is well maybe probably
less than that say invite 30 so that 25 or 20 turn up is really quite good
because that's enough for three different solid conversations which is
all anyone's really going to get into anyway and and when you have more people
you just up the level of complexity of keeping everyone organised and it doesn't
necessarily do any better for people so so larger meetings aren't necessarily
better the advantage of great big conventions or great big gatherings
generally is that more of the people you want to see will be there but you can
actually set up a virtual event with just the people you want to see on a
particular topic. I think for Zoom parties it's also not quite the size of
the room but the people in the room you need a certain amount of people in the
room who are reasonably happy to sit there and chat on Zoom and you probably
have some people who are sitting and chatting a little bit but mostly sort of
happy to listen like you need to replicate the dynamics of the conversation
in the Zoom if you have a quite full Zoom room but no one kind of knows each
other well and then not actually chatting then that's not going to work either
so the Wi-Fi sci-fi approach of having all right the author is in this room and
you can chat to the author it gives us all focus to them in a way that a
general Zoom room party does not. I have just realised that I have never
personally had the experience of being in a Zoom room and having nobody in the
room being willing to chat. I didn't want to name names it may be that not
everyone's experience is equivalent because I have like however much
endless management training from years and years and years being tried to
become a corporate cloud and failing I know I never find it difficult to start
conversations in empty rooms. It's also true that you will never be in the you
know when you when you have Zoom parties and put people into breakout rooms you
are never in the room you are not in. Yes if that makes sense. Yes. Like you
never know what's going on in the other rooms so you probably assume that all
rooms are kind of chatting away happily whereas I have been in Zoom breakout
rooms which are a little bit quieter and you're sort of waiting for someone to
get things going. The problem with a Zoom party I think no actually the problem
with a party is when you invite all of your friends and you're the only person
that everyone knows and so that means that you get the clicks and if you've got
like a couple of people who you're great mates with but I really know the rest of
your friends at all they're going to find a very difficult to interact and
that's true at any party but I think it's also true in Zoom parties where if
you've got a group of people all of whom don't really know each other and only
really know the host and the host is in a different breakout room that will
obviously be a problem. Okay so my most recent Zoom party was credited as
specifically a chance for European and Australian and New Zealand fans to get
together at a time which was more or less convenient for both of them but not
convenient for Americans because it had a structure I think that helped somewhat
with the thing and I kind of pretended that they were there to help me plan my
guff trip which they weren't they were just there to foster relations
between European and Australian and New Zealand fans which I think it did though
we did actually get any New Zealand fans except for Ming and Smitty who don't
count. For those who don't know Ming and Smitty both used to live in the UK before
emigrating to New Zealand and so counting them as New Zealand fans is
obviously fine but may not be the New Zealand fans you're trying to reach out
to in this particular case. I will also say on the topic of Australian and New
Zealand fandom we were recommended by Claire Breyerley a podcast called the
two chairs talking podcast which is hosted by David Greek and Perry Middle
Miss who are ex-chairs of the of of previous Australian World Cons and I gave
that lesson in between last episode and this episode and it's quite good they
talk about books if you like Australian people talking about books you may also
enjoy it so give it a look. Yes and they also I think record on a fortnightly
schedule as we do and they have quite a lot 27 episodes so far so they're a bit
ahead of us.
On the topic of things that have happened in recent times the Hugo finalist's
came out and we touched on this in a previous episode but we haven't really
talked about it in any great detail yet so we're going to talk a little bit about
that today. And also the BSFA Awards were announced in a glittering ceremony on
Zoom. I think three hours late because they timed their award ceremony to
coincide with Zoom's first major outage since the start of lockdown which is a
tiny bit unfortunate but I think they recovered quite well. Oh that's
unfortunate. Did you actually virtually attend? I did not because of the whole
middle of the night issue. I did not. I did not because of the whole not being a
member of the BSFA issue which I I've become I'm feeling increasingly embarrassed
about actually because one of the things I have been doing in lockdown is that
they've been running author readings to compensate for not being able to do
their regular pub meetings on a Wednesday in the middle of the month and I've
gone to a couple of these and they've been jolly good. So I turns out that author
readings are one of the things I quite like in lockdown. I like to be able to
put on an author reading while I'm working with my hands. Which is also good
because when I was more involved in the BSFA one of the things people would
generally say is the London meetings are great but I live outside London and
can't get to them and so in lockdown if they're now doing things broadcast by
Zoom again they can have a slightly wider audience. Yeah I think I say Zoom
there but I think it's actually Facebook Live so now they will only get
criticisms from people who are outside London and hate Facebook. It's the BSFA
vector reading series and we should probably put a link in the show notes.
We shall do that. So the BSFA Awards this year are great all of them I think. The
winner was of the best novel was Children of Ruin by Adrian Shikovsky.
Best shorter fiction. This is How You Lose the Time War by Amal Al-Matar and Max Gladstone.
Best nonfiction was the pleasant professor of Robert A. Highline, Farah Mendelssohn
and Best Art work was the cover for Warism and Other Stories by Ian Waits
by Chris Baker who's obviously better known as Fangorn. Yeah and they streamed
it on Zoom as we mentioned. It seemed to go well I saw people talking about it on
Twitter. I must admit I didn't watch because I am also not a member of the BSFA
although I am on the BSFA discord so you know maybe I should join up. It does seem
like they're doing some cool stuff for the machine. I should probably be on the
BSFA discord for that matter. That sounds like good people doing good things on it.
Yes I think they need to plug it slightly more because I think at the moment it is
rather quiet. I get the impression they're using it for their committee
meetings so I think it is being used internally by the BSFA and is therefore
at least somewhat active. We should put a link in the show notes.
Sorry yes I have read most of Thora's book which I found pretty interesting.
People keep thinking it's a biography which it's not it's a close reading so
it's probably of most interest to people who have read all of Highline's books
but quite a long time ago because I think actually Thora coming to it with a
fresh eye here in the 21st century is quite interesting.
I have read only this is how you lose the time war which I definitely enjoyed
but I think I enjoyed it but it didn't kind of speak to me in my heart the way
it has to a lot of people. I know it is one of those books that comes along
occasionally and a lot of people really really love it and I merely liked it and
really enjoyed it and admired it and think it's quite well done.
I will read this is how you lose the time war because it is on the Hugo finalists
this year so I will be reading it as part of my Hugo reading. I will read
Children of Ruin because I read the previous book in that series which I
thoroughly enjoyed after a colleague in my research group recommended it which
was called Children of Time and that was that was an amazing read so I do really
want to read Children of Ruin but I haven't got run to it yet.
But I have been reading the Hugo finalists I've made a start on chewing
through some of those and I've also obviously kind of watched and read
various bits of the Hugo finalists over the last year when they were
actually coming out and so we're going to talk a little bit about what on the
ballot that we have read what we're planning to read what we enjoyed and what
we didn't enjoy out of the stuff we know about and so the thing we're
probably the most well up to date with is the best dramatic presentation
categories which I think the three of us have have watched most of so shall we
start with long form. Yeah I've seen everything on BDP long form apart from
Star Wars which I did mean to go and see but it came out at the point when I was
about to go off on a long holiday back at the times when I was allowed to get
on planes for a long period of time and the reviews came out and everyone said
oh it's fine oh it's alright oh it's not that great really and I thought fine I'll
just go and see it later and then I forgot around to it so I haven't seen it
I understand it's fine to bad. I really liked it it made me laugh and grin and
clap and do all of those things I can entirely understand why people might not
have liked it. I think it is not a well-made movie but it is a fun movie and I
thoroughly enjoyed myself when I watched it. I enjoyed it more than I enjoyed
Endgame and that might be controversial. Endgame's plot fundamentally made no
sense to me and no one else seems to have this problem which is weird given
the number of people that had a problem that last year and I had a hyperspace
jump in it but like I don't know the time travel the Endgame was just nonsense
I don't I liked it it was fun it was a good ride time travel is nonsense in all
films apart from Luper basically so I just oh 12 monkeys sorry yes I did mean
primer not Luper. Time travel in the first Terminator movie holds up very well
it's just that Terminator 2 went back and ruined it shall I go back and do sorry
no we're not gonna let you undo your mistakes Liz this is all going straight
I had the same reaction every time I see a JJ Abrams film which is that I leave
the cinema going I thoroughly enjoyed that he did justice to the franchise
that he is working in and then over the next few hours or days or weeks the
critical part of my brain goes well did he really all he has done is parrot and
eight bits of it without adding to or extending them in a way that is clever
or interesting he just serves up fan service that is the cinematic equivalent
of a shoe bun and I'm not saying I don't like shoe buns but I feel that this was
the culmination of a series that I've been watching since I was 12 years old
and we deserved a little bit more than that especially given the second episode
had done quite a lot to say we are taking this in a direction that isn't just
giving adolescent men in America what they want so I've got two reactions to
that which is firstly I think that take on the two Abrams Star Wars movies
fundamentally ignores one of their greatest strengths which is I think the
characterization in both of them is the best characterization in any of the
Star Wars movies I especially think that's clear in the first act of rise of
Skywalker where the interaction between Rey and Poe and Finn does an awful lot to
tell you how much time has passed and how much they've gone through in between
last Jedi and rise of Skywalker in a way that doesn't need to be written down
because it's all there in the direction and the acting and I actually think
Abrams is the best director that has ever directed a Star Wars movie which
may be controversial I think last Jedi was fantastic I do enjoy last Jedi I do
wish that they hadn't decided to fundamentally reanalyze what it is to be
Star Wars in the eighth part of a nine part series because I think that made it
very difficult to tell a coherent story I think if the eighth part of your series
is something like but now what about something completely different there are
problems there and I think the other half of what's wrong with rise of Skywalker
is that it is very difficult to work out how you get from the end of the last
Jedi to the end of the nine part saga in a way that's anything approaching
narratively satisfying I do think that rise of Skywalker has some absolute
bobbins in it and it reminds me a little bit of some of the Rossel T. Davis
work on Doctor Who where you've got the bit at the end spoilers for those who
haven't seen rise of Skywalker there's a bit at the end Liz do you mind if I
spoil rise of Skywalker no go for it go for it go for it there's a bit at the
end where the Emperor basically uses force lightning on an entire solar
system and it's a bit like did we need that no if we did did that did we need a
little bit of text they explained why that was okay probably I didn't mind it
it wasn't great it's but Abrams does this he does the infinitely ratcheting up
the stakes which does cheapen the stakes in the earlier movies which is a shame
but generally speaking I thought it had flaws but I did genuinely generally
really enjoy it I still think the best of the three pre the best of the three
sequel movies is The Force Awakens which I thought in many ways was almost
perfect and I thoroughly enjoyed but that is by tape can we agree that you
should not give the Hugo to it I was suggested at the end of this segment we
decide who we should give the Hugo to I have ideas neither of them are rise of
Skywalker so I am not arguing that it should be Hugo Victor haha the Hugo
Victor Hugo it was a pun
I have not seen the two episodes of the Marvel Cinematic Universe extruded
product because it is getting very large and life is too short you only need to
watch two movies and two television series a year or something and you're
all right but that I genuinely enjoy the MCU I enjoyed Captain Marvel although in
a way it was like okay this is maybe the 10th or 12th superhero origin story in
the MCU I have seen and the exciting bit is now they keep setting them in
different random decades so they can have a different soundtrack and you can go
oh it's got some 90s things in but I did I did still enjoy it I would probably
go and watch another one I was thoroughly entertained for two and a half
hours or whatever it is and it is nice to see a female lead yes Brie Larson
is someone I really like and so I liked her in it I will say so I think I think
Alison's point about it being the extruded Marvel Cinematic product which
is a very evocative metaphor which I love I think it's true and I think it's
difficult because I think one of the really shining things the MCU has done
and whether or not you like the way it's done it it's really interesting that
they've taken a story and told it over a series of 20 movies with ancillary
material because I don't think that's really ever been done before and in the
closest you've probably got is James Bond but that doesn't tell anything near a
single story and so I think I think in some ways the MCU is actually really
revolutionary in a way that people aren't really talking about but I think
part of that is because it is really revolutionary at telling a story where a
lot of the beats are repeated and I could definitely see why there are people
who are getting to the point where they're like this is a bit I have gotten to
the end of my patience with this compared with most people I know I have very
low tolerance for the same story being told over and over with bigger bits over
series I'm television series as well I also struggle with this and we will get
to why I think the two short television series are my favorite things of what I
have so far seen I thought Good Omens was rather good I wasn't particularly
expecting it I mean I kind of knew it was in production I think that they did
it in a way that did not overstay its welcome I think that the fact that gaming
was on board probably helped sharpen the script to match modern sensibilities
because Good Omens is 30 years old now and there are there is a lot of subtext
in that novel that is not made anything like as clear as it was made in the
series I thought a lot of ways that they used animation and time travel and
all of that sort of thing were very clever and I thoroughly enjoyed it and
of the ones I've seen on this list which as you know is not very many it's my
second best I also enjoyed Good Omens I think I first read Good Omens when I was
10 or 11 years old and I loved it and it remains you know a book I have reread
many times of the year and still really enjoy and while I like the TV
adaptation it is almost too faithful to the books it felt to me like there was
too much trying to keep a lot of the actual wording of the books in by having
some pretty unnecessary narration narration from God and some of the bits
they kept in I think you could have cut entirely and also I think some of the
bits with yes I think some of the stuff with Sergeant Shadwell and Madam Tracy
has not aged particularly well and it's really noticeable in the show minus
spoiler the bit where Aziraphale sort of takes over Madam Tracy's body works
much much better in the books because in the TV show it just puts Michael Sheen
out of action for an episode so I would really like to actually if they've
trimmed it more maybe trimmed out some of the bikers of the apocalypse trimmed
out these bits that I think don't work as well on screen and it was almost too
faithful but it was way way better than what I feared we might get so I can't
complain too much so I will say I think I agree with you I think it was too
faithful I think they should have taken more liberties with it and I am also
in the same boat that I think I read Good Omens when I was 10 or 11 and it
remains a very very fond memory it was the book that introduced me to both
Pratchett and Gaiman's writing so it will always have a place in my heart I
think I agree with you that they needed to do more to make it into a TV show
rather than into a TV version of a book I will say that I thought the
chemistry between most of the characters was amazing and I thought the actors did
a tremendous job I am happy that Michael Sheen and David Tennant are getting a
lockdown TV show together as far as I could tell off the back of the fact that
they were good together in Good Omens which is Chef's Kiss I thought Jack White
Hall was very good which surprised me because I was expecting not to think
he was very good the thing you said about the bikers of the
pocket is really interesting because my main problem with that is that they
cut out all of the funny bits are left in all of the other bits and I think
they really needed to decide whether they were going to keep the hilarious
other four bikers which made it work or whether they were going to really slim
down that whole thing but they sort of went for a middle road where they took
the funny bit out and that I'm not sure I do wonder whether that's because it
was Neil Gaiman that was overseeing the adaptation and not Terry Pratchett
because I wonder whether some of the more out there funny bits of Good Omens were
more on Pratchett's side than Gaiman's shall we say but generally speaking I
thought it was very good I'm not sure it's my favorite of the
roster but I really liked it. Gaiman is very good at whimsy but he is not a
humorist in the way that Pratchett was and very little of Gaiman's solo output
is not out loud hilarious so I think you can reasonably assume that everything
properly funny in Good Omens comes from Pratchett. Everything that's
properly funny and I think properly sort of sharp
humor as well seems to be me to be more of a Pratchett thing than a Gaiman thing.
I mean obviously this is all speculation and we may be entirely wrong but it
seems reasonable for more we know about the two authors.
With a bit of luck we'll get a lock from Neil Gaiman telling us how we're going.
Ha ha yes Neil please write in and tell us how we've gotten all this wrong we
would love to hear from you.
I really liked Russian doll I like lots of things it did and I like the fact that
just I think I hadn't noticed when it came out that Netflix was in the habit
of just sticking up some stuff that was quite out there
and I like that Russian doll is I don't think it's like hugely original
but I like the fact it was clearly quite cheap to make and so therefore
it doesn't have when you reap novels and they're
great and interesting and weird you think well if this had been made into a
film or a television series people would have
shaved bits off the edges to make them fit more tightly into a mold of what
they think extruded cinematic products should be like
and Russian doll absolutely doesn't do that it's got a load of characters
and they're quite wild and they do a load of things you know a heroine is
actually spectacularly not particularly nice in a way that
is not that common even in the more elaborately very television that we get
now and it's short so they made quite a short amount of it
and it tells a whole story and then it's done and I don't know if their plan is
to do anymore obviously when things are a big success on Netflix they tend to do a
second series oh that's a little bit of a shame but it feels like it told a whole
story and it was done and it was and it had lots of
proper science fictional content which even now even with all the science
fictionters around us all the time we don't get as much of that as we
maybe should and I thought it was funny and entertaining
and I that's what I want from my long-form dramatic presentations thank you
very much and don't necessarily get it though it was
kind of it's kind of eight short-form dramatic presentations so
it once again demonstrated that the hugo categories are very complicated
I think I would say that it feels like something which fits much better in
long-form than many series which have been nominated
long-form because I think it does tell one complete story over eight episodes
and that's one reason why it's so satisfying to watch
without spoiling it it is not a concept that is entirely new
I did think that it is quite innovative in that it is a very
dark comedy in a way that you don't often see
US kind of situation comedies do and the he bleakness of it
and the humor of it was really refreshing I really liked that
I think it's relatively unusual for comedy to be taken seriously it's
relatively unusual for genre to be taken seriously so the fact that this was a
genre comedy that was taken seriously was really pleasing
and I think stands in opposition to the good place
which is another genre comedy that was taken seriously but has a very different
feel in terms of its optimism to russian doll and so I'm really happy
that russian doll is on the roster and I think it's one of the two
that I would be the happiest to see win and what is the other one john
the other one I would be happy to see win is us directed by Jordan Peele
I have not seen us but I do want to and I suspect it's quite good just because
everything Jordan Peele has ever done is good so we will not be spoiling so the
allison does not have to put her fingers in her ears and shout la la la
because I do not want to have to edit around that so Liz can you spoiler free
discuss what you liked about us I think what might be funnier is if I did
it with spoilers and elaborate hand gestures and
allison had to put it on mute and just watch me you know
ha ha ha mime the entire film but that would
probably not be much fun for the listeners
I will not be doing that as you can put the back in
I feel that would be too boring for the listeners
I think the best part about us was when the hoff turned up no um
I liked I don't watch a lot of horror films but I did find this one to be
scary but in a really sort of plot and character driven way if that makes sense
like it felt like a slasher film but with something really deep going on
under it I think that acting is fantastic I don't think it's really spoiling
anything because it's in the trailer to say that there are lots of doppelgangers
involved and I think all the acting of the people with their doppelgangers
is amazing you can always tell who is who even if they're not speaking
the acting in it is phenomenal and the direction is phenomenal
but I also think it is creepy in a way that I find most horror movies are not
but I think both us and get out are incredibly creepy movies that made me
feel really uncomfortable in a really nice way that's gonna sound weird but
like I enjoyed the feeling of uncomfortable I had while I was watching them
they really got under my skin and I really enjoyed them I think us is
really really great and I think you can see that Jordan Peele's background in
comedy is helping a lot with his ability to do the
timing I think his sense of comic timing is helping him a lot with the pacing
and the way he can make you feel uncomfortable through the film
I really liked it I would be very happy to see it when
I would highly recommend watching it me and a spaniel bought us and get out on
iTunes for 15 quid because they've got a bundle at the moment
we thoroughly enjoyed watching us the other week
so what do you feel should win based on the ones you've seen anyway
of the ones I've seen I've seen I've been voting for russia doll
for all the reasons about things not overstaying they're welcome and and
telling a story in the right amount of space that I've seen but I mean I'm
sure that us is well up there as well and I also like good omens
do you want to rank them in in order Alison like as you would on your ballot
of the ones I've seen I've only seen three of these haven't I she has ranked
the three she's seen I think which are um russia doll good omens
rise of Skywalker sorry I should say more clearly russia doll good omens no
award rises guy fair fair what will you be
ranking them liz
you've put me on the spot now because I hadn't thought about my lower
ranked choice voting I think number one is us
and probably russian doll I'm gonna have to think about it some more
there's things I love about good omens and captain marvel and avengers end
game but I really need to think about it some more and how much of it is
are my judging avengers endgame as a film or am I judging avengers endgame off
the 20th in a series of 20 films I think this is actually a really
interesting question because I kind of wish
that the marvel cinematic universe had been nominated as a single dramatic
presentation long for like the whole thing from my end
endgame because if that happened I would have ranked it one
but as it is I'm gonna put russian doll then I'm gonna put us then I'm gonna put
good omens then I'm gonna put captain marvel then I'm gonna put rise of sky
walker and then I'm gonna put end game because I
fundamentally didn't feel like endgame did a good job of wrapping up
the mcu I think a lot of people liked it because it had a lot of fan service in
it but I just didn't think it held together as a movie
very well at all but did enjoy seeing it in the cinema
and there are some really good bits I enjoyed all of them is the problem I
wouldn't pay any of them below no award we may we may get on to
discussions of when you would put something below no award
but this is not the category where I would yes okay I'm probably being a bit harsh
I just would be so sad if it if we got to virtual
conzeland and they gave the hugator rise of sky walker and I do think it's a
very significant risk because I think there are a lot of people at the
wilcon who've been watching star wars movies for
40 years and would like to see an award for that I think that's a good point
because I think if star wars and endgame are going to get ranked on
the entirety of the sagas they belong to instead of as individual works it
becomes much harder to predict what the fandom is going to give the hugo to
so I think if people don't do that it will go to either russian dollar
us I think if they do do that then endgame's got a really good chance of
winning it's my thought although good omen's has a
lot of fans so maybe i'm wrong maybe good omens could steal it
I wouldn't want a bit money oh good omens really does have a lot of
fans it really does okay so we were going to discuss best
dramatic presentation short form but it turns out we had a lot of thoughts
and so we're going to leave that for a future episode
do we want to touch on staying sane in the apocalypse
my method of staying sane in the apocalypse is having discussions with
youtube about the minutiae of disney based marketing schedules
how are you both coping? covid 19
i do find that making sure that i'm having chats with my friends and not only that
that i'm making sure that those chats go in different directions so that i'm
talking to different friends about different things on different
occasions is really important for me and that i do set up
zoom chats where unexpected people are talking to each other because i think
you get if you're always talking to the same people
even if you frame it around a board game or a quiz night or whatever
you would inevitably get to the point where somebody goes
have you ever have you been anywhere nice recently and the other person goes
well i went for a nice walk in bluebell woods at castle barnard
and then you realize there's only so much you can say about walking in bluebell
woods it's not true but you actually run out very
quickly of things to talk about even though we've all been watching things
and doing things whereas if you actually get some different people
together you can actually start to have the
meaty conversations about you know everything else in the world
because people from different countries and people in
different situations do have different experiences and they're good
i think i've been doing much the same have you been
talking to a plethora of people liz i mean i have but that's because i also
went out and had socially distanced outdoor coffee with some people yesterday
because we are on a much freer schedule i think
then you guys are at this point caroline came around and had a coffee at my
house and i did not think we had broken any rules but it
turns out that we did she came to my house and put six
georgettea novels on my doorstep whilst in the process of doing other
errands which are legal and then she went and sat in my front garden
some distance away from the house and i came out with a polypin of beer which
i was selling her and put it on my recycling bin and then we
had a cup of coffee together um at about three meters apart which i
thought was completely legal and fine now but it turns out
we needed to actually walk into the street because you could only do it at
this in an outdoor public place so if we'd had done exactly the same thing but
i'd start off by putting two chairs in the middle of the road
we'd have been good fair enough but as it was it was legal it was a great
fun though i've got to the stage where every time you see another human being
you're like oh this is amazing it's a person we can drink coffee we can
have a conversation yeah we we have in our garden we have a fence which is
short enough that if we sit in the middle of our garden
and our neighbors sit in the middle of their garden
we can shout at each other while having lunch
and that is quite good for conversation it does it does need you to shout you
can't talk normally but it works quite well actually
we're probably about three or four meters apart i would say
but yeah it's not bad and then i've also been having
Spanish lessons from my sister-in-law which has been fun
keeps you occupied and i really really hate talking in Spanish not because i
don't like Spanish but because as listeners will have noted i talk
quite a lot and talking and being unable to say the thing you want to say
because you don't know how to is a very frustrating thing
i think if you talk a lot i'm finding it really difficult but i am
persevering and it is quite good so far this is why
extroverts struggle with language learning because you know you have all
these things to say and it's incredibly hard to say them
and then you do language learning and i've got to the stage where i can read
quite a lot of Japanese now but cannot say anything in Japanese and that's
good and that's really embarrassing
you're learning tai-liz i am yes i'm i'm having online language lessons and one
of the problems is that it can sometimes be quite hard to hear
and one of the key things that we are supposed to be learning right now
is how to read the different tones from the different combinations of
consonants of vowels and so what it actually needs to
is me saying something and then doing a hand motion to prove that i do know
what tone it's supposed to be in even if it's not possible to hear over zoom
exactly what tone i'm using so there's a lot of like hands going up and hands
going down and hands representing rising and falling tones
it's quite funny excellent and we can have a octa thought where i speak in
Spanish list speaks in tai and alison is the only one anyone can understand
and that will be fun absolutely because you do need my hand
just to tell what tone i'm supposed to be attempting
i can embed pictures if you're doing them in the podcast art so i don't know
whether listeners have picked up on this but i put
i put pictures in the podcast so if you're looking at your podcast player
when a certain part of the podcast plays their picture will change sometimes
you know if there's a relevant picture to the
discussion and i could i could do second long chapters with liz
gesturing to indicate where her tone should be and that would be
a delightfully hacky way of solving the problem i think
thank you everyone for listening to the sixth episode of the octa thought
podcast we will see you in a fortnight time
but for now i have been john coxen and it's goodbye from me
and i have been alison scott and it's goodbye from me
and i have been a still amblest batty and it's goodbye from me
yay yeah that's six episodes that's amazing
are we not are we eligible for hugo yet the theme music for this episode was
fanfare for space by kevin mccloud at ncompetech.com
used under a creative commons attribution 3.0 license
you
okay so i think one of the really interesting things about the mcu is that
they're doing this kind of two or three movie a year
product where they're doing um movies which are in some ways very similar to
each other and then occasionally there's a movie which is quite different
like for instance the first card is the galaxy felt quite different or
the ant man films feel quite different but then other films feel quite similar
um and one of the really interesting things is that they did try that with
star wars they released solo which was an attempt to
do a heist movie that felt different from the saga
and it was relatively poorly received by the fandom and and financially
and i think they have have almost decided to retreat from doing
um a lot of movies into the realm of tv so they've announced
um they're doing the obi wan Kenobi tv series they're doing the mandelorian
and they've brought the clone wars back um i'm sure they've announced something
else that i'm forgetting um but a lot of what they're doing is star wars seems
to be more on the television slash book slash comic side
and they seem to be really hesitant to try and make a star wars
cinematic universe and i think it's really interesting
the way that marvel has been able to tell this multi-movie story
but when star wars tried something similar i think it was quite poorly
received and i am wondering how that's going to impact
Lucasfilm and marvel's decisions going forward from here because
for whatever reason i think they're in quite different situations with
regards to their fan bases and i'm not entirely sure why
well i i think part of that is that basically the film landscape is just too
crowded for disney right now because they have
marvel films they have star wars films they have
Pixar they have disney animation they have their live action remakes of disney
animation and they're in a position where if they're not careful they will
start cannibalizing their own audience but in a way i think it's also just that
solo was highly anticipated and not that great i think i would also cite
rogue one here which is also a chance to tell a different sort of story
in the star wars cinematic universe and i think which worked
completely on its own terms and was great
um so you know i think there is still there is more they can do here
i think i think i will push back a little bit on solo being hotly
anticipated i i i quite you may surprise you to learn
i followed quite a few people who have fans of star wars on the twitters
um but i didn't see a lot of excitement for solo
and a lot of people i follow were very skeptical
that it was a story that needed to be told and i think
part of the problem with solo is that it was a prequel
and i think star wars fans are very skeptical of prequels
um i can't think why um but and i think one of the really interesting things
as well was that because it came out five months after the last jedi
the last jedi had only been out of cinemas for about six weeks when solo
was in cinemas i just wonder whether they should have pushed it back to
there because because they had been trying to release all of these movies
at summer and they had all been pushed back to christmas
and solo was the first one of the new disney era
where they managed to release it on time but i actually think releasing on time
was a huge mistake because it meant you didn't have enough time to build up
that anticipation in between the last jedi and solo
um it felt like the last jedi had only just come out really
um and so i think i think there were a large number of missteps made
and i but and i agree that i think and i don't know whether i'm right
i think the reaction to solo was much more because
of the lack of marketing and the lack of thought about when to release it
than it was about the quality of the movie because i think
quality is almost irrelevant when it comes to blockbusters
and that's not just Star Wars it's like there's a very pessimistic view of all
movies yeah they had a very serious not Harrison Ford
problem too i watched the Star Wars movies when i was very young in like the
90s and i am not as attached to Harrison Ford as my parents are
who were very appalled that Harrison Ford was not in it
um but i do wonder whether that's the other part it's like a film
that's designed to appeal to original trilogy fans but it's a film that
treads on the old trilogy's toes in some ways um Liz did you have any
i do have several things can i say the several things i was going to say
yes say the several things so one thing i would push back on that is
Marvel released Captain Marvel and Avengers Endgame
two months apart um so i don't think there's a reason you can't release
these things in quick succession if you think the
you know obviously there is an audience there for some of them i mean
Avengers Endgame is kind of a special case but it didn't seem to hurt Captain
Marvel people were not staying away thinking oh i'll go and see the next one
or i've just seen one um and my main issue with solo is i don't
think old and error right does a particularly great job and i just found
it to be not that entertaining to be honest
so just to push back on that solo has a higher tomato meter score than rise of
Skywalker and a higher audience score than last Jedi
so if we're going to say it's about the quality of the movies i would have thought
i either rise of Skywalker or last Jedi should have been much worse
in terms of box office and solo i am and i appreciate
that the Marvel movies have been much closer together
and i don't know why i think the Marvel movies don't have this problem
but i definitely feel like there was a large reaction in the Star Wars fandom
which was we don't need this movie and a large a large lack of anticipation
in a way that there isn't for Marvel and so i agree on the face of it
i think it seems like you should be able to release solo five months after
last Jedi it should be fine but i am i'm just deeply
unconvinced that i think it was anything to do with the quality of the movie
because like i say in some ways solo was better received than episode eight and
episode nine and it and it did far worse in the box office
like far worse i miss what you were saying about last Jedi were you saying
about is what were you run rate rating lost Jedi by
so if you look at the last Jedi um like audience reviews last Jedi got 90
percent from critics and got like 40 percent from the audience
uh riser skywalker got about 40 percent from critics and about 90 percent
from the audience if i recall correctly or it might have been lower on the
audience side and then solo got about 70 percent on both
and so if solo is worse and that's why it did worse
then either last Jedi or riser skywalker should have done even worse
and the fact they didn't i think is difficult to explain
i think there is a quality based explanation which is that marvel at this
point is an extremely solid reliable brand and they very rarely
drop films people feel at duds so people are now
reassured that if they go and see a marvel film it will probably meet
at least a particular uh high watermark and probably go higher
i don't think people are convinced of that for star wars films yet
and i think there's also the obvious problem with looking at the last Jedi's
audience rankings in that we know the last Jedi
is really not liked in a particular subset of fandom who are probably more
likely to have gone and written reviews of it
we may be going too far into star wars versus marvel
and we do have one tiny more thing to say about marvel
yeah which is that one of the reasons i think that
marvel the whole marvel cinematic universe with all its
entrails and tendrils is accepted and even loved for that
by its audience is that it's actually coming from
a source which is its comics which because
Than Lee invented the system of getting people to buy more product
in comics by having all of these crossovers this is what this is it's
always been doing this it is the thing that is unique about marvel
and so to some extent they have just encapsulated
the marvel unique selling point which is they don't just sell you stuff they sell
you a very large amount of stuff and you like it
that's actually that's actually a really good point i think um
i think the fact that marvel has source material that is tried and tested may
also massively help um and it's very but i think i didn't
sorry i didn't intend to derail this into the discussion it's become
but i just i'm not i'm not sure i'm right but i'm not sure
it's obvious why star wars can't sustain the same level of movie releases as
marvel and it could just be that solo was empirically bad
but i am skeptical that's the whole story but i don't know
um and so that was all i was trying to um and so that was welcome to octa thought
where this week in the absence of new news from science fiction and fandom
we are having a two-hour animated discussion of star wars versus marvel
it's definitely on topic guys i think you're correct i don't think it
that solo is it's not a bad film i just didn't
enjoy it that much but i think had solo it turned out to be
a really really good film like a guardians of the galaxy
level of quality or something like that then people might have gone ah they can
make good films that are entertaining in between the
the big trilogy films oh i was not expecting a close reading of
the marvel of marvel v stores that was not where i thought this was going
not sure it was that closer reading ha ha oh fighting talk let's fight and
talk
jonnie you know to definitely like screen sharing with us deliberately
yes look at this graph oh i see okay this is the lockdown spike in
dex published per month on tv.com which i thought was interesting
because it just rockets what's the graph oh yes i've been you know how people say
you should not extrapolate from your personal experience
to to the world in general i've been extrapolating from the things my
um facebook friends talk about i have a fairly diverse large
i mean they're all middle class obviously but i have a fairly diverse large
group of facebook friends and i've been extrapolating like mad from my facebook
friends what they've been doing and it seems to work out and i have now noticed
that it also works on gaming i think people are gaming about three times as
much as they did before lockdown i guess but
the thing you have to bear in mind alison is that i am responsible for
how many alcom horodex have you made jonner how many of those that spike is
just you coming up with alcom horodex uh actually no so okay so that is
actually a very good question i will count it is not a trivial question
shall we finish the podcast and then and then get onto the more fun like
post podcast fit yeah 13 oh that's just you is it
oh sorry sorry i had not gathered jon is responsible for the global
spike in ocarom horodex probably
the after show how many so yes so three times as much gaming i reckon and that's
based on how many of my half stone friends are online at any given time
[Music]