Hello everyone, it's Jon here. Just before we get into the episode, Alison and Liz have asked
me to put a small disclaimer at the start saying that there is less content than usual this week,
owing to us being live from punctuation too. So I realise this is how the sauce gets made.
I'm going to shout hang on so I get a comment and then Jon will edit that bit out when we
actually edit the recording so it doesn't sound like I just shouted him. But I do.
Thanks.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 34th episode of Octa Thorpe, a podcast for science fiction and
science fiction fandom. This is the episode for the 24th of June 2021. I'm Jon Goxon.
I'm Alison Scott. And I'm Liz Batty. And did we mention we're coming live from punctuation too?
We should mention that. We're coming live from punctuation too. We have a live audience of well
43 but three of them are us so 40 and one of them is the person who's helping us so 30 died. So I
think that's not bad actually. That's quite good. That's one of those is the transcription
bot. So 38. Oh yeah okay so 38. They're falling away. And several of them are asleep so probably
about two. Thank you all very much for coming along and watching us.
Right so Octa Thorpe today is sponsored by Stow shirts. Come and find us in the dealer's room
by the punctuation too much or John is modeling a beautiful Octa Thorpe t-shirt. It's actually a
crap Octa Thorpe t-shirt but you can't tell on the zoo. I've got him to complain and hopefully
they'll be sending him a better one. They are. They are indeed. Did you hear back from them?
They said we will send you a better one and I said thank you. Yeah so hopefully so if you
get prints out the same then I'm gonna have to do something different for Octa Thorpe merch but
anyway we have Octa Thorpe merch. We have punctuation too merch. We have all sorts of other merch
for other conventions and also things that are not conventions at all and is that a minute yet John?
Yeah okay so and and basically if you'd like to sponsor Octa Thorpe that's also a thing you could
do because we now have quite a lot of cost to the fray and I'm looking at you Glasgow in 2024.
We have a we have a reliable listenership of about I don't know 80 something like at least 10.
So yeah so basically I wanted I wanted to buy a bit of software so I could do this. Oh for
sake and something will happen when you do that. Yeah what will happen or is it a secret? Is it a
secret? I don't think it's a secret. Didn't you just do it? I think I just did it. Do it again John.
Hang on. Jesus. Oh all right okay I heard it that time.
Hang on why am I paying for you to make a soundboard of me swearing?
It'll be grand. We have as ever some letters of comment but we also have a chat box
so people are posting in the chat so DC says that they resent reliable and resents the implication
that she is reliable so we'd like to say to out loud and is reliable and Roman says there's a lot
of anger about the word reliable and I we apologize we did not mean to imply anyone was competent
and we will uh fourth with acting away that makes it clear that no one is. That's not the sort of
reliable I really meant in terms of Ange because Ange is the woman who walked out this morning with
a cheese sandwich to a hotel. No reason other than to score points for her house. We're gonna talk
about that later for sure. Um okay so we have letters of comment we have a letter of comment from
DC starting out on a serious tone people which is DC points out that we said convergence would be
the first in person science speech and convention to be held post pandemic and they point out that
in fact we are still mid pandemic and um yes so uh it's tricky because obviously we mean kind of
conventions that can happen now that vaccinations are underway and there's more um uh scope for that
sort of thing but it is it is worth noting that obviously um is not just that we can ignore all
of these issues so good point DC. I think there is an interesting question to add at some point about
which point the pandemic becomes post pandemic and which point it becomes kind of covid is endemic
I don't think we're at that point yet but there will be a point where that will happen or it will be on
a country by country basis of whether you're sort of in a pandemic or in more of an endemic
situation and that's maybe not too much discussion for punctuation and I thought while we're here we
could look at Martine's letter of comment which is so they've already had a convention this year
in Poland and in fact people are in fact chiming in with more conventions which have happened in
person in various places already um which is interesting so places have had conventions you know
how large they were because I was thinking convergence at you know probably up to 3000 could be one of
the bigger ones that will have happened I don't know but I think I've also seen some of these sort of
like the ones I consider to be like sort of gate show type things the sort of you know things with
artists Ali and signing and so on I think some of those are already back but presumably they're
very strong like commercial pressures to get those back so they may not be operating purely on what
they think is you know for the best of the best option for fans and for fandom it may be what is
the best option for their business to to exist and Griffin has pointed out that it's the world
health organization that officially declares pandemics so they will officially declare the pandemic
over however it strikes me that it's not necessarily in the world health organization's interest to
officially declare the pandemic over until sometime after everybody's actually stopped treating us
it's like a pandemic said so we don't know it doesn't feel like it's over yet to me thank you
very much for writing in DC we also had a letter from Roman Ozansky who sent us some fanzines that
he had written um that are electronic he sent us a whole zip archive which we could unzip and it
was a website fanzine called the wild goose it was very good you could also find the wild goose on
the internet which is a sort of new fangled sequence of tubes that you can get and we will put a link
to that in the show notes but thank you very much Roman and Roman goes into quite a lot of detail
on all the different kind of formats and their and their thoughts on them so so yeah no it was
very good thank you very much for writing in Roman and Erwin Hirsch wrote to us and also talked a
lot about fanzines that there have been and the formats in which John Foyster and Bruce Gillespie
this must be kind of Australian obsession with fanzine with electronic fanzine formats really
given that we've had lots of this from both Roman and Erwin and also that Bruce Gillespie has
been publishing two versions of each SF commentary in both landscape and portrait so you can decide
if you're going to get SF commentary and pridged out and read it or if you're going to read it on
your device and which how you'd like it and he also says in the past couple of podcasts John has
mentioned his fanzine is that available on the web somewhere if so can you put the link in the
show notes John is your fanzine available on the web somewhere it is and in fact I wrote a new
issue for crustaceans 14 is out at this very convention the last issue was in April 2014 so
you know it's been a little while but yeah you can go to the fanzine lounge at this very convention
and read it now and I will put links in the show notes and I also write Losing with Ispania my wife
and I'll put a link to that in the show notes as well and we'll put a link to Alison's fanzine
in the show notes because she's got a right one right one yeah she's looking at me very
skeptically doing the official octa thought side eye and if you write very nicely to John
then he might even send you a copy that appears magically on your gindle and you don't have to do
anything but from you know turn the Wi-Fi on on your gindle and buy a kindle yeah okay yeah you'd
have to buy one she she knows this secret trick because I sent one to her kindle can you send me
one that appears automatically magically on my cobra email me listeners email me and tell me
how you want my fanzine and presuming it's like acceptable and doesn't involve staples then I will
comply what if I print out your podcast and put staples in it print out my podcast and put staples
in it sorry no I wouldn't print out your podcast most everything that would be quite complicated
what if I get the copy of procrastination she sent me print it out and put staples in it and
then send you a photo so I happen to know that Mark Plummer of this parish indeed used to whack
a couple of rexels through it as he termed in a lock once before reading it and maybe this is
something we should add to the scavenger hunt a stapled fanzine I gotta go and put that in the
air title I'm gonna put a stapled fanzine stapled copy of John's fanzine yep okay
we also got another lock from Christopher J Garcia who has a new job well done Chris
and he snipes me he says he was doing e-pubs of the drink tank in 2010 so I think that is our new
winner for earliest e-pub I believe so well done to Chris yeah so I do I do sometimes take the
Chris Garcia maybe when he is multitasking and listening to six podcasts and making dinner and
also typing up a letter of comment maybe he types a little bit too fast because he hasn't
been by saying most importantly we were filing cabinet so yeah we were filing cabinet I think
there's probably something profound in that we are all filing cabinet Liz he's also been on his
sweater vest yes thank you Chris we also did get um James Shields sent us dice of comment which I
should probably mention well he said you dice of comment he didn't mean dice of comment
didn't send me dice of comments so I bid I bid I bid on James Shields is at dice locked at
confusion which was Eastcom and I got outbid by Esther who bid 120 pounds on the dice and then
sent them to me which was very kind of her thank you Esther and so I got my octa my octa condai and
I got my Glasgow in 2024 die and I got my Dublin in 2019 die and I got my New Zealand in 2020 die
and I got my Chacon 8 die but I also got two octa-thorp dice so these are clear purple
eight-sided dice that have the octa-thorp on the eight and they are wonderful and I am very happy
with them so thank you very much to James Shields for including these as a brussey bonus in my
lot of dice I very much appreciate it thank you James and I've put a picture on the gram
which I will link in the show notes so that people can see who were not at punctuation too
although if you weren't at punctuation too did you really live this is the question I have tried
to put up my new Shieldsie as a service ribbon as a background to this but I don't think it's
worked properly I'll do it again another time
The convention is going well we mentioned the scavenger hunt and I want to talk about the scavenger
hunt because long-time listeners to the podcast will remember that we mentioned the PicoCon
scavenger hunt way back in a episode of octa-thorp that happened in February and I contacted the
person who wrote the bot that PicoCon used for their scavenger hunt and cheerfully forked it on
on github and made it work for us and then we had 90 items in our scavenger hunt and it has been
going very well and so far my favorite is that I put after Carrie mentioned liking cheese sandwiches
in hotels at some point yesterday I put a picture of a cheese sandwich outside a hotel in the
scavenger hunt yesterday and then we've had lots of photos of people outside hotels with cheese
sandwiches which is I I am very much enjoying very much enjoying this part of the convention
we also asked for a recreation of the punctuation to logo in an art form of your choice and I think
John is modeling one of the submissions for that this is Andrew January's submission
I we we haven't even better one but it's it was not quite finished in time to use it as backdrop so
if you wait if you wait to see me at the closing ceremony I'll be I'll be using that as my closing
ceremony backdrop I think and we will be opening these scavenger hunt channels at the end of the
convention so if you're curious about what other houses did for their alternate punctuation to art
then you can kind of go through and have a look at the closing ceremony and afterwards we may try
to create a highlight reel for you to for you to particularly be in or off but I don't know I mean
a list a list of things that we particularly recommend people go and look at because there
have been some excellent submissions if you're not doing the scavenger hunt then there is still
time you are in a house go and go and join in but it is a great way to have fun and I I think
John and I both had quite a lot of fun at Pika-Con playing the scavenger hunt and so we want to
do it here in that form and it does seem to go down quite well I think last time I suggested
we have houses and that we have some kind of competition and it would be fun and everyone was
like oh it will be like enforced fun like being in a school house and I don't think we did a huge
amount with it at Punctuation Mall we had some points but I also forget kept forgetting to post
like a house points update but this time it's not everyone in a house but each of the houses I think
has got quite into it and they are doing things like leaving the house at AM to go and take a photo
of a cheese sandwich in front of our hotel or doing spontaneous art or writing folk songs
and I love it it's kind of like the task master thing where even if it's quite a silly task
it's quite a silly item you have to get but then everyone's like oh points I like points
what do points mean prizes well they don't we don't have any prizes apart from maybe you can
probably have a ribbon yeah we don't have any prizes are we maybe should have told people that
they'll be a ribbon and you know bragging rights yeah I mean everyone's doing this just like bragging
rights and yeah as the Spanish says in the chat for the glory and I'm amazed that it turns out
people will voluntarily do things like wear silly hats and you know the contents of a witch's closet
and running around with cheese sandwiches well I'd also um so I don't know so Liz has um found a
downside to living in uh Thailand uh which is that when I because someone bought
Claire Booth Be a Cake uh because Claire had put in the scavenger hunt by a member of
Star for Cake and I was like this is a good wheeze so the next day when we uploaded more I added by
a committee member a cake I would not have let him do this I would not let him do this I should
say if the committee had noticed before they'd gone up I would have said that scavenger hunt items
that involve bribing the committee are are inappropriate and should not be allowed I'm just saying
however also and also nobody has sent me a cake and my addresses in the show notes right anyway
oh no no Alison you're you're you're actually not correct on that so Andrew January sent me this
coster bag of cakes which is very nice thank you Andrew January Emily January sent Claire Briarley
of Croydon a cake which was I think some cupcakes but I believe I just saw that someone has indeed
um placed an order for a cake to come to Wartham's though Alison so I believe you are about to receive
some cake um oh no no don't do that oh god I have actually not I have actually not put my address
in the show notes anywhere because I do I do think they should not bribe committee members in this
way I feel bad about it so but on the other hand it's on its way I said I do also love cake thank
you very much and also I bought like 12 brownies for yesterday and they've all gone and I can't
really blame my cohabities that much I think I think I have eaten more than my fair share of brownies
so yeah I did get I did get delivered cake by by my husband also and beer there are there are
photographs um yes indeed um but no the I have been I've been super super happy like I was a bit
worried that I'd feel left out of the coverage home because obviously we cannot participate because
we have to be the people scoring that's also great fun oh yeah but scoring it has almost been more
fun yeah like it is so good I don't know how many houses I have now told that their aug is not
off enough I loved um Special shout out to Vanessa who's Dalek and Dalek in disguise
well I really love quite a lot I really like that but all of the submissions have been phenomenal
thank you all so much for for really getting into it um Liz I put I put in that I put the one in
which shows a pop sign with lots of legs and my intention was you get like as many points as
there were legs on the pop sign that turns out to be quite difficult but now I love that everyone's
anticipating how many legs is lots of legs does this pub sign having a plague is again there's lots
of legs it's very good yeah they were kind of like is this pub side good enough and I'm like
no how many legs do we need not one too many lots yeah um indeed indeed
uh there was a controversy and we should discuss it here it's a serious business and it's one that
shouldn't be treated lightly and that is is getting up at 10 a.m. early some members of the
convention have strenuously denied such charges and claim that it is not early and that there are
earlier times um so Alison and Liz let's discuss this controversy now oh god it's early
the problem is now that I am old yeah I I kind of like well if we're doing parkrun or not parkrun
on Saturday we can do stroll within the entities which is kind of like a riff on worldcon stroll
with the stars because we don't have any stars we we only have the entities a convention stroll at
9 a.m. on sunday that will make perfect sense and Liz said yes who should I put that down for it
and I said me I'll find somebody to volunteer to look after it later could anyone spot the
the tiny floor in this plan you'll get around to it later 9 o'clock this morning I went for a walk
but lots of other people did just well we had about I think we had about 10 of us on the walk and
it was good including Liz who was not walking in the cool fresh post-rain air of waltz and stow she
was walking in the 38 degree baking heat of tylen did the mid-afternoon how empty was your parkless
so the park was quite empty I mean it's a small park walking in the park was lovely the problem is
I have to walk to and from the park in the street and it is incredibly hot and then I had to
essentially come back and drink a large ice drink and shower to cool down enough to do a podcast
so there are certain floors at this but yeah I was gonna say I am I'm old now like I would have said
10 o'clock was horrendously early especially for a convention where I will have been up till you
know three or four or something but now actually I just wake up at 8 30 it's bit despite you really
I have woken up the last two days just slightly too late to cycle the zoom but I mean it's been
okay I think yes no one noticed um indeed the chat seems to be about um about basically and
things it isn't early and everyone else seems pretty agreed that it is um I think the best one is
Maggie who says there are earlier times but she does not necessarily wish to experience them
and that is a fair way of looking at it I think. Farah does not think tylen o'clock is early as
we know because Farah was um at the vanguard of can you have parties earlier in the day and we had a
birthday's party at 2 p.m. In particular the voxel party which could not be earlier in the day
because if you're going to drink a vast amount of whiskey then fall over you do not want to do
that at 2 o'clock in the afternoon and if you do then um we'll just like talk to us like it's fine
but like reach out yeah no no there's help available yeah we have whiskey and Max has said in chat
live action feedback uptime and not uptime have all blurred into one big puppy care session and
I don't know what awake even is now that's fair Farah defends herself there are afternoon
alcoholic drinks gnt pims and that is a good point pims pims is very good in the sunshine at about
2 o'clock in the afternoon okay we are going to have an afternoon pims party at punctuation three
you heard it three here first because somebody tagged that in the next five channel so we don't
forget it uh what she might have was so no I mean and don't get me wrong I'm always up for pims
Farah is hosting the pims party hehehe now that is how you make a party
you heard it here yep you could get pims delivered from a number of excellent pims delivery
companies like sainsbury's tascos and a cardo I found out alby's does an off brand pims which
is apparently almost as good as the real thing and significantly cheaper um I think you probably
discovered that from James Bacon who um used it for doubling parties I think because you could
basically make a ton of pims using geeves I think it's called I think it is something like that for
something like a third of the cost right we should um i've just had a letter of comment it was sent
to only me for some reason and uh it's from the British Science Fiction Association and it says
that they're having an AGM which as you listen to this listener if you listen to it on the first
day it's available will be in two days time and there is um a guest of honor talk by alle
alizone scoot alizone scoot you know about her she seems a bit dodgy um the convention is called
"conspire yenui" who I do not know on twitter said "I cannot wait to hear from allison on fandom
experiences that seems to reflect our digital culture that is rooted in convergence culture
and theory and participatory revolution" and I saw that tweet and I thought oh well she's clearly
looking forward to my talk but on the other hand I felt like a rabbit caught in headlights because
the current state of my talk which is called "my year in virtual fandom" is kind of at the
I've been on zoom a lot recently level so I feel that in order to meet yens expectations I'm
gonna have to raise my game quite a bit of the next week um two days is your listening to this but
by the time you're listening to this I will be much closer to her having written my talk narrator
she won't have been um which means the time will not have done it but I will actually be panicking
by then okay yeah that I believe that I believe Liz are you gonna go to the bsfaagm to listen to
alizone talk about having been on zoom a lot so so I mean I'm gonna say to alizone that
possibly ring the Hugo voter pack and then an online convention and then going to an online
convention where you have to give a speech which maybe start you see many things for a six week
period the same okay so I've been thinking about this because I've become very self-reflective and
I've concluded that the last couple of months when I have prepared the Hugo voter pack and planed
done help with the planning of punctuation have been quite full but I would probably have been
able to cope if I had not additionally inserted 205 hours of Hades which is a video 205 hours
that's a job I mean right I think it's important I think it's important to contextualize this
that's eight and a half days I think of the 205 hours only about four of that was in four days of
that was in entire days and that's the sort of day where you wake up go oh I'm awake I can play
Hades and then two o'clock the following morning you go oh I should stop now and go to sleep oh none
of my limbs were properly so yes um alizone alizone has been enjoying Hades um but I'm sure it will
be a great bs-fay talk as well and I'm gonna go I've not been a member of the bs-fay for the AGM
before but I'm gonna go with that that was the thing I was gonna say is that you can only go to
full thing if you are a member of the bs-fay or the science fiction foundation um and I'm not
currently a member of either so I might try and do the thing I think they've got some spare tickets
you can pick up on event bright or something yeah I think it's free and you can get spare tickets
I you know and if not yeah but I've got a I've got to actively go and get the spare tickets rather than
like spontaneously waking up and going oh I can go watch Alice's talk so there is a small amount
of activation and if not I'm sure I can hit them up for a guest list so I will probably go to some
bits of it but I have to sort of register session by uh session and go and get them off twitter so
which is perfectly reasonable I should say it's perfectly reasonable that um yeah I hope they've
invited me to the whole day you know if you're members of these organizations you can go to their
whole day and otherwise you pick up some free tickets I just haven't done it they've sent me
a link so I hope I'm hoping that'll do for the whole day otherwise I might have to give them a
paddock to not stare or something I think if you're like I guess you get to go to the whole thing yes
I hope so um you think wouldn't you yeah yeah and right in the chat as a member of the BSFA
do I have to register on this link too I don't think you do because um I think I have a link to
the zoom link in my emails right at this very point um so and I think if you check your emails
you might find that the same is true um and indeed FARA in the chat confirms my suspicions
so thank you very much but it will be good um I have been a member of the BSFA for
ooh months now and I'm looking forward to diving in seeing what's up and we have for those of you
at the convention we have a panel coming up later which is entitled what did the UK's
national genre organizations ever do for us in which we discussed the role of the BSFA and
the British Francis Society and the Science Fiction Foundation in British fandom and um as you listen
to this if you were a member of punctuation 2 I believe you can check the catch up program link
because I believe it will be up for another week on an unlisted youtube link but that is off the
top of my head but I'm pretty sure it is being recorded for some length of time um so do check
back um but it will be a good panel and HARA yeah I'm moderating it so I like your your faith in me
John thank you one of the other things that's been nice about um this weekend is that we've had
representation from Winnipeg in 2023 and we went to their party last night and lost asked them lots
of questions about Winnipeg I feel like they weren't necessarily the most relevant to the world
con because a lot of them like is it true that it never goes above freezing point and is
Winnipeg the city that the song Red River Valley was written about and um what did Winnipeg ever do
for us anyway and isn't Winnipeg just a hipster version of um North London can you get mousse cheese
we asked about mousse cheese we did we talked about mousse cheese and I discovered a source
for mousse cheese that costs six hundred and seventy five dollars a kilo yep um so I'm not
not I have a kind of hard limit on the amount I'm prepared to pay for cheese and it's significantly
less than that I mean I'm not sure I would have said I did have a hard limit but significantly
more than Ian Sorensen who I discovered bought 14 pounds worth of cheese and then was surprised
to discover that got eaten up quite quickly by three visitors I'll hang on you mean 14 pounds
as in sterling rather than I mean as in um fake kilos yeah I mean 14 pounds sterling which is about
as much cheese as I ate for dinner yesterday yeah we had too much cheese his family was genuinely
worried she might be having a heart attack and then she was like oh no it's probably just I ate
too much cheese um which tells you how much cheese she had eaten oh yeah well she'd actually
done that on top of that cake that she was describing that consisted of you make a cake and then it's
using many different sorts of cream and then it's not creamy enough so you tip another couple of
pints of cream into it was that that's right is it not it's got an entire liter of cream in it
and then it's also got condensed and evaporated milk so it's quite good it's a very good cake
like you can confirm ah is it healthy no my long-time associates know the time extremely fond of
cardamom buns as sold by the fabric bakery and for briex recipe turned up in the guardian and I
discovered the reason that they're so good is that there was essentially about a kilogram of butter
in the recipe that's like oh that you can make anything more delicious by putting more butter in
it yes indeed um so DC says mistakes were made by everybody in response to espania saying mistakes
were made and that is true I also ate too much cheese and then I had some beer and then espania
made me a cocktail called a suffering bastard and yeah you know it's a convention I woke up this
morning late and bleary which is good John was the last per last committee member up this morning
which I think is pretty unusual yes that has happened before when we had the 8am committee
meeting and John went straight from bed to meeting oh yeah that's right having agreed to having an
8am committee meeting John didn't really turn up till about 8.25 and he was in his pajamas in a way
that was kind of like I have clearly rolled out of bed on to zoom I woke up and I checked my phone
and it had a message on it from one Alison Scott saying 'Oi meeting at eight' and I looked at the
clock and I thought 'oh bugger' and then I went to a meeting very quickly and that was a good way to
wake up with texts from me explaining why he should have been somewhere sometime earlier
Griffin in the chat has said 'this is why brioche keeps fresh for so long' and I can confirm that
in my house brioche keeps fresh for about two minutes after which there is no brioche that is fair
Farah says that buffalo cheese was located by Farah at the local artisanal market today
and as that moose and elk are the only dairy cheeses Farah can eat this was very happy making
yeah weirdie I couldn't find any local buffalo cheese I thought this is a lot of
water buffalo maybe there would be a buffalo cheese market but I haven't found it I have
also discovered that actually eating a load of cheese at midnight is not really a great idea in
terms of smooth sleeping it's supposed to give you interesting dreams it did not give me interesting
dreams it gave me indigestion well I think that's why it gives people interesting dreams right
yes but I regularly very large amounts of cheese at midnight so I don't regularly eat a lot of cheese
you see yeah there's no time of day at which I don't eat too much cheese I want to say thank you
very much to Anna after for proposing and getting the gin tasting started sadly Anna was ill on
Friday so couldn't make it but we were very grateful for her leadership and it was a good time
and I very much enjoyed my gins thank you very much to and for suggesting a box of cheeses for
the cheese tasting and for leading us through the discussion thereof on the zoom yesterday
and then a preemptive thank you to the unity brewing company the head brewer Jimmy will be
leading us through some of unity's beers later today and that will also be brilliant
and the tastings were one of the best bits of punctuation one in my opinion and so this time I
was very glad that we kind of did a more focused thing where people actually had the same stuff
if they wanted to and it has been it has been a real joy so thank you everyone for leading those
and thank you also everyone who came along and made them so so great really really enjoyed all three
although there wasn't an official cake for the birthday's party I think an afternoon birthday's
party with lots of cake was also a good plan oh yes yesterday all i ate was unhealthy breakfast
cake and cheese yeah we got we got our fry up delivered and then we went and then it's
banya had the sf cookbooks panel so she brought me a cookie and then it's banya had the birthdays
party so she brought me a cake and then some time passed and then Andrew had some cake delivered
to me for the scavenger hunt and then it was the cheese tasting and that was my that was my day
and um there's not it was so good it was so good i can't i can't emphasize enough how great it was
but it was very healthy but it was good i think what we've discovered is that socializing centered
around food and specifically food that you can go out and get in advance and procure and think about
is actually quite a good way of structuring your socializing when we're all in different rooms
so it gives us some kind of connection between us and also gives people you know some some specific
reason to be partying rather than just we're having a party although i do regret that i didn't buy any
birthday candles put in my birthday cake that was my failing
do any of you have any questions for ask och to thought i mean to be fair in the chat so um we did
ask what we what people wanted us to talk about and griffin did say that he wanted multiple letters
of comment from clever i live croydon and clairn ottie she's quite a few episodes behind and mark
did explain them that is because she's been spending too much time playing arkam horror um so there is
that um so oh my god malcom we should have done that um malcom in the chat says with lizzie's
suggestion that that um he should send out chocolate lists and yes absolutely how did we not i'm
sorry hashtag next time hashtag next time um now um and will john insert the sound effect correctly
in the final edit i mean i'll have a go uh never say never um and then dc they want us to do some
of the scurrilous gossip i could talk about time zones i could talk about um if you i mean this doesn't
this doesn't count here because this is part of the octa thought um collective and also part of
the committee so we have to we are very happy to make some allowances for the fact that she's um
seven hours ahead six we're not willing to get the number of hours you are ahead right but
we're willing we're willing to make allowances six hours ahead but in general if we're one of the
reasons why we specified punctuation as a british convention was that there is another model you
could have for online conventions where you really get into the global thing and you really do set
it up so that it is a 24 hour thing with program happening all around the clock that really brings
in people from around the world and i think that is a great model and somebody i would really like
somebody to take that and run with it um but it's not the model of punctuation which means that we
are thrilled that people join us from um all around the world but that but when you say oh it's a shame
you've put on something interesting at 11 o'clock in the morning we're kind of like three o'clock
in the morning um we're like well you know you can just stay up for it or get up for it you know
tough so i would say yeah i think it'd be great to do that but actually it's quite a lot of effort
to put on a days worth of things during the times when people in the UK are awake and it would make
things a lot more complicated because i already was thinking like in a few cases it's like oh this
person would be great for that panel right then i must you know i can only put it in these two or
three times locked when everyone is awake and that makes things more difficult and a couple of times
it was like oh this person's just joining they might be great for this item but too late i've
already scheduled it in and it's at you know 2 a.m their time so that is difficult but i would say
there is an example who does do a good job of it which is firecon did this they did last year
an architect to do the firecon fringe where they essentially will have 12 hours of programming
running in the 12 hours when east coast USA is not really awake so i think it was sort of 9 p.m
to 9 a.m and is deliberately made for people who are outside that time zone and that is still
free so you can still go and watch that even if you don't go to the rest of the convention so they're
doing a really good job of it and there's so much to look at but last year i think they ran it by
almost having two two kind of separate things there were people who ranked the fringe bit and people
running the regular bit so that's how you do it you've got to have multiple teams i think
i haven't quite realized that firecon fringe was was convention for the off hours because i was
expecting it to be more kind of convention adjacent activity is what i tend to think of fringes being
well if anyone if anyone did want to run a punctuation fringe with some sort of
amusing punctuation team name that ran in the times when we were asleep then i would not stop them
but i i think it also does need i mean in this case i think it was a group of people who were
you know very keen to have some something happening in their in their time zone
in you know in the same way that firecon works so basically we would need a fairly dedicated team
i think of people who are non-uk and dedicated enough that they you know i think most of our
Australians are happy to just try and get some program in the time zones when they are awake
british bradshaw suggests we call it the punctuation bangs which i like a great deal
um that's amazing so if anyone would like to run the punctuation bangs the next time
to it's worth it for the joke people for the joke i mean i think we may have to do it ourselves
actually we can't actually be in charge of it because it will be in the middle of the night but
that is a great great name it is i'm i'm yes yeah no brilliant i'm banging
uh do you hear me uh jerry we can't repeat that on the podcast it's a family show jerry you're
already going to be beeping out you've actually got things on your auto thing that you then have to
be pat of the podcast i mean look right that is not the point it's a family show and that was
the octa thought podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
[Music]
i've realized john that you know one of the people things that people of this is actual
content for octa thought which i'm doing terrible thing now um one of the things that people have
said about online conventions is that they don't like the feeling of talking into a void of having
your audience out there but not being able to see them or have them react and i would like to say
that doing a podcast for a year really helps with this feeling yeah we just recommend that
everyone who is struggling with this just just do 34 episodes of a podcast and you'll you'll be all
right um is that and may not be helpful no it's um it's interesting it is but it is definitely true
that when we do the live podcast it is very fun to have the chat going and like see everyone like
reacting in real time that is uh it's phenomenal um so thank you all very much for coming i'm not
sure it makes for an actual coherent podcast like i think it's possible doing the live ones maybe
makes the actual later recorded podcasts slightly less good because we are a bit like disjointing
tonight we pick up lots of stuff from the comments yeah i don't know how the i don't know how the
serious podcast we stole our format from um manages this we should we should pay some more
attention really i think the record for longer is part of it i think the live episodes are off
for quite long and then then get edited quite sharply one i think also they um they do um uh
they because we've done one live recording which we did standalone after confusion where we basically
just did the regular show in the chat burbled in the background and that felt less fun to me than
doing one where we pay a lot of attention to the chat and kind of interact a lot but i think probably
what they do is mostly ignore the chat unless they want like information out of it which is good from
their perspective but less good for fostering the community feel the theme music for this episode was
fanfare for space by kevin mccloud at ncompatec.com used under a creative commons attribution 3.0 license
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.