If I have strong feelings, I will think about them.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 134th episode of Octothorpe, a podcast for
Science Fiction and Science Fiction fandom, which is coming to you late. I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty. John, I think you should keep that real-time pause in.
For how long it took Alison to react.
Just realised we've had a letter from Tobes.
No, we've got quite a lot of letters.
So we do have a letter from Tobes. Do you want to introduce that one, Alison?
Happy to.
Tobes wrote to us after we discussed him last episode and he said,
"I met Jason Isaacs once. I still remember what he said to me.
Who are you and what the hell are you doing in my house?"
Such a sweet guy.
So thanks for that, Tobes.
We also heard from Clary, who said, "They really enjoy Octothorpe live and so
glad it seems to be a regular fiction now."
I think we quite like it as well.
I mean, we don't want to become one of those people who demand a spot on the program,
but I think hungover people enjoy us.
And yes, Clary reckons Octothorpe live gives a nice burst of community feeling before everyone heads home.
Also, Clary would like to apologise when flying on the Discord that Alison gave everyone COVID at Birmingham.
She gave me COVID at Birmingham, but that isn't enough data to support a strong statistical analysis.
Did you give Clary COVID at Birmingham?
Okay, so I have two things to say here.
The first is, I'm looking for some support for Liz here on the,
you can't actually tell who it was who gave it to you.
But also, I believe that Clary and I were in the same conversation for some time with the person who I played for giving me COVID.
And I suspect that that person gave us both COVID at Eastcon.
Yes, unfortunately, we probably cannot do this.
The statistically rigorous method, like reconstruct those chains.
Yeah, yeah. If I get COVID any more times at Eastcon, it will start to become a statistically significant data set of its very own.
But no, I didn't catch COVID this Easter, so that was good.
Congratulations.
At least not as far as I know.
So, well, hey.
We also heard from Collette Reap, who said that she was listening to the latest podcast this morning
and noticed that I was not sure how to pronounce the name Erian,
as in Erian Weston, who is a finalist for Best Fan Writer,
and so wrote in to tell me that that is how.
So thank you very much, Collette. I appreciate it very much.
Although she does note, disclaimer.
She speaks Swedish with a Stockholm accent.
Other Swedish accents are available.
Other Swedes, please write in with phonetic manglings of Swedish words that we will then bongon on the podcast.
Yay!
Or don't.
Multiculturalism.
It is possible that we have already mentioned this, but it's so good.
We're going to mention it twice, if so.
Rosanna Pendelbury had noticed that we mentioned in our last regular episode
that two of our picks had had in-depth reviews by Rosanna Pendelbury,
and the third had not being not genre.
So she went ahead and watched the Death of Stalin and did a fabulous review of it,
which you can go and read.
And I would recommend that you do.
And we're going to put a link in the show notes.
Thank you very much, Rosanna.
That is considerable commitment to the bit, and we appreciate it.
It was great.
I had an enthusiastic conversation with Rosanna about this at Eastcon, and it is very good.
Yes, me too.
Rosanna was the only person to take me up on the offer of
buy me a drink, and I will tell you my Dragon Age opinions at length,
and we did for like an hour and a half.
That was good.
Chris Garcia writes in to say, "They have nominated
Andrews to its TikTok feed as best-related work."
Fair enough.
And has also nominated a different TikTok in best dramatic presentation short form.
So, you know, there's a range of opinions on TikToks.
Chris does mention Chris Barkley's lawsuit against A. McCarty,
which we will get to later in the episode,
and says, "I have a Dungeons and Dragons box that Gary gave me years ago."
So, you know, good, good one, Chris.
That is probably in your best name drops that you've done.
So, hurrah.
Thanks for it again.
Probably not planning to sell it, is he?
I don't know.
I'd guess he'd put it in a museum, but I might be wrong.
Yeah, yeah.
Thank you to everyone who posted on Facebook,
so that his "I'm gonna read them all out."
*reads text*
In our live episode from Iskahn 133,
we discussed lapping the papal conclave,
and various people linked like RPGs of doing a papal conclave.
But someone, I think it was Tammy Coxin, reminded me that A.
Department does do a class every year at the University of Chicago,
which is literally lapping a papal conclave.
And this week got a writer from the New York Times,
possibly because the winner of the papal conclave has said,
"Well, I'm on the only Pope right now, right?"
So it is actually a delightful write-up with lots of photos,
because they all dress up in medieval costumes,
and it does look really fun.
I mean, I'm not sure the depth of research I would need to accurately portray
a character in this papal lab is obviously more than I'm ever going to do,
but I am delighted that there are a bunch of college students
who are just super excited to go to college and pretend to be the Borges.
*reads text*
Doing just a little bit about Corflu, so the cover makes sense.
Apparently, yes.
And listen.
So I just wanted to say,
we've been to conventions recently.
I think we're going to not talk about EasterCon terribly much today,
because we have some other things to talk about.
But I went to Corflu, which is the fancy advanced convention in Newbury,
the weekend before Easter and had a fantastic time,
including a trip out of Woking to see all of the HD Wells stuff there.
And it was all very nice and well done to Dave Hodsen and crew for organising it.
But because I've put something on the cover,
I thought I wanted to say a little bit about it,
which is that I made the fan awards for this year's Corflu,
the fan awards have given for fanzine activity.
You have to be quite a restricted definition of fanzine to win one of those,
and we've poked fun at that a bit in the past.
But as I was making the awards or getting the awards ordered,
I thought I'd better order a sample one to see if they were okay.
And that features on our cover this episode.
So this is not a real fan award we did not win a fan award.
We cannot win fan awards because we are specifically mentioned in the
write-up of the fan awards as a thing that is not eligible for them.
And people do keep voting for us, which is flattering,
but probably not necessary anymore.
Yeah, because Alison made us our own Knockoff fan award,
so we don't need a real one anymore.
Yeah, we've got a knockoff one.
I'm probably going to stick it to the fanfons auction.
For next Easter, or into the fanfons extravaganza next weekend.
Next weekend.
Next Easter, because we're going to be having an auction,
a silent auction, a table, a tabola, a direct sales, and God knows what next year.
I think it's quite nice.
So now you've filmed me with the dilemma of do I have to go and bid on it in the fanfons auction.
Day here.
Well done Alison.
Currently on my mantelpiece.
It's almost as good as when John donated the R2D to me a cat to the fanfons auction,
and I then bought it.
Yeah.
Okay, that's probably enough about Corfley, right?
Yes.
So we just wanted to bring up that locus.
I've started their 2025 fundraiser.
If you're a person who likes to go and contribute to fundraisers,
they do a bunch of nice novels and zoos' authors and other stuff on offer,
and their logo is pretty cute and you can buy merch.
I did go and compare their 2025 fundraiser to the 2024 fundraiser,
because I was interested in the amount of money that they were looking for.
And based on comparing those two, locus' revenue is flat,
but their costs are up 21%, and they are trying to make that up by having a bigger
crowd funner. And I know we've talked about locus before and the sustainability,
but it worries me that if they've had a 21% increase in one year and their revenue is basically flat,
that this is obviously not infinitely sustainable,
because you're going to get to a point where you're trying to get like,
you know, at this point they're trying to get over $300,000 from a fundraiser,
which is like higher than any of the semi-prosines.
I think that do these kinds of fundraisers, and I think they are risking getting to a point where
like the fundraiser is half their costs, and that's not only tricky to do,
but it's not an income you can rely on.
Yeah, I think ultimately we speak from a position of love, we want locus to carry on going.
We've said, broadly speaking, he said this before, but the main concern here is that if they don't
do something to work out how they can be sustainable, they are going to go away.
And I am not, I remain unconvinced that this is the way they should go, but they are continuing,
so I wish them good luck, and we will put a link in the show notes.
Is that fair?
I don't think I have anything more to say.
Quick, think of an opinion.
Print magazines, all print magazines are struggling at the moment,
and have to do a lot of work to continue to be relevant in the world we live in.
I'm not sure locus is putting in that work, and I think we said, I said this the last time.
Are they struggling?
I mean, someone has just bought Azimovs an analogue and FNSF to bundle them all up into one company,
and either they think they're failing businesses and expect to make no money,
or they're actually doing okay?
Difficult to tell.
Yes.
In between recording this episode and the episode releasing, the Arthur C. Clark award
shortlist 2025 was announced, and the books on that shortlist are Private Rights by Julia Armfield,
The Ministry of Time by Calli Ann Bradley, Extremophile by Ian Green,
Annie Bot by Sierra Greer, Service Model by Adrian Tchaikovsky, and 13 Ways to Kill Lula Bel Rock by
Maud Wolf. That shortlist was constructed by this year's judging panel, which includes me,
and Dolly Garland, Gene Rowe, Nick Clark and Glenn Morgan, and the winner is going to be announced
on the 25th of June, which is a Wednesday. So we will probably talk about that in a future episode,
but I wanted to record this little drop-in for you listeners so that you knew what was up back to the show.
We are aware that we need to talk about the recent Belfast East Kong, because we have not talked about
it enough, and we are also aware that there is some other news happening that we haven't really
discussed in any detail. Today we're mostly going to be talking about the Seattle controversy,
but just to highlight one piece of news that we haven't discussed yet. Chris Barkley is suing
Dave McCarthy and has written two articles on file 770 about that, so we've linked them both
in the show notes, and we will discuss this in more detail as and when a resolution is reached.
Right, is it time for the main course? It's time to discuss Seattle. Shall I attempt to
summarise the past week of Seattle stuff in 90 seconds or less? Yes, please Liz, good luck.
I'm just going to caveat that by saying, first off, that Alison, John and I are all
current Seattle Worldcon staff. That is our current declared interest. Still Seattle Worldcon staff.
Still, yes. So, what happened with Seattle Worldcon? On April 30th, when I was still recovering
from like Jetlag and East Kong hangovers, the Worldcon put out a statement saying they'd had
questions about the use of AI tools in their vetting process for program participants,
and they tried to explain that they did use chat GPT to try and automate some of the online
searches they do for participant vetting, and that it saved lots of time and they think it was more
accurate. Many people were not pleased with this statement because it doesn't contain an apology
or really a lot of detail other than kind of we did this and we think it's good. So then on May
2nd, there was an apology saying we did this and no, it wasn't good. Sorry. That was obviously
like an interim statement they put out. And then on May 6th, there was a second much longer statement
from the chair addressing, you know, the one instance where they had used chat GPT, apologizing to
everyone that they had harmed, and then kind of a long statement at the end from one of the program
team. I think they had the division head from program yet explaining exactly how and why they
had used the chat GPT and gives them like the exact prompts and what they did. In between
those last two statements, there was also a statement saying that the WISVIS division head
huger administration deputy huger administrator, Cassedine Eclisoye, and S. McAlum Stewart,
Heinrich Lissen Ester resigned from their roles at the 2025 Worldcon because they don't see a path
forward to making a contribution and saying that they hadn't used, you know, LLMs in any part of
the huger award process. So I think the first thing to note is that the spectrum of opinions on
AI usage of the podcast is quite wide from Alison, who is quite a lot more pro than I am and Liz,
who is in the middle. As usual. And we're not going to get much into that. I think that having
been on the internet and talked to members of the community and seen, you know, people discussing
this over the last couple of years, I think even if you think chat GPT is great, it was reasonably
obvious that the use of chat GPT coming out was going to go down poorly with a sizable segment
of the community. And I think that even if chat GPT was a great tool that saved a lot of effort and
was entirely perfect for this use case, it was still probably not worth the amount of goodwill
Seattle lost to use it. I am much more pro AI than either of the other two. I don't think we can
get into much of why that is. But even from a position of AI's got quite a lot to offer,
I think this was a particularly cloth headed use of it. And although I agree with John that it
should have been obvious it wasn't going to go down very well. It clearly wasn't obvious to
people in the Seattle team up to and including the chair at the point where they issued the
first statement, because they clearly thought that the first statement would settle it down.
And I just have a quote from Douglas Adams here, which is, "This has made a lot of people very
angry and has been widely regarded as a bad move. I think it has made a lot of people very angry
and has been widely regarded as a bad move." Yes, I mean, I think the thing is, I'm a little
bit more pro AI I think than John, because I have used it to kind of manipulate some incredibly
tedious kind of data cleaning and reorganizing stuff that it is quite good at. But that is usually
taking something which is totally public and then asking chat GPT to reform up the results for me.
And not, for instance, taking the names of program participants who have applied in a process that
is not like completely open and then saying, "Can you tell me if there are any scandals about them
specifically about racism and homophobia?" At that point, I think you go, "Is this a thing I should
be asking chat GPT?" Even if you thought it was okay at some things like, "This is a specific case
where you really should be ringing some alarm bells." I may have moved on to the next bit, sorry.
No, I think that's right, because the next bit is the statements and apologies, where I did say a
little bit about that before. I mean, the other thing I think is obvious when the first statement
is that whoever had, you know, presumably someone has raised these concerns and you would think that
someone raising the concerns would make people, you know, people who are putting out these statements
say, "Hmm, is this person way out on one side of the debate and that's going to be the only
like the sending voice we have?" Or should it make you think, "Hmm, actually maybe this is a
harbinger of the weight of the internet dropping down our head, which is to come?" I understand that
that there were concerns raised internally and that that led to some considerable debate internally.
Clearly, Kathy and Sonny Jim started off thinking that it was, it was that the time saved was worth
the effort and I think the internet has demonstrated that that's probably not the case because they
probably spent quite a lot of time trying to sort it out now. I think the second statement was
actually fine. It was a holding statement that said, "Oh no, we're sorry and we're going to take
the time to do it." Hairs were running pretty wild at that point. I think it was really important
to get an interim statement out and they did that. I think that first, so the first statement was
clearly, I think, not an apology and probably massively underestimating the reaction that would
happen. The second, the apology and response from Chair on the second of May is very good.
Kathy directly apologizes for the use of chat GBT, apologizes, well, says that she regrets
releasing their first statement and acknowledges her mistake and says she is truly horrid for the
harm it caused and it's like, "Yes, she has apologized directly and actively for both things
as the chair and that is good." And then the third statement goes into the detail. But I think the
apology was already in place on the second of May. The third statement is going into the actual
actions that will be taken as a result and the thing that actually happened for which they are
apologizing. And so the third statement is less of an apology and more a damage report almost.
But I do think at this point, the chair and in that third statement, the division head
have both actively apologized for the use of chat GBT and the chair has also apologized
for that first statement. And so, I think that is good to see those things happening.
We're being awfully moderate for what we want.
Being super sedate. Well, I think because I think it's not wrong. I want to carry on being
Hugo finalist liaison really. I don't think it's, I want to continue working in the division. I don't
want to try and undermine where it's got to. I would like all of the wisps parts of Seattle to
to go as smoothly as possible. I guess one more thing which is to follow on from what I said before.
What I think is interesting is that I can't tell whether there is a genuine divide between
Bandomat-Large and its opinions on chat GBT and the ones who are working on Seattle and their
opinions on chat GBT or if it's just the balance of opinions and in the early phase, certain ones
carried more weight than others. But it is interesting. I think if you have a bunch of volunteers
who are maybe trying to make their lives easier and see these tools as more acceptable,
and that's out of step with how the community is majority feeling. I've seen many more people
saying, "No, this is a nothing you should do than people saying, 'Yeah, this is a great idea.'"
I do wonder whether there is some division between people who are either retired or work entirely
for themselves, e.g. freelance creatives and people who work in large organizations because
the impression I get is that a lot of jobs in large organizations are making increasing use of
AI tools in their daily work. So we may be seeing a split there between people who are working on
the back end of Seattle who are using these tools professionally and certainly the creatives and
largely the creatives who have been absolutely adamant that this was a terrible idea.
Well, I also think we're seeing the disconnect between the people from whom the work has been
stolen and the people from whom it has not. And it turns out I think category A is more angry and
that isn't really surprising. Because for instance, all my scientific papers are available open access
because that's how you should do science. But it does mean that if someone decides to use them,
I don't get a say in that because I signed my right to it away. I have never written anything which is
sort of copywritable in a different sense. And so yeah, I am not as angry. This is not as personal
and affront to me as it would be if my books were in these training sets without permission.
And I think that's the other thing which is this is very personal for those people. Understandably
so I think. Johnny, your fans in the creative commons licensed. Yeah. Okay. Because I mean,
I am positive that my papers are like John's inner training data sets and work because that's
what I say I'm not for. But I also suspect that blog posts of mine are scraped and inner training
data set. Yeah, I mean, I think the stuff that you've just written on the internet. But I'm not very
good writer. So they're welcome to that. Well, that's the other thing, right? I don't have a
professional interest in my Twitter. It's true. I'm not earning any money from my writing or my
podcasting. Yeah. And that means that my opinion on this will be different. And I think I think I
am trying. I don't want to make it sound like I think that's unreasonable. I think, you know, if
this is your job and someone is stealing work you have done for your livelihood that you are deeply
creatively invested in, that must be absolutely fucking infuriating. And I'm not going to tell anyone
that they can't be angry about it because that seems out of step. So I do make my income
for another few weeks. Shortly, most of my income will be my pension. But I do make my income such
as it is from my art. And it all has been routinely stolen, not by being used for training material,
but just stolen because that's how the t-shirt industry in particular works, repeatedly and
consistently the entire time I've done it, along with everybody else who works in this space.
And we just kind of suck it up. Many of the places that the theft is happening are countries
where they don't have a copyright law that is anything like what we're used to in Europe and
America. So although I understand that that is a terrible, you know, the theft of material is
terrible. That theft of material is happening in lots of different spaces, not just this one.
Yes, and were you to be angry about it, I would support you.
I've given up anger, John.
The other thing I would say is I did see some debate about saying, oh, well, if they were logged
in, they use chat bbt for zero or whatever. And that's a different training set and maybe it doesn't
contain as much material. And of course, what I discover is it's very difficult to verify that
one because chat bbt will tell you it is trained on industry standard machine learning data sets.
But it won't tell you what an industry standard machine learning data set is.
So if you assume it's the same as meta who downloaded a giant pilot books off the internet,
then it's definitely got them in. But if there is some like repository of standardized machine
learning data sets that don't contain copyright material, then it's trained on something different.
But then of course, I guess you say, even if chat gbt for zero is not maybe previous versions were
trained on it. And so it has been implicitly used in the building on them. But I thought it was
interesting that I can't definitely verify like, is my stuff in chat gbt for zero?
I'm wary of getting too much into this. But the other thing is obviously if chat gbt has
demonstrated to for instance, stack overflow, that they can either have their content scraped
with no compensation unlicensed, or have their content scraped licensed and with compensation,
is that chat gbt? Like it may well be that chat gbt has now basically gone to enough
companies in the middle, like, well, now we will pay you. And if you don't say, yes, we're going to do
it anyway. And it's like, does that make it okay? I don't want to get into that because I think we've
spent an hour on whether that's okay. But what I will say is I can see, I can see again, how a
creative might be justifiably concerned that that does not make it all hunky-dory. Going back to
the statement that was made by on the sixth made by the chair and the division head of program,
I thought this statement was good for two reasons, which is firstly, it goes into detail on what
exactly happened, which I think is good. But secondly, it commits to five concrete actions
that will be done as a result of this thing. And I think Liz talked about these already
in her introduction, but they're going to redo the work that use chat gbt. They're going to bring
outside members of the community who have worked in World Compromor programming to come in and
perform an audit. They're going to allow partial or full refunds of memberships from members.
They're going to reevaluate their communication methods internally and externally, and they're
going to explore options for providing additional oversight and guidance to the chair and leadership
team. And that's going to be finalized in the in a meeting, which is going to happen in the coming
week. I think four and five are a bit woolly. I think but that's tricky because I think they
probably need to be a bit woolly because they need to be ongoing things. But the first three
things are very concrete. I think and they're very good. I think I think they are concrete
things that the convention can do to make the situation better in so far as it can be made better
and they are kind of actionable outcomes. What do you think?
I think it's interesting, but they basically, one of the things saying we're taking everything
we do with chat gbt and redoing it with volunteers, you know, so human labor. And that's interesting
because at this point, I think Seattle have already told lots of people that they are on program.
And they have a page of people appearing on the Seattle program. So say that chat gpt gave them
a false negative. It flagged someone as being fine to be on program. And then a human volunteer
goes through and does the checks and discovers actually we think this person probably should not
have been given the okay to be on program and they have to disinvite them. That's going to be a
very interesting process. I think they're good concrete actions, but I do think they're concrete
actions where the program process is really a long way along at this point. And so
they report on their recommendations. It's nice to have this, but if their recommendation is
you use chat gpt to do this thing and we recommend that you don't do that. They've already done that.
If they recommend any like other giant changes that they think are problems in the process,
it kind of depends on what the problem in the process is. Is it something that can actually be
changed? Or is this actually something where, you know, we're now doing a learning exercise for
learning more about what future world cons can do, except we're going to do it in a very public way
and put report out that everyone can then also have 27,000 opinions on. So I'm kind of in two
minds about that. That's fair. I think the audit statement is there so that people who are worrying,
you know, what else does this imply and what else might they have done wrong,
have some reassurance that if something else is wrong, it comes out and is dealt with.
And I appreciate that like working out what you can change if there is something rotten
is probably difficult. I will say though, I suspect my suspicion is nothing else is rotten.
And so the audit will just find that this was a mistake and that everything else is basically
working the same as most other world cons. I mean, and I hope that that's right. But we will see.
Yeah, it's basically, I mean, I think also at this point, it's like, if this is to regain trust in
the program division, then it's probably a bit late. If you don't trust the program division at this
point, you're probably better off with going with point three and getting a full or partial refund
rather than appear on tell program. I don't know. I don't know why I want to say about this, but I
guess what I will say is I time to take your point. But I think you do what you can, right?
You can let the community come in and inspect the way you've been doing things to work out whether
it was okay, except for this one thing. And so you can do that. And like, you can't go back in
time and not do the thing. And so they can't commit to do that. But they can commit as far as they can
to basically saying we're going to excise the bits that people have a problem with. We're going to
make sure the rest of the process is accountable as it possibly can be. And anyone who feels that
the first two things are not good enough can choose not to come. And I don't think I see what
more they could have done. I think this is basically them doing as much as they can to establish
much transparency as they can in, you know, the framework of linear time. I think they've said
rather too much here, this statement should be shorter and clearer and just apologized and got
out of there. But you know, clearly people like the fact it's a long statement. So, you know,
but also that's what they did. They did that on the second of May. If you wanted that statement
that was released four days earlier, this is the detailed statement for people who wanted the detail.
Yes. So the only thing I would have done differently is we won't is the first one had said we did
this wrong. It was stupid. We're very sorry. We won't do it again. And they're not said,
oh, and we're going to come back with more information. And yes, people would have said,
yeah, give us more, give us more, but they would have, it would have died down.
I do think it's good to have concrete steps they are taking, even if, you know, I may
would not have written exactly the same steps they're taking, but that's because I'm a different person.
What? I know. I'm not in charge of everything, John. Sometimes hard to believe.
Outrageous. Shortly before the second part of the statement was released, the division head for
Wispers Cassidy and the Hugo Administrator and Deputy Hugo Administrator Nicholas White and
Esteba Calum Stewart resigned. What do we think about that as three people who were working in
the Wispers division at the time? And I'm still working in the Wispers division as far as I know.
And are all still working in the Wispers division? My point being that you didn't start after that
happened rather than that you have stopped now. All right, John, I'm going on about linear time again.
I'm obsessed with linear time, Liz. We are not party and we're not party to the things that caused
them to resign in detail. And in fact, we couldn't have been because we didn't know they'd resigned
until they'd done it. They did say sorry for that, but it was a bit annoying. They have apologized.
We still love you, Nicholas and Esteba. It's all right. And Cassidy, that was very annoying.
Yeah, it was, I was, it was a bit of a shock to wake up in the morning and find that everyone
above me in the division had resigned overnight. And I found out about it from a statement on
blue sky. We had had a little, we'd had a precursor because they sent us a note to discord.
No, no, we hadn't. You had Alison and I had lizard had nothing. Yeah, John and I had had a note saying
they were considering their positions because I have worked in the sorts of large organizations
quite a lot. Have you you heard the minister say that he is considering his position? Yes.
I interpreted that as they are. I'm not sure if John thought it meant they could. I thought
it probably meant they were gearing up to resign, but I must admit I thought they'd probably
share the resignation statement with us before Facebook. Yes. It's also, I think,
important to note that you two are the Hugo fineless liaisons. So as soon as this happens,
you are going to get Hugo finalists asking lots of questions. Whereas I am just a Hugo
data minion person. And so no one's going to come and ask me questions about what's going on.
We've had relatively few. We've had a couple, but not really. I think, no, but the reason we
haven't had many is because we posted in the Hugo finalist discord saying we found out about
this at the same time as you did and we don't know anything. And that probably limited to the
questions we received on account of how people read it. And then, oh, they're not going to be
useful, are they? And the answer is no, no, we're not. Sorry, Hugo finalists. We're trying.
Yes. So I don't understand this move, if I am honest, because the statements are probably
imperfect in the way that all statements are, but certainly seem in general to apologize and to
make concrete commitments to future action. And so I don't understand what needed to be in these
that was a resignation issue. I think I will say. I think the thing where I would say that the
statement could have been better worded is because the statement does not say exactly why the three
whispers administration division had resigned. It led to a lot of speculation on the internet.
You mean the statement that the resignation statement from whispers rather than the statement from the
chat? Yes. So it led to a lot of speculation about, you know, even though they said no LLM's
agenda survey, I've been using the Hugo process at any stage. It led to a lot of people speculating
that was going on. It led to people speculating that there's something rotten in the Hugo's. It
led to people speculating that all kinds of other things would have happened. And I don't think
the statement was intended to spark a lot of, you know, debate about where these things have been
using the logos. But basically when I see lots of people commenting saying, Oh, I wonder if this
process that I was directly involved in use LLM's then it's like a bit like one, you didn't read the
statement and two, maybe the statement does not make it clear enough what the situation is. So I
think obviously it's hard for us to know exactly all that is going on and why people do not, as I
say, do not see a path forward that enables them to make future contributions. But I do think there
is always like a balance like a world call is a group of people. And the committee even is a group
of people who have to make collective decisions. And you will very rarely agree with all of them.
And some of them you will disagree with so strongly that they are a resigning matter.
And some of them you might not. And so I think it's basically a case of everyone's kind of personal
calibration of that. And maybe in this situation, I would have just been like, well, I don't fully
agree with everything. But I'm never going to agree with 100% of everything. Whereas they felt
this was a very strongly that they wanted to resign over it. I understand that Cassidy,
Nicholas and Esther felt that they needed to resign and that the internal discussions,
which as I've said, none of us approve you to, had got to a point where they didn't think they
could carry on. It's not obvious to me what caused that. I think the sudden resignation,
though of course they are remaining. They have helped a little with the transfer has left
Wussfuss division, which is quite a sensitive part of the world gone quite understaffed. And
it's going to be a big task now for for Catherine and Rosemarita to step up to their new roles.
I don't know if we've said yet. Catherine Duvall is taking over as Wussfuss division head and
Rosemary Park, who is the existing deputy division head for site selection is also going to be
deputy Hugo administration. Catherine will be Hugo administrator. And as one of the staff in the
division, I'm concerned that that's going to leave us in quite a difficult state if anything else
happens in any of the areas that Wussfuss is responsible for. I understand that resignation
and the threat of resignation is one of the things that you can use as a negotiating tool
in these sorts of difficult circumstances. But it is difficult for everyone around in a
star in the staff. We also wanted to talk a little bit about programme and the way it's done.
Way that the programme was done at Seattle is 30 track leads asked, were asked to select people
who they wanted to invite onto the programme. And then applicants recommended for participation
were moved on to the vetting process in which they were vetted to see if there's anything
that might disqualify them. And so basically they're looking for actions that would go against
the Convention Code of Conduct and anti racism statement, which is basically saying, if we think
that you are going to be a problem for our convention, if we put you on programme, we would like you
not to be on programme, please, which is relatively, I think, fair. The people who have received
declines at this point were people who were not selected by the programme track leads in that
first phase. The discourse on the internet has largely been like, how normal is it for this thing
to be done based on the track leads, recommending people to be on the programme, and then the vetting
being done afterwards. And I think the answer here is interesting, because I've seen two basically
contrary or seemingly opposing views, whether I've been people saying it's outrageous that the
track leads are using their own experience of the people that are applying to put them on programme,
and then there are people saying it's outrageous that people are being put on programme if the
track leads don't know who they are, and the track leads should know everyone who they're
putting on programme. And I think the answer is in the middle, I suspect track leads are aware of
people that they want to be on programme, because they're aware of the field that they're working in,
but I also suspect that people who have filled in that survey are sort of inviting some of those
people who have applied to appear on panel items as a result of filling in those surveys. And that's
so track leads based, there are decisions to invite panelists on the content of panelists application,
the track leads knowledge of the applicant and the subject area, and additional input from other
members of the programme team, which is basically, we look at your application to see if it's good,
if we know you're quite good, that also probably feeds into our decision, and if someone else on the
team knows you're quite good, that also probably feeds into the decision. I think that's pretty
reasonable. Yeah, I think that's pretty standard. Yeah, good. I mean, the reason this is done is
because you have more people who want to be on programme than you can have on programme. You
want to be able to tell people who are definitely on programme that they'll definitely on programme,
so that they can then, if being on programme is contingent on,
that if the appearance at the convention is contingent on being on programme,
which I feel is also a little more common in the US because you might get your membership
reimbursed for being on multiple programme items, then you need to tell the millionaire for them
to make that decision. And if someone is not going to be on programme, then you kind of owe it to
them to tell them that we don't think we have a space to use on programme. And then if they feel
okay, it's not worth me going to the con, then they can make that decision. And this feels like
a fairly standard way of doing it. Like, you can't, you can't rely entirely on knowledge because
the world can't, you don't know everyone. And you can't really rely entirely on surveys because
sometimes people who are great on programme might be terrible at filling out survey,
or they might be incredibly busy because they're incredibly great and they're launching a book
and they didn't have time to write a massive essay. So you kind of use a thing where it's like,
you're like, okay, do you think you can use any of these people on programme? And then if you
get someone who you say, okay, well, this is like a five time Hugo World finalists and no one says
they use them on programme, oh, it's probably because they didn't do very much in the form,
you might then kind of have a second look and make sure you want to use them. I think the only
thing that's different this year from kind of that sort of hybrid approach that I have known in
previous years is that sometimes you do the checking for whether they've said anything that
makes you think they'll break the code of conduct before you pass their names on to track leads.
And sometimes you do it the other way around. I think Worldcom programming is incredibly
complicated and really quite tricky to get right. I am surprised by the suggestion that
use of Chatty PTA saved hundreds of hours of volunteer time because it seems somewhat unlikely
to me that as lots of people have said, you could write a script to do the sorts of things it was
doing. You could ask Chatty PTA to write a script as somebody jokingly and perhaps save the same
time without needing to use generative AI. And the other thing that I wanted to comment on is that
at least one person has said, oh, I was talking to a track lead about a programme item and then
got a got a statement saying that I'd been rejected from the programme by the programme lead or by
somebody else in the programme division, not the track lead I was working with. And they went on to
say that must have been because of AI and I suspect it was because they were known to be
somebody who's difficult on panels, but I like to speculate. But even then, like, we were approached
about programme items at Glasgow that didn't end up happening. And I mean, I mean, obviously
Alison is incredibly difficult on programme, but me and Liz are delightful. So I think there are
reasons that people might be talking to a track lead and then not end on programme that are
completely innocent. Because as I think the statement says, or I've heard somewhere, it's
something like a third of all of the people. There's just not enough room to put them on programme.
And so you have a reasonably good chance of not ending up on programme, even if you're quite good.
And that sucks. It does suck. But also it's reflective of how many people want to be on panels
and the restrictions here. And there's also a thing here, which is obviously the more,
I think in the old days, sort of going back to when I started in front of them, it was very much
done on the, well, such and such as the track lead and knows these people and will invite them to
be on programme model. And I do like that we've moved to a more hybrid approach where we try and
seek more information about who might be good, because there are, firstly, people who might be
very good at being programme area heads who do not have the personal network. And it helps those
people and gives them that chance. But it also helps people who are new to the community and who
might not have the kind of the personal network in fandom, but might be absolutely amazing on a
panel. And so I do think in general, the community has gotten much better at how we approach
potential programme participants. And I'm certainly not longing for going back to the way it was.
Yeah. So I think a lot of the comments I've seen are the process for how this works is not clear.
I think Glasgow had a much clearer statement on how the process worked. I made it more clear
what the different stages were. But I think the thing is, right, if you reject someone because
you think they're going to break the code of conduct, you absolutely can't tell them we're
rejecting you because we think you're going to break the code of conduct. But that does leave a
bunch of people now not sure. I think the other issue is that if you're talking to a track lead,
it can depend. If the track leads approach you and said we absolutely want to do this item,
it would be brilliant. We want you on it. Then that's one thing. But that can, it could also be
that you approach the track leads to say how about this item and they were originally
keen and then they realised it would actually be way more work and we don't have the tech for it
or something. And that's how you get rejected. I think the third thing I might just say is that
there's usually a mismatch between the items the con wants to put on and the people they have to
put on the items because the con wants to do a balanced programme and not have a ton of items
in certain areas that lots of people want to be on. And I would say there's a lot of people who
would like to be on kind of like the techniques of writing panels or the business of writing panels
or how to get published and that kind of thing because I think they're quite good. They're always
something you can do if you're fairly new in the business and they seem like a great thing to kind
of go for. But I think if you ran as many panels as you wanted on like how to get published with
the number of people who want to be on them, your con would be like 10% how to get published.
That's it. Like if you say you would like to be on panels about anime, then you will probably end
upon as many panels as you would like because that's where we are underrepresented. So you
it does if you really want to be on programme, I think one benefit can be can be a little bit
flexible and say actually I would like to be on a wide range of stuff and then you'll probably find
a spot that fits you. That's a bit of a a bit of a detail.
I wanted to pull back a little bit to the vetting point which is that if it's taking hundreds,
I mean more than hundreds of hours because hundreds of hours is only the time that was
allegedly saved using chat GPT for the vetting process specifically. This is not to do with
whether somebody would be good on panels or how good of fit they are compared to everything else,
but for the vetting, making sure this person won't break the code of conduct, wouldn't it be better
to just not do that? I mean obviously if you already know they're a loose stare, you don't put
them on the programme but otherwise you give them the benefit of the doubt and you do not do
hundreds of hours of research into it.
I think that is one way to go. The one thing is that we've just talked about how kind of
personal information and word of mouth does not always work and so we can't rely on it for that.
The second thing is that the instant you put someone on a panel and they say something
absolutely unacceptable and then someone says look if you looked at their Facebook page for
one minute you would have known they would say this absolutely unacceptable thing, then you're in
a big pile of trouble and your calm has done something that people do not find acceptable.
This comes back to not having more programme than you can have where an individual has had
taken responsibility for making that programme item app, doesn't it? And I know that everybody
wants to be on programme. No, I don't see the connection you're making, please elaborate.
I don't think there's a connection there. I think if you are arguing that the programme items that
people put a lot of effort into can only have people, those people already know are safe,
I disagree with that. I think the hundreds of hours statement in the statement is probably
inaccurate because I'd be very surprised if it takes hundreds of hours to do this.
But I don't think there is a disconnect between making good programme items and looking at people's
Facebooks to make sure that they're not, you know, a wrong and necessary. Yeah.
I think it is an exceptionally time consuming process given that you are right, like 99.9% of
people who apply to be on programme will be fine and you will not see anything.
So the question is, how many hours is it worth to flag up each of these people?
But having done it, I would not underestimate the time it takes to actually do sort of a
gather information from what public sources you can find on the internet and then go and
report and spread to that you did it and there were no red flags. And then if you find someone
where you do find something that you think, you know, other people need to check and verify with
you and validate and make a decision, it takes quite a lot longer. So yeah.
I do want to say the risk reward is the problem. Yeah.
Because the reward for doing this work is that you don't have that
fire and like, especially now when almost every convention Glasgow was remarkably
controversy free, but sort of Chengdu and DC and Seattle have all had massive controversies.
You know, there is a lot of effort put in now to trying to avoid those controversies where
possible if they're predictable and I can't blame conventions for putting that effort in.
It's a thing that might come up that you know you can control a little bit and so we currently
put a lot of volunteer hours into controlling it because there's lots of things that might
become an issue at your con that you can't control and we don't always, you know, it's not like
the things always come out of left field, but sometimes they come out of the same few areas and
I think that is one of them is program participants who break the card of conduct on panels.
Will cons are very hard and we very much appreciate the people who run them, especially at senior levels.
Let's do picks. I want to pick sinners and I want to shout out Kat Korbetty who said, oh,
this is on and you should see it is great and you should go and see it in the iMacs and I
went and had a look at my iMacs, which is the BFI iMacs and discovered two things. First is
that they were showing the 70 millimeter iMacs print film version of the movie and
secondly that they were only showing it that day in the following day. So there i was at 1040 the
following morning watching sinners because it didn't quite sell out but it was very close to
being full as there's some terrible seats in our iMacs. Sinners is a film about two brothers who have
been in Chicago and have returned to their hometown in Mississippi and a lad who plays the blues
so well that he conjures the spirits of the past and future. I don't think that's a huge
spoiler because they say it like at the very beginning of the film and so the two brothers who
are chances who are both played by Michael B Jordan extremely well want to set up a Duke joint
and they do so and it turns out that all all is not well for a variety of reasons and all the
sorts of stuff that you might expect to happen is a horror movie i guess but it's not very horrible
it was a 15 rating and i was like that'll be okay i'll be able to cope with that but in fact
it was completely fine and it didn't have any problems with it at all because as previously
stated i am a horror was but what she's really about is well lots of things um the black experience
in America music and its power to transform what it is to be tempted and what temptation might look
like it's a fabulous film and you should all go and see it yeah but i mean a lot of you will have
seen it because it's also an enormous hit i do i do want to i haven't got around to you i can't
go into cinema until i know it sound like i'm dying occasionally so i haven't seen it in as
or thunderbolts which is a bit sad boom shall i go next you shall so i want to pick this
for the novelty that i am going to pick a roguelike puzzle video game that allison has not picked
but i also feel bad because allison might now go and play it and then we won't see it for another
six weeks so i'm going to pick blue prince which is uh it is a game about an inheritance you have
inherited a manor house from your uncle the baron but you can only keep the manor house if you can
and the whole inheritance if you can find the 46th room in the house and the way you find the rooms
is you go into each room and each time you draft from a set of particular rooms and you're trying
to build a pathway through the manor house using all these different rooms in order to
basically get enough puzzle solves and enough kind of permanent power-ups and knowledge and
information and so on in order that you can work out what you need to do on a particular day to
find room 46 and every day everything resets so you know you'll you might spend one day deciding
okay i'm going to unlock this mysterious room because i think it's got a clue to room 46 but actually
the the drafts don't go your way so you decide oh never mind i'm going to spend this play through
just trying to go to as many rooms as possible because that will help me solve another puzzle and
you unpack more and more and i have in theory completed it because i have found an open room
46 and know what it contains but actually i think if i was really dedicated this is about twice as
much more content in the end game than i have played so far it's just that the puzzles have
got to the point for me where they have got really quite complicated and i'm not sure i will get
enough satisfaction out of solving them to bother solving them but there's so much hidden stuff
it's like you know you go i went to a forum to be like you know it's like how am i supposed to
solve this puzzle and it's like oh it's a room that i have not yet even seen and i've played
24 days of this game with 30 rooms per day or something and things like that and then but also
satisfaction of figuring out oh i can oh if i go to this room and i push this button and then i go
back to this room and then i push this button and then i will go on and cover this whole extra thing
is is really quite satisfying and it's quite nicely done it's all sort of like line art drawings
and the rooms are themed by color to different uh different types of room and so on i've got
some nice floaty music in the background and it all feels very simple to play but obviously
complicated to remember i think i've got two and i've got two main criticisms and one is that you
can't play it without writing lotus stuff down and i think that's by design but it's a bit of a throw
back to be like now get your pen and paper out and write some information down that you will need
later on and two it's a rogue like drafting game and so it's very random and so when i got to
point where i was like right this is the puzzle i really need to solve i'd be like oh well i haven't
drawn this room today so i've got to go and try another three days until i get the exact room i
want next to this other exact room so i can solve this one particular puzzle and that's why i've sort
of not completely stopped playing it but i'm now sort of casually doing a little bit at a time to
see if i can finish some of the end game stuff but it was surprising i hadn't really heard about it
and then i saw a post on a forum and then it turned out to be a PlayStation plus game and so i just
gave it go and it is surprisingly fun hey arguably fantasy you know it sounds like it well i mean if
the room keeps changing it's if the mansion keeps changing its shape that's definitely
that's i doesn't change its shape it just changes the rooms within the shape anyway it is for PlayStation
5 windows and Xbox so i may have saved Allison from myself i can play it using g-force now apparently
in the cloud or crossover so i've been playing a game but it's a Hugo finalist and i got it in the
Hugo photo packet so i haven't had a chance to look at what new stuff is out there because i
be too busy playing Laura Lion's laser eyes oh yeah the Hugo photo packets out guys we've got to mention
that oh we probably should have said something about the Hugo photo packet being out i think in
the middle i think i think in the middle of picks at the end of pick number two is the perfect time
to devote that information excellent um guys if you don't tend to listen to picks this is the
point where we tell you the Hugo photo packet is out so if you're going to ask for a refund from
Seattle i would suggest you download the Hugo photo packet before you do that oh okay oh i'd
have to say that i mean i thought it was funny it's um it is quite funny as long as people don't
think it's genuine advice well i mean i don't think you should i don't think you should um ask for a
refund for Seattle i think Seattle will be a great con and they have done the best they could possibly
do to repair the damage so yeah that's a serious thing just keep being a member of Seattle and also
download the Hugo photo packet which has codes for four games is that right three games four games
four games four plus tactical breech wizards has a demo and a demo and nobody's and nobody's heard
anything from Nintendo for some reason i feel that so it should be i feel the Nintendo should be like
enigmatic and mysterious and just like suddenly appear to drop new switches and things like that
it is good that you feel that because that's indeed the case
but also when you're thinking about your ballot for next year consider not
nominating Nintendo games because they don't care now that that could be an ecumenical matter
also i just want to say for people listening Liz said blueprints and i heard blueprints um yes
so we might want to make clear that it is a prince who is blue i'm assuming there's a blue
prince oh but is it that's all point it's upon oh because you're drafting blueprints for your house
it's a rogue like puzzler whose name is upon alison oh okay i get it now it took a while but if
you're googling for it you need to google for blue space prints yes fair enough but there is a link
in the show notes or there will be although obviously you don't want to google for blue space space
prints why not well because then you'd be googling for a space a prince from space who is blue and
that is not what you meant god i see what you mean let's give you a look i'm googling i'm too busy
to give you a look oh god how quickly can i get a ps5 i'm going to pick a book and i'm going to pick
the mark by freeder iceberg translated by lorissa causa is this is a book set in near future recuivic
and basically it's set in the run up to a referendum in iceland as to whether people will be forced to
take a test known as the empathy test and mark themselves with their results and it's kind of a
book about privilege and about government overreach and about good intentions and bad intentions and
how how that all intersects and i thought it was it may be very angry in places it's a book that
doesn't lead you to a neat answer which i very much enjoyed and yeah i would i would highly recommend
people check it out it's very lovely um lovely is the wrong word very powerful and i enjoyed it very
much not sure it's lovely so yeah go check that out listeners that's my recommendation have you
read intrusion by kamakloud i can't remember which is the one where um you know that it's about
uh government enforcement of whether you take a pill to correct any genetic errors in your child
i have not because it sounds a little bit similar and i did like intrusion quite a lot so i think
maybe i should check out the book i will have a look at that it was nominated for clock award job
that was the Octothorpe podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
[Music]
i'm sorry this is pickers maybe very excited now i'm i'm gonna feel bad if you well one i'm gonna
feel bad if you don't like it and two i'm gonna feel bad if you immediately sink 200 hours into it
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud and comfatec.com
used under a creative Collins attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
you