Damn straight.
Alison just cut out for me for a minute then.
Was it just me or did she cut out for John as well?
Well she cut out for me but I'll hear what she said when I'm editing.
So...
And he doesn't care that much so...
I'd just take a very long view of these things, Liz.
I'm like one day I will know.
Hello everyone and welcome to the 12th episode of Oct. Thorpe,
a podcast about science fiction and science fiction fandom.
This is the episode for Thursday the 20th of August.
I am John Coxson.
I am Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Betty.
And we are not in Liz's house.
This is true of all three of us this week.
This is the bit where Liz tells us she's having a fantastic beach holiday
and we go, oh yeah no.
We quite fancy a fantastic beach holiday.
Thank you very much.
But it's not about to happen anytime soon.
Is it unless by fantastic beach you mean "margate" which we don't?
You could go to a night, you could go to like Devon or Cornwall or somewhere like that.
Devon and Cornwall are full.
I repeat, Devon and Cornwall are full.
Please do not travel to Devon or Cornwall.
They are full.
This has been a public service announcement.
But yes, I am having a very nice beach holiday on an island which is a very,
very long way from full.
It's been very nice.
Which is good for you and bad for the tight tourist industry.
It's also been a little bit sad to go into restaurants where clearly they have had three
customers today.
My experience of visiting the Arctic Circle in August was like that.
But obviously they would have had snow later and had tourists later.
I'm sure that Thai beaches will get tourists again in due course.
But it might be a little while.
Maybe a little while.
I am compensating by just going into restaurants and eating more food than I really need to eat
because I feel sad.
So that's your excuse?
That's the human condition.
I regularly eat more food than I need to eat because I am sad.
Which explains why I am this shape.
You seem to be a very nice shape, John.
Oh, thank you, Alison.
That's the episode, Ty, all right there.
You seem to be sort of John shaped, you know.
I don't know what to do.
Oh, all the glow.
Sorry, this is a body positive podcast which is not going to allow any body
just more for you to get by.
So we got a letter of comment from Amazon Music podcast team.
And they say, hello, podcaster.
We're excited to let you know that Amazon Music and Audible will be adding
podcasts to their respective services.
This information is confidential.
Whoops.
Thus concludes the letters of comment.
And then did they actually invite us to do anything or?
We can submit our podcast to Amazon,
which I guess we should probably do.
Like because they just link to it.
They don't rehost it.
So I have no, I have no like a priori objection to doing that.
Disorderable then say you can use your Audible credits to listen to what
to thought because I would have to say that would be a terrible, terrible idea.
Yes, if you are listening to this and you have spent an audible credit,
please contact us and we will send you a book.
It might not be the book you'd want.
I can't promise it'll be a good book.
We record an audio book of your choice.
That might be quite a lot of work.
It might be quite a lot.
It's a very hungry caterpillar.
Just send him a book.
You guys must have enough books.
You can just basically pick one at random and check it out.
Yeah, it'll be fine.
Okay, so I think probably we didn't get a lot of genuine letters of comment
because people were in the chat in the last live episode.
So made their comments there and we hope everyone enjoyed it.
[Music]
As we mentioned in the last episode, we shied away from talking about serious
fanish concerns because Alison was riding that Conzeland high
and I was sleep deprived owing to too many board games.
But this episode is the episode of the serious fanish concerns.
In the run up to Conzeland, there was a lot of discussion in various
fanish low-counles about the Saudi Arabia world-comped for Jeddah in 2022,
which was going up against Chicago.
The site selection vote resulted in Chicago being elected to Chicon 8
in a quite convincing majority.
But there was a lot of chats about Saudi Arabia prior to that happening.
Just for context, Chicago received 89.8% of the vote with 517 ballots cast in its favour.
Jeddah are rebidding for 2026 because they basically went for the first year that there were
no bids and 2026 is it.
So I have now become Facebook friends and also Discord friends, I think,
with Yasubad Jatt, who is the driving force behind the Jeddah-Con bid.
Anna Smith-Spark, who was the instigator, is not somebody I know well,
but I do know lots of people who signed it and they're kind of, some of them are saying,
well, we didn't really understand the Wusses process and we wanted to make a statement about
Saudi Arabia's suitability for Worldcons, which has left a lot of Wusses people feeling very
aggrieved, particularly the ones who went into their threads in the discussion on the
fantasy society. Facebook page, I think it was, that sparked this off and actually explained how
it all worked before the letter was sent and the letter got sent anyway and it got picked up
by the Guardian because the Guardian knows that a good way to generate hits and therefore
advertising sales is to find storms in teacups and say, would it help if we put this storm into
a bucket for you? So I think that made it quite a lot worse than it might otherwise have been,
because of the Wusses for members, as you would expect, voted overwhelmingly for Chicago,
with the other votes being split evenly between no award and Jeddah, so it's not even that Jeddah
got 10% of the votes, they got about 5% of the votes. But obviously they weren't the sort of
votes where people thought that they might win, so it's kind of petered out and if it comes up again
in 2026, I feel that Smoughs will ensure that there is a strong bid against it, because Smoughs do
that sort of thing. Which brings us to 2023, where we have a different sort of problem because we have
Chengdu mounting, as far as I can tell, a perfectly competent bid for China, which people don't want
to win for many of the same reasons they don't want Jeddah to win, but without the excuse that the
Jeddah people clearly didn't have the fattest idea what was involved in running a Wilcon.
It's clear that Chengdu know what is involved and can do it and have demonstrated that they
could do it with a large, as a convention of similar sort of size and structure, but all Chinese, to
which they invited a dozen Smoughs to come over and watch, so they clearly can do it. So that's not
an argument to not have a Chengdu Wilcon. The arguments have not a Chengdu Wilcon are much more
difficult, problematic and subtle, and they are up against Memphis, which is not the best bid for
a third consecutive US Wilcon. In summary, Jeddah just kind of spud itself out, and if it tries to do
it again, it'll get competed with. But Chengdu is a much bigger issue because on most objective
arguments, you would have to say that Chengdu have the better bid. So I think what the open letter
was calling for, basically they saw a place being allowed to bid for a Wilcon as an endorsement of
that bid in some way because we put it on the ballot. And I mean, I've generally been of the
opinion that fans will just not vote for things and that's okay. And I don't see it being allowed
to bid as being an endorsement of it, but clearly some people do and have a problem with that.
And I think the problem you then get to is, okay, so what you want is for us not to allow places to
bid because they fall below some human rights standard, but actually setting a standard for that
is incredibly difficult. And I'm not sure how I would go about doing it. I mean, for me personally,
I have no intention of going to Saudi Arabia. I think I may be allowed to go to Saudi Arabia,
provided, you know, I cover my knees and shoulders and possibly hair all times and so on. But
John would have to sponsor us. I think that would be very strange. I cannot imagine either of you
ever. Yeah, no, that was what my kenny said. I think it's I'm quite entertained by the idea that
we would do what John tells us. It has to happen at any point so far. I don't expect it ever to
happen. I don't think I'd ever try. I've got too much self-preservation. I believe that defenders
of Saudi Arabia do say if you think that women do what their male sponsor tells you to, you really
don't know very many Saudi Arabian women. But yeah, I can I can see that, you know, Saudi Arabia is a
place where I would not feel comfortable visiting. Whereas I feel that China is a place where I would
feel comfortable visiting. And I think for the majority of Worldcon attendees, they would not feel
that comfortable visiting Saudi Arabia, whereas many more of them would feel comfortable visiting
China, possibly. I don't know. I haven't pulled the Worldcon membership on that. But I think I think
setting setting a bar seems to be a non-starter because I can't work out a way you would do it.
And the way of doing it, which is it appears on the ballot and then we don't vote for them
seems better. But you're right. I mean, the other issue is that when the Jeddah bid was questioned
about things like, okay, so it is illegal to be queer in in Saudi Arabia. Their response was kind
of, well, if you don't tell anyone it won't be a problem, which is a completely unsatisfactory
response. Whereas I don't think that particular issue is a problem in China. It's more China's
general human rights record and also their, you know, recent actions in Hong Kong. So I think next
year is going to be very interesting because next year you truly will be voting on,
is this a place that you feel comfortable visiting or you feel comfortable awarding a Worldcon to?
And for Saudi Arabia, there was never a chance we were going to do that. So it wasn't really a
question. No, and this is, um, this is the problem because I think, and me and España had a long
conversation about this. For those who don't know, España is my wife. It is very difficult because
I agree that I don't really see how you can come up with a, um, coherent, single, um, statement of
who should be allowed to bid for Worldcons and who shouldn't be allowed to. Um, I, I think that
would be very complicated. I think you'd rather risk of excluding countries that are fine or
including countries that are not. Um, and like, I do also wonder whether the fact that we are a
predominantly anglospheric community means that we would be more likely to write the rules in a way
that made it easier for anglosphere countries in the anglosphere to, to not be penalized for
their various issues than countries outside the anglosphere. Um, see also like, you know,
US police brutality and stuff like that. I don't, I don't think there are people in the community
who have argued that the US shouldn't be allowed to host Worldcons, including Patrick
Nielsen Hayden. Um, but I don't know to what extent the US is as bad as China. Um, I suspect the US
is not as bad as China, but equally I am married to a citizen and I've been to the US a lot and I've
been over to China. So it may well be that my experience is my privilege bias me in my, um, decision
making on that. The issue is how you come up with rules that you could reasonably enforce. Um,
and then if you manage to do that, what body would reasonably enforce them. So I can see an
argument that it would be like fairer to have a codified rule. Um, rather than discussing it every
time there's a problematic Worldcon over again, but I equally don't really know what that would look
like. Okay, so every Worldcon is problematic in its own way. I was going to say all unproblematic
Worldcons are a light, but I don't think they're any unproblematic Worldcons. So I think, I think,
I think there are issues which might cause you to vote for or against any Worldcon that are not
entirely who is the team doing this and are they competent to do it. I think I did see when people
were discussing the Saudi Arabian bid, a kind of assumption that they must be backed by Saudi
Arabian government money, or they were doing this in some way to get themselves visas to visit
other countries. And it seems we make that assumption about the Saudi Arabian bid in a way I've never
seen as make about any other place other than China. And the some, at least some of the people
behind the Saudi Arabian bid have been visiting Worldcons since at least 2014. So there's no reason
think they're doing it just so they can leave the country. And I think they genuinely are just fans
of science fiction and Worldcons who would like to bring one to their country, but haven't really
thought through how they do that, or how their country would be perceived by the people voting.
I don't see any reason to immediately leak to assume that bids from countries that haven't
necessarily had Worldcons, especially non-Angleosphere ones, are somehow being supported or kind of
contrived in a way that we don't usually jump to think about say that Finland bid.
I agree. I mean Finland is semi-Angleosphere. I just thought of Helsinki as it's the only place
we can think of which is a new place we've taken Worldcons kind of that's non-English speaking.
Yeah, so so the question of whether China can, so there is a certain amount of racism in the mix,
isn't there? So I can see a situation where in a year's time there is an open letter in the Guardian
from a similar group of people who are decrying the Chinese Worldcon bid for human rights problems,
especially if what's happening in Hong Kong keeps going in the wrong direction, which it looks likely
to. And we have to have a much, much more difficult conversation about whether or not,
because obviously I think the three of us agree that Saudi Arabia is clearly overlying their
treatment of women as a country is clearly unacceptable. And LGBT, yes.
Their treatment of many people who are not cisgendered straight men is clearly a problem.
China, I think it would be difficult to argue, does not also have some human rights problems.
You could you could bandy around some pretty serious words about her treatment. I am
personally opposed to a Chinese Worldcon because of various problems they've got with their human
rights record in Hong Kong and like genocides that are perpetrated and things like that.
But I think the case against China is much, much less key a cut than it is against Saudi Arabia.
And my problem is like, what if the next time there's another country where the situation is
less clear cut but in a different way or less clear cut in a way that means that
wuswuswus members don't find it problematic, but people who are not. Currently wuswus members
might find it very problematic. If we keep doing this on an ad hoc basis, do we start running into
problems where our biases as a community end up putting us in situations where we have Worldcon
in places that actually probably we shouldn't. What do you think?
I think you're correct and we really need to brainstorm ways in which we can
come to some mechanism on this. I think you're writing that we can't leave it ad hoc.
I think also if you'd asked me five years ago if a Chinese Worldcon bid certain like a good idea,
I would have been much more positive than I am right now. So we know things can change quite
quite quickly as well. And I'm trying to think of like what would be the way of doing this.
Do we need a standard questionnaire so that we can ask bids to not just give us information
about how much it costs to fly there and where the nearest airport is and you know whether you
can smoke in their hotel rooms. But we actually need to say, you know, are there restrictions on
who can enter your country and what are they? I think those sorts of questions are already
covered in the Spanish Inquisition. I've also seen the suggestion that the code of conduct should
be submitted along with the bid paperwork, which seems to be to be not a bad idea because
as soon as you start bidding you need to have a code of conduct. Glasgow's got one, you know,
and that's not a very big imposition, I think. Every con by the time it files paperwork,
every bid by the time it files paperwork will already have a code of conduct.
Well, and I would say that in the case that having a code of conduct is a significant
imposition on a bid, then it's a sort of bid we need to be significantly imposing ourselves upon.
So that kind of works either way. But the thing that I actually wanted to say is I disagree with
both of you that this cannot just be left to the community. The community is all we have.
As you know, EasterCon runs without any sort of formal organization whatsoever and it's been
doing so for 70 years now. And I feel that as long as you can sustain it, having the least
amount of bureaucracy possibly can is a good and worthy thing. I feel that WorldCon has too
much bureaucracy, which is probably a how would we, what things would we take out of the Wispus
Constitution altogether, conversation for another time? I think the words we do not want it to be
ad hoc and the words we do not want it to come from the community are two very separate statements.
I want it to come from the community. I want it to come from the community in a way that is not
having the conversation over again every year in a way that doesn't allow for any nuanced thought.
Because I think that's what doing at ad hoc actually means. I think it means you do it
with shouting at each other or soapboxes. And I disagree that that is the best way.
And I think EasterCon works very well as a completely like an arctic thing. But I don't think EasterCon
is ever going to have to tally the human rights abuses of Saudi Arabia and China and decide which
is worse. So I think EasterCon has a little bit more wiggle room for not talking about these things
once a year at the bid session in a way that is relatively un-nuanced because the nuances aren't
as important. I think that's fair. So I have a few things to say. One is that you say things are
covered by the vanishing position. But I think the thing is we have this kind of codified set of
questions now that vanishing bids answer before the vanishing position and put online. And they
are mostly to do with the kind of practical and logistical things. And maybe we do need
some questions in there that are just as routine to every bit which are about, you know, can you tell
us, you know, how welcoming your country is to different people. I mean, it's going to be very
difficult to think of ways, you know, there's no way that a bid from my country with human rights
issues is going to write down. And also we have this massive human rights issue. But if you have
to write down, say for Saudi Arabia, the, you know, these activities are punishable by death, then
it does at least give you an idea of where this country falls. Second thing I think I would say
is that EasterCon does kind of move along ad hoc. But yeah, I think as John said, the issues are very
different because the worst thing anyone to really propose is whether we should move an
EasterCon to Jersey. So is this house? It's over the house in 2021. And also I'm, this is for a
different podcast, but I am very worried that we will find a point which the kind of whole ad hoc
nature of EasterCon collapses under some kind of stress like a pandemic. My third part was going
to be we may be unearthing a completely different thing entirely now is that I think the barrier for
entry to deciding where EasterCon's goal is lower than the barrier for entry deciding where world
cons go. We still need people who, you know, vote on world cons to be part of the community. But at
the moment, the financial barriers are doing that is pretty high. And there's not really way around
it under the current constitution. The barrier to entry for voting on a world con is less than the
barrier it's entry for a voting on an EasterCon because to vote for the EasterCon, you have to go
to the EasterCon to go to to vote to a World Conside selection. You only have to spend the
accurate. So I actually think although the fact that world con is gated in the way it is, I think
means it means it feels less inclusive. And I understand why you said that. I think if you actually
like do the cost analysis, unless you happen to live in the city where the EasterCon is happening.
It's true. But I was more thinking like if you're at the con, you can vote, right? If you're at an
EasterCon, you can vote. If you're at a WorldCon, then you have to pay more money to vote.
That's true. And also I was thinking more kind of the barriers for getting involved. Like if there's
an EasterCon bed, do you think it is going to go to a place and you don't think the EasterCon
should go? I think there is a lower entry to getting up another bed to try and send it somewhere
else than there is for WorldCon. But I think we have gone kind of way off piece at this point.
I will just say very quickly that in general, I quite like the fact. I think in general, I think
the last two decades have shown that Eastercons can undergo quite significant, for one of a better
word, constitutional crises. And still, the complete lack of any codified constitution
has just been fine. So I think the goodwill of British fandom and the desire for Eastercons to
happen will probably mean that EasterCon is fine without any codification. But I think that you're
right that this is a much larger. Before we move on from this discussion, we have been talking
about whether or not there should be more codification about which countries are suitable for world
combating and which countries are not. Cheryl Morgan wrote a post on the argument for an
incorporated WISFS and having more continuity in WorldCon and the fact that if you had that,
you'd be better able to implement these kind of long-running policies. I don't particularly
know if I have many ideas about whether or not that's a good thing.
I think it's another thing we should, if we're going to talk about codification,
it's a thing we could take when we talk about codification more generally.
But I've put it in the show notes. So if you want to read our arguments, please go and read it.
Good article. I also observe that WISFS only really, its entire procedural system is
used as a defense against people making effect, affecting any change. So this year, it took them
six minutes to totally run a coach and horse it through their procedures in order to clear up
all their business because the people who were in charge wanted that to happen. So as it works
at the moment, it's a very firm preventer of disrupting the order. If you want change in WISFS,
you have to put the constitutions essentially unchangeable without the process of persuading
people that persuading individuals that they might get on board.
Even if 95% of the Worldcon membership backed something as transparently sensible,
if the 5% of WISFS nerds didn't think that was a good idea, it could not happen.
And that feels to me to be a problem that WISFS should deal with,
so that its constitution and its procedures have not necessarily led to a good democratic state at this point.
Fair.
George R. R. Martin, a man who is famous for writing long rambling novels with lots of racism and
sexism in them, has turned out to be a man who is a fan of long rambling things that contain
lots of sexism and racism, which has apparently surprised large amounts of fandom.
Tell me more about how this all happened, Alison and Liz.
I have some sympathy for Conzieland here.
So it did surprise me, because I think if you come to me 5 years ago and said, do you think
George R. R. Martin would be a good Hugo Toastmaster, then based off what evidence I had from like
seeing it with the old Worldcon, I probably would have said, yeah, he'd be quite fun,
he loves Worldcons, he's quite popular and famous and people will enjoy it, and it would have turned
out that I was totally wrong. People did enjoy it, you just saw the storm in a teacup.
This probably was a storm in a bucket in fact, but lots and lots of people did enjoy his history,
they felt it reflected back to Silverburg's years as Toastmaster and his way of connecting
and tying by the community. I think those people are totally wrong and I think his speech was
very unfounded, but I agree that Conzieland didn't have a lot of choice. However, I'm going to do a
little bit of fan history here, which is that the Toastmaster, and you could tell this from the
thing, it comes from the days when the Hugos were a banquet and so if you're having a banquet,
you then have an afterd in a speaker, they're a Toastmaster and they give the toast, which in
this case are the Hugos, and it's all part of that very clubby sort of thing. Right, the problem of
Toastmaster as a guest of honour of the Worldcon is that it's been a problematic role for a very
long time and what most Worldcons that are sensible about this do is that they have, they do not have
the Toastmaster role, they have a Hugo Host role, which is not a guest of honour of the convention,
which is just a programme participant like any other, which means you can tell them what to do.
If you invite somebody to be to your Toastmaster, you probably can't tell them what to do. Having said
that, Conzieland almost certainly, given that George had said he wanted to do it and given that they
were looking at running a convention in New Zealand and they were worried about the whole issue about
whether people would come and all of that, at the point at which George said he would like to be
the Toastmaster, I don't think they had a lot of choice that it was at a point where I don't think
he was as problematic, I think he has become more problematic. I think he was clearly very upset by
what happened with the John W. Campbell Award and decided that he was going to use what he saw as
his chance to make a speech to weigh in on that. I think things have changed and the illustration of
this is I was talking about Lomcon because my phone likes to send me pictures of what I was doing
six years ago and apparently I was, you know, looking over this vast empty convention centre that
was short and can be filled with people. But anyway, the point is that at Lomcon we did the retro Hugos
and we did them, I think the same way Consi-Linted them, which is we had a special night where we put
them on and people dressed up and there was dancing and so on and we awarded them to, you know, John
W. Campbell and I don't recall hearing a lot of discussion about that after the fact, I think it
was just a fact that yes we gave him John W. Campbell. Whereas six years later we gave some
retro Hugos to John W. Campbell and that is very definitely not a thing that went without comment.
So I think that shows how basically in six years we've shifted from a thing that no one even really
blinked an eye about. It's possible there were people but I didn't see anything about it to a
thing where many people are saying no this is, you know, a thing which undermines the Hugos and it's
a disgrace that we presented any other awards in the same awards ceremony that undermines them.
So I think it is an illustration of how things can shift quite quickly and people don't necessarily
shift along with it. I think that Alison is right that there are people who probably did really
enjoy the look at the fan history that George gave. Lots of them. I think my main problem is that
the Hugos are badly structured to allow that kind of thing. Like because it would have been much
better if George had given like a like a bunch of Hugos and then there had been a 30 minute period
where George had given like a lecture on fan history maybe with some like props and slides at a script
maybe and then like he had given the rest of the Hugos and he and not withstanding any comments
that Martin made about John Campbell and how great he was in light of the fact that the Campbell
Award was changed to the astounding award after generating speech last year. I think that could
have been really interesting because I do think there's value to fan history. I do think obviously
Martin has a quite broad view of that. Okay on a point of order there was a separate program item
entitled George and Bob have a chat or something like that where George R.R. Martin and Bob Silverberg
sat down for an hour to chew the fat in exactly this fashion. Clearly the Toastmaster is there
to impart some of their personality on the ceremony. I think in this case the criticism was primarily
that it became too much about Martin but I don't think the answer was to completely shift it the
other way and I think the fact that you made the point earlier that there were people who enjoyed
his interlude means that there is clearly a sweet spot here not withstanding the thing where he
defended Campbell in a way that was frankly a rebuttal of both last year's ceremony and most of the
acceptance speeches from this year. The events director for Longcon who was responsible for our
retrohugo and hugo ceremony was Hela Montgomery. If Hela Montgomery had been events director of
this they would not have taken a number of interesting structural choices that the fact that people
have been trying for 50 years to reduce the length of hugo ceremony appears to have completely passed
cosey led by in terms of their design of the ceremony. Yes. I mean in my personal experience of this was
that I sent them my presenter speech and they said oh this is this is fine but it could be a bit
longer. It was the perfect length. It's longer that's the length I did was longer so it was shorter than
that so but it is still not a thing that I would expect any could have been ceremony director to
ever say to any presenter. Could you make that a bit longer please?
There is a video on YouTube called When the Toastmaster Talks Less that cuts a lot of the
content from Martin out of the ceremony and focuses more on the people who won awards and it is
four is one hour and 41 minutes long and I think there is a coherent argument because it doesn't
remove the points I don't think where he actually gives the awards to people. I think it just
reduces the speech of I. It still has plenty it still has plenty of George R.R. Martin's personality in it.
I think this belief that the Toastmaster's personality won't come through is wrong.
Yeah and that's the thing and he could have done a 20 minute long he could have done a 20
minute long talk in the middle and it would have been a tight two hours and that would have been I
think pretty much the perfect hugo ceremony because you would have had enough context you would have had
a focus on the winners it would have been two hours which is a fine length of time and I think
actually the the impersonaries could afford to be a bit longer because people are in a hall
chatting with their mates but when you're sitting at home three or four hours is pushing it but I
don't I just yeah I am bewildered by the choices they made because they could have had a really tight
nice two hour long ceremony and they they didn't and I don't know why.
Conzeland had a huge job of work to do to convert a physical convention into a virtual one they
spent as far as I can see most of their quite limited resource to make this happen on actually
tying together the nuts and bolts to make it happen and for the hugo ceremony they tried to make it
as much like a physical ceremony as possible. Now my feeling was that they should probably have
spent rather more time on the fun engineering parts of making that happen on the ephemeral
bits and pieces of what it is to be a world-con. They did do quite well actually and we're going
to talk about a convention that's not done quite quite so well in a little bit but they could still
have done more there. I went to see a different award ceremony as part of my guff trip was it was
the Oriales Awards and they just did it on zoom they had a youtube thing so you everyone could
watch they had all the presenters and all the nominees and all the acceptors on zoom and they
just had did and they had some nice skit at the beginning they had toastmasters with some flavor
to them and it was completely fine and it wasn't grand in the way the hugo ceremony tries to be
grand but this year it mostly just came across as amateurish and not in a good way rather than
stylish which is I think what they were probably going for and it would have been fine just on as
a zoom awards ceremony but I don't think they could have counted us that it wouldn't have
it would have been hard for the tech crew who were like oh we need all these direct live links
to go with that. Yeah I must admit I didn't really understand why they kept coming back to
George in his actual house live I didn't because I appreciate that the hugos are kept under wraps
and I appreciate that the winners are not known and so there is a coveted reality problem and
that's why you don't in general tell the people awarding each hugo in advance who's won the hugo
because there are problems if you do that but has there ever been a problem do you think that I
would have told people who won't divide known? In this case given that George RMR team did all
of the opening of envelopes and telling people who had won and given that George RMR team is
presumably quite good at keeping things under his hat given that he has to keep these other
his hat vis-a-vis like what's going to happen in Game of Thrones and stuff like that I kind of
feel like they just looped him in and then had him record all the envelope openings in the original
insitials I don't understand why they didn't it felt very strange. You may remember and I would invite
listeners Nicholas White and or Tammy Coxon to comment on this the hugo balloting process was
contracted and quite late this year and I think it's very likely that the awards were not concluded
before the point where George RMR team's video recording elements had to be done.
That's a fair point. I know that they did have they did have a tech team with George's Santa Fe
it wasn't just George and his and his webcam they did do quite a lot of work they you know they flew
people out to be with him so so they did they put a lot of tech into this. I think but then I would
argue that like if it was the case that he had already recorded the insitials I think I probably
would have just had like the name appear on screen with the man reading over the the or well it was
a man but all the lady what did it alternate it was a man it was it was Norman I think um the
co-chair of the convention. Oh was it? Who's voice of God in the hugo ceremony I believe so.
But like I would have just had the voice the narrator of the ceremony it outs the winners
because you could have saved so much time if you hadn't you would have reduced the risk of
something going wrong because we did go wrong it has started late and you could have made it a
lot snappier if you hadn't had George sitting in his theater doing the actual opening envelopes.
I think the actual tech was extremely complicated and and they were very they were all exhausted
and and very happy that they'd actually managed to hold all the technical bits of it together.
I think I think I agree with John I think if you've made it so complicated that all your energy is
going into making sure your complicated tech works and you need to take a step back and say okay
this is where our people points are going is this where they should actually be going.
I am very much with you that they should have basically pre-recorded everything apart from
if you knew you were going to have an acceptance speech live I think that was nice to have because
it was really nice to have those kind of on the spot acceptances but if that was also complicated
just record everyone's speeches edit it into one thing and just play it because there were quite a
lot of you know moments where it didn't quite cut back and forth nicely moments where it didn't
quite sound as good even if you had to record George like the day before reading out all the
winners and then edit that in quickly I think that might just have been easier because then
you would also know okay so we have no speeches in here from the winners and it is already two
and a half hours long you know we would know by that point that you have a problem.
Yeah oh it is certainly true that the Worldcon knew in advance that they had they could kind of
see a slow motion car crash around the Hugo's and it actually I realize now was overshadowing
some of the things that people were doing earlier in the convention and I think my favorite example
of this is that on about the Tuesday after the Worldcon don't I mean you can check the date
"discon" announced the hosts of the Hugo ceremony next year and they had a splash they said
"here are Hugo announced here are Hugo's hosts we're announcing it today" and what I learned in chat
sorry for telling tales out of school is that this announcement had been planned before
Conzeland so "discon" knew before Conzeland that announcing
apparently completely unproblematic Hugo hosts the day after Conzeland was going to be a really
really good thing to do so it's not that people didn't know there was a problem. I have one more
thing to add which is for many many years Robert Silver would stand up and talk out the Hugo's
he has not for several years and there was a decision made obviously this year to invite him
back and he added 15 maybe 20 minutes it seemed like of just kind of very rambling chat mostly
about John W Campbell so even if you found it very hard to say to Martin okay we need to shorten
your links there too long this is going to be very long at some points on my decision that they
would give a massive chunk of the Hugo ceremony over to someone where basically it would be known
what he does which has taught for a very long time and that seemed a very baffling decision to me
I mean I believe that Bob I believe that Bob Silverberg is the only person left who has attended
every Worldcon I mean I'm going to do the thing about the reason why we are told to honor our elders
is that it is sometimes difficult now I don't I would not have given him space at the Hugo ceremony
but I do think that clearly I see that what happened is that George wanted to do it and George
wanted to involve Bob and George wanted to hop back to the old days yeah and and you can see why
if you're in this big community that seems very disparate if you're an old man it probably seems
enormously disparate compared to the times that it was just you and your mates in the bar and
and you can see that old people would have a lot of nostalgia for when everyone knew everyone
and helping people understand that there are some merits to having a broader community where
not everybody knows everybody else and not everybody does that that doesn't necessarily be
that's a bad thing I think you're right I think you know he may be the only person who has been to
every Worldcon and we do need to find a way to recognize that but I just don't think the way to
recognize that is to have quite a long segment of the Hugo's and it particularly wasn't even a
segment that seemed to kind of link his whole history with Worldcon together it seemed to be
a segment which talked about things very much in the past and this was really my problem with the
whole thing is if you're going to do Worldcon history I want you to do that in a way that links
it up to the present and future of the Hugo's and this just didn't do it it seemed to kind of stop
at the point where they sort of stopped maybe enjoying Worldcon so much I mean I think my final
comment on it is the comment I made about 10 minutes into the ceremony where I said something like
you haven't missed anything yet he's still rambling on and that was still true three hours later
when I went back to sleep I was about five minutes into the ceremony I was in a zoom chat with
an opera very interesting people and we watched the ceremony in about five minutes in the first
it was like when you're a thunderstorm is about to start or that it is not raining and then you
just feel a drop of rain and somebody made a comment and then somebody else did and then it was just
like a torrent of oh my goodness how is this happening with a certain amount of yeah well we
can't do this it's going to be what happened but but it was it was embarrassing for the Worldcon
and it was it was embarrassing for the Worldcon we want to be and can I also say that the retrohugos
are an abomination and it should not be they should people should stop doing them they certainly
shouldn't increase the number of years for which they could be done this is another I'm looking at
wussfuss here because this is something where wussfuss extended the range of years for which
retrohugos could be awarded making it so now you can award a retrohugo for a a Worldcon where
there wasn't even a Worldcon and oh god and that's what leads us to this I think I have previously
made my opinions on the retrohugos no one on this podcast which is let's just stop now no no
they should never have started time it was a terrible appalling idea anyway why I quite like
them but uh I'm not gonna I'm not I don't feel strongly enough about it to defend that against
the disagreement uh but if you are listening to this also thinking I quite like them you are
not alone why do you why do you quite like them John just did they kind of neat I said I told
you I don't have a good argument I understand I understand all the problems with them the problem
with me is that my default state is quite liking things uh and that is difficult um whereas my
default state is loathing for everything that has not yet proved itself worthwhile I mean I'm not
trying to imply that but I am thinking it very loudly.
"Etheism of the New Things" quickly followed by Disenchantment and Rage. Disenchantment and Rage is
the name of your um next fanzine. Is that the new name of your sex tape John it's the name of your
next fanzine. It's my podcast appropriate phone. I'm not sure that Disenchantment and Rage is the
name of your sex tape. Um and I am not sure that Delving Deeper into the
reconvened 2020 uh it was a convention. Blinking you'll miss it. It was a flashcon.
I mean have a bit of a lie in or be doing something else for a couple of hours and it's gone.
It turns out six hours long. Five hours long? Six hours long? Something in that region?
Liz did you go to reconvened 2020? No uh because as as stateless podcasts many times there are
many good things about virtual events and you can join them from around the world but reconvened
2020 was exactly 12 hours behind my time zone and so I think it took place between 10 p.m. and 5 a.m.
so no I don't love conventions enough to stay up literally all night while on my holidays.
It um that is a good that is a fair comment here it started at 4 p.m. and went until 11 p.m.
10 p.m. I think it was 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Eastern time yes. Portal 10 for us. That's good beer drinking
time. It was um and Oi went and I believe Alison also went. They had some apparently
excellent panels with excellent people on who in fact I did quite want to see but because I was
doing something else with some other people I I missed the Ted Chang one which was the one I
particularly wanted to go to because I've never actually heard him speak and um and then they were
all just kind of panels and I was like well you know panels and then they flowed into discussions
in chat which I I understand were quite good discussions in chat um which were also happening
during the panels as well as as after the panels and they were discord fan tables um and I spent
some time hanging out in discord fan tables most notably the Glasgow table but I mean my comment on
text chat is is party like it's nighty nighty night and um I feel like I feel like text chat does
not do it for me and they didn't they had discord chat tables but again because I was doing other
things involving zoom that weekend every time I try to run discord video I have to reboot my
computer before zoom will ever work again and and that is very tedious so I I would have definitely
joined a discord table if there'd been somebody I really wanted to talk to on it but there kind of
wasn't um and in fact there weren't that many people there were only maybe typically 20 or 25
people on on discord chat tables and in it you know in the in the audio and video um and as always
I'm at several different conventions this weekend and one of the other ones is um the stereoscopic
photography convention which is is despite the fact that it is mostly old white dudes they are
enthusiastically embracing new technology because 3d they are testing out a thing called high fidelity
where you can wander around an audio map and and see a cluster of people and then find yourself
in an audio chat with those people which you will not be able to hear if you move away from them
I think this is an intro I want to try this out with a bunch of my mates but it is only audio
rather than video so we we we kind of I still don't think the perfect answer exists but anyway
so it wasn't social enough for me there was no there were no zoom parties I like zoom parties
so um yeah so um I went to reconvene I saw the Ted Chang panel it was um very good that was the
panel I ran away from the zoom that I was in with you and Claire and Mark to go and see
I was very interesting I do find I think I agree with you I'm not I did not find the discord for
reconvene was particularly compelling it if if that I have been to online conventions where the
discord has been compelling um but I found that the reconvene was perhaps not busy enough or not
very enough or there was something about it that just I didn't really it was fun I was fine I was
checking it but like it didn't feel like it was replacing the social aspect of a real con for me
um and I remember what you said um last episode about conzeland having kind of eight hour blocks
so you um you suggested that it would have been a good idea to have like five hours of panels
and three hours of parties and then repeat and I do wonder whether reconvene would have been better
because they had six hours of panels which seems like an appropriate number of panels
then if they'd just had two hours of parties at the end the party was decided at 10 finished a
bit night for me um and then I could have got to bed and I would have gotten all of the the
socializing with with different fans uh uh around the world but they are test surrounding options
for boss scone and there's a limit to how much convention they could pull together in a very
short time because reconvene was pulled together very quickly I think the the plan would be to to
expand the social spaces I mean they certainly knew that they weren't as focused on on party on
generating parties as as other cons might be in general I think the model of having like a short
convention which is maybe sort of eight to nine hours long which is kind of five hours of of
panel and programming and then kind of three hours of of socializing and parties is a a model I
would like to see become a thing where you can just you know you and a few mates if you're an author
or even if you're a fan my own fan run conventions that did this um you know to put on you know maybe
two or three streams of five panels, sots and then do a big zoom with breakout rooms at the end
for people to come and just chat you know did you see that panel that was good wasn't it and I've
got a beer where do you come from you know like in regular convention bars and that would have
very good so I do think that they could have it would have been almost perfect with just like
you know a couple of hours of zoom on the end but but remembering that the zoom model is still
not a great model for parties and I'm I am still looking for alternatives that make socializing
better what we need is we need discord to have the zoom video features if discord could buy zoom
or zoom could buy discord whichever is richer and then just fold all the good bits are both perfect
okay so so it's not uncommon for amalgamations of this kind to end up with all the bad bits of
both yes that is a very good point and again we come to the fundamental difference in our looks um
no yes they yeah I mean I am mostly being facetious but I think if discord had better um
video and kind of live socializing options I do think yeah I mean discord does show you who's in
which chat which is the critical critical thing people want to be able to look at clusters of
people and go oh gosh Bertie Smith is in that cluster I haven't seen him since 1924 we could
talk about how shocking it is that they changed the name of the John W. Campbell award okay so
but I don't think this is also I'm going to talk a little bit about the difference between
British and US outlooks on conventions because it's not it's not uncommon for American conventions
to not really have any space where you could socialize in the way that the British socialize in the bar
to the extent that people the same people who are worried about um problematic things in
conventions often say that one of the things that is problematic about conventions is the bar
which speaking of somebody who holds up in the bar at the second they arrive at the convention
and and can only be winkled out by by biological imperatives um I'm slightly worried about this
but I do understand that there is an issue about alcohol and its relationship to fun that the
British may have a bigger interest a bigger problem with um maybe we should have this as a topic for
a future episode. The weekend of the 21st to the 23rd of August is NASFIC the US national
science fiction convention which is held in years where the world con is held outside the US
obviously because the internet is um in some ways outside the US NASFIC is happening this year
and so um Alison I believe it's going to be on the program and she's going to be talking about her
guff trip do you want to tell us a little bit about that Alison? Well I'm hoping to be talking
about my guff trip but it is very much the very first cut of a talk that I have additionally offered
to Futuricon where I really will be that'll be October and I hope that by that point I will have
a proper presentation where I talk for half an hour and then take questions about my guff trip
but this one's much going to be much closer to I have a list of bullet points and I'll talk for
half an hour and then take questions. Nice! Um but it won't be I won't have worked it up properly um
I got very much looking forward to it um it's got a more global um reach than it normally does
because online um it turns out that shifting your body clock five hours late so that you can
get up at noon and go to bed at five o'clock in the morning is it's not that hard compared to
going to New Zealand um and I'm hoping it'll be good again I will obviously be looking at it
from the point of view of how is it managing its social spaces because really how is convention
how are conventions managing their social spaces is the thing I'm more interested in than anything
else right now um because I don't think it will be to get in purpose person for a good while.
Next weekend I am going to virtually Expo which is the online edition of the UK Games Expo
I am going to be playing Arkham Horror with Liz as part of that convention um Liz won't be out
the convention but she will be playing Arkham Horror with me while I am at the convention so she'll
sort of be one degree of Kevin Bacon from the convention one degree of Bob Silverberg.
Is this technically ghosting or is this more kind of some weird tentacled version of a ghost?
Ha ha ha no the UK Games Expo is free except for role-playing games so um you don't there's no
really there's no real way to ghost um but yes yeah no I have a membership though I'm not
I am not certain how much was the weekend it's my nieces eighteeth's birthday next weekend and we're
going to an actually not socially distanced family party it is going to be outdoors but I think the
garden that's being held in the number of people who go which is not that mainly like about 20
could not literally fit in a socially distanced way into that garden which is about the size of
this study. I think I would say I am technically going to UK Games Expo but only to play this one
Arkham Horror game and someone in the Arkham Horror game has to do all the complicated bits
and that will be John. It will I'm looking forward to it and we are definitely going to do
Octa Thought plays Arkham Horror as a as an episode that we can drop in sometime when we can't record.
Yes we're committing to it now this is all going in the episode um so you heard it here
first folks are we are we going to do that I think it would be fun what do I need to do I need
to buy something to make that happen or can we just do it with kind of online versions or what
you need to buy tabletop simulator uh huh okay send me send me links I mean it's just going to be
two hours of Alice in asking questions and then we'll make that and then we'll have to find a
date for that because it can't be a regular recording time because if we do it at a regular
recording time it will not fulfill the function of being an extra episode that we can drop in
in an emergency and we could when we when we draw the podcast we could also like do a youtube
video so you can see the pictures if you want to okay so that was the 12th episode of the Octa
Thorpe podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me the
theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud at ncompetech.com
used under a creative commons attribution 3.0 license
but can I can I mention my anecdote about podcast editing what because I want to get this in and
jonak and use it a lot of new chooses which is that I happened to listen to the unedited version
of my favorite podcast the other day um I did this because they recorded a day late which meant
that when I was accustomed to listening to it it wasn't there so I went and grabbed the the
members only live bootleg and they spent for example 20 minutes talking about what they were going
to discuss things in and honestly I have huge support there for everybody who edits podcasts
that's what I always do but um it it it is an amazingly entertaining podcast that was much less
entertaining in the not edited version this is one of the reasons why um and this will go in the
after show but this is one of the reasons why whenever there's a podcast that's like you can
subscribe and get access to the unedited version it's like yeah because I want to pay you money to
make your product worse it'd be like if apple said you compare a section grounded you have to make
the computer I'd be like nah you're all right I'll pay the less money for the better thing
it doesn't I understand that it's like an easy way and I understand why they do it and I'm not
criticizing them at all but I've never been a USB for me at all because I'm like yeah editing
yeah but I did want to listen to it on Friday morning so there's that yeah that's fair I tried
it with do do the right thing have a podcast uh a patreon tier where you can get the edited
podcast and I tried it and I was like oh no the editing does make it better I shall just listen to
the edited versions I have been to see I'm sorry I have a declue being recorded oh yes and I can
confirm that although these are very funny people who are professionally funny and famous for it
it is still much better on the radio yes so I listened to I listened to I'm just gonna put my
anecdote in here nice I listened to a cycling podcast and during the grand tours they do a daily
episode and the you know the stage will finish for the day at maybe five p.m and usually the
episode would have been out by you know 11 p.m so somehow these guys record an episode and it gets
edited in like five hours flat and I don't know whether they just naturally sit down and do you
know 45 minutes of coherent stuff that doesn't require editing or the editors of magic but either
way there's some magic involved there to get that done and I'm you know now I have a podcast I'm even
more impressed about how good it sounds.