*laughs* Sorry, I've been distracted by John eating a sausage sandwich. Is it a sausage
sandwich? No, it's not. It's pesto and tomato. Oh, sorry, I've inadvertently kind of ordered
you up. But I'm not sure I'm really going anywhere with this or have an interesting
point to make.
*music*
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 63rd episode of Octa Thorpe, which is coming to you
on the 4th of August 2022. I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott. Oh no, I'm Liz Batty.
And we have some letters of comments on episode 61. And first up, we have Christopher J. Garcia.
He says that Alison is right about the no awarding of categories and that it should be
ahead of the ceremony instead of during the ceremony. And he says that this is true of
Olaf's proposal and we need to do a small apology because Paul Meimer wrote in to remind
us that it isn't just Olaf Rockne's proposal, but it is also Amanda Wackerock's proposal
and they co-authored it. So sorry to Amanda. And yes, that is both people involved. So
thank you very much for writing in. Paul, we did correct it in the show notes, but we
didn't correct it in the audio itself.
Although that is, I mean, Chris's thing is slightly different. That is where no award
actually beats out all the nominees in the puppy ears. And this is more, you know, where
there is no award, not because no award was voted above everything else, but because
the went in the votes. And I don't know if we should kind of take those two separately,
but at the same time it might be, it might be nice if the people who are going to get
no awarded knew they were going to get no awarded before they went and sat through the
whole ceremony.
And also it would have the advantage that if there was not going to be an award, you
could just not award that award in the ceremony, which would potentially be quite good. But
yeah, I don't know. It's an interesting point. And yes, you are right that they're slightly
conflated.
Maybe we'll see in six weeks time. Please vote in the hues.
Yes, please vote for a fan cast and for all of the other fan categories. Doesn't have
to be for us just for things that you like that have the word fan in them.
Yeah, I just, it's true of the others other categories as well. You know, to talk, such
a lower interest, you know, please vote.
Is please vote for best novel in case you had been planning not to novels deserve recognition
to listeners.
So yeah, no, but I know we're going to say this every time, but do please do please vote.
This also writes to say that he has two rumors, one of which is a prototype he got from the
museum because they had already got four rumors. So he took home, which is a flex about as
big as the time. Chris told me that I was looking at the only computer which had been
to the moon and also in his car.
And that his second rumor, he gave to his children to take apart, which I don't think
I could do because I've named mine a given it googly eyes. So I'm just going to have
to give it if it ever breaks is getting like a Viking funeral, I think I'm now attached
to it.
I have a rumor called Colin.
Oh, jot me to post you some googly eyes.
What from Thailand? I'm sure there's a more local stock to me. It's
Padland.
Yeah.
Padlands like Thailand, right?
In what sense? I don't know. So, and it's very good. It's good. It's named after the
robot that for prefect re programs in mostly harmless because it is a bumbling robot that's
very friendly and goes were and it hovers up the cat litter and that's good. So, hoorah,
10 out 10 robot would robot again.
And then we also had an email from Roman Orzansky. He writes in on the subject of the
wasfus constitution clause about minimum number of votes. And then he says that a more interesting
question might be the language of first publication because at the moment, finalists need to have
publication in English, say there is a South American world con and there was a big number
of Spanish attendees say there's a novel published in Spanish, which has a very small English
translation print run. It might gather sufficient votes to win not because of the standard of
the English publication, but because of the standard of the Spanish one. He then asks,
if the Hugo is a world award, why does it focus on first English publication?
I mean, it, it, it doesn't though, does it? There is no requirement that no one a, no
many for the Hugo's need to be in English. There's only an eligibility extension that
they are eligible again when they are published in an English translation. So, there's no
requirement that they actually be in English. It's just, it's never, it's just never come
about. I mean, it may come about in 2023, if there are sufficient voters who vote for
something in a Chinese language edition, I think that is one of the more plausible scenarios
just because if they have loads of members and many of them are not reading English language
science fiction. Thank you very much for that, Roman.
So we had a comment on Facebook in which Bridget Bradshaw says that if someone told me they
were pregnant, would I tell them they needed a P test? And that is a joke about statistics.
So thank you very much, Bridget. Or pregnancy tests. One of those. It's a joke about statistics
and lateral flow tests. So it definitely pills the two thirds of this podcast, possibly
all of this podcast. How do you feel about P test, Alison? Honestly, if I'm pregnant,
that's going to be the least of all worries.
Right. FantasyCon has been cancelled, everyone. Don't go to FantasyCon. It's not happening.
Oh, hang on, breaking news from a week ago. It's happening again. Yeah. Okay, we should
talk about this. Thank you very much, FantasyCon, for canceling and then re-instating themselves
in time for this episode so we can discuss the entire thing rather than discussing it
in two halves because that's very useful. We'd like to thank them sincerely for their very
thoughtful timing. Yes. So it appears that FantasyCon, which
was planned to be run in September 22 in London in, I think, the Radisson Conference
Centre where Eastacom was also held. They announced that it had been cancelled due to
lack of ticket sales. There's a message picked up from file 770, which says that they had
sold 200 memberships when they needed 400 memberships, which would give them a large
shortfall. And so they cancelled. And then afterwards, there was a survey which went
round essentially saying if we didn't run FantasyCon as we were planning to, but ran,
you know, a different style. So I'd have one day one or a two day one or a virtual event,
would you, would you attend? And it seems like this got enough positive messages that
actually they just reinstated FantasyCon as a slightly shorter two day event at the same
hotel on the same weekend. So it's basically back. I just found this whole thing quite confusing.
It's interesting to think about how the finances work. If you only sold 200 memberships and
that gives you a big shortfall, but then you must be pretty confident that if you run
a two day event, you will be able to sell enough memberships to make it viable as a two
day event without using a load of money. And I don't know anything about FantasyCon's finances,
but I wouldn't have thought running a two day event in a hotel was that much cheaper than
running a three day event in a hotel, especially if you're trying to get people to book more
hotel rooms.
I have two things about this. The first thing is, yes, it doesn't, it's not a great look
for a convention. I understand that the running of FantasyCon is franchised by the British
Fantasy Society. So they basically say to a committee, please, please run this on a behalf
and you can do what you like with the profits and so on. And so there is a certain amount
of, this isn't quite the same group who were originally going to run it, running it. So
that might explain part of this, but I suspect what actually happened is that they went to
the hotel and said, "Oh, we don't have enough people, please cut us a better deal." And
the hotel went, "No, shant." And so they went, "Okay, we'll counsel then." At which
point the hotel said, "As hotels want to do, oh, wait." So my suspicion is that by announcing
the cancellation, they have been able to get a better deal with the hotel, including also
obviously cutting the amount of hotel space they'll use because it's only a two day event
rather than a three day event. But that would be my guess is that they've cancelled, is
that that is what happened.
And so let me just say something entirely unsubstantiated and with no evidence, because you know.
That's what I said.
But I feel like I heard someone say that like in the aftermath of the cancellation, like
there was a rumor going around that the hotel had basically been like, "We're not going
to give you a better deal," and then they kind of like, "What were going away then?"
The hotel were like, "Oh, we would probably give you a better deal." And so maybe I think
that, Talies War, you just said.
That was certainly true for Pascon quite a long time ago now.
No, I heard it recently about FantasyCon. I can't remember where, I can't remember who,
and it might not be true listeners.
I had not heard this as a rumor. I had only made it up out of my head on the basis of
previous experiences of that exact process happening.
I mean, it makes a lot of sense, right? Like...
But hotels, if somebody comes to you and says, "If you don't give us a better deal,
we are going to have to cancel our event." Do not call their bluff.
I mean, yeah, it does seem a bit strange. The whole thing seems a bit strange at the moment
with venues, foreshadowing, for later in the podcast listeners.
What could we possibly talk about to do with venues for conventions?
Hmm.
The convention was only six weeks away, eight weeks away at the time.
So probably if they went to a town and said, "Well, we're going to cancel the hotel."
We're then like, "Oh, well, actually we can't get anything else in here at that time."
You know, it's out of school holidays, so there's not going to be as many people wanting
to stay in a Heathrow hotel. Yeah, so they probably...
They may have been inclined to say, "Actually, how about we give you a reduced price for
a reduced amount of space or something similar?" But we don't know.
It makes a lot of sense, I think. So who's going to FantasyCon?
I might be at FantasyCon. I think it would be great if I wasn't FantasyCon.
I confess I was not really planning to go, and the Covaville has not really affected that
in any way. I do wonder, to what extent a convention cancelling and then reconstituting
itself affects people's likelihood of going? I can't imagine it's helpful, but it might
not be a very big negative effect. But I don't know. If you're planning to go to FantasyCon
right in, if you were planning to and you're not now right in, if you weren't planning
to and you are now right in, or if you just think things right in, tell us what you reckon.
It might make a difference, because there might be people who are on the fence about it,
but then if it's like, "Oh, well, actually, we're in difficulties if we don't get some
more people, this event will run," they might decide, "Actually, yeah, okay, I'll go along
even if it's just for a day." I mean, I'm not going because it's two weeks after WorldCon
and thousands of miles away, so...
Yeah, I mean, I do think you have a better excuse.
I have a pretty good excuse, yeah.
This is not unlikely that I will be there for various reasons, but partly, but I might
quite well be commuting, which, too, he throw is a pain. I mean, people who think that London
is quite small, it's quite a long journey from here to Heathrow, because it's on the
exact diametric opposite side of London to me.
So yeah, FantasyCon. Hopefully, it'll be great. Do we know, I think the "chandmiti" has changed,
right? Do we know what's happened to the committee? Who's on it now? And who is not?
Do we know? I do, in general, find it very difficult to know what's happening with FantasyCon,
whatever I want to know. When I was looking up FantasyCon stuff for the podcast last year,
it was almost impossible to find out concrete information, and it wasn't helped by the fact
they had two different websites, and it was all very confusing. So I do sort of wish there
a bit more on the board with that. As it happens, the FantasyCon website currently still says
that FantasyCon isn't being run, and they should probably fix that, because it is.
It's got a link to an alternative, but it does appear that people who are joined FantasyCon
will get a refund and then have to join the new one.
Yeah, but also if you go on FantasyCon.org, it says it's cancelled and there's news about
what might happen here. And then when you click through to what might happen, it's like,
"Oh, it's running!" And it's like, "But you might want to mention that on the website,
click here for the rescheduled FantasyCon." It's very strange, I don't understand.
I have something that's definitely for podcasts to say about this, which is that if I was
running a convention and was worried that I didn't have enough members and needed to
get a lot more members, then my first course of action would be to make sure that all of
my comms messages were lined up and saying the same thing and made it very easy for people
to find out about the convention and join. And my second course of action would be to
do a load of social media posts about how marvelous the convention was going to be and
how it might be a really good idea to come along because you would be missing something
if you didn't. And as far as I can see, FantasyCon did not do either of those things.
No, it's very strange. I don't quite understand why. But I'm sure it'll be a great convention
and let us know if you're going listeners.
The Clarke Award shortlist has come out.
The book is actually presented in Orkney and in English so that you can read it in English.
The book is actually presented in English so that you can read it in English. So I'm going
to read it as a parallel text. Oh, that's really cool.
And I think that is a first for the Clarke Award and that's quite exciting. It's probably
the first science fiction book to be published by a major publisher in the Orkney language
and I do speak Scots reasonably well having lived in Scotland for four years and I'm quite
looking forward to this. Nice.
I had not appreciated that. That is good knowledge. Thank you very much, Alison.
Yeah, I have seen, I haven't got Deep Wheel OK, but I have seen pictures of it and yeah,
I think it is presented in both languages which is quite interesting and I look forward
to seeing how that works on my Kindle.
Oh, that's a good question, isn't it? Oh, oh, hang on. Is this one of the ones I bought?
Yeah, I think I think this is one that I've got.
It is. I have got it. How does it work? Oh, it's just the Orkney and then the English.
They're like, passagen or kney passagen English. Lots of little nice pictures separating them.
Clentice? Also, I will say, I assume this isn't a problem with my e-book, which is always
an interesting sentence, right? Like, is this how it's supposed to be or is it a mistake?
Because I have been wrong about that in books before I've been like, oh, this is very artistic
and there's like, no, you had a misprinted copy of what you do. But it does like, it
has the word skilled wise magical cautious or one word and it has the word jut thrust
and the word tap, chapped takes. And I assume these are, these are in the English segments,
right? I assume these are artistic choices and not just like the e-book has the spaces
in the wrong places. I don't know. If anyone's got the physical copy, please let me know.
Yeah, that is correct. There is a review of this book in the Scotsman that says, "Canny
is translated as skilled wise magical cautious and I would translate canny as canny, but
then apparently I use big words." Yeah, like skilled wise magical cautious.
I would translate canny as canny. I didn't know that was particularly Scots because it's
all over Newcastle. So, yeah. Yeah, you're pretty close to Scotland, aren't you? Yeah,
but we're not in it. Got a big wall to keep them out, you know. Very important. And how
well is that wall working out for you? So I've bought Deep Wheel or Acadia, Skyward
Inn and Wurgen, the alien love war. I've already read to them our team and the other
two which are a difficult time and Clara and the Sun are, I believe, available from my
library. So I will get them out from there. So that might be a spoiler for a future filler
episode of Oxford. We'll have to see how many, how much people like our previous filler episode
first because we, on which we have had no feedback. Yeah, no locks. No locks whatsoever.
It has been a solid 12 hours since I dropped that episode. So it looks like a good, looks
like a good roster, I think. Always exciting when it's mostly books I have no idea about
because, you know, more books. And also books I had heard vanishingly little buzz about.
Like most of the you goes, I was like, peripherally aware of, but the clerks are like, yeah, I
had not really, it's just fine. I'm not plugged in enough, maybe.
Well, I think that's the nice thing about the clerk is that it usually picks some books
I've heard of and then some completely left wheel choices and some of them are absolute
genius and some of them are absolute nonsense. So I always look forward to, but I'd always
look forward to reading the shortlist in order to see which way they've gone, they've gone
this year. I think there are two reasons for that. And one of them is, is excellent and
delicious. Well, they're both good, really. The first is that the clerk judges actually
read all the books. So if a book is very good, but it has almost zero marketing budget, then
they will notice it and say this is amazing despite the fact that it had zero press. But
it also means that sometimes you get a book that somebody on the judges absolutely adores,
even though everyone else thinks it's a complete nonsense and it gets on because one person
is prepared to fight for it hard enough to the point where everyone else goes, oh, good,
we just want to get out and get to the barn.
So I read, I mentioned last episode that I read the first Becky Chambers novel on a
beach on my honeymoon. And the reason I did that was because we had to board a stage prior
to the honeymoon to get beach reading. And there was a table of clerk award nominees.
It was one of the books that was nominated for the clerk that year. So that's how I came across.
Mainly because it had been nominated for the clerk and had a good title. I mean,
I suspect me and Liz slightly differ in which side of the nonsense, not a nonsense divide.
Do we think that book falls on?
Well, that's, and this is a reason why we might want to discuss the clerks because
my perception is that Liz and I have mostly very different tastes in Sartre's fiction novels.
There is a very real risk that we read them all and go,
yep, let's go feel Katie Martin again, please.
We can just copy and paste the bit from episode 62 where we discuss the Martin to drop it in
to whatever episode we do for the clerk and we don't have to talk about it again, right?
No one will notice.
Speaking about back shadowing, David Grigg, who does the two chairman podcast,
also does a newsletter called Through the Biblioscope. And he discussed the books,
the finalists for Hugo's this week. And for the Martin, he said, oh, this is the one I haven't read
because I hadn't read the previous one and I didn't have time to read both of them and didn't fancy
it. And then he goes on to talk about the other novels in a way that makes me think that he's
likely to like the Martin a whole lot and I have commented to him to say so because otherwise his
ranking was not as similar to ours.
And then we've been foreshadowing it. We've been building up to it. You've known about it for a
full two weeks, but let's discuss the very exciting news about the conversation venue.
Take it away, Alison.
Yes. So in the patch of time today that I might have been preparing for the podcast,
I was busy announcing conversation, which is next year's Eastercon, which I am on the committee of
as a site, which is the Hilton Birmingham Metropole. We will ask there for
Ennominate in 2017. And we were previously there for Beccon 87. So that was a little while ago.
It's much improved since then. And I believe it has somewhat improved since
Ennominate. We've actually been there at least once or twice between that as well. It is a very
large, very well appointed hotel, extremely close to a railway station and by a lake. And it is
properly accessible and has all of the function space and all of the other facilities that we
need and we are very excited to be using it. We'll be opening her hotel bookings quite shortly.
I don't know whether that'll have happened or not by the time the episode comes out, so I don't
want to say. But quite soon, if you haven't joined, we will also be increasing our membership rates
quite soon. And again, I don't know whether that'll happen before or after this episode comes out.
So but if it hasn't, then you just don't have long now, you should definitely get on and join
the convention if you're planning to come because we're going to put the rates up.
It was also the site of illustrious in 2011. Yeah, that's right. Illustrious was the other
plate. Because I was like, I've been there twice. I know I have and I know I didn't go in 1987 for
reasons. So there must have been one in between. For reasons we're not going to talk about. Yeah.
But Caroline was on the committee of that one. So she's chairing this one and she was on the
committee of that one. So it's kind of a return to a site that she's very familiar with. And although
it's changed in some ways, there are some other ways in which it's just the same.
In 2017, which was in nominate, they had Easter eggs in the foyer and conversation guest of honor,
Neil Harrison won the bid at the fan fund auction to be able to pick his Easter egg and eat it.
And he chose a very beautiful egg, which was actually a tree with lots and lots of eggs.
And I have very fond memories of him basically having massive analysis paralysis as to which
of these beautiful Easter eggs he should take for his winning bid. And it was very good. So I'm hoping,
I mean, all I'm saying is drop lots of hints. Because it's good to auction Easter eggs at the
foyer off the fan fund auctions. True fact. So I have fond Neil Harrison based memories of the hotel.
I have quite a lot of fond memories of that hotel. I've often stayed at one of the multiple
cheaper hotels offsite, sorry conventions. And I have quite fond memories of either like
staggering back through the car park at 2am or in one case the hotel van driving us back to the
hotel. Just very nice of them. I mean, I am going to say as I would do, like all Easter cons, we have
a room block that we need to fill and we have a food and drink target for the beverage target
that we need to achieve. But so we prefer people not to go book elsewhere. But you know,
it's if you need to, there are plenty of other options in the area at lower rates, indeed,
is this I don't think I think the only times I've ever not stayed in the con hotel are times when
the con hotel was too small to stay in. It's like Bradford. I remember one of those I didn't and
Harroga. I didn't. But the only other time is I think satellite for which is 2014 one. I stayed in
the camp and I'll instead of the con hotel and I regret it every single minute of it. So, you know,
I am a bougie boy and I require my breakfasts. Abooji. I quite often stay in the nearest premiere
in which usually do pretty good breakfasts. Premiering breakfast is not bad. The World Con Hotel doesn't
come with breakfast, by the way, John. I'm just mentioning that now before you get your hopes up.
For Chai Kong? Yeah. Oh, no, I knew this. American hotels very often don't, but that's fine because I
do love extremely cheap diners. Yeah, because American breakfasts are amazing. So, you know,
getting a good breakfast near the hotels is not going to be difficult. I wouldn't have thought.
Oh, you need Southeast Asian breakfast, by face. I do need that. I didn't know I needed it, but
do need it. Can I get those in Chicago? Probably not, no. When Liz runs the Bangkok World Con,
sorry, Globe Con. That's a deep cut for the listeners. I went to conference. Let's go in 1993.
It's Paniya's first convention. And we stayed at the ANA. The ANA is the Japanese airline. It had,
what I think is probably a Southeast Asian hotel breakfast buffet, and it was fantastic.
Yeah, they basically try and cater to people who would like a sort of Western-style breakfast of,
you know, pancakes and waffles and fruit. And also, usually, there's like an egg station that
will make you whatever type of egg you like. Plus, there'll be like noodles and curry and egg fried
rice for people who like a more savory breakfast. And on one memorable breakfast buffet, there was
ice cream. Nice. I like breakfast. Egg stations are the dream. If you're at breakfast with an egg
station, you know that's an excellent breakfast. Yeah, the plotter.com that was in Leicester had
an egg station at the Holiday Inn in Leicester. That was very good. Nice. Oh, the Holiday Inn
in Leicester. I know it well. That's very good. It had a very, very good breakfast. That was by far
the best thing about the, well, probably about the whole convention actually, certainly about the
hotel. My favourite breakfast in the country is located in Leicester in a small bar called Bados
Hamanos. And they do a phenomenal full English breakfast and also a very good cadre. So that is
very conflicting. So where are we thinking of holding punctuation, the in-person punctuation then?
Whoever's got the best breakfast? Yeah, that's right. No, I mean, I'd be well if I holding that in
Leicester. There are good hotels there. I like that city a lot anyway. And it's got the space centre.
Leicester's a pretty good place to hold a convention. Not an East con, doesn't have sight,
apart from the Hinkley. Let's not talk about the Hinkley. Hinkley isn't Leicester. It's quite close.
Hinkley's a terrible town. Yeah, I mean, it's sort of in the same way that Crawley isn't London.
Hinkley is not Leicester. I mean, I think it's in the same way that Croydon is actually London.
Yeah, that's why I didn't say Croydon. Oh, he throw.
Croyley is overflow Croydon and Hinkley is overflow Leicester. Croyley's quite nice, actually.
Well, okay, they used to be a very good breakfast of holding Croyley. That's what I mean.
Those are different things. There's a great beer festival in Peterborough. You'd never hear
me arguing Peterborough was nice. I would say that the Hilton Birmingham Metropolitan has a solid
breakfast. First-class breakfast. It does. It really does. And they never make you feel like
because the 2011 Birmingham Convention was obviously between the second and third Ocons.
And the contrast in the breakfast was very noticeable because they had like
black and white pudding and they were friendly to you and smiled. And none of these things were
true of the Ocon hotels. The Radisson non-
waftra, I think did I do guys? You did one for a galactic journey. Oh, I was going to plug
a galactic journey. Yeah, but in fact, I'll just do that as part of these things I've actually put
in here, which is I wanted to do a quick plug for the Chicon Fringe, which is going on at the moment
and is a series of discussions, some of which are local in Chicago. So if you're in Chicago,
do go along to them. And some of which are online. And some of those are being run by Glasgow in
2024, which is a bid for the 2024 WILCON. By the time this comes out, you will be too late to support
Glasgow in 2024. So I probably should have plugged that last time. I'll go back and insert it into
our episode before last. But meanwhile, there's a bunch of events going on under the Fringe banner.
And I think they weren't quite a finished by the time we get this out. But I did one on Best
Fanzine when I paid attention to and had a good look at all the Best Fanzine finalists and
concluded that I quite liked all of them and had some nice things to say about them all of them.
So thank you to everyone who came along to that. And everyone else reads the Best Fanzines. Go and
look at what they've put in the Hugo Vert package, which is a great place to start. And what you'll
find is that they are all very different, but also all very interesting and well worth your
Hugo vote. This is linked to that previous plug to go and vote for fan things in the Hugo vote
for the fanzines because they're jolly interesting. Also, as part of that, I had to declare an interest
because I have now become a columnist on one of those finalists, which is Galactic Journey,
which is a fanzine that is experiencing the world through the eyes of a traveler 55 years ago,
exactly day by day. And so every couple of days it does an article in time about what's going on in
science fiction and fantasy and fandom and culture in that time. And it's a very interesting high
concept thing that I think everybody should be paying attention to. They also have a series of
TV nights where they watch Star Trek, which I don't go to because it was not broadcast in the
United Kingdom in 1967, but they also watched the first global TV broadcast together, and that was
quite good fun. Wait, Alison, are you a purist? And so you're only writing about things that you
personally could have experienced in the UK 55 years ago. So no Star Trek. I'm obviously
blurring the edges around this for all sorts of reasons. I think one criticism of Galactic
Journey is that it keeps in time, but it approaches things with the perspective of people in the
2020s, though not the actual knowledge of individual events. Yeah. Yeah, I'm mostly just making a joke.
There's an argument, I suppose, that if it wasn't doing that, you could just read
fanzines from 1969, and that would be simpler. So I do think part of the interesting thing is the
dramatic irony of it, almost right? Like the fact that you know what will happen and see you can
play with our little bit is good. It's a really interesting project, generally speaking.
They notice things that fans who were actually writing in 1967 don't notice, partly because you
don't notice the sea when you're swimming in it, but partly because the fans in 1967 were
mostly coming from one perspective, and there were a lot of other things going on in the world
that were not necessarily from that perspective that are interesting, and were interesting at the
time if you'd known about them, which she didn't.
Shall we do picks? Why not? So my pick is a slightly unusual one, even for me having previously picked
a rumba. Mine is a video called The Great Potato Wall. So you need a bit of backstory here, which is
there was a Minecraft YouTuber by the name of Technoblade, who I had never come across until a
couple of weeks ago when he died tragically early from lymphoma and the internet basically started
posting a load of links in tribute to him. And so I started watching them. He'd been a Minecraft
YouTuber for I think 10 years, you know, he started when he was only 13 or something and built this
huge fan following. And The Great Potato Wall, I think, is the funniest one I've watched. It is
the story of a man who in a Minecraft world attempts to become the number one potato farmer
in the world. And I just recommend you watch it. It's 20 minutes, it's pretty funny. And there's two
sequels to it where the man he beats to the spot of the one potato farmer does to get his revenge
on him for trying to beat him to the pinnacle of potato collection. And can you make your Minecraft
farm get you 1.5 million potatoes per day and so on. So yeah, it's pretty funny. It's something I
would never have come across. Unfortunately, apart from people started posting the videos after his
kind of tribute and a bit to restarting going around as well. And it makes me a bit sad that I never
saw any of these videos when he was around to make some more. So I recommend, yeah, give it 20
minutes over your time. I shall do that. My younger child, who is only a little bit older than,
only a little bit younger than Technoblade, was extremely upset about his death, which was
was an enormous shock to the community. And we had to have a non conversation about the way it is
possible to be, to grieve for somebody that you've never met and only know over the internet from
the things that they've done. Oh, absolutely. I mean, one of the podcasters who runs my,
well, probably my favourite podcast, again, died tragically young, you know, literally the day after
he'd made a podcast. And it was, it was just straight with this community who you've never met the
person, but at this point, I'd listened to kind of hundreds of hours of his podcasting. So you felt
like you have a connection to him in a way that you don't really, because he had friends and family,
and you were people he'd never met. But you did all kind of come together and grieve for this
person you had a very kind of parasocial relationship with. Yeah. And so this kind of reminds me of that
in a completely different community. I haven't had that. The closest I've had is like when people
like Terry Bradgio, I'm very little to have gone, and you feel like you know them even though you
didn't. But yeah, it's tricky, right? Because you don't know them, but you're still very, very
sad about it. And I say like Technoblade and his community have raised, they raised over half a
million dollars falling from a research. So. Crikey. Yeah, they've done pretty well. That is,
that's good going. Yeah. For a good cause. Mm hmm. My pick is in the vein of picking things
that are up to date and relevant and down with the kids. I'm going to pick a 20 year old video game,
a little number you may have heard of called Star Wars Knights of the Old Republic. Now,
this is a relatively skewer game that hasn't had much of an impact on Star Wars fandom.
So allow me to explain. This is a game by BioWare and it's a big old RPG and you can get it for
almost every platform you could possibly imagine. It's like Doom. I believe it's been installed on
a pregnancy test. Yeah. But I have it for iPad and I think I also have it for computer
for on Steam. But basically I've discovered that I can connect my PlayStation 4 controller to my
iPad and then I can play Kotor for long train journeys. And I recently had a trip to Coventry
and a trip to Peterborough. And so I played a lot of nice the Old Republic. It's quite good.
Listeners, I've discovered this and I'm telling you and this is the first you're hearing about it.
I have a query. What's the query? Can you get it for the M1 Mac? Yeah. You get it for Apple
Silicon Macs? Yeah, I think so. I think I could play on my computer. I don't particularly want to.
Because most most Steam games don't play on Apple Silicon Macs in a very considerably
annoyance thing even if they do one. If you wanted to play games, you probably shouldn't have bought
an M1 Mac. I don't really like playing games on computers, if I'm honest. I like playing games
mostly with controllers. But also I like playing games on platforms where you install the game
and it works. And my experience of playing PC games when I was a kid is that the PC is not the
platform you want. If that is what you are aiming at. I quite like my PlayStation 5 and I quite
like my Nintendo Switch and I quite like my iPad and they let me play between them a lot of games.
And you attach a controller to the iPad to play this sort of game? Yes. How? Which controller are
you attaching? I'm attaching a PlayStation 4 DualShock 4 wireless controller. Which is red.
Oh, and it just what it just syncs with your iPad? Apple have built in to their offering systems
support for the PlayStation 4, PlayStation 5, Xbox One, Xbox, whatever the current one is,
and Nintendo Switch controllers. And they're all Bluetooth controllers. So you just connect them
and they just recognize automatically. The really cool thing is that if you connect the Switch
Joy-Cons, they're clever enough to know when you're using them in single Joy-Con or whether
you're using them connected and the iPad can just like work out what you're doing and do it all
magically like the Switch would. So it's quite a good implementation. But because I had a spare
PS4 controller from when I sold my PS4 to Alison, I used that as my like controller for my iPad and
my Mac. And I've been playing KOTOR with that. It is better than using the touch screen. I think
the touch screen controls are all right. But like I think using a controller is better.
But yeah, KOTOR is good. Yeah, but my eyes lit up at the idea of using Joy-Cons because Joy-Cons
are tiny. So in terms of cutting them around, it's not like cutting a bloody controller around, is it?
Yeah, I mean Joy-Cons do give me Handcramp, which is why I've bought a Switch Pro controller
because there's really interesting article somewhere on the internet about how
Nintendo designs for child hands and Sony designs for adult male hands.
Our next box is on for giant hands.
Hey, my hands are smaller than you think they are. And it's so true.
So true. We lost week with little stubby hands. And I was like, Sue, I've got little
stubby hands in this picture. And then I looked at my fingers and I was like, oh, it's probably
all right, really. But I will say, I want to quickly say something about the law of the
nice old Rorick. Oh, that's a fantastic game. The game is basically a D20 based role-playing game
running in a video game, which is never something I really got behind. Because the great benefit
of Paper RPGs is that you can let your imagination run wild. But I wouldn't argue that the simulation
aspect is like as good as a video game, can simulate things necessarily. But what this does
also mean is that when you become a Jedi, it's not really a spoiler to say you become a Jedi,
because of course you become a Jedi. You have to choose one of three Jedi classes,
and they're very rigorously defined, and you fall into one of them. And it's like,
what's going on? This doesn't make any sense. And that bled through into a lot of the expanded
universe media, because it was like there are these three types of Jedi. And that is how it works.
And it's like, one of the great things about them having moved away from the expanded universe
is that this model of how the force works has gone away. And that is probably better.
See, I picked my class while rolling my eyes into the back of my head. But I have a lightsaber now.
And I think it's yellow. Might be blit. I can't remember. It's A color.
Kortles are pretty good game. Yeah, just very quickly. Star Wars Nice Thoroughly Republic is indeed
optimized for M1 Max. The current Star Wars games that are are X-Wing, TIE Fighter, Nice Thoroughly,
Nice Thoroughly Republic 2, and Rebel Assault 1 and 2. The others I have are not.
But now I know I can play it straightforwardly on my iPad. That's what I'm going to do.
Yeah, I still haven't bought an iPad. And now I'm like, oh, I could buy an iPad and play
a night. So probably got it with my PlayStation controller. So it's even more likely we'll get an iPad.
Yeah. So we are recording early listeners. You may not have noticed.
So I am going to tell you about an exhibition that I'll go to in the future,
because I'll go to it tomorrow. If we were recording at a normal time, I would have gone to it and I
would have been able to have it as a pick. But I am going to it tomorrow. It is at the Hayward
Gallery, which is the Gallery Bit of the South Bank Center in London. And it is called In the Black
Fantastic and the Blurb For It Is, an exhibition of 11 contemporary artists from the African diaspora
who draw on South's fiction myth and Afrofuturism to question our knowledge of the world. And it has
had rave reviews with the England Standard saying there is unlikely to be a better show this year.
The Observer saying a magnificent experience, spectacular from first to last. Several of my
friends have seen it and raved about it. And then just lots of five star reviews. And I am going to
it tomorrow with FARA and some other people. And I'm very much looking forward to it.
But I haven't actually seen it yet, but I'm going to pick it anyway so that you can get on and get
to it before it closes. It runs till the 18th of September and it's 13.50. And that's probably
concessions. Because this episode doesn't come out for two weeks, obviously Alison will be taking
a microphone with her and recording some live thoughts, which I will drop in now.
It will be practice for our, you know, whatever guerrilla recording we decide to do at Ch icon
and or when John is making lightsovers. Oh, cabaret, the gorilla's amazing.
I would just say, I don't understand what that means. I want that wasn't what I was going to say,
but you just said. Okay, so cabaret has a gorilla in it for people who don't know. And this particular
production of the gorilla has gone really into it with with a very realistic gorilla suit and
people doing and a person doing generally very realistic gorilla movements. Whereas normally it's
obviously a person in a gorilla suit. Nice. Spoiler for cabaret, which I can't really have as my
pick because cabaret is not science fiction. I would I would really like to go and see it though.
It looks great. The current, the current production of cabaret is unbelievably good and
and it's currently the guy from Hawkeye, right? Yes, Fraffy is the MC and Amy Lenox is the current
Sally Bowles and it's so good. When you say the guy from Hawkeye, I think Jeremy Renner and I
don't think you mean Jeremy Renner. So it's the I can't remember his character's name, but the
deaf he's the the one from the gang who is the deaf girls friend from birth. Oh, okay. Okay, cool.
I like that guy. Anyway, that was the Octa thought podcast and it's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
That's probably another another stream deck, fresh jump.
I'm going to press the back on track button and we're going to get back on track, nailing it.
We have a back on track button. Wait, yeah, that'd be really useful. How the fuck does that work?
Yeah, because I need to know where I need to know where we got back on track. If there's a huge
aggression, I need a button that told me where the end of the aggression was. I mean, in this case,
it hasn't worked because it has triggered another aggression. Oh, I see. So it's not a button that
gets us back on track. Like, you know, it's not right. Oh, Liz, if I could have a button that got
you back on track, I mean, like 100% I would. The podcast recording would be much shorter.
God, if you have got a button that will get me back on track, I could really, really use it in my
daily life regularly. The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod
and Comprotec.com, used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.