I might just cut that sentence out because it didn't really add anything.
John, if you cut out every sentence, it doesn't really add anything.
The podcast would be 25 minutes long.
Victory.
For me.
Yeah.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to the very 161st episode of Octothorpe,
a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom,
which is finding a weird robot child in a junkyard on the 4th of June,
2026.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And I got that reference.
That was good.
Yay.
Today,
listeners,
we are discussing the Arthur C.
Clarke Award,
2026 shortlist.
I was a judge for the Arthur C.
Clarke Award this year,
alongside my fellow judges.
Antony Jones, Eliza Filimon, Esther MacCallum-Stewart and Tiffani Angus.
Ooh.
Cool.
Good judges.
In this episode, we're going to discuss the shortlist and then we're going to discuss
judgment.
And so the shortlist, which has been announced today, comprises the following books.
Dungeon Crawler Carl by Matt Dinneman.
The Dream Hotel by Laila Lalami.
Luminous by Sylvia Park.
There Is No Antimemetics Division by qntm.
When There Are Wolves Again by EJ Swift
and The Salt Oracle by Lorraine Wilson.
Fun fact
when John said
I've got early access to the
I've been authorised to give you early access to the list
so that you can read them and we can do a podcast about it
it turned out that
Liz had already read all six of these books
and I had already read one of them
and I'd only read it because
John and Liz had bleated on
about it so much over the last year
Unfortunately that is incorrect
I'd read four of them. Oh, you'd read four of them. Okay. Sorry. Okay. I had read all six.
So I should jolly well hope. Yeah, my thing is announced you probably should have read them all
at least once, right? I mean, but we'll talk about how judging works. And you can explain that bit
later. I was like, will I have time to read all these books and then record a podcast about it?
And John was like, yes, yes, you will. He already knew that I had read four of them. And indeed,
picked three of them on this very podcast so it's a very liz coded year and i was like will i have
time to read all of them and then record a podcast and john was like yes you do not need to eat or
sleep well i just i just um confidently predicted that giving you a deadline would uh would mean
that you read them all and i was uh largely correct yeah correct i i have read them all
yeah that's good so yeah very liz coded list i think i think it's a very good list um so there
are six novels two of them are not for me but i think there are novels that people will like and
that a lot of people do like and the other four are definitely novels that are for me so i thought
it was pretty good yeah shall we discuss them a bit and then we'll give our verdict on how
clarky etc this uh shortlist is and there is no overlap with the hugo shortlist which i thought
was very interesting i think this year there were a lot of strong books and i think it is probably
a reflection of that that there is more diversity i think years where the lists converge more
might be years where the there is a less broad spectrum of quality does that make sense like if
the if the nebula and the hugo and the clark are all converging on sort of eight novels that probably
tells you something about the the field outside of those eight novels whereas they're converging on
sort of 16 novels that probably tells you there were more top-notch novels in that year there are
also no books in common with the nebula novel finalists this year which i thought was interesting
as well for those who might be new listeners the the hugo the nebula and the clark i would say are
the big three um science fiction awards i think that is fair um i'm not sure i mean if you look
at the nebula list there's at least three on there that i know of that i would call pretty
much fantasy or horror and so i would have been surprised to see them turn up on the clark list
anyway and the three i haven't read actually i think at least one of them is quite uh horror
slash fantasy so i'm not that surprised there's not a lot of crossover with the nebula a little
bit surprised there's not a crossover with the hugo but we can discuss the books and why we think that
is yeah i think one of my friends who i've stayed with this weekend said i really like the clerk
because it focuses on science fiction um rather than being more genre broad and i think that is
true i think it's an award for science fiction novels and i think you can argue that all of these
books are for science fiction um and i think five of them are novels so i think that's pretty good
intriguing you gotta do a bit i think you gotta do a bit of squinting in places anyway
well we could talk about that some of them wear their science fiction quite lightly
shall we go quickly through the list individually the first book on the list is dungeon crawler carl
by Matt Dinnaman.
And this is about a man
and his ex-girlfriend's cat
and they play a live-action roleplay
against their will.
I've forgotten the way
that John summarises things.
Yeah, when John was like,
I'll summarise them if you want.
I'm like, oh, what?
Yeah, John's going to summarise them.
So Liz loves these novels
and had previously picked
Dungeon Crawler Carl.
I think...
I don't think this book is a novel.
I think that novels require a resolution and I think this basically dumps you opens up a lot
of questions dumps you part way through the story and says read number two if you want to find out
what happens next and I don't think it should be on a finalist list but there we go lots of people
love these books oh and also it has a talking cat so there's that it's a great talking cat though
no okay it's a talking cat you've got to remember Alison doesn't like animals Liz
like and fine if they do animal things i mean i i don't like anthropomorphic cats in science
fiction novels because they're generally terrible and this is probably better than some of them
i read this i mean i got to the end of it and i was like oh i have to read book two now and then
i went oh no i have to read all the other books on the shortlist now so i am going to read all the
rest probably or at least i mean i tend to get bored part way through series so it's possible
that sometimes it took me about 100 pages or so before i started enjoying this one but
but by the end i'd kind of been won over by many things about it it's not at all a bad book not a
novel arguably science fiction i think there's some science fiction premise in here but it's
it's not i mean there may be i mean there's a lot more books so by the time he gets to the end it
it all makes sense when i think i don't intend to draw a comparison to the quality of the books
but i think it's as science fiction as ready player one in that if you've got aliens who make
you live through a fantasy world that is still sf yeah no no my my problem here was it's non
novelness not it's non-satisfaction that's really i mean yeah it is the the first part of a serialized
story but i i think there are other good books where you could argue oh they really exist in
order to make the so you will go and read the second book but unless you want to like diss the
lord of the rings or whatever let's diss the lord of the rings i will say the lord of the rings is
terrible science fiction yes but also the lord of the rings was you know tolkien thought it was one
book it was only published as three books for marketing purposes well possibly matt dinaman
thought that one 7 000 page book or whatever would not be so good for marketing purposes
yeah it is it's quite serialized a chunk of a much bigger story it's a serial and you've got
the first part here i'm not prepared to throw out books because they are the first part of a longer
story because i think there are many many books which are the first part in a longer series i take
the point that it could have come to a slightly more conclusive end but the way the books are
structured is that carl and donna are going down into a dungeon with levels and so you i think you
do get a pretty reasonable self-contained story on each level as well as it being heavily serialized
i think looking through previous years that the last books to be clark nominees that were part of
a wider series are um both of the to a memory called empire and a desolation called peace
were both finalists by arcady martine and they're a duology and then in 2019 rosewater was nominated
which has two sequels
but I think generally speaking
the clerk does not tend to
do installments in series
I think normally
like both of the books
you've mentioned there
there's an arc of story in the novel
as it stands
I read Rosewater and enjoyed it
and I didn't think
oh no I have no
nothing has been resolved
in Dungeon Crawler Coal
nothing is resolved by the end of the
first installment. I think that's the difference for me. But you know, people like this book a lot.
I also, a lot of the humour in it didn't land for me. I didn't find a lot of things that were
clearly intended to be funny, funny. And I think that's a problem. Because I think, you know,
it's clearly, it's humour for people of a different generation to me, or with a different sense of
humour to me, or maybe both. It's the second episode in a row where we get to play the games
the boomer yes yes absolutely but but it's just it's just not no i know i know it's just there's
a lot of there's a lot of kind of rather and then there's kind of some horrible so one of the things
that's really good about this is that it doesn't shy away from the appalliness of the setup and
there's some lots of stuff that is horrible in lots of different ways and i did quite like that
dichotomy but then there'd be kind of a joke that you were clearly expected to find funny and i was
like oh this is like those films that people like that i don't think are funny so i think it is
reasonable point out that because i read the ebooks which are what available to me i may not have read
exactly the same book as john and allison because i cannot oh no also i read the ebook i'm sorry i
didn't read the paper book i should have said that earlier because i think it is specifically the
paper book and i think there are differences yes so for those who don't know the paper book you
you can't buy the edited by an editor book as an e-pub but no so the e-pubs are the e-pubs matt
dinamon retains the rights and does those himself and then the traditionally published books have
gone through like an editor and a publisher and all of these things but you can't buy the text of
the physical books as an e-book and i don't know how much they differ um the version that was
submitted to the clerk is specifically the the english physical copy and usually that doesn't
matter but here it does yeah so this is the thing i don't know because i you know i read it over
i read it about a year ago now and i remember i enjoyed it and i enjoyed enough to pick the series
as a whole but i would say the first one is still quite rough around the edges and i wonder how much
of the rough around the edges stuff has been uh sanded out by the editor so it is a little hard
for me to give an exact take on this i haven't read the epub so i don't have a i i have the
opposite problem. Yes, that's saying I don't know if anyone has read both or if there is a direct
comparison. It's the same with like, spoiler, there is no antimemetics division where we previously
discussed that there are like multiple versions, but the older version remains online. And so you
can go and take a look. I don't have access to both. But that's it. I wonder if that has trimmed
down some of the lengthier bits, probably remove some of the jokes that don't land, etc. Like there
is stuff in that that I would expect an editor to edit out. It would be really interesting to see
the differences and then see if his editor deserves a best editor you go nomination if you ever wanted
to know what people do for their best editor noms do you have anything else liz i do not just say
if you want more dungeon crawler carl chat uh i discussed it on episode 147 the next book is the
dream hotel by leila lamy which is about it's about a woman who has some dreams the government
find problematic and so they lock her in a school for a bit and it's it's about kind of american
government it was not even specifically american it's about kind of dystopian government and um
your rights as a person and that kind of thing what did we think of this one so this one i liked
but didn't love i think because to me it didn't feel particularly a fresh concept it's i mean i
know you said it's not specifically american and i don't think it's specifically american but it is
kind of like if I extrapolated out in a straight line from like the current state of things about
five or maybe 10 years you could get to this book and it felt like the the one big idea it has is
this idea that not only are they kind of screening you for pre-crime but they are screening your
dreams because everyone has machines that help you sleep which turn out to have a license agreement
that lets them look at all your dreams and I thought that was its really big thing but otherwise
it felt like a well done sort of near future dystopia but I didn't particularly have it stand
out as a near future dystopia that made me want to spend lots of time there and maybe that is also
personal thing in that if I was choosing books to read I probably would not at this point be reading
near future dystopia I can't say it's a bad book but I can say it's not a book I particularly
engaged with so I really like this book Liz has accurately summarized so half the science fiction
concept is the same as the one in the minority report which is a classic work of science fiction
that was made into a classic movie the other half is indeed this kind of dream harvesting thing
but none of those although those are the premise of the novel none of it is actually used to direct
any of the plot which is in fact a novel about what it's like to be detained without charge in
a for-profit prison which is allowed to make additional profits by extending the length of
your stay and all of that is something that is happening right now in the United States so it
felt to me like all of that was not actually science fiction at all and the science fictional
bits are kind of tacked on around the edges but it's not really what the novel's about so um
liked enjoyed it immensely loved reading it um I think the ending's got there's a bit of a fairy
tale aspect to the ending but I think it's fine and I really really like this novel um but again
And this is the one where it's like, is it really science fiction?
But anyway, this one did land for me.
Really liked it.
I found it very realistic that the United States finally realizes they need to do something about gun violence.
And instead of banning guns, they enact this massive dystopian system that lets them do future crime and thought crime.
I thought that was an inflection point I found very believable.
Worryingly so in some ways.
I thought I should also mention one of the things I thought was interesting about this book is that if you want to...
implement pre-crime and lock people up in order to reduce gun violence.
It's interesting, this novel focuses on a woman to whom this happens to and a woman's
detention centre, because in fact, 97% of the people who you would want to lock up in reality
would be men. So that's a thing. And it's interesting.
Yeah, so that's the thing, right? Like, it's not kind of extrapolation to say that
the legislative forces in the US would do anything rather than just actually ban weapons because
that's what they do. I did think it was very well written in, you know, there's some very
atmospheric bits. The main character is an immigrant. And so the parts where she is like
describing how that she gets the benefit of like automated screening at airports because she no
longer has to interact with the immigration officers. And then of course, this one time
she comes through and they do actually arrest her. I think it's kind of like the thing that she's
no one was always lurking and then she had sort of appreciated this technology taking that away
and then it comes back is kind of a really interesting perspective on it and it is also
a novel of climate change in the foreground there's some wildfires there's also a lot of other kind of
you know effects of climate change going on which i thought were pretty neatly done the blending in
of the climate change aspects i think is good yeah yeah really enjoyed it very glad i read it i do
think there are so that the there was one point where it sort of shifts perspective abruptly i
like that no i didn't think that really worked i would prefer to keep it on the kind of tight
perspective we had and have them figure out this is the first um near future dystopian novel by this
author but i'd like to read other things that that she's written next up we have luminous by sylvia
park which is about trauma and about how to be who you are i think chiefly what did we think of this
Shall I go first? This is my favourite book of the six. I really, really liked it. I mean, it has everything I liked. And I kind of knew as soon as I started, I was like, oh, yeah, you know, it's got some multiple perspectives. It's got some robots. It's got lots of questions about identity and where robots stop and how personality gets passed from robot to robot.
and it's Sylvia Park's first novel.
It's not entirely coherent all of the time
because parts of it were originally written as a young adult novel
and then it had extra bits glommed onto it that weren't young adulty.
Some of the stitching still shows a bit,
so bits of the novel are different in tone.
Did John do enough of a summary of that?
I hope not.
We have various viewpoints from a woman who is extremely good at robotics and has designed herself a robot lover.
We have her brother who was very injured in a war and has been largely reconstructed.
But, you know, he's 72 percent, 72 percent robotic.
And we also have a young girl who has a degenerative disease and is being kind of kept together by exoskeletons, but who would really like to be 72% robotic.
And she finds a robot playmate in a junkyard, which is, I think, the beginning of the episode thing.
And they're the perspectives.
And then they're all obviously linked together in various big and small ways.
And I love this novel.
So much what I want my science fiction to be like, guys.
That might be another boomer thing.
Well, I picked it in episode 143,
and I know that I did not read it at the time when I picked it.
Sorry, I obviously should do better at reading Liz's picks.
The Reckoning.
Yeah.
But yeah, I also liked it.
I think what I said at the time is it basically feels like
novels which are kind of like, oh, robots.
How human are they?
How much like people are they?
The blurring of the lines, not super new,
but I think this one does it in,
it has enough of its own perspective on it.
And there's things like it is set in Korea.
It's in a unified Korea.
And that is part of the background of the novel.
I think like one of the plots,
so, you know, June is a trans man
who has ended up having kind of bionic implants
that make him more masculine
than he could have otherwise achieved. And that's a kind of a really interesting conceit I don't
think I've seen done before. I think it's very solid concrete first novel. I would like to see
what else they do. And yeah, I enjoyed it. Oh, I don't know if it's my favourite, the six. I haven't
picked a favourite yet, though. We'll carry on. Interesting. Now, I think the point you made about
June being a trans man is that's one of the bits I really like about the book. I think in general,
the book does a really good job of contextualizing the questions it has in the reactions of its
characters and i think the very best science fiction takes the conceit and examines conceits
through human lenses to arrive at different conclusions and i think both luminous and the
dream hotel do that very well do you want to try and explain there is no antimemetics division john
Oh, I don't remember, Liz.
Okay, so, There Is No Anti-Memetics Division is a book about an adorable pet and a man who follows it about.
I am regretting agreeing to this with John.
There Is No Anti-Memetics Division is a book in two parts.
The first part follows Marie Quinn, who is an extraordinarily competent and talented agent working for a mysterious organization.
And then the second half follows her husband, Adam Quinn, as he gets up to shenanigans.
I don't want to spoil it.
It's kind of got shades of the laundry files by Charlie Strass back when they were a bit more.
I think it's got shades of the peak of the Laundry Files series.
I think I've probably said that on the podcast.
I think I've probably said that on the podcast before.
Yeah, it is.
It is basically like peak Charlie Strass when it still had the power to kind of make me go,
oh, wow, this is pretty mind-blowing science fiction.
Yeah.
I don't think it's, you know, I don't think the prose is as nice as the Lallami or Sylvie Park.
But in a way, it doesn't matter.
Because I was just like reading it going, oh, yes.
This is extrapolating exactly what I want it to extrapolate. Please continue.
Yeah, I don't want to spoil it. I did enjoy this a lot. I'm not entirely sure I understand the
ending. I think I got all of it, nearly all of it in the end. You have to work quite hard with this
one. Makes you think a lot. If you'd like to know more of our discussion, you can go back to episode
153. Yes. Where I picked it. I was going to say, we've also discussed it. It has repeatedly come up
since then as well so like there have been reference to this peppered through the the podcast um since
we first discussed it anything else on anti-memetics no just yes as we said this is another one where
it was self-published first and then eligible for luck when it got a full paperback uk publication
yes it has a very interesting publishing history because it started as a post or a series of posts
on a kind of X-Files-like wiki.
It's all quite strange.
All of that has been taken out of the novel
before the version of it that you see,
or it has been replaced by a fictionalised version of it.
Yeah, but here we are judging from the published version,
not the previous website version.
Then we have When There Are Wolves Again by E.J. Swift.
This is a book about two women.
It kind of follows them as they progress through time.
One is a documentary filmmaker and the other is a conservationist.
The other has a variety of facets and it's difficult to distill her down into one of them.
And they sort of keep just missing each other through time.
And this is a book about what will happen when King Charles dies.
Yeah.
I think it's also an overshoot novel, but Neil can write in and correct me if I'm wrong.
Yeah, I've just been describing this as a damp novel about wolves.
I mean, it's okay. I thought it was okay. It's got some nice bits in it. There's some bits that
are quite optimistic in some ways, in a way that I think is not sufficiently justified by the text.
you're kind of like, oh, yes, so this is going to happen, right? And how does the money work?
The answer is it doesn't. It doesn't make any sense. It's fine. You know, it's pleasant enough
to read. It's okay. You know, it's the sort of book I would like, but I would like it to be doing
a lot more than it actually does. Oh, I like this one a lot more than Alison.
I would have picked it except it was the time when I was not picking 2025 books.
I really like it's kind of, it feels, yeah, okay, the finances don't work.
But I mean, it feels like a kind of at least semi-interesting to think about
way in which we can build a more optimistic, brighter future.
But in a kind of fairly, told through some fairly small and domestic episodes,
which I really liked.
I love the beginning, which is like any novel which sort of begins with a plague,
except then you realise at this point the plague is COVID-19, which is very well done.
Yeah, I think some bits of it are implausible.
This was a pick for my book group and we had a good long argument about whether
the bit with what happens after Charles dies is at all realistic.
And I was like, maybe not, but I'm going to go with it because I'm kind of enjoying where this is going.
It felt like a sort of small-scale domestic version of a Kim Stanley Robinson novel.
Yeah, that's actually a really good way of framing it. It had a lot in common with Ministry for the Future for me.
It fits into a tradition of English cosy catastrophe novels as well, so it is one of them.
I think it's tricky because I take your point about the money, but I also kind of feel like if we can't fix the planet because there's not enough money, we might as well just kill ourselves now.
so I'm kind of glad the authors are exploring how we might go around the more optimistic version
it is it is quite an optimistic novel in lots of ways and it is nice every I mean I quite enjoyed
E.J. Swift's previous novel The Coral Bones which I think was also nominated for the clerk
and I think maybe I like that slightly more but I think this is I mean I enjoyed all of the I
enjoyed reading it all the way through and then I got to the end and I was like oh yeah okay is
that all we get i mean i i did enjoy this novel when i read it and i think i will keep reading
ej swift who i think has a lot to offer here you know a very exciting author and and it's delightful
to read the characters are great i love the way that it it kind of takes them most of the way
through their lives in in a pretty plausible way you know they're old women at the end of the book
and i think that's great yeah it's also um it's dedicated to christopher priest and nina allen
which is sweet. And then the final
book, The Salt Oracle by
Lorraine Wilson, which is about
the kidnap
and abuse of a child on a
on a
on an oil rig, effectively
including certain
details of the plot. The final
the sixth. I mean this is
basically a riff on the ones
who walk away from Omelas but with more
academic infighting. Yes.
To do a John style.
She says it's a dark academia book.
Yeah, so I did like this.
The main problem is that in order to properly appreciate it,
I read the kind of linked prequel novel,
We Are All Ghosts in the Forest first, which I like more.
I shouldn't have done that.
I think it stands alone.
I think it does, but I chose to do that, which is fine.
But then unfortunately, it does mean that I didn't find this one quite as good
because I really liked the We Are Ghosts in the Forest.
and then I read this and was like don't like it quite as much but so I did not know this was uh
the second novel in the universe and I got about 10 pages in and I was like I am hopelessly not
this must be the second novel in the universe and went and googled and of course it is and then I
but to be very clear it doesn't need it there's one scene in this book that relies on the previous
book and it's about halfway through okay it is a standalone novel but my assertion is if you
had read the previous one there's a bunch of stuff that would have been introduced to you more
gradually which when you read this one you are dropped in and it's not actually the most
transient it's not the most lucid novel anyway so that really made it quite a hard the first 50 pages
hard and then I got to about halfway through and I noticed I was still at that state where I'd read
a page or two and then I'd go oh maybe I could check my phone I mean novels don't have to be
repulsive but I didn't have any problem reading any of the others of these six and this one I really
found hard to read I just kept putting it down over and over and over again I think it's okay
you know it's she has a great sense of place and really gives you a really immerses you in this
in this horrific oil rig academic nut house thing but I think she's got a lot of characters and I
don't think they're very well delineated um i think it's possibly the most boring book i've ever read
where somebody dies every few pages you know i i want if it's going to be a thriller it should be a
bit more thrilling so this was the other one that was not for me but i again i can see why people
like it and there's lots to like here and that i thought your summary was completely right it is
about the kidnap and abuse of a girl that's what it's about yeah so i i mean i don't think this is
totally not for me but i also found it to be a little draggy at times i was getting a bit
yeah a bit like okay and then then you're right it's kind of like it seems like not a huge amount
of stuff is happening and then someone dies and because i didn't know most of the characters who
died that well it doesn't have as much effect as like the first person to die in the first 50 pages
it's so spoilers anyway, but it's kind of the main character's kind of mentor slash teacher.
And that death has kind of more effect than when someone dies at page like 300,
who we supposedly spent 300 pages with, because I don't think they were as well fleshed out as
this one kind of character was through the perspective of another in about 10 pages.
So that was kind of interesting. Yeah. So I just feel that like, it felt like we kind of have a
scene and then i'd be like well but we had a scene that kind of did a very similar thing before i do
think that it's like the writing is very nice especially from the perspective of the the girl
the salt oracle of the title um although it's hard to figure out what's going on until quite later on
but i think you do you do kind of figure out what is happening in her sections but it just didn't
quite grab me enough and in terms of science fiction it's you know sort of science fiction
The core science fictional concept is that the world has collapsed and all the data is roaming around as ghosts of electromagnetic bits of code.
I guess that's a bit fantasy for my science fiction, but I'm prepared to weather it.
Yeah, I'm pretty with it, but I thought it was done more interestingly in the other one because then there's a lot of stuff about like going back to natural remedies and how natural are these remedies or is it just, you know, science in a different form.
I thought that had a more interesting discussion of that, whereas here it's kind of more about you just kind of take that for granted.
And then there's some stuff that happens later on where you have to go, OK, yeah, I guess that's how digital ghosts work in this world.
I'll go with it.
But you're not reading it for the, you know, plausible science fiction-ness of it.
Right.
So there we've been quite nice and then sometimes a bit mean about John's six favourite science
fiction novels of the year.
So...
Yes, obviously, this is the six favourite books of all five judges speaking unanimously.
So yeah, some books, hopefully thought-provoking, interesting books.
Are you going to give us a bit of a mini peek behind the curtain, John?
What you can tell us?
Well, do you have any questions?
So I think people who listen to the podcast might want to know a little bit about how the clock works.
So how many books were submitted this year?
It was in the range of 130.
Yes, there's 130 books and they are submitted.
The submissions tend to start about usually just after Worldcon.
I don't think that's on purpose, but that's like when it starts gearing up.
The nominal deadline is the end of December.
And I guess they're submitted by publishers.
So there's always questions when some things don't appear on the shortlist.
You kind of go, oh, and of course it might not have been submitted.
And we don't necessarily know what was submitted.
There isn't a list of everything submitted, is there?
Yeah, there is.
There will be, but not yet this year.
No, so there's a Clark Awards substack and there's a Clark Award medium.
different things get posted in different places and i find the approach of the clark award to
information dissemination more opaque than i would like but yes so the medium has the complete
judges reading list for the arthur c clark award 2025 and that was posted last year 10 days before
the 10 days before the shortlist announcement so if if that happens again this year listeners i will
try and remember to put it as a link in the show notes but last year the number was 112 so this
year has been an uptick it gone from 112 to about 130 if i recall correctly yeah and it's good to do
that because sometimes the answer is to to why is thing i really like not in the shortlist is
wasn't submitted yep not everything gets submitted there are i think and we can ask like the judges
if they spot something hasn't been submitted we can be like oh can you encourage that company to
submit this thing because we think they've missed it but like obviously it is eventually up to the
publisher it's not up to the Clark Award itself what is in contention because it is a an open
submission process you pay your money you send your books and it's it's submitted unless they
break the rules in which case I think they can disqualify things for rule breaking last year I
believe there was a book that was disqualified because it was a tie-in novel to a media franchise
which is explicitly prohibited by the clerk rules why that's a great question okay ask
i think there might be a feeling that the number of books the judges have to consider in a given
year is already quite high and allowing media tie-ins would inflate that number and it's possible
that it wouldn't inflate it with many truly excellent examples of science fiction but it
did mean i wasn't allowed to advocate for any adrian tchaikovsky warhammer 40 000 novels and
that was sad yeah i mean i think the thing is this does not you've got to set a cutoff somewhere
and if that cuts out like potentially like an extra 150 especially maybe from sorry i'm googling at
the same time and therefore causing problems if that cuts out you know there might be publishers
who publish like a hundred different science fictional tie-in novels and so that is a sensible
cut off to place but you might occasionally miss stuff that you think is really
Clark worthy well I mean I guess I'd like to know if it's an award for science fiction novels
and and requiring things to be both science fiction and a novel rather than a a novel length
excerpt from a longer work that absolutely does not stand alone
and who gets to decide this one alice i know i'm i know i'm i'm i'm definitely not the it is
explicitly an award for novels and it is in the gift of the jury to decide what is a novel that's
completely fine and it is also in the gift of the jury to decide what is science fiction but like i
would argue for instance deep wheel orcadia which won in 2022 is definitely not a novel yeah it is
a poem or a novella yep yep and yet it won and i think it was a worthy winner there is a kind of
argument here about whether something feels like a short novel or a long novella which gets into
very different you could define it as a strict word count thing like the hugo does i i don't
think the clerk wants to define these things in quite that rigid a way and i'm i'm happy for the
clerk to define their things yeah i'll i'll be a little bit sad if dungeon crawler cole wins
but if it does win i'll um i'll read the paper book just read the next seven it's fine
i'm i'm basically fine for the clerk to do this and also that they have to try and keep it
manageable and numbers of submissions are going up and that you have to at least you know maybe
draw a line somewhere but it does seem a bit sad that you get you go you might get edge cases that
cause problems and worthwhile books are not on the list but there's probably always going to be a
worthwhile book that did not get submitted so it's the best of the ones that get submitted yes and so
do you just do two years as judge john are you stopping now you can't do more than two years
there are occasional judges that have but i think it is like that is an exception rather than a rule
that the rule is that judges do two terms they don't have to be consecutive so i did two in a row
but like the other judge so when i was judging last year the other judge that was in their first
year was gene rowe and he took a step back this year but like he could do it again in the future
i knew because of having done it it's quite a lot of work um and the one of the frustrating things
is that although tom and andrew do a good job of preparing you for certain aspects of how the award
works there are aspects that are things you have to learn for yourself as you're going through
and I think like even though Nick Clark who was a judge last year had tried to kind of warn me about
some of that or maybe not warn me but like tell me about some of that I think it's difficult to
take it on board until you've actually experienced it and so I wanted to do it this year because I
understood the way it worked a lot better experientially and I thought I could do a better
job this year than I did last year which I'll say I did a bad job last year but I thought I could do
it to a more self-satisfaction this year. I think I have done that. And also, I think chiefly,
the thing I realized is that you've got to be repeatedly telling the other judges the books
that you're reading that you think are great. You can't read in a vacuum. It's got to be a
continuing discussion, which might seem like an obvious statement, but I don't think I'd quite
internalized it the first time through. So there are a couple that I really loved that I did not
persuade my fellow judges were worthy of consideration and like i've picked a bunch
of books from last year on this podcast now listeners you can probably have a stab at which
ones those were but this year i think i've done a better job of highlighting if if one of my
sort of bays doesn't get to the final six it's not because the other judges were unaware of it
well i mean obviously i think it's clear that some of your bays won't get to the final six
because everyone else will also have bays.
I mean, all these books are worthy.
And then you've heard here that Liz and I have wildly differing opinions on them.
Yeah.
When also like, especially like, there's also more than six books I thought were great.
So that is also hard.
I think we've got, there's like 19 novels between the Hugos and the Nebulas and the Clark this year.
So that's a lot of novels.
Yeah, I mean, there's some differing eligibility, right?
Fantasy, notably.
Well, I think the Swift and the Wilson possibly are not published in the US yet.
Oh, yes.
I think the Swift might be a 2026.
I'm not sure about Salt Oracle.
And Dungeon Crawler Carl, it depends on your eligibility,
because if you were going by e-book eligibility, it was years ago.
Yeah.
So Dungeon Crawler Carl was published for the first time in the UK in 2025.
So it's eligible for the 2026 Clark.
Oh, yes, of course, that's true.
Was that the only volume published in 2025?
Or could they have sent you multiple volumes?
They could have sent multiple, but they did not.
And they quite reasonably felt that if they, you know,
they submitted the first one and they were like submitting two and three,
it's unlikely that they're going to pick number three, I guess was the logic.
Liz, you've read all of those, haven't you?
Well, I've not read the eighth one yet because I was busy reading for this podcast.
But is it a reasonable assumption that if you didn't like number one,
you're probably not going to like number four?
um yes but it depends why you didn't like number one like i think they do get more polished i think
the like they get more complex i think the jokes get less like self-consciously jokey i think if
you don't like princess donut in book one you're probably not gonna suddenly love princess donut
who is the cat but i think she gets a lot more kind of depth and a surprising you know amount of
emotion behind essentially what in the first book is a bit more of a talking cat joke.
I was hoping you were going to say, well, she gets killed off at the end of book three,
which would be a good reason to read book four.
I think if you're hoping that the cat dies, you should probably not read the rest of the books.
Look, if I said there's a surprisingly moving moment involving a goat person in one of the
later books, then that tells you where we're at.
I'm sure there can be moving moments. There were lots of things that were interesting and
and then kind of just left as dangling storylines for the other volumes what's interesting is my
impression from reading i've not so i've not read books two through eight yet although i have got
book two on my bookshelf but i understand from reading reading other people reporting on reading
interviews with him because i actually read the interviews myself but he is a pantser not a plotter
oh no oh god but the people are like there's lots of threads coming back later where he's like well
just let that dangling i didn't know what i was going to do with it but then i did this with it
and people are like well it's very coherent and so i'm interested to see how that goes i'm interested
to because that's one of the things like i remember i was playing a role play once and i did a plot
and i realized towards the end of one of the sessions that the person two of my players had
decided to start working for someone and the other two players had decided to take a bounty on someone
and i realized towards the end of the session oh these are the same person and my players were like
did you plan that all along?
And I was like, no, I realized it 10 minutes ago,
but it was awesome.
Yes.
And I think actually, if you're going to write a book,
which is lit RPG,
doing it that way where the plot can come emergently
from playing in the world as a writer,
I think is a really good, probably a really good approach.
And so I'm interested to see how that comes about.
But yeah, I'm interested to see how the series unfolds.
But I haven't read any of the others yet
because I have been diligently avoiding contaminating my Clark Award judgment with
subsequent stuff. Future knowledge.
Yeah, I try as much as I can to treat every book as its own work rather than trying to read around
the context because I think, and obviously that's a personal decision, that's not mandated,
not every judge will do it that way, but I think for me it helps me consider the book as a standalone
rather than as part of a wider thing.
I think that's good.
But you had previously read the other Lorraine Wilson, though.
Yes, that's unavoidable because that was eligible last year.
But it wasn't a finalist, I think?
No, it wasn't.
It's a very British list, isn't it?
So that's one of the reasons there's no overlap with the other awards.
It's sort of, I mean, the second half's quite British.
The first half is a Korean American, a Moroccan American and an American American.
Yeah, but the...
Okay, so three of the novels are set in the UK.
Two of the novels are set in the UK, right?
No, obviously two of them are set in the UK and the other is set in the Baltic,
in an environment that's going to be a lot more familiar to UK readers than to US ones, I'd say.
Yeah, probably.
There's a bunch of...
One of the things I didn't say about the Lorraine Wilson earlier is there's a bunch of stuff
that reminded me of the shipping forecast in this book.
High praise.
Yeah.
North at Syria rising.
I mean, I very much like the idea that she's written a book about
the crash has happened.
There's also references that we had, like the climbing tipping point.
And she has set it in like the Baltic
with a cast of mostly Finnish, Estonian and Russians,
rather than setting it in the UK or the US.
I think it's interesting.
I think you probably have a whole discussion about,
Because Lorraine Wilson is a Scottish author, I think you could have quite a wide-ranging discussion about Scotland and its relationship to the Nordic countries culturally, because I think there is a link there.
And I think that is a Scottish aspect to things.
No, it is a very interesting novel, I should say.
There's lots to talk about there.
I just didn't enjoy reading it.
I mean, I'm very glad to have read it.
feels to me a bit like there's a really interesting novel that's sort of kind of wedged into this
academia thing that i didn't think worked as well for me intriguing okay so that's the clark award
listeners and so when's that's the other thing is when is the announcement when is the big ceremony
john the winner will be announced on wednesday the 12th of august 2026 um i hope everyone who
goes has a lovely time i will be being flabbergasted by a total solar eclipse in northern spain so i
will not be able to attend but i hope everyone else has a lot of fun i will also be watching
the total solar eclipse from northern spain a different bit of northern spain from john i think
i wonder if anyone else will be in spain for the eclipse that day there's got many potential
autothop listeners please write in if you're going to be in a different bit of northern spain
there's a lot of Spain
yes
the eclipse is going
all across Spain
Spain's quite big
really big
you wouldn't believe
just how mind-bogglingly
big it is
especially when you see
the tapas Liz
because that's really
small by comparison
also I know at least
one person is going
to Iceland
going to Iceland
you go to Iceland
for this eclipse
or you can go
on a cruise
in the Atlantic
right
for the eclipse
and that was
the Octothor podcast
and it's goodbye
from me
it's goodbye
and it's goodbye from me
but wait we didn't predict a winner
oh right no hang on yes we've got to predict a winner
i'm not going to predict the winner guys
what do you think will win
no you probably shouldn't predict a winner oh i don't know if we could predict a winner i can
say which one i it's got to be it's got to be mimetic anti-mimetics well you've got to do which
one you think should win and which which one you think might win my favorite book was luminous
anti-mimetics division ran it quite close i think there is no anti-mimetics division will win but i
could be wrong i think i think my favorite is probably there is no antimemetics division
but i think i think when there are wolves again will win fair enough there you go i'm trying to
second guess the judges let's see how we do predictions the theme music for this episode
was fanfare for space by kevin mcleod and compotech.com used under a creative commons
attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.