Hi everyone, it's editor John here, just a couple of quick notes before we get into the
episode. Firstly, if you took any photographs of me or Alison or Liz or any combination
thereof, we would very much appreciate it if you would email them to comment@octorbcast.uk.
Secondly, thank you very much to Ian Clark for the beautiful cover art this episode. We
invited Ian to do a cover for us when the best fan artists, finalists were announced.
We got chatting at Worldcon, he was like, "I'm really sorry I never got back to you."
I was super stressed out because I was designing the Hugo base and I was like, "That is absolutely
understandable." And then he sent me photographs of the prototypes and with his permission,
we are using them as the beautiful cover art this week. Thank you very much everyone and
see you on the other side.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 117th episode of Octothorpe, a podcast for Science
Fiction and Science Fiction fandom, which is coming to you on the 29th of August 2024.
I'm John Coxon, I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
And as ever, we start with letters of comment. Thank you very much to everyone who congratulated
us after the Hugo's, it was very lovely and it was lovely to see you all.
Several of our friends actually wrote their reports and comments on the Worldcon that
seeing us with a Hugo was an absolute delight, a particular joy of the Worldcon and that
was really nice to see. So thank you. And apparently, and we did not know this, a huge
cheer went up in the fad bar when we were announced. That was nice too. That links into
our next topic, which is, "We want a Hugo." But you know, it was very nice of everyone
to congratulate us on Sunday and Monday, including the security guard at the SEC who
had to check my back with a Hugo in congratulating before it. That was nice.
That was good.
Oh yes, so the security guard at the SEC did congratulate Siva on did Hugo, because he
was carrying my Hugo when we went through security.
I'd like to take this opportunity to formally congratulate Siva on his Hugo and I invite
him to write in and tell us all about it.
You'd have to listen to the podcast first, wouldn't you?
Yeah, we also heard specifically from Renee. So Renee is from Lady Business.
We should say this letter is pre- I was winning the Hugo. This is way back from July because
we haven't done letters of comment for a while.
We have not done letters of comment for a little bit on a counter how we are bad at
podcasting, but also on a counter how there was that time we did the 70 minutes on the
business meeting and it turns out there wasn't a lot of extra time in that episode and then
we did a live episode and we weren't very focused.
So Renee from Lady Business sent us an email on the 21st of July, 2024, which is about six
weeks ago when you listened to this. She said she had a thought about our thoughts about
recusal.
The reason Lady Business recused after our first win for the next year but not the year
after was because of Renee's theory of voting momentum. Once you've won a Hugo, it's potentially
easier to win again in the next year because of name recognition and familiarity that builds
for each consecutive win until you end in a person who has won the award 900 times place.
The idea of her was to break up the momentum of the name recognition for a year just in
case.
And then she goes on to say there's a likely an argument for permanent recusal in some
cases. She says she will save her loud opinions on that for another day. Send us your loud
opinions Renee. We'd love it. But one year recusal and courage of voters to look elsewhere
and past winners can use it as an opportunity to advocate for their peers. Win, win, win.
And so we didn't announce this on stage but we will be recusing at least for next year's
Hugo Awards. Please go and nominate other fantastic fan casts including but not limited
to Hugo Girl who are the best.
We will be recommending hopefully highlighting interesting podcasts in this space all year.
I have a little bit of form here because Plochter won the Hugo in 2005 and I don't think there
was a habit of recusing. There were some people who'd like won whole shelf falls of
Hugo's at that point but there wasn't this kind of habit of people recusing in the fan
categories. And we won again much to our surprise in Los Angeles in 2006 and I think it is exactly
that. It was Hugo Momentum. It was people going, "Oh, I hadn't seen this fanzine. I'll look
at it now. I like it. I will vote for it." And if it had been the popular fashion to recuse
for a year, we probably would have done that.
Yeah, I was going to say Renee as well as being one of the people behind the giant Hugo
spreadsheet that we use regularly when we're discussing potentially Hugo-nominating works
which we love.
It's also going to be on the Stitch and Bit show to talk about the Hugo in 2024 and that
is another podcast. Well, I think it's a video podcast which was in the long list for 2024
so you can go and start there.
We will have a link in the show notes. So Liz and I are in charge of the blue sky and
Mastodon respectively. Liz, do you want to say anything about how many new followers we
got after we won a Hugo?
Some?
Yeah, the Mastodon because obviously no one really uses Mastodon which is why I love it.
We got multiple new followers and I was like, "Oh, this is that thing where you win a
Hugo." And I was like, "Oh, hang on. They must actually be all right then. I should
give them a try and I haven't really given them a try up to now." And so, yeah, I think
recusing for a year like Renee says, I can see it was really noticeable that the pattern
changed. It didn't change loads but there was a noticeable effect. So I found that interesting
because I wasn't really expecting it despite the fact if I sat down and thought about it,
I probably would have been.
If anyone is listening to us for the first time or the second time, if you're welcome,
traffic to the plot to website doubled in 2005 after we won the Hugo.
It's got a nice...
So if you're a new listener, I'm sorry, we're always like this. Sometimes we're worse.
Have a look at our Wistful Business Meeting again. So did you say it was our second most
downloaded episode ever, John?
Yeah.
People liked the business meeting content.
Some people.
Look, right, we're pivoting to the all business meeting, all the time listeners.
No, we are not.
It's our new brand.
Oh, okay, YouTube can and I will go find...
We've found Alison's line. I've never found it before but it's here.
John can use the previously stored after Alison and Liz quit cover.
Our most listened episode is episode 102. I fully comprehend the mysteries and that's
where we broke down everything that happened in Chengdu and what was going on and why.
Episode 115, I like the way Glasgow did it, has a solid hundred more than our third most
downloaded episode.
We've got an email from Doug Font and he says, "Since you ordered the show about the
upcoming business meeting, I'd like to hear your taken explanation of the results."
Thanks, Doug.
Now, we will at some point do a very brief summary of the business meeting and how it
went.
We're going to mention one aspect of it this episode but the minutes are not up yet and
we're going to wait for the official minutes before we do it.
Keep your eyes and ears peeled, Doug.
And for everyone who is like, "I don't want to hear more about the business meeting,"
we're really sorry, blame Doug.
In a lovely way, thank you, Doug.
Okay, and we're going to leave the rest of the letters until later.
As Alison says, we're always like this but the live episode will reveal that when we're
tired and excited, we're even more like this.
I would like to apologise for the fact that Liz maybe got forwards in the entire episode
because I'm usually better at making sure but I would do the edit and I was like, "Oh,
God, there's not a lot of this in this one."
Sorry to all the Liz fans out there.
Yeah, I was like, you two were so like, cheery and happy and fun.
It's like, I don't want to interject with seriousness but you were very hard to control
in any way.
It's like, well, it's good.
It's like, how do I know I don't have ADHD?
[laughter]
Exhibits A and B.
I was really like, is this going to go in the podcast?
And now it's definitely going in the podcast.
Okay, brilliant.
I should say again that I do not have a diagnosis and I want to respect the people
who do have a diagnosis.
I merely have some characteristic, I occasionally display some characteristics that are shared
by people with ADHD.
This is my new way of introducing the three of us which is I have an ADHD diagnosis,
Alison does not have an ADHD diagnosis and Liz does not have ADHD which is, I think,
factually and accurate and conveys the idea.
And you can put that as the subhead of this episode.
But we made that joke last time, John.
Did we?
Excellent.
Okay.
So, the first thing I want to say is that I have an ADHD diagnosis.
I very much enjoyed having the discord up in the live pod.
I do think it's fun, but I also want to know if I need to ban you too from looking at
it because you cannot.
I can't look at it much.
You started posting ribbons to the live panel during the episode.
Oh no, I only posted a ribbon because I got shamed into having not posted a ribbon by
my co-editor.
I was not going to do it because I was not looking that closely at the discord because
I know what I'm like and John was like, "Oh, was it John or was it just..."
No, it was me.
It was me.
That is what I mean.
As I did, I just posted it into the entirely the wrong discord.
When I have had more sleep and less excitement, I am a little bit better at thinking about
keeping on track and that morning I was not good at it at all and I think it really shows.
And I had a lot of fun that morning, but it was not coherent.
I'm not sure if you go back and listen to our other live episodes that they are significantly
more coherent.
Maybe not.
Now I don't want to.
The one where we had you in a totally different room.
It wasn't an interjection from the room.
It was my face.
You had us in a totally different room?
No, the one where we put you in a totally different room because you had Covid was a bit
more because you couldn't get word in edways.
We had to be a bit more coherent then because we had to be very careful to bring you in
because obviously if one person is on a link.
Can I make a joke about winning my third Hugo now?
Yes.
So I am fond of three person collaborations.
They're very good and I won two previous Hugos with Steve Davis and Mike Scott for
Blocktor.
So I have a third of a Hugo for each of those and this time I have won a third of a Hugo
with John and Liz for Octa Thorpe.
So now I have an entire Hugo.
No, not over.
It's kind of how it works in my head.
I mean I respect that.
I have an entire Hugo all of my own.
I respect that very deeply.
I also have three rockets.
I don't think the trophy is the thing and I'm kind of, I have a mantelpiece which looks
great with two Hugos on it.
So I have a plot to Hugo and an octa Thorpe Hugo and now I have another plot to Hugo that's
kind of shuffled off to the side and I'm wondering if I should give it to another person who
was involved in plotter or auction it for the fan thumbs or flog it on eBay or something
of that kind which is kind of weird.
I haven't decided definitely yet but I think that's likely to be where it ends up.
This is exactly the opposite of all other, like all other cases because basically I think
Alison likes stuff more than I do and I'm like no, no stuff, no books, no nothing and
then my Hugo, no you will pry that from my cold dead hands.
Oh yeah, no that's how I felt about the 2005 one.
Never getting rid of the 2005 one.
Never getting rid of this one which is the first Hugo I have won for this project even
if John might have licked mine.
I didn't lick yours.
I licked mine.
But then at some point we put them all down on a table and then we think we picked up.
People kept moving them around and I was like actually it's like when you have a baby
right then you kind of want to go home from hospital with the same baby you gave birth
to but they keep moving the babies around and it's quite scary.
I mean I haven't left my baby on a table in the middle of a party so I have left a baby
in the bar famously but that was only once and I got them back fairly quickly.
You've got the same one back you can probably tell from conversations with said baby who
is now 24.
So Liz is Hugo arrived in the post.
Liz do you want to talk about your Hugo arriving in the post?
My Hugo arrived in the post.
I didn't want to carry it back because I already had a lot of luggage and not a very
large carry on bag and I was like do I want to put it in my suitcase where it might get
squashed or do I want to try and hand carry it through two sets of customs who were going
to say why are you carrying this big metal rocket and so I asked the con to ship it the
con did ship it it then got stuck in DHL for about 10 days because someone at DHL had
written down my phone number on and today it has arrived but they did make me pay duty
on it fortunately they have valued a Hugo at 50 pounds so the two two's were not too
bad.
Good.
I mean it's obviously prices but I think actually it's probably worth more than 50 quid.
Yeah the rocket must be and I don't know.
And I don't know what the rocket is made out of do either of you know I assume this is
known.
Yeah it's in Pete Western to think about it isn't it.
Chromium plated steel isn't it?
Yeah someone was asking and I was like is it aluminium and I was like cannot be aluminium
it's far too heavy to be aluminium.
Chromium plated steel but the exterior is chrome because it is basically a very large
good ornament.
I think we have mentioned this on the podcast but for new listeners Hugo's are all made
in the UK in a factory somewhere near Birmingham which is one of those things which is quite
lovely.
I can link again to the article about making Hugo's.
It never gets less interesting to me.
We also wanted to pick up something from the Hugo award live stream which is we read the
comments and this one which Alison posted in our group chat.
From Ultima Facts so if you're out there Ultima Facts Alison looks exactly like she
sounds but lol but John does not.
I'm curious like what do I sound like?
We do not understand this at all.
Do I sound like an old I kind of imagine I sound like a sort of 65 year old BBC presenter
from the 50s.
Is that it?
Oh and you should have a sweater vest and be presenting the 2M Open University things
about the planet.
Yeah.
Yeah exactly.
Do you mean a tank top?
No I mean a sweater vest.
That's a tank top.
I think in the modern usage of tank top I would not say that it's tonked up.
Yes no I understand that.
I believe this but you know if you're talking about the 50s then it was definitely a tank
top then.
And also how does Liz stack up with how Liz sounds?
That's the other thing I want to know.
How would you tell from listening to the podcast?
I'm not sure I want to know really.
Oh god we are so jazzed we need to I need to drink less coffee and chill a bit sorry
guys.
That's alright I think we are jazzed.
So we said we weren't going to go into the business meeting in very much detail this
episode but there is one thing that I absolutely have to talk about.
I'm just bursting which is that much against our advice the business meeting decided to
extend the eligibility for Godzilla minus one because it had been insufficiently distributed
and it had only limited distribution with their argument and it that passed.
And then on Sunday night of the Worldcon the long list of Hugo stats came out where it
turned out that Godzilla minus one had exactly the same number of first preference and
accommodations as poor things and very nearly made the ballot anyway.
Following this on the final day of the convention in a business meeting session that often
doesn't exist the business meeting decided to do a kind of timey wimey suspensiony wench
and a bit of magic and go back in time to the eligibility discussion and retroactively
decided it was not eligible after all.
So Godzilla minus one is not going to get a second vote at the Hugo's which is absolutely
the right decision and also the one they should have made in the first place without the benefit
of the stats in my view.
So there was a lot of discussion in the business meeting channel on the Worldcon Discord about
how you know maybe some of the nomination stats should be made available earlier or maybe
the whole stat should be released to the business meeting as a privileged thing so that these
decisions can be made with the full knowledge of what's happening and a man called John
Coxon remarked, "If only there was some way we could make decisions about eligibility
extensions without doing so at the Worldcon."
Some sort of virtual business meeting and Vice Chair Margarit Smith said, "John I'm
not sure your staring spoon is long enough shushing face emoji."
Fair. John there's a much better argument here which is stop making extended eligibility
arguments for things that made 30 million dollars.
Like this has never come up before right because normally we nominate something that got three
screenings.
Basically if you start extending the eligibility of things we've seen by lots of people then
this is going to happen so we could just stop doing that.
I'm going to say do not extend the eligibility of anything where they released it in December
specifically so it'll catch the award season.
They don't want the to get an award in 2025, they want to get an award in 2024, let them.
Right, I think I'm going to say two things there which is Godzilla-1 is a bad example
of that because of the exclusivity.
For those who don't know that American Godzilla films and the Japanese Godzilla films have
like an agreement where they can't be in cinemas at the same time and so Godzilla-1
came out of cinemas early to let Godzilla versus Kong be in cinemas.
I want a massive kaiju fight I am just saying.
But yeah, I mean I basically just think all of this, all of what we have just said, there's
no need to do it at the convention, there's no need to change how we release the stats
in order to make the business meeting happy, there's no need to extend the eligibility
of films that have made 30 million dollars, there's no need to extend the eligibility
of films that got wide cinema releases.
The correct decision was made and a lot of people are saying 'oh we need to change
how it works' it's like we don't.
I also want to say there were some very strange arguments, well to my goodness I perceive
a strange about how oh but Godzilla-1 was not in every market so I personally couldn't
see it.
Well, welcome to not living in the USA.
That is all the business meeting for this week listeners, there will probably be more
in the future at some point.
This episode we're going to, and probably next episode because we can't record next
week, so we're going to try and record a double and split up in some sort of thematically
sensible way.
But basically this episode we're going to talk about Worldcon.
So we sort of did talk about Worldcon at the live show but it was as previously mentioned,
quite a lot less coherent than it might otherwise have been, so we're going to try and have
some sensible and collected thoughts on how Glasgow 2024, a Worldcon for our futures,
went.
I was just about to type in the show notes, can I put a tiny overall thing in at the
beginning?
Yeah, do you want to discuss overall, the convention overall at the start and then dive
into specific themes afterwards?
Yeah, and as soon as we get into tiny little details, this has to hit us with a Liz Bat
and we'll go on to the themes.
No, no, no, no, Liz Bat.
So I wanted to say something about the Convention overall which is it was very big, it had a
huge number of people in person and also quite a lot of people online as well.
I think 600 online members and quite a lot of people who were attending but actually
came in online because they weren't actually at the convention.
So it was just enormous and I think overall the feeling and the ethos of the convention
was fabulous in a load of different ways.
I think Esther, Marguerite and Meg as Chair and Vice Chair did a wonderful job of setting
the scope of what they wanted the convention to feel like and I think by and large that
came off.
So we're going to, because we're a podcast and we commentate, we're going to carpal out
lots of things but I think we need to keep that in mind that they have 1,300 first time
world con attendees, 1,300.
I hope every single one of those, no, I hope 90% of those had a fabulous time and are like,
"Oh, what more conventions like this can I go to?"
And then I hope that that didn't work for quite everybody because if you work for everybody,
it indicates that you're not quite stretching your reach out, you want to encourage people
to come along who then go, "Oh, well, I've tried it once but it was me and I'm going
to do something else next."
That's because that is actually quite good too.
Oh, so that, so many good things.
They had so many first time attendees that they ran out of first time attendee ribbons
which is a good problem to have.
I think you're completely right.
I think this convention did a lot to bring people in and was just so, seemed so warm
and welcoming.
I don't know, as the convention goes on, it all bubbles to the surface and it's just
like this lovely, lovely feeling which I felt really good about.
In a way that I don't think previous world cons have achieved in the same way and I'm
not sure why but Glasgow definitely felt different to me right from the beginning.
I'm going to look at a little bit of credit to the Discord here because I think one of
things the Discord did was make it very clear in its introductions and newbies channel how
many people were coming from a long way away, were bringing different aspects of science
fiction fandom together.
Now, that is always the case at Worldcon but I think the fact that you had an introduction
page made it very obvious to lots of people including lots of old lags.
Yes.
It's a fancy new editor from Finland and here's a SF writer from India and all of that and
it was great.
Yeah, I don't know if I think it was specifically better than any other.
I mean, I think Finland had an awful lot of like enthusiastic first time world con goers.
It's just hard to know exactly how many.
So I was wondering like obviously we get stats break down for the locations on world con
pages.
But do we get stat breakdowns for like first time attendees and by gender and things like
that.
So let's go out of first world con membership, right?
So that's how you know.
I mean, one way you know is how many people bought a first world con membership.
I don't think I can drill down to that on their demographics page though.
Um, I haven't looked at it recently but I mean they did sell a specific.
What I will say is like, so we do know the number for Glasgow.
Like Alison said, it was somewhere in the region in 1300 but I guess it would be nice
to see world cons regularly break this statistic out so that we know.
I guess is what I'm saying.
Yes, I think the thing though is if you like we know that because there was a specific
category of membership they bought.
If you don't have that, then you have to start asking more questions during the membership
purchase process.
Yeah, no, that's fair.
And probably if we collect gender, we have to have some basis for why we are collecting
stats on people's gender.
Yeah, no, that's hard.
Which is protected information.
The age profile of the convention, I think European world cons tend to trend slightly
lower than US world cons but it felt like the age profile of the convention was quite
a lot younger than that than Chicon was and I don't suppose we know that either in the
demographic data.
But I think, I mean, I'm an old person and I think having lots of young people at the
world con is really, really good because it gives me hope that there will still be world
cons for me to go to where I am too old and frail to actually help run them in any way.
Do we know what the one body count was for Glasgow?
A touch over 7,000.
It is notable that that is bigger than Dublin and bigger than London and probably smaller
than Helsinki.
I think because Dublin was a bit more overcrowded, Dublin felt bigger but it's very hard to
live in between oh, there's 6,000 people in this building versus the 7,000 people in
this building.
It's a lot of people.
Glasgow never felt crowded because it had a lot of program space which it was putting a
lot of people into all of the time.
It was very noticeable.
I was in the dealers room.
It was very notable that in those 30 minute gaps between program items, the dealers were
filled up and then it went to what Ebbton flowed and that was because lots and lots
and lots of people were in program.
The toilet queues during the half hour changeover were sometimes horrendous.
Yeah, lots of toilets in hall 4 and 5, not so many on the con course.
That's probably not useful information until they do it again.
My impression is that Helsinki counted slightly differently so I am unsure how their numbers
compare and this is something conventions often do where it can get very difficult to
actually work out the same number for two conventions which is one of those things that
sounds daft but if you don't deduplicate in the same way you can arrive at different
conclusions.
It is way harder than you think to count this number even for quite small conventions it
can be quite difficult and for worldcones it's really hard.
I don't think Helsinki did, so there's a note on the long list.
Okay, so no, there is a big long list of conventions, workons and their attendances with lots of
footnotes.
We will link to it but it is also in your super near book if you have one.
It is also on the website not yet updated past 2021 so whoever is doing the website you
probably want to put some numbers on there.
Anyway it does say for worldcon 75 which was Helsinki, there are a lot of attending membership
sold at half price which was basically because they had a strong discount for first time
worldcon members and I think Glasgow had the same so I think that is a fair comparison.
Glasgow has gone through and deduplicated day memberships and the reason I say I think
Helsinki might have done it differently is I don't think Helsinki did that but I might
be wrong.
So Glasgow is deduplicated day memberships because that is quite important because Glasgow
you could buy five day memberships for Glasgow and it would be cheaper than a full attending
membership.
So yeah I think because the way gaming cons very often do it is they report just the total
number of days sold which is then gets really complicated because if you've got it's basically
just it's basically just a messlessness.
Yes so one of the reasons why people don't think our traditional SF conventions are very
large is that most of our members come for the entire weekend and we then compare ourselves
to gate shows which just count the number of emissions per day and so it looks like it's
for a worldcon it looks like it would be five times as big but of course it's not.
No it's probably something more like three times as big.
It is also worth noting that some gate shows do try to deduplicate so they will give you
the number of uniques which would be the equivalent of our attendees.
So where in overall does this sit?
I think it was almost certainly the fourth largest worldcon.
It's still pretty damn good like that's the thing right?
I don't know if I think that it's important to be biggest so I would argue that the number
of new attendees is more important than the number of total attendees because I think that's
the number that tells you more about the health of the community like and how we're growing
it.
Do we want to talk a little bit about registration and how it worked and and queues and back checks?
My registration was fine but I did it on Wednesday evening.
There were some queues at some times but I don't think they were massive.
The big queues were to get into the SEC because of bag checks every morning.
I don't particularly blame the SEC for having bag checks.
We did not have exclusive use of the site.
The badge checkers were always very nice to me.
There was one bag checker who was a bit RC but everyone else was lovely.
And there was at least one convention member that got banned from the SEC by deciding to
have a bit of a joke with a bag checker in a really daft way.
So don't do that.
If people want to check your bags, if people want to pat you down, it's like the cricket
right, you know, just understand that bag checks are part of what you do in order to
go into love, large events in the UK.
And also like everyone involved knows that they're not stopping anything but you just
don't say so and it's fine.
Like if they had properly been analyzing what people were bringing in, it would have been
a massive problem and they're not, they're doing it to appear that they are and we just
all need to be okay with that and move on with our lives because complaining about it
doesn't make it quicker.
They're discouraging people for bringing in beer and also weapons and even if they discourage
people a bit, I think that's fine.
Yeah, they just don't have a courtesy look and then squeeze your bag and if there was
anything particularly solid in it, they'd have a look.
If it's not, then it's like, okay, you've got a jumper in there.
Come on.
There was a life hack where Liz and I discovered towards the end of the convention that if you
were carrying a very full shoulder bag and a tote bag with a fanzine in it, they would
look in the tote bag, see your fanzine and wave you straight through because that is
secure.
So the number of times I just got through super quickly by carrying my strategically
loaded tote bag was quite high by the end because I was like, this is a great ways.
But ultimately they're all just trying to do their job.
They're all, they're all there.
They were friendly.
It was fine.
I think it came as a surprise to the convention that there were going to be bag checks.
So I feel a bit sorry for them.
That must have been unpleasant news.
There were clearly a couple of SEC things that surprised the convention at the last
month.
Like, for example, they'd planned to chalk the outside route on the ground and they were
told they couldn't do that like on the Wednesday.
Had to take all the chalking out of the program.
I saw them washing off the chalk and that was a really good idea.
So it was a bit, it seemed a bit silly, but, oh well, good idea on the conventions part,
I think.
Yeah.
Well, I have a couple of very itty bitty tiny criticisms in the way that we do.
Firstly, my badge said England.
I don't mind.
I think of myself as English and British and European.
There were definitely people I spoke to at the convention at England or their badge who
do not think of themselves as English.
And I was a bit like, yeah, okay.
And I was a bit confused because previous World Gons I've been to have had the name of
your city.
Like, so at Chicago, I think my badge said Newcastle, Bonstein, UK.
And I would have preferred that.
So I think previous World Gons I've asked before printing and I think that would have
been good.
But I do also wonder whether.
So I was staff and that meant I had to go to a different desk, which was the solutions
desk.
The solutions desk, which was one person and the person in front of me actually had a
problem with their membership.
And I mean, I had to queue for a very long time and I was a bit like, this seems weird
because I understand staff, but I don't understand why staff parties weren't just a separate
pickup.
I don't really don't get that.
And I don't get why it was merged with a troubleshooting function.
Those are my two very small criticisms of registration.
Liz has said further down, but the info desk needs to be in the concourse, which is where
it's been for the last two World Gons rather than in Hall 4, because it was in Hall 4,
everyone is going to ask the people who are in the concourse.
I think it needs to have an outpost there during registration because I was doing program
participant package pickup on Thursday.
And basically, if you are a helpful looking desk across from registration, people come
over and ask you all kinds of questions that we cannot answer.
And so we will have a bash at answering them because we are nice people, but a lot of them
were like, we don't know.
And then it was like, where's the info desk?
And that point I was like, actually, I don't know.
Maybe you could look at a map.
There weren't any maps.
So that was another thing we'll get to later.
But that was a bit of a thing.
We really needed a big info.
Then if someone wanders on and goes, well, I'm not registered.
How do I register or how can I do this or whatever?
There wasn't anywhere obvious them to go.
So they go and stand in like the solutions queue.
And that was really partly for staff.
Patch pickup, which just seems strange.
I want to say, I thought in general, there were a couple of things I really liked about
registration.
I very much liked how you picked up your badge and then there were other bits that you went
to for your other bits.
I very much liked that Liz was there.
Then our 10 would have Liz there again.
I was like, Liz.
Yeah, it was so happy when I went to the program desk and it was Liz.
And I don't think that might not have been quite so obvious at the time because I was
kind of stressed and tired and wanting my pins and things.
But yeah.
Yes, it is also quite tricky to do program participant registration when we have to keep
going out and holding people.
Oh, Liz, did you have to hug too many people, Liz?
Yes.
And by too many people, I mean, jump.
Oh, hang on.
Well, you didn't have to come out for me.
I went round.
I was like, I really want to hug Liz, but I can see that she's working and it would be
like petting a guide dog.
I am not going to do this.
It was just it was very well laid out in general.
I mean, my mind and it pick I mean, the mind and it picks we have about like help desk
and like people looking for information, notwithstanding in general, it felt very good
to me and it felt like a space where you could move forward.
I did not stand in the very large queue, but I saw some of the queue entertainment and
I want to give a shout out to the person and I will put a link to he's got like a page for
his cop late on the internet.
But there was a quest giver who had a yellow exclamation mark above his head and would
give you quests in the queue and he was brilliant.
And if you did the quest, you got like a class and a little book of more quests and like that
was very that was very good.
I believe Cardinal Cox, who is peacocks who runs the Peter of Science Fiction group, I
believe he was reading poems in the queue.
So like, yeah, I think I think the queue entertainment was good.
It looked like the queue was moving quickly.
Toves was in the queue.
I like tobs to know 10 queue.
There were queue ribbons and they were different each day.
They had things like Deja Q if you already had a queue ribbon.
And I didn't queue for apart from like a very brief queue at registration on my first day
and then bag checks.
I don't think I queued for anything all weekend.
I will say, I mean, I think the queue, it looks like it sounds like the queue entertainment
was quite good.
I also didn't stand in a big enough queue to get queue entertainment apart from once when
I was standing in a queue to get some soup and it was not very long queue and someone came
along to do queue entertainment and actually delayed people at the front of the queue from
doing anything because they were still doing the queue entertainment.
So please don't do it if the queue is only like six people were good.
I think in general, I mean, obviously there's going to be some queues.
There's going to be queues for popular program items, especially popular program items that
are not being streamed.
And there's only so much you could do about that, right?
So I think they did a good job with it.
I don't think the queues felt much less bad than at Dublin or London to my not very queuing
perception.
Yeah, I mean, I think Helsinki and Dublin were the high watermarks of queuing.
Oh, and Helsinki, yes.
Helsinki was big.
Yeah.
I did queued Helsinki quite a lot, which considering how little program I go to is startling.
And like, yeah, certainly my perception of queuing was that it was better than Dublin or at
London.
Sorry, I agree with you there.
And I was thinking, sorry, I agree.
I mean, I do, I will say, I do approve.
I think in London, it kind of caught us all by surprise because we just didn't expect
to see that many queues at least conventions are now like, yes, we might have queues.
We have a plan.
Well, because ultimately if a thousand people rock up and want to speak to five people who
are sitting behind a desk, there is going to be a problem there because it is difficult
to think of a way of solving that problem without there being some sort of a queue.
So I do think, I do think being realistic about the fact that we are going to need to
deal with the fact that we'll be queued.
Do you, do you want my professional experience on Qbusting?
If you've got a lot of people arriving at once to do something where there are only a few
number of people to do it, there are ways that you can deal with that to not involve
queues or they don't involve people standing in line.
They don't involve that aspect of queues.
What you do is you give them numbers to come back at a particular time.
Yeah, but do you think people who arrive at 10am on Thursday morning, I don't want you
to say here's a ticket to come back in an indefinite amount of time when your queue number
comes up?
Indeed.
But I mean, even so, you can't, but you know, there are, there are many different sorts
of queue busting techniques that can be used to break down a big queue so that it doesn't
look like as large a queue as it is that you use in professional environments where if
you had a queue of a thousand people and five people dealing with them, you would get fights.
I have experienced the model of queue busting that Alison describes when I queued at the
Croydon Home Office for his Banyard's immigration policy and I can confirm I'd much rather
stand in a queue because sitting and panicking is actually worse than standing and panicking
in my experience.
#NotAtAllAblist There was also, it is vital to say, an accessibility, like if you had
access needs, you were bumped to the top of that fucking queue and that is right and proper.
Gotta go, there's a whole thing about some, some people don't know if they've got an
access need or not and I think I would encourage those people to say, yes, you have access
need, like somebody who's just trashed their leg of foreshadowing.
Well, I'm dyspraxic and I'm trying to get better about sitting down on trains because I nearly
fall over a lot and one day I'm actually going to fall over and I'm trying to get better
about being like, no, you have balance issues, it is silly for you not to take a seat on a
Metro.
The beginning of my leg story started with about four months ago, my Apple Watch started
saying, you appear to have some balance problems.
Oh no.
Since well, I've fallen over a lot, including all the Thursday of Worldcon.
Though, I mean, I did trip over a massive thing.
So I spent a lot of the early part of Worldcon in huge pain listeners, which was not fun
but gave me lots of interesting endorphins.
Let's talk about the actual program that was here.
Yeah, okay.
So we mentioned this earlier, half an hour gaps are good.
I like, I am now of the opinion that if you are a convention and you are putting 60 minute
items in 60 minutes lots or even 45 minute items in 60 minutes lots, you, I just think
I can get in the sea now.
I am full on the 60 minute in a 90 minute slot train and I am welcoming all comers to
buy tickets and join me.
You get a funny hat.
I feel like if you're running a single stream program with a single stream in a bar or a
single stream in a workshop in a bar, I think you're probably all right.
Still, still have your program items in 60 minutes lots actually.
I think it's Eastercon and above size where you need to give people space to get around,
get a drink water.
But newer people to the community.
I started going to Eastcon in 2007 and this has been an innovation that has kind of become
more and more prevalent during my time in fandom.
I think the first time I saw it was 2011 Eastercon where no offense to anyone involved with
that Eastercon.
But I think the problem was they did not have enough program to do 60 minute items in 60
minutes lots.
So they did 90 minutes lots to make it look a bit better.
But actually, I think every time I have seen it, it has measurably improved my experience
of a convention.
So I am glad that this is an innovation that has happened over the last 15 years.
I feel like the more people you know and the more people who are going to catch you
between program items to say, "Oh, John, let's have a quick chat about something."
The more you like this innovation, I suspect that if I was at my not so much the world
come where I'm getting around as useful and long queues for the toilet and everything.
But at Eastercon, I feel like if I was at my very first convention, I would be like,
"What are all these gaps?"
So it's not any.
If you're new writing, I like them.
I think they're good.
But then as you know, Bob, I would like that to be less programmed.
So 30 minute gaps is part of their being less programmed.
So I'm a forward for it.
Yeah, I mean, I don't think you would have wanted to see class go with less program.
That was exactly what I was going to say.
Because then those half hour busy slots would be, you know, the half an hour that were
busy in the dealer's room would be all the time.
I have no problem with that.
Speaking of somebody who had tables in the dealer's room, a foreshadowing across which
we took a great deal of money, more people in the dealer's room would have been great.
Yeah, but it's more people in the dealer's room, it's more people in the concourse.
There was a massive difference between the queues for like food during panels and between
them.
So I think that kind of kept things a bit more manageable.
I mean, I think we're smaller con, you can still do 75 in a 90 slot.
That works okay.
And I think it was nine worlds who used to do 75 in an hour and 15 minute slot.
Sorry, 75 in an hour and 45 minutes slot, which I don't like because I can't do maths
with quarter hours.
Now that seems like the worst of all possible worlds to me and that can also get in the
sea.
Also very long program items.
Quite a lot of panels actually work better if they are tight 50 minute panels, but you
know, it's okay.
So, and I did want to say I was sort of keeping vague track of this through the week.
And I think every program I was in was more full than it was empty and it was often sort
of 80 or 90% full.
So and there were a couple which were extremely full.
The other thing I think is it is not clear to me if you make their be less program, I
don't think what happens is people are like, Oh, I will be quite happy because I'll just
be in the dealer's room.
I think what people do is try and go to the program that is don't get in and then complain.
And so I think you probably have a lot more ill feeling and then the people complaining
are going around the dealers being grumpy and they're not spending all their money because
they're grumpy.
And I think what you want is happy people more than you want lots of people.
So I did go to it.
I was on a couple of program items that did not attract a lot of people.
And I think we could maybe have done more to surface, you know, the fan program and why
you might care.
I mean, two people care.
I guess never really cares.
I mean, I guess that's a question.
What there were two items of fanzies at this entire convention and neither of them got
very many people to them because all the people who really liked fanzies were in the bar.
So you know, but in fact, one of the things we did with fanzies was to have an instant
fanzine workshop, which was like, Oh, the very definition of a of a cursed program item
that was very difficult to get together.
And in the end, we just kind of sat in the fancy lounge and said, right guys, right,
fanzies stick to this discord, we'll put it to the thing.
And it ended up as an actual fanzied and woof, which is not bad in places.
And I think that's that's evidence that you.
And so some people were like, Oh, no, this is great.
So maybe the way to get people into fancy fandom is what is a time in tiny workshops.
I mean, I was going to say imagine that the rooms in the SEC in the grandplow is an extol
one more modular.
You could join more of them together.
You could have a different set.
I think it's you use like you could put a fancy item in a bigger room.
And I think you're still not going to get a giant audience for it in 2024.
So that's the thing.
So it's like, there are certain things that you can't, certain things you kind of can't
cut from the program despite them having kind of extremely niche appeal.
Like if there were no items on fanzines, I guarantee someone would have been, why they
know items on fanzines at this world, calm.
And if we had said that's because no one comes to the items on fanzines.
So putting in an item on something which is vastly more popular, that's maybe not the
way to be doing it.
I'm just saying if we did cut the program down, then it may not turn into a smaller program
of items that appeal to Alison.
This is an argument we've had before on the podcast.
But yes, I keep coming back to I think Alison wants the program to be smaller.
And I think all the things I would cut first would make her punch me.
And this is a real tension with this argument because I quite like that we have the fanzine
panels.
But if you put a gun to my head and said reduce the program, I would get rid of the fanzine
panels and that I love fanzines.
But we were part of the problem guys because we were a fan-ish program.
We were a fan-ish program.
But we were streamed and recorded unlike much fan-ish program.
What you need to do Alison is start a fanzine history podcast.
No, I think Joe and Edie have done a very, very good job of that with the fanac.org
YouTube channel.
And I think probably in the very next episode, I need to plug the fact that one of the upcoming
things is the secret history of Plochter.
Basically, somebody has that covered and they're doing it very, very well.
Joe, Zichlurry and Edie Stern for those who are not familiar.
I have fanac.org and they are mostly, I think the podcasts are mostly Edie's work, but I
wouldn't like to say that for definite.
And it's a YouTube channel which means it is eligible for your fan cast vote people.
And indeed was in the longest.
Okay, we've recommended two this episode.
On the subject of program, we did a table talk and I thought that was quite nice.
I don't know what percentage of the program was table talks.
Yeah, so there were a thousand items, but quite a lot of them were things like table
talks.
150 table talks out of 1000 basically, so 15%.
So they offered John a table talk and then he said no, let's do an octa thought one and
it was great.
We were oversubscribed.
We loved talking to the people who came to it.
We said this on the live.
But I think like it is tricky, isn't it?
Because I would, I think next time, I really liked doing the table talk and it was really
lovely to me, everyone who came.
They were eight people table talks, which means if there are three of you, they're five
listener table talks, but table talks are normally 10 and they can sometimes go to 12
and we would have been perfectly happy with a 12 person table talk in which case we probably
wouldn't have been oversubscribed.
So hmm.
Although then we might have had one of the people who said I will go to any table talk
that's undersubscribed, randomly turning up and being very confused, which would have
been quite fun.
But it's okay, we just appointed them at our WUSFUS business meeting special and then
they'd be assaulted.
Yeah, so table talks or cafe clatches or literary beers or all of those things are kind of complicated
because you, most conventions have a few people who will get hundreds of people coming to
them and then a load of people who will get, not for many people coming to them and actually
managing that balance is invariably quite difficult.
I think Glasgow did a great job of it.
I think the thing where they said, oh people can get random, can go to a random table talk
in this time slot was great and I hope that the people who did that had some extremely
interesting conversations as I bet they did.
If you did some of that right in, because I'm really interested.
There were something like a thousand, we're going to keep using the number of thousand
programs I think there were actually something like 960.
Liz has noted that about 250 of those were table talk signings, tours, strolls and meetups.
That means there are about 750 panels, talks, etc.
And of those, about a third are available for replay.
And that corresponds to EasterCon where I think about 85% of their program was available
for catch up after the convention.
But it's quite a lot lower than levitation.
I think this is tricky because on the one hand, obviously I was at the convention and
I could have gone to things.
But on the other hand, there were things I did not get to see because I was busy that
have not been streamed and I am sad about.
And I do think, I don't know, there's like a couple of things where I'm like, why was
that not streamed?
And I sympathize with, obviously, there will be people who do not want to be streamed,
but I cannot help but suspect that part of it is that nothing in the crown plaza was
being streamed at all.
And I do think that it is a shame that not more was able to be streamed because I suspect
that my suspicion is that it's a lot more to do with how much they were able to stream
rather than how much people opted out of.
Does that make sense?
Have I said that well?
I think it's a mixture of those two, isn't it?
So partly it's that some rooms weren't streamed and therefore weren't recorded and therefore
weren't on replay.
And the other thing is that the permissions for streaming and recording were very much
opt in rather than opt out.
I mean, opting in is fine, but I think it was possible to go through the programming system
without ever being confronted by a box saying we're intending to stream all this, please
say yes.
And I think so they ended up having to send providers to people saying make sure you've
checked your streaming preferences in your profile.
If people didn't do that, they were noted as not streaming.
So both of those things I think led to it.
I think you are leaning much too high on the people opted out to streaming rather than
whole rooms were not streamed because I think nothing was streamed in the crown plaza and
the crown plaza had a lot of small rooms.
So I think also maybe they didn't stream forth and Garl are the ones in that armadillo.
I'm not sure about that.
Well they didn't stream die and I can't, given the panel, I can't imagine any of them
would have opted out.
Yeah, I mean, if you want to figure this out, you can figure this out by essentially you
filter on replay and room and you could figure all this out, right?
There's nothing streamed from Castle.
There's nothing streamed from forth.
There's nothing streamed from Garl are sorry.
If you weren't there, these are all the different rooms like there, whereas like a lot of the
ones from the SEC are streamed.
And I also was one of the people who went through and made sure replay was off for people who
were requested not to.
And that was not a huge number.
I think it is very much more that because of the room sizes, even though the ones in
the crown plaza were smaller and maybe were kind of low attendance panels, they ended up
not being streamed, whereas the bigger rooms that probably in the SEC did get streamed.
I mean, this is a slight side point, but what I also think is it's amazing how fast we
have gone from nothing at World Cons is ever streamed or recorded apart from the Hugos to
we are now expecting like everything and when it's only 30, 40% of program items available
for catch up later, we're like, well, why isn't all of them?
So it's a big shift.
Okay, so in a few years where people are like, what do COVID ever do for us?
Just remember this.
I think we've said that before, right?
I think one of the there's not many silver linings to the pandemic, but remote working
and things being available online much more freely, like are definitely two of them.
At this point, I'm going to say no, it's amazing.
The fact that we've got 252 items available for replay is fabulous.
It is thrilling.
I am just looking slightly sadly at the fact that we designed a model for conversation.
You know, we had a vision and then JT designed it and implemented it and then ran it at
levitation using RC specifically knowing that it could for what is actually quite a small
proportion of a World Cons total budget be rolled out to almost every piece of formal
programming in every room, including the crampypaster and armadillo rooms for not an enormous amount
of money.
And obviously they did put streaming into the village for the business meeting, but using
that model.
And the World Cons decided not to run with that option.
But I think that is a bit of a shame.
I just want everything and I want it now.
Please have a pretty day to Darwin's.
That's me.
So on a personal note, there are panels that I did not get to that I really wish had been
streamed and like that's selfish.
That's a selfish reason to be annoyed.
But like there was one on gods and faith in fantasy, which I really wanted to see, which
didn't get to decolonizing games, which I didn't get to see.
I don't think that's on replay.
But because obviously it was in a like it was not on replay.
I was on a panel on safety tools and RPGs, which I thought was really good.
And like about half of the audience had never used safety tools.
So like it was actually really nice to see how much interest there wasn't learning.
But that's not on replay.
And I would have loved to have been able to point people at that.
Claire and Espaez panel on first time World Con attendees isn't there.
And I really wouldn't have minded rewatching that because I loved it.
And then also the die panel that I saw and picked last episode isn't.
It's probably indicative of psychology, right?
Because it's very easy to see the things you're missing out on or not.
See the things that you're getting.
And I think you are right that we have done a lot better than we did at any point pre-pandemic.
There's kind of two things here, which is firstly I wish I was able to see all these
things.
And secondly I wish a British World Con had been like, no, this is how you do it.
Come on.
But no, but I am mindful of the fact that as Liz says, like it is still astounding that
there's effectively one could say there's enough panels on replay that you could run
a whole nother convention with them.
So we've got something to announce.
We have a project.
You have something to announce.
Do not wrote me into your project.
We are running a small convention.
It is called Glasgow 2024 back to our futures.
And it will be on the 1st of November and it is online and we will have no program whatsoever
because the entire program will be provided by the 252 items on Glasgow replay.
You have to be a Glasgow member to come to this and attending member of Glasgow.
All attendees 16 and over are welcome and you sign up through the Glasgow portal and at
the moment it's just an expression of interest.
At some point there will be an actual link in the portal that will get you into the convention.
As well as the replay we are also going to have a Discord where you can chat and some
Zoom rooms where you can hang out in bars and do little things like parties and meetups
and stuff like that.
"Team is me and John and not Liz because I only asked her three times."
And she said no very firmly each time because this has good boundaries and was like this
doesn't sound like any fun at all so I want to cover log and kavech.
Is that right Liz?
No, I think I said it sounds fun but if the idea is to all watch replays together then
I am seven hours out of sync with you so I'm not going to do a lot of it and also I don't
want to do any work but I did say I would come in sitting in your Discord and back channel
which is entirely correct.
Sounds good.
Would you like to be the official back channeler?
I mean if I can't hit his role, yes.
So John and me and Klebrali and we have Andrew January and Emily January who between them
know probably more about convention discourse at this point than anybody else on the planet
and so we think they'll be able to help us with this one.
And Meg MacDonald who is an actual vice chair of the convention.
I would like to say to Andrew and Emily and Meg if you need lessons in saying no to Allison
I will provide.
I mean I think you could curtail that sentence for certain people in that advertisement.
I mean if you need lessons in saying no in general but you did a lot of work for the
convention you can have a rest.
Okay I think this will, I hope, I mean it's being a bit frenetic at the moment because
we are launching in between the point where we record this podcast and the point where
the podcast goes out which is why we're doing this thing now.
It has been quite frenetic for the last few days but I don't think it will, I'm not expecting
this to be a huge amount of work because we are not having a program.
My role on this team is to repeatedly say we could do that but it sounds like effort.
Did you notice that I've done that a couple of times already because I have learnt my lesson?
Yeah no I'm proud of you.
The idea behind this convention is to deliver huge fun at not much effort prices.
That.
I think it's a good idea because obviously what happens is I intend to watch lots of
replay and on New Year's Eve I'll be like oh fuck I watched no replay and this will
actually encourage me to watch some.
So I'm excited.
I have watched a couple of bits.
I watched the Chris Priest Memorial which was very beautiful but I haven't watched a lot
else.
I suspect it will encourage me to watch replay but not on the weekend of the first to third
of November because I expect him to be a bit dizzy that weekend hanging out in the bar
with people.
But hopefully I'll get some replay done before that though I haven't started yet because
apparently I've been really busy ever since welcome which is not how it's supposed to
work I was supposed to be wrestling.
And we will see you at back to our futures but for now that was the Octa.podcast and
it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me.
I had a lovely rest and sent Alison a message saying I'm on holiday.
Please get back to me later.
But I did also then drop an episode of Octa thought without actually asking Liz and Alison
whether it was okay so you know it wasn't a perfect experience for everyone.
Sorry peeps.
I mean I thought yeah I thought you were on holiday it was like yeah it's fine John you
don't need to edit podcast you can have holiday and then I was like wait John why is the episode
like 45 minutes long.
I was like oh yeah I've done an episode.
There was one I did and there was also something where I would probably have asked you to take
a tap but it's a bit like now.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod in Competec.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
[BLANK_AUDIO]