Hello everyone and welcome to the 44th episode of Octa Thorpe, the podcast for Science Fiction
and Science Fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 11th of November 2021.
I'm John Coxon, I'm Alison Scott, and I'm Liz Batty.
We have a letter of comment this week. So Chris Garcia writes to say that it was another
wonderful episode and Alison got the correct answer on her second try and as we all know
Americans are always wrong the first time. So that's good. You've been promoted to American
Alison, so hurrah for that. And he also says that he disagrees with Alison that a single
person on Twitter can blow things completely out of proportion because if that were the
case his calls to have every Big Bang Theory episode forever deleted would have worked.
And that is a good observation. It's random? Random Big Bang Theory episodes deleted.
No, I mean I do like what John says there actually is that it's not that a single person on
Twitter can can blow things out of proportion. It's that one person says something in this
sort of snowball of lots of people saying what they might have felt but did not otherwise
say on Twitter that can sometimes happen. So it looks like everything has suddenly exploded
but actually maybe it's just one person voicing the opinion that a lot of people go, "Oh actually
it's more than me who feels this way. This is worth speaking out about."
Chris also says that he didn't know Shang Chi was set in San Francisco and asks if you can
see his car in any of the shots. And when I re-watch it Chris, I will let you know, are
you still driving that car that was quite beige?
Yeah, I think unless like Chris is driving the ween of a beale is going to be hard to
pick his car in the shots.
And then we got some comments on Facebook from Fran and from Farah.
Well I think Fran's is just like one of many comments we've received disagreeing with
Alison Stunts on Squash is being the only carvable fruit or vegetable because people
have reminders that you can carve melons as as Fran said and at the smell of burning melon
will haunt her forever. I just think we don't need to give that any more context.
This year I have a pumpkin dremel and I am slightly concerned that because normally I
carve pumpkins using liner cutting tools and I'm slightly worried that the dremel is going
to create a smell of burning pumpkin flesh in my kitchen.
As you say we also got comments from other listeners suggesting that we had neglected
the idea of being able to carve turnips.
Yes, a Scotsman who should remain nameless because we forgot to ask him if we were allowed
to quote him. So we're just going to quote him but not tell you who it was. Who could
it be? A Scottish person John and Nizno commented that he used to carve nips when he was a nipper
and nips I gather are not squashes.
There's a thing about American cultural imperialism where people go aha, carving carving pumpkins
is American cultural imperialism because in Britain it is traditional and it is traditional
to carve turnips or nips which are sweet and they do make quite horrifying and hideous
Halloween faces but they are also hard as rocks. They are very hard to carve and children
have memories of carving turnips but I think in many cases they didn't actually do very
much with the actual carving themselves, their parents kind of took one look at what they
were doing with a very sharp knife and went oh why don't you watch while I finish off
your pumpkin dear and pumpkins are much better for carving than turnips. That's why the American
tradition has taken over because you can carve pumpkins and you do quite well to get a kind
of two eyes and a mouth as bad as much as you're going to get out of a turnip even if
you're quite good but you're right they're not squashes.
So we are going to discuss some news from the Eastercon. So the first news is the Eastercon
has a hotel and this is going to be the Radisson Hotel and Conference Centre London Heathrow
which fans may know better as the park in. It's the same hotel that was used for Etervium
and Disprosium which were the 2019 and 2015 Eastercons both of which I think went smashingly. I had
a good time both of those. I really like the park in so I am excited about this. Part of
the reason I like the park in is because I like their breakfast so I'm really hoping
that the rebrand hasn't changed the breakfast. What do you two think about this excellent
news or do you think it's terrible news that's have some hot takes?
I'm happy enough with the park in. I think it would be nice to have tried somewhere new
but they couldn't make it work so that's okay and I'm happy enough to go back there.
There are some access issues with the long corridor at the park in and I'm sure they're
going to be thinking about how they can mitigate those. I personally like the park in because
both times we've been at the park in before I've been doing the newsletter and they've
given us a room right next to the real L bar with an absolutely fucked ton of Powerpoints
and internet so that's made me very happy. I actually didn't go to Estercon in 2019.
I think it isn't true. We're going to end up with like three of the past four in person
Eastercons. We're actually being in the same hotel but at this point it's like Estercon
needs a hotel and at this point I think there's just you know you can't really go out about
it. We've just got to go with whatever hotel is actually feasible and if the formerly parking
now Radisson is feasible then yeah let's go for it and I actually don't mind Heathrow
because it is a bit in the middle of nowhere but it also does usually have quite a lot
of like alternative accommodation in different price ranges which I quite like.
And it's convenient for foreign travellers. #HintIntLiz
Here's a shimmy you want to like walk straight off a plane and into Estercon yeah although
I think that would be extremely discombobulating experience.
Ispania did that. Ask her how much, no don't ask her how much she enjoyed it. Ask her why
there's not a single photo of her at that convention where she's smiling. That's a
better question to ask. That will more quickly get you to the answers you desire, listen
to it. But yeah it turns out doing at least a call on eight hours of jet lag in the wrong
direction isn't fun. We also had some news from Estercon, they announced that they were
going to have a new guest of honour and the new guest of honour is Tasha Suri who is the
author of the epic fantasy The Jasmine Throne and she has won an award, the Sydney J Brown
Awards from the British Fantasy Society and has been nominated for the Astounding and
Locust Awards. So yes I'm excited, I had not heard of her before but she seems really
cool and I'm going to have to read some of her books. Are we excited about Tasha Suri
joining the guest of honour roster? Yes I'm excited because I have heard of her and
I've heard good things about her books but not actually got around to reading any so of
course this is the perfect excuse for me to get around to reading them.
I observe that she's got a book coming out which is what souls are made of, a young adult
wuthering heights remix and I kind of thought that wuthering heights was a young adult
wuthering heights remix so I was fascinated by this but perhaps it was just a young adult
but when I was a young adult I mean it was entirely read by moody teenage girls.
Alison was alive in Jane Austen's time. Not quite but not far off.
It's young adult in the sense that it's a book you would actually give to a young adult
nowadays whereas I'm not sure I would give wuthering heights to a young adult.
That was what I was saying but I was saying it with more meanness. High five John.
So the other sadder piece of Eastcon news is that unfortunately Zencho has had to pull
out of the guest slot for family reasons and so this is a great shame. I'm a huge fan of
Zencho so I was looking forward to seeing her at the Eastcon but I hope her and her family
are well. Yeah pretty much the same it's it's sad she had to withdraw. I was really looking
forward to seeing her because her books are great and I've seen her on panels and she
is also great and obviously you know we wish all the best to her and hope she can come
to a future Eastcon. Yeah no I don't really have anything to add to that. It's just sad.
And then that wraps up the Eastcon news. So listeners we're going to insert a discussion
we had a couple of months ago now on kind of the topic of Eastcon venues in the future
with Covid looming large over the community. We wanted to wait until Eastcon announced
their venue because we didn't want any of what we're about to say to be taken as a device.
It's all extremely speculative and kind of us just kind of musing and pondering. Also
two of us are on committees of Eastcon bids and so nothing in this should be taken as having
anything to do with our work on those bids and either of us are responsible for sight.
We're both responsible for communications that's quite funny really isn't it?
It turns out we have similar interests listeners who knew. I would like to know the only time
I was communications from Eastcon I was rubbish at it so. Excellent excellent thank you Liz.
So now Eastcon has announced that they are in a hotel we can immediately have a long discussion
about but what if they weren't which will be hopefully interesting to you the listener.
And we will see you for pics after this brief sojourn backwards in time.
Is the Twilight Zone Music public domain? Because if it is is going here,
and if it isn't I'll just keep that statement in!
Today we are going to be discussing the future of EasterCon.
Especially spinning off of a discussion on the UK EastCon community group on Facebook,
talking about EasterCon in the times of Covid and what needs to happen to EastCon going forward
sort of over the next five years. So you might think this is too time super timely but as you'll
actually be listening to it at Christmas or something it won't necessarily be. And when we say the
future of EasterCon's we should make it clear that we mean the future of EasterCon's in a generic
sense and not the future of EasterCon's the project that ran for several years a few years ago and
drew no conclusions of Wound itself up. I think it concluded that lots of people had a lot of
opinions but none of them were very coherent or consensual and so EasterCon might as well just
get on with it until the next crisis. And so here we are.
Do you fair? I made a bunch of graphs for that project and I can't remember whether there was
an action with me to make more graphs which I have not done and therefore doomed a future
of EasterCon. No it really did. The project Wound itself up and made a report. It is done.
It was fine. It was correctly managed but it didn't change anything because it concluded that there
wasn't a balance of people wanting the EasterCon to incorporate. Nick Whitehead on the UK
EasterCon doing the group asked a question about the site for rectification which is at the time of
the recording the next EasterCon and there was a response from the Reclamation Committee
sort of saying we are in negotiations and we can't really say anything yet but we are working on it.
And that was about two weeks ago. There has been a flurry of discussion over the last three or four
days and Liz do you want to kind of outline and summarize the discussion so far?
Yeah I will try and summarize it and I will say that for this discussion I'm not so much
interested in all the specific comments there as kind of the broader conversation which hangs off it
which is to me kind of maybe two parts to it. One is that we are in a strange new world
for venues and so after essentially two years of council events I think the environment for
finding hotels and booking hotels and making deals and contracts with hotels is probably quite
different than it was in 2019. That's something that's alluded to in the thread about sites wanting
wanting big deposits or wanting different styles of deals and I think that's something we're going
to have to deal with going forward and the second one is well and the second thread is that it
seems clear now that COVID unfortunately it was not COVID-19 and it's there for a year and it's gone
away and we don't have to think about it anymore but it might be that we have to make general
adjustments and think about things for several maybe many years to come and it's worth thinking
about what adjustments we can make and what adjustments we might want to make and what adjustments we
might want to make that would help very much with say the COVID situation but would kind of make
the EasterCon maybe not the EasterCon anymore and so there are those two things to discuss.
This is very relevant to the work that I'm doing for EasterCon 2023 where we are explicitly
starting to think about asking the community what is it that you want from an EasterCon? What things
make it EasterCon like and you know if EasterCon turned out to be a
convention limited to 100 socially distanced people in a tent in Florida would that still be
EasterCon and you know I think most people probably say it wouldn't be but there's probably some
intermediate points where it would still be the EasterCon and what does that look like?
One of the things kind of that has come up in this thread is talking about whether or not it's
going to be possible for EasterCon to kind of continue in hotels so do we want to talk about
kind of the alternatives to hotels and what that might imply for EasterCon going forward?
Sorry yeah I think we do. EasterCon has flirted with the idea of going to a holiday camp. It has
actually gone to student accommodation but only once. There are a number of sites dotted around
the UK that are kind of they were colleges owned by large organizations but they do still exist
and they are sites where you could run conventions not necessarily EasterCon but certainly there are
sites of that kind and all of those seem plausible and then people have actually said well maybe we
should reconstitute the EasterCon as a festival and put it in a field with tents rather than
in a hotel. So yeah I think that's kind of the space of that. I don't know and then obviously
there's virtual conventions as well but I think most people agree that the EasterCon could be
physically we'd like it to be physical if it's possible. I think it would be interesting to revisit
the idea of sort of student accommodation type things because I think it is a while since EasterCon's
been there and my impression is that a lot of the sort of student accommodation places have gone a
bit more market and mainly things like for instance on-suite bathrooms and you know beds which are
not extremely uncomfortable single beds. So it's probably worth investigating what's there. A lot of
these places have double beds even and quite a lot of them have a mix so they have quite a lot of
double rooms and they still have quite a lot of single rooms and so you'll be able to offer things
at different price points which I think would be quite welcome to people because it's clear that
the traditional way of saying oh it's going to be ex-emmowed if you're in a twin or a double and
and somewhat less than ex if you're as a single that's not the way the hotels work. It hasn't been
for some years so it's becoming very expensive to attend a single person unless you're prepared to
share. And the other thing they may also have is you know some student accommodation may have
flats with kind of multiple bedrooms in one kind of complex which could be a quite affordable option
for families or for friends who want to share. Multiple bedrooms in a kind of complex with a
kitchen and I think that's very attractive. Certainly I've self-catered for a number of
conventions in the past and found it a very good way for doing a longer convention. I think
three days is about as much as I'm prepared to eat entirely hotel and restaurant food without
becoming quite unhappy about that and self-catering is an option for people so I think this is the
sort of thing that we should be exploring. And this is this actually ties into conversations that
being had in academia as well kind of in parallel because a lot of academic conferences are seeing
the benefits now to being able to use university accommodation. So when I started going to conferences
as a student most of the conferences were held in university accommodation but they had like
hotels or arrangements with B&Bs because the student accommodation wasn't really up to much
and that has been changing as I've been in academia so I do think that is something
the universities are trying to do as an extra profit center effectively is make their student
accommodation more appealing for the sorts of events that might once use the space and East
Com probably does fit into that bill. But one of the things about university accommodation is that
although your rooms are probably still enclosed and your conference space still has some rooms that
you need to manage the corridors in university accommodation tend to be outside and that actually
helps with you've got more ventilation you will move from unless unless the conference center is
really grander than I think it is you will still have a certain amount of moving around outside
which does mean that you will get wet but also means that they will get some fresh air and I
am a hearty believer of fresh air. I have several comments one is that I am on currently as we
recall this I am on day nine of eating exclusively in a hotel and it is starting to wear a little bit
which is why I'm going to the supermarket in half an hour. Two are they actually corridors if they're
outside? Oh good question no and and I think that is basically one of the main trade-offs is trying
to work out the extent to which the outside bits are mitigatable that's one of the huge challenges
I think but I think it's a challenge we can meet and I also think having the bits in between
parts of the convention being outside will make it more Covid secure and that segues very nicely
to how about we had East Com in a tent? Yeah so one of the options that people have suggested for
East Com is that it runs like a festival and I think unlike Liz or John, Liz do you do festivals?
Not really no. No so unlike Liz and John I really really like festivals I quite like camping I don't
camping is not as comfortable as hotels but it is quite nice to be able to drink a vast amount of
alcohol and then sink into a tent rather than having to worry about getting somewhere else that
isn't the festival so it's kind of like everyone gets to stay in the convention campsite. It's nice
waking up in the morning in a campsite because it's kind of clean and fresh and lovely but
there's quite a lot of big butts here festivals come in a couple of different flavours so they either
have all of their stuff outside in which case you need to deal with rain but you also need to
deal with the fact that outside is a terrible environment for the spoken word outside is a
brilliant environment for music it sounds amazing it looks amazing you get to dance in a field it's
great it's really not such a good environment for the spoken word and so you find that a lot of
festivals have smaller stages for spoken word events and most East Com things are spoken word
events the thing about these these smaller stages is that they're often enclosed they're often
actually tents with walls and that's just a room like any other room so you you immediately lose
some of your benefit and yes you can take the walls off and improve the covid secureness of
your site by having mockeys with open side walls and we had that at the festival I was at last
weekend and it does help a lot especially if it's cold and windy but you know it's going to be cold
and windy at Easter Easter is a terrible time we would probably have to move to the summer
and then you're going to discover that all of the event infrastructure in the UK is in use all summer
every summer that's how it works so you and everybody else is is bidding on event infrastructure
and and also we would need an expert we need to basically co-opt I think Linda Kriekki is the only
fan who does this for a living but we need to find somebody who could then contract an events
management company to do it for us we would not be able to run it the way we run other bits of
Easter Com by by well I know so-and-so's got a suitable hanger he can bring it's not going to work
you you need to you need to subcontract that and at that point you're probably into festival price
so which should be it's okay no so that that was one of the suggestions on the on the Facebook
group it was kind of mooted that we could move to campsites which might be a more affordable
option but I think the key problem there is that campsites tend to be in use at bank holidays and
when it's nice enough whether to have an event at a campsite yeah so there's an alternative that we
could be on a large fixed campsite but again they're full all summer Easter Com thrives in part
because we use hotels at a point where no one else wants to use the hotels because most hotels
the conference spaces are outdated for professionals who are not going to professional conferences
over these two weekend and so we can sometimes get cheap accommodation so it might be that we
are actually not going to find that moving to outdoor locations suits us particularly well
side-line this is much less true than it used to be yeah I think it is still more true for hotels
than for place-like balance and pondings that we are currently in less competition for those spaces
yes we are not the only hobbyist it used to be that we were really quite unusual as being a hobbyist
conference over Easter but that's not true anymore there are quite a lot and we're not even a particularly
big one so it's also absolutely true if you look at like holiday camps like the butlins and the
ponthins type thing that every weekend in the off season is a different weekend interest group
and that's basically what keeps them going between the the school holidays when they are
extremely expensive and full but even even so there are that many kind of special interest groups I
think that you might even find a free weekend that there isn't something on at the ponthins
no I think we could do a deal with a holiday camp if that was what people wanted but it would
have to be an off season I don't think it could be east weekend because it's in the school holidays
EasterCon one of the core features of EasterCon is that it is a four-day weekend that everybody
in the UK pretty much gets off apart from Vickers and and that's been quite a good thing
for creating the community obviously people can take holiday around
conventions and quite a lot of our members are retired or work flexibly and can take
can take days off anyway so we I don't think the commitment to Easter is as absolute as it has
been but I think it would be quite hard not to run it over Easter and also I think there are still
sites I you know it's not that there are no sites it's that there are no perfect sites
but there are a lot of sites that are more perfect than ponthins one of the things that comes up in
the thing is that um Kate Solomon said that some affluent class fandom will grumble about not being
in a four-star hotel and at this point I would like to wheel out my privilege and say that one of my
absolute things I like when I'm staying away from home is to have an ensuite bathroom and it is my
understanding it is difficult to have that in a tent and so I do quite like I don't need to be in a
four-star hotel but but I do I do I think a campsite would be the point at which I was like do I
really want to keep going to Easter cons and that would be a shame that there is a solution for you
which is campervan hire oh but I mean it's expensive but I mean I think I would turn to the people who
go oh I'm not prepared to be in a tent because portal is and say campervan hire you know if
if that's something that's really that's really a deal breaker but you might find that it's not as
bad as you think portal is not as bad as you think yeah but I don't like the idea that there's this
idea that I can drink a lot of beer and then fall into my tent sort of falls over if I then have to
keep running out of my tent to go and find the portal. Okay this is there's probably too much
information here there's a whole process whereby you go to the loo before you leave the festival
site then you go to the loo again just before you get back to your tent and then you're okay
and until you wake up in the morning and and then very occasionally you wake up in the night going
oh shit do you need to go to the loo but then you keep a pair of crocs with you as well as your
regular shoes so you can just shove crocs on. You can't you can't piss into a croc all of the
way you would fall out yeah and to be fair people do also take toilet tents with them and things
like that you know it's not totally there are there are solutions. I am also in the category of
people who don't enjoy driving home from convention so so a camp around would not but I take your
point that this is not necessarily insurmountable and if East Kong did change to festivals I would
give it a very good go before I gave up you are you are right that I would be exploring all of these
things. I might also contract as well as contract with somebody to actually run the site for me
which we would definitely have to do. I might also contract a glamping company to provide us with
like the I mean so the ones we had this weekend was the last weekend which were absolutely lovely
I'm going to say who they are they're a company called Norfolk Bells and they did a lovely bell
tents they didn't have support but but the more expensive glamping also often has a glamping
area where you have your glamping tents and proper flush toilets and showers and maybe a central
tent with a concierge and charging stations and electricity so you can plug your straightening
arms in and things like that so so glamping comes in a number of different systems and I think I
definitely think if we were doing an Easter con in a field we'd have charging facilities it would be
one of the things that we would do you know we'd have electrical power in a place where you could go
so you do there's a security risk but I mean we'd be quite small for a festival we're big for
a we're quite big for a hotel but we'll call us more for a festival. Well you get you get the
thing where you know you you lock your phone in a locker to charge it and then come back and get
it won't you or something you know there's there's ways to overcome this and we'd already be having
to contract with people to help us with the electronics anyway because you know Eastercon cannot
itself set up you know electricity in a field. The people I would go to are the people who run
this kind of like this kind of like nerdy hackers festivals in fields and I think they they boot
strap at all using volunteers so they could give us some learnings and they probably also know
what you need to do to get enough internet into a field. Yeah it's like is it EMF camp I think
I'll look that up and we can make sure it goes in yeah yeah something like that. I mean I'm not
totally averse to the idea of doing a convention of field because I quite like being in fields but
I think I like being in fields but I don't like being in fields in March that's a problem. Yeah no
we definitely did not a Easter if it's if it's a if it's a field if it's a festival a festival type
thing then you do it in the summer. I would say I think we were quite worried at the Harrogate
Eastercon because there was one access issue where to avoid a flight of stairs you had to go outside
and I remember we were very concerned about that because of inclement weather and I think that didn't
turn out to be too much of a problem. Am I remembering correctly because I wasn't really running the
con by that point? It wasn't really too much for a common problem because most people decided they'd
cope with the flight of stairs and we actually did have golf buggies to take people around and
that was the the hotel had golf buggies and and drove people back and forth and the people who
used it like that service and thought it was a good accommodation. I think it was much harder for
the people who who could walk a few steps but walking up and down a flight repeatedly was
was difficult for them and I think we could have done a lot more to encourage those people to make
use of the buggies but it's certainly true that outside does have quite a lot of access issues that
are not immediately. I mean it's normally pretty flat and you could you could have scooters. Scooters
work much better in fields than they do in hotel corridors. You said scooters work much better in
fields than hotel corridors? You mean the other way around? No, they're fine in festivals that there
are festival friendly scooters. Oh okay. The only problem is that you do get people who have never
used a scooter before who have drunk 18 points of world worth success and those people are not safe
and I think we would probably have to say that if you are using a scooter then we would expect you
to very much limit the amount that you drink and I understand that that is infringing on people's
liberties somewhat but it would be important for safety. Yeah, designated scooter drivers.
I mean one thing I didn't say is that the best example of a convention you know that ran in a
sort of semi-field situation was uh blocked com. It's where lots of time running around in the dark
doing your fucking scavenger hunt I think. It was like scavenger hunt. Okay so we were when I say a
semi-field this was the civil service college so it was really pretty nice. It was some primitive
in some ways and some of the rooms were better than others so some of the bedrooms were still
kind of hard single beds but but it's quite nice and we were over Maybank holiday so it was
quite nice weather as well and people went swimming and things. Yeah in the sort of model that of
you know my bedroom was in one room and then I went outside and crossed like some green space
in order to get to the convention center bit but yes my room there was lovely and we had lovely time
running around outside in the dark for some reason eating pizza outside but we weren't supposed to
have got pizzas delivered but we did. Hey I don't think they minded I think we were relaxed. Yeah
I think it's one of the advantages of these sorts of sites is that they are much more relaxed than
hotels about you bringing food and drinking because students bring food and drinking obviously
and the notion that they shouldn't let people hasn't really occurred to them. No it's good but
no it was it was basically fine and they were very keen to secure custom but I think since then the
entire site has been sold for housing really I think it's longer but I'd always wanted to run
a convention at the civil service college I've always thought oh that would be a fantastic site
for a con and it's safe we didn't have to spend anything on tech because one of the nice things
about academic sites is that every single room in your academic site is set up for the sorts of
things you want to do it at least to go apart from maybe put a big band on and I think if I was
running on a site like that I might just go no we won't do that but they often have theatres
and you can use if they have a theatre you can use the theatre for that sort of thing. Yeah one of
the things that came up on the discussion thread on facebook was basically one fan with access
requirements was kind of discussing the difficulties of moving outside there were some people in the
discussion who were not taking that as seriously as they might have done that I think that would be a
big thing you'd need to think about but I'm not sure whether it's intractable or whether it's just
difficult that would be something we'd find out if we ever did it but as we've noted SFX
Weekender already uses a site like this and so presumably they already have some expertise in
what the issues here are and how you might want to mitigate them so it might be that we could
pick their brains if it ever did come to that. We're talking about the possibility of doing a
COVID-safe convention here or a more COVID-safe convention and given that people are going oh well
it's fine to exclude every child under 12 to make our convention more COVID secure I think you may
have to say oh actually there are access needs that can't be met if we do this this is something
that we will be deliberately choosing but certainly access is harder for outside but you know there
are people who like festivals who become disabled who go to extraordinary lengths to get to festivals
with their disability so it is doable it is just quite difficult and it would be an awful it would
be a huge change for EasterCon fans who are who are used to used to hotel spaces. I mean I would say
the excluding children are 12 it's a thing that I assume is temporary like will probably be for
this year only until we basically get around testing and licensing vaccines in small children
whereas I think I was thinking you know if this is like three or five years down the line and we
still need to be trying to do good ventilation and social distancing how is that compatible kind of
long term that might be more of a digression than we need and I was saying the SFX weekenders
I think the thing with the SFX weekenders are the ones I went to is the sites are large but usually
very flat the kind of single story type things basically all on tarmac and so the issue is more
I think the distance and I'm not sure how any kind of accessible shallows they have but I suspect
the ones they do have are very close into the central facilities. I would just say something I
want to add is I've just looked up SFX weekender and it happens in early February in North Wales
so like there is clearly there is clearly an extent to which you can do these things at times
when you might think the weather might be in Clement. Yeah I was talking about a Greenfield site a
festival SFX weekender is in a holiday camp which is like that there are no tents involved
shallows and central buildings so it's quite primitive in places and the site is very large.
Okay cool. I mean I would also say that yeah they do do them in February in a holiday camp
and it is fucking freezing. I mean there's no getting around they should like shivering in
the queue for vision dips. Oh no but my point is that they still do it it doesn't stop them.
Doesn't stop them no but it does have some downsides. This segues into a couple of questions on
kind of the traditions around Eastacon and whether or not those traditions need to be more
codified so one of the questions that comes up in that thread about future of Eastacon venues is that
there was one hotel that was asking for a £200,000 deposit before allowing Eastacon to book the
space and that is the sort of money that if there was a central Eastacon organization that managed
the pass along funds we might be able to do that but like certainly not with the way that we do it
at the moment and also kind of if there was a codified Eastacon Constitution would that constitution
demand that you held Eastacon at Easter and would that prevent moving the convention in
summer for the warmer weather and the outside? So what do we think the implications are for all
of this and kind of the traditions of Eastacon and does this have any bearing on the arguments around
you know does there need to be a written or a codified Eastacon Constitution?
That does not need to be a written or codified Eastacon Constitution.
I think the hotels that are asking for £200,000 deposits are taking the piss because that's not
normal in the industry and it's a nonsense and if you went and said I'm thinking of holding a
wedding and they said oh we need £200,000 deposit you've come off it mate you know it's just nonsense
and I think that's that's part of how you go about managing the negotiations.
Hotels are very skittish because of the lack of leadership from government on supporting venues
for events. Now there has been a scheme announced it might only apply to festivals but it might apply
to events generally to provide COVID insurance for 2020. So if the government 2022, if the government
is going to pick up COVID COVID cancellation insurance for events then that is something
that we might be able to take advantage of but that's the reason they were asking for a huge deposit.
It's not because they would normally do that it's because they're kind of trying not to go bust
and go in oh but we can't afford the risk that this event will fold a couple of weeks out leaving
us with nothing. So I feel like if you did have I think this is a very good example of why you
don't want to codify constitution there because if you have a if you give east-coder constitution
then what things do you mandate in it and of course Wilcon went the route of mandating very
very little in the constitution you have to have the hugos you have to have as a business meeting
and that's it and even so they found that COVID actually created circumstances they hadn't really
considered for the constitution and I don't know that they've quite managed to sort those out.
So I think you might you probably wouldn't want if you did write a constitution freeze to
card you wouldn't probably want to specify that it had to be a t-ster. I think we would probably
look favorably on a bid that came along and said well we've got a great site but we're going to have
to move it to Whitweek. I don't know people might struggle. What's Whitweek? Whitweek is the late
the late Maybank holiday, Huitsun and it is the most expected it's very unlikely that it
needs to cause everyone but going to move there because it is the most expensive week of the year
for holidays and of course everyone holidays in the UK now which is so hotels are finding that
some hotels are finding that they can't actually sell their rooms in a way that they weren't expecting
to. So it's very it's complicated. I think I agree with Alison in that in some ways it is nice to give
each convention the freedom to kind of do what it likes. I think it's I don't want to you know
yeah prescribe what they have to do and therefore stop them you know experimenting with different
things. I think it is also true that Eastercons do follow a lot of unwritten rules and I worry
that kind of having a big set of unwritten rules that you kind of don't really know about but sort
of have to follow because everyone has for the past end years is also quite off-putting because
it's kind of this big burden of institutional knowledge that you then have to try and pick
up on before you can really get thoroughly stuck into the Eastercon and I also worry that if
if an Eastercon does come along and do something which is not a whole part of you know any constitution
but it's one of these unwritten rules that they might end up with quite a lot of backlash.
I mean I think one thing Follycon did that was quite controversial at the time was we changed how
the art auction worked didn't we? I think we had a silent auction. Yeah which is a time I think
there was some push back against but ended up working fine as it was. I mean people were unhappy
about it and some artists didn't exhibit but we had a good art show and people made more money
than I have previously so. No and I think I see what Liz means like I think that it cuts both ways
which is it gives you the freedom to do what you might want to do or might need to do but it also
gives you enough rope to hang yourself with if you do like inadvertently decide something that
the community generally is a bit put off by. I wonder whether having it at the Easter weekend is
one of those things that would put people off. I really like having a Easter and I think
so again with my academic hour on the brilliant thing about Easter is that universities tend to get
days off either side of the bank holidays so it does mean you have like a date pack
a date to travel and then a date to come back and decompress which is really really nice.
I don't know like obviously academia is not a large enough segment of the random for that to be a huge
thing but for me it's a pretty large segment of the fandom. It's a huge huge it's much bigger
segment of the fandom than it was when I got into fandom. Yeah but I do wonder whether
if you tried doing it a different date you would find very abruptly that was one of the
more important than written rules. I don't know. I think if you tried to run Easter come not at Easter
there would be a convention there would be a convention happening at Easter because people would
just kind of go oh there's a void I can put a con there it's got four days it'll be good.
No and like I've always wanted to see a real life schism so that might be fun.
The year we ran the first fully con at the same time as the traditional fans were absolutely up in
arms at these crappy media fans taking over their lovely Easter con the media fans were running
another convention that weekend because Easter con wasn't anything like media enough for us that
there was a convention called Elador that I think lots of people we know went to including Clara
Mark and that happened over the Easter weekend through four years I think before
before folding and that was a media con. It was more me it was still still towards the
fanish end of media cons. I think it was probably most like redemption and now obviously the redemption
and Elador people will come along and say no it wasn't like that at all but I think it was
closer to redemption than to to what we think of as gate shows so it wasn't a gate show.
I think one other aspect we hadn't thought about about moving from Easter is essentially the only
time that people with children can take their children away for a four-day weekend is during
one of the school holidays and Easter is probably the only one where you could run a con at reasonable
prices in a hotel that is part of the school holidays so I think that's that as well.
You know if we moved it to a random weekend and we've tried to pick a random four-day weekend in
April or you know June or something that wasn't a holiday that would be an issue.
No that's actually a really good point I hadn't really thought about that but I guess Easter
doesn't just tick the box of four-day weekend that you don't have to take any leave to attend
the hotel might not be hugely expensive for but it also ticks the box of in the some holidays so
parents can come. Not some holidays sorry in the school holidays so the parents can come and that
I guess is pretty much the only time at which all of those things are true so it may well be that
moving away is is difficult but then you know World Cons and NASFIX manage so I guess there's a
counter-argument which is if other countries can have their flagship conventions at different
times of year maybe the UK could do. I guess world contents be over the Labor Day weekend and I don't
know what the US school holidays are like but that might be a factor. It hasn't been for some years
so World Cons sort of lost the Labor Day weekend because they were having trouble getting sites
because that weekend had become very popular for conferences and although traditionally schools
didn't restart in the US until after Labor Day that's no longer true in many parts of the US
so people were finding that kids were back in school and then now I think World Cons
be mostly on summer weekends for several years at this point. Of course when the World Cons comes
to the UK mostly I don't know if this is true I might be talking bollocks. Was Lunkon over the
back holiday weekend? Well no I don't think so it was mid-August right? The Glasgow World Cons were
over the back holiday which is the obvious place to put it. If you go to lunkon3.org you get a gambling
website these days. I would have kept the website. It was 14th to the 18th of August.
Yeah so it was the week before. I can't remember if it was but I mean there was a reason we had
to do it on that weekend because that was when we could get the Excel I think. What I can't remember
was whether that was it was it within the school holiday still I guess it would be. Yeah mid-August
is. I think that was quite important to us. Just one very quick remaining question I have
which is we were talking earlier about the reason that Hojals have been asking for those huge deposits
that we referenced earlier is probably due to the increased risk which is almost certainly true.
Does the increased risk make it riskier for convention committees to run east-comp?
And like how can that be mitigated? Is there a way or is it just we have to shrug out as Roald doesn't
hope? I'm hoping that the fact that there's a Wilcon coming to the UK in 2024 probably that will
have a budget that for exceeds that of any Eastercon and what will happen is if Eastercons
around that are struggling will kind of get the Wilcon to lose our losses in their rounding
figures sorry Esther. A more professional way of saying that would be that Eastercon one of the
nice things about the Eastercon community is that on the rare occasions that something has gone wrong
the community has rallied round to ensure that large losses have not been sustained. But there's
a risk. I mean Eastercon running has a kind of inherent risk in it but then everything does.
And one of the one of the big arguments for incorporating is that if you incorporate that risk
does not settle onto the committee members but it is still there in the community because if
Eastercon goes bust if we made it a company and then the company went bankrupt that would make it
much harder for people to run successive conventions. That's a good point. It's one of those things
where I'm sort of vaguely aware when running Eastercons that there might be some like repercussions
for the committee should we have no money and go bust but I sort of assumed that at that point
there will be enough kind of community rallying around and bits of pass along and so on. I mean
assuming that you know the Eastercon goes bust you know not through the fault of the committee
being terrible and spending all the money on bouncy castles or something like that you know.
I assume that we'd all sort of go around and help but I mean when you're getting into some
like we want an enormous deposit because you can't get insurance that becomes more of an issue. And
also all the Eastercons I have worked on where I've been high enough to be paying attention. They've
all had you know insurance in case of you know disaster and not being able to hold the convention.
That's fair. Yeah.
So let's do picks. Alison you go first.
I went and saw Dune and I did it in the cinema because I kind of, I was conditioned by Lawrence
of Arabia as a small child and I kind of think that if you're going to see a movie about desert
scenery you should probably go and do it on the big screen. It wasn't as bad as some other people's
cinema experiences I might docked again. Quite enjoyed it. Dune is pretty good probably worth
seeing on the big screen. It is only half the novel and in order to I think avoid David Lynch's
problem of having massive gobs of exposition. Villeneuve's decided to not have any exposition at all
which is fine if you've read the book. If you haven't you probably aren't going to realise
what's going on because nothing is explained and when things are explained that are absolutely
critical they do it with a very with a thundering score over the top of it. But I might like to
anyway lots of good performances. Look forward to the second one.
Liz put a comment on the Dune soundtrack in the show notes listeners and I'm going to
reproduce it here. Did that come through? It worked alright for me. I definitely heard
a good thundering. That is the inception. Blah and that was Liz's soul comment in the show notes
on I was like fair enough so is it my soundboard now. I don't really have a second pick but my
second pick is just to say that I watched Black Widow last night and because I've been quite rude
about the Marvel Cinematic Universe. I quite liked it. I don't want to say I really quite liked it a lot.
I especially like the way in which Natasha's sleeper cell is depicted as a sort of
screwed up version of The Incredibles and they have the like most hilarious family superhero
shenanigans I think I have ever seen in a movie and I really like that a lot.
Nice. I have not seen Dune. Oh my go and see it at the cinema but it is like over two and a
half hours long which is usually my threshold for not seeing things in the cinema. Oh yes it's
it is a test of your middle aged bladder control is Dune. Bring back into missions that's what I say
but I did I saw Black Widow in the cinema and I very much enjoyed it. I thought I mean I love
Rachel Weiss and I love David Harbour and I love I hadn't seen the lady who plays her sister
before but I loved her. Florence Pugh she's amazing she's really really good absolutely top talent.
Florence Pugh is in Little Women with Timothy Chalamet so there you go tie up.
She is amazing in Little Women as Amy. Timothy Chalamet actually is much less impressive in Little
Women than he was in Dune. I thought he was fantastic in Dune. I'm confused as to whether I'm going to
like Dune because I love Derival but hated Blade Runner 2049. I have no idea which end of the
Villeneuve scale this movie is going to be on. It depends what you hated about Blade Runner 2049 I
think. I think mostly the the the writing acting and direction. It was very pretty. Well I think
it says a different writer and different actors but the same director so let's see. Okay. The things
I didn't like about Blade Runner 2049 were largely about the agency of women in the film and the
directorial approach to that and this is also a problem with Dune just because Dune is a novel
written 60 years ago by a white guy and and it's kind of like Dune works within that and it does
lots of things to try to get over some of that but it kind of you know it's got its source material
and and if that's a problem then it remains a problem. So one of the particular problems with
Blade Runner 2049 is Villeneuve's male gaze and although there's a little bit of that in this film
it's not irritating in the same way or at least it didn't irritate me in the same way. It's not as
good a film as a rival but then there aren't very many such films that are as good as a rival and
it's also only half the book so we need to see Dune part two to really draw conclusions about
where he's going with all of this and he said he wants to do Dune Messiah as well so he can do
the whole story of pull. I think that's fair because I think some of the like more male
gay-Z bits of Dune are explicitly because they're kind of from Paul's perspective and so they help
remind us like who his character is and I've now forgotten what was your other point about Dune
about Blade Runner? I remember now which is that yeah I think Dune you know basically gender swaps
on the characters in order to improve that and it works perfectly well. I went to Croydon
and attended an in-person gaming event with 43 other people. That's my pick.
What sort of gaming event? I'll give you three guesses. Oh it would be an Arkham horror thing.
Yes guess one correct. It was a thing called Arkham Knights.
And how did it how's your sanity? My sanity I came out alive and they kind of gave a lot of swag away
and they did loads of games and it was good. We played a thing called the blob the blob that ate
everything. The blob ate our ability to eat food and drink which was very annoying for the cafe
we were playing in because the way to skip coming around and saying do you want anything we're like
we can't blob-et it and explaining that to someone who doesn't know the game is a bit complicated.
But it was very fun and we won and it was good there's a big group photo that I'll put in the
show notes but at this event I played a game which is new which is called Unfathomable and it is a
social deduction game set on a 1910s ocean liner called The Atlantica and you are crossing from
Southampton to Boston when you are attacked by deep ones and the game is basically you fending
off these deep ones as you try and get to Boston. But some of you are in fact deep one hybrids and
you are working against the group to try and sow discord and mayhem. And if this sounds like a
familiar premise to you and you have played the battle cycle act like a board game that is because
it is indeed based off the battle act like a board game. It's a lot better than the battle
cycle act like a board game so if you've played that and you're like oh god I hate that game
it's so badly paced and it takes too long they have fixed the pacing issues and it takes less time
so that's good. It's also a social deduction game where if you are sitting thinking aha I am
terrible at social deduction games because I am a bad liar and I do not like playing games where
that is a problem for me. It's a game where you can immediately announce you are a hybrid and just
be very obvious about your sabotages or you can be very subtle and sneaky and do it that way. So
it's a game that kind of rewards both playstyles which I think is good and I really really enjoyed
it which is good because I'd already bought a copy but it's nice to know that I won't have to
sell the copy I bought. Hoorah! The and I will also say the ludicrous in Croydon is possibly the best
board game cafe in the UK it is very good I would highly recommend if you live anywhere near it
going to it is lovely. That feels like I should have an entire weekend where we go and stay with
friends in Croydon and spend one day at the ludicrous playing board games and one day at Flip Out
Pinball. Would you take those friends and go and play Alkam Horror with them? Well Alison.
I mean I might need ropes my entire and then it might actually become kidnap rather than escorting.
I will do a quick pick. I am continuing to work through the Hugo finalists because having thought
oh the Hugo's late this year I have plenty of time I in fact have three weeks. Who could have
thought that would happen? I know who could have who could have considered this so I read one of
the best novella nominees The Empress of Salt and Fortune by Nivo. I will know actually all the best
novella finalists are from Tor.com this year they have really been putting out a lot of good novellas
and this is it's a nice fancy novella it's basically a cleric who is going around trying to collect
the history of the Empress's life or Aspect's Empress's life after this Empress has died
and so she goes to the house in which the Empress is once exiled and here's the story of the Empress
from Rabbit who is an early woman who turns out to have been the Empress's servant and they kind of
go around cataloging the contents of this palace and while they're cataloging it you kind of get
all the different aspects of the Empress's life you know she basically has a diplomatic
marriage to an emperor who banished it after he has an heir and you know she basically
secretly plans her revenge from exile with the help of her friends and servants and it sort of
you know tells that whole story and ended up being you know they're after the coronation of the new
Empress and it's just a nice setting I like the conceit of having like the cleric who is collecting
these stories and kind of what is what is Rabbit telling the narrator and what is she not telling
her the idea that you know Rabbit is essentially goes overlooked because she is a peasant girl who
is a servant when actually she's one of the keys to the whole thing and I think it works really well
at novella length as well it gives you enough to kind of flesh out the characters but it didn't
need to be a really long story so I I very much liked it so I'm gonna read the rest of tour.com
best novella finalists now and see which one is best I've read the Empress of Salt of Fortune
I really liked it it is one of my two favorite novellas on the roster Liz so you may you may
disagree with you may think other ones are better than than I did but I thought the Empress of Salt
of Fortune was probably either the best or the second best I think it largely depends how much
you like Finnr which is a brilliant story set in an Ikea I loved that story but I know that it didn't
land for everyone if I tell you I've read three so far and Finnr is at the bottom of the pile
basically is said the the conceit is that there are parallel universes and the membrane
between the universes gets more porous when those universes are like closer to each other and Ikea's
they are especially porous because every little zone of an Ikea is basically its own parallel
universe anyway and so basically you can go to like interdimensional Ikea's and they do and it's
brilliant yeah I thought the conceit of Finnr was great and then the actual novella was like
just kind of a let down because it couldn't live up to conceit so do you guys know about the
people who filmed a series of YouTube stories in Ikea's around the world well really they're local
of Kea's amazing I did not know that and it gets very meta because it gets the point where every
Ikea in North America has the photos of these people taped up in the staff room saying if they
come on site because I mean Ikea's a great place to film your home video right because they've
got all the sets that was the Octa thought podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me
and it's goodbye from me
[Music]
I don't know is there a kind of clean term for a giant large amount of something like metric
fuck ton but podcast appropriate you could just say a metric ton I guess it's not very much fun but
I mean I would say like a shitload and I guess it can't say on the podcast either
it's four in the funk and morning and your funk and hip hop is keeping me awake a metric
frack ton of power points and internet which made me very happy like that will that do yeah
fine I'd have kept the fuck ton in can I have one fuck the theme music for this episode was
fanfare for space by kevin mccloud and compactec.com used under a creative commons
attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]