Um, oh hang on, is there a live letter of comment?
I already did that one, cool.
Is a, is a live letter of comment just a spanner sharing at you from the other room?
In this case texting.
[Laughs]
[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 97th episode of Oct.
Thorpe, a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom,
which is coming to you on the 23rd of November, 2023.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
And today we have heard from some people about some things.
Who?
Who did we hear from John?
We heard from Lee Edmonds who wrote about historical sources vis-a-vis NASFIC.
Lee tells us that we can blame the NASFIC on Australia.
So there we have it.
And then, leaded some more research and said, "No, you can't."
It's more complicated than that.
And basically goes into a lot of detail.
So when the Wussfiz Constitution was first amended,
so it used to be that the Wussfiz Constitution was split into
split the US into zones.
So the Worldcon couldn't be held in the same zone of the US twice in a row, basically.
And this has been superseded by something in the Wussfiz Constitution
that means you can't hold it within.
I think it's 500 miles of the city at which site selection is conducted,
which is an attempt to prevent it just staying in the same place every other year.
And goes into a lot of detail about how the NASFIC was added
as part of a lot of stuff to do with overhauling that.
So the NASFIC came into being when Wussfiz moved away from that mechanism
to force the convention to travel.
And his Spaniard told me, and I did not know this,
that Westercon started originally because the people who went to the first Westercon
were so annoyed that the Worldcon was always on the East Coast.
And so they started Westercon to be on the West Coast.
I might just paste this somewhere and link to it from the show notes,
because it's very interesting.
Yes, thank you for your research, Lee.
I think you do deserve a quiet lie down after trying to work out
what was going on with the NASFIC and Worldcon constitutions in 1970.
This is what Lee lives for these days, research into incredibly
obstruscent complicated things.
I have one of his books for a fanfunds auction,
which is all about the history of a company that made bacon.
I realise I'm at risk here of a deluge of emails,
but if anyone else wants to research obscure,
fanist history topics and then email us about them,
I like reading them.
I can't go and too will read them all out,
depending on how long your letters get.
No, yes, thank you very much again.
That was very good.
We also heard from Ispania, who asked on Mastodon
whether there would be a photograph of us in purple octthorpshirts
in a purple premier in room at Glasgow.
There might be, except I don't have an octathorpshirts,
but I have purple Glasgow shirt.
No, it would have to be an octathorpshirts.
I may skip out of the premier in at the point where Glasgow launches
its actual room rates, right?
You might.
I might, but I might not, depends on the room rates.
My premier in booking is cancelable,
and the intention was always to slip into a Glasgow room if those looked like they were better.
So in the perfectly public programme item at Novicon,
where Esther updated everyone on Glasgow things,
she said quite a lot of rooms at between 150 and 180 pounds a night,
but not all, obviously quite a lot of more than that as well.
Like the lower end of that is still starting above what I'm paying for premier in if I'm in it.
So yeah, andals, but also it'll include breakfast.
So maybe include breakfast.
We'll see. Anyway, all of this is wild speculation at the moment.
January is the date we have for room bookings.
I mean, the other problem is that fans have wildly bid up the premier in
room pricing by all booking a year out, and then if we all cancel it,
the price won't come back down.
We also heard from Christopher J. Garcia.
He said Taff was the first time fandom changed his life,
and that's only happened twice.
I think Chris is trying to get us to ask what the other time was,
but I refuse Chris, I refuse.
Chris, what was the other time?
Do write in and tell us?
You panda to him, you spoil him.
Yeah, well, it's 2023, so that's fiction year of the panda, isn't it?
Laurie Anderson on Facebook appreciated your hanger jokes.
Laurie Anderson on Facebook is a person of impeccable taste and judgement,
who went into detail on street addresses.
Do you want to tackle that, Liz?
Yes, in a minute when I get up.
Yes.
Laurie, yes, said me again, maybe I should have sent an email.
We accept emails, Facebook comments,
Macedon messages, Twitter messages.
We might just occasionally miss them and not realise for six months.
Laurie would interpret postal address to mean mailing address,
as distinct from residential street address,
which I think is just confusing things more,
because now we've got mailing address, residential address,
street address and postal address,
and they could all reasonably be interpreted different ways
by a different set of people in a different country.
She does say that she hopes postal address does not end up being defined
as residential address, because it will endanger those people
who use a PO books for safety reasons, which is a good answer.
My brain is working at like 50% capacity, so I cannot say residential address.
So yeah, the agenda for the business meeting,
I think the one that won was the one that dictated postal address,
but it says postal specifically.
So I would agree that Laurie's interpretation was probably correct,
but like, I don't know, it annoyingly vague.
She also says that we should take a shot every time someone says pro-keal
and then go directly to hospital.
That was it, that was all the letters of comment.
Ooh!
Yeah, if you have any comments, please write in.
But what do you Chengdu News? Chengdu's!
How have we got this far without that joke?
I think Liz wanted to discuss this, so would you care to introduce it Liz?
Yeah, now I have to be coherent for 30 seconds.
Okay, so Chengdu further follow up.
It seems like more con reports are coming out,
especially ones from the Chinese attendees who I admit
I've been reading these reports only through Google Translate,
so I'm going to get the gist but not specific nuances.
But it does seem like there's been a bit of a divide in the experience
between maybe the foreign fans who were looked after very well
and the Chinese fans who do not seem to have got such a good deal out of it.
And we'll link to one of the issues reports in the show notes,
but there seem to be a lot of things with foreign attendees
generally being in the closest hotel, the hotel price for that hotel being extremely high.
Anyone who voted at DISCOM would have already had a full attending membership,
whereas it seems it was quite hard to buy memberships and some of them sold out.
Issues with people volunteering and then not actually hearing anything
back about their volunteering offers,
although that is not going to be exclusively a Chengdu problem,
that is a problem of all conventions I think,
especially World Cons, things through the cracks.
But it does seem like the attendees came back and kind of said,
"Wow, this was great!"
I think a lot of them had a handler to help them get around,
to help them with issues with translation and things like that,
and they were in a close buy hotel, and it was kind of easy to deal with,
and then some of the attendees not having such a good time.
So I think it's going to be interesting to see maybe in a year from now or six months from now,
when everything is settled down, how people feel it went,
and whether Chinese fandom thinks this was good, we want to do it again,
or do they think this was not good, we want to do it again and do it better,
or do they think, "No, that was it, we've had a WILK on now, we're done."
- Hmm, yeah, no, it will be interesting.
- I think when we listen to some of the things that Chinese fans are saying about it,
they are giving the impression that it kind of all got taken away from them.
So something that they felt started as a fan generated idea,
became something very, very different to the end.
Certainly a lot more money was spent on the WILK on
than could be accounted for by the admission fees.
- Weirdly, I keep getting invited to physics conferences in Chengdu at the moment.
I don't know why.
- Mm-hmm, same basic deal is it.
Somebody's paying for all of the costs of the physics conference,
and presumably, maybe Chengdu University just has a lot of money.
- Oh yeah, I'm sure it's completely above board, etc.
It is interesting to see the reports coming out.
I'm glad that everyone who had a good time had a good time,
and I hope it was a net good for Chinese fandom, but we shall see.
- I want to say I like living in the future because I like the fact that I can understand
nearly all of a Chinese report on the WILK on by putting it into Google Translate.
And even a couple of years ago, that wouldn't have been the case.
Things are moving very fast in those automatic translation and automatic transcribing spaces.
- Yes, getting all of this stuff translated would be non-trivial.
- Well, it's so good that when there's a word that's been translated wrong,
it was like, I think the astounding award got translated by Google as the surprise award.
And the translation is so good that when something like that happens,
I realize I've forgotten I'm reading it in Google Translate until I notice something
that's obviously wrong.
And I go, "Oh right, remember, the whole thing is in Google Translate so you are losing nuance."
I think that's just a very, I think there's a lot more you're losing, a lot more nuance.
I think that's just the very obvious thing that pops up there.
Because you're going to miss things, like there's incredibly subtle things in language
that we're not getting in, especially here where they're criticizing a lot of the stuff that happens.
I don't know how harsh some of this criticism is.
I don't know how much I should think this is in an angry tone or a fairly resigned to it tone.
Like there's all that sort of thing that I would be picking up if I was reading this in English
that I'm missing.
So factual stuff is good, but I can't really get too much about how the author feels.
It seems like the author feels pretty angry about it, but I don't know if that's just because that's
how it's been translated, like words like irresponsible and things like that.
I think there's a lot of like potential ways to translate that.
We might be getting off topic into translation, but I think there's that.
And also when I read things by different authors that have been put through Google Translate,
I'm not sure I could tell you major differences between the writing styles, which I could if they
were languages I could read.
There's two things. I've got two things and then we'll move on to more on topic things,
which is firstly, obviously it's very difficult to compare a Google translation into English
versus reading it in the original language if you don't speak the original language, right?
So like I speak a little bit of Spanish, so I have like a vague idea of this,
but like not anywhere near enough to comment qualifiably.
But second comment, obviously this is why God gave us emoji,
because if you use emoji, they won't need translating and you'll understand exactly how
angry someone is. So just use normal, nice, basic words and have loads of emoji.
That has the future of language people you heard it here first.
Winky face.
Shitty Tingrin emoji.
Can that be the episode title? Perhaps not.
And obviously there's still no stats. One day there will be stats.
Stats, stats, stats.
We've been told we'll have stats by the latest day in which Chengdu is not in violation of its
responsibilities under the Wistles Constitution.
Did I see and Liz might, one of you might have been on the discord.
I'm sure some posted link which is like has it been 90 days since Chengdu yet or something like that?
It might have been a dream.
Maybe for Christmas Santa will bring us stats.
I'm also going to point out like if Chengdu missed the deadline for publishing the Hugo stats,
what's going to happen?
Nothing would happen.
Exactly.
On the topic of Chengdu, the Wistles first minutes aren't out yet, but there have been
reports and there are videos of what went on.
So we're going to discuss that all a little bit here.
And to do that we'll need
Liz bat to the Batmobile, Liz bat.
What they've now published on the Wistles first site is the updated Constitution and
Standing Rules which basically means it includes everything that was ratified or was a rule
change that didn't need ratification that took effect in 2023.
So you can now look at the new Constitution if you want because they highlight the changes.
So the changes are pretty minimal in the actual Constitution which is to include
best game and interactive work and a definition of game or interactive work and also to remove
the rule by which no award is given if it's less than 25% of the total number of award ballots in any
category.
So those I think we agree are both great changes.
Good to see them.
Hooray, but they also amended the standing rules which are kind of the rules by which
the governance of the business meeting takes place.
And there's now an extra one at the end.
Rule 7.9 proxy and remote voting only Wistles members physically present at the business
meeting shall be recognized for purpose is to debate or may move second or vote on motions
on the floor of the meeting proxy voting is not permitted.
So this was not in the agenda that was on the website and when I went and looked at the
recording of the preliminary meeting and I've got to thank Kevin Stanley for putting up
and making the recordings of the business meetings at Chengdu so we can even go and look at this.
It basically comes up very, very late that there was a super late change the standing rules to put
this in.
It was felt that it kind of formalizes the current practice of business meetings not to
allow any proxy or remote voting and so it kind of was thought to be just kind of an
explanatory change to the rules and so it could pass in one year.
Yes, by six votes to four.
Yeah, so I think so basically this was done, this was brought by Dave McCarthy and
waved through by the 10 people in the room because as it stood this was not ruled against or four
in the standing rules and so it does seem a little bit crappy that Dave did this.
I think it acts to preserve the status quo and preserve the privilege of the people in the room
without much thought for what might be good for the community going forward and yeah,
I just I was a little bit sad to see this happen and I don't think it reflects well on any of the
people who enabled it.
It's my basic take.
So Kevin Stanley is posted to say, oh no, it's not like that.
Where something's not covered in your standing rules, you kind of go to the generic Roberts
Rules of Order to see what you should be doing and the generic Roberts Rules of Order say no
proxies or remote participation unless you already have provision for it in your organizing documents.
So therefore it is his argument is this is a clarification because we didn't have anything
and so so it actually was automatically part of the rules because we were using Roberts Rules of
Order.
Let me go back to saying Roberts Rules of Order is completely unfit for purpose for parliamentary
work in the 21st century or even the 20th.
It was getting out of hand by the end of the 19th.
We should have a better parliamentary system.
I understand that that might never happen because it's quite a complicated thing to sort out but
still.
But that's the issue is that apparently Roberts Rules already has this provision in it.
So by not having the thing in a standing order, it doesn't mean, oh, you can do online participation
if you like.
It means, oh, you should go back and use whatever Roberts Rules says generically.
I do think this was pretty underhand anyway.
If you were going to do this, you would probably want to let people know in advance you were
going to do it.
I feel like six votes to four.
The quorum for the Worcester Business Meeting is more than that though, of course, presumably
some people abstained in this vote.
Yeah, I mean what I'd say is if it's already, so if this is already just making explicit
something that we think was covered already by the rules, then I don't know why there was
need to put it in as like a super last minute thing that wasn't on the public agenda.
Because if it's not on the public agenda and people don't know it's happening,
then they might think, well, actually, I don't need to go to the preliminary business meeting,
which is mostly about setting times for debate and doing objections to things that we don't
want to debate.
You might skip that and think you'll turn up on the next morning for the main business
meeting and you've actually maybe missed an important bit of business.
Well, and the answer to your question of why would you do it like this is duplicity.
Simply put, I think, like, you know, I don't want to be too mean, but yeah, it just leaves
a bad taste in the mouth.
Or propose a rule change.
Yeah.
Glasgow.
Why not?
You want to spend all of Glasgow in the business meeting, right, John?
Do we want to talk about independent film?
Yeah, I want to talk about independent film because the reason I'm not going to be
introducing a new amendment on remote participation, though, obviously, I'll enthusiastically support
anybody who does, is I'm going to be busy trying to kill a pair of new hughos for long-form
and short-form independent film, which have been half ratified with zero attention or care
directly due to the fact that the World Cod does not have online participation of voting,
because if it did do, it wouldn't have passed because the usual suspects would have stopped it
from doing so.
Are you sure?
Because if you're in, I'm just saying, if you could even out participation, not only would
maybe the usual suspects of remote participation in, but maybe loads and loads of other people,
maybe loads of Chinese people in the program?
So last episode, we speculated that maybe some of these amendments and whatnots that were
made and need ratification at Glasgow had been made by Chinese fans who were just like,
you know, I get to be in the meeting and I get to propose a thing for a thing I like
and it gets it in the conversation and hurrah.
And I was like, "Oh, that is actually a fair thing to say and it's a good thing and we don't
want to just be three Westerners opposing, you know, what Chinese fans want from a nominally
world organisation."
But it turns out the person who is trying to get these independent film hughos through
is Louis Avi, who runs sci-fi London, which the astute listener may notice London is not in China.
And so this does not look like it is a grassroots, enthusiastic Chinese thing.
It looks rather more like it's someone with an interest in independent film trying to force
through a hugho on independent film without really engaging with the community first,
which suddenly recasts it from me thinking, "Oh, well, it's kind of adorable, but I don't think
it will work." And I go from that basic opinion to, "This is what the sad puppies were trying to do,
and I oppose it extremely vehemently."
So it has completely recontextualised my thoughts on this with one screenshot of a
Facebook post, which is really interesting. What do we think?
Previously on this podcast, we may have suggested that Louis Savi was a generally good egg and
that we were big fans of the London Sci-Fi Film Festival. We just wanted you to know that we have
now changed our minds and he's confirmed rota. No, we have not changed our minds. You have changed
your minds. So yeah, no attributing opinions to me that I do not personally have.
I don't think he's a rota, but I am deeply uncomfortable with it.
So all I would say is we've seen a post from Louis Savi on the Glasgow Facebook group saying he
was hoping to come to Glasgow and help push through the ratification of these things.
What we don't know, and I think we're speculating quite a lot, is whether the people who proposed
in China were actually supportive independent film in China or whether they were just people he
had found to kind of propose it. We don't know to what extent there is a grassroots movement or
rather not a grassroots movement, but maybe just a big movement of independent film in China,
which possibly Louis is well aware of because he's really deeply into independent film.
And also I think it's better fair to say he's coming in from outside. I mean, he ran the film
program in 2014. He's not a complete outsider to the community. Okay. Yeah, no, that's fair.
And you know, they had the Clark Awards at sci-fi London for a long time as well.
Yeah, I don't think he's a rota. I think these are very badly founded hugos, and this is a real
problem if they were to pass next year. I think there is a differentiation. I guess it depends
which community you're talking about, right? Because I'm very much specifically talking about
the WorldCon community. I had not appreciated he was involved with programme for LondonCon,
but I don't know that I think having the clerks at sci-fi London means you're part of the World
Con community because I think the clerks and WorldCon are separate things that are interlinked.
And in my defence, he does say in the post he proposed the Hugo Awards. So I am assuming,
therefore, that he proposed to them. But if he did not, then that is an error and I regret it.
But he must have had some people helping out to get them passed. So, but this is one of the
reasons we the minutes, I suppose. We may need to listen to more video as well that we haven't
listened to yet. Yeah, but it just, it slightly frustrates me because the other thing is
that if this was something that he had felt, there's an optic to this, which is choosing to do it in
China when you know that there won't be many people at the business meeting and you know the
next meeting will be in your home territory, does not feel like it wasn't a considered decision to
make it more likely that this would get through. And maybe that is me putting a lot of negative
like assumptions on him, but the optics of it are not great. I think that's definitely how it can
be observed whether it was the intention or not. Because if you know the business meeting, you know,
the Chinese, the Chengdui one was going to be sparsely attended and probably easier to pass
stuff at. And that's going to be the impression people get, even if you didn't actually know that
you just knew that there were independent film fans in China who might be amenable to
helping with this proposal. Okay, having said that clearly savvy is a rata, how about taking
that the other way around and going, oh no, if I want to do this, I want to have the ratification
discussions at Glasgow, because it's in the UK and Chengdu just happens to be the year before.
Why don't know? I still think it's weird that you'd think about it in terms of the ratification
discussion. I think that's what's the red flag for me. Because yeah, look at best game
ratification. The substantial discussion happened the year it passed, not the year it got ratified,
although because the ratification was in Chengdui. But you know, normally you were seeing substantial
discussion happen before something gets on there, not things not being ratified. So it will be a
bit of a difference to the usual procedure. Yeah, it will. It would be terrible if these passed.
It will be interesting to see, in fact, Glasgow, you know, a few people turn up who quite like this
Hugo and it's resoundingly defeated. That makes it look a lot less problematic than it does if
sort of 50 independent filmmakers turn up an all enthusiastic leave out to ratfly.
So it'll be interesting to see what happens. I'm going to reserve judgment, but it definitely
feels a bit hinky in a way that I don't enjoy. And maybe I'm just like on edge after the last
kind of stuff that's happened in the last 10 years with the Hugo's. I don't know, I'm a bit wary of
people trying to change things through fiat rather than through community involvement.
Well, hopefully there'll be a year of discussion about it and the best outcome will be if
then that comes up with a list of really good independent short films to watch.
I mean, I'm also just aware that we're basically never going to get rid of any Hugo category ever.
So I don't want to just keep adding them at the rate of two or three year.
The problem is that the Hugo categories until now have always subdivided Hugo content. So that
was the reason we had that huge argument about the young adult Hugo that became load style.
So these don't, these are extra Hugo's for things that are already winning Hugo's.
I mean, Tamsa Muir could have won two Hugo's this year. I know they're not for exactly the
same thing, but one would be a subset of the other. Okay, so don't make me hate best series again.
I mean, I'm certainly up for having best novel have a provision that is best novel,
open brackets, not part of a longer series, close brackets. And if you ever write a sequel,
we come and take your Hugo away.
Break into their house. I presume that this is also a problem with novel because
so although Flowers for Algon and didn't win the Hugo in his novel form, it did win the
nebula after having won the Hugo for its short story form. And so it is already true that
if you write a short story, Hugo just did the episode about the Danny novella, which is basically
just the Danny chapters of Game of Thrones published as a novella before it came out.
I presume that would have been eligible as a novella and then Game of Thrones would have been
eligible in novel. So I think part of the problem here is that it's very difficult in the
because obviously short story through to series all are basically rewarding text storytelling.
Like, you know, you can rework those things in various ways that might mean you end up being
eligible more than once for similar work. Yeah, but the independent films are for the same thing.
They are eligible in both categories. You wouldn't want everything everywhere to win
two Hugo's in the same year for exactly the same. I mean, maybe you would,
because lots of people liked it, but like, I would like it to.
But I mean, the everything everywhere problem expresses the main problem here, which is
what counts as independent, what's an independent film, what's an independent brewery.
What will happen with this, even if you had it almost certainly is that for the long form,
certainly you'd get the most widely, it would be an award for most widely distributed independent
film, which is not necessarily what you want. Yeah, I don't know because we don't have the
minutes yet. I don't know what the definition of independent is. I think it was probably on the
agenda, but I don't know whether it got changed in the room. But I think in general, I don't love it
when an attempt to add a Hugo is coming from someone who is directly involved with enterprises
that make money from the thing they are trying to get a Hugo in for. And so I would actually mind
much less again if it was someone who just really liked independent film and didn't run
an independent film festival, because I do understand that that probably means you have a lot of
affection for the form, but it also means it gets hard for me to disentangle the less noble
incentives from the more noble ones, if that makes sense. But that might be unfair, I don't know.
It reminds me of the push for a Hugo for Best Audio book, which was suggested by a paid-up
member of the audio book publishing industry. Yeah. Sorry, I've got very distracted trying to
work out if I'm a Caffrey managed to win a Hugo for the same thing twice. Oh, good knowledge.
No, is the answer. Listeners, if you can think of any instance where someone did win a Hugo for
the same thing twice right in. Martha Wells. I mean, Lois McMaster-Boudjold, if we go in that
route, but that's not quite what I meant. Okay, sorry, no, I finished checking and she didn't.
It's because she won for Novella, which became the first half of a novel, but that novel was not
nominated for Hugo. The sequel to it was nominated for Hugo. So I think we're good. That was a nice
D-rail, wasn't it? Sorry. Lovely. I still don't think that winning a Hugo for Best Series is the
same as winning a Hugo for something that's component part of Best Series, but by C-Darguant.
But that isn't that exactly the same novel argument as if you win a Hugo for a Novella that then becomes
part of your Hugo winning novel. I don't also don't really have a problem with that. Yeah, okay.
The argument I'm in fact making is I think it's not like Flowers from Algonon wouldn't have deserved
the Hugo for its novel form if people thought it was the best novel that year despite the fact
that I had previously won for short story. It is sort of exactly my point really.
Glasgow have a press release. They have announced their online attendance plan. Their online convention
experience is going to do lots of things which are great. It is going to be based on hopping events
from Ring Central for video streaming and Discord for text interaction and community forums and
all adult and younger adult attending members will automatically receive full access or you can buy
a online attending ticket for £35 which will give you full access to the online experience.
I mean or you could buy an online attending membership which also includes Wussfuss membership
for £75. So yes. Yeah, and there's a discount for existing Wussfuss members to update to online.
And hopping events, their streaming platform is Streamyard which people who came to punctuation
remember. Oh yeah, it works. I like it. So we're trailblazers. They're much bigger now and they do
much more things but that's Streamyard at its heart. That is fair. Yeah, I think Streamyard
seemed quite straightforward for participants to get the hang of. We've got to say and you can have
like someone in there secretly, you know, putting the spotlight on different people and muting
things and turning things on and off and putting a presentation up which means you don't end up
with the kind of 10 minutes of, oh, can you see my screen? Oh, I'll just turn it on and off the
screen sharing. Oh, can you see my screen? Oh, it's in presenter view. Oh yeah.
Yeah, but Liz, stop talking about the beginning of this podcast and let's get back to discussing
Glasgow. Yes, I misread the press release but yes, you can, if you're an existing WISFS member,
you can upgrade to an online attending member for cheap. So that's good and it will be lovely.
You know, I think it should be lovely. I have huge faith in the people who are doing tech for
Worldcon and I think they're going to do a good job. I'm glad that they're using a platform I
have some familiarity with and I'm also glad that they decided that Discord was the way to do
text chat and that that was a useful thing to do because I think
Discords have been great for conventions over the last couple of years and I want them for all
conventions really. Yeah, don't make me learn another platform now. I'm too old. I'm stuck now.
I'm never going to progress best Discord. But they are suggesting that they're going to do some
virtual events in the new year so that we can all get used to the platform well in advance of the
convention. So that sounds exciting too. So hopefully by the time the convention comes around, we'll
all have used the virtual stuff and have found out how it works. Yes. And as a result of that,
the last Glasgow Presents events, we mentioned Glasgow Presents a few weeks ago, was last night.
Alison hosted it listeners. I hosted it. Yes, I was moderating Peter Espiegel and Catherine
M. Valente in conversation. Ooh. I don't think your name was on the poster. I don't think your
name is on the poster in big letters next to Peter Espiegel. For some reason, for some reason my
day was not on the poster, but I was the person managing the questions and lots of people came
along to the event bright and lots of people watched on YouTube and it was just great. Thank
you everyone to Cucame and it's interesting if you're interested in Beagle and I know you probably
have to be a person of a certain age. There were a lot of people of a certain age in the audience,
I'd say, who were very inspired by Beagle's work when they were kids. But also, Kat Valente
writes Middle Grade, I think. So she's going to have a very different following. And the thing
starts with a me cute about how Kat Valente met Peter Beagle. So, which is well worth listening to.
Do we want to do NovaCon? I've got a tiny touch, I just want to say, I went to NovaCon,
neither of you came to NovaCon. Somebody bounded up to me and said, "When is Octa thought live with
Stunt John and Stunt Liz?" I was like, "Oh, you're drinking with it right now." You should have,
you should have a pint glass that says Octa thought live on it. So whenever you're at a
convention on your own, you can just be, you can have Octa thought live. No, I was not in NovaCon,
I was somewhere else. Where was I? Oh, I was cottaging. We had quite nice weather, so
Buxton was absolutely lovely. And there's a new beer bar. So it really is just like,
we get up in the morning, we walk out of the hotel into this street full of lovely beer
shops and drink beer all day, and then come back and then repeat. And then there's the beer tasting.
And there was also the Glasgow gin tasting, which I managed to get to a short amount of.
But there was phenomenal advantage in that, so I got to say I was about 50 miles from NovaCon
and I didn't go. Oh, well, you guys were missing out, it was great. I nearly did, but then I had to go home.
That is reasonable. Guests of honour for an Overcon 53 has been announced, and it is Alan
Stroud, the chair of the BSFA. But I'm glad you had fun Alison, I'm glad you drank lots of gin.
I drank lots of beer and lots of gin, I have a lovely time actually, it was good.
Sorry, I didn't mean to leave out the beer and I regret the error.
And lots of gossip. Way. Lots of, lots of Spanish gossip.
Okay, so now it's time for pics. So, shall I do mine then?
Goliath. Yes. Yes. So, I think I've actually mentioned this on the pod before. My pick this
week is Goliath by Toki Onyubuchi, which is another of these books that people say,
oh, this is one of the best books of 2022, but unaccountably it did not appear on award short lists.
And so what is it? It is a book of the near future. We are in an America where most of the rich people
have fucked off to space, and we have a bunch of people who are left behind on Earth.
We learn a lot about the world, but we learn a lot about the world kind of in the sidelines of
the book for reasons that I'm about to explain. But the people that we are mostly spending time with
are kind of scraping a living together from what remains on Earth after most people have gone.
So those people form the bulk of the protagonists of the book, and then we also see two
gentrifiers. The book is called Goliath, and the gentrifiers are called David and Jonathan,
and they have decided to return to Earth and make a life there because they think that it will be
more real better, or Jonathan thinks it will be more real and better to live in the actual world
with air and nature and things of that kind, and also obviously a lot of pollution and a whole lot
of crime and other things going wrong. This book is difficult, and the reason that it's difficult
is that it is told in a series of fragmentary scenes from lots of different points of view.
They are differently spaced in time. You are given almost no clues as to who is narrating each
section, or why, or you work it out. So in general it is a book that is much harder work
than most of the books that I have read recently that are SFN Fantasy. I think probably it's a decade
since I read a science fiction book that was as hard to read as this. So I kind of stopped reading
it the first time and put it down. It was only because a couple of the people who think that it
definitely should have been on the short lists told me to pick it up again, that I picked it up again
and finished it, and I really, really enjoyed it. But like I think a lot of novels that are not
science fiction novels, but very few science fiction novels, you have to work out what's going on
from things that you're not necessarily told. You're expected to do some of the work to come to
this and understand what is the story that you're doing told, what has actually happened here.
I guess some people, so therefore lots of people hate it. Goodreads has got about a third, I think,
people who were minded to say that they did not finish this book of the reviews on there.
It's very rewarding if you keep at it. I don't think the individual parts fitter are very hard,
but certainly piecing together what's going on was plenty hard enough for me. I thought what was
going on was very good because I think the story it's telling is quite an important one. I couldn't
help comparing it with the previous novel I'd read, which was Babel, which I really didn't like very
much because Babel not only tells you everything it wants you to know, but it tells you everything
it wants you to know two or three times in increasingly strident terms, especially with footnotes.
And it's kind of a real palate cleanser after that because it was kind of saying no, we can write
an important novel about modern America and racism and the near future and the sort of society that
we might find ourselves in if we just carry on the track we're on without having to tell you
everything very explicitly all of the time. So strongly recommended hard work, you know,
set yourself some time to do some reading. I've not read Goliath and I have only one opinion about
it therefore, which is, and I don't know if I've ever banged this drum on the pod, but there will
be people in the audience who have heard me whine about this before, which is the title of Goliath
is Goliath, colon, a novel. And I'm like, oh good, I was worried it was a kitchen sink. I do not
understand. It would be like if Monopoly was called Monopoly a game. Yes, we know why it winds me up.
Lots of games are called a game. Is it called Goliath and novel? It just said Goliath. Yes, I've just
put links to it in the show note, Alison, and I bristled. Um, obviously this is not a comment on the
merit of the work in terms of, um, you know, any reasonable metric. This is just a soap box that I
found and decided to stand off. I think this is just on your British lawyers. He probably said,
no, it's definitely called Goliath. You cannot call it anything else. The, the biblical story of
Goliath is critical to the, to the reading that you'll have of this. And the lawyers will have said,
but no, we need to separate it from all the other Goliath's out there. Um, how about if we call it
David and Goliath? He was like, no, no, no, or, or Goliath, a story of the far future. And that'll be
where they ended up. No, no, it's, it's the same as, um, so like, if you look on hive.co.uk and you
type in a novel, there are so many books that have the subtitle a novel. Like Dan Morin's first book
has a subtitle, a novel. And there's definitely nothing else called Caledonian Gambit. It's just,
it's a publisher thing. I can't imagine the author caring, but yeah, it drives me up the wall. Anyway,
publisher affectation. Yes, but I'm glad you liked it. Can I also complain then? Oh, yes, Liz, you can
complain. I haven't read Goliath and I really want to read Goliath. I'm just waiting for kind of the
right time to read it, which probably would have been when I could dominate the wards, but too late.
Um, but what I was, no, I was, because I was going to complain about a completely different thing,
which is I did try for a while having a policy of I'm not buying anything, which has got an
incredibly long winded subtitle on Amazon to make it pop up in searches. Like, I'm never buying a
TikTok main me buy it or the most emotional romance of 2023 from the Sunday Times bestselling author
or, you know, TikTok maybe buy it the addictive and darkly romantic fantasy, but I had to give up
because there are actually books I wanted to read which are all in this, the bestseller you
have seen on TikTok. But just to know is me, just give me the name of the book. One other thing I
remember what I did want to say about it is that it reminds me a lot of quite a lot of SF from the
70s, which was experimental and literary in just this way. Balard, priest, those sorts of people.
Oh no, I think your mistaken priest doesn't write science fiction. He just writes words.
Yes. Well, he wrote a set of words called fugue for a darkling island in which the story then gets
chopped up and reordered before you read it and Goliath is a desire to read us that.
I thought I always used to think Chris Priest was being very cantankerous about these things and
then I had an argument in the pub and I'm full on Chris Priest's side now. genres are a lie.
Yes. So there are a lot of people going, is this book science fiction? And I mean,
obviously it's science fiction, but people read it as not science fiction because it's kind of a
work of the near future. And so somehow that speculative fiction of therefore literary and
not science fiction at all, it's obviously science fiction guys. Or 100%. Why not? You have to
you have to bear in mind that it's speculative fiction. I mean, as opposed to all of the fiction,
which doesn't speculate, which we call nonfiction. A novel. Well, welcome to John is apparently
grumpy. You do have a bit of a cup on you today, actually. I thought I was quite cheerful and happy,
but maybe not. But we've destroyed it. Liz, do you want to talk about a book which as far as I can
tell does not have the subtitle a novel. So it does not have the subtitle novel, but it does have an
intriguing subtitle on Amazon last time I looked, which I would get into. So my pick of a book is
Titanium Noir by Nick Halkaway. It is a detective novel. So it is a noir novel about a detective
named Cal Sounder who gets called into work on particularly sensitive cases. And he gets called
into a murder scene. And what is interesting about this murder scene is that the victim is
extremely tall. And so what is going on here is that you have the titans of the title. And there
is an incredibly expensive gene therapy that only the super elite can have, which, you know,
resets your aging process and heals you, but also makes you taller. And so you have essentially this
like literal race of super men and women who have taken this anti-aging technology and come out
slightly taller. And these are the titans. And of course it's all about the super rich boss who
invented it and has taken the titan treatment multiple times and become this kind of giant godlike
man. Man rich enough that he is essentially a law unto himself, becoming like your, you know,
Noir, my boss or whatever. And the reason that Cal investigates these murders is that his ex-girlfriend
is the daughter of, you know, the boss of this massive empire. But why I liked it is because it's
it's a really good noir novel. It is kind of sparky and fun and has good dialogue and people
bouncing off each other and the detective goes to a bar to investigate and talks to the bouncers.
And it just feels fun to read. It's well paced. It's got an interesting mystery, I think,
that unravels very nicely. And I just think he's got a very good hook on the like, Noir feeling of it.
And then as this science fiction thing on top, if I was going to criticise, I would say, it's
it's a little bit literal. Like there are literally these people who are essentially the 1% the super
rich and they have now become literally healthier and younger and taller than us. And that is
a quite on the nose, not even metaphor is it? That's quite on the nose. And I don't think it does a
huge amount with it. But it is kind of sets up this fun, you know, society of have's and have not's
which is very much like our own except with this added, added twist. So yeah, I enjoyed it. And what
I was going to not quite complain about is that if you look it up on Amazon, it now says titanium
Noir brackets Cal sound a series, which means maybe there'll be a sequel. Then we can nominate it
for best series. Hey, other Hugo Awards are available.
Spoiler, did you, when you were doing your Hugo reading guys, read Ogas by Adrian Shikovsky?
Yes. No, well out of time. It was very, very, very good.
I mean, I thought it was pretty good. And I don't want to spoil that discussion too much.
And España was very annoyed by the, by one of the decisions he made in terms of the language of
the book. And then she was one of the things that really made her love it was that at the end,
it's justified in a way that she found very satisfying. I think I've been, yeah, I'd be
interested to see what you think of it as about really big people. Maybe. It's about Ogas.
It's about Ogas. Oh, yeah. No, I know what the language thing that you're complaining about is now.
Yes. Because I remembered, oh, yeah, no, that's something that always really irritates me. And I
thought Shikovsky actually managed to pull it off. And I that was amazing. Look, I might get to it,
but I've got 20, 20, through reading to be done. So I can make you all read my favorite books before
Hugo nomination time. Okay, I'm busy. Oh, there's too many books. Oh, there's too many books there.
There's another Shikovsky soon. Come on. Oh, God, the man works very hard.
I've got the Tragovsky on my birthday list, obviously, because I'm non-idiot.
Oh, happy birthday day, you've, by the way, we're recording this on your birthday.
40 today. Crazy. But I am in the last bit of the year after the Hugo Award deadline. And we know
what that means. It means it's time for John to read all the Star Wars and Arkham
Horror tie-in novels that he didn't get to in the rest of the year. Because I've read all of the
good books that people are like, you have to read this one. And now I can just read straight nonsense.
That's very fun. I'm going to pick The Wicker Man, which is a movie, not the Nicholas Cage one,
the 1973 one starring Edward Woodward, Britt Echlund, and Christopher Lee. 50th anniversary, right?
It is indeed the 50th anniversary. We went to see it as part of the
Whitley Bay Film Festival. And we went to see it in a village hall in a place called Earsden.
It was great. Slight spoilers for The Wicker Man will appear as part of me telling this story.
So like, but I don't think there's anything you wouldn't also have worked out from, you know,
the poster or its role in modern culture. So, you know, really good, really, really good.
Really enjoyed it. Really liked the way that it plays with the audience expectation in the
same way it plays with the main characters expectations, like build a sense of unease.
You understand what the main character is going through because you are also kind of like confused
about what is happening and what I mean by that is there is a lot of nudity in this movie,
like a lot. And I was a bit like, oh, I knew it was the 70s, but blind me.
See 1973.
So the main character is kind of a Christian fundamentalist, which is really interesting,
because the other thing you kind of have this like tension between his reaction to what's going
on, which is objectively very weird, very creepy, but also the fact that like his reaction to
what is going on is in some ways basically religious intolerance. So that's kind of
an interesting dynamic. But most interesting is that the bit at the end where they burn him in
the wicker man, they lit the village hall windows to make them look like they're on fire. And it
was amazing. It was so good.
Highly enjoyed it. I thought it was a really good film. So yeah, I'm glad that I watched it.
And it is homework for something I will inevitably pick on a future episode. So yeah, shall we wrap up?
And that was the AutoStore podcast. And it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me. And it's goodbye from me.
[Music]
Now it's time for Octa Thop Gaming Corner.
Have you played any games recently, Jod?
I went cottaging. Why? Yeah, I played some games. And it was, there's just so many games. But
I played Moon, which is very good. It's about the Moon. And have I through you played Villagers?
You say villages or villagers or villagers? Villagers. I think no. I don't think so.
I mean, it wasn't a trick question. Like, so yeah, so Villagers is like a kind of drafting
engine-building kind of game. And the same person who did that then did a game called Streets and
has now done a game called Moon. And they're in a sort of loose trilogy. Because obviously,
if you extrapolate, if you draw a line between villages and streets, and then you extrapolate that,
the next step is Moon. I think we can all agree. So he's made about to go out of the Moon. But it's
very good. It's very, very good. It's kind of very, it's like an engine builder,
tableau builder kind of game. And it's just really nice. And it comes with loads of adorable little
rovers. And it comes in a lovely box. And it was pretty great. I also played a game I loved the
Nick and Neil have. But last time I was at the house, I was like, this is a shrink wrap. We could
play this. And Neil was like, I don't think I want to play that. But it turns out it's really good.
Well, it's called Insider. And it's 20 questions. But one of you knows what the answer is to obviously,
the person answering the questions knows what the answer is. But then another person who is
ostensibly asking questions also knows what the answer is. And they have to try and get the group
to the answer without making it too obvious that they already know what it is. And that was real
good. We played that quite a lot. And we also played a game called Cheering Machine, which was
fine. I have played Cheering Machine quite a lot online. I thought that it was a bit
it felt like a bit like work, really. It didn't scratch my puzzling itch anything like as much as
people online seem to think it does for them. And I'd rather just be playing one of my little
road likes or something that does the same sort of thing, but in a in a less bored game way.
Yeah, I was really excited about Cheering Machine. And then I don't think I like it as much as
Cryptid or Search for Planet X. Like, so it's a kind of logical deduction game. But it's very solo.
Like there's vanishingly little player interaction. And yeah, I don't know. I just feel like having
played it. I'm not sure I really want to play it again, which is a better problem.
So the idea is you play it a few times and then you start making it harder. And the more harder you
make it, the better it gets people say. But I didn't I found it a bit kind of headcrunchy.
And and obviously then you then might need to handicap it for different people. It might be
one of those games like set where the same person will win every single time unless you're careful.
We played like the first two introductory games in the rule book. And then I was like,
well, this all seems fine. Let's just do the daily challenge. And I did the daily challenge
and I solved it in the same number of steps as I solved the second puzzle out of the rule book.
So I'm like, it might be that the daily challenge was just quite easy that day. But I have a worry that
yeah, I don't know. I'm just not sure if it ramps up the difficulty enough to keep my interest.
But I might just have gotten lucky with the challenge I played. I don't know. It's a shame
because it looked really cool. You know, Marianne and I played it because it takes no time to play
online. Marianne and I played it about nine times in an evening. So that's the other thing is that
it's part of what people like about it is the kind of physical box design, which game design,
which means that it solves the things using punch cards, which is kind of very retro and charming.
Yeah. I do know how that trick works because it's like binary chop. I played a game called
Hadrian's Wall, which I've been wanting to play for the longest time. And it's suddenly turned up
on board game arena. So we played it the other day. It is like the world's biggest, most complicated
role of right. But that is also extremely solo. So honestly, the only interaction between people
really is that you compare scores at the end of the game. You know, your your your Romans, your
building, Hadrian's Wall, you're you're doing other things. You have a lot of things to do.
It's really interesting because it generates a very lot of interesting game choices from
almost no randomness. So there's just like you draw a couple of cards at the beginning of each
round. There are six rounds. And apart from that, there's nothing random happening at all.
And yet there's the scope for a lot of it. So people do like it a lot.
Nice. Liz, have you played any board games? No. Oh, and that was the first board game I had
played for two months, John, two months. Yeah, because you were but you yeah. I went on my
tap trip. I saw my first board game cafe in Toronto, because that was when they were still like a new
quite whimsical idea. Okay, we'll let Liz go to sleep now or you know, stay up all night partying.
Liz is looking pretty tired. I'm playing a game.
What game are you playing? What right now? I'm playing this game that I think I linked in discord.
This the root trees are dead like deduction game. It's basically revenge of the Obra Din,
but a bit simpler in a new browser. And it's got tricky. Please put a link. Yes.
And that was how Alison got no more done today. Yeah, I really got sucked into it. So if I got
sucked into it, I'm a bit worried for Alison. I Obra Din, I played for three hours and then
stopped playing it and I've never picked up again, but I probably will pick it up again at some point.
Oh really? Remember, I like I prefer non-narrative games. Big butts and I cannot lie.
Oh, it's Obra Din narrative. Obra Din is a narrative game. I mean, it's a stop, you know, you're working,
it's a puzzle game, but you're working, you're working a thing out.
I mean, I liked it well enough and I, I shouldn't have stopped it. I just, you know,
I had somewhere to be. I just carried on playing until it was done.
So this is very similar, but there's like less blood. So you might like it. Did you also see that
there's a YouTube Sudoku solving channel who decided to do a playthrough for avenge of the Obra
Din? Well, it's probably cracking the cryptic, isn't it? Probably. Cracking the cryptic,
the, the, the kind of tentung gorilla of Sudoku channels and they did Bobbirous U and I think
they did a bit of the witness as well. The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by
Kevin MacLeod in Competec.com used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.
Thank you.