Hello listeners, John here, just before we start, Liz was using the wrong microphone,
and so I am aware she is in a cave. I apologise for her being in a cave,
she will not be in a cave next week. That was the Octothorpe podcast, and it's goodbye from me.
[splutter] I'm still eating a muffin, that was very quick, hang on. You were not expecting the end of the podcast after you
finished your last pick. Nobody expects the end of the podcast. That's why we give them the beep.
[music] Hello everyone, and welcome to the very 103rd episode of Octothorpe. A podcast for
science fiction and science fiction fandom, which is winging its way to you on the 15th of February
2024, just in time for that post-Valentine's Day lull. I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty. And speaking of Valentine's Day, we have some letters of comment, and one of
them is from Christopher J. Garcia. Hurrah. Who I think we can all agree is the Cupid of Science Fiction
fandom. [laughs] He says that this is the best of all episode art, and he was not wrong, it was pretty
dang good. And Raj wrote in on Mastodon to say, "Bohemiancoast, do you happen to have a gallery
or something somewhere with your cover art for Octothorpe and other fan art? I'd like to find
examples I can provide for Hugo nomination purposes." So, Alison, do you have a website?
It is great that you should say that, because I do in fact have a website, which is called something
like alisonscottfanart.myportfolio.com. I don't know if that's exactly right, but we will definitely
put the real link in the show notes, and I just got ambushed with that query, so thanks for that.
Yay! Thanks for everyone who said lovely things about the cover, because yeah, no, I had spent two full
weeks giggling about it before I actually delivered it, so. Yes. But thanks for your lovely letter,
Chris. He did say, "The thing I find so disheartening is that a member of the Hugo subcommittee flat-out
said she knew that votes were thrown out due to a slate and no one seems to care."
I've heard this as a rumour, but I've not seen anything written down that says it or anything on
the record, so if you are out there and you have this report, if you'd like to report it to us in
a bit more cogent way so that we could talk about it, we'd love that. Thank you.
If it's true, it's very damning. Is it – so Chris does say there's no more perfect description of
Dave than arrogant, haughty, and insolent, and I'm going to have to start using that, and I am slightly
regretting that I've already put my ribbon order in for Gallifrey 1, but at Glasgow, will there be
ribbons that say arrogant, haughty, and insolent? I could definitely make one. Also, there is no more
perfect description of Dave than arrogant, haughty, and insolent, but what about Hugo Pope?
I mean, I'm definitely considering cosplaying as the Hugo Pope.
Oh my god, and Hugo Boss, apparently, Dave McCarty, for those who have not heard this, was
signing autographs at Chengdu with the words Hugo Boss.
Which, fun fact, is not something that a member of the Mark Protection Committee should ever do,
because there have been letters exchanged with Hugo Boss about the Hugo trademarks.
So firstly, there's only one Hugo Boss, and it's a clothing company, and secondly, there's only one
Hugo Boss, and it's a comedian called Joe Lycett, and thirdly, Dave McCarty is the boss of precisely
nothing except for bad decisions. And fourthly, we don't have a Hugo Boss, because we did have a
Hugo Boss, it's likely that none of this would ever have happened. If Dave McCarty is the Hugo Pope,
then Nicholas Whyte should be the Hugo God. Hugo Cardinal. Chris also says Liz does need to offer
her services as vote rigger for all sorts of awards. Liz, are you available on commission?
What are your rates? [laughs]
I actually want to say Nicholas, Nicholas, please, please write in with your preferred
Hugo title, and then we'll use it in future. Hugo Messiah, perhaps?
Hugo Tsar, perhaps? Yeah. Really, whatever it, whatever you would like. [laughs]
Mark Plummer of Croydon wrote to us and said, "This is not a comment on Octothorpe 102,
as I haven't listened to it yet." Did you know that Liz's entry in ISFDb contains a note saying,
"Perhaps a thinly disguised pseudonym for a person called Elizabeth?"
[dramatic music] Liz, did you know this? [laughs]
I can reveal exclusively on this podcast that yes, it is a very thinly disguised pseudonym. In
fact, some would not even call it a pseudonym, but maybe just a nickname?
I figured this out. Actually someone pointed it out to me a few months ago, and one,
I was surprised I had an ISFDB entry, but apparently I do for doing some layout for Vector years ago.
But also, I realised ISFDB are very obsessed with properly naming, listing all possible pseudonyms,
alternative names, etc. To the point where they do do some really weird and quite unwarranted stuff,
I think. For example, Lee Mandello, who has changed name, is listed under their previous name,
and I think they've only just managed to get it changed to list their correct name. If you look
up the author, S L Huang, it says, "Legal name removed at author's request." And if you look up
some other authors who have changed name, then it lists everything that they wrote under their
previous names, even in cases where they've maybe been republished under their new name.
It's just weird. Right? It's just trying to be super-completist about publication, but not really thinking that
there's a actual person here who maybe does not want to be reminded every time someone looks up
their ISFDB page that they had a previous name. I mean, in my case, this is a nickname and I do
not care, but it is a bit kind of... It seems to have improved a bit, but this is something I think
people are not aware of. I think the obsession with pseudonyms dates from a time when a lot of
science fiction authors wrote under a vast number of different names in order to sell multiple stories
in the same month to magazines. So obviously, at that point, a lot of people did a tonne of
very painstaking work to work out who all of these pseudonyms are, and they've kind of forgotten that
actually there are lots of other reasons why you might not use your complete legal name to
write fiction or do whatever else you do in the science fiction space. And you certainly
might not want your previous names to be included. So, you know...
I will say, Liz, that this, combined with the vote fixing, it's really starting to look bad for you.
[Laughter]
It is. I'm never going to be a Hugo administrator now.
Have you now, or... when did you stop rigging votes, Liz?
We also heard from DC, who had caught up with Octothorpe. We've not heard from DC for a while.
Thank you very much for writing in DC, and they say that the phrase "useful idiots" was
pinging around in their head as well. So, yeah, it's a very useful, very useful term for what is
going on, I think. And DC also thanks Liz for the work in looking at the stats, and congratulations
us on our hundredth episode. We do have to protect Lenin's honour. It turns out the phrase "useful idiot"
comes from American newspapers in the 40s and 50s, probably, because I did some... I fell down an
internet rabbit hole after editing that podcast, but it is a very useful phrase, regardless.
So yes, thank you for writing in DC.
Lenin's probably okay at this point.
That's going to be the episode title.
He's probably not listening.
[Laughter]
Uh, Liz, do you want to do some Blueskys?
We will do some Blueskys. I should say that I have...
Is it pronounced... So, I listened to a stream and somewhat called it blue ski.
It cannot be pronounced blue ski, can it?
I don't pronounce it blue ski. I'm going to pronounce it blue sky, but if you want to
pronounce it blue ski, you know...
Okay, good.
I'm casual about it. I'm going to call it blue sky though. I should say that I have the keys to
the Bluesky account, and somehow I managed to post the wrong link to the podcast last time.
So apologies, thank you to everyone who pointed that out. This is not like, you know, learned
competence so someone else does the Bluesky, I'm going to get it right. Thank you to Kevin from
Hugo, Girl!, who commented, say it was nice to hear people say that, you know, the Hugo is still
something to be proud of, as they are 2023 winners. So thank you very much, Kevin.
And Robot Archie, who is also Martin, does comment to say that a Worldcon bid being initiated
by enthusiastic but inexperienced fans and then taken over by those with more business and
organisation experience is far from unknown in the West. I think that may be true. I don't know,
I don't go far enough back into Worldcon bid history to have been personally involved with
one of them, but it does seem plausible that some people enthusiastically start one and then have to be
rescued by people who actually know how to organise things. But in this case, it seems like it really
was business experience in that, you know, they were doing business, not that they were taking
their business experience and using it to run Worldcons, but they were running the Worldcon a bit
more like a business. I don't know, yeah, I don't know whether this has ever happened in a Western
convention that was not a Worldcon, but certainly I do not think this has ever happened in quite this
way in a Western Worldcon. I think there is a difference here.
Yes, I mean, not like this, not like this. And also it had already been taken over by big business
at the time of the vote. Let's be clear here. The people who run it were the people who
engineered all the streams and making sure that lots and lots and lots of Chinese SF fans
were involved. That was all done by Science Fiction World.
I will also note that if this happened with a US con, we'd also be angry about it,
or a Western con, I should say, like look at how much criticism there was of Raytheon
sponsoring the Hugos. We are not shy about letting Worldcons know in the West when we feel
their corporate influences have been unsuitable and there have been a lot of times where fandom
has reacted very strongly to that. So I don't, I will also say, I think if the same thing happened
in a Western con, we would be having very similar conversations.
Oh, yes. I just want to say this isn't really a letter of comment, but I just wanted to give
a shout out and a thank you to Mike Glyer from File 770 when we were putting together the links
for the show notes in the last episode. I emailed Mike to ask whether he would mind
tweaking a File 770 post to make it a better roundup of what was going on for our show notes.
And he extremely kindly obliged. And he did not have to do that. So thank you very much to Mike.
And obviously we linked to File 770 a lot in the show notes. And we mentioned it a lot on the pod,
but I don't think we ever necessarily sing its praises. It's real good guys.
I think the fact that the amount we're relying on File 770 is a good indication of
File 770's criticality to the genre at times like this and what a lot of good work Mike and
his team have been doing. Yeah. And especially when stuff is split across streams and, you know,
the last remnants of Twitter and then bits of Bluesky and bits of Mastodon and bits of blogs,
you know, it is good to have somewhere that kind of if you just read File 770, you'll basically know
what's going on. File 770 pretty great website. Ali Baker Brooks wrote to us to say, I am now
Octothorpe complete with your latest episode. So well done, Ali. And I'm just going to remind
people that you do not have to listen to all of them. There are 102 of them. That's quite a lot.
You don't have to, but it does give me the warm fuzzies, whatever someone says they have.
But there's no obligation, but it is nice though. Thank you, Ali.
Yeah, I mean, if you want to give John the warm fuzzies, this is a way to do it.
Farah writes to say, I agree with Liz on the gifts. One week we could shine with my university
as I had to either buy a new suitcase or just abandon things. Farah left the paperweight and
the framed artwork behind. Yeah, it was a framed print of Dave McCarty.
I guess that's getting cut, but I still think it's funny. Liz has given us a Look. Also on Facebook,
Ming says, "Pondering a crowd funder for 30 pieces of silver." I didn't get that. I am bereft.
It's like Dave McCarty is the Devil, right? Or Judas. I see.
Okay, that's quite good. Farah also asks whether a collected comic could be included in Best
Series. And the answer is yes, if it's very, very, very long, I think Liz said. Well, there's a word
limit. 240,000 words. The minimum number of words for being a Best Series, so it would have to be an extremely
wordy comic. And I don't know if you can get word counts for comics. And I don't think a picture counts as
the thousand words for the purposes of Best Series. I think that that's one of these things that's
been discussed in the past on Hugos. There is a journal called the Journal of Geophysical Research.
And when they were making the change from doing their fees in terms of how many pages it would be
in the physical journal, they obviously changed that when it became clear that journals were going
to be primarily PDFs, and so that didn't really make sense as a model. And they decided that they
would do publication units, and a publication unit was 500 words or one figure. And the editors did
note "this does of course mean we are devaluing the picture". I thought that was a very good,
very good comment from him. James Shields points out in terms of series that all of the collected
Judge Dredd strips from 2000 AD are easily going to go over 240,000 words because there's about
2,400 issues. So you'd only need a hundred words an issues and obviously there's a lot more than
that. So we're going to be talking about Hugo nominations in a subsequent episode. But you can
expect to see the collected Judge Dredd from 2000 AD on my Best Series list. All right, so
I need you guys to do Bat John because it's not often that I'm the one that goes to the
WSFS constitution. [music] Bat John! I think comics are not eligible in Best Series. And I think
the reason is 3.2.7, which provides that the categories of Best Novel, Novella, Novelette,
Short Story and Series shall be open to non-interactive works in which text is the primary
form of communication. And I think it would be argued that in a comic, the text is as important
as the graphics and is therefore not primary. I think the graphics are also primary, I suppose.
But I think the intent is that graphic novels are not eligible in any of the Novel,
Novella, Novellette, Short Story and Series categories. The thing is that if you rule comics
are eligible for series, I think it also makes them eligible for Short Story, Novellette, Novella,
and Novel and I think that opens a can of worms. So is my is my belief it must be in Graphic Story.
A can of graphic worms? Oh, I'm going to write a massive series entirely comprised of ASCII art now.
[laughs][ Well, and also like it is the sort of thing where I can see a Hugo administrator... If there was an
overwhelming will of the voters, I don't know what you'd do, but it would be interesting.
I feel like Hugo Messiah, Nicholas Whyte, would let the overwhelming will of the voters have its way.
Yeah, if the Hugo Holy Ghost, Nicholas Whyte could write in and let us know what his– oh, he can't
this year because he's actually the Hugo administrator, right? I think Big Hugo Banana is his official
job title. So we won't be offended if the Hugo Zaphod Beeblebrox does not write in and tell us what
the skinny is here because it might be a conflict of interest. Zaphod Beeblebrox isn't a title
is it? His title was like president of the universe or something. So if the Hugo president of the universe...
Nicholas is just this guy, you know?
Oh, that means it all has to stay in. God damn it, Liz.
[music] The BSFA Longlist is out. In fact, it was out two weeks ago, but we were a little bit
busy with another award having some problems. So we didn't get to it. But basically the BSFA
Longlist... as I understand that there is now like a multi-stage nomination process. There's a long
list in which all BSFA members can nominate things to be on the long list. And then there's
a long list and then you can vote for those things on the long list to be on the short list. And then
you can vote for the short lists and all the Eastercon members can also vote on the short list. So the
BSFA put out the long list, which, you know, I'm fine with this as a thing. I think there have
been cases in the past where the BSFA have not had a lot of nominations in certain categories.
And so putting out kind of a long list of things people can go and check out and then
nominate their favourites and then vote on the favourites seems good. But I'm pretty sure what
they did is they took a big Google Doc or something that people have been dumping their
long list nominations in and then they just put it onto the internet. And I think they could have
maybe done a bit of editing first? Because for instance there's quite a lot of errors.
They probably do need to do a certain amount of eligibility checking before posting.
There's quite a lot of errors in it. The things like there's quite a lot of misspelled names,
which is just... it's not good for if you turn up on the long list and your name is spelled wrong.
There's some things that possibly are eligible but in the wrong category. And so they could really
do with being moved before all lots of people nominate them and then you have to move them later,
things like that. And something we should remember for next year, which is that the BSFA
long list in order to get things on the long list, you have to remember to read your BSFA email
at exactly the right time and then vote before the end of the year, which is really unusual for
awards. Normally awards nominations happen at the beginning of the new year rather than
on 31st of December because 31st of December is too early, right? Because stuff could still be
being published. I've known in practice not very much is published between in the last two weeks
of December but it could be and it should get its fair shout at eligibility.
Mmm, that is true. I think it's just kind of compressed time-wise because they've got to do all this
process before the Eastercon which this year is March. Yes but they could still ask for the
long list by the middle of January instead of the end of December. Right. The long list is out.
If you are a BSFA member you can now go and vote and move things onto the short list. There are
new categories this year. I think they generally did want to sort of split their short fiction
category but I don't quite... it was not clear to me what is best short fiction and what is best
shorter fiction. There's also a best short non-fiction category. There is still
a best fiction for younger readers category which only has eight items in which means that could be
literally eight people and then it goes through to a short list of five. Probably could be one person.
Can only put so many things on the long list. I can't remember how many. It doesn't say there is a
ton of interest in this which is unusual because there is a lot of YA out there and you know the
Lodestar is showing there is a bunch of stuff but obviously it's not quite caught on among the BSFA
members. But anyway if you are a BSFA member go, have a look, read things, nominate them.
I'm wondering whether a learned person who listens to this podcast and who knows about children's
literature could provide recommendations to the BSFA voting membership about what they might
want to read from a given year because I don't really have a very good view of any of this at all
and so I think having that would be helpful, and I'm not mentioning any names, Ali.
Oh so you mean someone who consistently listens to this podcast? [laughs]
That was the BSFA awards. Obviously the thing you all need to vote for is All These Worlds:
Reviews and Essays by Neil Harrison.
Okay so next up on our list this week is fan funds and we have three fan funds and they are at
slightly different stages of happeningness. So TAFF is running a race from North America to Europe
to attend the Glasgow Worldcon and it is happening now and you can vote online or probably by
other routes as well and there are two candidates who are Vanessa Applegate and Sarah Gulde and
they are both lovely lovely people and they've put their explanations in and you should go and
vote for one of them. I kind of like seeing who people's nominators are, so Vanessa has been nominated
by Dave O'Neill, Chuck Serface, Francesca Myman, Alissa Wales and somebody called John
Coxon. Hello there. Sarah has been nominated by Chris Garcia, Seanan McGuire, Kevin Roche,
James Bacon and Johan Anglemark so I would say that is a good set of nominators on both accounts
but I think we can probably say that this podcast is supporting Vanessa, can we? We don't have any
strong reasons not to say that. This podcast supports TAFF. Yeah. And you should vote for whoever
you think is best, listener. My nomination probably gives a clue as to which way I am leaning but go!
Read them. They're both great people. I've worked with them both on fanish endeavors. They would both
be extremely good TAFF delegates. I will be voting for Vanessa in one and Sarah in two. Hopefully one
of those people will be at the Worldcon. They've started an EFF race. This is the European Fan Fund
which will bring a lucky European fan to the Eurocon which is in Rotterdam in mid-August this year.
The candidates here are Jane Mondrup and Joro Penchev, Jane I think lives in Denmark and Euro comes
from Bulgaria. They're both great candidates I think though in this case I do not know either
of them so it's the other way around from the TAFF race. I agree with Alison. And on GUFF,
GUFF have issued a call for candidates. GUFF is going to bring somebody from Australia or New
Zealand or the Pacific Islands I guess, that sort of area, to the Glasgow Worldcon and we'll have a
link to that call for nomination. So if you are in that part of the world and you would like a free
trip to the UK then do not under any circumstances self-exclude. This is a great opportunity. I love
doing GUFF and people should get their nominations in. We like Fan Funds, Fan Funds are good.
[music] So a committee has been formed to bring the 85th Worldcon to Montreal, Canada in 2027.
Yeah it's basically looks to be many of the same people as did 2009 I think? Although we don't
really know who they all are yet they don't have a website... Oh, no, they do have a website
ignore me. They do have a website, it just doesn't have the names on it.
All right they do have a website. It's led by Terry Fong who has been involved in lots of
Canadian conventions. They plan to use the same venue as 2009 which I think everyone liked.
Yeah and the other bid for 2027 was Tel Aviv so yeah I mean I don't know if they just completely
give up but I'm pretty sure that Montreal is going to be more popular than Tel Aviv. Tel Aviv is
a more challenging venue now than it was when they first formed that bid. There is an update on the
Tel Aviv bid website but do me a fairly recent one saying that all members of the committee are safe
and they're devastated by the recent tax and they basically betting that things will stabilize
and they will be able to continue but I don't know for how long that is going to seem plausible as
you get closer to the actual 2025 boat. That's true yes. I will also say that all the Montreal
in 2027 pre-sports and so ons have funny names which appeals to me so if you give them $20 you
can have a nifty ribbon with lemmings you know I like that. Donation only no membership tier really
you had to do this no lemon ribbon for you you get a black ribbon so there. Okay so I have just
looked up on one of the tiers is named after an owl. So funny animal tiers we approve
so well good good luck to them. I really enjoyed Montreal in 2009. I think we need to say
Pemecon was not an unalloyed success and I think we'll probably walk to ask this bid
what it's going to be doing to make sure that some of the mistakes Pemecon made are not repeated
in 2027 but nevertheless I think most people would much rather see a Montreal will come
than a Tel Aviv one at the moment. Yes so Montreal and Tel Aviv will be being voted on in Seattle in 2025
the bid that will be being voted on in Glasgow will be the LA bid for 2026. That bid's currently
unopposed we believe. We were very sorry to hear of the death of Chris Priest since we last recorded
he was obviously a huge tiring force in British science fiction and really responsible for a lot
of the more literary SF that was produced as in actually over his fantastic career obviously he
has some success towards the end of his career with his book The Prestige was picked up by
Christopher Nolan and turned into an excellent movie but but he'd been writing wonderful,
challenging, thoughtful books for a very very long time. He was also one of the first science
fiction authors possibly the first science fiction author of any note that I met because he came to
talk to Gus Uswell I was one of the officers and in fact my flatmate my roommate and I fed him
breakfast because we put him up in the college but we were the cussus was too cheap to actually
stand in breakfast at the buttery so we cooked him eggs and bacon in our room which I think seems
appalling to me now but was kind of just the sort of thing we did back in the 80s sorry Chris.
For those who are unaware Cussus is the Cambridge Science Fiction Society.
Cussus Cambridge University Science Fiction Society. I mean whenever John was talking about
Imperial and how they were perhaps not the most organized I cast my mind back to some terrible
things that we did when we were students. Oh I mean my my opinion of that came from the same
when I was a student involved in my student societies like I am not expecting I guess that's
that's where all that comes from is like I know what I was like and I am not expecting
the students of today to be any better than I was.
No I never met Chris Priest but I did see him on panels at Novacom 50 and at the most recent
satellite convention where he was against the Waller and he was witty and erudite and incredibly
grumpy and he was very good to listen to on panels for that reason. Yes I mean he wrote you know a
whole range of really really good novels I think the time I came into fandom was about the time
that like everyone was talking about the separation well we'd run the Beers of Fey award and then
won the clock award it's about the time I was like to pay attention to the clock award I think and
then I read a lot of his subsequent books filled in a lot of the backstory. The Prestige is a great
novel as well as being turned into a great film the glamour the information in the inverted world
this feels completely different to all the rest of them but it's great. He wrote some really really
good stuff and he was also very intensive and I think he had a reputation for being grumpy maybe
because he was on panels and he was famously very grumpy about the clock award one year. The Glasgow
Worldcon also linked to. Was that the year he wasn't nominated? I think that is a bit harsh but yeah he
was very commercially about it and he also was on panels and so when I had occasion to email him
for convention stuff I was always a bit worried that he was going to be really really grumpy and
he was very nice I think it was very much a this is this is the way he exists and he was
homogeny about the clock award but I think because he genuinely did want to see really great stuff
nominated for the club award and he felt that that year it was not. I am going to quote from
the Guardian's article on on Christopher Priest's rant. "The judges should be fired or forced to
resign," says Priest and the 2012 awards suspended. If his quote, Moss's suggestion is taken up he says
and enough people believe the proposal was made in his own interest he would then withdraw his own
novel The Islanders from the running. "That was 11 years ago, good god, 12 years ago."
Absolute Titan of the genre will be sorely sorely missed. The Glasgow Worldcon linked to his 2005
guest of honor speech a Worldcon which I don't think I don't think I went to that or I missed or
I haven't remembered but it is it is quite funny because you know what you're going to say about how
you know the guest of honor and riches Easter Convention gave his speech of mind-knowing
tediousness and to polite to name him and then like you know to progress later ex-only names
was Larry Niven and it goes on like that. We're really sad he was one of the possibly the greatest
British science fiction author and we miss him and it's a shame.
Yeah so for listeners who are unaware the Hugos are a popularly voted award that's given out by a
convention called the Worldcon. So we're going to start with the trademark kerfuffle. There was
a Twitch stream in which Mike Dunford and Will Frank both of whom are lawyers who specialise in
sort of intellectual property and trademarks talk about Hugo Awards due to a thing that happened
on the internet. It's related to but slightly separate from the stuff we discussed last
episode about Chengdu but it is related to the pickup I put in last episode about Kevin Stanley
being reprimanded. Effectively Kevin Stanley said at great length on a variety of social media platforms
that there's no way for the mark protection committee to enforce any rules on the Worldcon
who is administering the Hugo Awards. There is a problem when you say that in US trademark law
and the analogy given in the stream basically goes something like this. We will link to the full
stream if you want more details because I am not a trademark lawyer. This is my understanding
of what a trademark lawyer said. So basically if you go to McDonald's you are expecting a certain
level of service and your personal opinions listener about McDonald's not withstanding.
So if you go into McDonald's and you order a big Mac you can expect a certain thing to be given to
you and the thing the trademark basically warrants is that the thing you get is the thing you expect
to get and so the trademark effectively is to do with your perception of the business and the
standard of the service the business will provide to you. The problem is that that mechanism requires
the company that controls the trademark to be able to take the trademark away if the quality of the
service rendered is subpar and if the owner of the trademark publicly says repeatedly that they
have no mechanism with which to do that they invalidate their trademarks under US trademark law because
that is a key part of US trademark law and so by saying all of this Kevin might have inadvertently
opened the Hugo's up to legal challenges. The reason that's the case is because if you do something
that you suspect might get you sued in the US you can sue first. So you can basically sue to say
we think we might get sued and we want to sue to establish that the thing we are doing we can't be
sued for and so if someone starts awarding a Hugo award they could sue Worldcon Intellectual
Property Inc preemptively basically saying we think you might sue us but you don't have standing to
sue us so we can sue you first. Basically if someone does start awarding Hugo awards they could
preemptively sue and then win a case that says we can award our own Hugo awards because the trademark
is null. That is my understanding of the Twitch Street. Liz do you have any things that you think
I have misrepresented or got wrong in my capacity as definitely not a lawyer? No because I would say
I am also definitely not a lawyer. I didn't finish the entire stream but that does appear to be the
gist is that like there are multiple things involved in having service marks or trademarks and there's
lots of bits I wasn't aware of that you kind of should be doing. I would also say that like I've
followed Mike Dunford on Twitter, Blue Sky, whatever for a while and so you know I think a good goal
even life is to not do something which is legally so deaf that Mike Dunford does a whole streetly
bank. Is that a good rule of thumb? Alright Alison do you have any penetrating and
incisive questions? I have a couple of not necessarily penetrating and incisive comments
the first is I am not a lawyer but my actual day job involves working very closely with
detail of American trade bar copyright law all of the time they are not the same thing but this
one in this case we're talking about trademarks not copyright but yes I think my understanding is
that you are completely that is a completely correct summation of my understanding of the US
position as it as it is operated so if you have it seems likely that you have therefore represented
the stream correctly rather than that they said it wrong and then you inadvertently said it right
afterwards you know but my second point is that I just wanted to say when you were talking about
the big back because you know when you go to a harvester you know what you're going to get you're
never disappointed at a harvester and you're both looking at me completely blankly so I don't
think I've ever been to a harvester I don't know if Liz has ever been to a harvester no this is a
joke about Greg Wallace have you heard Greg Wallace has been in the news no it's a popular
culture reference melod I'm sorry it's also worth noting I don't know if I know it's noted this in
my big old diatribe about trademarks Will Frank who was on the stream was the vice Hugo administrator
under Dave McCarty as Hugo administrator on a previous Worldcon and he does have some
choice words to say about Dave so like I don't necessarily want to get into that again but like
if you if you want to listen to someone saying things about Dave McCarty then you can go and do
that that is why Kevin was reprimanded the statement from Worldcon intellectual property which we
linked last episode said in the description why he had been reprimanded because he had
inaccurately made statements causing people to believe we are not properly servicing our marks
or something to that effect that's not a direct quote whereas the others were all censured because
of the cover for we discussed on the last episode there was a great description on file 770 of the
difference between being censured and reprimanded where they kind of had a series of so they had a
set of rebukes all the way from a slightly strange look to to immediate execution
we will put the link in the show notes listeners so if you're still watching the hugos after all
of this and interested in what Dave McCarty's thought processes were while going through all
of this Chris Barkley sat down with him at Capricorn and did an coddling interview about 40 minutes
and has put the entire thing unedited on the internet and it is one of those cases I believe
where people believe that by giving being given a chance to tell an unvarnished their side of the
story things will improve for them and I'm not sure this is the case what is your impression
John and Liz why would you ever do this interview why it does seem very strange it doesn't I've not
I for this closure I did not listen to it I am I am I'm bad I did not do my homework um but I just
don't I have not seen anyone say anything about this interview that basically think it was a wise
thing to give this interview and it is it's fanny is fanny's take on it was basically like she always
thought that Dave had a lot of contempt for fans but a lot of respect for the institutions of fandom
and it just made her think that actually he has contempt for everything except Dave McCarty
arrogant, haute and insolent we will put a link in the show notes listeners if you want your blood
pressure to rise yeah so I just want to put a couple of things which is you know Dave says there
are two mistakes of substance in the stats that are currently published and it's like why didn't
you check for this stuff and you know he goes on and talks about how like the SQL queuing from the
data in the ballot counts has a flaw and it's wrong and there's some bits that are wrong and I'm like
what did you spend 90 days doing and also I think I mean a lot of his stuff about how he talks about
how he feels he was delivering what they wanted to have in China is very like sort of paternalistic
like I felt I was living what they would want in China it doesn't sound like it sounds a bit more
like kind of Dave saying this is what I my impression of what China would want is and I delivered it
rather than what the Chinese fans actually wanted yeah but I think that's Dave covering up for his
Chinese people that he doesn't want to implicate isn't it it's difficult because we don't know
it could be but there's a lot of very sweeping reactions about how you know their culture is
different this this is like not what the Chinese spirit is and I mean I know we generalize it
sometimes but it is kind of a very a lot of generalizations about like what China is and
and allows from yeah an external perspective it's a bit weird but then we don't have any
interviews with the other bits of the administration team because all the other bits of the Hugo
administration and World Concomity are very very quiet so I guess we just have to take what Dave
gives us on the subject of Chinese interference there is a post from Chinese social media which
has been translated which some people are interpreting as a smoking gun for state interference in the
Hugo's we'll put a link in the show notes my view of this is that I can see why people are saying
this is a smoking gun but it does not contain the word Hugo nor the word award it talks about Cheng
do in a way that you could read it to mean that there was involvement in the Cheng do program
or you could read it to mean there was involvement in the Cheng do awards but it doesn't it's not
specific enough we will put links in the show notes you can form your own opinions listeners
uh Tammy Coxin wrote some thoughts a few weeks ago on Facebook about the Hugo kerfuffle and one
of the things she said was none of this matters because the World Concom will almost certainly be
defunct within 10 years there are almost no viable bids for future years and a serious lack of
World Concom running energy I'm going to say two things here which is firstly I am tired of American
fans saying the World Concom is dying when we have just had a decade with the most international
World Concomies we've ever had and there seems to be more interest in the thing worldwide than there
has ever been at any point in its history secondly there is a large amount of the way World
Concomies are run to do with the worst business meeting at Roberts rules of order and all of that
that mean people who try to go along and do things with the World Conc end up being severely
rebutted by people who are very big fans of those structures and that puts people off and if you
are a part of that structure then you are part of the reason why people do not want to engage with
the Worldcon and volunteering for it because there are massive fan run conventions all over the world
so it's not true that they're dying more generally and if there is a specific problem to Worldcon
we should be thinking about why and we should be addressing that as I just want to it's a very
quick but I feel very strongly about both of those and I think I want to give a shout out to Glasgow
they obviously have six months to go six months to go oh my god that's not long but they have six
months to go but they have a huge team of engaged and enthusiastic volunteers many of whom have never
worked on a Worldcon before and I'm sure that at least some of those people will still be enthusiastic
after the convention you know there's no reason why they shouldn't be and and this is the key to
having more enthusiastic Worldcon runners going forward is get people in get them working get them
engaged and get them happy with what they get to do and also don't mess them around
another way we could involve more people in the Worldcon and make them feel more involved in it
is by not doing things like sneakily introducing amendments that prevent online voting
while other people are out of the room Dave oh who did that can you remind me who was the person who
introduced that amendment I do feel a little bit sad that we haven't heard anything from kind of
Finnish fandom about any repeat Finland bits just because I really liked Finland and would like to
go back and I do feel maybe we have burnt out all the Finnish fans with one Worldcon which would be
a shame but you know they don't have to do one every very often maybe in 15 years they'll come back
and do normal I think doing one more than every decade would be foolish and so 2027 would have been
the earliest I would have expected a resurgent like Finnish bit so we will see it might be that
there's a 28 or 29 bit but we'll see we've currently got a pattern where the UK is doing one every
10 years and Ireland is doing one every 10 years and I feel like that's probably the absolute
tippy top of what those two countries can manage but yes we're going to talk about all of this in
more detail later but we didn't cover it last episode and I feel strongly that there are issues
here which are going undiscussed which I think are important
[Music]
Liz do you pick what pick you I've forgot about picks to be honest um
you've read three million books so you can definitely pick one of them
I know but I've got to go remember what I read
plus some of them were a lot of them were for like Hugo nomination purposes right
I am going to pick a book which was eligible for Hugo last year and I'm so sorry for the author
that I took too long to read it okay so I am going to pick a pair of books well I'm going to
pick a book but it has homework which is slightly irritating I'm going to pick How to Find Zodiac
by Jarek Kobach which is a sequel to his book Motor Spirit the long hunt for the Zodiac
these are books about the Zodiac serial killer who killed at least five people in the 60s and 70s
in San Francisco and the boy debate area. Motor Spirit basically sums up what we know about the
Zodiac and does quite a lot of very good work if you've seen David Finch's for excellent film
Zodiac starring Mark Ruffalo and Robert Downey Jr in Amazing Roles Before They Were in Marvel
which is a great film which I love the book does an awful lot to unpick why the conclusions the
film draws you to are probably not actually worth the celluloid they're printed on so it's a good
film that doesn't tell you much about the murders. How to Find Zodiac is a work of fan history about
a fanzine fan called Paul Duh who lived in Vallejo California at the time of the murders and it is
absolutely fascinating because the book basically starts with Jarek Kobach Zodiac made a lot of
very obscure pop culture references to comics and books of the day. Kobach said that he thought
one of Zodiac's kind of ticks in his letters was probably a pop culture reference that no one had
been able to find yet and he expressed this suspicion to a friend and the friend said it seems like
the sort of shit you'd read in fanzines and that sent Kobach down a rabbit hole and there was a
rabbit at the bottom of its spoiler yes so basically long story short Kobach starts out he finds a
fanzine fan who lived in Vallejo at the time and he starts trying to exclude that person and
basically on the basis that he's probably not a zodiac every other suspect is not being zodiac it
will be possible to exclude this person and the more he finds the more he's like oh no this doesn't
exclude him and at the end of the the search he's like ah there's nothing that excludes this person
and in fact there's quite a lot that points to him. Now this is a decades old case and like it is
not necessarily likely that this person is is the zodiac but it's very interesting walk through
fan history and investigative journalism but it also has one key thing which is zodiac left his
fingerprints at the one of his crime scenes and this person served in the US military and their
fingerprints are on file so at the point that anyone decides they want to know for sure whether
this theory is true it will be possible to check because the relevant law enforcement agencies if
they want to will be able to tell so it is at least a theory that can be firmly true-false which I
like but it's very interesting even if it's wrong. The detail I most liked and this might be a little
bit of a spoiler for the book is that at some point Kovacs turns up on Dua's x-yves door step
and says so I've been looking at this thing and she was like oh I've been wondering when do you
guys turn up. I will say the writing style is idiosyncratic and although I find the content of
the books very interesting I wish they were differently written is probably the kind of
just way to say it but it's clear a lot of workers gone into them who wants to pick next.
After a pick I am going to pick a book which is not really genre it's got some you know tiny
bits of sort of genre Jason stuff in there but it is mostly a kind of mainstream historical fiction
it is called Northwoods by Daniel Mason which is basically a story about a house in the woods
over time and all the people who live in that house in the woods over time or come to find that
house in the woods and each bit is kind of written in a slightly different style about a
slightly different set of people you know some very mundane some very exciting and it's also kind
of about the nature of that you know it follows the nature as it evolves around the house the trees
the animals what is there in the woods and how it changes over time and it's just kind of very
engrossing story about it I got nominated for lots of awards and things so yeah that was it
that's my whole thing the Guardian said it is an epic of American lives yeah he's fair enough
which travels to the limits of what the novel can do no it doesn't really it's quite good
it does sound interesting though I mean unless you think it's you know having lots of kind of
interlinked short stories that form a novel is pushing the boundaries of the novel which I do
not think is correct but you know not in science fiction well probably fantasy I've read um
what's name that one book Wirgan Wirgan the alien love war was that it that was a good book
oh Liz that was one of the better clerks that year I thought but yes um interlinked stories is a
very classic form of the genre it's very much a way that novels can be my pick this week is because
last week I did a print and play game as my pick and it went down really well I decided to do a
different one this week I promise my next three picks will not be print and play games lies I did
this one I thought well this is a very interesting game and it's also the sort of game that might be
very interesting to our listenership and here's why this is a game called fantasy map maker that
was designed by Harry Metcalfe and was an entry in one of the board game geeks contest last year
it's got a little bit of a build so it uses cards but you can get around the need for cards because
they're only used to roll quests at the beginning of the game and so you can um you can either roll
them on a chart or you can use pre-printed sheets that have your quest pre-rolled the point about
it is this is a roll and write game which is a game where you roll dice and then draw things on
on your or your game sheet but in this case your game sheet is a blank fantasy map and you draw bits
of your fantasy map onto the game and then you have quests which you get points for fulfilling so
it's actually got quite a satisfying game in there because you have to score a certain number of
points to win and this this appeals to my the gamer in me and it also makes you think oh if I put an
island there I might be able to put a lighthouse on it afterwards for the big points on things like
that and you end up with an actual map that you can frame or paste into your journal or use for
your role-playing game or your or your novel situation and in fact I ended up with two castles
in a very small space and I was like well why would that be and I created an entire backstory
about two warring um civilizations who both built castles in the space and I was like oh you could
you could actually spin an entire novel out of this so it clearly works not what I'm going to
but I thought it was great and I thought it might be of interest to people in our listeners who do
that's who who do things that require maps it's just a fantasy mapmaker at the moment so I guess
there's a he could easily expand this to be a science fiction mapmaker or a steampunk mapmaker
or a horror mapmaker or any sort of mapmaker you might like but it was very good really enjoyed it
and there will be a link in the show notes and of course it's free because yeah I mean it's free
until somebody decides that it's worth publishing which I think we probably probably somebody will
decide this is worth publishing because it's pretty good this is a sort of thing where it might well
be very useful for role playing games I will say like like how easy would it be to do other genres
in this game um yeah harry says he's about to make an announcement on this game so there's a chance
that that all will become clear but I think he is thinking about expansions but if he decides not
to think about expansions what the role and writers do or what the printed play gaming fans do is a
thing called re-themes where they take a game that is good but is not necessarily in the genre
they like and they remake it in the genre the genre they like that would be pretty simple to do I
think oh and also this this pick is a absolutely transparent excuse for me to stick my art in the
chapter art i.e my finished map from my playthrough of this that would be good okay that was the
octa thought podcast and it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me is goodbye from me
i mean obviously the greatest idiocy of it was the um the testament of Jesse Lambie embassy town
have you guys both read embassy town yes i have not read embassy town and the testament of Jesse
Lamb i'd have to go back and reread them but i think you're right that like from the vantage
point of 12 years i've probably picked embassy town over the testament of Jesse Lamb i'm going to
pick either them over all the other three so oh yeah yeah that's fair i've read hole 0 3 like i would
describe it as fine i have a bias towards works of science fiction which talk about how alien aliens
are and how difficult language is and embassy town does boast those and it does it better than
possibly any other work science fiction except for perhaps a rival and like i can't think of any
others that do it better so like i adore that book but i am biased the theme music for this
episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in compactec.com used under a creative commons
attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]