Listen, you've gone very quiet, which is good because that means I can just say something right?
I think you may have changed microphone because you sound less clear. So while Alison is sorting
out her microphone. Hello everyone and welcome to the very 50th episode of the OctaThought podcast.
This is the episode for the first of October 2020. I'm John Coxson. I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz
Batty. And who'd have thought we'd still be doing this in October?
Yep. Or that we'd stick to a schedule. Yes, I have retroactively edited our release date so the
schedule looks more coherent than it actually was. But don't tell anyone. It was pretty coherent.
Yeah, we've been doing I think we've been doing pretty well. Coming out on a Wednesday or Thursday
every other week. So that is nice. We have had a debatable plethora of locks because roughly half
of the locks were to chime in on whether or not it was acceptable to use the word plethora. So
yes, let's do them in some sort of order. So the first lock was from...
Well, actually no. So the first lock was from Claire Briarley and she wrote us about episode 13.
But we got the episode, we got the letter of comment after we had recorded episode 14.
Claire does not think it's a good idea to introduce virtual ribbons to online conventions.
I suspect this is because she dislikes ribbons in all their forms. Is that possibly on presence?
Yeah, I think if you like ribbons, the idea of virtual ribbons is great. If you think ribbons
are already in abomination then I can't see a virtual ribbon is going to convince you. Although
it probably is better for the environment. I guess so. Yeah, I would assume so. Probably.
No, I think ribbons are a major cause of environmental damage.
That's fair. We haven't... Here at the Altitop podcast we have not commissioned any research into
the environmental impact of ribbons. Also in Claire's lock on episode 13, she says, "I think the
Marvel Cinematic Universe would be improved if some scenes were replaced by a caption card,
stating five to ten minutes of implausible fighting ensued." And I wanted to read this
out because A) I have watched multiple Marvel Cinematic Universe movies since our last episode,
but also I too am now in the habit of sitting in my living room going, "This is boring now,
isn't it? Is it boring? Steven, is this boring and Steven going?" It depends if you like that
sort of thing. There's no car chases, Dr Strange. So this is what substitutes for a car
chase in this one. Great I go, that's still very tedious. Could we just get onto the character
development bit and have I just watched a female character dying in order to further the character
development of a man? Oh probably. Should they really be doing that sort of thing? Probably not.
God these movies are terrible. When are we watching the next one? But if the fight scenes were shorter,
I wouldn't have time to think about how bad the movies were until after I finished watching them.
What I would like Alison is you and Liz are both aware that I've started my own Arkham horror
podcast on the side. I would like you to start a podcast which is you recording Alison and Steve
commentaries of MCU films that I could sync up the audio to the film and listen to it as if I was
watching with you because I think that would be quite funny. I think it would make lots of people
very angry. So yes. Oh god I could have done a good one for Dr Strange. Steven was like, "Oh,
um, so you thought that Tony Stark was a bit of a git?" But that's the emotional journey Alison.
He says it's a less of a bit of a git. And then there's a white lady playing an Asian lady,
but she's not Asian so it's fine. This attracted some criticism at the time. I would argue that
one of the things that makes the better MCU films better is that they use their fight scenes
in a way as to further character development and often do kind of intelligent and slightly,
I'd put it. They often do fight scenes which go just a bit beyond we've got two guys in robot
suits and they're going to put each other. So I would say like, I really like Captain America
the Wind Soldier, which I think uses its fight scenes basically to do the emotional development
between Captain America and the Wind Soldier or Thor Agnerock where you get Thor and he meets the Hulk
or a lot of the ones in Black Panther. Whereas the ones in sort of like, I'd say Iron Man 2,
which is somewhere down at the bottom of the MCU rankings as some really boring fight scenes.
And it's just like guys shooting each other with the giant robot suits.
Okay. So the other thing I wanted to say about Dr Strange, none of this might go in the podcast.
I may have to do a different MCU podcast, is that when I was a teenager, I lived in America and in
every shopping mall in America, there was a shop called Spencer Gifts and the back and the final
third of the shop of Spencer Gifts was a black light room which was full of black light posters,
which I thought was just about the most amazing place on earth when I was 13. And anyway, the final
third of Dr Strange, this might be a spoiler, is like the back end of Spencer Gifts in 1979.
Almost exactly. My main comment on Iron Man 2 is that Iron Man 2 has one of the best villains
in the MCU, which is Sam Rockwell's portrayal of Hammer and I love him. And it also has one of the
most boring villains in the MCU, which is Mickey Rock's portrayal of whatever his name is.
And it's a real shame. Slappy guy. Slappy guy. That's the guy. And like, it's a real shame because
I think Iron Man 2, if it had focused way more on the Tony Stark, Sam Rockwell thing, would have been
so good because I love Sam Rockwell. I love him in that role. But just a good third of the movie is
a tedious Russian man. And it's like, I feel like Iron Man 2 pulled its punches that the final line
of the movie, this is probably a spoiler. Yes, the final line of a movie does tend to be a spoiler.
Is somebody saying, is it amazing how annoying a little prick can be?
And if you actually take that as the text for the movie that Iron Man 2 is a film which
Stark does not get a redemptive arc, he is in fact completely appalling from the beginning to the
end of it, despite the fact that he's nominally the hero. And Sam Rockwell, as you say, has quite
a nuanced role despite the fact that he is clearly intended to be the villain. These are both scare
quotes things. And clearly, there was a much cleverer film in there trying to get out. But
eventually someone went, oh no, no, you have to sympathise with Tony Stark. I don't sympathise
with Tony Stark. I feel that Tony Stark really needs a slap. And anyway, no doubt Iron Man 3 will
convince me, but I am not, I am not persuaded. Iron Man 3 is a very, very different movie.
And anyway, Doctor Strange also a git. Also gets his character development through The Death of Women,
which really pisses me off here in 2020 or whenever it was produced 2016, already a trope they should
not be using. Okay, so I've got two comments. Firstly, Iron Man 2, I sympathise with Tony Stark,
he's dying and he's sad about it. Like, he is a git, but he's lashing out because he's dying.
I know, many people who have known that they were dying and who were sad about it, and who in fact
were in fact dying, rather than it that merely being yet another plot point, and who nevertheless
were honourable, noble, look at Martin Bennett, who permanently improved the state of British folk
music after he discovered he was dying. You know, because it's if you're dying, you might have
made decisions with a shitty, and I quite like sympathising with a character who makes him
chitty-sitting. I quite like a film of our character who is in a shitty situation and makes
shitty decisions even though you sympathise with him. I thought that was well done. I have never...
Ah, ah, I see what the problem here was. I sympathised with a bit with the fact that he was dying,
but I didn't sympathise with him because he's a tosser. But I don't think... yes. I think when
you are angry, you have made shitty decisions that I still like you and sympathise with you.
So I think in general it is okay that I could view characters and films and sympathise with
them even when they make shitty decisions. Um... and I'm not saying he covers itself in glory,
but I still like... yeah. Shall we move on to Claire's second letter? Yes. I will... Can I say about the
third Marvel movie I've watched first, which was Captain Marvel? No, you didn't put any of this in
the show notes. You can put it in the show notes, Alison, and then we might let you talk about it,
but till then, you can see yourself on the notice. You can have one minute on Captain Marvel,
which is I would quite like Marvel to make a movie where a woman is the lead character,
and we don't have the origin story for a man and the man stealing all the scenes, please.
I don't know who you mean, but I really... I don't really think any men did steal the...
like, I don't understand how a man... Oh, okay, so Captain Marvel is the origin story of Nick Fury,
and Nick Fury gets all the good lines and the good scene. And you haven't noticed that because
you're a man. No, I think I didn't notice that because I really liked Rylaarsson. I think you might
not have noticed it because you don't like women enough, Alison. Did you consider that speechlessness?
Oh no, I really did like, um... I like Black Widow in Our Man 2. She was in fact the only good
thing about Our Man 2. That is true. That is true. Yeah, and I like Gwyneth Paltrow in Our Man 2.
She was good too. Yes. So two good characters who in fact talk to each other, which is more than we
can say for Doctor Strange, where the female characters only interact with one of them's
cobitos. Anyway, that's what... Bob, will we? I am literally playing with fire, so uh...
Excellent. Anyway, sorry enough about that. This is why we should have a bit of time to fap about
before we do whatever the thing of the week was. But clearly, um, that was all follow-up on letters
because Claire mentioned the MCU. Yes, yes. Seamless it was. That was follow-up on the first
letter. We have like six more letters.
Faaar... Kay. All right, so Mark Plummer wrote in to say that he may be wrong, but it's his
impression that the language shift on Plathrow might be further along than Alison thinks. Um,
and he says, although he accepts the arguing for the excess definition, doesn't feel as pedantic,
as say, insisting decimate still means one in ten. Um, and he encourages Alison to argue that
fanist podcasts should be recorded on Twill Tone, and I don't know what Twill Tone is.
Oh, that's quite funny. If it was recorded on Twill Tone, to be fair, it would be a fan
scene, not a podcast. Twill Tone is that kind of rather fluffy paper that you print, um,
duplicate onto because it takes a duplicator ink very nicely. Oh, okay.
There were grot you that Twill Tone does sound like a recording technique rather than a paper stock.
I assumed it was like something to do with audio, so I read it as if he was
encouraging us to use wax cylinders or something. But no, fair enough. Um, he also wrote a
clairehue. Um, do you want to read the clairehue, Alison, because it is about you.
Alison Scott's erudition does not enslave her to tradition, but John's misuse of the word
plethora will be the death of her. I liked that. I thought it was good. I'm glad that we got the
poetry back this episode. He also talks a little bit about East Colin Overcon, but I suspect we
will talk about both of those things later in the episode. Claire Briarley says, "Too many courgettes
is any number of courgettes because she doesn't like courgettes." She says other things in her
lock, um, but that was my main takeaway. Your main takeaway was courgettes because that,
generally speaking, I go for like chicken ticka masala or something.
Listener, you merely have to listen to it. I have to experience it. Liz.
I am bewildered by this dislike of courgettes because I love courgettes and courgettes are
actually quite hard to find in Thailand and I'm very sad that I can't eat courgettes all the time.
So I would encourage people to send me courgettes, but that's clearly not going to work either. Um,
I actually, I did think, oh, I could post some courgettes to listen. I realised that that was an
absolutely terrible idea. No, this would be even worse than posting weeterbicks.
I like courgettes. Oh, there is also a, there's a poetry and Claire also says,
"Can we please have more of Liz's nature notes?" comedy bleeping included.
She says she's not sure she should comment on John's bedtime tones though.
The bit I personally liked in, in, in Claire's letter was the bit where she says,
"I haven't been to Alison's not very big house, only the five bedroom one in in London."
Yeah, I also really liked that.
Taking as a man with, I would, I would characterize warehouse as a two and a half bedroom house.
Um, I would, I would say that in my defence, the rooms are remarkably small for reasons
and it's only, the only way you could describe my house as in a London is if you live in Croydon.
Shots fired, Claire. Shots fired. This will become one of the great Spanish feuds.
Um, because it's no idea in a London.
Um, so she does, she does write. He writes a poet.
Time for poetry corner. This isn't prose, perhaps it makes it better. At least it's all in email,
not a letter. Discussing podcasts makes you rather meta, unless it's more, so let's not get courgette.
Thank you, Claire. I like, I like the commitment to the A, ruraming scheme. B is for cowards.
We have a letter of comment from Alison Scott in which she replies to a letter of comment from
Lillian in which Lillian replies to a letter from Alison in which Alison says to Lillian that
the tweet she denters didn't have anything in it. But if you click the tweet, you get a screenshot
and the screenshot says that, that Zoom's going to let you select your breakout rooms.
So thank you to listeners, Alison and Lillian for that.
For sending us a screenshot explaining something we mentioned in the last podcast.
Yeah, no, I'm.
I wasn't sure. Alison is just making a face. That's very
symmetric. Well, I've ventured to Alison. It's all content.
Hashtag content. Yeah, I thought I was going to rant about them MCU for 25 minutes without drawing
breath. You didn't like that content. You said start your own podcast.
If you want to talk about the MCU. I mean, I'd subscribe. That's all I'm saying.
What he actually said was that I should start a podcast where I,
where Stephen and I do commentary on the MCU as we're watching the movies. But if we did that,
then I would talk for two hours and five minutes and Stephen would say nothing.
So it wouldn't be much of a podcast with it. Yeah, I don't know. So Mark sent us a second
lot and it contains a joke. And I'm going to read the joke for your listening pleasure.
A man goes up to a grieving widow at a funeral. He explains that he was an old school friend of
the deceased. And if it's okay, he'd like to say a word at the funeral. The widow says, yes,
that would be lovely. Thank you. So the funeral comes and the man goes up and stands in front of
the assembles and says plethora. And he walks back to his seat and as he goes, the widow catches him
on the shoulder and says, thanks, that means a lot.
The stunned silence reflects the quality of the joke.
I did laugh the first time I heard it to be fair. Oh, yes, me too. I liked it a lot.
Which was not when Mark sent it, but you know, it's fine. It is very topical joke.
I laughed the second time I read it when I got the joke.
Well, I must admit that because of the way Mark formatted the email, it took me a couple of seconds
to realize that the third paragraph of the email was not a continuation of the joke.
And that forced me to go back and look more carefully for a punchline, which when I found
out, I very much enjoyed the he also says that Steve, and I'm very sorry if I pronounced the
surname wrong, Snaid. Snide, I think snide. Steve Snide, who was a champion of poetry in SF and
fandom. He thinks he would have approved the fact that we have a poetry quarter in our podcast.
So yes, we are continuing Spanish traditions. And then we have one. We have one further letter
of comment in which after Claire's mention of my bedtime tones, Bridget Bradshaw writes in to say
that she has been very much enjoying the multitude of sounds and bings and sexy johns with which we
end the podcast. And this may be spiral a lot. So thank you very much, Bridget.
I'm this is almost john fan mail. I'm not opposed.
You really need to be able to see Alison's face. Right. Name of your sex.
That did sound worryingly close to being a solicitation of sexy fan mail.
And it seems like a terrible idea as emails to the people to write to us and ask me to say
sexy things. I am not none of that seems un unwise to be. That seems fine.
Okay, so I get 14 emails of that kind every day, but luckily my email program tends to
filter them out without me seeing them. Well, yes, I should say I should say
sexy people who actually exist rather than fake spam sexy people who I also receive multiple
like it mostly Instagram and Facebook requests rather than emails. But yes, it's very straight.
I assume they make money, but I don't know how don't really want to know how. Let's move on. So.
Last episode, we talked a little bit about Eastcon and what we thought they might be doing
in the next few months to talk about going online in the interim as is tradition when we're
talking about what Eastcon might need to do in reaction to the pandemic. The government made
some announcements about the pandemic that make it look even less likely that a physical Eastcon
will be able to happen next year. The rule of six looks likely to extend into I think March 2021.
And that's assuming that it doesn't get worse, which has not been ruled out.
So the Eastcon did tweet to say that they are aware and are thinking about kind of the online
things they're going to have to do. So it sounds to me like they are planning to go online.
I should confess that I fermented that tweet by following our discussion. I wrote a little
snip about. So, you know, if you happen to still be thinking there's going to be an Eastcon,
then you should probably stop thinking that. And Vanessa suggested that I was creating
tempests in teapots. She's a potster, she says the pot, which incidentally is the name of Alice
and live Shakespeare troupe. They perform in a variety of tea rooms. I thought it was going to
be the name of my podcast commenting in real time on every Marvel Cinematic Universe movie.
Now there's got to be a bit of a spider-man on the sofa. I don't know. But that makes it
sound like you're sitting on Fran. Okay, so this is not going in the right direction at all, John.
No, okay. So yes, we are more reassured, or well I speak for us, I am more reassured than I was
last week. The Eastcon is kind of actively thinking about what's going to happen in the future.
I would still like to see a little bit more concrete information by I'm kind of glad that
they are heading in the right directions. I'm glad to see they said something, but it is
notably devoid of any concrete timescales or anything beyond we are paying attention.
And I think if you're running a convention, I would hope that you are paying attention.
I'm not so pessimistic as I think it will still be Rule of Six by Eastcon time, but there is a vast
void between you can only have six people in one place and you can have 500 in one place,
and I don't think we're going to get there by April. I should say that the Rule of Six,
which is still being widely misinterpreted, does apply to private gatherings and there are all
sorts of circumstances in which more than six people can gather. They just can't mingle. The problem
with Eastcon's is that Eastcon's are for me all about the mingling. But luckily, Novicon, having
anticipated this announced that they weren't going to run in physical form and they weren't
planning to do anything online either back in July, which left a healthy lacuna that could be filled
by somebody else. And I was wondering whether anybody knew of anything that was happening to
fill that void in the Novicon weekend, John and Liz. I have to bring you up here because
according to my quick Google, a lacuna means a cavity or depression in bone. And I just want to
know in which sense July is a bone. This is an hour age, Alison. I'm going to make this into a
regular feature where I use obviously wrong interpretations of the words you're using in order
to be faux pedantic. And I think it could go down either very well or very poorly with our
listenership. So write in. I thought that was quite funny. I have to say. Good, good. No, yes,
they did. They left a... And I will help you by using a wide spread of English words as
within somebody with a basically educated vocabulary. How? How very dare you,
my lady. Would you say that you're going to use a plethora of words? No, just the right number.
Boo, I want you to use too many. Um... Well, no, I certainly am going to use too many
words, but not necessarily too many area type words.
I've got to go inside because it's got dark, so... Liz is leaving. Right, sorry, I'll be back in a
minute. So Liz has gone inside. She has gone from being on an excellent holiday outside in
Toyland to an excellent holiday inside in Toyland, which is still a far cry from me and Alison's
not holidays in Southampton and Waltham so respectively. I was going to have a staycation where we,
because I am on holiday this week, where we went to exciting places for the day, but I think we've
concluded that we're in fact going to have a nestcation where we sit on the sofa and catch up with the
MCU. I am also, I am currently on leave, um, and I have been doing, well, I've been doing con running.
Oh, so what convention have you been running, John? We'll get there eventually, won't we?
We will, yeah. Sorry, I should have turned the video off for that bit while I wandered around,
but yes, I had come inside because I forgot it gets dark. Um, yeah.
Hang on, did you forget about nighttime or like, go into this a little bit more?
I think Liz probably means that it gets dark on holiday where they have limited amounts of power
in a fantastic rural retreat, isn't that right Liz? No, it's more that I forgot that it,
when it starts to get dark, it goes dark quite quickly. Like, because we are much more in the
equator, um, I always forget how quickly it gets dark basically. I'm used to this long, slow
evening and actually doesn't it starts getting dark, gets dark. Also, it started raining again,
which is why it was getting dark. It turns out so, so you're saying it's dark, cold and wet.
I think it was cold. Oh, okay. I was just going, you could be a Waltham's stove. Come to Waltham's
stove. Waltham's stove is great for holidays. Oh, God. Oh, dear. The sadness with which you said
that, Alison. Can I ask you to take a couple of things?
I did actually read a useful thing that said, essentially, the reason you're all really miserable
is because you've, you're six months into this change in the way we live now. And that's a point
at which humans have to go through an adjustment phase where they move from going, oh, this is a
short-term thing we will get through into being a long-term thing that we have to change the way
we think about things to accommodate. And you're all struggling with that at the moment. And I
went, well, that makes sense. That would explain why I'm so incredibly grumpy all the time at the
moment. I had, um, I had the adjustment yesterday. I realized that waiting for the world to get back
to normal before I decided to start wailing and cleaning and riding my bike again would mean that
by the time that happened, my bike would have been fully consigned to the scrap heap. So yes,
that I cleaned and oiled and rode my bike just for the purposes of making sure my bike worked.
And I have set a reminder to do that every month. And that was my kind of concession to the fact that
this is, this is how it is now, which, you know, is fun.
"Hark to Thorp, come for the witty banter, stay for the depressing COVID talk."
Yeah, so what are we doing to stay sane during the apocalypse, boys and girls?
Well, I was quite enjoying the thing I was doing was to keep nearly announcing that we're
running a convention and they're not quite announcing it. And I was having quite a lot of fun with that.
We could probably do that, but only until the end of the podcast, right?
That's the thing. We should probably at some point announce that we're announcing a convention.
Are we announcing a convention, John?
Yes, we're going to run a convention.
Me and Liz and Alison and Steve Davis are going to run a convention called punctuation.
And it is going to be the Novicon weekend, which for those who don't know is the 13th to the 15th
of November 2020. It is going to be a GMT-friendly convention, but people from around the world are
more than welcome to join us at the points in which GMT overlies overlaps.
Which is all of them really, because I mean, we're not saying you can't
get drunk and stay up all night and then have your breakfast at six o'clock in the morning.
That's true. We would never say that. I feel very confident.
We are saying we won't provide you with that breakfast, so you might want to make other arrangement.
Yes. But yes, so this is our... So, the Eagle Eared listener may have noticed last week.
That we did more than usual talking about if we ran a convention, how would we do it,
as opposed to simply talking about how other people do it.
And that was because we were already beginning to ruminate on this
this convention we are ready, and we are now ready to announce it and let people know that
it's happening and to reserve the weekend. At the time of recording, we are not ready to take
payments. It's going to be a fiver. The fiver is basically to cover our costs, which are sort of
not huge, but more than we'd like to do out our own pockets. Any profit we make will be split
evenly between the League of Fan Funds and a charitable cause, which will probably be decided
by a vote from our members. We will select some charities we like and then we'll let people
have some input as to which one they think should benefit. Yes. So, how are you two feeling about
running a convention? I'm very excited about running a convention. I think one of the big things
about adapting to the world we now live is to stop saying, "Ah, when everything gets back to normal,
we'll have conventions again" and start saying, "We're going to have conventions again. They're online."
And there are a lot of conventions online already, but they've all been slightly not quite right
for me because they have been what I think covers program-first conventions, where the idea is to
have a fantastic program and what I want is to have a social first convention, where the idea is
to have a fantastic bar. You'll have to bring your own beer or drink of your choice. Yes.
So, punctuation is a social first convention. Liz, do you want to talk about it near that?
Slightly old sex tape. So, my feeling is apparently if all my friends decided to join a convention,
apparently I would join them in running a convention. No, that doesn't make sense because I heard
the wrong word. Well, I mean, you know how some people said, "If all your friends jumped off a cliff,
would you also jump off a cliff?" And it's basically this book for con running, which is,
when I was in general, like, "Yeah, let's run a convention." I'm like, "Yeah, I guess so,"
because otherwise we're going to spend all of what's up talking about this convention anyway,
so I may as well help. And also because I am that person who sees a convention and I'm like,
"Ooh, maybe they're doing that wrong and I can complain about it." And in this way,
I don't complain about it. I actually do something about it. It's that positive enough.
The my favorite joke, which I've seen this last two weeks is, "If all your friends jumped off a
cliff, would you jump off a cliff too?" Machine learning algorithm. Yeah, yes, yes, I would jump
off the cliff. Anyway, that might just be me. Apparently that wasn't funny either. I'm sorry.
I quite liked it. Yeah, that's basically it. It's like, "Well, you're going to do this anyway,
so I can either join in or I can watch and sideline." I thought, "Well, why not?" Yeah, no, we do. It's
a small British SF convention, which means it's going to have some serious programming and some
not-so-serious programming. And it is going to be more serious earlier in the day and less serious
later in the day. And we are going to encourage you to do some things that are not just sitting on
your arse for 48 hours at a convention. So we need to, we haven't quite worked out what those
will be, but we want you to move around a bit as well so that you don't feel that you are
turning into slughood whilst also attending the convention. But obviously you won't actually be
meeting up because we're not allowed to do that. And we very much want all of your help to tell us
what we should be doing. You can write to us, there's an email address, which will be in the
show notes, but I think it's punctuationcon@gmail.com. And we have a website and we have a Facebook page
and we have a Twitter page. And as I think John said, it will be a fiver. We think that's going to
cover our costs. It rather depends because if 20 of you sign up, it probably won't. But if
a thousand of you sign up, it definitely will. Yes, we're assuming that our final membership will
be somewhere between 20 and 1000. But we haven't gotten any more detailed forecasting than that. So
join up, tell us how much we're looking at. I mean, to be fair, our costs are relatively fixed.
So yes, John has not run a convention before. And so he is saying things like our costs are
relatively fixed. And I have run conventions before. And I am saying things like it would be on the
whole better to underestimate the amount we need so that we have some room for error rather than
over it. Sorry, I overestimate the number one. It would be better to leave some slack in the
budget so that there is some space to do things because in general, you have costs you aren't
expecting when you start these things like any other project. And given this is a virtual
convention, anonymous, have run a virtual convention before, we may not even be able to take an
accurate guess of what things we will need to pay for that we forgot we might have to pay for.
The opening ceremony for the convention will occur on the evening of the Friday. I don't think
we've nailed down a specific time, but I'd expect it to be six and a log or seven o'clock or
or something like that. An appropriate time to get in your takeaway and crack open your first beer,
that kind of thing. But there won't be any formal programming on the Friday except for the opening
ceremony. It will be social spaces hanging out and establishing our hangovers for the Saturday
program. And then Saturday will have and Sunday will have two blocks of program and two blocks of
social time. So it'll be program social program social through the day. The earlier block of program
will be more serious programming and the later block of program will probably tend to war
silly drunken programming in the grand tradition of British conventions. We have got permission from
the Novicon committee to use their weekend, but we are not affiliated with Novicon and we are also
not affiliated with, well, Liz and I are not affiliated with Plochter and Steve and Alison are
one third of Plochter respectively. It depends how you count. That's actually, I think just kind of
saying, I think probably saying it's probably best not to mention Plochter really because we're
kind of not saying that it's anything like it. Listen, or if you could please ignore the fact we
mentioned Plochter, we would appreciate it. Oh, and Sue Mason is drawing us up. That's our other
link with Plochter is that we have a fantastic logo which we will put in the show notes that is based
on art from Sue. Yes, we will sort of put it in the show notes because we will put a link to the
conventional website on the show notes and everyone will click it and they will be able to see the
fantastic art of Sue Mason and it is really beautiful. Can you put chapter headings in our
with actual art in our podcast, John? Because I know that some podcasts do this and you could
definitely have the art in that. Well, you, not only do you know that some podcasts do it, but I
think you know how a podcast does it. I think I know that we have done it. Oh, good. Do we do it
every time? Whenever it's funny. Okay, so I've got this thing that I listen to podcasts rather than
looking at them. I don't know if this is normal. When I look at something, I tend to think it's like
a vlog. Well, fair enough. Or a television show or an MCU movie or something of that kind.
But I do understand that some people like pictures in their podcast.
Yes, well, it's good. So yeah, so we're going to be running it on discord and zoom. So the kind of
the backbone of the convention and the kind of social spaces between the parties, the room parties
or the zoom parties will be occurring on discord. When you pay your £5, you will be sent a link
to the discord server and you can hop on and join the masses. And that will be available as a sort
of text medium before the convention starts. And then when the convention starts properly,
we'll really get swinging and links to the panels and stuff will be posted on the discord.
And they the panels will be happening on zoom. There will be zoom parties a bit like the first
Thursday meetings or the Sheffield third Sunday meetings. And so there will be zoom stuff happening.
And we will also probably be experimenting with some of the other social tools we mentioned a
little bit in our last episode. So, or maybe as the episode before, what is time?
We might experiment with some of those before the convention so we can see which ones work.
Yes. And if you join early, you might be invited to help us.
If you are listening to this going, oh, I'm not sure about discord. I haven't tried discord.
It's another thing to do. I think one of the things that your fiver will get you is some
is some technical support to get on to discord because it's not very complicated.
And I think do want everybody to join the discord if at all possible. And we're not
quite sure how we're going to sort it out for people who don't. So, you know, I will also say
that if you are thinking, oh, this sounds good, but I really can't afford a fiver at the moment,
then just drop us an email and we will sort it out. It's a recoup of our costs. We don't want it to
be a barrier to entry for people who really can't do that, but it just helps us cover the Zoom.
Yeah, that we are. We are not planning to spend a lot of money implementing a financial gateway
that means that people who haven't paid can't access the convention. We are planning to use the
very traditional English gateway of orimate. You appear to be in the bar, but you're not on the
list list. I've got here. Where's your fiver then? Yeah, and I think I am in general looking forward
to we've had we've had Liz. So Liz is as regular listeners will be aware and people who have paid
attention in the previous, however many minutes of this episode will be aware. Liz is oftentimes
in Thailand. And what this means is that when Alison and Steve and I spend an evening drinking
beer and brainstorming program ideas, Liz wakes up and says, "Aha, I see that the silly program
ideas have been well considered. And we are also going to have some serious ones, which is going
to be good." I thought of at least two serious ones and that they'll be brilliant. So yeah,
that's the Coxing Guarantee. The things I think are probably brilliant.
Yeah, I am quite looking forward to working out what we can try that hasn't been tried before,
certainly in terms of social space. We certainly got Zoom, but maybe trying to make sure Zoom is a
sort of friendly and welcoming experience for everyone at our parties and social spaces. I'm not
quite sure how we integrate that with Discord, but we'll have a go. I think Alison is definitely
keen to try out some non-zoom things and see if we can find ones that work in a more organic way
than sticking people in Zoom breakout rooms. But I'm also quite keen to think of ways we could do
program, which is not just you watch five talking heads on a Zoom window and send us some, you know,
text message questions. So if anyone has any great ideas for exciting program formats or
exciting program items, they think they would like to have a go at in a virtual way. Let us know.
And we're going to be thinking about it quite a lot. That's kind of what we're doing at the
moment when we're not on here. We are busily running our convention 24 hours a day, seven days a week
as the internet now provides. Yes, except for when I'm in the garden with my cats or playing a
board game and except for when Liz is drinking coconut room on a beach. And except for when Alison
is shouting at MCU movies instead of recording a podcast about them. Note that I didn't say we
weren't running it in our sleep because that would be disingenuous and untrue. Honestly, what we
should do is that Lillian and I should do a close rewatch of the MCU movies whilst commenting on them.
Okay, and literally John, I'll only do that if you agree to edit it.
No, the beautiful thing with this kind of podcast, Alison, is that you don't have to edit it.
Why do you think I'm doing my arc of horror play? It takes me three seconds, but all these days,
glorious. This episode also serves as a challenge to the hosts of the This Never Happens podcast.
We challenge you to some sort of panel or parlour game to be played at punctuation, to be
emcee'd by someone who we have not yet picked, but will certainly give us an unfair advantage.
Do you dare to challenge us? This never happens. I hope they say yes, it'll be really funny.
I also hope they listen to this episode. Otherwise, that's going to fall completely flat.
Somebody will tell them about it. If you listen to This Never Happens,
please send them a letter of comment asking if they have listened to this episode of Octa Thought.
Let's properly militarise our listenership and get this going.
You know what? I could actually do that before our episode comes out.
Singers, I think so far, they're the only person who has complained to us that we didn't mention
one of their letters, because at the point where we, they hadn't actually sent it to the
point where we recorded the following episode. But yes, no, we think it would be good to have
some sort of parlour or panel game, which is Us vs This Never Happens, and within that it could
be good. So yes, hopefully we will be able to make that happen. We will see.
Suggestions for appropriate games we could play are welcome. I have the excuse,
so if it turns out to be an inconvenient time zone for me, I will just duck out and make some
kind of stunt person place me. It will be good. It will be an appropriate selected person.
Well, we got anything else to say? No, I don't think so.
Yeah, it's okay. We're further along than the people planning the virtual.
I'm not. Oh, God. Why do you say these things? Give me an edging noise.
Because they're funny. I'm bleeping at Alison, bleeping it. But yes, no, it will be good.
We're looking forward to it. 30th to 15th of November, be there. We hope to see you all and a lot of
your friends as well and tell everyone you know. Anyway, and thanks very much again to Novacom for
cancelling nice and early because we have, although it looks like we're announcing this at last
minute, we have actually been working on this for a little while. We'd be thinking about it for some
time. Yeah, so I mean, thank you to Novacom for cancelling in time. You know, thank you to Novacom
for cancelling in time and saying quite clearly, we're not going to do anything on that weekend,
which meant we could say, okay, this is a time where maybe a lot of people are feeling like they'd
normally like a weekend of discussing science fiction and hanging out with their mates in a bar.
And Novacom's in that sort of cold, dark bit of winter when it's not Christmas yet. And so maybe
you need something to kind of get you through the darkest bit of the winter. And we could be that,
except we won't be darvacol here. But anyway, your coke, Liz. Somehow I will cope with 30 degree
temperature. It won't be quite like Novacom though. If anyone would like to come along,
please go to the website and either clicking the join button will take you to a place where you
can give us a fiverr or clicking the join button will take you to a place where you can put your
email address in and be notified when you can give us a fiverr. If you have any ideas for things
you'd like to see that would make punctuation feel a bit more like going to a Novacom or a
plopter con or an Easter con or that kind of British convention experience, please drop us
a line. We're curious to know what people have been missing from the UK convention scene. And
yeah, we're keen to involve the community as much as we can in this style of the great fan run
conventions. Oh, should I talk about the t-shirts? Given that Alison is involved, there will certainly
be t-shirts. Yeah, there'll be a t-shirt with Al lovely logo on it. I think there'll probably be a
link to that in the show notes if I get my act together by Thursday, which I might not because I'm
having the week off, but you know, probably will do. Should be able to manage that. You will have to
provide your own mushrooms, I'm afraid. Yeah, we could have like a breakfast workshop, couldn't we?
We could just have a bring your fry up where you will, you know, bring your fry ups and we
argue about whether they should include hash browns or not. It's a generational thing. Oh, we can have
like, we could have like social space at breakfast where although Zoom generally is choose your own
breakout rooms, we're going to say you're not allowed to have more than four of you in any of them and
you have to find some knives and forks from another table and the hotel will randomly put you with
people that might not be who you decided you wanted to have breakfast with and then you'll be able
to see the next table where somebody much more interesting is having breakfast or you'll be having
a hangover and you will nevertheless be having your hangover in the company of spending the
unvaribly cheerful in the morning who plocks themselves down at your table and is full of beans.
So first off that will be me because by the time everyone in the UK gets up with a hangover,
I would have been awake for 6,000 drunk a load of coffee and two, can we replicate that experience
of being able to see that the hotel have decided on site whether you are Spanish or not and therefore
directed you to the nice breakfast buffet or the slightly shit breakfast buffet. Sorry I said
shit, you can't say that can I? You can believe that. The slightly less good breakfast buffet,
I mean or it's possible that some of you will be the sort of people whose breakfast is excellent
and who will naturally be sitting down to a plate of a delicious freshly cooked full English and
others of us will be trying to find out if we've got any cornflakes that aren't slightly moldy.
So there is a cafe near to my house and they do fry-ups to go and for the princely sum of 12
pounds you can get two fry-ups with black puddings and mushrooms and bacon and sausages and toast
and hash browns and beans and tomato and it is good. Oh that sounds amazing. And on the south coast as
well which is. Oh okay so in Epping Forest and I know that some of the people who listen to this
podcast already know this, there is a hut called the log cabin that serves food and drink almost
all the time. I think they might be 24 hours a day most of the time and at the point where lockdown
happened they seamlessly switched to just eat or delivery or something like that or Uber eats
and they will send massive baguettes full of eggs and bacon and sausage around to your house
and I haven't done this but I think I'm actually going to and in fact I'm going to encourage everybody
to on punctuation weekend have their breakfast delivered because I think that's very cool and it
won't cost you anything like as much as going to a convention would and we can all see what
people's breakfast that are delivered are like and that would be good. Upside to the convention
basically starting about 4pm is that I will be able to go out and have a nice brunch before we start.
No this is up there because I went to a convention that started 9am US time and it is kind of nice
to have the morning just sort of puttering about doing chores and then settle in for a day of
convention. So yeah it does it works quite well. Yeah although I'd clearly be sleeping off the
hangover. Yeah. Yeah.
Oh I'll tell you something that has happened which is the great leapfrog
which is that Smofcon 2020 is now Smofcon 2022 and Smofcon 2021 is continuing as planned in
Lisbon. Oh yeah yeah okay are you looking puzzled at me. So the idea of 2021 don't want to go later
because they're all going to be busy running Glasgow in 2024 but 2020 can't happen. So basically
the 2022 bids agreed to stand aside and let 2020 hop into 2022 and then 2021 don't have to move.
So they can't just all push back a year it's got to be a hop over. Right so yes so Smofcon
makes sense. Do we think that Smofcon in 2021 will run? Yeah I did think it was a bit of a
stretch. I mean I'm kind of like how do I feel about Eastercon 2022 at this point? So Smofcon 2021
for listeners will be running on my birthday. So December 2021 for those who don't know when I was
born. I think this is all of this is why I feel that I kind of want to start creating the new
world we're living in rather than anchoring after the old one. I think Smofcon might run because
2021 we're talking about December so late 2021. It seems plausible to me that you could run a
Smof... European Smofcon is likely to be I would say 100 to 150 people and you may not get as many
North American visitors as usual but I think you might be able to have people traveling
within Europe for smallish gatherings like that in 2021. Yeah I mean I think my gut feeling is
that if things are as they are now it's unlikely to go well if things get better over the next year
and a half then it might be more likely to work. I am I think basically for the next year I'm
skeptical but I do think eventually. I just thought it was interesting that I thought that the way
that Smofcon had handled this was starting to think through it was an alternative that wasn't
just cancelling everything forever right it was saying there are other ways to do it that are not
just bouncing the whole of our lives forward for a year but it was still essentially going oh well
we're not going to run the convention which I thought was interesting. That was the 15th episode
of the OctaThaw podcast and for now it's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod at Ncompetech.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 3.0 license.
That makes sense John you look puzzled. Yeah I am I am that makes sense sorry I got I did that
thing where I start immediately working on a thing that I decided I should work on and I should pay
attention instead. Oh I see you're actually doing something else rather than paying attention to.
Okay John that's all right. It turns out that the the iPlayer has almost no genre films on it
except for King Kong. But King Kong is a great start. Well yeah but it is it's not it's mostly
and actually there's quite a lot I would like to see because a lot of them are caper films and I
do like a caper film. Will they do have night of the living dead? Anyway I will well I'll come back to
this. Oh yeah come on John. But that all makes sense. I've never been to a smothcon and last week
when Alison said something happened at smothcon she meant it. I didn't mean con runner yeah and
con runner is kind of British smothcon. There were two I think con runners run in the run up to
lncon 3. They've got 12 monkeys. Sorry sorry they've also got a lot of grand day out and
volus and corona grand day out is definitely sci-fi. It is but it might not still be there it might
not still be there in November so that's something this is this is a hold that thought for the moment
yeah uh 12 monkeys are Netflix for me so it might be on Netflix for you so there we go. Yeah nothing's
basically in general nothing is on Netflix UK that's not a Netflix origin. This podcast will end
at the beep. Beep.