Hello everyone, it's John here.
Just to let you know, Liz was travelling this episode and she is using a headset mic which has a very attractive low hum during parts of her recording.
This came and went and changed and it made it very difficult to get rid of it.
So there are still some traces on the track and there's not a lot I can do about that, I'm afraid.
But I hope you enjoy the episode anyway.
On with the show.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 151st episode of Octothorpe
Which is lying in front of the bulldozer and wondering why its house is about to be knocked down on the 15th of January 2026.
Happy New Year.
I'm John Coxon.
Happy New Year, I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
We're a bit rusty, aren't we?
Look, right, all of the pauses will come seamlessly out in the edit, Liz.
Has it been a while, guys?
No, I think we should leave them in.
I don't I did send a bad precedent that.
I hope everyone had a lovely festive period.
Um, yeah, no, no, it was good.
I played a lot of board games.
I dri a I ate a prodigious quantity of cheese.
Do
Prodigious.
Well we had twenty two cheeses.
Twenty two cheeses?
That's quite a lot of cheese.
Yeah.
I
Quite a lot less cheese than Allison, I think, is the answer.
It's not hard to eat less cheese than Allison.
I have persuaded all my family that what we need is consumable.
Christmas presents and several different people bought us cheese this year.
Plus I kinda panicked and bought a load of cheese in just in case there wasn't enough cheese.
There's still some cheese.
It's fantastic.
Oh, I don't know if I've ever told this story on the podcast.
When I was eighteen, my my mum I'd I'd learnt to drive, so I could be sent on errands, and my mother gave me twenty pounds and the instructions to go to Waitrose and buy Brie.
What do you suppose I did?
Bought twenty pounds worth of brie.
Alright.
Liz, can you say bought twenty pounds worth of brie because Alison's currently got a mouthful of cranona?
Porridge, yes.
Bought twenty pounds worth of brie?
Yes.
And then I got home and she said, Oh put the change on the counter and I said, What change?
And she went, You don't mean to say you've spent twenty pounds on Brie and I said, Yeah
What else did you want me to do?
Anyway, this has passed into legend as a funny thing that John did at Christmas, but I maintain it was the reasonable thing to do.
You know, other soft French cheeses are available.
I wasn't asked to buy the other soft French cheeses.
Yeah, I mean the the main problem is that it's too much Brie and not enough other non Brie cheeses.
Having trouble with this concept 'cause I feel like you said too much Brie there.
Yeah, too much brie without you know, you want a balanced cheese board.
Johnny's just bought twenty pounds worth of brie and now there is no money for other cheese.
To be fair, I'm sure there was money for other cheese.
Really, come on.
Yes, I think it's fair to say, I mean I don't want to
I I I d I don't want to um oversell our wealth as a family, but I will say that there was probably more than twenty pounds available for cheese at Christmas.
Which is its own form of privilege.
It's so oh yeah, so much.
Check your cheese privilege.
But also I find that when I have a balanced cheese board, it is common for the soft white French cheese to run out first, so
I don't think it's insane to have a cheese board that is oversupplied in brie.
I was worried we wouldn't have enough to talk about this episode, but I forgot that we could discuss cheese apparently.
Thank you to everyone who uh wrote us letters of comments.
I am gonna get the ball rolling.
Casella wrote on
Blue Sky saying, sorry if I missed it, but I've been waiting for weeks now on the whole MathMos business, assuming it was an intricate Barbarella joke setup.
But apparently not.
And then um Hispania uh linked um there were there was a group chat where people were like, what is he talking about?
An Hispania linked Barbarello Meets the Matmos, so I'll put a link in the show notes.
But no, we were in fact not just uh in a Barbarella-themed joke with Emily Tesch.
uh we do not have that level of foresight or planning.
Um but it is very funny so thank you very much Cassella.
Hang on though Barbarella meets the Mat Mouse.
Yeah.
Matmas.
So that's probably not the origin of the term in the first place.
I don't think Cassella is arguing that that's the etymology of the tone Cambridge.
Although Cassella, if that was the argument, please write in.
No, I th I thought his argument was that we had made this whole thing up from whole cloth as a barbarella joke.
Oh that that would be elaborate for us.
The yeah, the one that would be a very elaborate set of forward planning required from us and we would have had to pull Emily Tesh in on the whole joke and indeed the whole audience of your Novicon live pod.
Yeah, your your typical Novicon audience of Cambridge Math Mose.
I just wanna say, you know, um sorry to Cassella, this is in fact real.
This is how
Daft it is.
And I think I think it's worth noting that it is it is probably fair to say that Cambridge University is less believable than Barbarella.
I can having spent three years at Cambridge University and only two hours in Barbarella, I can confirm.
Uh yes, indeed.
So thank you very much, Casella.
We heard from Paul Weimer, who uh discussed T shirt versus fleets versus shorts weather, the ongoing conundrum.
Um and he says nine degrees here in Minneapolis.
St.
Paul is t shirt and grilling weather.
Uh no.
You may you may not know this listeners, but I normally live in a very warm place, and currently I am in the UK where it is not very warm, and I have complained about it near
Additional to this our houses are kind of bad.
I mean not everybody's, but certainly mine has cold bits and I'm sitting in one of them.
Um to record the podcast.
I've been sitting in perfectly nice warm insulated houses.
Including John's house, but maybe not John's attic.
I gave you the thick duveilers.
You did.
I had to get and then I had to get the second duvet out.
Yeah, that is fair.
Um
It turns out you can take the girl out of Lancashire and you can take the Lancashire out of the girl.
Paul also says that Nuremberg vs.
Australia is a tough choice.
Uh because yeah, like
And points out that the the Australian one is timed for the for the lunar eclipse.
Solar eclipse.
So that is an extra added thing if you are going on an adventure.
Sorry, solar eclipse, solar eclipse.
Uh Paul actually said solstice, but I think he means solar eclipse.
So I was inferring anyway.
Yeah, we have solstices twice a year, Paul.
Three times on uh leap years.
That's true.
That is a red memo.
Is that a civil service slang for bollocks?
Uh no, it's a blueprint slang for bollocks.
Okay, cool.
Uh the solar eclipse is in Australia.
It's worth noting it's not in Brisbane.
I am slightly like you would still have to go and stay in a different city after after the world con.
to see the the solar eclipse and Australia's big enough that that is perhaps non-trivial.
Being Australia that could be eight thousand miles away.
I got an app, listeners.
This app I don't think exists on Android, so sorry to the Androiders among you, but there is an app called Eclipse Live, which shows the next like hundred years of eclipses and their paths on the Earth, and you can filter by like types of eclipse and stuff.
It goes through Sydney, which is not too far south of Brisbane, sort of relatively speaking to Australia.
Does also go through like a large part of the bit of Australia that's not got anyone in it, so
If you've got a tent and a camper van, you can probably find somewhere to see it.
July 2028.
Yeah, I think it's a reasonable assumption that most of the people going to Australia will probably go to more than one city anyway.
Yeah.
No, and it is quite easy in Australia to get to some very dark places.
So we heard a lot about Rwanda um and especially on the visa topic.
So
Um Casella and Tammy wrote on Blue Sky about Rwanda.
So Tammy highlighted that multiple people applied for visas and
Meg MacDonald wrote in the Facebook comments that I think it was eight people applied and were denied.
File seven seventy has the um scoop in which Tammy says the Swedish authorities are remarkably frank about their prejudices.
Uh and also notes that personalized invitation letters were issued despite the reaction of the Swedish authorities.
Frederick Coulter wrote in our Facebook
He's been supporting the Chigali bid because he thinks widening the WorldCon audience is a good thing and he's never been to Chigali.
I've never been to Africa.
I've been to Morocco, but I really kinda think there's some very real senses in which that doesn't count.
Well that's interesting because what Frederick suggests and Lillian Edwards highlighted is that it might be that having Morocco as a WorldCon destination, like for example Casablanca
might be a good way to have an African worldcom that gets around some of these visa issues.
Lilin also says Morocco isn't really Africa in that kind of sense.
It's like a much more
uh on the European side of things.
And then says maybe Cape Town in South Africa would be a good venue if you wanted to have an African WorldCon.
So so this is a sort of suggestion that what the WorldCon might need is Africa Lite TM
Well I think what you do is you do what you can to build the momentum, right?
Um and so I don't think anyone's suggesting I don't know if Africa Lights the right framing, because I don't think
I think that has a kind of a pejorative sense that I don't think is intended.
Oh yeah, no it was one hundred percent intended.
By me.
By well in that case, I think the idea is if you can start if you can have an African WorldCon in a place where it's possible, can you then build to having an African WorldCon somewhere where it's much harder?
So Meg notes, um, as someone who works in HEI the rate of visa denial no longer surprises her at all, and that is it's sad but true.
And I don't know how you get around any of this stuff, which is a great shame.
We did hear from Tommy Ferguson by email.
Tommy linked us to the Corruption Perceptions Index.
And Rwanda has a score of uh fifty-seven out of a hundred and is forty-third out of a hundred and eighty around the world.
Is that thirty-third most corrupt or thirty-third least corrupt?
So Denmark is the first ranked.
So I think forty-third means that it's the forty-third least corrupt country.
out of 180.
I feel like that's actually quite good.
Well, yeah, so what Tommy basically says is 43 is not bad, but
He says given its location, he would still be looking at restricting engagement with a country at this rating and would be looking at payment controls.
Looking at the list, it seems like it's probably
one of if not the highest African country in terms of its in terms of its ranking on this metric.
It's much higher than Morocco, for instance.
Yeah.
I was about to say that.
Much higher than Morocco.
You know, which is a a h a a a common holiday destination.
It's it's higher than Spain and Italy.
For instance.
It's it's higher than China, it's higher than South Africa.
Yeah, so so and it's also increasing sharply recently.
So one of the things that's going on here is Rwanda is clearly
trying to be taken seriously as a safe international country.
And is is suffering some perception issues with that.
Yes.
I think we should not get too f deep into to international
politics and perceptions of Rwanda because it is complicated and I don't think we can really do it soup super full justice.
I I'm wary to draw too many conclusions because obviously we're not experts.
It is.
It was interesting to hear from someone who is.
So thank you very much, Tommy.
I guess the question is, do we want an African WorldCon for the sake of having an African WorldCon, in which case, like Morocco slash Casablanca might be the way to go?
Or is it because we want to accurately
bring in parts of the international community in which case Chigali is the place that seems to actually have some fans who would like to hang out or well
Chigali is the place where African fans seem to quite want us to come and hang out, so maybe we should be like not saying, well, have you thought about this place?
It's more acceptable to the Western side of things.
Or is that useful to build momentum?
I think it's a really hard discussion.
I'm mostly just heartbroken at how hard it is for the people to actually participate in in the fandom, because it's very sad.
Yeah, I mean eight eight denials out of eight is a lot and a lot of work and a lot of expense.
I think I'd also just say that no, like Rwanda to Morocco is
Quite some distance?
Hmm.
Yeah, yeah.
Well that's everything, right?
Africa's huge.
And the flights internally are not as well joined up.
So it may be that actually that is not a particularly easy destination.
for African fandom to get to anyway, even if they can get visas.
So I think I'm with the if they would like to try it in Chicali, let's like help them do it in Chicali, rather than suggesting
you know, do it somewhere else.
And I think it was a well meaning suggestion.
I think it's an interesting thought experiment.
But yeah, I don't know I don't know that it's the best way.
Another thing that was written on Facebook is uh Meg corrected us, uh, SmothCon43 is being co-chaired by Esther and Vince Doherty.
We got a letter from Christopher J.
Garcia.
Yo.
He says, Jolly Crimbo to y'all.
Hey, Jolly Crimbo, Chris.
I've never said Jolly Krimbo.
We could tell from the delivery.
I don't think I have either to be fair.
Uh he also says I am chaotic question mark.
Let's leave that as a question
for the listeners to answer in the privacy of their own homes, Chris.
Um yeah, he's found some jugger teams in California and is gonna go and buy some merch.
Yeah, and b basically the best thing anyone can do for a seated world con is to throw money at them, which maybe I'll be correct.
This is r relv related to our discussion of Montreal, which we'll come back to later.
But yeah, basically buying memberships and throwing money at them is a great big thing you can.
Yes.
The it's the three stats for a world con in ZooCon are people, good will, and finance.
And if you can materially increase any of those points
then you are doing good for that worldcon.
And you know, so volunteering and giving the money to excellent ways to help out.
And he says that Nairobi is the African city WorldCon should hit first.
Possibly.
Interesting.
Yeah, I think that's probably true.
Well uh certainly an argument.
Having seen the Weeble and Bob uh video
About Kenya, I agree.
I mean it's I guess I have been to Kenya and I have successfully, you know, paid for things in Kenya and had no problem with banking and so on.
So he's probably right for the average punter there.
I haven't spent any time in Nairobi though.
Uh it does have lions.
I can tell you that one.
It's also got tigers and it pisses all over Norway.
Would you like photos of lions for the cover art this week?
Uh yes.
Obviously.
Yeah, let's just do that.
I co I could do with I could do with a week off art.
Alright.
Sounds good to me.
Uh and that's that's Chris's potted lock.
I if you could get three lions in a row
I do have three lines in a row.
Yeah, and if and if and if two of them could be wearing glasses.
Mmm.
And that might be a stretch.
Might need some Photoshop.
Photoshop is something I can definitely do.
Okay.
Um I have linked to the Weeble and Bob video, Where Can You See Lions in the show notes, listeners, and if you want a slice of early internet, then it is available for you.
The weird thing is
I don't think I've ever seen this one.
I could have sworn I'd seen all of You never see Lions again ya.
It's an absolute classic.
I know.
It's one of the foundational texts of my whole personality, which is a bit worrying, but there you are.
I mean, I've been earworm with it now and we'll have it for the rest of the day, so
I'm just waiting to see if I can hear the sound of where can you see lions leaking out of Alison's headphones.
Alison looks absolutely delighted, listeners.
Her face is agape, her hands are up, she looks she's radiant.
We're going to Kenya A free snorkel with every biscuit.
Yes.
No, I've never seen that one.
I am I am I would suggest I'm probably better versed in early internet memes than
Any of the rest of us?
I can't do memes now, though my children sometimes send me them.
Yeah, I mean I think the other th but the the thing I would say, Alison, is that
When I was looking at internet memes, you had small children, so Oh yeah, no n no my my internet memes are way before that.
They're like hamster dance and all your bass that belong to that and okay.
Yes.
Yes
I'm aware of all internet traditions, Alison.
Um I don't we uh we we we know the forms.
We know the ancient words
I mean, okay, I'm just gonna say I'm not I'm not gonna try and but I did get the first spam message along with a lot of other people, right?
But but that was cool.
Everyone sit around and what Mar Allison tells you stories.
Right.
Did Chris say anything else, Liz, or was it just a very brief lock this week?
Uh he did also uh talk about hotel breakfasts.
Oh yeah.
I like hotel breakfasts.
Everyone likes hotel breakfasts.
We also heard from Tommy Ferguson again.
He said on Smovcon, he's still sad that he missed it, but could confirm on the organizational front, especially for newcomers, that everything you said was true.
Amanda Sloan attended on her for her first time on a bursary from Reconnect, and there was nothing for her to register, say hello, or signage on the Friday.
She didn't know very anyone, and it wasn't really until Saturday that she met a few people that
that James and I have pointed her towards, mainly through the fan tables.
It was a really disappointing start for someone who I think will be a great com runner in the future.
So this is something that Lisbon will be looking at and I'm sure Lisbon are already looking at it and I know that Lisbon some some members of the Lisbon team listen to this podcast, so go.
if you've got newcon runners th they need nurturing and and attention.
Um Tommy also says his weekend runs are getting longer, so you will have to make your episodes longer.
I'm going to suggest, Tommy, that you should just run faster.
It's good advice.
That's the standard of sports coaching you're gonna get from Octothorpe.
Run us right in.
But no, I don't think we're gonna make the episodes longer, but we can recommend other podcasts you might like to listen to.
Hugo, Girl! and Critical Friends and A Meal of Thorns.
We should probably do at some point we should make this into a topic because we haven't talked about other fan casts for a while and we probably ought to.
So thank you for the nudge, Tommy.
We also heard from Darren Briskman, but we're going to promote this into a full segment, listeners.
Um, because Darren is the co-chair of Montreal 2027 and he wrote in with a uh PDF of the Montreal org chart.
I and I do love an org.
Oh, you know I love an org.
And he says, we're very happy you've been discussing our upcoming WorldCon on the podcast, and we always appreciate helpful criticism.
He says that
He knows they need a new website and there is now a new website which is available.
We'll talk about that in a second.
And then he says, uh, I was surprised to hear the comment about perceived failures of recruiting.
We have a full slate of division heads and a nearly full slate of deputy division heads and most of our area heads.
We're strong believers it's never too early to recruit.
and engaged staff and with strong believers in asking in seeking to recruit leaders and volunteers who haven't yet participated.
We
He attached a copy of the current org chart.
And then he says um it was d apparently it was available in the information packet that was part of the Smovcon QA, um which we did not spot.
Um, but he says that you are unaware of this helps us understand we need to be more assertive in communicating the status of our recruiting.
I would say that the new Montreal website does not have a copy of this on it that I can see.
When I go to a convention's website, and I know this might just be me, but the committee and staff list is normally the first place I look.
I don't think it's the first place I look, but it's often one of the things that I do want sort of you know, it's on one of the things I expect to see and I will go to the website to try and find that information.
So I will say I will say nice little nice little webpage with all of this on would be would be top notch.
But um I will find it on the SmothCon website and I will link it in the show notes listeners so you can follow along.
But I have a copy open and we can talk a little bit about it today.
Is it definitely on the SmofCon website?
Uh I'm I should double check, shouldn't I?
Doot do do do.
Well that's tricky because
Uh it's actually genuinely unclear to me that the things are still on the SmothCon website at all.
Hold on.
We linked a bunch of these in the previous We did.
Oh Future Conventions QA.
It's gone, hasn't it?
Has it actually gone?
It's not just me being daft.
It's like a blank page.
Yeah, okay, so I'm gonna say
Further to SmothCon being, I'm gonna say it at this point, a shower, um, the QAs are no longer available on the SmothCon website.
They've been deleted, which is
An astoundingly community hostile thing to do.
Okay, so the QA's are still there, they're just unlinked, I think.
Because I found some links on file seven seventy and they still exist.
So let's see if it got crawled by the Wayback Machine.
It's not.
Tumbleweed just scrolling across the screen as we're like, can we guess the Montreal PDF?
No, because they're not obvious obviously named things, they're like randomly named things.
So we've got this PDF.
We'll try and put a copy of it in the show notes, listeners.
I'll
pop it in my dropbox and make a link that way because if it I I think I'm gonna take Darren at his word that it was already publicly available and therefore assume it is fine for us to disseminate it.
So it will be in the show notes.
But Montreal
Put your organization chart on your website.
Ideally not as a PDF.
Ideally ideally as a actual webpage.
But if all we could get is a PDF, that's better than nothing.
Guys, I found I found it.
Hoy I found the Montreal QA.
It only lists their uh division heads.
That's the list we'd seen last time.
Yeah, so there's extra stuff in that old chart.
Uh i this may also be um slightly out of date because I've just pulled out the one I could find in the Wayback Machine.
Oh right, okay.
So it's possible it's old.
This is the one I remember seeing.
You think it's the one that was handed out?
Okay.
It probably is up to date, but there might have been a later version we didn't see.
Because I have to pull them out of the Wayback Machine 'cause all the links have gone.
So I'm still hammering your website for the download if that was a bandwidth problem because I fished out of the Wayback Machine and then download it from the site.
So they're not gone.
So it's not probably not saving you like
like downloads if that was the what they were trying to do.
So that's bad fired as well.
And also like if it was a bandwidth thing, put them on Dropbox and just link to Dropbox.
Like there are ways around that.
But anyway, yeah, so this has some interesting information in it.
So it restates all of the uh division heads we knew.
Um it makes it clear that there is an online operations division, which I don't think we knew was a thing.
uh and that has no uh division head or deputy division head yet.
And it also makes it public who the deputy division heads are.
So we can say that the Deputy Division Head for Exhibits, going in alphabetical order, the Deputy Division Heads for Exhibits is Rene Walling.
The Deputy Division Heads for Finance are Joanne Lawler and Sam Shiner.
The Deputy Division Head for Member Services is Saul Jaffer.
Apologies if I've uh pronounced your surname wrong, Saul.
The Deputy Division Head for Programme is Gary Feldbaum.
The Deputy Division Head for Tech is Paul Timmins.
uh who has a note saying that he is specifically uh IT um and then Linda Deneroff is the last DDH and she is Wussfuss
And then there is uh some information on area heads which So um what do we think about these Deputy Division heads, guys?
Uh there's one in particular I think we might discuss.
Montreal said that one of the things it was going to do was to rehabilitate people who had served their time and that is clearly a reference to the fact that um
Renault Walling is one of their DDHers.
I I think it's been a long time.
I think that's kind of okay, actually.
Um
You know, René was extremely apologetic and said he would work better, and that was like over ten years ago, so I feel like that's probably all right.
Yeah, I feel like we may need to give some context for listeners who, you know, were not around many years ago on the internet like we were.
So so we we can link two uh page about this, but essentially in
Uh twenty twelve, uh an incident of harassment was reported at Redacon, perpetrated by Renee Walling, um, and he was given a two year ban, uh which was later revised to a lifetime ban from Redacon.
So yeah, that was twenty twelve.
That was thirteen years ago.
I think my comment would be i it's kinda weird to say we are doing like rehabilitation.
'Cause what I would say is it is a while ago, but I don't think I've heard anything at all from Renne, which is probably
As you would expect.
You know, you disappear from Fandam and, you know, do other things.
But I think there will be issues here because
What there isn't is any kind of demonstration of anything that has happened in the intervening years, um, because he's been kind of very much in the background
So I I guess the issue is and we've discussed this, like if you are going to do this sort of, you know, transformative justice kind of work, then probably you need to be able to show people the work.
And I don't think we've seen that.
And possibly they are planning to, you know, discuss this more openly.
But I think there will definitely be some discussion of his position in a
very high level at the um Montreal committee.
The problem is that when you let people into a community, you have to think about the people whom that tacitly discourages.
So like it's the parable of the Nazi bar, right?
If you have a bar and you're tolerant of Nazis, even if you don't let them be Nazis, if you just let them be in there, any person who comes in and sees the tattoos and doesn't want to be associated with that w will that will leave.
And eventually what you find is you have a bar where only Nazis drink, because you've been tolerant to a point where
only the intolerant people are actually coming.
And there's stuff like the t the parado paradox of tolerance and things like that, which which tie into this.
Where it's basically like to make an inclusive space, you actually have to do some include exclusion.
And the problem here is
That Rene might have served his time.
Rene might be genuinely sorry.
Um but that doesn't matter
If having Rene as the deputy division head of exhibits makes anyone who has a problem with his previous behavior want to not be involved with your convention, and those people will primarily
Maybe not ho they won't they won't wholly be women, but it will definitely skew towards women.
And so you're basically making quite a this is quite an uninclusive move, and it is an uninclusive mood which will affect women more than it affects men.
And that is a thing I would not want to do if I were a WorldCon chair.
Even if he is sorry, it will still put more women off than it puts off men that he is involved at all.
And that is a problem, I think.
I entirely understand where you're coming from on this, but I this is the approach that means that it's very hard for people who've been imprisoned to get jobs.
people go, oh oh I I don't care that he w served six months, eight years ago, but um uh
But but I'm not having him working in my business, you know.
And I I feel like th this is a real problem.
We have to accept
That that people can change and get better.
I agree with that, but I think it's a lot easier to accept that someone's changed and got better.
if you see the work they've done, which I think is the point Liz made, it's not clear to me what the work there is.
And the fact that they haven't said I actually think the fact that they haven't hung a lantern on this and said, like, we're gonna do this and we want Renee to be involved and we think he's served his time and like
you know, here's a you know, here's his take on it and stuff.
I think I would say two things.
One is I mean, it's not a job.
It's it this is your hobby.
It is personally harsh if you say to someone you can't be on our committee because
you know, because of your personal actions from twelve years ago and that we don't think there's any way to change that, but it's not gonna prevent you know, it it's not like gonna leave people destitute or anything like that.
I think so I think there is a bit of a difference there.
I I will say I agree with Alison.
I do think rehabilitation is important.
I do.
It's been a long time, guys.
But then that's the question is, should it just be should it just be time?
Should it just be time?
And secondly, does it matter if you lose a lot of volunteer resource because of this decision?
That is bad for your WorldCon.
I guess and that's I know I guess that's a choice you can make eyes wide open.
If you're like, you know, we gotta start it somewhere, we think this is philosophically an important thing to do, and we're happy to reduce our volunteering because we think this is an important thing to do.
That's a fair choice.
But again, I think you need like a letter from the chair explaining that or like setting out that philosophical perspective.
Like you need they need to hang a lantern on it and make this case.
Um I think what you'd say is we're we've recruited Rene into this role.
He's learnt his lesson, he he has not exhibited any more
untoward behaviour, which I believe is true.
Um we hope that won't cause anyone to um feel uncomfortable about volunteering for the convention.
Um and I'm very happy to talk to anyone who is concerned.
Something like that.
You know, hang a lantern on it, as you say.
I don't think they've hung a lantern on it, have they?
And I don't I will also say for those who aren't as familiar with this, we will try and dig out some resources um from the time.
But I also believe I'm right in saying that there wasn't like a huge number of accusations.
There are a lot of people who basically said he's a bit weird.
But there wasn't like it wasn't like one person made a complaint and then twenty others came forward.
I I think maybe one other came forward and I think
Uh i this is a case where people go, no, Rene was a kind of awkward dog to a degree that I and I know that that is used as a cover up for a lot of people who are predators, but you know, I don't
I think I agree with all of that.
But and I think there's also a thing here which is Liz's point about it it's not a job, it's volunteering.
Like I think we should let
If you go to prison for murder and you are then released, I think you should be able to get a job afterwards, and I think it is possible to be sort of sorry and reintegrate society after you've murdered someone.
Although I am not sure that if there was a uh murderer who'd been to jail and then had been released, I'd want them like working dealers from an Easter Con.
Because those are different things.
Like there's a thing there about volunteer positions and building communities that is a bit different from
Letting people work to make money to live.
And I don't know exactly where that line is, and I'm not sure I've got the social science background to confidently draw it.
Uh and I suspect there's an awful lot of people who have thought a lot about this that I'm unaware of.
But it is tricky because these aren't jobs.
These are volunteer positions in organizations that are being run as hobby projects and
That makes it harder.
Well, I think what I would say is about you know, Alison's proposed statement, which I would agree with, is words are not actions.
It doesn't say he'll be working in this position and
What we are gonna do is anyone in this division will be able to go straight to the chair and discuss anything they feel like.
And also
We will be running a series of workshops on how to combat sexual harassment in your convention and how to create an environment which is welcoming and things like that.
Like there is more you could do.
I will also notice note that
For instance, there is no code of conduct area head yet.
And I think that's the other thing.
If you are going to make someone who has been accused in the past of this sort of thing one of your DDHs
You need to have those policies, you need to have those roots.
They need to be in place before you make that appointment.
And that's unfair because I think a lot of other conventions could do that a lot later.
But if you are going to do the rehabilitation, you need to make damn sure that you have your safety procedures in place before you start trying to do that.
And I am not confident Montreal has achieved that.
They've got a code of conduct.
They have a code of conduct, but like they don't have anyone who's in place to be the code of conduct person, and I don't see anyone else who's like in charge of
safety or listeners or anything like that.
You know?
Like having a code of conduct's great start, but it is not enough for a convention where you have appointed
someone with those previous accusations to a position of that seniority, I think.
And I freely admit that is not a standard I would hold a WorldCon to if they had not taken this decision.
But I think it is fair to hold a WorldCon that does take this decision to that standard.
Yeah, and I think also you need to the code of conduct um
Is totally fine but it also reads very much about the convention and not about the pre convention lead up.
Um
So then you need to make sure and make it clear that your code of conduct applies to all precon activities and volunteers and so on.
I I do feel a bit sorry for Montreal here because I realise that they have uh you know, in good faith emailed us a copy of their old chart so we can see that they do have a bunch of people in place and are doing, you know, reasonably well at recruiting and and staffing up, although there are obviously still quite a lot of gaps.
to be filled.
Um but what it has unintentionally done is given us this entirely separate discussion.
I mean I think like and I think there are some positive things about this org chart, right?
Like finance seems to be mostly staffed, which is good.
Um the communications division seems to be mostly staffed.
Um again I will say I think it is a problem
D Darren is also the area head of editing website content in the communications division.
And and at some point I do think you need to probably recruit someone specific for that.
Um because I don't think it should be a chairs level job because the chair is probably busy.
The Worcester Division has some area heads, it's mostly the usual suspects.
Keith Smith and David Wiener are the website infrastructure area heads in the tech division.
And Keith has worked on E's to cons.
I'm assuming it's the same Keith Smith.
I don't know.
Smith is a common enough surname that I might be wrong, but like there is a New Zealand there is a New Zealander in British fandom called Keith Smith who does a lot with tech and things, listeners, and has done some good work over the past volunteering, and I'm assuming it is the same Keith Smith.
Apologies to both Keith's if I am wrong.
I I mean that Keith does not do websites.
So I think some um my assumption would be it's a different person.
They are stuffing up, it seems to be probably about where you would expect ish.
I don't know.
I don't habitually scrutinize WorldCon old charts.
you know, eighteen months out.
No, it's tricky.
I do worry that we're holding Montreal to a different standard to other world cons, but it's
I don't know whether that's just because we're I think the problem and this echoes something we said last time, which is once you're grumpy with a convention, you start paying more attention and that snowballs.
Whereas if a convention's doing well
it can often escape that level of scrutiny, which isn't fair, but I think is true.
And I don't think it's only I is just true of the whole shebang.
I don't think it's like just true of the three of us
Yeah, exactly.
I think we are I'm probably being harsher to them um because we have been harsh to them until now I'm scrutinizing everything they do um in a way that I'm not like
looking at LA's committee and stuff and going, ooh, that division head is an area head.
There was a thing that Montreal released about giving people second chances some time before the bid.
And I said, Oh, at the time, oh, that must mean that they've got Renee Walling as a division head which means that I think that they were deliberately leaving
Renee's name.
But it the the the the org chart that went to SmovCon was division heads only, it wasn't the full org chart.
Yeah, no, because the one that went to the s also the one that went to the SmovCon QA
is not necessarily one that they may have been distributing at Smothgotton, because I've seen people do this like on paper and so on.
I think basically because of their disorganization, it's very easy to jump to other explanations when probably it's just that
the left hand is not quite talking to the right hand and the website is obviously about a week old.
I don't yeah, I certainly don't think any of this stuff is being done in bad faith, if that makes sense.
Even if I
Disagree with it quite strongly.
I th I think got a little technical I've got a little technical issue for us.
Um Genevieve Valentine's original reports of
Her um harassment by Renee Wallinger no longer on the internet and they don't appear to have been copied out anywhere in terms.
As best I can remember it, he made
a number of comments which he thought were positive about her appearance, but she did not welcome.
She told him to stop.
He continually hounded her
later at the convention in order to try to apologize and explain how sorry she he was and ask for her forgiveness.
I ev and she told him to stop that and and he didn't and at at least at first.
And eventually he did stop, but he was very clueless about it.
So that's why it was persistent harassment.
But it was because he was trying to say sorry but but didn't realise that his apology was neither required nor welcome.
I think
I think that matches my recollection of how it went.
You can fish the report again out of the Wayback Machine.
No, I mean I literally as in I have just done that and I have found it.
Hey!
But I would also say that I think twenty twelve is I think
About when people were really starting to flip from, oh that guy is well meaning
but oblivious to his harassment, you should just ignore him and, you know, tell him to back off and I'm sure he'll back off to know this is actually a serious problem which is deterring a lot of people from coming to our conventions 'cause this happens over and over.
And yeah, I think it did lead to a big uh shift in how conventions treat it.
I think it led to us taking it more seriously, and that was a good thing.
But I do think this one incident probably this incident was repeated at many conventions around that time and did not become
quite the point of change that this one did.
And that must have been in part because Rene had been the chair of the two thousand and nine WorldCon, and s smoffs kind of gathered round him at first.
Ooh, did they?
Yes, Redacon gave him a two year ban rather than giving him a lifetime ban because of all the people going, Oh, really?
Uh despite the fact that they had a zero tolerance policy and uh commitment to lifetime bans for harassment.
I think what came out of that
Partly was that having zero tolerance policies that mandate lifetime bans with no um with no nuance at all
is not always the best way to write your policy.
Can someone who's not a man say that?
'Cause I think it's true, but maybe it shouldn't be me what says it.
I think it's fine and I think you can leave it like that.
I think it's fine, yeah.
Can I say can I say something before we move on?
Yeah.
I think I just want to say to listeners, our priorities in this community
are the safety, happiness, and well-being of everyone in the community.
And I really hope that it comes across that we have tried to conduct this discussion with um
thought, compassion, delicacy, and uh awareness of the safety of all attendees, including um those who are marginalized.
And we are we are attempting to have this discussion in good faith and I hope that came across in the preceding section.
So, uh moving on to a totally different topic
We got a letter from uh Hugo winner and fanwriter Renee, who has the Intergalactic Mixtape fanzine and also runs that giant Hugo spreadsheet with a very timely
uh letter featuring their new guide to how to participate in the Hugo Awards and it is a very good brief introduction
that tells you all the stuff you need to know about how you participate in the Hugo Awards and will make it kind of very friendly for new people who go, Oh, I've no idea how this works.
What are all these different types of memberships?
What do I do?
What is a Worcon?
And it kind of lays it all out and it's it's very well timed uh since the deadline is January 31st to join LA Con in order to get to nominate in the Hugos
John, I believe you have more information on this.
Molly Templeton, who is someone who writes for Reactor, among other things, and handles the Ursula K.
LeGuin Prize, among other other things.
Basically skeeted, saying she had read Renee's newsletter and it reminded her of the conversations that she had had that year with curious, well-read folks who have no real idea how the Hugo voting process works, that anyone can do it, or that you get a voter bracket.
And this sparked a lot of discussion between Molly and Renee.
What came up was a discussion about gatekeeping.
And I highlighted that both Renee and Molly have platforms that they could use to demystify some of these processes in the way that we try to here.
And I said, one of the things from my background as a physics lecturer is that you have to be very careful when you're explaining things that can seem complicated.
that you don't start with, this is very complicated and hard to understand because that is a really good way of making people think that things are too complicated for them to bother with.
Um so one of the things you have to say is this will seem complicated, but actually I can explain it to you in a way that will make it much less complicated and then you will understand it.
And I have to do this with with plasma physics and things like that.
And I've used this tool in both lecturing and in terms of science communication with kind of primary school kids trying to explain to them.
fundamentals of how it all works.
And then, you know, we had a bit of a lively discussion, which I think was quite constructive.
And I said, like, one of the things we should do is we should work on
a resource that people can point to to be like, this is the simple explanation of how the Hugo Awards work, how they are voted on, how you can get involved and all of that.
And then I thought, yeah, we should definitely do that.
Uh and now it's five months later and uh Renee has written it.
uh and sent us a letter of comments with the uh resulting document which we will link in the show notes and this is very good.
Uh so Rene wrote a few
Weeks, months, I forget when.
It turns out it was ages.
What is time?
Um John and I tussled on Blue Sky regarding Hugo participation
Uh, don't remember the details because gestures to lif living in the fascist imperial corps.
Fair.
And uh her main takeaway was that we agreed that to solve the participation problem we had to stop making the Hugo process seem opaque even as a joke, because that joke's backfiring.
And uh a while back, Renee had an offline pal ask about the process and she had their first chance to explain without that it's hard joke and he appreciated it a lot.
And then
Renee had the brilliant idea to turn the email she wrote for him into a general guide that now lives with each Hugo spreadsheet.
And she says it's probably imperfect
It's written for non-Wusfuss people.
And I have read it and I think it's pretty damn good.
It's well it's well designed.
It's got nice little um ribbons next to each um little heading.
And it explains everything quite concisely.
And yeah, I think it's really good.
So this, I think, is 10 out of 10 smash in.
And we will link it in the show notes.
Yes.
And I would also say the the beauty of it being like a Google Doc is that it's got a big register for LA Con in the middle, a big button saying register for LA Con.
Which can obviously be updated every year to just point to the right spot.
And yes, I would say that the deadline for being a member of LA Con in order to nominate in the Hugos is the 31st of January.
They have just announced that they have virtual memberships available, which are eighty-five dollars, which will get you you'll be able to then nominate and vote in the Hugos and get the voter packet and have a access to all the online convention.
And I think that will include the business meeting, right?
You just have to be a virtual member, you don't have to be a full member.
Yeah.
No, that will include the business meeting.
Which is good, because I've just bought one.
About which I will say more in a minute.
I will say LA
With who are a bit mean to uh Montreal, I will also be slightly mean to LA, which is just put a great big like join LA button in the middle of your like in the middle of the top of your website or something.
And then on the actual registration page put a big like click here to join button.
Cause it's way down the page.
And Molly Templeton is the
Editor of Reactor.
Yeah, and so she has also in Reactor put a guide to how to vote in the Hugos.
I haven't seen if she has, but she might've done.
Anyone can vote in the Hugo Awards and here's how.
So so when you said as editor of Reactor Mag
you have this huge platform where you could be demystifying the process.
She took your advice, John.
You might have had a ding-dong with both Renee and
Molly, but they have both as a result published guides to how to vote at the Hugos.
So I think you should take some ding dong credit there.
I do
Try and only ding dong for good, not for evil.
Oh that's um I know there are a lot of reply guys on these.
Um, I to try.
I'm not sure I always succeed, and I think sometimes I could probably word things better.
But I am um I am very glad to see that on Reactor, because that is also fab.
And I think this is exactly what I wanted.
I think the more we publish ways to demystify this, the better we will all be for it.
And yeah, we will link to the reactor mag in the show notes.
So I will say that during the start of this podcast I was registering for LACOM.
Which all went very smoothly, but then I realized the phone call I've missed is my credit card company saying, Did you make a suspicious payment to lacom.
org?
and cancelling the payment.
So I'm gonna have to sort that out.
Um watch out overseas users um because I did have some problems getting that payment through.
And right now I have not paid but I do have membership.
So
Sorry, LA, I'm gonna have to email them and sort this out if it doesn't automatically like come back and say you Can I find whether I'm a member or not?
I cannot help you with this problem, but I mean I suggest you just search your emails for an email that is titled um
LACON 5 registration confirmation.
And if you have it, then you registered.
But if you didn't so if you voted through site selection, and this is actually a a rant I was gonna have later
to show that we don't just um criticize Montreal.
We criticise all worldcons.
We do criticize all world cons.
LA Con does not have a membership list on their website and there is no way to check your membership status without writing to them and asking.
So I wrote to them and asked, uh, I still don't know my membership number, so I have to reply and ask, yes, but what is my actual membership number?
Because it's not linked on Planarama and I want to put it in.
So I wrote in, I am a supporting member, but I've never had an email from LA to confirm that or tell me that or anything.
Uh I have you checked your spam?
I I nearly said butthole there, but I said spam because I got an email
No, but I got an email on the sixth of September twenty twenty four saying that I was a Worcester member because I had voted in site selection.
Twenty twenty four, yeah, no, two days after the WorldCon.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
You can't.
Did you s
But so so I did get an email, but yours might have gone gone astray for some reason.
But I do I do ha I searched using the search string Liz has just given me and I did find my registration confirmation.
So I am a Wusf member.
No, I do not I do not have that email.
I do sporadically check I do relatively often check my spam, but
But it's just frustrating, right?
Because if there's one email, it could go in someone's spam, and there should be resources on the website where you can look up what the list of members is and you can look up whether or not you are one
Like why is there no login portal?
Or at least look up your own membership.
I'm sure Seattle had a login portal at this stage.
And when it says
Upgrades from Wusfus only, which I am and I now want to upgrade to virtual.
The website says contact us, which is as a as a kind of proper nerd, that that is not what I want to see on a website.
So I think LACON's registration approach is quite poor if you have already voted in site selection.
It may be quite good if you haven't.
But this is distracting from Renee and Molly's excellent resources.
So thank you very much to both.
Um I think these are great.
It's it's really good to have
multiple ways of explaining things simply because th if y you don't always resonate with one person's explanation to having multiple
persons explain is really really good.
So hurrah!
And if you're listening to this listeners, you can be a voter in the Hugo Awards and we recommend it.
Um, so given it is Hugo registration season, which will probably shortly be followed by
Hugo nomination season.
Um I thought I would highlight a couple of things.
One is to highlight Renee's uh Intergalactic mixtape uh I I like to call it a fanzine.
I think it is, strictly speaking, a
Mailing list.
Mailing lists are a subset of fanzines.
Yeah, I think so.
Um But Renee does basically link to a ton of stuff, including a lot of book reviews, a lot of recommendations, essays.
And, you know, given the time of year is there a lot of like end of year roundups.
So I think it's a good time to be going looking at
what has been recommended by people and then you might say, Oh, that sounds really good.
I've got time to read it before Hugo nominations open.
And separately I was going to highlight uh a similar essay that Kat Corbetty wrote on their website.
Because I think they've highlighted some stuff that people might not think about and think is actually eligible but they're really interesting.
So for intro instance they've nominated um
An album, a science fiction concept album from a Dutch prog rock artist called Arjen Lucasen
um which I might go and listen to.
Uh they've nominated a lot of the sort of nice YouTube commentary and essays that I quite like to watch on various science fictional topics
Um but the one I'm gonna really pull out because I've also read it and agree it's great, is a very long essay by Elizabeth Sanderfer called The Cuddled Little Vice.
which is all about basically it's the Neil Gaiman it it basically puts Neil Gaiman's whole career in context
Um, mostly focusing on a lot of his early comics work and but it's a really good kind of overview of of his work at a time when we are kind of reconsidering
what we know about him and the legacy is left to fandom.
Um and so I really, really recommend it and I think it is definitely going to get one of my spots for best related work.
And I think that's the one thing I would recommend everyone goes and has a read through if you feel like you can.
Have either of you guys read it?
Apparently it's sixty one thousand words, which I didn't realise
when I was reading it as a blog post, it doesn't feel nearly that long, but it is a very substantial piece of work.
I've not read it yet.
Um and that's exactly why I'm mentioning it in January.
I should have made it a pick really.
I I I feel like I do want to w
To read the whole of Last War in Albion, not merely this chapter of it.
In that case, just start with the first one, right?
Yeah.
This is book four?
Oh god.
Hmm.
No.
What?
The m Gaiman the Gaiman one is book two, isn't it?
It is chapter three of
Book four?
Oh, okay.
Interesting.
I might have gone a bit confused.
So is the whole book serialized on her website or can you buy it as an actual book?
I think it's serialized, but you may be able to buy them.
Cause that's the problem.
I'm not gonna sit and read a website for like an hour, but if it's on my uh ebooks, I might well.
So like, yeah.
Might might need to dig around and see if there's like a proper book copy, whether that's E or otherwise.
I mean not all the not all the things are sixty-one thousand words.
The Last War in Albion is a history of British comics and she started it in twenty thirteen.
This is a thing like I'm like how figure one the great bearded wizard of Northampton, how can I not have previously been aw aware of this?
Cause you're not omniscient.
As it turns out, none of us are.
There's just too much stuff to know everything.
I how did that happen?
When did that happen?
I th I think the failure here is that I have never mentioned it to you.
You might have.
I will say that when I go on her when I go on that thing
The little thing at the top says Last War in Albion Book 2.
So I'm very confused that it's chapter 3 or Book 4 because Oh, it's the new epilogue to book 2.
Okay.
So it is so I could so you've only got to read two books to get to this epilogue, Alison, if you do it in order.
I might just read this article because But if the epilogue is sixty one thousand words, that does rather raise the question of how long the books are.
So you could buy the first book as an ebook.
I've certainly found it on Amazon, it's probably in other places, and it's about it's 788 words.
So it's hefty.
Seven seven hundred and eighty-eight words.
Sorry, seven and eighty-eight pages.
Ah!
Okay
Yes, but it's probably got some pictures in it.
Well anyway, yes, thank you very much for directing our uh um attention to this, uh Liz and Kat, because
Hurrah!
This sounds great.
It's not expensive.
It's free with Kobo Plus, which I had a for a while by accident, but I've cancelled now.
So I might take it again.
I can't remember whether Sandafer's uh previous book, um, about the alt right and so on, was on the Hugo shortlist.
It may have been in the nominations
Yeah, I I'm so much more interested in the history of the British comics than I am in the alt right.
I'm sorry, I know that's No, that I mean, I think that's fair, but yeah.
It was kind of the alt-right as it.
Connects with fandom in some ways as well.
Yeah, I think I'm interested in how things got where they are, but
So book one or volume one is on is available as an ebook.
Doesn't look like volume two is yet, um, but Kobo tells you the actual word count.
So volume one is two hundred and thirty-three thousand words.
I'll put a link in the show notes.
Yeah, I think it's just when they are complete and collected.
Nice.
I love the cover.
Handsome Grant Morrison versus Alan the Gentleman Moore.
I met Alan Moore in nineteen eighty-five.
Alan Moore came to talk to Custavus in nineteen eighty-five, j which was just bef
while Watchman was being written but before any of it had been released and everyone was extremely excited about it.
That that night had a great impact uh had a profound effect on me.
Touched by the presence of extremely stoned genius.
Um, 'cause we all went back to somebody's college room for a party where he was showing round pictures from you know, r uh early, early art from Watchmen.
That was fabulous.
Oh nice.
Take take opportunities, guys.
When you get chances to do interesting things, do them
Shall we go to Picks?
Uh go quick.
My pick is K-pop Demon Hunters, which I I had been vaguely aware of
Because I am vaguely aware of memes, but um Netflix says you might like K pop Demon Hunters over Christmas.
through memes in multiple locations, including ukulele forums and trivia quizzes, before I got round to watching it.
It is a film about a girl band who also
Fight Demons.
Um, it's an animated film.
It is not Korean, it is American, but it um essentially channels a lot of Korean
Culture it's entirely made by Koreans and Korean Americans and I really enjoyed it quite a lot.
And there's a sing-along version because it's actually a musical.
Um
And yeah.
It's it was a lot of fun.
I I think I'm going to suggest it for your Hugo consideration.
Um, but it's obviously not maybe the deepest movie in the world, but it will
Mm take away all of your cares for about one hour and forty minutes and what more do you want from life?
K-pop demon hunters, I submit.
I liked it.
Yeah, I've watched that.
It's fun.
But you enjoyed watching it, right?
You're glad you saw it and it was fun.
And also I'm now down with the kids because, you know
Children know what this movie is.
Well, and also you'll probably have seen one of the best dramatic presentation long form finalists when the Hugo Awards dropped.
I did say, for your Hugo consideration
But I would be surprised if this wasn't on it, 'cause it has achieved cultural penetration.
But we had some people in uh K-pop Demon Hunters costumes uh trick or treating, so Yes, I now understand a lot of
photos I saw on my feeds around Halloween because Netflix nobody thought they would need to make a billion
K-pop demon hunter costumes and put them on the market as a result of which there were none to be had and there was a lot of creative costuming going on.
Liz, do you want to do your pick?
Yes, my pick is going to be an exhibition, just because you guys are always picking exhibitions and I never do it.
Um and so I went to the National Maritime Museum in Greenwich with some chums who may be listening to this podcast.
Hello.
Uh and we went to see the Astronomy Photographer of the Year exhibition, which does feel very much like someone saw that the National History Museum make a lot of money from Wildlife Photographer the Year exhibits and thought they would have a space one.
Um but on the other hand
And space is very cool.
So it's very similar to that.
There's different categories of photo.
There's one for auroras, one for like galaxies and nebula and the sun and the moon.
And it's just like the best photographs taken of those objects.
I think in the last year.
I think this one might have been in twenty twenty four, twenty twenty five, possibly.
And they're all nicely laid out.
What I did find is that a lot of because a lot of like astronomy photos are
generally kind of composites of different time lapses and different length exposures.
So it feels a little bit more like these are all kind of things people have put together and need a high level of skill.
Whereas if you look at like wildlife photography year, even if I couldn't take those photos
I do at least get that feeling of, oh yeah, that's great.
You just have to be in the right place to catch the llama or whatever.
But some of these are like, you know, some of these photos were taken with like
the deep space observation telescope in Chile and things like that, which are a little more distant.
I know I could not actually take the Wildlife Photographer of the Year photos, but at least I have
feasibly taken photos of wildlife in a way I have not feasibly taken photos of the M thirty nebula in the hydrogen spectrum or whatever.
But I did enjoy it still as well.
I think what I would actually love to see is a bit more about how people do do the process of compositing and so on.
One of the best bits was they had a big video where you could
Uh they did interviews with a couple of the winning photographers and they talked a bit more about how they took the photo and and what they did and that was pretty cool.
And there's also like an open category which uh you can use any data, so it's a lot of like repurposing and reprocessing and imaging of like data from like space telescopes and stuff, which was quite cool.
Anyway, it was fun.
It's in the National Maritime Museum, which is uh pretty good as well.
It's a nice fun day out, and you can go and see some photos of space
Space.
There's a I mean this won't surprise John, I'm sure, but obviously astronomy photos there's a bunch of kind of recolouring and reprocessing and filtration.
There's a bit of Photoshop and
uh you know, it's i there's a ton of stuff going on here and in fact there is a page on their website saying how the winning image was created and there's a lot of different stuff going on there.
So and it does explain it all.
So at just at the point where you were saying I wish I
There would be more about how it was done.
I was reading or looking at an article about how it was done, which I will I can put in the show notes.
Uh alright.
I'm gonna pick um uh Blast from the Past.
Uh I'm gonna pick the Umbrella Academy, which you can watch on Netflix.
Have you finished it now?
I've seen the first two seasons.
It's good.
I was a little bit skeptical of season two, but I think it does keep being good.
Uh yeah, we just finished season two and it was it was very enjoyable.
We're taking a short break before we dive into season three to watch Pluribus.
I have watched the first episode of Plurverse, and I will say that I have the same problem with it as I did with the Planet of the Apes remake.
And what is that problem, John?
People working on these things would have better understanding of how quarantine works than it is exhibited in those works of art.
I have suspended my disbelief, but there's no way any of the things in the first fifteen minutes of Pluribus would ever have happened.
But once I got past that, it seems to be cracking.
Fur first episode of Pluribus is very much not like the whole of the rest of the show.
I'm looking forward to experiencing the rest of the show.
And that was the Octothorpe podcast.
And it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
I would like to make a personal appeal to Ed Morland.
Ed, please write us more letters about Cyclocross than I can annoy John and Allison.
Ooh, and we can talk about Flam Rouge.
I I like Flam Rouge a lot, but my family it's one of these games where one of my family doesn't like it and so we don't it doesn't get played.
Johnson's like, why not just play Heat?
And I'm like, well A, we don't own Heat
And B, they're not the same game.
They're not the same game.
I will say I think I am on Jonathan's side that he is probably my preference of the two, but they are both cracking.
I mean Cyclocross isn't the same as like
The Tour de France stuff, is it?
I don't know what Cyclocross is.
What's cyclocross?
Is it like mm marathons but for cycling?
No.
Is it like steeplechase but for cycling?
Is it the one where you go round around in a circle?
I don't really know what you mean by steeple ch you mean running steeple chase.
Obstac I mean like obstacles.
I don't really want to talk more about Cyclocross because I don't even watch very much Cyclocross.
I just was having a little anti-cricket moment.
Shall we go on with the pod and do another letter?
We can do it if you like.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod and Compatech.
com, used under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.
0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.