Don't worry, John, I'm here to tell you you're wrong,
even if Liz isn't stepping up to the plate.
Yeah, you might want to record that one for future reference.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to the 48th episode of OctoThorp,
the podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom,
which is coming to you on the 6th of January 2022.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And we have a letter of common from Fara.
And it says here in the show notes, but what did you think of
Discon 3?
What?
What did we think of Discon 3 people?
I quite liked it.
I'm looking forward to the programme being on catch up because there were some items I missed or I was double booked for.
And there are items I would quite like to go back and watch.
And I think it is, I think it's actually really good that they didn't have the programme for catch up over Christmas
because I would have watched precisely zero programme over Christmas.
And I know that they're only going to be putting up for a limited time.
So if that limited time starts after I am not super busy with Christmas,
I think that is only a great thing.
So congratulations for Discon 3 for that excellent planning.
And I'm looking forward to it all coming online so I can do some watching.
Yeah, I saw a few items.
I missed vastly more because I was 12 hours out of sync,
which meant there were maybe two or three programme items in time.
So that's when I would normally be awake.
So I watched like one or two items per day.
I hung around in the discord a bit.
I missed some items I would have liked to watch because they happened to be at times.
I was awake, but in rooms, which were having problems with their streaming, which was a bit unfortunate.
Yeah, but generally what I saw, I quite enjoyed.
I saw some great panels.
I saw some panels, which were kind of excellent descriptions that went quite rumbly and vague.
I went to some panels where I read the description, thought I'll give this go
and it turned out it wasn't my thing.
So I tried something else.
Yeah, we went back and discord.
I think I went to one party, which was not a party.
It was Alison's Let's Have Coffee Moose in a Zoom.
And we got a tour of the hotel at like six in the morning, which is very nice.
So yeah, I mean, I had a nice time, but I can't really say I saw much of the convention
just because I was asleep for most of the time was happening.
So I went to the convention virtually for five solid days.
I had not been intending to do this because I'd been expecting to have Christmas
things over the that weekend.
And in fact, they all got cancelled.
So I got five days at this con, which was great.
I really enjoyed myself virtually.
I had a lovely time talking to people from all over the world.
And that was really, really good.
And some of them are now kind of cafe moose regulars.
And that's nice.
And I think they did a really, really good job of spinning up the virtual side
very quickly, more or less in, I think, the last month before the convention.
And given that, I think they did fantastically well with it.
And there was lots of good stuff.
I do have quite a lot of takeaways about how to run virtual and hybrid events.
I think my biggest is picking up on what Liz said.
I think if we're charging $75 for a virtual membership, then the ability to
time shift the program items in real time needs to be part of that and part of
the planning from the beginning.
For another time, I understand why this con didn't do it, but I think
Wilcons should have that as kind of the starting point, because it's not just about
having the program and being able to watch it later.
It's about being able to talk to people about the stuff that you're seeing on the
program in the social spaces over the weekend.
That's what we do at conventions, right?
We see program and then we talk about program to our mates.
And that's the key thing we need to enable.
And then the other point is that when we have these hybrid conventions, we seem to
have two conventions going on, one, one of which is a virtual convention happening
in Zoom and Discord around the place.
And one is the actual physical convention.
And I don't think we're doing enough yet.
This is not a criticism of Discord because we've only just begun.
I don't think we're doing enough yet to link up those two events so that people feel
they're at both of them.
But they're actually getting the benefit of the physical convention.
In the virtual spaces.
And so the people in the physical convention also recognized that there are fans who are
their friends and who have things to offer in the virtual spaces as well.
Those are, so those are my big two, two big takeaways from DiscCon.
Really enjoy myself.
Had a great time, was then very behind for the next three weeks.
My big takeaway from DiscCon was sushi.
I had a large amount of sushi.
I did not book enough takeaways.
I think I know now that you, one of the nice things about virtual
conventions is ordering your food in.
And I should have done more of that.
We did a little bit and I did not cook or do anything like that.
I just got looked after by my lovely and very long suffering family again.
Or as you like to call them, gophers.
It's certainly true that when I take a role on a convention,
I generally discourage Stephen from taking a role on the same convention
so that he could be like my personal aid for the weekend.
Every so often he gets one of these hero of the convention awards for doing this
because other people don't.
Brilliant.
He's the best.
I love you.
I love you darling.
I mean, I know you don't listen to the podcast, but you know.
What?
This is an outrage.
He does sometimes.
So yes, generally speaking quite positive, I think, on DiscCon.
What I also want to say about DiscCon is they did have some items which started,
well, they would have been very early in the morning in the US.
They were early evening for me, but these were part of their quite extensive stream of
items on African science fiction and fantasy, which they were obviously running at times
that were more suited to the participants who were nearly all on the ones I saw virtual
and actually joining from Africa.
So I think there was a real strength that they could do that,
that they could have all these virtual participants who could not make it to the con for financial
or the reasons, but they can actually now join in and they were also available for viewing on site.
And I'd be really interested to know whether people who had the opportunity to view the virtual
panels on site went to them or whether they sort of saved those up for later viewing because
they knew they would be recorded and available later.
So I think that's an interesting thing from hybrid conventions.
If you allow people to watch virtual participants, do they actually go or do they decide, well,
actually, if it's just going to be four people over Zoom, I could easily watch that later on in
the comfort of my own home. I'll go to ones that aren't being streamed where the people are actually
on site. So let us know, just gone, attendees, what happened?
We do know from much smaller conventions, SmothCon and Corfloo, that some people do go and people
also quite like to watch virtual events from their hotel room. So the number of, the report
back from Discon was that virtual events were not well, the virtual events that was
streamed into the convention were not well attended, but I don't think we necessarily know
the full extent of how that doesn't necessarily mean they're not popular.
Yeah, that's fair.
Yeah.
And also, Doug Form tasks us, what are your thoughts on Christmas music and the WorldCon
opening ceremony? And mine were, I love Christmas carols to bits, you know, I love all sorts of
Christmas music including a lot of religious Christmas music. And I thought this was way out
of order and I don't think the excuse that that happened to be what the local choir had prepared
for Christmas. And so therefore, that was what they had was quite adequate because I don't think
they should have done that. I think it raised eyebrows and made people feel excluded and happy.
And I think having a program of Christmas music that might have included one religious
piece of Christmas music would have been fine, but I think it was a bit, a bit much.
As my pals though, I have a Christmas list with thousands of carols on it. I have hundreds of
versions of some carols, I love them. So yeah, I still didn't think they should have done it.
The problem here is obviously that we didn't give our picks for SF no Christmas songs until
after this Com3. So really, we do have to date full responsibility and we apologise to the
wider science-rich community. Yeah, I mean, I'm guessing it was just one of the things where
where the choir went right. It's Christmas. This is our busiest time of year. Here's our
like set of possible songs and then it's come some compromise where this call said either,
okay, well, just do one song at this opening ceremony then or where they try to range with
them to learn something else. But I can understand they're having been in choir at Christmas. You
have the set of stuff you're learning and then you use it at every possible opportunity.
I think it's just one of those things. Probably no one vetted it where it occurred to them that
this might be a thing. I bet it didn't. I mean, it was really strange to me because so much
Christmas music in America is deeply secular because of the whole church and state thing. So,
and it seems enormously surprising to me that the community choir would have an entirely religious
programme and yet not be a gospel choir because I think if they had booked a gospel choir, they
probably would have expected that. But it wasn't. I circumvented all of these considerations by
going to the panel item about role-playing games, which was happening at the same time as the opening
ceremony was good. Yeah, I circumvent the whole thing by being in bed. So, yeah, so I did go to
that panel on role-playing games. But then I, because the ceremony was still going on,
you could time shift to the extent of running back a live broadcast to the beginning and then
watching it, which is what I did. Oh, cunning. I've had a great conversation since the last
talk to thought with Iro Alexandra, who is the person who is most pushing for best game hugo,
which we talked about almost a year ago at this time in our Christmas episode in 2020.
And in the process of that excellent conversation, I learnt how they pronounce the name, which is
not how we pronounced it all that episode. So, I'm sorry. But I hope to be working with you in 2022
as you get this to the Christmas meeting. We also heard from Duncan McGregor, who said that he
understood Tenet. Crazy. You'll have to explain it to me at some point, Duncan. And we heard from
Chris Garcia, who said that he drove from the desert to Los Angeles for some garlic paste.
Fair enough. You do you, Chris. And then finally, Flick wrote in to ask us why we hadn't mentioned
the Xinjiang region as part of our discussion of the Chinese Worldcon. For those who don't know,
this is a region of China in which the Chinese government is perpetrating various acts against
the native Eoyga Muslim population. And this has been described by some, including a House of
Commons motion passed here in the UK as a genocide. The reason that we haven't discussed this is
because none of us have the expertise or knowledge to discuss it sensitively and well. And so we
agree that it is a horrible thing that is happening. And we are not sure this is the venue to discuss
it. But we do want to say that we do thoroughly disagree with it. And I think also, and I don't
think we made this clear last time that some people are not going to the Chinese Worldcon because
of the actions of the Chinese government in Xinjiang. And absolutely, that's a valid choice for
those people to make. And I mean, that is pretty much the reason why I voted against them. Basically,
I very much like the bid team seemed great. I think it would be great to have Worldcons in
more countries, but you know, taking it to China at this moment in time when there is a lot of
repression and internment and other actions taken against minorities in China was not something I
felt I could support. Yeah, but I think it's in turn, we want to kind of lay our position out.
But it's not something we have any particular expertise in discussing.
Yes. And just to echo Liz, I also voted for Winnipeg much to do with this issue and other issues
related to China's human rights record. Yep, E3.
So we're going to discuss the Hugo Awards a little bit. We did touch on this last episode,
but since then there are more stats. And we love stats here on the old thought podcast.
We have the long list, which is officially called the Hugo nomination report.
And that tells us how many people nominated what in which categories, which is obviously
very exciting and interesting stuff. But the most exciting thing on it was that Octa thought was
the last fan cast to be knocked out of Best Fan cast. So we were seventh, we were very surprised,
and we were very thrilled. And we thank you all very much. Those of you nominated us, that was
lovely. However, we didn't actually get all that many nominations. And by number of nominations,
we'd have been 12th. So Liz, would you like to explain how the nominations work? Because I
spent a long time scratching my head over this. And I think some of our readers might also do.
Yeah, so I had to go and reread the E pluribus Hugo method a couple of times before I got it.
But basically, I think I do now have a handle on it. So basically, you have a point which is
split across everything you nominate in a category. Every item you nominate gets a fraction of your
points awarded to it. So when you start off, say you put five items in a category, they are all
worth 0.2 of a point, so it adds up to one. And basically, what happens is they go down the list
of nominees and they look at the two each round, which are bottom in terms of number of points.
And they knock out the one which has the lowest number of actual people nominating it.
So basically, every round is a contest between the ones which have the bottom two points. And
when one of them gets knocked out, if you nominated that item, the redistribution of points across
your other nominations means that they will now have a slightly higher points total and are more
likely to carry through. So it's, I think it's quite an elegant method, actually, of saying,
look, if you nominate stuff such that when we get to the last 10 or the last five, lots of other
people have nominated the same as you, then they won't all make it onto the ballot. But this kind
of extra check where you don't just remove the last one on point to remove the one of the last
two on points with the fewest nominations means that basically if you and lots of other people
all nominate a set of the same items, one of them will always get through because it will have a
lot of people nominating it, even if it doesn't have a lot of points. Yeah, that's completely transparent
and clear, isn't it? Absolutely.
So this means that when we say we were the last one to be eliminated from the ballot, it does mean
we did not, we were not the seventh most number of nominations, but because of this contest happening
repeatedly through the nominations, we were the last one to be contested before the six finalists
in that category were selected and what a slate of finalists they were. What this means in practice
is that most people who nominated us did not nominate any other fan cast in the top 16.
Which is, which looks to us like our listeners rose up on mass to support us and don't otherwise
listen to that many other fan casts, but it could also look to somebody else like, oh god,
they just rounded up their mates and got them to vote for them. Which Nittles White says is
a known feature of EPH. Thank you, Nittles. So you guys should be listening to more good
fan casts and to support that, we are going to in 2022 tell you about some other good fan casts
that you might want to be listening to. And also you tell us if there's fan casts that we should be
supporting that we are not already doing so. As we said last week, best fan cast is one of the
categories where there is a risk of it not getting enough votes. So we very much want to make sure
that everyone knows what fun casts are good and have a listen to them and voting them because
we love this category. Yes, because we do a fan cast.
We got a tweet of comment from Robot Archie on Twitter, who is Martin Easterbrook, who asked us
what we thought of EPH continuing to be in effect after the problems posed by the puppies had gone
away. And I have a couple of thoughts on this. So firstly, I think that part of the thing with
EPH is the fact that it is in effect may be a contributing factor to the fact that attempts
to game the Hugos have decreased markedly since that happened. So I'm a little bit reluctant to
get rid of it, just in case it is having a deterrent effect on the people who were trying to game
the Hugos. There was one category, which was best fan writer in which the sixth finalist to make
onto the ballot got on because of EPH related effects, but then ended up winning the category.
The other thing I think is that any mechanism which gets the eventual winner of a category
onto that ballot is probably a good mechanism, because if the electorate think of those six people
that person is the best, that to me indicates that person should have been on the ballot to be
selected from. So I think in general, I am pro EPH remaining in effect, even after the slate
voting has subsided. And I think it may also not be a coincidence that the Hugos have seen a very
diverse range of voices being nominated since this came into effect as well. So I think in general,
I see several potentially very good outcomes for the Hugos coming out of EPH. And then my co-hosts
will tell me why I am wrong. I wasn't going to say you were wrong, actually. I was going to point
out that the fan writing question is Elsa Schunerson. And actually, she had a book out in October 2021,
which I saw being mentioned in quite a lot of places. So I wonder if actually she was nominated
on the basis of previous work, but then when people went to find out more about it, they found her
recent book, and that may be a contributing factor for why she came top in that category.
Yeah, it's also one of those problems with fan writing, which is if you write a lot of
blogs on a subject and you're very good at it, then turning those blogs into a book is a natural thing
to do. And in this case, it was tweets rather than blog posts. But this is a work that is a
professional work that has arisen out of what was fan writing. And this is something that does make
the whole link between Fan and Pro, which we've talked about before, and we'll talk about again,
very complicated. But that doesn't mean we shouldn't recognize fan writing, which Elsa's work clearly
was. My worry about TPH, and I think on the whole what you said about it's fine, and it's not a bad
mechanism, and I quite like it, I don't like mechanisms where if I am nominating, I have to think,
oh, so I love this thing. And I have to consider whether I should nominate everything else, because
if I nominate anything else, it reduces the chance the thing I love gets on the ballot.
And that seems to me to be the big downside of EPH for me, is that it actively discourages,
would discourage me because of being a kind of gaming mathematician from nominating more than one
thing in some categories, on some occasions. I mean, I think that is only true if the thing you
nominate at all extremely unpopular. That's right, because basically if you're nominating because
you need, you're something needs your votes to get through to like the top 15 or something, then actually,
and it would be diluted by nominating anything else, then if you know, everything your nomination
is quite unpopular. Whereas if you nominate something which is nominated by lots of other people,
and something which is nominated only by you, and your thing nominated only by you gets knocked out,
it just kind of increases the points you get from your other nominations. I mean, my theory on EPH is
one, yes, it's a deterrent. It basically means if you're a slate, you can get one thing on the ballot,
and people are not keen enough on getting one thing on the ballot rather than six to pay for
lots of supporting memberships to do that. But also it feels like it fits kind of with
transferable vote, which because single transferable vote ends up kind of picking often not the thing
that the most people put in first place necessarily, but the thing that maybe the most people were
happy with having ranked highly, you know, it's not a first-pastor post-system. And now in the
nominations, we've kind of caught with things which tries to pick like a set of nominees such that
the largest number of people will see something they nominated on the ballot. So I think you could
make an ideological argument for it there, but I think a much better argument is if we got rid of
it, we might then have three years where someone was like, "Ah, I will now get a hundred of my
friends to nominate six things, and it'll take us three years to put EPH back in to fix it again."
So EPH actually made very few differences of ballots instead of just taking like the top six
on nominations, but one place it did make a difference is in best editor's short form where Lee Harris
was seventh, whereas he would have been sixth under like a pure nomination counting system.
And this feels particularly harsh because he was also the last person eliminated in best
editor long form. So he essentially was the last person limited in both best editor categories,
which I feel is a little, it's just a little bit of a rough deal, especially as there's very few
other changes that EPH made apart from I think one, one change in novella, that kind of thing.
Lee were very sorry if you're listening, which you're not.
The other interesting thing is the Mandalorian. So the Mandalorian had two episodes nominated
and in the top six on best dramatic presentation short form, and because of that, they were removed
from best dramatic presentation long form. And I assume that's because it managed to get two on
the ballot in short form and one in long form, but actually it had the same number of votes for its
highest ranked episode in short form and for long form. So I wonder how you actually decide
which course you take there, because obviously it makes a difference to what gets on the ballot
in fifth and sixth place in those categories. So if you are a Hugo administrator and you'd like to
comment, do get in touch, Nicholas or Kat. But no, I mean, you're not, you know, just because it
is interesting, it is very interesting. I'm also going to link to a bunch of blog posts from
Camistross for that done, where he has dug into the Hugo nominations in even more detail. So if
anyone really likes that, there's some more stats. And we are also going to link to Nicholas White's
analysis of the Hugo Awards. We dug down the long list because I love digging down the long
list and I found a lot of interesting things in it. There are always interesting things. And the
first one I want to talk to about, no, somebody else can talk about Best Series. Best Series is
my favorite Hugo Award category, because it is the category that consistently throws up things that
I like in the genre, because most of my genre reading is big old series of great books. Ben
Aranovich's Rivers of London series is amazing. I just read the short story anthology in that
universe that has come out and I really enjoyed it. And I've loved all the books. I've recently
started reading the comics as well, but I would love to see that series win the Best Series Hugo
down the road. And yes, hopefully, hopefully we will nominate that again in future years. Someone
else can talk about young wizards. Right. Okay. So Diana Dwayne's Young Wizards, So You Want to
Be a Wizard, Fantastic Books. Strongly recommended. They're amazing. In general, I am, as regular
listeners will know, not a fan of things that are about the process of the conventional Hugo
Awards getting nominated in their own right, because I feel like it's a bit circular and not
necessarily what we really should be celebrating. We should be looking more outwards from our own
mechanisms. However, tucked away in the long list were some nominations for something called
the Hugo Spreadsheet of Doom, which I was not previously familiar with. So I went and looked it up.
And it is a spreadsheet of possible things for the Hugo Awards. And I am quite a big fan of crown
sourcing lists of things that might be eligible for awards. And I think these sorts of lists are
great if lots of different people contribute to them so that you have a really broad
set of things that people could be reading and looking at. So we are going to put a link to the
Hugo Spreadsheet of Doom in the show notes. We'll put the link to the 2022 one so you can start
nominating. And we think it's open for your suggestions. And because I particularly think that the fan
Hugo is currently being a bit poorly served by the nominators and voters, I particularly suggest
that you get all your suggestions for fan works, fan artists and fan writers and fanzines and
fan casts onto there. And for those who don't know, the Hugo Spreadsheet of Doom is hosted and
maintained by the fine folk over at Lady Business. I'm just going to point out that I didn't realise
you hadn't seen the Hugo Spreadsheet of Doom before. And I've definitely put it in the show notes
at least once. Brilliant. Did you know about it, John? Yeah. It's only me. So lots of the things. So
for example, also on the long list with the fact that Outworlds, which was a bit of a poster
child fan, fanzine fan on this year was kind of people really, really wanted to get outwards
onto the ballot and they did not manage to do that. But it was quite close. This was the last
issue of Outworlds. So you're not going to be able to do another one. The giant Outworlds
71. Just say that and then Mark can write in and tell us we're on. Right? Good lock hook.
Outwards 69. Nice. Which is definitely correct. Uh... Outworlds 71, I say slightly, not quite sure.
Lee, please write in Mark Plummer. So it's its last episode of Outworlds. So that was its last
chance. It didn't quite make it off the ballot, but it did do very creditably.
William Brydings, portable storage, which is my number one thing for if you like interesting
fanzines that do a lot of different things, you should definitely be checking out portable
storage because it is full of... Ah! Circon articles, fanish articles, articles that are like way off
everywhere. It's just the most extraordinary thing and it's on efansies so you can read it for free.
And also the drink tank was something that looked like it. To me, looks fanzine shaped that was
just a little bit below the ballot by a... by friend of the show, Chris Garcia. But I don't think any of
those fanzines were on... were on the Hugo spreadsheet of doom and in my view they should have been.
And if I had known about the Hugo spreadsheet of doom at nomination time, they'd all have been on.
Raytheon sponsored the Hugo Awards in some capacity and later Discon 3 released an apology
for this and I believe donated the amount that Raytheon sponsored to various charities dedicated
to peaceful works. We will put a link to Discon 3's apology in the show notes. Lots of people were
very sad about this because Raytheon has done some things to do with the US military industrial
complex and understandably if you have problems with the US foreign policy vis-a-vis the US military,
you may therefore have problems with Raytheon and their capitalist influence.
Well, I mean they make bombs. Raytheon make bombs. They make bombs work. And that is a thing that
upsets a lot of people, anti-topsets a lot of people on Twitter and I think more generally people
going that this is slightly off as a sponsor for the Hugo's. The other sponsorship for Discon was
Google which nobody people sometimes have a problem with Google sponsoring things but nobody really
has a problem in this case because what Google sponsored was the human transcription of almost
every programme item and that was popular with everybody was not obviously selling Google though
obviously it's quite related to the sort of thing that Google cares about and likes and will mean
that those transcripts are probably indexed forever in Google's set of indexing the world's knowledge
but it kind of feels very much aligned with what the Worldcon is about and I think the Worldcon didn't
do a good enough job of demonstrating how Raytheon sponsorship might also have been aligned with
the sorts of things we do at Worldcons and people were extremely upset about it. What they did was
sponsor the red carpet. We don't know the exact amounts of money but what it meant was that the
Hugo, that the backdrop for photographs of the Hugo Awards was a backdrop that had
the Hugo Awards and Raytheon as the co-branding on the backdrop and I feel like this is something
that I would like the Mark Protection Committee to have a think about and might say to future
Worldcons you are not allowed to have anything on the backdrop for the Hugo Awards banner apart
from the Hugo Awards and maybe the name of the convention. Of course the Mark Protection Committee
can't do that because they're outranked by the Worldcon Committee so if the Worldcon Committee...
It's the use of the Hugo Awards brand? The Worldcon Committee has the
final say in how that's used so if the Worldcon Committee and the NBC disagree on
Hugo or branding the Worldcon Committee wins because the entire point it was for
us is to vest the power in the Worldcon. Ah this is with my tedious NBC hat on.
No this is great so does that mean that the Mark Protection Committee could issue a non-binding
resolution? Suggesting that this would be a good idea. Basically the whole of us for
his design so that was first doesn't have much actual power over the Worldcon which is on purpose
but it does mean that Worldcons can dig themselves giant holes and that it's very difficult for
us first to legislate in a way that prevents that in any meaningful sense. Which is probably the
right way for it to be. Yeah which is probably what we want but does result in the occasional
big whoops. Okay so this was a bit of a big whoops. I think I want to go back in time a little bit
on Raytheon and Discon which is that a couple of months before the Worldcon it didn't have any
money and they were definitely scrubbing about quite vigorously to to try and find some sources of
money because they were worried that they were going to lose a packet and this is of course before
they got 2000 unexpected supporting memberships from China which almost certainly sorted their
financial problems out much more than and so therefore they were then in a position to give the money
to a suitable cause but certainly there was a point where everyone was like this Worldcon has
no money we are really really tight it's going to be very very difficult and I think it's in that
context that they took the money. One of the things that was pointed out on Twitter after the
controversy over the Raytheon sponsorship was that Raytheon were also one of the contractors
employed in launching the James Webb Space Telescope and so Sean Duke tweeted saying that he was
eating popcorn watching everyone who was offended by Raytheon being involved with the Hugo Awards
also being involved with a thing that everyone was celebrating. Yeah I mean I think it just shows
that this is you know the issue of who should sponsor Worldcon and in particular the Hugo Awards
is probably not a particularly clear cut thing I mean I think it's worth noting that like Raytheon
is actually like four subsidiaries and you know one of them is the Missile and Defense One and
it was the intelligence and space part that was sponsoring the Hugos but you know can you really
separate what a company does out into these different parts so easily and also does it mean
that they essentially can say well actually know this isn't a bit that makes missiles
that's sponsoring you this is the bit that just makes the radar that guides missiles or something
like that so I think it's just it's it's it's complicated to do this sort of thing under capitalism
because I bet there's like three companies capable of making the guidance system for the James Webb
Space Telescope and they probably almost all have some hand in you know defense defense related
companies and technologies as well and you kind of have to accept that if you want to have space
telescopes so maybe the thing is we should all we should be interrogating maybe who sponsors the
Hugos and who we kind of have putting their names on the backdrop of our biggest awards and you know
I think future conventions are going to have to come up with a policy for this because it was
definitely being asked of the next conventions but maybe it is something where we should also say
actually is it great that we can only do space exploration essentially with the help of these
companies that are also heavily involved in kind of the defense industry which may be getting a
little wider than you know the issue of World Cons sponsorship and this is one of the problems
with scientific endeavor is that it's very difficult to do scientific endeavor without engaging with
capitalism and obviously especially in space physics you do end up relying on companies that
also do missiles I mean the entire field of endeavor is based on the v2 rocket which was not
an ethically great development but you know then we walked on the moon does it is very complicated
very complicated for all mankind season one does quite a good job of unpicking some of these
things in an interesting way oh well don't forget to just back on top picture but I will also say
that google is also a defense contractor and no one has mentioned google in that light I think
it's probably because obviously that makes up a much smaller part of google's profits than rathion
so I completely understand why but it is interesting that it is clearly about you know there is an
acceptable percentage of defense contracting that will not stir controversy it's really difficult
it's a really hard thing so if you're a defense contractor and you'd like to sponsor octa thought
please get in touch
file 770 reported that in the aftermath of Chengdu in 2023 becoming the seated world con
winnie bag are exploring a bid for the 2023 nazvik which is the north american science
fiction convention which will be held in excuse me which is held in north america in years where
the world con is not in north america and this makes a lot of sense because they can repurpose
normal under the work they've done in that regard chris gossia friend of the podcast has told me
that he's planning to run nazvik as a relaxicon i think it is front room something like that
so that might be a third bid chris if you're out there tell us about your 2023 nazvik bid but
definitely a relaxicon nazvik which i believe means the and that's relaxed con of the american
sense of a convention without any program rather than the british sense of a convention that has
entirely too much program and i mean with with the world con being in Chengdu i'm sure the nazvik in
2023 will be extremely small and will fit easily into chris's front room the orlando in 2026 world
combat is also pivoting to bidding for a 2023 nazvik and this supersedes their 2026 world
combat which means the bidding conventions for 2026 are now jeddah in saudi arabia los angeles
in california usa and nise in france which is where briece is from so everyone should vote for nise
very excited gonna go and briece cosplay if it wins uh so you know briece briece dinese one of the
best french films oh so good briece dinese please put a link to that in the show notes i will yeah
cuz i'm not spaffled it's it's like uh yeah it's very good and if winnipeg wins the 2023 nazvik it
will be the first ever nazvik to be held outside the united states that's diversity pals i mean it's
also worth noting that at the moment there are two 2023 bids but also if glausco in 2024 win the
2024 worldcon which looks quite likely as they're currently unopposed and there'll also be 2024
nazvik so maybe one of them will decide to to swap but obviously the 2024 nazvik will be much
smaller and that segues nicely into glausco's new push for the new year and they have launched um
glausco fan artist hugo finalist Ian Clarke has done a lovely poster for glausco um showing with
scenes of glausco and the slogan i can move 500 miles for glausco in 2024 which is clearly a
reference to the proclamers song 500 miles which we're going to put a link to in the show notes in
case you haven't heard it um because octa thought the podcast of sartz fiction sartz fiction fandom
and massive earworms the idea is that you do exercise over and above your normal amount of
exercise for over and about your normal walking around the house actually get up and put your
shoes on or roll your wheels or swim or climb or whatever you want to do for 500 miles before
glausco wins the bid or glausco gets to shycon 8 to try with the bid sorry if 500 miles is not
enough for you and you think that's not a long way to go in in a couple hundred days then why don't
you walk 500 more run or swim or roll or whatever it is that you'd like to do to move and i will as a
committed member of the youth be instead moving 804.672 kilometers outbla i will say although i think
this is a lovely concept and i think it's to be applauded and i completely understand why they've
done move 500 miles instead of walk 500 miles because i have been thinking about moving house i was
like i mean i am gonna move to new castle from south amptom but that is an unrealistic expectation
of everyone in british fandom to do so i am glad that it is exercise.
Hoorah for glausco encouraging us all getting out and moving a little bit more
i think that is a fantastic thing to be doing and i am absolutely committed to this and if i
stuff it up then um yeah wait till i get my picks for why i might stuff it up so let's do picks
picks per bit pick picks so i've been quite busy this two weeks but i've discovered a great new
science fiction show on television everyone should be watching and i have watched um season one episode
one of the expanse which is on amazon prime and it's very good and i think you should all be
watching it i know that some of you have been going on a meet-and-watch for approximately 47 and a
half episodes of this podcast but there we go i've caught up now except for the other 68 episodes
and in 2022 i'm going to be doing a lot more of a lot sort of things including watching the whole
of the expanse and um reading more books and reading more fanzines and doing more fanak and
doing more art and um doing some more work because i have to make some money and um i haven't really
decided what i'm going to do less of but i'm thinking about giving up sleep very sensible
okay that'll work guys i look forward to chronicling your attempts to do this in or in an audio
medium every fortnight for the next year i like the expanse i'm glad that allison is watching it
first episode was great it's still going to be as great as that it has its ups and downs i wouldn't
say it was always amazingly good but it is as a whole very satisfying and i am enjoying it and if
you're very quick you could catch up before they finish you got like two weeks
that is optimism that that wow i look forward to you picking the expanse as your pick for the next
68 episodes then i promise not to do this i'm going to read some real science fiction in the
next two weeks or so i have actually um coincidentally just uh just placed a hold on the ninth book in
the series at the library so i will be reading that hopefully in the relatively near future
i think it'll be about six or seven weeks probably um but yes do you know do you know what i did on
my holiday allison i read some science fiction and fantasy oh excellent so my pick is vita noster
a book originally published in russian by ukraine writers marina and segue die cenco and i obviously
read the english translation which translated by julia miteff hercy you can reduce it to say that
it is essentially a russian magical college novel kind of you know in the vein of harry potter
the magicians etc but it's actually much more interesting and weirder than that it essentially
follows um sasha a teenage girl in russia who is approached by by a wizard basically and and carries
out a bunch of kind of pretty onerous and strenuous tasks for him um and then these are basically
our entry into a magical college and she goes to the magical college where it turns out that magic is
just kind of much stranger and weirder than i've i've seen in most novels and it's all about how
essentially learning the process of magic learning to like they end up reading what starts off as
gibberish but becomes something which is intelligible to them it's basically the magic system is about
kind of retraining your mind to kind of reshape the world in a different way and yeah it just it
just feels very different to kind of other magical college type novels i've read sasha obviously
has great power but um it's not always able to control that great power and the end i think is
basically an allegory for sort of the creation of the world and there is a figure who may or may not
be kind of the devil involved and it just kind of you know it feels diffused with this sort of
particularly russian russian background it was all about kind of living in these dormitories
through the freezing cold and and sneaking in vodka and i really i really enjoyed it it's very strange
it ends in quite a strange way but um it's definitely worth reading nice i may look that up
when is it eligible for the hugos Liz or is it before that no i think came out in 2018
oh for an old hat yeah i am going to also pick a very recent and up and coming tv series
that i'm sure no one has heard of and everyone will rush out and watch
hispania and i just watched the last episode of Buffy the vampire slayer which i'm told all the
cool kids have already watched ages ago but i didn't watch when i was a kid so i've been catching up
i really enjoyed it season six was not as good as the other seasons season four is clearly the
best season don't at me no it was i did like season seven quite a lot but yeah i really enjoyed
it on the whole we've also about halfway through season three of angel and i'm very much enjoying
that as well so yeah i i have been hugely enjoying that kind of trip down memory lane and then the
next job after that will be babylon five with adverts because it's on i am db tv and that has
adverts so that's fun it's not fun but you know it just downloaded from the internet no never
it's on amazon prime isn't it it's on i am db tv which you access through amazon prime but
you can also get if you don't subscribe to amazon prime but it means that it has adverts because
that's how they pay for it i see yes because i am db is owned by amazon and has its own tv
service yeah anyway streaming yeah it's all very easy to understand what's going on
the other hilariously retro pick i have is co-co which is less hilariously retro but we
rewatched it on christmas day because i felt like i hadn't leaked enough tears that day
and i needed to do some more and yup still blub the whole way through the ending oh my goodness but
i do love that movie haven't seen it should i watch it oh it's so good i love it i don't know why i
haven't seen it i liked it i need to get marion round and say we're gonna watch co-co today i also
watched it and i also cried a little bit i mean i also cried it up and toy story three so it was
obviously pixar i saw up in the cinema and i went to do what i was absolutely wrecked 10 minutes
into the movie so yeah we watched co-co the thing is when you watch co-co or any of these other films
we've mentioned in a cinema it's dark so no one can see you ugly crying but when you watch it on
christmas day with the lights on everyone can see you ugly crying and you can see everyone else
crazy yeah you know what's worse i watched it on a plane oh oh yep no for enough
uh yep yep yep yep okay right in with your favorite crying at movies and it goes
listeners uh because i suspect there are some doozies in our audience but for now that was the
octa-thaw podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me
it's not 500 miles is it 500 kilometers john i know i think it's about 500 kilometers
but obviously i'm not moving north of new castle for the joke uh so it will have to do
yeah it turns out john you thought you were moving to new castle but you're actually
gonna have to move to abadine i don't want to live on abadine i'm a dean fandom i'm gonna write it
it's just not where john's job is new castle is uh yes um 500 kilometers almost uh almost exactly
should we be starting the entire bit again and going turns out john is going to move 500
kilometers because he's one of the youth no oh yeah oh do we have to start the whole thing again i'm
really hungry the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in comfatec.com
used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]