Hi everyone, John here, just before we get going.
Alison is about to tell you a thing, and that thing has meant that the audio on her track is very slightly worse than usual.
I've done my best with it. Hopefully it's not too catastrophic.
But sorry about that, in advance.
And onward with the show.
I brought my microphone and my microphone stand and my microphone cable to the place where I'm staying this weekend,
but I did not bring the little doohickey that my microphone clips into before you were taken to the stand.
So I'm holding my microphone like a cabaret singer.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 113th episode of Octa Thorpe podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom,
which is coming to you on the 4th of July 2024.
I'm John Coxen.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
I assume you have also posted or voted Liz.
I proxy vote actually.
Or...
You'll be able to listen to what you thought while waiting for the election results to come in.
I mean, I don't know how you mean by you, well, I won't.
Our listeners.
Our listeners, this is a good distraction.
You all our listeners will be able to listen to the podcast while you're waiting for the election results to come in.
Yes, and if you are eligible to vote and you haven't voted, turn off our thoughts,
run to the polling station.
Actually, you know you can listen to what you thought while you run to the polling station.
Then vote, then come back.
Yeah.
Yeah, John, you need to get this episode out before 10pm when the vote...
False, Liz.
It's up to you, John. We're counting on you.
I want to hear more about Liz's proxy voting, which we interrupted in the middle of this and was interesting.
Well, I have a proxy vote. I'm not sure if that's interesting.
It is interesting.
Well, basically you just nominate someone who has to vote at your polling station.
So the polling station is where I would have voted before I left the UK.
So I can nominate someone who goes to that polling station and votes for me.
And I nominated friend of the podcast, Ruth O'Reilly, who gets to go to the polling station and vote for me.
And conveniently, she votes to the same polling station I used to.
So basically she just gets two goes.
Nice.
Back back to the letters of comment.
We have a letter of comment from Karen Schafer who processed a lot of pounds of peaches while listening to Octathor
talking about human nominations, which is an exit news of Octathor.
And if you want to send us any pitch jam, pitch cobbler, anything like that, we accept all donations.
Peach bourbon.
Oh, this one. Well, I mean, you basically take half a bottle of bourbon and you stick as many peaches as will fit
and you wait for months and it's very, very good.
Have you had Octathor recipe quarter?
That does sound pretty great.
I've also found a recipe for peach and bourbon pie, which sounds pretty great as well.
Peaches.
Karen bounced hard off some desperate glory, but it's going to give it another go because we endorse it.
So I mean, I think yay, but I hope that doesn't mean you read it and just dislike it.
I read it because we told you to.
And the same that she is reading the final architect trilogy, which I think I have endorsed quite heavily.
But we have endorsed basically all Adrian Tricoski products.
Yes. And also apparently we occasionally pronounce a word fantasy,
which I'm pronouncing very carefully here, in a way that sounds like fancy,
which is probably true. Probably you say fancy.
Fancy.
Fantasy, yep.
Fantasy.
It's because English.
It's because teas are a lie.
Yes. Sometimes English decides that syllables are not entirely necessary.
It could be replaced by a glottal stop.
Yes. And then we come up with the idea of fancy con.
I would go to fancy con.
This is the sequels of fun con.
If you did fun con, did you fancy doing fancy con then, you know.
And it could be ambiguous about whether it's just a it is a fantasy con or just a fancy con.
I assume it'd be a romance convention.
It's going to have good cosplay.
Why would it be a romance convention?
A fancy con.
It's about people who fancy other people.
It wasn't a good joke, but it was technically a joke.
I mean, I feel like I've been thinking,
what can I put on a river?
What can I put on a river?
I feel like it was technically a joke.
It's not a bad choice.
Yeah, that's fair.
Christopher J Garcia wrote in saying that he had no idea.
It was the 20th of June.
So cool.
Good Chris.
I'm glad we could educate you.
He also says that he knows the exact image that Liz is talking about
of the Netflix CEO.
And he's pretty sure that Ted loves that vest
because every time Chris sees him eating at Orin's Hummus in Las Gatos,
he's either wearing that exact vest or a t-shirt from
whatever the latest terrible Netflix series their slinging is.
I just, it's the very finest name dropping.
If name dropping was remarks and Spencer's, this would be it.
It's a specificity, isn't it?
Yeah.
It's not just that he sees the Netflix CEO
is eating at Orin's Hummus in Los Gatos.
Yeah, exactly.
Which means the cats.
Spanish Corner.
That's a rad.
Vanessa Mitalin wife loves bats so much.
There are multiple framed bat skeletons in the house.
That is pretty goth.
And then he says,
"Eastcon releasing financial reports is a good thing.
Convention center prices are astronomical,
so much so that even the middle big media cons around here
started using hotels for their events,
which is interesting because it's interesting to see the US kind of
events going more in a British direction.
I just want to say we had multiple people comment on the last episode that
we had made it sound like levitation had chosen to use a conference center
and that they should have used a hotel because it was cheaper.
The intent was to tell people who are less familiar with Eastcons,
why most Eastcons haven't used convention centers,
and why this conversation is new,
not to indicate that levitation had a different option.
We regret any confusion caused.
But we are trying to bear in mind that not everyone listening has a
historical view of these events.
And we're trying to give them one, but we will do better next time.
Yeah, they definitely didn't have a suitable quote from a cheaper hotel,
which they would probably be used if they had done.
But yeah, that's why it is also why historically
Eastcons have not been very expensive for the amount of programming they provide.
So, you know, because we were doing these deals.
America gets to do what has been described by Chris because
America has these enormous hotels.
Yes.
And Britain does not have hotels the ties of a small city.
You know, I've lived in villages smaller than the high at Regency Chicago.
Chris ramps up his lock by saying he hasn't seen the latest Godzilla,
but he's considering a chronological rewatch with the kids.
And I can't remember whether this made it into the episode last week.
But there are 38 of them, Chris, like in what order and which one are you skipping any?
And like, do you mean chronological in release order or in internal chronology?
Like, please write in with a full and detailed plan.
I'm not sure they're all suitable for kids.
And then I think it's Alison with Peter Sullivan's lock.
I'm not sure that Peter Sullivan's lock is a lock, actually, so much as a plug.
He says, "I've planned for online for Glasgow, coming long nicely.
We will have 10 streams of program from the convention itself,
plus two more online-only streams.
We've also taken onboard Alison Scott."
Who is that?
Alison Scott's first line of online socials, TM,
which I would basically summarize as, quote,
"They don't just happen.
You need to provide some sort of framework," end quote.
And so they have assigned a designated person for socials on Discord.
And I believe that person is John Coxon.
Hey.
Yeah.
Well done.
That's all sounds good.
I personally will not be my second law of online socials for in-person conventions
is that you have to have people who are not actually going to be at the
convention in person in charge of the online,
because the people who are at the convention are probably going to be a bit busy.
But, you know.
So are you thought the person who's going to sit in the SECC
connecting people in Glasgow to people online?
Is that the idea?
No.
What are you doing then?
My plan is to spool up the Discord some time beforehand
and to get people talking on the Discord,
so that by the time we get to the convention,
we don't have to do that, because people are doing it themselves.
Oh, I see.
Because I think if you start trying to get people to talk on the Thursday of the Glasgow,
of Glasgow, where everyone at Glasgow is ignoring Discord,
that is a plan that is doomed to fail.
And so that is not my plan.
We're going to do a scavenger hunt,
and we're going to do choose your own adventure if I run the zucon
so that people can do it, and then we're going to get Esther to do it later,
and we're going to see whether she does better than the denizens of the Glasgow Discord.
Oh.
And we're going to have a sort of chaos costuming thing during the convention.
We wanted to do like a Hugo Red carpet, but I don't think they work very well.
I think it's a nice idea that everyone ignores, basically.
Okay.
Are you going to have a scavenger hunt with most items,
which you can find not at the convention,
but a couple of items that you can find at the convention so that it needs teams
that have both on the line and online offline people?
No, because the scavenger hunts will be happening before the worldcon,
because at the worldcon, there will be quite a lot already happening.
The idea of most of what I'm doing is trying to get people on the Discord in advance,
and making people feel like the Discord is a place they want to be talking,
because as I say, if I think I'm relying on people online,
nagging people on site to pay attention, I've already lost.
Is my strong feeling.
And then we have Kat Corbet from Liz.
Yes, we have a letter from Kat Corbetty,
who listened while she was at the gym on the treadmill.
See, we're full of like healthy options here.
People listen while they're going for walks,
they listen while they're on the treadmill.
They listen while they're pressing peaches.
They record while they're in pancakes.
Yep, John records while he is eating pancakes,
and every time this happens, I get very sad,
because this banner is not bringing me pancakes.
Yes, to return to Kat's letter, she suggests more George McKay goodness,
including Sunshine on Leith, a Pratlamas jukebox musical.
Femme, in which he plays a closeted gay thug who attacks a drag queen
and ends up being seduced by her out of drag,
which she says is phenomenal, it does sound phenomenal.
He's in 1917, the World War I film shot in a single take,
and apparently he has also in another SFN film, How I Live Now.
So there you go, if you want a George McKay cat-drop list,
we have one provided by our listeners.
Mike Scott writes, "The large games convention that Allison attended in the 1980s was Gamesfair,
organised by TSR in Reading long before they sold out to Wizards of the Coast.
It seems to have almost disappeared from the historical record,
which is what I'd found.
It was probably the 1984 one, I think it was the 1985 one in fact,
because we didn't do East Columbia and I think we did do Gamesfair."
Yeah, so yes, it was Gamesfair, it wasn't that huge, but compared to modern conventions,
but it was quite big, much bigger than the Stabcon.
"And you can buy on eBay ends in two days and two hours,
so it might not still be there, but I'll put a link on the show notes if it is.
You can buy the Gamesfair 85 AD&D team competition module on eBay,
The Great Paladin Hunt by Mike Brunton."
How much would I buy it for?
11 pounds 20.
Oh, so if I wanted it, it wouldn't be that much, because it, you know,
so if you're a rare D&D stuff collector, then, I mean, it wasn't,
I was just doing tabletop all weekend, I didn't do any, do you do as far as I remember?
Fair, I just googled Gamesfair 1985 and the only thing that came up was that one thing on eBay.
Malcolm Hutchison writes in saying we were discussing East Kong's at Worldcon years and
their Morship numbers and he points out that the 2014 East Kong probably had a boost from initially
having to approach it as a special guest of honor, and that is a good point.
Johnny Bradley writes, "Aliceson, you made me blush. It would not be the first time, Johnny."
And he has pointed out that my husband Stephen knows no fear.
A man who will air saxophone, yakety-sax, ain't afraid of napping.
And there is quite a funny video, but I'm not sure it's available, though,
if you follow the, if you follow our Facebook group, then Ivan, who ran the item, has said,
"Oh yes, I have videos, so there are videos." It was very funny item.
It sounds good.
Fun facts, Stephen strained various muscles at Funcon and I had not previously thought about
the air saxophone being one of the causative occasions for that, but it might want to be.
Glasgow in 2024. I had an email from Glasgow and I think there are some people who have had
this email. I had not had it yet, so I've had it now, asking me to fill in the confirmation of
participation email, and they will say, "They said that they hoped to send me my provisional
schedule in the second week of July." So next episode, we might be able to report what's on it.
But yes, I know there were some people who were a bit worried that they hadn't had this yet,
but like I think it's coming out in stages, so if I had mentioned I'd received mine, Liz and
Alison, have you had anything from Glasgow? Yes. Way. Mine says, "We are delighted to welcome you as
a confirmed programme participant, which is presumably the email, and it says, 'We hope to send you
your provisional schedule by the end of June.' So I wonder if they have revised that prediction
since sending mine, because they sent me that on the 17th of June, which is some time ago.
So I might be fairly early in that process. And they may have gone, 'Ooh, the end of June, that's
pushing it a bit.' Yeah, I mean, I don't think it's really, I mean, I have inside a knowledge anyway
what was being on the programme team, which means I have been scanning Planarama looking for
participants and stuff, and everyone has little flags saying like what status they're in, so I
kind of knew if everyone's been accepted or what. But I don't think it's going to say that like
they will prioritise people, they expect to use a programme like say Hugo finalists,
and possibly they also did it in Alphabetic Lorda, which is why it's so strictly high up.
Hey, it's for Alison. Yes. We always alphabetise our letter of comment contributors by first name.
That's not true, is it? It is true. Is it? Yep. John, look at our letters of comment, they're not
alphabetised. Look at the show notes for episodes 112, 111, 109, 108. No, wait, are you
alphabetising them in the show notes? Yeah. So they're not in the order that we actually read them out
on the on the show? No. You absolute mad lad, what are you doing?
So we read the matter to give an order based on how we think we'll make a good show,
and then for doing the show notes, you then put them back into alphabetical order
so that people can find their figure the index, but we'll have to listen to the
entire show to work out what we've actually said about them. Yeah, I mean, I don't think knowing
what order they're in in the show meaningfully makes it faster to find a specific one anyway,
because it's not like you know how long we spend on each. I guess I could put a chapter marker in.
No, no, don't do that. Where did this end, John? Are you just going to start putting
pics at the beginning of the show notes? You know alphabetical order? No, because letter, yeah,
L comes before P-list. Oh, oh, but then we'd always do well-con at the end. Yeah. Ahead of only
yachting and if at what if we do Glasgow, just like our first then? No, because G is after like A,
so if we did odd part, sadbing before Glasgow. Anyway, other funny animals are available.
None as funny as an odd vark. Oh, to be fair, it's deeply inconsistent because you only have
to go back like six and you find what I forgot to do it. So, so fun fact, there is currently a
humble bundle for the whole of Syrabus the odd vark by Dave Sim. And this is occasioned much
discussion on online forums I'm in about whether any of Syrabus is worth reading or whether the
entire thing is irrevocably dood by the fact that Dave Simbeth went a bit bananas part way
through the run and got increasingly unhinged the more of it he wrote.
Didn't someone just finish like a complete review of Syrabus? Like they read all of it
and wrote about it in detail. Does anyone know what I'm thinking about? I do not. I'm looking for
Syrabus review and there's a ton, there's a problem. Hmm, I will try and find it.
It will either be in the show notes or if it is not in the show notes, please write in.
Yeah, if we put a link we found it and if we didn't we haven't.
Yeah, so uh, Syliz, am I going to be on any program?
I can't tell you. Oh, it's a secret.
Secretless. You'll just have to tune in next time.
Yeah, soon we will know. I can't go around telling people things. I also
sign the thing saying I would not just like use Planarama for frivolous reasons,
look at people's email addresses and stuff like that. So I actually don't know.
Yeah, I wasn't, I wasn't asking you to tell me like Neil Gaym is email address.
I feel like my my proposed infraction of the date of policies was I think quite me specific.
All right, do we want to talk, are we got anything else on Glasgow?
I'm excited about Glasgow.
I could say I am collecting a lot of combages at the moment.
I am drowning in combages. People, people keep saying, oh, would you like some combages from this
con? I discovered that there was a series of cons conventions, not only had I never heard of them.
In general, student-run conventions in Britain that I had never heard of, but they were 11 off the
which is quite a lot. So this project turned out to be quite a bit bigger than I thought.
It started when we were given a large posthumous donation of combages and it was said, would the
fan funds like to do something with this? And and instead of what we should have done, which was
go, yes, we would like to put them unexamined into the into the bin. We said, oh, it would be good to do
a display for Glasgow about convention badges. So there's going to be a display at Glasgow about
British and European convention badges, probably. And in support of this, I've been collecting British
and European convention badges in order to not go bad. I have decided arbitrarily that these are
fan-run conventions and that they are conventions about science fiction and fantasy and related
subjects generally, rather than the works of a particular show or author, because actually it's a
huge job even with a general brief. And then after the WorldCon, I may be going to expand that to
include all of the other conventions, the Star Trek conventions and the Discworld conventions and
the H.H.I.K.S. conventions and all of those conventions. But at the moment, it is just kind of all of the
it is for general conventions. And I've got quite a lot and it is not going to be complete at all.
So the title of this display is provisionally an extremely incomplete guide to the convention
badges of Britain and Europe. And it's lots of fun in a kind of, oh God, did I need another large
project inserted in my life this close to the WorldCon? To which the answer is no. But there we go.
I've also done the guest of Honor exhibit for Claremark, so that is done and has been delivered
very early. So that is not because of me, that is because of Claremark who were very efficient
in giving me everything I needed to do it. And so I think it's fair to say that if you have any
combatges you don't want, bring them to Glasgow and give them to Alison as a surprise.
You know, actually that's fine. But don't be surprised if I then put them straight in the bin.
I mean, the fanfants probably does want your collection of combatges, but please,
please remove weird, you know, not if they're weirdly stained unless it's a very rare badge.
Are you just doing the badges or is it badges and people's giant ribbon collections?
I am not doing giant ribbon collections at all. I think I've decided I don't really care. I think
there is another project that in actually collecting and documenting and his terrifying
convention ribbons I think is quite interesting. But I am not going to be that person at least not
this year or next year. Well, the year after. Probably not the year after. But I mean, if
nobody's picked up that fan historical idea, I think it's partly my feeling that a lot of the
fan historical material is very text based. And I would like to see us do a better job of collecting
the artistic illustrative material around fan history than we are currently doing.
But I don't want to be the entire person who does this because, you know, I have other things.
But I'm happy to do this. But it did grow into a much bigger project than I was thinking about.
Right. That's that's all I'm well con. After that, my only remaining world con task is to
organize the fan fun tables in the dealer's room. If you have been a fan fund delegate,
if you think fan funds are interesting, if you're coming to Glasgow and if you'd like to do a
couple of hours on the table, we would really appreciate it. Let me know that sound, you know,
because we need lots of people. We're going to have three tables. We'll need quite a lot of people
to help. And it's going to be a lot of fun because being in the dealer's room is fun and having
being on the fan fund tables is fun. That's it. That's all I'm doing at Worldcon, I think.
Fair enough. And I have got to the stage in my life where people keep emailing me with questions
about the world con despite the fact that I'm not actually working on the Worldcon at all,
which is interesting. This is because every time anyone mentions the Worldcon, you have several
opinions. And so they know that if they email you about the Worldcon, you will have opinions,
and so they might as well email you to get the opinions. And if you want them to stop,
there's a clear and obvious route that I think will never happen. Do you think?
Most of the time I'm saying to people, why don't you ask this question in the Glasgow
Community Group on Facebook? I repeat, the Glasgow Worldcon Community Group on Facebook,
which is an excellent place to ask questions like, why is my Baldur's Gate 3 code not working?
Where is there a laundrette near the SEC? Or did you know that someone posted this funny meme about
Haggis last week? Except don't post funny Haggis memes because that group is going to get more
and more active for the next month, right? Let's not clog it up entirely with Haggis memes.
Let's only partly clog it up with Haggis memes. Okay, octavort listeners, if you have a Haggis meme
you don't want to do. No, I realised too late what I'd done. There's the last name in it, the
the Streisand effect. Streisand effect? Where you say something should not be a thing everyone talks
about and you saying the thing means that everyone talks about it. Named after Barbara Streisand who
asked people to stop talking about where she lived and that caused an awful lot of attention to be
diverted to the topic of where she lived.
Since we last recorded, or actually one of these came out before we last recorded, we just forgot
to mention it. The winners of the Locust and Nebula Awards have been announced. So they have
announced the Nebula's and Locust Award which I guess from my perspective is partly interesting
because it's a good way of, it's a good sort of prediction for the Hugos. And I've got to say,
say in the Nebula Awards, the St. Bright Doors won Best Novel, which I was not necessarily expecting
given that Anlechia and Martha Wells are both in that category. So I think that both are well
for the St. Bright Doors at the Hugo. Best Novel Act was the year without Sunshine, which I was fully
accepting, expecting to scoop every ward because I think Naomi Kritzer has that and also better
living through algorithms, which is also on the Hugo Ballot, Anel, the Nebula Ballot.
We're both kind of, they're good stories but they have this particular vibe which is like
people working together as communities is a good thing and the story is basically
asked, stories of how people start working together more and that is good and nice. And in fact,
the novel that's in the Locust Award, Liberty's Daughter, is a little bit of that. So I, and I think
that is something that the Hugo's kind of likes to reward. I think they definitely have a soft spot
for well-written good stories which have a sort of hopeful community binding message. And so, so I
slightly surprised when it did not win Best Novel Act in the Locust Awards, it went to the Rainbow
Bank by Ochechicu Nwaka from Giga Nautosaurus, which I actually haven't read or heard anything
about but it won the Locust Award. So, I guess my take-home messages, the Nebbers and Locusts are
probably a good prediction of what's going to win the Hugos except for when they are a terrible
prediction of what's going to win the Hugos. I think it is interesting that St. Abright Doors
won Best Novel of the Nebula's and Best First Novel at the Locust Awards. It is also interesting
that some desperate glory did not even get nominated in the Nebbers and lost out to St. Abright
Doors in First Novel in the Locust Awards. So yeah, we will see if that presages things in the Hugos
as this says. Also, Baldur's Gate 3 won Best Game Rating at the Nebbers and I have started
playing Baldur's Gate 3 and I've played one hour of Baldur's Gate 3 and I suspected is going at the
bottom of my interactive work ballot because it is not my cup of tea.
Are you off the spaceship yet? No. I think I've just triggered, oh no I am. I had to watch a very
there was a very long cutscene and then I was on a spaceship with sphincters and then there was
another very long cutscene and now I'm on a beach. Okay, so that is all that has happened in the first
hour. I would say there's a no cutscene in Baldur's Gate 3 has yet to be let it seem like as long as
the cutscene in Horizon Zero Dawn that almost caused me to give up the game permanently.
But that was just one. The point is that Horizon Zero Dawn concentrated its cutscenes into one
incredibly long lump of exposition about halfway through. But also Horizon Zero Dawn's cutscenes
had characters in that I cared about which is one quite big difference so far. Yeah, so you're
gonna care about some of these characters but you don't care about them yet do you is the point
about Baldur's Gate 3. I've met some people but I immediately unmet them again and they all seem
terrible. I'm not saying it's a bad game everyone loves it it's clearly a great game but oh I'm not
sure it's a John game. That's interesting because I always thought you were way more into narrative
in games than I am so. I am that's why I don't like it. Read us write it. I think if there hasn't been
it feels like so far and I'm hoping this gets better and I will keep playing it to see if it gets
better but so far it feels like a bad Captain America movie but fantasy. So it feels like the
level of writing of the MCU but like two steps down and in a genre I don't really care for and I'm
like is this the pinnacle of games in science fiction because because I would argue no but but
as I say lots of people love it so maybe I just haven't got to the good beat yet. Yeah I liked it
much more once I got into the gaming game but you know as I said it's clearly not my game either so
I didn't pick it last week but I picked it because you know I was just so amazed that I could play
it on my Mac which then died so I don't know whether those two facts were collected. And then
the other one is Two Shape A Draggers Breath 1 the Norton Nebula Award for Middle Grade a Young
Adult. I have been reading that it's quite good. There's no other crossover between the load star
and the nebula so I suspect it is the only Norton finalist I will read. Yeah but also then in the
Locust Awards Charlie G and Anders promised to stronger than Darkness 1 which is also a loads
star nominee. Yes I read the first of that trilogy when it was up for the Hugo and I thought it was
okay. I will also say at the Locust Awards congratulations to Tor for winning Best Publisher
for the 25th year in a row. Get rid of the category. There's no point. We know Tor's a publisher.
We know they're good. The nominees are interesting though right because the nominees do include
things like Neon Hemlock who are a very sort of small press who published a lot of interesting
looking novels and novellas. Hello everyone John here after we recorded this but before it went live
the most recent Locust editorial says that the Tor Publishing Group which includes Tor.com publishing
as well has recused itself from consideration for the Locust Award Best Publisher for a few years
quote to allow others to shine unquote and they note that this year's award is in fact the 37th
that Tor has won. Applause for this classy move which we will talk more about next time.
Commiserations to all these world reviews and essays by Neil Harrison in the Locust Awards
which did not win. It lost to a person a little known person in the genre called Ursula K. Le Guin.
If you're going to lose there are worse people to whom you might but I'm expecting people to come
out for the hugos. Vote Neil unless you don't want to in which case don't but I think you should want
to. I think your campaign slogan needs a little bit of work John.
Possibly. I had a lot of space chrome being discussed in discussions of what one might
vote for this year in non-fiction categories. Nope I never heard of it. I've heard of it now but
you know. Part of the reason I do a podcast is because most of my non-fiction is in podcast form
may not be surprising. I had not heard of it because I'm not sure I'm particularly well read
in that regard. So what you're saying is that Neil should start a podcast for you.
Yeah I have told him that repeatedly but it is not taken. He was on I think critical friends right?
Yeah.
Right so since the last time we recorded there has been an announcement of a bid for a world
convention in Brisbane in 2028. This is not being a real I think by Brisbane fans if you're a Brisbane
fan writing but by fans from around Australia who have put together a bid they the committee is
chaired by random Jones who I do not know but also includes on the main committee Eureech,
G, Green and Tax both of whom I met on my guff trip and liked very much and so obviously that's a
great reason to to think people will be able to run a world con. It's not necessarily but they seem
to be sensible interesting people with a lot of good ideas when I met them and there are a number
of other people involved and also an advisory committee which includes Rose Mitchell and
Perimidleness who are previous Aussie con chairs and they are running they are hoping to hold Aussie
con 5 which is a thing where they've actually said this which is not normally done but they're
running they're hoping to run Aussie con 5 in 2028 in Brisbane and if they succeed in that day they'll
be they'll be bidding at the 2026 World con we don't know where the 26 World con will be but the only
site that has filed papers is Los Angeles so they will be bidding in Los Angeles to hold the World
con in Brisbane and if they win I will try and get to the World con in Brisbane because I still kind
of want to go to a World con in Australia or New Zealand not having managed to do so in 1990
in 1990 2020 my brain is completely fried guys I have reached senility another year has turned on
the year clock and I'm clearly heading down the slippery slope anyway they they don't currently
have a method of joining them or paying them any money but they do have a Facebook page you
could go enjoy to learn more about the bit and they do also have a web page and we will dig into
those things in the show notes I think I know what you mean about people don't usually announce what
the name of the convention will be but I think a careful read of the previous names of Australian
World cons probably could have had a stab anyway so for the listener they were called Aussie con 1
Aussie con 2 Aussie con 3 Aussie con 4 it's a good brand so and they're hoping to have a table at
Glasgow I should probably have said this and obviously I'm looking forward to meeting all the
people I met at Australia again in Glasgow lots of Australia fans are going to be in Glasgow which
is very exciting to me see you all there guys I think this bit is basically not connected to the
previous Perth in 2025 bit I think this is a new thing that's spun up right Brisbane in 2025
I think it was Brisbane in 2025 as well Brisbane's got a right sized convention centre and the
thing about Brisbane is it somewhere that's the weather's pretty good in the middle of winter
for running a World con so I think it's got a good a good choice of location all right there
was definitely at some point a Perth in 2025 bit so this is and then there was also when Brisbane
in 2025 bit so now we're on Brisbane in 2028 okay they announced the Perth 2025 bid
before Dublin and then by Dublin that was on hiatus and then that bid folded and the Brisbane
bid came about in 2025 and now it is Brisbane in 2028 so it was PRK who launched the Perth
bid and they're on the advisory committee for Brisbane in 2028 and 2025 the Brisbane in 2025
one was Devin Madsen and Leaf Leaf I don't know how to pronounce your name I'm sorry Shell Cross
and I don't and neither of them are on the committee or the advisory committee for Brisbane in 2028 now
so I don't know internal Australian politics presumably if you are Australian and internal
right in so the current line up of World Conbid for the next few years we know 2026
Los Angeles Anaheim is the only bidder 2027 is currently Montreal versus Tel Aviv I haven't
heard anything from Tel Aviv for a while but I suspect that's going to be Montreal's yeah I would
be surprised if a Tel Aviv World Conbid won the bid session next year yeah 2028 is now Brisbane
versus the Kampala Uganda bid yeah and then 2029 is Dublin currently unopposed that does appear to
be correct in previous years there have been persistent repeated but ultimately doomed bids from
France and Japan which have made it seem like there are a lot more bids happening but whenever you
go to their parties it's like this isn't probably actually going to be a thing is it because there's
like two people and a small tub of beer and so it's tricky because I think in the last decade it has
seemed like there are more but I do wonder whether the number of like actual going concerns is staying
about the same and there are just few people fewer people doing it sort of speculatively but I would
still love to see a nice World Con I would love I would love to go to France World Con yeah is there
anything in 2030 and beyond nothing in 2030 so far there is Texas in 2031 yes why are they not
running 2030 because they don't want to okay and then presumably there will be UK in 2034
and then I mean place your bets now as to whether or not I'm high but New York in 2039 I have no idea
you'd hope there's a lot of enthusiasm for it but it's it's quite complicated
is yeah and it's going to be interesting to see what the Irish what the Irish fans do
because they have carved the nine out but if they are up against New York in 39 I do not think
Dublin will beat New York so I don't know they'll be interesting to see how that shakes out but it
might just be that there isn't a New York bid the reason for newer listeners or listeners who are
less familiar with World Con history the reason we are discussing New York in 2039 is because the
first World Con was in New York in 1939 and fandom does like an anniversary right yes I'm reminded of
the Olympics where they were very very keen to get the Olympics back to Athens for the 100th
year anniversary but it just did not come together they did later but but there was all this oh well
Athens will definitely get it from I guess it was 1996 and of course it didn't it was just
impossible and and that might happen with New York because putting a World Con in New York is
quite hard so but I'm sure people would love to see it if it was possible I don't know 2039 it's
a long way away I don't know what I'll be doing in 2039 it's a long long time it is a long way away
it is a long way away it is and remember 2073 is getting closer the reason Alison says that is
because there is a Minneapolis in 2073 bid which was initially extremely funny and presumably gets
a bit less funny with each passing decade. Transitioned to a real bid some time ago it was like when
they failed to win in 1973 or whether 1973 bid didn't come together they were like oh well we will
you must run again and they were like 100% will run again we will run for Minneapolis in 2073
and the funny thing about time is that if you if you just don't do anything it just kind of carries
it anyway. There is an email newsletter I read since we are now in like there are an a sense of
internet email newsletters got put onto it actually because of a post they did about a graphic designer
called Barbara Salfatcher Solomon who died a few months ago who did the entrance of SF MoMA if you
remember that John with all the red and the black phrase tracking signs anyway even more of a
digression that this email newsletter is all about the preparations for the LA 2028 Olympics and kind
of what that means for LA and the surroundings because the idea of LA was you know the previous
one was oh we can do this on the cheap will reuse existing venues I think it's still the only
Olympics to make a profit and so the idea of going back in 2028 is you know can they do that again
and the Olympics is on a completely different scale but it is another event that is running into
well this is expensive where can we hold it what do you actually need how many of the things we
kind of assume you have to do for the Olympics actually have to happen that that kind of thing
and I find it quite interesting although occasionally a bit inside baseball on things like how you pay
for bus tickets in LA it's good it's called torch by a lister walker. It's such nice please put a link
in the show notes in this part of the podcast which we're talking about the Antipides. If you are in
the Antipides or if you like the Antipides and you are free this weekend the New Zealand
Nikon is happening on the 6th of July it is happening online and we will put a link in the
show notes I went to this latter I was one of the online guests of honor at it and it was very good
fun and I kind of time shifted a bit for it and it is also in person in Wellington so if you're in
or near Wellington which most New Zealand fans are then you've got an actual convention to go to
this weekend for the first time in quite a long time so and if you're otherwise in a time zone
that's New Zealand compatible then then there's a convention going on virtually as well and if
you're listening to this I think you've got like one day to buy a ticket before they close memberships
so yeah get on it oh yes though you need to get on to it yeah you're walking you're walking to the
voting center but stop stop walking to the voting center buy your membership to this and then
keep going unless time is not on your side in which case do it the other way round but don't
vote for the Nikon remember to take your photo ID with you yes to both to both I don't know if
you need it for the for the New Zealand that card but you need it to vote um right yes and
congratulations to New Zealand for getting their national conventions back rolling more conventions
more news more zealand's
true do picks my pick this week is a video game that is the video game which I started playing
well I got a bit bored of Baldur's Gate 3 which was slightly after two weeks ago's episode this is
a game called animal well and in this game you are in a well and there are a lot of animals and I'm
following up the John descriptive game descriptions
file do you want a little bit more than that no it you play as a tiny little blob and it is a
sort of game called a metroidvania which I think obviously people are kind of extremely steep to
games will immediately know what I mean by that but for everybody else it is a game where you are
um jumping around and moving around a little 2D area and every so often you find a thing that
will help you solve some of the puzzles in the area that you are in and also help you with some
of the puzzles elsewhere of the thing and there are great many puzzles and a great many secrets
but I am enjoying it very much and I am very much expecting to continue to have fun as I go through
it's getting a little bit harder but I'm still making progress every time I pick it up well
these games tend to get to a point where I stop making progress without having to check the
internet and I think that's a bit boring I don't want to be checking the internet all the time
and also I have an OLED switch and this is the first game I've played that
we're really having really dark blacks are really nice for the game so it looks really really good
on OLED if you have an OLED screen to play it on some steam and switch and other things I don't
know I should probably have checked what things it was on it is on steam and switch and ps5 because
I just checked if I can play it yes and it's it's fabulous oh so anyway this is my this is my first
here is a copper bottomed choice for the 2025 best game or interactive design Hugo in my view
because it's there's not going to be six games I enjoy more than this this year okay I am going
to pick Alan Wake 2 which completes our group picking of all of the interactive work finalists
that we are going to play we haven't played the Zelda so we're probably not going to pick the Zelda
would be my guess and there's Liz has been like frantically playing Zelda and I'm just unaware
which is not impossible but yes no she's shaking her head Alan Wake 2 is real good I like it a lot
it is bloody terrifying I played a little bit before bed the other day and that was a mistake
I would not do that Alan Wake 2 is about a lady called saga and she has and I cannot stress this
enough an amazing jumper saga jumper Alan Wake 2 Anderson
saga Anderson yes it does not initially include anyone by the name of Alan Wake and I have not
played the first Alan Wake so I was you know there are messages there are like there are hints
as to who Alan Wake might be and there's definitely weird stuff going on and you play a bit and
it gets weirder it definitely gets weirder I really like it I'm not good at it okay so the website
the Alan Wake 2 website includes a knitting pattern good the official knitting patterns for sagas
it looks like a fairly ordinary Icelandic type jumper of the sort that Anna Fruilliedaldan knocks
off in a couple of days I love that there's an eating guide that's amazing if you're watching
this Anna John would like a saga Anderson sweat of Christmas I am I like say I'm really enjoying
Alan Wake 2 it's really good I think it might be second on my baller but it is I'm really struggling
to work out which I like best out of chance of sennar and Alan Wake 2 I will say that John
texted me and he said this game is a perfect storm of all the things Alison does not like it
video games Alison would absolutely test this game I stand by that yeah I can't play it because
although there are codes at the Hugo Pack I do not have the necessary hardware to play it with
but it does sound like as a primarily narrative game with limited gameplay choices with the horror
theme that is really unsettling it's probably not my game no so Liz picked chance of sennar on a
previous episode and I have now played it as it was in the pack um and I I did adore it I thought
it was really really good um I'd be very happy to see it win the the category I think it's very
good but I I also really like Alan Wake but they're quite different games and I'm really struggling
to think which one I like best so I like them both a great deal I think at the moment and I
have just looked and I lied to you listeners because I have not yet picked Star Wars Jedi
Survivor yeah no you haven't and I will pick that next episode I guess so I won't talk much about it
now but that's definitely going to get third for me and then Dredge and Baldur's Gate will be
very up the rear I like Dredge a lot but it's like there are a lot of good games in this category so
yeah it's very good it's very good category this year it's quite nice having such a lot of interesting
things to have and it's not there's not an obvious thing where I go oh it is a tragedy that this game
from 2023 didn't get on the ballot because I don't feel that's the case fun fact based on
last week's stuff I have now watched Godzilla - 1 because it turned out I did have Netflix after
all I think I might have said on the pod I don't have Netflix but I do what is my life like and
Godzilla - 1 which I think YouTube both said last time was good Godzilla - 1 is shockingly good for
a monster movie it's very good it's it's got loads of things I like to hold lot shouldn't be
shockingly good we both told you it was good yeah but I kind of you like Marvel movies right yes okay
it's shocking if you're a snob I will give you that is that helpful oh 100 but well also it's it's
Alison did laugh Alison did laugh for that listeners it's just quite funny anyway Liz do you
want to do a pic yeah so I don't really have a pic so John has been suggesting that since
he has picked Alan Wake AW and Alice has picked Animal Well AW I should pick something with initials
AW but instead I'm going to pick something with initials WA whoa I'm basically going to plug
something that I've plugged elsewhere but having just checked I have not yet plugged on the podcast
basically there is a YouTuber called Will Anderson who is the 2017 North American Scrabble Champion
and he's got a YouTube channel all about Scrabble and it's great I'm no good at Scrabble I don't
play Scrabble and yet I will like go to his channel every time he posts a new video to look at some
awesome Scrabble playing I recommend Will Anderson Scrabble channel that I sound like the source
of YouTuber I like I mean I think if you like cracking the cryptic you'll probably like the Scrabble
YouTube well I'm hoping that cracking the cryptic play Animal well actually I mean I'm sure they
will at some point might be a bit un-puzzle-like for them I do have problems when they play video
games because they end up like shouting at the screen I mean when they're doing a Sudoku I'm not
pointing out things they're missing but when they're playing video games I'm like no go and do this
instead don't push that yeah oh I do that when they're doing Sudoku because they do often one of
the things that's so good about the channel is that they're absolutely brilliant at Sudoku but
obviously they'll sometimes miss something that you have spotted and you'll be like 29 minutes later
they'll finally make that collection you go you'd have found this puzzle quite a lot easier if you
noticed that you know 25 29 minutes ago do we have anything else on on Scrabble I've never well I
know that John likes Scrabble but I and I guess I don't I've never liked Scrabble very much because
I I probably like so many other things I'll probably be fine with Scrabble if I played it with a chess
clock I mean you do play Scrabble competitive Scrabble they do have a clock and that does
come into it as you'll find out if you watch the latest video on well Anderson Scrabble YouTube
channel at time of recording anyway cool back but but lots of people don't like chess clocks in
in casual games because they're kind of like obit makes the game so much more pressurized but I
kind of I would much rather have the game have that little bit of pressure caused by a timer
than the very large amount of pressure caused by somebody taking 25 minutes about a move especially
it's me I think Scrabble is also worse and I believe I believe this is a house rule that
Alison plays with but a lot of people play with a house rule where you can look up words in between
your goats and Scrabble is infinitely worse if you are allowed to do that Scrabble is great when
you have a word on your rack which you are 95% sure is a word and will win you 50 points and you have
to work out whether the 5% chance that you're going to lose your turn is worth the reward and then
it becomes a push your luck game and an area control game and that is where it sings for me
but a lot of people do not do that and I think that is I know takes away a lot of the crunch
from my perspective the other thing is if someone plays a word which you are 95% sure is not a word
and you challenge them then that also goes bad for you and then the game lives in those percentages
and those percentages are something I love in gaming so yeah I like that push your luck aspect
almost to Scrabble that was the old podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me
and it's goodbye from me
[Music]
Do you know do you know where our listeners come from John? 40 42% of our listeners come from the
United States and 37% come from the United Kingdom okay five five and a half percent from
Australia 3.15% from Jersey so hello to our two Jersey listeners and so on and so forth
and presumably one from Thailand yes well no well I don't know 0.33% of our listeners come from
Thailand but I should think Liz does not download the episode once it is out I do not download the
episode once it is out because I've already listened to it spoilers listeners I listed before you
no but I did I think I have gone and I have gone and downloaded some in order to correct our
transcripts for Hugo purposes so that is almost certainly me and not anyone else gonna say I have
downloaded downloaded a few from time to time that's fair do you want to guess where our largest
non primarily English speaking country is so for the purposes of this I'm I am deciding the
United States United Kingdom Australia Canada Jersey and New Zealand and Ireland are primarily
English speaking countries I do not intend to erase any of the other languages spoken in those
territories but where is the where is the highest country that is not one of those Poland not Poland
China China not China China China does not appear on this list shockingly believe Chinese
government don't appear on your download things despite the fact there are accessing your material
Finland not Finland close though Sweden Sweden two percent of listeners Sweden Netherlands
Belgium hello Nicholas Germany Norway Israel hello Abigail and then Russia at Finland India
Austria Bulgaria Brazil Switzerland Denmark Italy Japan Korea Mexico Philippines Portugal Turkey
in that order but for Sweden I would say hello Shana hello Johan but don't know if he listens but
hello anyway hello to everyone we know in all of those countries hello several people called Anders
I am fascinated by so of the bright lake who is the one download in June from Turkey I don't know
but hello to whoever they are if they download again if you're in Turkey and you're listening
please let us know yes anyway that was a digression the theme music for this episode was
Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod and Compatec.com used under a creative Collins
attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep