Alison, your turn.
Give me a second, I'm busy looking at Tom Roberts' art.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 158th episode of Octothorpe,
which is coming to you early on the 21st of April, 2026.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And we are coming to you early, listeners, because we have had an embargoed press release.
Ooh.
Because it is Hugo Awards season and we know what the finalists are.
And we're going to share that information with you, the listener.
So we're going to go bottom up on the list and we're going to start with Not a Hugo,
the Astounding Award for Best New Writer sponsored by Dell,
The nominees are Sophie Burnham, Camilla Cole, Antonia Hodgson, Molly O'Neill, H.H. Pack and Jared Pekicek.
Yeah, some authors.
I've read one by Jared Pekicek, I think, but I can't remember what it was called.
Yeah, probably The West Passage last year was his debut novel, which was very good.
Oh, I haven't actually read that. I just know the name from last year. Fair enough.
I will look forward to reading it.
Okay, fair enough if you haven't read it.
Antonia Hodgson is the author of The Raven Scholar, an excellent fantasy debut.
It's interesting because she has other previous novels, but they were not science fictional.
And so she's still eligible for The Astounding.
Camilla Cole was nominated for The Lone Star, I think, last year.
Sophie Burnham, I think, is a recent debut fantasy novelist.
Yeah, looks like a solid, solid list.
haven't read something by all of them but have read have read enough to know that i will have a hard
time deciding between jared peshacek and antonia hodgson even without reading anything else um no
i haven't like i say i haven't read anything by these people but i look forward to it and i've
been hearing buzz about many of them so i think um i think this is good yeah i mean there was a lot
of buzz about the west passage um because it's very good i was gonna say did it win an award
one sec yeah because the west passage run the run the won the crawford award for uh the debut
fantasy in the year it was published so sylvia park and barbara true love were both both had
enough votes to qualify but both had qualifying publications prior to 2024 so were not on the
ballot i knew this was true of sylvia park um because there'd been a discussion um i was privy
to in a discord about it and i don't think i've heard of barbara true love but they're not on the
ballot what was coming in in that category because i was doing the hugo nomination vetting i knew
lots of people were nominating Sylvia Park and I was like no she had a prior public prior qualifying
publication which is basically one story about five years ago uh on Reactor which became part of the
novel so it is kind of a shame that um she's not eligible um because I would have put her down and
it's great uh and spoilers she's not going to be there in best novel so that is a shame uh next
category is the lodestar award for best young adult book and we have among ghosts by rachel hartman
coffee shop in an alternate universe by cb lee holy terrors by margaret owen oathbound by tracy
dion sunrise on the reaping by suzanne collins and they bloom at night by trang tan tran i've not
read the most recent tracy dion book but i've read one of the earlier ones and i thought it was
intriguing so i'm uh interested to read that and i enjoyed the hunger games so uh the suzanne collins
is intriguing but again I haven't read it yet. Lodestar I don't know if you two agree with me
but my knowledge of YA comes almost entirely from what gets nominated from the Lodestar.
Yeah I think that's fair. I was really pretty familiar with the YA category when I had kids
who were teenagers young and medium-sized teenagers and I expect that to happen again
if I ever have grandchildren who are medium-sized teenagers. I personally don't read very much in YA
I did have a strong visceral reaction to one of the titles in this category.
I sighed a little, which is Coffee Shop in an Alternate Universe by C.B. Lee.
Now, I hope that this is a really trenchant, ironic take on the Coffee Shop in an Alternate Universe subgenre of fantasy.
And that my fears are unjustified, but I rather think it won't be.
Definitely when I think YA, I think, yes, I want the books to be trenchant ironic critiques of the category.
Okay, so can I tell everyone to go and read William Sleater or, for that matter, Alan Garner?
I mean, I have read a lot of Alan Garner.
No, I just I just think we're kind of like saying, oh, well, you're saying you don't want this to be a typical take on a, you know, coffee shop romance, cozy fantasy genre, which I think it could be.
but there's also a place for those books and maybe having one or two of those in the YA category is
fine they can be doing other interesting things without the within the genre without being a
complete you know critique of the whole thing um and I think don't judge a book by its title
which is perfectly fair yeah you're trying to you know you're trying to position your book you're
gonna probably try and jump on the things which are currently selling books if one of those is
being a cozy bookshop coffee shop romance then yeah i mean among ghosts is another of uh rachel
hartman's ones in uh the same series with start with the seraphina so test the road was nominated
i think a couple years ago so i'll definitely be interested to read that yeah summarize on the
reaping as we said is another hunger games sequel what was the one i thought was interesting it was
missing they bloom at night is also um looks like it's young adult horror which is interesting
oh i like horror i've only become aware of this fact about myself recently as as long term listeners
i think i've mentioned on the pod before but uh i'm excited therefore that sounds good i did try
and recommend a horror book to you but to be fair it was probably not quite the right horror book
for you oh the bloody one yeah that's the that's tricky i'm almost certainly up for young adult
horror because i think the things i don't like in horror rarely appear in young adults the next
category is a category that LA are running as a special Hugo Award in advance of it being ratified
at the LA Comm 5 business meeting and that is best poem. The finalists here are Care for Lightning
by Mary Ness, Hex Supply Customer Support Log by Ellis Montgomery, How to Become a Sea Witch by
Theodora Goss, Landing Seattle by Brandon O'Brien, The Morning Robot by Angela Liu and The World to
come by jennifer hudak i've put links in the show notes listeners to all but one of those landing
seattle was read at the seattle opening ceremony and so i don't think it's available online but i'm
sure it'll be in the packet poem i mean i like poems i've read one of them i've not read any of
these poems which poem have you read liz i have read a hex supply customer support log because
there was some discussion of it going around on the internet and so that's how i became aware of
it i quite enjoyed it and it has kind of a kind of an uh reason why it is a poem embedded in the
poem which is quite clever oh nice okay that sounds cool yeah i'm actually quite excited about this
category because this is the one where if we'd had the results just a tiny bit if i'd had the results
a tiny bit earlier i probably would have read it's a little poem would you though
listeners it is a sunday morning and i'm challenging allison as to whether she would
have actually sat down and read poetry for half an hour she might have done it's not the strangest
thing she could have done no it's true right the best fan artists the nominees are terry ash
geneva bowers sarah felix richard mann ispania sheriff and you may yes how do you feel about
this category john uh i think ispania sheriff does good fan art liz that's my official opinion
Yes, I think we extend official podcast congratulations to Espania.
Yes.
Otherwise, I think you, well, Sarah Felix and Richard Mann certainly repeat nominees.
I think you may is also a repeat nominee.
Yes.
Geneva Bowers is an interesting one because she's a professional illustrator.
So I'll be interested to know what her packet submission is like.
because I can't tell from her website what is pro art and what is fan art.
Terry Ash is probably better known for being involved with geek calligraphy.
So I've linked to geek calligraphy in the show notes, listeners.
Rigidman took my wedding photos and is lovely.
Sarah's also lovely.
And I have never met you, May.
But I'm sure they're lovely too.
But yeah, good mix of new and old, I think.
Yeah.
And I mean, it is interesting that you do have someone who does both professional art and fan art.
And then it's kind of hard.
Yeah, it's going to be hard to disentangle what you're judging on.
Just because they obviously like you can go and look at their pro art as well.
And I will say Geneva Bowers' pro art is beautiful.
I really like it.
But yeah, it's going to be complicated.
Interesting.
I would say that you may does something that I think is really good for professional artists to do.
and that does, I think, connect her more with fan art,
which is she has a bunch of tutorials on her site
showing people how she generates her,
the effects and the sorts of things that she does in her art.
And I think that is a really, really good thing for artists to be doing.
Oh, she's also a professional artist as well.
Again, I think primarily.
Yeah.
So next up, we have Best Fan Writer
and we have Jay Brantner for Tarvol,
Alex Brown, James Davis-Nickel,
rosanna pendlebury jason sanford and oyan weston congratulations rosanna yes we were really pleased
to see this so i think that is five repeat nominees and i think jay brantner for tarvel is new yes i
think he is yeah i mean i'm most excited about rosanna i think rosanna's fan writing is really
really great um oyan weston does the micro sff blog and it's interesting here because it's
interesting to me that jay brantner has had his blog called out in the list of finalists but oryan
hasn't because the vast majority of oryan's work is in micro sff um so i've linked in the show
listeners but i just find that interesting as a as a nerdy style thing no i i think people are they
ask when you accept your so behind the scenes when oryan asked for this last year he was told no
the only other person so i read jason samper's email newsletter he has massively pivoted to
talking about ai and i used to read his stuff for the genre news and and it seems like he has not
done much genre news recently um i don't know whether that's just a coincidence of like what's
been happening or what but i've enjoyed some of his previous kind of talking about sf fandom and
we've linked to him in the show notes before listeners james davis nickel is like an old hand
he was one of the finalists when I presented my Hugo Award
he coined a phrase once
listeners, and he's quite good
Alex Brown, I've never read any of their
long form stuff, but their
posts on Blue Sky are so
hot takey that I am not
inclined to go and do so
Yeah, I have read some
I think I have read some of their stuff on
Reactor, but yeah
I occasionally get them like
re-skeeted into my timeline on Blue Sky
and I was like, ooh, I disagree
with a lot of stuff here
yup
so but you know
they write stuff that I disagree with
that's also a form of fan writing
yeah yeah absolutely
fair enough
I've just got distracted
and gone down a big old rabbit hole
on Jay Bratless blog
so I think it's probably quite good
yay
having discovered it two minutes ago
this is why I love the nomination lists everyone
and those who were sceptical
that Alison would have read all the poems
this might be a reason why
because she probably would have got distracted
by something in one of the poems
and ended up on a fanzine blog being like,
I disagree with this article about battleships from 1976.
Hashtag only just unfair.
I wasn't actually going to suggest it was unfair at all.
All right.
Best fan cast.
The finalists are A Meal of Thorns,
Eating the Fantastic,
Hugo Girl,
Octothorpe,
That's Us.
Yay.
The Cooed Street Podcast and Worldbuilding for Masochists.
So, yes, this is a very good roster, I reckon.
And I'm not saying that because we're on it.
This is a great list full of some of my favourite podcasts.
And I think we've talked about every single one of these podcasts at some point.
So go listen to them all.
It's a very solid list and I look forward to losing to them all.
Yep.
And I'm not doing that out of a sense of false modesty.
I think we've all had pretty good years.
I listen to, I think, do I listen to all?
I listen to all of them semi-regularly,
apart from Worldbuilding for Masochist,
which is a bit on the writer-like tech side for me,
but I have listened occasionally.
And I also know that they have come very close to winning
two years in a row, and so I think it might be their year.
But on the other hand, Hugo, Girl are back.
Eating the Fantastic, I think, is a new nominee.
I think everyone else is a repeat nominee.
Obviously, Cooed Street are up to 700-ish episodes now,
so they've been around for a good long while
doing quality stuff.
Yeah.
I think this is the first time that Scott's been on the ballot.
I believe that's true.
And I think he's been doing great work with Eating the Fantastic,
and I'm not just saying that because he bought us lunch.
Yeah, so we have been on a recent episode of Eating the Fantastic.
Oh, is it out yet?
I don't think it is out yet, but look out for it, listeners,
and we'll link to it when it does come out.
But yeah.
It's a shame because it would be really funny to me if the episode,
which was current at the point he got Hugo nominated and everyone looking for it,
is you two having Nando's.
That would be great.
I don't think that's going to happen, but it would be great.
They often go to really nice restaurants and eat really good food.
Did you suggest going to a nice restaurant or did you suggest going to Nando's?
We suggested going to Nando's.
Well, there you go.
Yep.
I think this is a great thing.
And obviously, Transatlantic besties Hugo Girl.
I recently listened to their episode on the movie Battleship,
and it made me want to watch Battleship, so...
Wow, that is a strong effect.
Yep, you're not wrong.
But no, I mean, I like their mix.
I mean, we love them.
We love them, listeners.
We may not be entirely objective about some of the nominees.
We may not be, but that's all right.
The nominees for Best Fanzine are Ancillary Review of Books,
an unofficial Hugo Book Club blog,
Galactic Journey
Intergalactic Mixtape
Journey Planet
and Nerds of a Feather Flock Together
Yay!
Have all of those been nominees before?
Oh sorry, have all of those been finalists before?
I think Intergalactic Mixtape is new
Intergalactic Mixtape is new
and I think thoroughly deserved
That is great
Yes
Great to see Renee on there
Was one of my nominations?
Yes, me too
I think yeah these are all good good picks I think all of them do really interesting stuff in
different ways um and yeah congratulations to everyone and I don't know which one will win
I'm very pleased to see Galactic Journey back on here yes because they've had a couple of years
off I think and they've still been doing great work um the journey's I guess it's into the 70s now
is he going at a rate of a year per year yes 55 years behind okay cool that's good
So it's 55 years ago, all of the time, every day or every other day.
I think it posts every other day.
While we're here, I was just going to say, you know,
I think Ancinerary Review of Books have a Kickstarter,
which you can go and support.
I'm not sure if that Kickstarter will then make them a semi-prozine next year.
I think I supported that Kickstarter next episode.
Then we come to best semi-prozine.
we have escape pod creole magazine on spec the canadian magazine of the fantastic strange horizons
the deadlands and uncanny magazine yes there are some good people here beneath the seas the skies
received enough nominations to be a finalist but declined nomination and we've talked about that
on previous episodes listeners um on spec i believe is a new nominee on spec i think it's
on spec i did see a lot of discussion around on spec um definitely the unofficial hugo book club
blog were discussing it uh because it's their final year of eligibility because they have um
stopped publishing and so i think it was part of a push to get them a uh hugo nominee hugo finalist
position in their last year which you know seems well deserved they have been publishing for a long
time and it is nice to see new semi-prosines because there's not that it's not a category
are hundreds and hundreds of things that are eligible there's not that many semi-prozines
or at least not ones that i know about and so it's nice to see them uh new things get nominated
and also i mean it's possible there's a new semi-prozine imminently because if
locust funding goes badly enough maybe they'll bump back down a category
i think they would have to drop a lot on an infinite time scale all empires will fall
is the deadlands a new nominee or is that so the deadlands is not a new uh not a new nominee
it was nominated uh last year at least and they do have some interesting looking stuff
their latest issue uh has guest fiction editor vajra chandasekera oh known to listeners of this
podcast for writing great and weird novels yep so semi-prosing is basically the same as last year
except we have lost uh fire magazine and replaced it with on spec which is a shame because i do like
fire magazine yes um and they've only won once so i would not be sad to see them on there again but
on the other hand you know i do enjoy seeing things being shaken up a bit so yeah there you go unless
fire mag are now a pro zine which would be great for them but i don't think so okay so now we have
best professional artist and the finalists are lulu chen kelly chong dave kellett tran winn
john picascio and tom roberts john picascio is good at art don't know any of the others off the
top of my head um but going through it's notable that dave kellett writes sheldon comics and that's
interesting because everyone else it looks to me is a basically a book cover illustrator and then
you've got one comic artist in there and i yeah that's going to be hard to judge because they're
quite different types of art well that's the joy isn't it that is the joy very much of the opinion
that variety in this category is a joyful thing for everyone um but also it'll be hard to pick
um although perhaps not as hard as the next category do we have any other thoughts on pro
artist i mean the thing for pro artist is basically it's six people who all make beautiful art of
different kinds and i did a lot of it for me just comes down to like what art is to my personal
taste um i will say even if you don't know the name i suspect you've seen some of kelly chong's
book covers uh they do covers for uh there's a novel called fathom folk by eliza chan
and one called Tales of Celestial Kingdom by Su Lin Tan,
which I think are both fantasy novels,
which have a pretty distinctive cover style, which I like.
And if that's your thing,
then I think you will be looking to put them high on a ballot.
And if it's not, then maybe not.
That went a bit rambly at the end.
I'll let you trim it entirely if it's boring.
But basically, their stuff looks nice.
Yeah, no, I mean, I think...
Yeah, the art's always absolutely amazing in this category, so...
Lulu Chen's stuff looks adorable.
Yeah.
And there's some animation, which is delightful.
Little cartoon breads.
Yay.
So I think what's interesting is,
I think there are five nominees in this category
who weren't on the ballot last year.
And indeed, I think most of them have never been on the ballot.
I think it is possibly four new nominees,
plus John Pekasho, who's been nominated multiple times before,
and Tran Nguyen, who was there in 2025.
So that's very interesting.
that makes sense because i have not i don't think i've seen any of the others on the on the ballot
and i should have connected that with new people um but yeah no that is that is very encouraging
right that's cool i have found tom roberts page and this stuff is fantastic i've so i've put a
link in the show notes listeners tom roberts is not the british artist who died in the 1930s it is a
different one true fact i've i've got his instagram which i think is great because it shows both the
art and the books i've tried to put links in the show notes um for all the categories uh listeners
let me know if i have got the wrong person in any category because i'm doing this based on
my googling not on the communication from lacon so any errors are my own and please feel free to
correct them so in best editor long form we have carl engle led jamie goe lee harris jenny hill
joe monte and diana info lindsey hall refused nomination so they did not appear on the ballot
i guess my question in this category is always which books did they edit i need to know which
books they edited to really get a take here i would love a little list of books edited in 2025
and previously any of those editors want to provide that would be cool i think it is four
repeat nominees including uh last year's uh winner diana foe and notable i think that uh
jenny hill is an editor at orbit in the uk and you know they've been publishing some good stuff
and jamie go i think is also a new uh a new uh name on the list jenny hill notably is uh the
person who edited ancillary justice oh okay cool yeah it's one of the very that was one of the very
early uh works i think so yeah nice to see because i think sometimes you get a lot from sort of the
big us lists and not so many from the uk one so it's nice to see a bit of uk rep on there
about all i have to say i don't have anything to say because i don't know what these people
edited and I don't know the impact that their edits had on the works so yeah I probably won't
rank any in this category because I just I just as always feel completely completely ill-equipped
to actually judge in a informed way yeah you really sort of the only way you can judge really
is kind of on did they acquire stuff I liked Joe Monty is the editorial director of Saga Press
there's a list of authors there one of the things I found interesting when Patrick Nilton Hayden was
nominated in the recent past was he wrote in the thing like in his packet submission he was like
obviously i'm like a commissioning editor for tor but like the books i actually had an impact on was
this list and i think that's tricky right because obviously the commissioning editor does have a lot
of control over like a publisher's output but is that what we're judging i don't know what this
categories for if i i don't know i just have grumpy things to say about how this category doesn't really
make any sense to me which is not particularly fun for the listener i'm sure sorry listener let's move
on best editor short form we have scott h andrews jennifer brozek neil clark lee harris michael
damien thomas and sheila williams this is a bit easier to judge because a lot of these people
are editing magazines and you can kind of see the impact more but the thing i wanted to pull out was
I find it interesting that it's not the Thomas's.
It's just Michael, Damien Thomas.
And I think previously they've often been nominated as a pair.
Yes.
Now let me check, but I think this is because he is now solo editing Uncanny.
Oh, interesting.
That is interesting.
I did not know that.
Yeah, that's why.
Yes.
Otherwise, I think these are all previous nominees.
Five of the six were finalists last year, including last year's winner, Neil Clark.
All right.
Best game or interactive work.
The finalists are Blue Prince, Citizen Sleeper 2, Starwood Vector, Claire Obscure, Expedition 33, Dispatch, Hades 2, and Hollow Knight, Silksong.
I mean, it's a good list.
It's notable that there's no tabletop games in there.
One day, listeners, one day.
You tried, John, you tried.
I did.
I have not actually played any of these yet, but I have played quite a few of the prequels to these.
So Hades I thought was good and it won a Hugo Award, listeners.
Hollow Knight, I don't like Hollow Knight.
I can't imagine Silksong is going to be the game that I think, yeah, no.
I got stuck on Hollow Knight quite early on in the game.
I believe they have an easier setting, but I'm proud.
I know that's daft, isn't it?
But I feel like the structure of the game isn't quite what I'm looking for in games.
I love blueprints I expect to like Hades 2 I can't play Clare Obscure because it's not on a platform
I have and I'm looking forward to playing both of the other two which I hadn't previously heard of
before reading this list yeah there's two there's two I've never heard of I've never heard of Citizen
Sleeper 2 or Dispatch or I think I've vaguely heard of Dispatch but I haven't played it
Citizen Sleeper is a game that Hogg put me onto and that is the game I'm most excited about on this
list because it is inspired directly by tabletop role-playing games and it's set in a sort of
futuristic cyberpunk setting uh and i own it and it looks incredibly like my bullshit les
highly aligned with john interests oh so that's quite close to tabletop i think they're planning
to do a tabletop spin-off of it but what i do what i will link in the show notes is that
quinn's quest did an actual play role playing in the world of citizen sleeper with the developer
which quinn said was quite daunting because yeah it turns out if you run a ttrpg with the person
who invented the world you're running it in that it's playing on hard mode um but i'll put a link
in the show notes um but i'm excited about that one i mean i i played brewpints and liked it hades
i liked uh again like allison i played hollow knight for some hours and then was like no i'm
not going to like carrying on with this am I? I just stopped. I would like to play Claire Obscure
but it sounds like narratively I would enjoy it but I'm not sure I would enjoy the gameplay style
and that's why I have been putting off tackling it and I just bought Hades 2 so that's going to keep
me going for some time with games. I'd be playing Hades 2 right now were it not for the fact that
my life has been completely derailed by Slay the Spar 2. Oh I thought there was going to be a sad
thing about your life having been completely derailed by something and then it's like no it's
been derailed by another game okay that that was the effect i was going for so though i've been
i've been destroyed by a 2026 video game or possibly a 2027 video game because it's an early access
yeah so hades is only i think officially released very recently and so it's basically been nominated
on the basis of its early access to i don't think it's been early access i mean i think it's 2025
game well this is gonna be interesting when when do you count the release date right because case
could have been in early access for about 11 years okay so the thing is it came out in 2025
on the switch but it's only just been officially released on playstation and xbox so that's why i
have just started it dispatch looks cool i've not i know rosanna loves claire obscure i know there
was controversy over Claire Obscure um I my my main thing looking at pictures of Claire Obscure
is that it looks very brown and I tend not to enjoy very brown games um but maybe that is
reductive but the website is incredibly brown I watched some let's play and it looked interesting
enough that I stopped watching because I think I might like to play it at some point but basically
the the kind of RPG combat style yeah not sure I will enjoy but then there's probably like an easy
stick it on and play for the story it looked quite french to me i enjoyed that dispatch um looks
amazing it is a superhero workplace comedy i'm down oh that does sound amazing in general i usually
find that the game i really glom onto is the game that everyone else is kind of not talking about so
i confidently anticipate that will be the same again now it's it seems so implausible that a
game's going to supplant blueprints in my affections for 2025 but it's possible fair yeah solid solid
picks you your voters thank you it's so nice to see this category kind of i think going from
strength to strength after all the time it took to get it you know into the list i feel like that's
a bit like that with poem because i think we're getting you know i think we're getting a good
slated poem there's no kind of sense of oh there's not enough poetry to fill it up you haven't read
any of them though shush you can't call it a good category that you haven't read any of i think i
you need to readily swarm i think i will say that both poem and game look healthier than a category
we'll get to in a minute maybe more than one category it is still sad that it seems to have
become a video game but i also like video games they're all right so in best dramatic presentation
short form we have doctor who the story and the engine murder bot all systems red murder bot the
Perimeter, Pluribus, We Is Us, Severance, Cold Harbour, The Wheel of Time, The Road to the Spear.
So these are six episodes of television shows.
They are.
And I've watched one.
So I think I've watched four.
Murderbot is really good.
I have to wonder whether the Worldcon fandom's known affection for Murderbot is going to mean
that that is the winner.
because, well, we do love Murderbot.
It has won a lot of Hugo Awards in written form,
and I wonder whether that will kind of continue over to dramatic presentation.
I think Cold Harbour was a work of absolute.
Like, it was a masterpiece. Severance is great.
The one I think should win in this category is Severance.
We as Us is good.
I think it's a very effective first episode.
I am not convinced the rest of the show lives up to the promise of the first episode.
And it's generally not common that a first episode is the one that gets the Hugo nod.
So I think the uneven nature of Pluribus as a show is probably highlighted by the fact that's happened.
I've not watched any Wheel of Time, so I can't comment on that.
I have watched some of season two of Doctor Who.
And it must get a lot better after those early episodes if it's on this list.
Because good grief, season two does not start well.
Wait, how are we numbering Doctor Who?
Or season whatever it is, but season two of Tuties.
Season 77.
I believe a lot of the online...
No, I genuinely don't know anymore.
No, a lot of the online sources do label it as season two.
So, for instance, I think IMDb lists this as season two of Doctor Who 2025 because it was soft rebooted.
But, yeah.
Okay.
Wow.
I am several years behind with Doctor Who.
And I don't really mean behind.
I mean, I just don't watch it at the moment.
But lots of people do.
And it's still getting things.
I bounced off Murderbot, but people do seem to like it a lot.
So I might pick it up.
I don't think Pluribus is uneven.
I think it's doing exactly what Vince Gilligan wants to do with it,
which is not what a lot of viewers would like him to be doing with it.
I think I agree with Abigail Nussbaum,
which is basically he is not taking the concept as far as he should have been.
And he's squandering a lot of the potential of the concept from the beginning
by not actually exploring the science fiction enough.
But I think if you're not as interested in the science fiction,
it might be a lot better.
I think the science fiction is background to what he's wanting to do with this, which is the study of the character.
And I think that's a fine thing to do.
But I think it's not surprising that most of the science fiction fans would like him to be leaning into that a bit more.
I think I would agree with you that although I haven't seen The Wheel of Time or The Doctor Who,
I think that Cold Harbour is an absolutely splendid piece of television.
And you do have to watch all the rest for it to make any sense, probably.
Which does beg the question of what is short form for.
But oh God, it's a great show.
It's a great episode of a show.
It's so good.
That will have my vote.
It's the only one I've seen so far.
So I'll probably vote for it.
So it'll have your vote too.
Yeah, I mean, I've just got back on Apple TV.
So I've got some stuff to catch up on.
I think it is notable that there's a lot of representation here for Apple, right?
All apart from Wheel of Time and Doctor Who.
I was about to say four out of six for Apple TV,
A streaming service which apparently nobody in Britain has.
Though obviously John and I do.
But, you know, some people in Britain have.
I think quite a lot of people have it.
But maybe I'm wrong.
But, yeah.
I mean, it's just really good.
Like, it's definitely where the best science fiction is being made at the moment.
So it would have been weird if it wasn't dominating.
Like, because, yeah.
Because they have half a dozen very interesting science fiction shows that are not on here.
Maybe more.
Yeah, if you're not subscribed to Apple TV as an SF fan,
that is a choice.
It's a perfectly defensible choice.
It just means you're missing out on a lot of cool stuff.
If you're not subscribed to Apple Everything,
report to me for indoctrination.
Ha ha!
I was very sceptical of Apple TV when they announced they were doing it,
and that scepticism has largely proved to have been unfounded,
because I think they've been doing smashing work.
And like I said, I did not expect them to.
Because Vince Gilligan, basically, if Vince Gilligan has a new TV show,
he could basically go anywhere and people are going to say,
yes, here, have some money.
And obviously he went to Apple TV,
maybe just because they offered the most money,
but presumably he had faith that they would give him lots of time
to do what he wanted to do,
given they don't do that many shows
and tend to keep them around for a while.
Sorry, I mean, surely it's that he went to Apple TV and said,
would you mind if I spent several months in the Canary Islands
filming aerial shots for fun.
But I think Liz is right
that Netflix would have also said yes to that.
Yeah, but Netflix might have come back
in a year's time and said,
well, we're not so sure about this.
Can you wrap it up in one more season?
The new rule about having not too many episodes
of a show on the ballot
means that the third Murderbot episode,
Free Commerce, which had enough nominations,
did not make it onto the finalist roster.
And then we have best dramatic presentation,
Longform,
and finalists are Andor Season 2,
Frankenstein,
K-pop Demon Hunters,
Mickey 17,
Sinners,
and Superman.
I've seen all but one.
Which one have you not seen?
I have not seen Frankenstein.
I confidently predict Frankenstein will not be my favourite,
but I will watch it and report back.
I do like Yoma de Toro though.
I have seen four of these.
I've not seen Frankenstein and I've also not seen Superman.
So you can tell me what you think of it, you two.
Superman's fucking great.
It's good.
It's going to be a really hard choice between Sinners and Andor Season 2 for me
because I think they're both great and they do totally different things.
That was what I was going to say.
I strongly suspect the winner in this category will either be Sinners or K-pop Demon Hunters.
And so I think the thing you really have to decide is,
are you on the Sinners train or the K-pop Demon Hunters train?
Well, I'm on the single transferable vote train, so.
Yes, but I don't think there's any chance of Andor winning.
Oh, I do.
I'm with Liz on it'll be Andor or Sinners.
I think K-pop Demon Hunters will probably be third after those two.
And I think I will watch Frankenstein, Superman and Mickey 17 is fun but flawed.
I think both K-pop Demon Hunters and Mickey 17 were picks of mine on this very podcast.
And they both have things I liked very much about them and things that are not quite so great.
I think the most interesting film on this list in some ways is Mickey 17 in what it tries to do, but I agree that it doesn't necessarily nail it.
I think I'm going to say something about the internationalization of global cinema now and the way that it's got a lot of a lot more international influences than it used to.
I think this is a very interesting list that you would not have seen as the Hugo dramatic presentation list 20 years ago.
all right i'll bite why not you know so both um both mickey 17 and k-pop dean and hunters are
essentially korean movies made in america with american money sinners of course is is a hugely
ambitious movie by a black director and with a largely black cast um and that is also is also
music is very woven through sinners if you haven't seen it it's not just about it's not just a
fantasy movie it is also a movie about a lot of other things as well including the way that music
shaped the american south and or is the most interesting i mean and or season two is a great
example of an extremely good bit of science fiction television that was not on apple tv last year
and is you know it's incredibly interesting and literate science fiction and as i said haven't
seen Frankenstein but it's Guillermo del Toro so it's going to be it's going to be out there isn't
it I think Superman's the most likely one to have been on a list 20 years ago and I think I think I
understand that this is this is a reboot this is rebooting the franchise in an interesting way
I think I'm gonna say I'm not sure that an American studio hiring a South Korean person
means that it's a Korean movie in much the same way that I'm not sure that if they'd hired a
british director it would be a british movie 20 years ago or well 2007 i was gonna say guillermo
del toro one for pan's labyrinth guillermo del toro one for pan's labyrinth and the other ones
were children of men the prestige of scanner darkly a v for vendetta so it's not like i mean children
of men is alfonso cuarón right which is as not american as mickey 17 i knew i knew you'd call me
on that this is what the problem with doing hot takes right you're probably right that there's
some influences from internationalization i need to respond to your hot take first because i disagree
with your hot take which is i don't think this is a hugo audience changing i think this is
long for media changing netflix emak sorry that was the point i was trying to make okay in which
case i think hugo voters voting for things that were popular productions by big mainstream studios
is not a particularly hot take.
Okay, so some of my hot takes are bad.
Who knew?
I mean, I think it's much more out there
that like last year we got,
I saw the TV Glow,
which is a small budget film on there,
along with, you know, Flow,
which was a big hit,
but from a non-US studio.
You know, in previous years,
we've had stuff like The Wandering Earth.
Yeah, God, that was terrible.
You know, Space Sweepers,
which is a Korean film.
Okay, can I try a different take?
yes take two it's a good is a good one there's two there's at least two films on this list where
one actor plays two or more roles yep superman clark kent and superman three then
but do they appear on screen at the same time i knew for sure that wasn't what you meant and i
was like i've got to do it um but yes no fair enough no good point good point see that's heart
take you can have because it doesn't make me feel strongly about it yeah yeah i'm allowed that one
am I? Approved.
And one of them won the Oscar
for Best Actor and one of them did not.
Yes, no, that's fair.
Or so fair. I don't think
Mickey 17 troubled the Oscars very much.
So, best related work. We have
Colourfields, Writing About Writing
About Science Fiction by Paul Kincaid,
which is a book. Inventing the Renaissance,
The Myth of a Golden Age by Ada Palmer,
which is a book. Last War
in Albion, The Cuddled Little Vice
open brackets, Sandman, close brackets
by Elizabeth Sandifer, which is an essay.
Positive Obsession, The Life and Times of Octavia Butler
by Susanna M. Morris, which is a book.
History of Westeros, Ragnarok vs. The Long Night,
which is a podcast episode.
And The Hugo Spreadsheet of Doom,
maintained by Renée, which is a Google Sheet.
So three books, one essay, one podcast, and one spreadsheet.
I have a hot take here.
Aha. Go for it.
So Inventing the Renaissance by Ada Palmer
is one of the very best books I read last year.
It is absolutely not genre related.
If that is eligible in best related work,
then literally everything ever is eligible in best related work.
And the Hugo eligibility checkers should have called this and said,
you're what?
And even if they didn't, Ada should have turned down the nomination and said,
I'm so proud that you thought I was a great person and should be on the ballot.
And this is a fantastic book, but it's not related to the field of genre,
of science fiction or fantasy, except in that a science fiction author wrote it.
That is certainly a take.
And you should put it below no awards, all of you,
despite the fact this is a brilliant book and you should also all read it.
I mean, I think it's clear that best related work in the minds of the few voters
is a category into which you put all the stuff that we like that doesn't fit into another category.
All the genre related stuff we like that doesn't fit in another category.
Otherwise, I'm nominating cricket next year.
But I think it has become just things which are peripherally related to the genre.
And therefore, the fact that Ada Palmer is a genre author makes it related.
I'm not saying I nominated it.
I'm saying this is what people feel.
I think the category is broken.
But I also don't think we'd improve the category by saying everyone who nominated this book,
we don't think it's sufficiently science fictional related to the genre.
And so we are throwing out.
I don't know if you want the Hugo admins to go down that road.
Yes, I really do.
If something has no connection,
the category definition requires it to be related to the field.
If it has no connection apart from somebody
who has also written science fiction wrote it,
it's not connected to the field.
I mean, I get that.
I'm just saying, do you really want the Hugo admins
to act in a completely different way
than they have done for many years
by overriding the will of the voters?
It is tricky. It is tricky.
Because you can when it's as cut and dried as this.
They do. Well, I mean, they do.
If a novel's too short or something, they would.
Yeah, but that's something where I can actually say this novel is too short.
It's a novella. It goes in a different category.
Yeah. So here you can say it's a nonfiction book about a historical period.
Unless I've missed some elves in it somewhere.
And if someone says, but I won, they'll have to read all the nominated books and then make a judgment call on whether they thought they were related or not.
I just think, you know, length of a book is a thing that can be measured.
Genreness of a book is not a thing that I can measure, you know, on a binary scale.
Okay, apparently it's just me.
Well, I don't think it will just be you.
And I'm not saying that I think it's a great nominee.
I mean, I haven't read it.
If it really does have no connection to the genre, then it's just someone in the genre wrote an interesting nonfiction book we want to reward.
And we've got other nonfiction books that I'm happy to reward on the list.
But I also don't think it's a good idea to go down the route of the Hugo admins.
Get to make those determinations.
And the other thing is that you don't want different administrators to be differently specific about it.
So like A City on Mars is about space travel and won the Hugo for Best Related Work.
And I argued it should be eligible because it's about space travel.
But like, it's difficult to argue that it's about science fiction.
And so like, should that have been disqualified?
And like, you can go back and you can find other things as well.
And it's like, I don't know.
It's hard.
I take, basically, I take Liz's point.
I also take Alison's point.
I probably will not vote for this work because it isn't related to the genre.
And I don't think it should win.
But if a lot of the voters do think it should be on the list, it's hard.
It is hard.
Hugo does generally respect the will of the voters more than the will of the administrator.
You have just argued in quite a good way against my point, and I'm going to slightly expand
therefore.
A City on Mars is genre related not merely because it provides, because it's about space
travel and space travel seems to get a kind of bonus entry into science fiction discussions,
even when it's real life space travel. But it's also a piece of work that underlies world building
in science fiction and fantasy, because it would be a good book to read if you were thinking about
writing in that genre as part of your backstory. And you could argue the same for inventing the
renaissance because um the renaissance is i can tell you a foundational text for much fantasy
world building no that's actually really because i was gonna and i was also gonna i was debating
whether or not to go down that road um i think i think that is a another potential avenue of
argument right which is if you look at a world and you critically evaluate it does that have an sf
place purely based on the world building reading it's hard and i think that the key thing is it's
hard right i think that's the thing if you've got like the hugo nominees nominating this do you
countermand them or not i think is a very difficult decision world building for masochists please
write in or do an episode on it that would be interesting that would be interesting yeah i think
that's exactly right and you've just basically made the argument that shows probably why we should
not be letting the admin have all the discretion here because maybe they were like uh i like to
sit on mars you know one year we allow a city on mars in on the basis that it maybe contributes to
world building and one year we don't then you get into very kind of tricky waters i think oh i mean
do you want to jump jump more hot takes on best related work yes yes yes i mean i love i love
spreadsheets she fucking loves them listeners you know how much i love spreadsheets yep but i think
i like it better when the hugos don't get too self-referential and i think nominating the
spreadsheet where we put the things that we nominate for hugos is on the wrong side of that
line perhaps yeah i mean there's loads of other good stuff in this category that i will have either
have read or will read and listen to and you know make my vote accordingly um but i just find it very
like let's not get too much into that i mean there's also a poem which is like from the seattle
world con right haven't read the poem might be great but i think we're getting a bit
self-referential like when we nominated the hugo ceremony as a dramatic presentation i think on the
subject of the poem from the opening ceremony i assumed that that was their poet laureate yeah it
is if a world con guest of honor did a reading from a book at a world con and then that got
nominated like if they're the poet laureate they're probably quite good at poet oh yeah it'll definitely
i mean it'd be a good poem i that doesn't strike me as self-referential in the same way i guess is
is my point although i i take the point it might not be good for the broader health of the category
if one of the things is the thing everyone saw because they were at the world con because i
think that's what's happening in the uh category that i'm going to moan about next yeah i mean as
far as I as far as I can tell on very short notice I can't find this poem online and so it must be
people who saw it at Seattle which I guess is not unexpected but I'm not I'm not as bothered about
that one I just use it as kind of another example of let's try and stay on the other side of the
line and I I do like the Hugo spreadsheet of doom a lot and I think Rene does good stuff but I think
intergalactic mixtape is the really good thing that they got nominated for I'm very happy with that
Yeah, I think I would agree with that.
I mean, I respect the fact that the Hugo Spreadsheet of Doom has been a bunch of work over a lot of years.
And in some ways, it's quite nice to see some things like that creeping onto the ballot.
But I agree that it is quite self-referential.
Can I say something really, really nice about one of the other nominees here, which I have not read?
Yes.
Which is that...
You can say something nice about Paul Kincaid.
I want to say nice things about Paul Kincaid, but I want to say I was pleased to see Colorfields writing about writing about science fiction by Paul Kincaid.
And I think it is an interesting topic for a book.
And I think it is an interesting book, which I have not actually read, but I do own, of course, because I own everything that has so far been published by Briardine Books.
I just want to say it's nice to see them getting on the ballot.
And I'm loving that these very interesting British critical works are getting traction and getting onto the Hugo ballot.
I think it's great.
And they're also beautifully designed and also, I think, very well copy edited by John.
Is that right, John?
I don't do the copy editing.
I do the typesetting.
Typesetting.
Yeah, but they are beautiful.
So as well as everything else, they are lovely books.
And I'm just so glad that Bradine Press exists and that Neil is doing this work.
So good.
And I think that kind of gets to my slight unease with the spreadsheet, which is I'm glad it gets recognized.
But there's so little room for thoughtful criticism in our field that I don't want to take energy away from the spaces where we can recognize it.
and so I would prefer a critical work one in this category I think yeah I mean that's there's
basically one spot on the Hugo ballot where you can put critical works and this is it and it's
basically the category for critical works and also a lot of other stuff and I don't think we're going
to ever shift it back you know we're not going to shift it back to being just critical works but I
think it is nice to see some substantial critical stuff being recognized like last year's winner
which was the speculative whiteness science fiction of the alt-right by Jordan Carroll
that was also up against like a very wide selection of stuff and did really well I think
I think this is Paul Kincaid's third best related work nomination she's pretty solid
at least four of these six are critical works not necessarily about science fiction
yes I don't know about history of Westeros Ragnarok versus The Long Night but my guess is that's
probably also a critical work um and i'll listen to it sometime quite soon and if it's not i'll come
back and say oh it turns out not to be i believe it is a um the description of the podcast says it
is a deep dive into prophecy and cataclysm using both science and mythology all wrapped in a song
of ice and fire package so kind of comparing comparing different mythologies about ragnarok
similar events with mythical no sorry fictional treatments of those themes so yeah yes it looks
interesting so but yes I if I had if I was designing the Hugos I might ditch one of the
existing categories and make space for a best critical work category which I think we should
absolutely have but I would I wouldn't require it to be a book obviously podcasts and extremely long
essays on the internet also seem fine to me our next category is best graphic story or comic
and the finalists are absolute wonder woman volume one the last amazon a girl and her fed a wizard
of earth see a graphic novel the invisible parade the power fantasy volume one and the space cat
power fantasy is excellent um kieran gillen is great uh highly recommend that to everyone
two of these are on the ballot because they are sf that's been done as comics which is the wizard
of earth sea and the space cat um and they might be amazing but i'm skeptical that they were the
best graphic story or comic released in 2025 and then i've not read the invisible parade or a girl
and her fed or absolute wonder woman volume one um but uh i do know that the absolute i read absolute
hunter and that was great so i am excited to read wonder woman but this basically is my main
criticism of this category is unlike game and unlike seemingly poem this does not seem to be
in conversation with the wider world of comics at all it seems to be an extremely narrow view of
what good comics that are and i don't think the hugo electorate is well suited to this category
that's my hot take here i was looking at that and thinking well some of these are adaptations and
Some of them are original.
And I look at Best Dramatic Presentation Shortform,
where my two favourites in this category are the two original works of science fiction.
And I am much less happy with Murderbot.
And I haven't even looked at The Wheel of Time.
Doctor Who's obviously original IP as well.
What about Mickey 17?
I was looking at Shortform.
In Longform, indeed, we have, I guess, Frankenstein, Mickey 17, Superman adaptations.
Yeah, I'm just not sure.
Okay, I'm not sure what point you were making about the adaptations.
No, I think it's just, well, it's established that in dramatic presentation,
you're always going to get a mix of original IP and adaptations.
And so you therefore expect that in graphic stories as well.
So it doesn't seem surprising to me that we're seeing those things.
But I think I'd agree with John that I don't normally expect that to be where I look for excellence in graphic novels.
I tend to think that that's where the excellence starts and then they get adapted to other forms later.
Is that reasonable?
Yes.
And I think basically it's like, how would it be if best novel was half movie novelisations and half original works would be the parallel I would draw.
are harder to make and there is a much bigger culture of adapting known quantities that it is
thought are popular and will work it might be it might be that i am just being a curmudgeon
i am just i'm just continually unsure that graphic story is a particularly exciting
category of the hugos but maybe maybe i am being a big old grump listeners write in i mean i think
the main thing i would say is i look at the list and i'm not feeling super excited about it i read
the power fantasy it's great um i think it may be the one that i think kieran gillen's never won the
hugo but been nominated multiple times and i think this might be the one that gets it for him yeah
hopefully i hope so because it is really good yeah i mean i've got no complaints about star trek
lower decks won't be wrong winning last year well that's actually a really good point right because
that is an adaptation that was phenomenal um as ed i think it was ed morland who put it saying
sometimes there's a nominee which just which is just isn't ursula k leguin good and it's like yes
but is that notable in the way we want it to be notable yeah no i think that's fair i also i'm not
i should read more graphic novels because i love them i don't know what's wrong with me really
i mean i do know what's wrong with me right and instead of focusing on what's wrong with alison
shall we move to best series yes the best series the finalists are emily wilde by heather forcett
october day by shauna maguire old man's war by john scalsey the chronicles of osreth by katherine
addison the craft wars by max gladstone and white space by elizabeth bear i don't think i've read
any of the recent books in any of these series i've read books in the october day and old man's
war series from way back when um but the others well i read an early catherine addison which might
be part of this series i can't remember is the goblin emperor part of this series yeah the goblin
emperor is considered the first of these series but i feel like the series has gone in a slightly
different direction since then yeah you can include that i mean that was a phenomenal book so i'm
looking forward to reading more of that series i am not quite up to date in this series but
this leaps off the page at me as the one series here that I am fond of and follow and would expect
to read all of or all of until I get tired of it which does happen to me with series.
Max Glanston I have heard very very good things I have not actually read any of his stuff but I
have friends who think he is really really good so I am also curious about that one. Old Man's War
I liked when I was little but I don't know if I still like it now we will see and I've not read
anything i've not read any of the emily wilde or white space at all and i don't know anything i
mean i've read some of the craft sequence and enjoy it i haven't read the uh latest ones um i
think sorry i'm gonna have to go and get the best series hugo page up which i'm remiss because i
think max gladson has been nominated before yes so the craft sequence was nominated in 2017
and now has enough volumes to be re-nominated.
October Day was nominated 2017, 2019, 2021, 2023 and 2024.
So it is astonishing that, you know,
for a category where you have to do so much to get another nomination,
it is putting out at such volume that it's had like six previous nominations.
I feel like Seanan McGuire and Adrian Tchaikovsky
should have a volume off competition.
in best series there are two works that received enough votes to qualify for the ballot but were
found to be ineligible they were the lady astronaut series by mary robinette koal which had fewer than
the required number of new words since its last appearance and the singing hill cycle by nevo
which still has not got enough words to be a series there might need to be an addendum to the
best series category which says something like or six individual volumes because it does seem stupid
that a series of six novellas doesn't count as a series and it would be a relatively minor tweak
but yes poor nevo because they're also not this is spoilers but they're not in best novella this
year either best short story the finalists were 10 visions of the future or self-care for the end
of days by samantha mills in my country by thomas ha laser eyes ain't everything by effie seberg
Missing Helen by Tia Tashiro
Six People to Revise You by J.R. Dawson
and Wire Mother by Isabel J. Kim
I look forward to reading them when the packet comes out
Yes
I've read two of them
Did you enjoy them?
Yes
I think they were probably on the Locust Recommended Leading list
which is where I get a lot of my short fiction reading
generally done in a hurry shortly before the close of Hugo nominations
I read In My Country by Thomas Haar
which is about a country it's about a repressive a repressive country and a man and his son and
i don't really want to spoil it and it's hard to kind of hard to describe but it's like stylistically
i think is a good read and why a mother by isabel j kim is a short story where you know her mother
is like an AI
or there is an AI
who is one of her parents
and yeah,
I can't remember
all the exact details of them
but I did also enjoy that
and it's about a teenager
working through issues
with her parents
but one of her parents
happened to be a simulation.
Yeah, I think it's a good list.
I mean, I've read other stuff
by Isabel Kim and Thomas Haar
and really enjoyed them
and Samantha Mills wrote
Rabbit Test,
which won a few years ago.
Good list.
Yeah.
All right.
So in Best Novelette,
we have Kaiju Agonistas
by Scott Lynch, Never Eaten Vegetables by H.H. Pack, Rapport, Friendship, Solidarity, Communion,
Empathy by Martha Wells, The Girl That My Mother Is Leaving Me For by Cameron Reed,
The Millay Illusion by Sarah Pinsker, and When He Calls Your Name by Catherine M. Valente.
I've not read any of these, but I've heard of several of the authors and they're good.
Is the Wells a murder bot? I honestly don't know, I haven't read it.
Great question.
Yes, it's about, there's a ship in one of the Murderbot novellas called Perihelion, right?
And it's about that ship.
Oh, I see.
So it's kind of Murderbot adjacent?
Yes.
I have read Kaiju Agonistes by Scott Lynch, which is...
Ooh.
It's a bit Godzilla minus one in that you have essentially the idea that Kaiju are sort of planted on planets by a galactic civilization in order to sit there and try and like prevent them destroying themselves with nuclear weapons.
Nice.
And I think it is quite fun.
I think it is a little bit long.
I don't think it's like quite as it's not quite as kind of I don't know.
It's hard to kind of do this sort of satirical thing, I think, at the length it's doing it
and maybe should have been a little bit shorter.
But I did enjoy it and it feels a bit different to other stuff I've read.
And it's got a kaiju in.
Nice.
That is the only one I've read of the novelettes so far.
I'm very excited to see novelettes by Cameron Reed and Sarah Pinsker here,
who are two of my favourite current authors.
Yeah.
Spoiler, I'm about to pick a novel by Cameron Weed next week.
For you, Dory.
Next episode.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, she has retrospectively already picked it as a thing
because of timey-wimey.
Timey-wimey.
Okay.
Best novella.
The finalists are Automatic Noodle by Anneli Newitz,
Cinder House by Freya Mask,
Murder by Memory by Olivia Waite,
The River Has Roots by Amal El-Motar,
The Summer War by Naomi Novik,
and What Starts the Deep by T. Kingfisher.
Again, these are good authors.
I've not read any of the books.
but I've heard of several of the authors.
I picked The Summer War.
I was going to say I thought Liz picked The Summer War here,
so we've talked about it before.
I did.
I thought it was a perfectly solid fantasy novella from Naomi Novik,
you know, in her usual great style.
Yeah.
I do have The River Have Roots.
I just haven't read it yet.
What Stalks the Deep is another of T. Kingfish's novella
in the ongoing series of kind of horror that was previously nominated.
I don't think they're my favourite T. Kingfishers, but...
No, that's fair.
That's the thing with someone who writes, like, multiple different ongoing series.
It's like sometimes I have, like, more favourites and less favourites.
And so, yeah, the previous one was nominated What Feast at Night.
This is, in fact, T. Kingfishers' fourth consecutive nomination in Best of Ella.
It's pretty good.
Nice.
Well done, T. Kingfisher.
She's very good.
Yeah.
Amal Elmortar won in 2020.
It's back on the balance.
Is this Olivia Waite's first Hugo nomination?
I don't know.
Might be.
I've not heard.
That's the one name I didn't know off this list.
Because Freya Mask was in Best Series previously.
And Anna Lee Newitz has won for Best Fancast, among other things, in previous years.
I'm getting beating us for Best Fancast, right?
Etched on my memory, Liz.
Oh, I have read a book by Olivia Waite.
I thought the notes sounded familiar.
uh yes i read a book called the lady's guide to celestial mechanics which is a romance novel
about science really oh i like science i read it a while ago it's it's about six years old now
it's two about two ladies who end up collaborating on a sort of uh research project and uh things
spark nice i read one of other books possibly but i think i know i'm mainly as sort of a more
straightforward romance novelist um and this is a science fictional romance novella murder by memory
becky chamber meets miss marple in this sci-fi ode to the cozy mystery oh so some people are
obviously going to like this very much.
Well, I liked
Lady's Guide to Celestial Mechanics, so
I expect to like it. Sounds intriguing.
But it's also...
Is there like a trend for like
sci-fi mystery novels
on sort of interstellar spaceships?
Well, they're locked rooms,
aren't they? It's obviously a great location
for your mystery novel. I'm down.
Yeah. Yeah, but why is everyone suddenly
putting them in space? I think because space
is cool, Liz.
Perfect for fans of the plot twisty
of Dorothy Sayers and Al Leckie,
two authors who are not previously put into the same sentence.
It is.
I mean, it's a fun micro-genre because it could be good.
Gonna put it in the same box as alternate universe coffee shops.
Ooh.
You are very saucy today about some genres.
About micro-genres, yeah.
I mean, I'm reasonably saucy about this
because I remember that we had to read The Spare Man
back when it was hugo nominee and i did not like it much at all this is in that the same genre as
that book yes yeah but i also read you've got to give me a minute to look up the name of the book
i read that i did like in this genre that's the problem what's the one by the woman who does that
thing with emily tesh rebecca framo yeah um lady's last con yeah yes that's the one so that was much
better yes which i did like this micro genre yeah well what's it there was something else in i don't
really think lady eve's glass con was in this micro genre but perhaps i'm drawing the micro
genre too closely or maybe you're doing that thing where you go oh but this one was good so therefore
it's not in the micro genre in the same way that people do with their serve oh i preferred i preferred
the koal that you guys didn't like to the frame oh i liked the frame oh but i thought it was
insubstantial oh i thought these were these are both i mean this is basically like is candy floss
lighter or heavier than blamange i think that the actual the actual cozy mystery i think i would
compare it to is i know where this is going the tainted cup oh that's not where i thought it was
going which is definitely a cozy mystery because there's no point at any point where you doubt that
they're gonna do it because it's sherlock holmes oh no that's fair okay sherlock holmes is the og
cosy mystery book series.
Oh, well, I mean, in that case,
Dorothy L. Sayers is in there,
but Anne Leckie?
I mean, Dorothy L. Sayers,
I mean, you know, I mean...
Well, Anne Leckie does do
twisty plot books.
I don't mind mysteries that are cosy
in the sense that you know
that the detectives are going
to solve the mystery
at the end of the book.
I feel like that's part
of what I am buying into.
I thought you were going to say
Six Wakes as your example, John, but...
No, I don't think that was cosy.
It was less cosy.
There was a lot of blood.
but it is on a ship it is on a ship there's a venn diagram here of murders on a ship
coziness yeah i guess it depends which micro genre we're we're picking neil right in i'm
looking forward to murder by memory that that description has piqued my interest i want to read
it i want to read it more than any more alternate universe coffee house fantasies and this is more
of a general observation that this is the only fiction category with no men in it we have the
category of best novel and in the category of best novel we have a drop of corruption by robert
jackson bennett death of the author by neddy okorafor shroud by adrian tchaikovsky the
everlasting by alex e harrow the incandescent by emily tesch and the raven scholar by antonia
hodgson and this is a cornucopia of delight how many of these have you read john i have read
all of the ones that are not fantasy and one of the ones that are fantasy i've obviously read the
tainted cup but i haven't read the drop of corruption yet part of that was because i
figured it would probably be on the ballot so i might get a free copy death of the author i started
and did not finish because this is a book about an author who's writing a science fiction story
i found the character the central character extremely unsympathetic there's a point where
she has met a new suitor and she asks him some questions and he responds and she's like she
thinks to herself he's passed the test and i was like you don't you don't test people to see if
they're good enough to be friends with you that is deeply unhealthy i don't like this person at all
um and eventually i stopped reading partly because of that but also but also partly because
the central story is not science fictional and the story she's writing is science fictional but i
didn't find it interesting enough as science fiction to continue and i probably won't go back
to it shroud by adrian trykowski it's not as good as tyrant philosophers i did really like it it's
about capitalism and wage slavery and it reminded me a lot of alien and that is a beat i am currently
on in my head and so i really really liked it and then i read the incandescent by early tesh which
is amazing and would highly recommend and i haven't the everlasting by alex e harrow is the first book
on my pile of post-clark reading that was already true and then the raven scholar i have not heard
of and not yet read i i've heard of the raven scholar because liz mentioned it earlier in this
podcast well okay yes i've heard of it because i read the i've read uh four of them which ones
have you read liz which is i've read a drop of corruption shroud uh the incandescent and the
raven scholar i mean this this feels a bit heretical but i didn't like shroud that much
maybe i need to give it another go maybe it just wasn't clicking oh liz i really like the
incandescent i really like the raven scholar i liked a drop of corruption but thought the tainted
cup was there's some bits i don't like about how the different settings in a drop of corruption
merge together i haven't read death of the author and nothing i've read makes me think i will really
like it but i'll give it a go anyway the everlasting i've read stuff at wildly different ends of the
spectrum about uh of positive and negative reactions to this so uh that's going to be
interesting oh that's interesting so i have liked everything i've read by alexie harrow so i kind of
want to read that one i have read two and a bit of these novels um i've read a drop of corruption
and enjoyed it a great deal but i think indeed i liked it slightly less than the tainted cup
and i've read the incandescent and although i think it's quite good i don't like it quite as
much as everyone else seems to but you know that's okay um and i haven't read shroud but i've drunk
the beer it was a good beer yeah it's good beer um so i'm looking forward to reading the other ones
and the Raven Scholar does sound quite good.
Yeah, it's like 700 pages or something.
Maybe I'll read the short stories first.
I think it is a pretty good roster.
I was disappointed that there is no anti-mimetics division wasn't on here
and I was disappointed to see no when there are wolves again.
Oh no, there is no anti-mimetics division.
Oh, that's sad.
Yeah.
I think that would have been good.
I look forward to reading A Drop of Corruption and the Raven Scholar.
They sound interesting.
So do you want to do some overall thoughts?
It's quite good.
Yeah.
I think this is a good list.
Yes.
I was, you know, there's almost nothing on there that really made me start apart from the Ada Palmer and I understand why people put it on.
It's certainly not because it's bad or anything.
You know, there's nothing here where I go, oh, that's likely to be terrible or that is terrible.
And there's lots of things I'm really excited to read and find out about.
Yeah. How about you, Liz?
Yeah, it's a good list.
I feel a lot of the categories are, you know, a mix of nominees we've seen before and completely new things.
We have like someone on the Hugo, the best novel list is a mix of people who've written like 20 books and people who've written one or two.
Antonio Hudson is both in the astounding list and this is a debut fantasy novel.
And the same is true of HH Pack in Best Novelette.
Yeah.
And I think Tia Toshiro has previously been an outstanding nominee.
I mean, I've watched most of...
I've watched a lot of the dramatic presentations.
The ones I haven't watched, I'm still quite excited to watch.
There's games I want to play.
There's art I want to look at.
So it feels like a very meaty shortlist.
And there's a lot to dig into over the next few months.
Yeah.
And congratulations to everyone.
Yay!
Including us.
I mean, I feel like some of the excitement has died down
since we have known we were Hugo finalists for some weeks
and have been keeping it under our hats.
But it's still very, very exciting.
I'm very pleased.
It is very nice.
And thank you to everyone who nominated us
and who likes the podcast
and who says nice things about us.
We should say that.
Thank you.
Oh, yeah.
We should probably talk a little bit about that, shouldn't we?
We have been nominated for a Hugo Award
and that is very lovely.
And thank you to everyone.
Hurrah. And that was the Alter Thought Podcast. And it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me. And it's goodbye from me.
I wonder whether if they were doing a year every six months and they eventually overtook
went into the future it would basically be the fanzine equivalent of for all mankind and i can
just imagine that exciting neil and like i'm not saying they should do that because i think what
they're doing is great but i do wonder what a fanzine which is 55 years in the future would
look like it would be quite a good deal harder but i would i would read it that would be fascinating
and indeed i think you have put your finger on a key issue with um for all mankind which is that
as it gets up as it started to get nearer to the current day but with accelerated science
it became less and less plausible um and also and not necessarily quite as good
so i think that's also a risky risk for a fanzine in the future i mean especially when you get into
the future fan feuds i think writing fictional fan feuds between me and liz when we're both like
the both like yeah well i assume i assume there'll be a bitter thing where we're both
chairing rival worldcon bids for the uk in the same year and rendering uk fandom asunder
yeah that's the kind of thing i think you could you could send up you could send up stuff that's
happening now by transplanting it 55 years in the future making it ridiculous and i think that would
be a good basis for a fanzine but i think it would be difficult to do it i assert that is also the
episode title it could well be it could well be i do feel john that you have invented a revolutionary
new science fiction at this point uh yeah no that might be fair that might be fair why are there no
science fiction fanzines guys right in the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by
kevin mcleod and compotech.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.
Thank you.