Hello everyone and welcome to the very Adadine.
Oh god, oh god, it's so wrong.
So wrong.
Ah
Hello everyone and welcome to Octothorpe, a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom, which is coming to you live from Eastercon!
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
I'm Claudia Rapp.
Before we get going, who here has never listened to Octothorpe before?
Oh yes, we've got some people.
That's a surprising number.
Excellent.
Join us.
So we talk about
a range of things including conventions and picks with a P and uh and then we will we will answer some questions at the end.
I like a hard pick myself
Uh a throbbing pick.
I have so many regrets
Okay.
It's your handwriting though.
It is my handwriting.
I've made it more clear now that I've I've I've put a bigger I've put a I've put a bigger stem on it
Um it's true I have.
Okay, so um Claudia, hello, you are our stunned Liz.
Ah I forgot how I forgot how chaotic the live ones are.
Okay, so um Claudia, do you want to introduce yourself for the audience and the listeners at home?
Okay.
I am a writer, translator and con runner from Germany.
Uh I'm the chair of this year's uh Eurocon in Berlin.
So you are running the twenty twenty-six EuroCon?
Yes.
And you have run other conventions before?
Well just one before.
Kind of we actually immediately uh thought of doing a Eurocon but you can't start from nothing.
So first we did um just a German
Um con to see uh um if we could if we could pull off something new.
Um we call it Metropolcon
Because it's in the metropolis of Germany.
Um and the first edition uh ran in two twenty twenty-three and um
we had uh five hundred people over three days.
So I think for for people who had never done anything before and just thought
Let's try this.
Um it wasn't too bad and so we were megalomaniac enough to then bid for Eurocon
straight away.
And that's and what are the dates of Eurocom?
That's what?
What when when is Metropolcom happening?
Oh it's the first weekend of July, second to fifth of July
Um so probably Berlin will be nice and warm.
If it's too hot we have air conditioning.
Hey much like this hotel
Gabo, what's the weather been like this week weekend?
The weather has largely for me been nando's
Um I mean it's sort of not actively raining, but other than that I don't think I've seen the sun.
What crazy if we open the window the tech crew will get angry with us.
Doug says if I've been in Nando's can we have a chick pick and the answer is no.
I think that's a get out really isn't it?
Um yes, that's a that's an obscure reference.
Um so yes, and how have you enjoyed Eastercon?
Is this your first Eastercon?
No, it is not.
Um
It's my fourth, I think.
My first one was twenty nineteen and that was actually the moment um
Late late Saturday night at the disco where I suddenly thought, I want to do something like this.
No, I can't
But the d the disco was the moment.
I was just sitting there watching people dance and suddenly felt the urge
Need to do a lot of work
That that feels like so are you from You remember that, right?
You remember the next moment.
I do.
Don't talk about it.
I um
But I understand are you from Berlin or near Berlin?
Uh no, I but I lived there for ten years.
Um Yeah.
So so I mean I can see that anyone who had ever been to Berlin might see a convention disco and think I can do better than that
No, no.
Actually Berlin didn't have a convention for a long time.
There there were smaller ones.
in the eighties and nineties but not much after that and so it felt like why?
Because the venues are expensive
Now I know.
We haven't had I um for the for the fan funds quiz um which was yesterday
Was that yesterday?
Yes.
I'm hearing confirmation from the audience.
Tobes is like, yes, it was, you bastard.
Um Toes was on the panel.
Um
But I had to I I did ask Mark Plummer, does Heathrow count as London for one of the questions?
Um but it hasn't been in central London for a very long time, right?
And I guess that's similar reasons.
Don't know.
I I defer on all questions of London geography to people who care more about it than I do.
Well I mean I live in London and and Docklands is near the centre.
So that was nineteen ninety five.
So that's still quite a long time
Yeah.
Um but yes.
Shh sorry.
Sorry everyone.
Um so yeah and
Uh so what we thought about this Eastercon.
Someone in the chat, I think it was Johan in the chat, says that this Eastercon should be Metropolcon, 'cause we're in the Metropole.
So it's just to conventions.
God damn it, we need to trademark Metropolcon now, right?
Yes, you've got to get on it.
Trademark it before Hilton notices.
Oh wow.
Uh but yes, how have we found the convention?
Well I just got we drove.
Yeah my my friend and listener Andy Openshaw uh posted in the Discord saying, Does anyone want to share a taxi from New Street to the hotel?
And then I saw him later and I was like, You've got a taxi and he went, No, I looked it up on Google Maps and I realised I was being a bonker and I was like, yes.
So so Andy has something in common with my daughter who also bought a ticket to New Street and said can you get Dad to come and pick me up from New Street?
For some reason Stephen said no she can get a bloody train.
Yes, it's not.
Yeah, it's not.
Um it's hard to imagine a more convenient train line really.
Um I guess it could go directly to the Hilton, but it's only twenty fifteen or twenty-minute walk.
Um
But yes, how did you find the convention, Claudia?
I really enjoyed myself, even though uh I've beforehand I thought I uh
I would have too many things to do with being put on four different program items and with walking around trying to be
uh a living fan table um and drinking and and all the other drinking things that you need to do when you're at an Easter con
Um we've got a comment from the room, Mark Plummer says the last Central London Easter was nineteen seventy.
And that is Plummer Facts.
Round of applause for Mark.
I don't know if Bill Burns is in the audience, but Bill Burns was one of the people organizing that convention and was explaining to me in the bar
One night this weekend how absolutely terrible the hotel was.
Um which is a consequence presumably of being in central London.
So
Fan history, living fan history.
Buy Bill a drink and ask him to tell you about fandom before you were born.
Yes.
Um do do that.
Bill's good.
Bill's a good egg.
Um he brought me zines from America
The land of opportunity and also several other things we're not going to go into.
Yeah, no, that we don't talk about on the podcast because it's too depressing.
It is really depressing.
Um so program.
Anyone done any program?
Oh the audience has that's good.
You're all in program now.
So the fact that only like five of you cheered is bad.
So so
How many program items have you been to that you were not on this weekend?
Okay, so I'm gonna in the interest of full disclosure say that the ratio does skew to panels I was on rather than panels I was not on, but that's the beauty of catch-up
Yeah, yeah, so I mean catch-up changed my life because I used to not go to the program and not regret it.
And now I don't get round to watching
I think the program has been good
I'm gonna um start us off.
Good program.
Yeah.
Good.
That made less I was hoping for more than that.
Audio?
All right.
Have you and have you been to any program items?
I have been to one program item, but as we that I wasn't on, but as we traditionally pick an item a program item in
in dicks.
Um I'm shoot I'm holding I'm holding fire on that until we're holding fire on your dick.
So so but I have been to some programmes that I've been on as well.
Claudia
Yeah, um I think I enjoyed the hay lecture the most actually.
Um I always liked the science stuff.
Um
Because I learn a lot every time.
Um sometimes I don't understand it but that one was very um accessible and very so who who was the hay lecturer this year and what was it about
It was about uh creatures of the deep ocean and I think Tasha Phillips was the speaker's name.
The name sounds like that.
I'm gonna give I'm gonna give um future John work and say that we'll put the name and title of the Hay Lecture in the show notes so um check there.
But I think that's right.
Yeah, but that was really cool.
The um
showing animals that uh have inspired science fiction and animals that still should inspire science fiction.
So she tasked everyone with uh writing about sunfish monsters.
So to to sort of put it short.
Okay
There's actually there's a um there's a there's a sketch show called John Finamore's Souvenir Programme, of which there may be aficionados in the audience.
At least three.
I was like
Oh, this is clearly a a comedy show with me in mind.
But I do wonder whether uh his audience might have been quite small at that point.
So um so when if you ever go and see it live, um he does a sketch that I don't think has ever been on the radio, but he does live about anglerfish and it is so funny.
And I won't I won't try and do it here because I'm not as funny as John Finimore or all the professional comedians he pays to be on his show, but it is very good.
But and and and and that that the BSV lecture i not the BSV lecture the hay lecture is uh one of the things that is on my earmarked for catch-up
thing because I missed it but um I am enthusiastic to watch exited look horse.
And you will encounter the anglerfish again.
And it sticks
Oh god.
Um and I I went to a program item.
I went to the uh the BSFA lecture.
I'm bad at lecture names.
The BSVA lecture was really good
Foreshadowing.
Okay.
And I also went to an Ind TCRPG panel and a couple of other things and it's been very lovely program
And I believe the tech team has been doing a lot of work on making the program go.
So that has been without tech we would be lost.
Um I've been coming to conventions for a very long time, so I do remember when we had we might have had some tech in the main room, but most of our
programming was done without the benefit of lights or sound and then I've also been to a World Cup World Cont in America where a lot of the programme is done without benefit of lights and sound.
So you know
Yeah.
Um so it's great.
We we like we like the setup we have here a lot.
Well we don't talk about it enough, but like EastCon is far better run than quite a lot of the professionally run conferences I attend for work.
Like we do we do a phenomenal
The the amount of the the level of quality we deliver for the price we charge uh is absolutely mad
like and we hold and the community holds itself to such a high standard and it's it's yeah, I think we could be rightly proud of what we achieve here.
as like a community.
I mean and that's not that is tech, but it's also everyone in green room, everyone in every other function.
So yeah.
Big cheer now lights.
Do we need a scout?
Alright.
Everyone was like oh no, John's John's being sincere.
We don't know what to do with it.
Talk more about dicks.
So Metropolcon.
Yeah.
Who are your guests of honor?
Um our guests of honor are uh two
Two German writers.
Bernhard Hennan is like an institution in German fantasy.
Best selling author, also translated into I think ten different languages.
So you might even find some English.
Books are missed.
And then the the shooting star of German science fiction, Eike Mira.
really exciting stuff but I think so far it's only short stories that have been translated.
We hope very much that the novels will also
Find a wider audience.
And then uh we have Becky Chambers from America.
Um and we have um
a creator couple who write r or who draw really uh interesting comics, uh Stepan and Linda Sheic from Croatia.
Um
They're very well known in certain circles, sort of, but they also deserve a wider audience and they um they
Yeah, independent comics artists and did two very successful uh Kickstarters just recently with each I think more than a quarter million dollars.
So really none of the
I'm an independent artist, but I have to have ten different jobs to make it work, so to speak.
And then we have like a one panel
virtual guest of honor.
Kim Stanley Robinson will join us for just for just one panel on the first evening when it's morning at his home in California.
So a lot of the um and a lot of the other guests and things are also from um people that have just been translated or will just be translated into German.
So it's it's like now
you know there's a there's a um there's an opportunity for for us to to talk about to talk about or to talk with people
just because they hopefully get now a wider German audience.
And of course the other way around, introduce people to German SFF.
And if I'm going to Metropolcon, which I am
And how much of the programme's going to be in English?
Because although I have some German, I'm not I'm not that good at it.
Um I don't even know the quota right now, but it's
It's it's I no no no I don't worry.
I think it's more like three quarters in English and one quarter in German actually.
So so I can miss three quarters of the program in English.
Exactly, exactly
And there's also stuff like we have two concerts on two evenings.
Um and I think with music it doesn't matter so much whether the people sing in English or German.
Because one is is a du duo where the singer
Sings only in German, but I think the the atmosphere comes across.
And the other one is a cyberpunk duo.
I think they sing in English, but yeah
Yeah yeah no exactly
And then a disco and then a karaoke session and all this stuff.
So you can Oh I want to do German karaoke, that would be very funny.
Oh yeah, only German songs.
That's an idea.
Yeah.
So so one of the things I like about because I go to Germany quite often, one of the things I like about Germany is that it's it's very keen on um Celtic folk music
So there's an enormous enthusiasm there, so a lot of when you and I think it's partly because
So Germans do like getting drunk and singing along to things.
What?
I know it's hard to imagine, but you know, in that same way that there's a set of songs that all English people can sing when drunk
Um but I think that's probably that.
Because you see these things and you see the songs written down and you think, well what what's that about?
And then people start singing them and the entire audience
join in this this well very random s uh to my mind very random song and they explain that they sing it at the football and I go hi No I I
I fully understand that.
Or the c or they sing it to the carnival or or so even if you don't want to you know the song.
Even if you prefer not to.
Even if you prefer not to have another beer and then you can't do it.
No, we w so we worked so I went to London, um which is a city in the UK.
For those who don't know.
Uh and um we were getting the tube home from the theatre and there was a busker doing Sweet Caroline and everyone on the on the escalator down like chanted.
And it was great.
It was so good.
But there are definitely calls and responses, that's true.
Um and then so y are you involved with the Nuremberg Worldcon?
Um no I'm not really.
Um and mainly that is because we're in the middle of planning the Eurocon and then suddenly
uh a wellcon bit comes up and it's like you can you can start working on this now while you're working on this other thing.
So um
So all I'm involved in is sort of introducing people to people.
But I I thought I'd hold off on all the rest because I'm already
doing too many things.
So so that's why I'm not involved yet.
Who knows?
And then we'll we'll see if I get it.
Um I predict I I kind of
You I want to pick up something you just said there, which was, oh I'm not doing any work.
I'm I'm just kind of introducing people to other people.
That is actually work
That is a a a function.
So you're basically helping Florian and the Nuremberg crew meet all the German smoths.
Well well I think they I think the other German smoths.
I think that
I think they're c um very much capable of meeting them.
But yeah, I mean if I already know certain groups and I think this could be helpful, then but but that that's about it.
And I said
For now, don't ask me anything else because yeah, I have a lot of other functions and hats and you know we're wearing too many hats already.
So
Um but it's exciting that there is a German World Convent.
I just wish it would be for a later year.
That would make it so much
Easier to be more involved.
Yeah.
Why is this a thing to laugh about?
Oh where the listener
Yeah, but that's not me because I don't have a beard.
There's a person with a beard dabbing and knocking a lot of hats off his head.
He's in a room with stripes.
I'm bad at alt text.
I only saw that gif after it had stopped gifing and
It was just a man wearing a lot of hats.
Oh no, the gifts are proliferating.
There is there are basically people are posting gifts of lots of hats.
Uh you you don't uh what's it what's it like only having um uh a limited number of jobs that are very manageable and exactly the capacity you have
I'm so glad that John has just fed me that straight line because I was about to talk a little bit about having too many hats.
So this convention I've been in charge of the Well yeah, that's a good one.
Sorry.
I'm just gonna turn around and watch the gifts and and you can have an opinion by yourselves.
I I have been running the newsletters.
weekend.
Yay!
Good cheer.
Has anyone not seen the newsletter this weekend?
Excellent.
So one there was one person.
Declan Declan has not seen the newsletter, he reports.
But we've been putting alt text into the paper assiduously.
If you feel it very so all the QR codes have little raised pumps on them.
They don't they've got QR codes if you wave your phone over it, Declan
Every so often a w a an accessible website will pop up.
Hashtag no promises.
You can probably screen read the PDFs
Well but you can maybe.
Newsletter's been a bit different this year because um Andrew January has
Probably not in the room, he's in the room.
Andrew January, he's hiding hindsight.
He made he made us a CMS, so we can now
A content management system.
So we can now um post things from the newsletter onto the screens, um, onto the bl uh a blog on the website and it's
into the Discord.
We have used this power only for good.
So far.
Thank you.
And now it's like the spoof time so we might
So so it's been quite good.
That's been good.
I've really enjoyed having that.
And then also I've been helping out a bit with the fan funds and the fan fund auction.
Um so and the FAM Fund if you've been listening to Octhorpe you know that John Coxon has been trailing a mystery package and I can reveal exclusively now.
because I bought the mystery package to people who were not at the fandom.
And I'd like to welcome you to the Hugo Awards ceremony
for LA Con 4 in 2006.
And in the category of best fanzine, the
Nominees are Banana Wings, edited by Claire Brawley and Mark Plummer.
Challenger, edited by Guy Lillian III.
Chunga edited by Andy Hooper.
Oh no, far too many of the people on this list are dead now.
Chunga edited by Andy Hooper, Randy Barrels, and Carl Juarez.
File seven seventy edited by Mike Gly, you better cheer otherwise he will get the humphole.
And and I'm expecting a big cheer now
Plocter, edited by Alison Scott, Steve Davis and Mike Scott, who's also in the audience.
Steve here.
Mike's here.
Is Steve here?
Anyway, and the winner, that's the envelope, it's a genuine envelope.
I've never seen this before.
And the winner is Chunga, edited by And the winner was Potter.
So and I and and I have a little story
Can I how how much time do you can I digress stupidly?
So I mean, I was camping in the Oxfordshire countryside.
Oh right, okay.
And
And um I got a photo I saw that there was a text on my phone when I woke up or a mess a message to call Pat McMurray
who lived round that corner from me at the time and I was like, oh darn it, my house has fallen down or is on fire or something.
Oh oh my goodness.
And and so I phoned Pat back.
Uh at that point it was three o'clock in the morning.
California or something.
And he was like, You won the Hugo and I was like, Oh, was that his weekend?
So yeah.
So now I have the the genuine and and I saw Brian Lisbeth in the bar um after the auction.
He said, I've been I've done a lot of
Done a lot of charity auctions and seen a lot of things that have had teaser trailers and this is that big item and I have to tell you that's the worst I've ever seen.
It would have been better if you'd played along.
Yeah, what actually happened was he brought it in and we were both like uh Mike and I were both like, oh no, we're both decluttering.
Why would we want this?
It's very small
It's fan history.
But it's worth it because we we got a bit out of it.
We did get a bit out of it.
Um and yeah.
Claudia, have you ever been a fanzine?
Have I ever been in a fanzine?
No, have you ever been a fanzine?
Not yet.
Not yet, but still time.
Um the other thing I've uh we had a fanzine panel.
They had a fanzine panel at this convention.
Where were you
We're gonna have a cleansing panel as well.
Yes.
I don't think so.
Good
I think it might be nine thirty, so
But also uh Dave Hudson will or is producing uh bilingual fanzine specifically for the Metropolcon with English and German content.
So I did actually I'm sorry that sounded like feedback m so so no I so I did that and then also I've been in the games room a lot this weekend because
I'm playing so I've probably mentioned this on Opthought before.
I'm playing a different board game every day in 2026.
And in April I'm trying to play a pirate board game every day.
Because Allison doesn't have enough going on
It's very important you realise.
Alison her life is bereft of things and she needs to add more things to it.
Yeah.
Um
So luckily they don't actually require it to be a pirate game.
They're kinda like it can have a it can be pirate because it's about sea or ships or have a monkey in it or a parrot in it.
or if you drink rum while you're playing it.
Ed Moreland has said, could the panel define pirates please?
And I I did indeed have a conversation with with friends of the podcast, Rosanna Pendlebury and Ed Moreland, and we came to the conclusion that your definition of pirates is moist or shiny.
Would you care to comment?
Basically any game that's moist or any game that's shiny appears to be in the middle of the year.
Moist and Pirate Flux which is moist and Deep Sea Adventure which is moist and shiny and
Shiny and loot, which is which is moist and probably shiny.
Yeah
It's a surprisingly good definition of pirates.
I'm glad I've made you say the words moist and shiny so much.
That's good.
And uh Paratum Kappen which is the best pirate game, which German game about pirates.
Nobody has played all German games.
There are a lot of German games.
I th there are actually.
And I I think there's even one guy who produces half of them.
Yeah, it's not that he's designed a lot of games because there are other people who've designed a lot of games, it's that he's
the average quality of the games he's designed is really pretty high.
He's the German game designer Adrian Tchaikovsky.
I think is how I would pitch it.
Yes, his games are very, very long and come in three parts.
That's not that's not true of either of them.
Um but he's never done any games about spiders, so
I don't know I've said that there must be one.
Someone Rosanna is currently frantically back checking.
Oh yeah he did, he made a Lord of the Rings game and that has Shellob in it.
I am wrong.
Immediately disproved.
Thank you, Duncan
That's what we need our audience for.
Immediate disproof.
Yes.
So so Nuremberg, how do you feel
How do you feel about this bit kind of coming out of nowhere?
Like was that a surprise?
Was it a good surprise?
Was it a bad surprise?
Do you have misgivings?
Well it was a surprise.
Yeah.
Um yeah, I mean as I said, I feel it's exciting that finally after what fifty-five years there there is um
Another bit, or maybe there was a bit, but there is another possibility for a German Worldcon.
But as I said
My preference would be to to sort of have have more time to to build a community and to convince people because
Germans are skeptical.
It's hard to convince them of things.
It's hard to have them play together and
So Which means not a problem any other science fiction has.
Science fiction Japan has.
So it's weird that that's true in Germany, because like obviously in Britain and the US we'll just want a cohesive whole that never argues on blue sky.
But
But I mean from the sort of outside it looks like the British Phantom at least manages to pull together to get something done and
Maybe that is like that.
It won't be easy, but it's still exciting and I mean even even if it
doesn't work in the first at the first try, it's a good chance to to actually build something and then try again.
So Yeah, I think even if Brisbane wins this vote, then it will have set the idea of a German world call in people's minds.
Because for a long time everybody
I talked to in Germany were saying ah we can't do this anyway, it's not gonna happen.
Just just like that.
No no further discussion.
So at least someone's daring.
So I
Hat tip to people even more naive and megalomaniac than me in the beginning I didn't like to say it.
described Barrell the the way you described running Metropolcon as like a um as a as a test ground for whether or not you could do a Eurocon, I think it's a very different
way to try and build the capacity than the way that the Nuremberg mid is going about it.
So I think that's an interesting contrast.
But still I think I mean if the bit wins I think nobody wants to be left behind.
So even the people who usually are like nah
I'm not playing with this guy.
I I don't want to be on the panel with that guy and my fandom is better than your fandom and so on.
Maybe maybe they will rally then
And that that might be a good point because obviously like the UK has run WorldCons about once a decade, going back quite a while now, and I wonder whether
If you're running Worldcon you can't do as much of that in fighting because you do just need you need area heads, you just need meat, fresh meat.
Um and so I wonder whether a Worldcon in a given country does unify a country in a way
behind a fandom.
Yeah.
That would be great.
I mean because it's frustrating when you when you always run into this ah but I only read Perry Roden
Nothing else.
So why would I go to a con that has other stuff?
I've heard of Perirodents, that's good.
Um
And what do you think of the Brisbane bit?
Because you were quite excited about Brisbane, I think.
Yeah, especially I was excited about it before I even knew there would be a German bit
So that's kind of you already have your your sights and this could be a chance to go to Australia because I've never been and it's it's it would be a once in a lifetime thing.
And also there's a totality there, there's a lot of other stuff you could do around, but but that would mean a massive trip.
So I don't even know if I could afford it anyway.
But um
Yeah.
Yeah, for gov.
Yeah, I read up on it.
Yeah, I mean I think it's very I definitely would try.
I won't be the guff administrator for the next race.
Um
But I I think like I i if if Brisbane wins I would have thought it would be extremely likely we would run a gul race.
I think I would go further and say if they don't run a gough race to Australia that would be an an abdication of responsibility.
Farah.
Well and I will say uh there are many there are many epithets people have applied to Farah over the years, but an abdication of responsibility is not any offer.
When you think of Farah, you don't think irresponsible and lackadaisical is what is what I would is my thesis.
Um I think k i
How's the organisation going?
Oh no, yeah no, it's gonna be alright in forest.
Um and I think it will be a popular guff race, which would be good.
Should we move to picks?
I want to say one other thing that happened to me this weekend and if the woman who is in the audience I c didn't catch your name
But I was st standing at the fanfun's table sitting at the fanfur's table and somebody came up to us and explained that she was at her first Easter con and she'd be having a nice time on E
Had that sort of conversation said, I did I thought that if you wanted to attend a panel you had to sign up.
So I I got went into the programming thing and signed up for a bunch of panels so that I could attend some
And I I'm not they gave me two of them.
Brilliant.
I like that that I like that ended up with someone 'cause you often hear people saying I didn't think I could sign up for
panels because I'm not a pro and then I like that someone signed up for loads because they were like oh no I want to go and see them and now they get to be on the program.
That's a very happy ending.
We need to I've been thinking about this we need to write an idiot's guide to Eastercon
Because there's a lot of knowledge we take for granted.
And I think we underestimate how how like there's some really basic things you need to know about how the convention works that people just don't know if they haven't been told.
And we probably need to write it down even if it sounds daft.
Like what is a groat like and and that kind of thing.
I I I've been I've been noodling on this this weekend because I've had a couple of conversations that have been people just don't know the traditions, which is obvious.
They they come we don't explain them, how are they gonna
What will they do at the Hum and Swipe?
Well Nurse Right.
Um but yes, do you have any dicks?
Um I actually um I actually went to the publisher's website so I wouldn't forget all the praise.
I my pick for the renunciation.
uh would be a a German novel that unfortunately hasn't been translated to English yet but it has won two um two of the German um
uh speculative fiction prizes when last year when this year and it's Lineham by Niels Westerberg.
And um I just
I just thought I uh I read some of the praise that um they collected for for the publisher's website.
Gigantic, spectacular, fantastic, a milestone.
of local science fiction, local meaning German.
Finally science fiction from Germany, which should be read by the whole galaxy.
And I like I really like that one.
Everything is more complex, more warm, uh, more surprising.
I know the guy, I I actually know the critic, so um he's he he is always more complex than necessary, but so
Oh that's not common in critics, is it?
That's not a thing we see.
I want to just say that that is the sort of sentence in these words complementary in brackets written after it in crack.
Probably it also means if you like very simple, straightforward science fiction where you don't have to think, may maybe it's not for you, but
Um but it's also not but it's also not like too too complex, too like uh I don't know, German romanticism complex, but dark on purpose or so.
No, but I I was really uh
I was really fascinated because I had been dipping into some recent uh SF and apart from our guest of honor, Aikimira, most of it is very
Unsurprising.
um not one of the smallest publishers so there there is a chance that they actually sell the rights and and that you will get to read it.
And also his
Uh novel before is being um um being turned into a movie which will come out in twenty-seven.
So I hope
This will also reach a an audience beyond um it it's movie in German.
Probably in the first instance.
I could even do that.
That's my job.
Part of my job.
Well
Someone has to give me the money, then I will translate it and dub it and all that.
So you can you can translate this fantastic new novel.
That would be cool.
I might I'm I I'll do that.
So what's your take?
Like it.
So I I traditionally try and pick a program item from the convention that I'm not on and I went to one this time.
So I'm going to talk about it, which is the Eastercon big session.
open brackets not business meeting, bid session, where we talk about the future Eastercom bids and this time we normally have a little presentation from Glasgow this time because they were
So full of future bids for Eastercom.
That's pretty exciting, so I want to say.
Very exciting.
So Marcus Street's um bid for 2028 and has got it, that is contract.
Yes.
And their tagline is because everything is better with the book, which I I m uh my eyebrows ra rose a little at that, but we're gonna talk about the the bids and stuff in a bit more detail in our
next episode because I don't think we've really got time today because there were so many of them.
But we also have the launch of so congratulations to Marcus.
I'm very pleased to see that we've got an Easter con in two years' time
And then Mike Scott and Farah Mendelson presented Chronologicon for twenty twenty nine in Chester.
I love Chester, and they are
banking on it being a smallish Eastercon because it's a world cone which is a a good bet, except that obviously Chester's about the best place in the world you could go for a weekend.
It might not be quite as small as they hoped, so they might have to capture when they actually win the bid next year, which I'm sure they will, join early.
And then we had a presentation from Alan Stroud, who wants to run the biggest Easter Con ever.
He didn't say that out loud.
Um he wants to combine the Eastercon with the Eurocon and make it a i a product of the British Science Fiction Association.
Which I think we all know would be a a quality product.
And as you know if you've listened to Optathorpe
we have some skepticism about the ability of the British Science Fiction Association to run the British Science Fiction Association.
So um so anyway, so the that skepticism is not evenly applied across all of the people involved.
There are some people like yes, they can definitely do it, and some people were like
We're rather more sceptical of that one.
I think the actual issue is that the BSFA has kind of delegated things to new people and the new people have done them badly and they haven't quite
got the m balance of how you delegate and but then hold enough control that the m that the people you've delegated to do the job properly
I think that that's fair.
We talk about this a lot anyway.
So anyway, Alan wants to run it.
So I should say Marcus is coming back here.
I think this hotel's been lovely this weekend, apart from you know being the hotel it is in the place it is
What I really mean is I've had such good breakfasts.
Yes.
This is my second favourite Easter Con hotel I've been to.
Yeah.
Um and then so Alan and this in two years time we'll have roughly the same function space we've had this year, which is you know, not the big suite at the end, but everything else.
And um in t I think
Alan has also got an agreement in principle with this hotel and I think he might be looking at using the whole of it if he can.
And then Mark Bailey came along and
channel Tommy Ferguson to say that Belfast would like to bid hold the East Kellagel in the early twenty thirties.
Yes.
Which seems mad to me.
It's like
Why are people talking about what they're going to be doing for the Easter Con in front?
But it's quite nice to have it that kind of forward program.
So that was all very nice.
There seems to be a lot of energy in the Easter Con.
I really enjoyed it and I recommend you look at it on catch-up because I don't think I've
fully captured the flavour of that meeting and I would recommend it to people.
Yes.
I I couldn't go because I was on programme
I think it's exciting also that it for two thousand thirty then it will be sort of a half opposed bit because if if he's if uh
if it should be a combined Eastercon uh Eurocon, there there will probably also be a bid for uh Eurocon in Copenhagen for twenty thirty.
if they don't step back.
So what happens if if you know he doesn't get the the Eurocon but the Eastercon?
Then he's worked the details of this out.
Yeah, he did get asked what if you uh what if you don't win Eastercon, don't win Eurocon, will you take your ball away and pull out?
And he said, No, no, no, no, no, I will
We'll we'll just have we'll just run the Eastercom, it'll be fine.
And but but that is a risk because I think the I think the Eurocom bit is already opposed.
Yeah, but they may move.
I'm yeah, I'm not I'm not I'm not sure how how committed the committee is to that year, the the Denmark committee.
It's gonna be difficult as well, because if it's a choice between Copenhagen or Birmingham, I mean which do you go for?
'Cause the NEC is really scenic
The food options are excellent.
And Copenhagen, I don't know, man.
You know, it's not like there's a lot of Lego.
Oh I didn't even bought that.
Oh that yes, no I mean that is yeah no okay.
I mean Birmingham does have a lot of Lego, that is true.
In the in the lobby though.
That much.
Yes.
Um so and of course the the Eastercom bid isn't opposed yet, but it's two years till the bid.
Um
So that's my pick.
And I'm gonna pick uh some German television science fiction.
I'm gonna pick World on a Wire
Um so this is a three hour long TV series um that was made in Germany, I think, in nineteen seventy.
Um and it's about
It's about a man who gets a promotion and is very unhappy about it.
Um but it has slightly more steps than that.
It evokes
It's really tricky to talk about it without spoiling it, but the um but the basic premise is it's about a man who is running a simulation
and doing experiments on the people in his simulation to see how they react to various moral quandaries and then things become rather less certain from there.
Um and it's just really good.
I I thoroughly enjoyed it and I was I was not sure what to expect.
It's on the list of uh the best 100 um
science fiction films from time out so we watched it and I would recommend it.
If we wanted to watch it where could we find it John?
On DVD sorry sorry I
Yeah.
I'm not sure I heard that correctly.
Are you You purchase?
It comes in fact in fact I am wrong.
It is on DVDs.
It's on two DVDs because it's too long to be on the single DVDs.
You have to change the DVD halfway through.
Some people are old school, Ellison.
Yes.
I could, I suppose, lend you it.
You've got a PS four.
If we had had this conversation a week ago, you could have brought it to Easter.
So I'll see you again sometime.
Um and I will pick I was gonna I was also dithering about the BS FA lecture, but I might talk about that next time.
So we've got about seven minutes left
And we have an audience.
Audience.
Do you have things to say?
Faro was straight in with a hand.
We have a roving mic.
being um roved by um oh thank you very much constanza uh and other people think of things you wish to say your voice could too be on octhorpe
The big social media pick has been Project Hail Mary and I just wondered if you'd seen it and what you thought of it.
Um I am this may be a spoiler for a future pick.
Although I suppose I could just talk about it now.
It's better than the book
So so I left the cinema and said it's definitely not as annoying as the book and Stephen turned who has not read the book said
Well the book must have been really annoying.
So I have a whole rant about Project Hail Mary and maybe we should keep
Oh no no I I have a new rant
I have the old rant and then I have a new rant, but I will I will summarise the rant very briefly by saying it's so amazing to see underrepresented groups like American and White
Able bodied men repring getting their occasional place in the sun on these things.
Right.
I only know that uh Ryan Gosling wears a cardigan and looks good.
I I I it does have that Ryan Gosling.
I mean Yeah.
Ryan Gosling getting to do comedy
is like all comedic roles, he doesn't get enough of that, so I think I I liked that about it and I liked the vibe of it a lot.
I think the best thing about it, and I don't know her name, but it's the German actor um who plays his boss back on earth.
She is phenomenal, and those scenes I thought
were great.
I really enjoyed it probably more it it sounds like I enjoyed it more than Steven um but uh it sounds like that wouldn't be difficult.
Um but yeah no I thought it I thought it was good and uh but Ryan Gosling i I think if they if if they'd cast anyone other than Ryan Gosling I probably would have been significantly less interested in seeing it because I'm a big Gosling fan.
We probably do need to have a whole section on it but because there's quite a lot to say about Project Pell Mary we should push it in for another episode.
And also the uh channel is now full of uh gosling gifts and I'm here for it.
Um just I mean, uh just Ryan Gosling.
I'm just big, big fan.
Except for in the film, has anyone here seen the film Is it First Man where he plays Neil Armstrong?
I thought he was I I that film we have an in joke in a little group of friends where uh I say, Well I'm sad about it, but I'm not moon sad.
Because just how sad can you be while being on the Oh I really didn't know that movie.
I is the book a lot better, says Simon.
I will I will check out the book.
Um right, do we have any other questions?
I think Declan has a question over there.
I enjoyed the book and the movie, uh so I disagree with you on that.
Uh Andy Rear had another book about a heist on a moon and the name of which I forgot but it's really good.
I just wondered if any of you have any theories on why
That wasn't turned into a movie yet or is that going to be turned into a movie next?
So uh that's a book called Artemis, which is a murder mystery set on the moon.
Uh and instead of having a white man, I think it has it's definitely a female protagonist, and I think she might be a person of colour and I assume that's why it hasn't been turned into a movie.
Um so that makes me a little bit sad.
Um yes
And I it's a very cynical answer, but uh I think that's my take.
That is why my Project Helm Mary Rant is now also includes the line it's not just Andy Weir
That's not the whole problem here.
Just a quick fact check, it is being turned into a film.
It's just making people look like they walk on the moon is significantly challenging.
So yes.
Okay, I did not know that.
That's good.
It is Artemis is, I think, better than Project Hell Mary as a book.
But I love murder mystery I love science fiction murder mysteries, so I am biased because they're just great.
Right.
Thank you for the fact check, Dave.
Dave ran a long way around to give that fact check.
You know you can raise your hand and we bring the microphone to you.
Well I say we Constanza brings the microphone to you.
Thank you, Constanza.
Um do we have another question from the audience?
We do.
It's James Shields.
Does Claudia like the UK?
Eurovision entry.
Was it was it with some German
Lyrics or so?
Yes.
Yeah.
Oh I only heard it once and I was like, what is this again?
But but the
The I can say even worse things about the German entry because there were some really cool uh
Running runners, but um they chose the most generic most um eastern block looking and sounding
Girl in a short dress with a lot of fire around her once again.
Oh, this is new.
Um that's that's that makes me a bit sad.
There were some really cool um other possibilities
Um the Austrian one is kind of catchy.
Sie brauchen einen Tanzschein.
Denn ohne Tanzschein
Kommst du hier nicht rein?
I don't know what it means, but I liked it.
Talk German to me, Claudia
Um, okay so so we'll so we'll do the only German karaoke, I see.
Y these are spoilers.
You've got to wait for Eurovision.
That's when you see the Eurovision.
People watched them before and I'm like, this is wrong.
This is morally wrong.
I'm outraged
As you should be.
Do we have we've probably got time for one last question.
Oh, we've got one in the in the front row from Andrew.
The moderator guidelines say not to call people by name.
Yeah.
But it's not a good idea.
After your comments on Hail Mary, uh could you come up with a science fiction movie that you actually think is good in most respects at least?
Arrival
Arrival is good in all respects.
Gataka.
Gataka is great.
I want to do a double bill between Gataka and Under the Skin because they both have swimming in them.
Oh good I can use them for pirate month.
Yeah Gataka famous pirate movie I think we all agree it is definitely moist.
And shiny
I don't think it is Kataka shiny.
Oh yeah.
This is a conversation for the Baha'i.
i some of its aesthetic is all kind of metropolis.
It's got that kind of what the future looked like in the mid 80s look to it.
So let's let's finish with another recommendation since you keep bringing up moist
There is this whole internet conversation that people, you know, get the ick just hearing the word or reading the word.
And Ash Dylan, I think, is the name of the author.
He wrote a whole book
Based on that premise, it's just called moist.
Amazing.
Moist.
A recent
Just a good SF film given.
Um I agree with Arrival.
Um
Nah, I no, I haven't I haven't seen many um recently so yeah.
That's fine.
I mean Brazil I think is third on my list after Gatakar and arrival.
I totally knew it
Yeah, definitely new.
Um but there must be some good ones.
There are definitely good science fiction films.
Right in, listeners.
Okay.
Um
So I think it's time to start wrapping up.
So um Claudia, where can people find you if they want to follow you on socials or do any of those things?
Um
You can find me on uh Instagram, Facebook and Threads.
We will put links in the show notes.
Um yeah, you you find me easily go by my name.
Sometimes with a D E at the end, not for dicks or anything, just for just for just for Deutschland.
Okay.
Yeah.
Thank you for being our stunt Liz.
Thank you for having me.
Liz sent us a location report
Did she Yeah have you not seen this?
No.
It's in it's in the Ops Stop Discord.
Sorry guys, we're just going to do a tiny bit of inside baseball.
That means that we're going to be able to do this.
Yeah, uh put it putting it in the Discord now.
It is is
She's not watching the stream.
She is on a beach.
And frankly, that's fair.
Okay.
So thank you very much to the tech crew at the back.
Big round of applause, please, for tech.
Woo.
Thank you very much to Fonsanza for running the mic.
Thank you very much for the uh to the programme team for putting us on the programme, uh despite I think all of their better judgments.
Uh thank you to the CONCOM for having
us as well and running this amazing convention.
Thank you very much.
A poor round of applause for all of them.
And then that was the Oct Thought Podcast.
And it's goodbye for me.
It's goodbye from me.
And from me.
But this podcast will end at the beep.