Yeah, it would have been good if I could have remembered what the blurb was.
It was a book, right?
Six clones, locked room, murder, they've all been killed, blah blah blah.
Read, go and read the Goodreads page.
Hello everyone and welcome to a special book club episode of Octa Thorpe, the podcast for
science fiction and science fiction fandom. I'm John Coxon, I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty
and today we have read a book. Have you finished the book, Liz? Yes.
We have all read the book. I'm good, I've done my homework. I read it yesterday and Liz read it
yesterday and the day before. Yes. And Alison read it a couple of weeks ago, I think.
Months ago I can't remember anything about it. I'm sure I made some notes.
Aye. So the book we read was a book called Six Weeks by Merlafferty.
This was on the Hugo Ballot at the San Jose Worldcon in 2018 and I believe it lost out to one of the
NK Gemmerson trilogy but I can't remember exactly which instalment which is, you know,
if you're not going to win a Hugo, not winning a Hugo in favor of NK Gemmerson is not a bad one
to lose to. And yes, I liked it when I read it back then and so I've taken the opportunity to
make Alison and Liz read it. So Six Weeks is a book about a generation ship or not quite a
generation ship but a sort of colony ship that has been launched from Earth and is heading to
a planet to colonize it and it follows six people on the ship who are the crew and the novel opens
with basically these six people coming awake from cryo sleep from their last mind map which is
their last kind of memory backup which was taken just as they boarded the ship and slowly realizing
that perhaps everything might have gone incredibly wrong at some point and no one really quite knows
why. And so it's in some ways a kind of locked room mystery set on a spaceship in which the
murder victims and the investigators are the same people. Have I missed anything out? Do you think
Liz? No, I think that is fair to me. It is basically a locked room mystery although I'm sure there are
mystery fans bigger than us who were writing on tellers if this is actually a locked room mystery.
I don't know if it actually is because a locked room mystery the idea is that it's kind of
impossible and you have to work out what impossible thing has been breached where this is I think
lesser locked room mystery as much as a interesting murder mystery where the people investigating it
are the people themselves who have been murdered which is a particularly nice like science fictional
twist. It's not just that they're investigating their own murders but they also know that
one of them must be the murderer and because none of them remember none of them like no whether they
were or not so that is kind of another wrinkle in the ointment which is quite nice. I don't know
whether we want to start with Alison and then Liz or or vice versa but I'm up for either. Rather
than you because you made us read it so I know I would I think we should start with maybe John
explaining a little bit more about why I picked it would be nice. Okay, fair enough I could do that.
So this is something Liz mentioned when when we were kind of describing the kind of core setup of
the novel but one of the things I really like about this novel is that I think it's a story you
couldn't tell if you didn't use both of the genres it matches up. Like I don't think you could tell
this story in a pure crime setting and I don't think you could tell it in a purely SF setting. I
think you need tropes from both genres and I really like that the way that Lafferty blends those
together and I thought it was I mean as someone who likes crime fiction anyway um that really
appealed to me for obvious reasons and I also liked how I don't think I don't think it's impossible
to see the twists and turns coming if you're paying attention and I suspect that I suspect that Liz
and Alison might both have seen various of the kind of revelations coming over the course of the novel
but I really like how tight the book is if something is mentioned it's usually because it's going to
come back later in the novel and be a key point and even parts where I didn't remember how it came
back in on the reread I was pleased to see the threads kind of being marshalled back together at
the end which I did really enjoy. I also very much found the characters kind of compelling I've
always liked I've read most other work and it's fair to say I like the shambling guide to New
York City and it's sequel better than I like her other stuff but one of the things I quite like
is kind of like her sense of humor and her sort of um approached character both of which I thought
were very good in this book. Since this book she's written another crime science fiction novel which
I was less impressed by it was it was good but it was very much it was much lighter and much less
well done than this one. Yeah I like this a lot. I guess the other thing I like is the way she
layers the revelations is also interesting because you find out quite early on I think that things
are not as disconnected as they seem but the connections keep being layered on and so that kind
of makes it interesting as well because even if you think you've spotted a connection I was never
sure like I've spotted a connection but is that going to be the final piece of that puzzle or is
there going to be more to reveal later and that that was cool. And then the main reason I love it
is just because of the premise I think the premise of six clones having to investigate their own
murders on a spaceship is just a friggin wonderful idea and that you know I went through the entire
book on a cloud of kind of ah this is great. So I was very I was very um well disposed to it going
in I think it is fair to say when I first read it. That is quite interesting because I think I
agree with John that there is a great premise for this book but I didn't think it was it I don't
think it actually is a great book. Fair enough. But it's interesting because I think some of the
reasons John likes it are also the reasons I don't like it in in some ways. I mean a bit
harsh I didn't like super dislike it I just think if I'd read it on a Hugo ballot I definitely would
have you know put the NK jemisin above it and it was enjoyable enough but I'm not sure it's one I
would have picked to recommend. Yeah some of things John likes I think are the reasons I don't like
it. So one thing is I think you're right in that it needs to be like the mystery and the science
fiction to get where it's going and it has to be science fiction to do this fascinating the clones
wake up and are investigating the murder of their previous bodies but I didn't find the mystery at
the end very satisfying. I didn't feel it kind of paced itself quite right for me. I think that
there's quite a few revelations that come near the end that are too close to the end and a bit too
much maybe it's not exactly bagginess at the early stages but laying the seeds for things that come
back later but there's too much laying of seeds and then you're like okay well you keep mentioning
this so when is this going to come back to being the super important thing and so that kind of pacing
didn't really work for me as as well as it should have and I get you kind of want to have like a
very big dynamic reveal at the end but I think it went almost too fast with the revelation of a
oh that's how it was done and then it goes into kind of a I'm trying to work out if I can do
it without doing enormous spoilers. I think maybe I'll try and do some without spoilers and then
we'll have to have a listeners stop here if you don't want spoilers section. It basically goes into
the end scene which I found a little bit there's like a kind of end climax which was a bit too
much stuff going on and too confusing and then it kind of ties itself all up. So I just felt like
the structure and the pacing after kind of the initial really interesting first bit didn't work
for me throughout. Yes so I'm going to start as always with something which I absolutely loved
about this book which is that it turns out to be a piece of FTL fan fiction. I mean in the
afterward Merlafter says it's not a piece of FTL fan fiction but it arose out of consideration
of how FTL's clone bay mechanism would play out in real life and as somebody who's played really
far more FTL than is good for me I really like that so so I thought that was a very good example of
art inspiring other art in a really interesting way and she could perfectly well not have mentioned
it and sold the book you know it's not actually FTL fan fiction it's not otherwise like FTL at
all I don't think it's just that one point about FTL's slightly nonsensey clone bays and what that
might look like in a book. I will tell the listener FTL is a roguelike video game it was released
oh few years ago now it stands for Fast and Light obviously it's available on multiple platforms
basically the idea is you are on a ship and you fly through a sequence of points in a galaxy
trying to get from where you started to defeating an evil empire. The plot isn't really the key part
it's a very fun game apparently came out in 2012 so it is 11 years old now which is you know
terrifying. Ancient in video game terms but it's okay because it turns out they did make good video
games in the past. It mashes up crime fiction and science fiction so crime fiction for me and
I'm not a great crime fiction fan so I may be getting this wrong tends to have stuff that is
more what I think of as detective and mystery novels and stuff that is more sort of thrillers
and this thinks it's a detective novel but it's actually a thriller and there's a couple of
reasons for that the first is that it's got a lot of absolutely horrible stuff in it I described
this as a slasher thing there's a lot of the action that takes place in in real life is actually
people whacking each other with swords and things so you know if you don't like that sort of thing
this might not be the novel for you but the other way in which it's more thriller like
than detective like is that the information you would need to solve the mystery is deliberately
withheld from you and in fact it has to be deliberately withheld from you because if any more of it
were revealed you would immediately guess what was going on even more than you already do
so it doesn't really it doesn't really function on the detective or it didn't for me function as a
detective story it functioned us so although you've got these people trying to work out what's happened
to them it felt as for me as if it was much more over to the thriller or horror side than it was
over the detective side mystery side and so because in so far as I do like crime fiction I like
the sort of cozy detective novel where sweet little old ladies go and go and um investigate
horrible murders without actually ever getting terribly close to them it was that bit doesn't
work maybe as well for me as it might have done did like the science fiction bits of it quite a
lot though yeah so that was that was so I think I said in a previous octa thought record might have
fallen out in the edit um it was it was a bit nasty for me it's a bit over to the horror side for me
there were scenes I was kind of like oh and in fact I said I couldn't remember how I'd read this but
in fact what happened was that I started it it felt a bit horrible I put it down for a bit but
that I was like oh I have to read it for octa thought picked it up and then read it all the way through
in a single lump because I did find it quite gripping so so it was a it was a grippy novel I
read it I thought it was an easy read and I read it all very happily after the first few bits apart
from every so often I said you that's horrible yeah so I think that I think you're right I don't
think you can um work out what's going on from the beginning but obviously it's tricky because
that it's basically the science fiction equivalent of the amnesiac um thing right where like they
don't have the memories or the logs and so I wonder whether that's kind of shadowing what happens to
the characters so I didn't it kind of felt like you have as much information as the as the characters
do at any point or maybe not entirely obviously if you had all the information that every character
has you'd know the answer but because there's no way for I guess Mercado did it from a single
viewpoint and given you all the information about one character and none of it about the others
but I thought this struck a good balance between kind of keeping you as in the dark to a similar
level the characters are so I completely think you're right but I think that worked for me better
than it worked for you probably I will I will say I also when I reread this I blasted through it I
read it in a single sitting under a cat which is very good so so I thought the authorial voice
was a bit of a mess this is one of these technical details because the way that you do that is have
separate sections from each character's viewpoint but in a way that has the character narrating
and what we actually got was omniscience where we have a an authorial voice that is omniscient but
actually doesn't tell us things if it doesn't suit it and that's a bit old. So I feel like that
was an editorial choice and there are a few things about this book where I think ooh editing
ooh maybe the editing could have been a bit more rigorous and that may be part of the issue why
it didn't I don't think it found a UK publisher ever for what is oh I think a perfectly solid book
yeah no it didn't I don't know I mean I pass I know what you mean I think I do wonder whether
in the beginning of the book the first couple of chapters like until I got into the zone of the
novel I think like there are the odd character perspective shift that like slightly caught me by
surprise and so I do know what you mean that like maybe better clearer delineations might have been
good so yeah I can see that I'm a big fan of unreliable narrators but I don't know if that's
what she's trying to do I don't really think she is yeah I don't think you can have seven of them
anyway or six of them or however many there are I think that is too that is asking a lot of your
reader I always say so I guess we should sound the spoiler klaxon quite soon yes is there anything
else we want to say without spoiling this novel so I don't know so this is not really a spoiler but
I will say it's something that colored my view of the book which is that if you currently buy it off
a UK Amazon Kindle store it has a bunch of formatting errors and I realize yeah it doesn't
have her it doesn't have a British publisher so she self published it yeah and I realized that
when I got to the end and it says you know you can you can write to the author with errors so I may
do that but the the errors specifically are line breaks in the wrong places so in the middle of
paragraphs and not between different characters speaking and so that has probably colored some
of my opinion of the book because they are unfortunately it's in the edition I'm reading
there are throughout kind of errors in the formatting that make it kind of hard to
kind of spot which character is talking at times it actually has character shifts in the middle of
paragraphs as a result of this but I think I caught on fairly quickly that this was actually a formatting
fault rather than a deliberate authorial choice and once I got used to it I recognized when they
happened but that yeah that that does make it harder yes so I mean it's this is not it's not
really coming into a spoilery territory I guess but what I would say is one problem I had with the book
is I think the character's voices sound pretty similar and so the fact that occasionally their
conversations were all running into one line and I had to go back and reread it to make sure I
knew exactly who was saying what line that did not unfortunately help the experience of reading
it but I recognize that is a formatting that like is a formatting error and you know it's
I presume that has crept in at some point with a Kindle update but it was causing me a few
problems when I read it so I can't really kind of disentangle that from the reading experience
unfortunately I read it in paper because I imported it I bought it from Blackwell's when it was nominated
the first time because it wasn't in the packet if I recall correctly so I bought the paper version
from from Blackwell's so I did not have I did not have that experience but yes that sounds annoying
I mean this is a regular criticism of books that have a lot of different viewpoints okay still not
too spoilery not everyone on the ship is who you are initially led to expect them to be or acting
in accordance with the motives they initially say they're going to have I don't think that's
something that's particularly unusual this is one of the ways in which I think science fictionally
the book was quite good in fact it did some things in quite a clever way around the the nature of
self and what indeed is meant by cloning and all of that stuff and some of the ways in which
everything gets tied up together is jolly good but but that does lead to this you probably wanted
more distinct voices than you got but I understand that I'm not I'm not a writer and I don't know how
hard it would have been to to write those voices I I can't because I can only write in one voice right
guys I can I'm I'm resolutely Allison all the time that is that is definitely true just think
case any listeners were wondering yes agreed if I write if I write a novel people will complain
that all the characters are a bit like me but it is I can see it being like a coherent critique
shall we sound the spoiler horn
so yeah so one of the things I think the other thing I really like about this book and I like this
in general in fiction and it probably says a lot about me that I do like it is that I really like
books that can have happy endings which don't feel like just they're out of nowhere like the happy
ending in this book is well telegraphed in advance with the pig and I really like that because I
think if you're paying attention you can probably work out that the fact that they can cook a pig
means they can probably recreate the humans but I have a note here which is check-offs food printer
why is maria cooking a pig the plot demands it if you had if you had a 3d printer so so this bit
that John liked is something that I thought was fucking stupid oh no okay you know absolutely
appalling and and and I was like why can we clone humans but not vegetables that's insane that's
absolutely ludicrous and then it turns out that they can clone vegetables perfectly provided its
hemlock oh well done guys I think um I think they say they can is just not as good which I assumed
was because life was protein and vegetables are not made of protein but I don't know because most
of the world effort in 3 printing food at the moment is very focused on meat and protein and I
don't know how that will change in the future where's the money follow the money well exactly
right when also follow the climate change because I can see why in general cows are worse for the
environment than this is this is something I know that there's debate on and I want to present
this as like a fact necessarily but I know that like one of the reasons there's a lot more research
into 3d printing meat is because its thought the meat is worse for the environment than the crops
and so like I don't know I mean yeah it's tricky no I think it's where the money is because meat's
vastly more expensive than vegetables so if you can if you can make meat you can sell it to people
for more money than you're going to be able to sell vegetables for and but also you are correct
that the demand is probably there because people want to remove meat from their diet first this
is a digression but all to say did you think this book had a happy ending yes I did why
because it does for whom for Sally no although I did Liz what do you think of the ending I mean
I think it's potentially a happy ending but you know what we know what we know from the book
listeners is that instead of this being a crew perfectly picked to psychologically balance each
other out over the immensely long space journey is a bunch of people picked to be the worst possible
companions on a space journey I had Eastcon flashbacks all the way through this I think your
happy ending is predicated on them now having gone through this experience and being like now we
are going to get the long fine and it's great rather than it being okay in 25 years they will all
also have stabbed each other to death again also from my notes why is the AI program to return to
earth if this entire mission is designed to sabotage what makes anyone think there's a planet at the
other end what on earth makes that plausible the more effective sabotage would be to have way less
synthesis since this goo on the ship the necessary to reach landfall and indeed no landfall to reach
I think I'm just a nihilist in terms of my science fiction I think the argument might be that an
eternity of never getting anywhere is worse punishment than a shorter eternity and so there's loads of
synth goo because she really wants to drag it out but basically listeners it turns out that as Liz
says all of these people have been very carefully selected they are all enemies of a character we
meet quite earlier in the book called Sally Minon who is an certified rotter and this is the answer
this mission is the answer to the question how do you get revenge on your enemies if death doesn't
matter and the answer is you fire them off the earth and force them to spend untold years in a
small tin can which is it's an imaginative answer to the question yeah so the thousands of people
in cryo sleep are also Sally's enemies because she's one of these super rich people who has a
lot of enemy enemies and they're just going to die quietly so I thought that was kind of interesting
as well yeah yeah because she's not actually giving them a terrible death she's only picked these
six characters for the terrible death yes I will also say in some ways so we discussed how it's
see it was inspired by a 2012 work which is a FTL in that it was like based on FTS musings about
how cloning would work in a science fiction novel I also wonder if it was partly inspired by another
2012 work which is the Ridley Scott film Prometheus because Prometheus is a film where it purports that
the crew are very carefully selected to work well together and then portrays an utterly incompetent
mess of idiots and I'm like maybe this is maybe this is MERS take on that because there are
points where I'm like yeah this does feel very much like the crew of Prometheus in terms of
their ability to work well together but yes maybe I don't know so so will the crew of Prometheus
deliberately chosen not to work well together or no it's said in the movie that they're carefully
selected to be like an elite team and then nothing in the text of the movie at all in order for the
movie to go they all have to be utter imbeciles you argue all the time and like the film just tells
you these are the people at the top of their field and they're all going to work very well
together and then nothing in the text of the movie it's been like Ted in How I Met Your Mother
everyone in How I Met Your Mother repeatedly says Ted is the best bloke but he is a stone cold
asshole from episode one to the last episode and it's really there's a huge cognitive dissonance
and I like fiction where that's true and this feels like a book where she's using that trope
she's using the fact that very often we are told these characters will work well together
and then the writing really doesn't reflect that but she's doing it on purpose to sort of
play with her expectations a little bit which I do I did quite like that aspect of things
yeah I did like that I did like all the stuff about them well not being themselves all the
fucking around that had been done with their brains at various different times in various
different ways and the way in which she came across she looked at that from multiple different
angles and that was all great so the science fictiony bits of it really liked this I really
like the science fictiony concepts but in practice in the book the science fictiony concepts feel like
you know one character is one of those like genius hackers who types away and all the
text goes green and then they figure it out it just relies on me to think that someone can
basically instantly look at some kind of computerized map of a human brain and perfectly isolate a
single trait and remove it and on with their DNA there was some there was some slightly wobbly
stuff there it just it was it was much too easy a lot of the time to do the very precise hacking
yeah we're not we're not necessarily shown that we have done the spoiler warning that we're not
necessarily shown well enough why Maria is that person yeah we never see a no we we're told she
has the background but we we do see it to her doing it a bit with a food printer but maybe not
enough and maybe her not noticing that the food printer is exactly the same replicator as the
cloning bay is is implausible that's a thing that we've not been told and when she makes that
but when she realizes that you're kind of like well surely if you're the character you've
been described as being you would instantly have realized that I mean surely if you have
a food printer that can actually essentially grow people a new body and put their brain into
it it could also make a lettuce I don't know well indeed I really everything about vegetables
really wow if I've been if I've been beta reading this there will be a there's a whole
section at the beginning where there which I think is meant to be character development and
introduce use the characters where they're kind of tetrally talking about food in this locked room
and and all of that I found kind of tedious and not moving things forward fast enough and not
really expanding on the characters as much as you might think it would I can see I can see the
vegetable thing being annoying it is like one sentence um I'm like yeah here's to really
annoy both of you which fair but like and again I think it's sentence that makes sense in in
terms of like the current state of the art in food printing but if she had just deleted that
one sentence no but but then but there's actually a lot of stuff about when they're kind of talking
about the early scenes so they're clones and they none of them know each other at all at the
beginning of the book they're all they're all blank clones and they're supposed to be having
the sorts of conversations that you have with people that you've only just met and the conversations
they have are not at all those sorts of conversations um they are they are tetrically conversations
between people who are massively not guessing along with each other which just fit with the
end of the book but but it is also tricky because if I woke up and found my own dead body floating
in front of me I don't know how similar that would be to an icebreaker oh I've had next time I'm going
next time I go on a management training course I have a whole plan oh no oh no but yes I think
the point about hacking is frustrating I do get that I will say in general willing to forgive
this in all fiction because vanishingly little fiction actually gets the act of hacking right
um like Murderbot's a great example where none of the computer stuff makes any sense at all
but I kind of just let it wash over me and this felt like that but I can see the point for sure
I liked actually if you're gonna go on to different bit can I just come back on that I think there
is so there's well there's two reasons that annoys me one is it talks about DNA in ways I think
a don't seem super realistic about DNA there's a bit where um yeah like Maria is um who is the
hacker character it seems to be sort of telling the AI out to do something about like making her
own DNA matrix and it's just like easy but I think the real reason it annoyed me is it comes to
have another bit of the book which is this is like fairly mid to far future and it doesn't feel
very mid to far far be like 30 years time yeah that's fair I think that that's a coherent um I think
that's a current point I will say as a physicist it always amuses me when biology is in science
fiction because I think we've said this on the podcast before but I mean Liz like oh my fucking
god if that annoys you imagine if you're a physicist because it's all nonsense it's true because I'm
like FTL fine what that should I talk to you about mathematics in science fiction sometime
when it's happened episode one day about just like the one that gets me the worst is alien
covenant with the solar storm at the beginning because it's just like everything at the beginning
of that movie is totally wrong and like it's closer to my expertise than usual so I did find it harder
but yeah no I mean it is that it's interesting that she basically positions like DNA and
personality hacking as effectively computer hacking but like the bit where she like you can
comment out someone's personality like I don't know like I suspect that's impossible but then again
like you know maybe in 500 years or just something we all do who can say yeah can I can I make some
suggestions I can absolutely call it with applause all the way that you would kind of you know have
a way that you silence the you know various bits of DNA with a you know halfway plausible mechanism
but what it sounds like is she just kind of goes at the computer and types some hashes in and then
it doesn't do anything it just felt like it was all a bit too close to like this magically happens now
yeah but I think this is any sufficiently advanced technology right yeah but I think
does it tie into what Liz said earlier about it doesn't feel far enough and I think I wonder if
the setting felt further future elsewhere it would be easier to forgive those bits maybe that is
a thing I mean absolutely like these things would be these things would probably not bother me if I
you know other bits of the book were making up for them for me but since I didn't particularly
like other bits of the book they then become really annoying I mean that does that definitely
happens the bit that annoyed me I did have a bit that did annoy me is Maria why not just let them
shoot her whenever she gets kidnapped she knows she's gonna die eventually so just like don't like
I get and I guess that like I don't think she does I think it comes as a bit of a surprise
hmm I think she says well the first time I don't think she does but I think the second time she does
because the second time she remembers she has the gap of three weeks and she's like oh shit this
is happen before but like so the first time I can see why she complied but the second time I was like
oh no I think it's because they would destroy her clones right oh do you think oh I hadn't thought
of that the reason she's being brought back to life is because they know they need her again
if she doesn't go along with what they want they will they'll kill her and not and make sure her
clone isn't resurrected yes oh she no okay I like that I like that explanation actually yeah fair
enough plus it's it's horrible I mean they're threatening to torture and you might say well I'm
gonna if they kill me I'll be resurrected I won't have any memories of this but in the moment I
don't think that would be a very compelling argument no that is fair but also Allison's point
like I think there's a point where they mail her clone back to earth right yeah and they wouldn't
do that and then she'd never be resurrected yeah the reason they're doing that is they know she'll
do it they know she goes through with it and it's possible that eventually she wouldn't and indeed
she gets packed off by Sally on her ship full of un-munch deplorables deplorables yes
it's in I mean I do yeah I do like how they're all connected at the end the the second time Sally
was mentioned I was like oh clearly they're all she's she's deliberately got them all together now
why so I didn't hadn't worked out that they were all people she really wanted to effect effect an
event a revenge on but you know I did it was obvious she was gonna come in for each of them
because otherwise why on the other hand I was fairly blindsided when it turned out the AI was
the seventh character and I was very obvious if you were reading the book so you know I get some
things I don't get other things in the bit we recorded before the spoiler I said like there are
enough revelations that if you this book kind of I guess there's two ways of doing a twist which is
you can have one twist and you're just very confident that you've disguised the twist well
enough that people won't guess it or you have 17 twists and you operate on the basis that if
someone gets 12 of them five will still be surprising and this book definitely takes the second option
but I don't think it does it it doesn't feel I mean the way I've just said it out loud listeners
you might be thinking god that sounds awful but I did not find it awful because none of them felt
like completely out of the blue like Alison says like when the seventh character is revealed
you're like oh no okay yeah no that doesn't it doesn't feel like it's out of nowhere because there
is a character who has been mentioned multiple times who it turns out is the AI and like you say
like you work out Sally's involved very early in the book but the the full extent of the plan
becomes clear later but you might not spot it if you think you've already spotted what's going on
so I did I did quite like those aspects of it we've been recording for 43 minutes should we like
record final thoughts and wrap up um or does anyone have anything burning that they would
still like to say out loud I think I've covered most of it I'm trying to think is there anything
else I knowingly wanted to say I'd I had one thing I did work out that I wanted to say which is that
I am not alone in thinking the dialogue in this novel leaves something to be desired that um
quite a lot of the dialogue has both the problem of being clunky things that people don't say to
each other and also the two sides of the conversation not sounding as differentiated as you want to
in novels where you're deliberately stylizing the conversation so it it both had the problem
that novelistic dialogue has and it didn't have the excuse for it that was my dialogue point
it wasn't just a dialogue for me I think the writing is very you know it does what it needs to
but I have been reading a book that's kind of more on the literary end of science fiction that has
very kind of a very distinctive style and kind of makes the character voices more distinct and I think
this book probably unfortunately suffered from being read straight after I was reading that one
so this book was up against the following novels when it was on the Hugo ballot it was up against
the stone sky by N.K. jemisin which is the conclusion to the to the trilogy it was up against the
collapsing empire by john scowsy new york 2140 by kim stonley robison provenance by ann lecky
ravenstrategy by yun harley and then six weeks by merlafti four orbit one tall one salaris in the
end so like for me this book is like in my top half of that ballot but i don't know whether you guys
have read the others and have an opinion i think i've actually read all of those maybe not it's a
collapsing empire the first one of that series by scowsy yeah in which case yes i have read all six
and i would probably put this one in the bottom half sorry john pare enough i like it i like it
better than provenance and the collapsing empire i think and i like it probably slightly better than
ravenstrategy but i thought ravenstrategy was the worst of that trilogy so yes i think i think it's
about i wrote about the same as provenance i think i like ravenstrategy a bit more but in a way
the ravenstrategy and in fact the whole kind of hexarchate novels and series of stories basically
scrapped some kind of itch for me that i really like and so i'm willing to forgive them a lot
in the way that i think things that annoy me in six weeks you are willing to completely forgive
i bet the maths in the ravenstrategy drives alice not the wall um i have not read the raven
stratum but maths in science fiction novels generally drives me up the wall what you have to
bear in mind about the unaali trilogy is it's span a scene of science fiction because if it's
science fiction it doesn't make any sense at all oh unaali um that's the one that's the one
because speaking as a man who understands time well as well as anyone understands time
like those books are cray but they're great i love them yes nine fox gambit nine fox gambit is the
book that i have started to read and stopped more often than any other book ever in my life
Liz you guessed correctly and and and this is why it's the book i was grasping for and i said
earlier oh god don't get me started on maths's science fiction novels no i mean yeah uh fair
i'm glad we brought it up now the point about maths is that i understand why physics could
be tush or biology could be tush but maths just is it's a description of the way in which
it's not like physics is lies alice and no it's pattern the point is that you can imagine a
universe in which you had different physics or different biology right but the maths is just
a description of patterns and how they are that's what it is that was the old thought podcast and
it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me
[Music]
john have you been listening to tansy garden striking out podcast because one thing she
declares up front in that is basically she's got like a fog horn noise and whenever there is
like a person she has to discuss but she wants to let you know that you know there have been a
bunch of me two reports and you know accusations of harassment or whatever about the particular
person after the first time she just sounds the fog horn in the background so she'll say you know
something like screenwriter paul haggis rob and then it will just carry on as normal and i think
we want that noise we don't need that necessarily for our podcast but i do enjoy that it's just sort
of a fog horn noise the theme music for this episode was surf shimmy by kevin mccloud and
combatec.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep