Hello everyone and welcome to the very 53rd episode of Octa Thorpe, the podcast for Science Fiction
and Science Fiction fandom. I'm John Coxon and you may be able to tell that my voice is slightly
different to usual and that's because I have managed to catch COVID in the same week that I
moved house, which is just 10/10 planning on my part. I think I have absolutely nailed it.
As a result, we're dropping this little mini episode to keep you all tidied over until we
release a proper episode again a fortnight today and this is the chat we had when we were answering
Coribulat's questions about our fancast and we linked to that post on her blog and this is the
chat we had that went into answering those questions. So I hope people enjoy it and we'll see you all
in a fortnight's time. Tell us about your podcast or channel. It was John's idea. Octa Thorpe has a
tagline, the podcast of science fiction and science fiction fandom and we do talk about science
fiction, a fair amount, but we do talk a lot about fandom, about upcoming conventions, about things
that fans do and that is I think where our heart is and we also have a very engaged community
who write it and tell us what they think about all of these things and we are very pleased about that.
Yeah, so I think we could probably do like the first three questions because the other ones are
who are the people behind it and why did you decide to start? So I think, so I decided to start
a podcast and I recorded, I actually recorded a pilot episode of a podcast with Meg Frank back
in 2013, which never, never actually made it. That's a long time ago. I knew I wanted it to be about
fandom and I knew I wanted it to be in the style of the Apple Tech podcasts that I love and I eventually
discovered that Alison also loves the Apple Tech podcasts that I love and so I said Alison do you
want to be on a podcast because you're quite loud and then I knew that Liz was a good egg and I wasn't
talking to Liz as much because she had gone to Thailand and I was like Liz is good, she's more
sensible than me and Alison, she has more reasonable opinions and she will be a good moderating
influence on the two of us and so I asked Liz how did that work out for you? I think it's gone very
well and maybe I was just ruminating, I went down to get my water and I was thinking that was a really
good episode, I really liked talking to Alison and Liz every two weeks and I really like getting to
listen to it again when I edited it and they made me laugh and I very much enjoy, I very much enjoy
my Sunday mornings and yes so I think it is good. I have been wanting to do a podcast ever since
the very beginning of podcasts but it turned out that if you want to do a podcast you have to find
someone who's dumb enough to do the editing for you. That's fair because otherwise podcasts don't
happen, so if you want to run on your own podcast the core thing you need is somebody who's up for
doing the editing which is significantly more work than recording the podcast. It doesn't take longer
but it's just not as much fun. Once you get into a swing of it I think it takes roughly twice as
much time as the recording length for the style of editing what you do, so it isn't about three
hours probably to edit each episode. Liz tell us about your deep-seated longing to be on a podcast.
I didn't have any time to be on a podcast or to start a podcast or really to really work around
podcasts but John was like do you want to do a podcast? I think I was like maybe and then there
was a coronavirus and so it's like well now I literally have nothing else that I need to be doing
on a Sunday afternoon so let's do a podcast and I am just constantly amazed that we have made it
42 episodes and there appear to be at least 10 people actually listening. One of the things it says
is what format and I would quite like to speak to that one so yeah go for Alison why do we do this
format? What format did you choose for your podcast or channel and why did you choose this format?
So there are quite a lot of podcasts out there for science fiction in particular and none of them
quite did what I liked in terms of the sort of podcasts I like to listen to because John mentioned
Apple podcasts and indeed their Apple podcast but they are podcasts where a bunch of mates
get together every so often and chew the fat about current things going on in the area they're
interested in and those are the sorts of podcasts I like and none of the other science fiction
podcasts were quite doing that and critically the sort of podcast this isn't it's not really an
interview podcast so a lot of podcasts involve the host interviewing different people each week so
it's not that sort of podcast it's the sort of podcast where people chat about things it is
explicitly modeled on a couple of Apple tech podcasts except unlike those podcasts there are
women on this one ha ha ha that was that was definitely something I did also want to make sure
I did I did not want to be another white dude podcast I think there are probably enough of
those already and I'm one of the things one of the things I really loved about that style of
podcast was how discursive it was and I thought that really tied into the letters of comment
from kind of old school fanzine fandom and so that was kind of one of the reasons why I thought
the format would work in a fanist context was that I thought it actually harped back to fan writing
in an older sense and I didn't really think it was something that was happening in in fanish
podcasting so yeah the fan categories are the heroes were there at the very beginning but they
are also the categories which consistently get the lowest number of roots and nominations so why
do you think fanzines castes and other fan products are important Alison probably has the strongest
opinions I'm a fan of science fiction fandom as much as I am a fan of science fiction if I look
at my reading and my watching some of it is genre as much of it is not but if I look at the people I
choose to spend time with their science fiction fans that it's actually the community of fandom
that I find so valuable and the thing about fan cut about fanzines about fan writing about fan
castes it's very much the forefront of what they're doing that they are actually celebrating
the thoughts of the people who like this stuff which is the stuff that I found interesting
and that's why whenever I'm looking at conventions I'm like let's talk about how we manage all the
things that aren't the program how we how we make sure that the social spaces are engineered right
because it's the social interactions between fandom that are what I'm here for and this is what
is known traditionally as being a fake fan that is fair that had scare quotes on it by the way
fair enough because obviously it's the most real fandom of all yeah I think and I think like I got
into frontom largely through kind of zzz at nine but also like one of the early fandoms I was in
was fanzine fandom so I think for me it kind of was just how I came into fandom to a large extent
so I think that's probably why I think it's important it's just it's where I came from when I wrote a
fanzine between 2007 and 2014 ish called procrastination which I recently published a new issue of
and so yeah I think it's I always liked and I like reading blogs and stuff as well and I like reading
kind of Twitter and Facebook as as fan writing has evolved I have enjoyed interacting with it
I want to say two things which is I think is very nice that the hugos from the start have
rewarded kind of fan endeavors alongside the professional ones and I think it's nice to have
them there also so that people who maybe are not as familiar with fandom might at some point
look at the list of hugo winners and go oh fanzines fan cats maybe I should check some of these out
but also I think as long as there is a vibrant community I'm not particularly bothered if they
get fewer votes and nominations than other categories I mean I think it's nice that they're there for
people but I don't necessarily worry that there aren't as many people nominating for best fanzines
there are for best novel or best short story I think they are just aiming at a slightly nisha
segment of fandom I don't want to get too low because I do want like the hugos to be to maintain
some prestige and I think if you get to point where you know you only need five nominations to get
on the ballot then that is too low I mean there is there is a built-in thing in the hugo rules that if
the number of votes ever drops too low that there will will be you know no award in that category
so I think there is that built-in at least so it never falls low a certain threshold and I do
want to see it kind of you know maintain a good level of interest but I'm not necessarily bothered
that it's that it's lower than it is in some of the other categories I'm going to make that sound
snappier when I edit it that's a good thing. In the last 20 years fanzines have increasingly
moved online and fancasts have sprung up or do you think the future of fan media looks like?
I have opinions on this as as some people may know one of the reasons I wanted to do a podcast
was because I thought that the sort of style of fanzine I quite like with the focus on fandom
is something that I feel like hasn't really made the jump to more modern media which is a problem
for me because I enjoy more modern media and I completely respect there are fanzine fans who
are like very into their printed materials and PDFs but like as someone who enjoys that style of
writing but enjoys more modern forms quite like some of it to be available in those more modern
forms and so I do three fanzines one of which is I experimented with kind of doing e-pubs and stuff
fairly early on and now is a blog one is an email newsletter and the other is a podcast and I think
especially email newsletters are currently blowing up with sub-stack and stuff there's a lot of good
fan writing you can get like delivered to you now. I think the future is going to be in kind of
using these new technologies that come up stuff like email newsletters which are very old in some
ways but have had a renaissance and I think people have noticed that this is actually a fantastic
way of doing it but also using stuff like WordPress and using kind of YouTube and podcast platforms
to do this stuff will be very popular in the future and that's where because I'm trying to
skate to where I think the buck is heading and that's been what I've been trying to do in my fan act
throughout. So I think the last 20 years I've seen a massive fragmentation of the sort of
fandom I like which people bemoan quite a bit but but one of the problems is that I don't think the
most of the older fans who were used to doing paper fanzines have found it very easy to engage
with with the more modern things. I also think there's a problem with so the thing about paper
fanzines is that you can pick up a paper fanzine from many years ago say on a table at a convention
and you're suddenly transported into the life of these people and a lot of the things we've been
using now for our fanish links and communications have been much more ephemeral than fanzines so it
would be quite nice to have some things that are not so ephemeral. Now people may decide in the future
why would anybody listen to a podcast from 2021 but they might not, ultimately they might go,
"oh what were people thinking? What were they saying?" People did go back and listen to some of the
earlier episodes of OctaThorp before this Easter were like, "oh apparently you have been bleating
on about this for a year." So you know there's something about what all the time fans even fans
call time binding about making things that have a degree of permanence and I'm slightly struggling.
I too have an email newsletter which is not getting around to doing its third issue at the moment
but it will do quite soon and one of the reasons it's not is that it had a, I wanted to put a lot
of links in in the first two and I did and then I realised that links start rotting immediately
so you immediately lose the permanence of your item and I'm thinking about what more I can do
about that to keep a sense of permanence about the stuff that I do. I want that in the future in the
event anyone cares there will be something there for them to care about. Yes I think what I've noticed
is maybe it's not coming, it's not coming I think out of the sort of more traditional historical
fanzine fans but there's a lot of people on YouTube talking about books and a lot of them have
pretty big audiences and a lot of viewership and there's definitely kind of an audience out there
and I wonder if more and more will sort of drift towards that video model. Booktube they call it.
It's basically Booktube yes. That's not for Korra who knows this perfectly well but for our listeners
Booktubes maybe you think they haven't come across so we should probably talk about at some point.
Email, you know email newsletters are an extremely throwbacky idea which has come around again
so maybe the next thing is going to be like a live journal revival or something. Who knows?
Or it'll be a completely different set of media that we haven't even invented yet.
Yes I think that may indeed be the thing.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod in Competech.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.