I'm glad you attributed to me a joke I didn't make. That's quite good. You're now hallucinating
jokes you think I made. So I'm just gonna take credit.
Yeah, it's the dream Liz in John's head made that joke.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 146th episode of Octothorpe,
which is finding a board game in its parents' attic and being transported into a magical world
on the 23rd of October 2025. I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
Hello Liz!
Hello, I'm back.
Yes! Hello Liz!
Who are ya? Who are ya?
Because last time we had an emergency stunt, Liz.
yeah I think I'd vaguely said guys that date might be difficult oh guys I think that date's
really difficult oh I think that's gonna be really difficult I think I can't do it
and then at some point we kind of went oh wait we don't have any episodes in the bag
quick stunt Liz so thank you Tommy for being a stunt me and a very good stunt me
yes it was great it worked out very well I agree I got to listen to an episode that was very nice
you're welcome back anytime Tommy except for if Liz is available I got dibs and also we obviously
have all the other stunt liz is to work through not repeated yet we have two letters of comment
uh because the episode went up about five hours ago as we record listeners um firstly johnny
badly says he also didn't know about irish fandom day so there was there was one yes
uh two two now there's but there's lots liz liz you also didn't know about irish fandom day
no and then secondly i got a dm from my friend ian who says i'm still wrong about the raid
in in what regard i don't like it ah he does like it your friend could keep sending that
once a week and they'd still be right that's true not that i wish to encourage harassment of john by
uh instant message because he's a wrong head it's not that you want to but you don't not want to
it's not like there's an objectively correct opinion here right i mean speaking as someone
who works in physics which you'd think had lots of objectively correct facts and yet there is still
quite a lot of disagreement what even is correctness anyway story of the 21st century nobody knows
anything um yeah thank you very much for writing in both i think i do feel a little bit bad because
i feel that by releasing an episode while christopher j garcia is probably asleep and
then recording another one before he wakes up we've we've robbed him of some chances to uh
to write a lock oh i mean i'm i'm refreshing my emails periodically because i think there's a
sizable chance he'll write in while we record but we'll see a live lock excellent um we had we also
had a letter of comment from doug fawn who says how can we talk so much about core flu and not
mention the upcoming one in santa rosa um there's an upcoming core flu in santa rosa listeners
coreflu.org for more details coreflu pickles can we add a state to that because i don't know where
Santa Rosa is. Santa Rosa in California. It is the home of Peanuts and the place that the Peanut
Museum, Peanuts Museum is. Peanuts rather than Peanuts. The comic strip Peanuts. I thought you
said it was the home of Peanuts and I was like, well, where do Peanuts come from? Oh, okay.
And their tech ops volunteer is listed as Tommy Ferguson, tentative. I am very much,
I'm not planning to go to Corflou Santa Rosa, but I quite like to.
They've got lots of good ideas and they keep publishing restaurant reviews
because the committee keeps going to visit restaurants in Santa Rosa
and then writing about them, which seems quite nice.
That's fair.
Yeah, and if your committees still like each other enough to go to a restaurant,
then you're doing pretty well.
Committees don't tend to fall out very much doing Corflou
because it's not very hard convention.
so after a period um where not a lot's been going on or at least we've not been hearing a lot about
it um easter con 2026 which is iridescent iridescence not iridescent iridescence yeah
because it's plural oh no iridescence because it is a noun yeah and it's plural no if it was a noun
and it was plural it would be iridescences i think is that right i think iridesopods we we have some
funny names for easter cons these days anyway the 2026 easter con iridescence has risen phoenix-like
from the ashes and is getting on with things. And they have announced they've opened their hotel
booking, which is probably the most exciting to many of you. So if you're a member, you would
have had an email telling you how to book a hotel room. And if you haven't had any emails from them,
because they did send an email saying in a little while, but you're sending an email telling you how
to book a room, then you should check in your spam folder and whitelist them because the way to
book is to click on the link in your email. You have to be a member of the convention before
booking rooms. They've got quite a good rate for the hotel. There's a rate with or without breakfast
and I think the way in which the rates are particularly good is that the single room rate
is 50 quid lower than the double room rate.
So very unusually for Easter cons,
you can actually get a big discount if you're on your own
rather than having to pay almost twice
what a couple would for the same room.
No, almost twice what each half of the couple would
for the same room.
They have also opened applications for bursaries
if you'd like to go to Easter con,
but you would need some help to make that happen.
The deadline for that is the 31st of October.
So you've just got a little over a week after this episode goes out.
Their volunteer form is open and they're encouraged,
even if you've made some formal arrangement, informal arrangement to volunteer where you always do.
They've suggested you fill in the volunteer form so they know that and know who you're working for and what you're doing.
And speaking of who you're working for and what you're doing,
there should be merchandise out by the time this episode goes live.
So you should be able to buy an iridescence T-shirt.
Who's doing the merchandise, Alison?
Well, it's using Espania's lovely design, but I'm making all of the merchandise happen.
But I haven't actually done it yet.
So it's a kind of theoretically I'm making all of the merchandise happen in the next few days.
So what you're saying is we should hassle John by DM about his opinions on the raid.
But if you really want an Iridescence T-shirt, you should hassle Alison.
There'll be a link in the show notes when this episode goes live and you'll just be able to click on it and buy it.
Am I right in thinking that the single room discount is because the Hilton is one of those weird hotels that actually does have some actual single rooms that you can't put two people in?
We were talking about this. Once upon a time, there were two hotels. This is like a long time ago.
And they loved each other very much.
Called the Metropole and the Warwick. And they were both owned by the Metropole, but the Warwick was full of really tiny singles.
And I think that might still be the case, but other people say, oh no, it's all been completely
refurbished since then. So I think probably it is those smaller rooms and they'll be sold as
executive singles or very, very small doubles, but they might be proper singles.
What is an executive single and why is it different than a single?
An executive single has a bed that is bigger than three foot, but one side of it is shoved up
against the wall. Ah, okay. In general. For executives. No, just not absolutely. But I mean,
don't quote me. They might just be regular singles. You know this whole podcast is on the record,
right? I will be going around telling people, look, Alice and Scott told me that's what an
executive single is. And if I ever get an executive single where the bed is not up against the wall,
and again, I will be in your DMs. Yep. That bed will be first against the wall when the
comes. I was thinking about
non-con from last week
and thinking, ooh, I could go to non-con
and I could go and stay in the bullet again.
Speaking of hotels where the rooms were.
Rather pokey.
Could just go to Belfast.
What, without visiting a convention?
Yeah, we'll make our own con
with cocktail bars and breakfasts.
That's crazy.
Crazy talk, Liz.
Crazy talk. Seems unlikely,
doesn't it? But I am a bit worried you're going to start
proposing cons in Belfast
just solely so that you can go to that hotel i mean there are worse reasons so have you put your
hotel rooms then yes yep have you no are you going don't know that's why i haven't booked
um so i'm not a member yet um i think the first night is non-refundable it is so yeah if you know
you're going go and book if you're not sure then you might want to hold off unless you want to
accidentally lose a night's room payment.
I'm sure there are hotels in the area that will sell you a refundable booking.
Yes, although when I looked at the Premier Inn,
there's a little note basically explaining that you can't cut through the car park anymore.
So it might not be such a good wheeze.
People were talking about the Moxie?
Yeah, that's just next door, isn't it?
I don't know where it is.
It's between the Metropole and the NEC, right?
It's on that block there.
Yeah, so when you come out of the big, like, massive bank of doors,
the Moxie is, like, right ahead of you, like, on the left.
I seem to recall hearing from someone, I think at a UK Games Expo,
that the Moxie is a bit crap, but I don't know if that's actually true,
and it might be getting confused with someone complaining about the Moxie in Glasgow,
and, like, I don't know.
So, again, don't quote me, listeners.
Fortunately, none of this is being recorded, so it's okay.
The Moxie is what it is.
I liked the Glasgow one quite a lot because it had...
If you're there for a convention, if you have a lot of luggage,
then you're going to struggle because there isn't any spare space in your room for your luggage.
But otherwise, it was completely fine.
Whereas regular listeners will know that the Hilton Metropole is quite nice.
It's not Hilton Metropole, is it?
Hilton Birmingham. Hilton Birmingham Metropole.
I'm getting confused with the Brighton Metropole.
Hilton Birmingham Metropole is quite nice, but has no drawers.
Yeah, well, the Moxie doesn't have drawers.
What it does have is if you wake up in the middle of the night and stumble to the loo,
it has automatic underbed lighting that comes on,
which just I thought was the best thing ever, and I want every hotel to have that now.
I'm clearly the old person in this conversation.
I mean, I can turn the light on.
Yeah, but if you turn the light on, you'll wake up Stephen.
I mean, you won't wake up Stephen, but I will.
I won't wake up Stephen.
I have so many questions about what you two are doing in hotel rooms at conventions, but I ain't asking.
But, okay, I've been in plenty of places where there's, like, underbed lighting, and I agree that is quite neat,
but I also can just turn it on with a switch.
I don't need it to pop on automatically and scare the life out of me at 2am.
I think I don't necessarily want automatic lights, but I'm not.
It's fine.
I made four different thumbs-ups appear.
yes so listeners write in if you're going to iridescence um we will see you all there
iridescence is sharing its hotel with an anime convention which is called
something it's definitely called something yes harui con hawai con harui con h-a-r-u-h-i um
next spring 35th of april at the hilton birmingham metropole yes and i wanted to ask do you think
that they might do some sort of membership sharing between the two conventions given that they are in
the same hotel didn't they talk about trying to do something but presumably they're still
uh chatting about it and not ready to announce i guess like if they could do some sort of mutual
access to the vendor areas that would be neat because vendors like that. I think there should
be some scope here because I was assuming that it would be a gate show and primarily selling day
passes but it's not. It's tickets for a whole weekend. They are £75. That doesn't sound very
different from the Easter con. It's three days not four days but yeah they probably need to go and
talk about it. It feels complicated. I think it would be neat to have something because it would
be you know i am probably never going to go to an anime con but it would be neat to be able to go
and see bits of it i mean i'm assuming that i will get to see a lot of cosplay anyway but it would be
neat if we could kind of arrange something so i could see at least bits of it and similarly the
other way around we might attract people who would quite like to see bits of uh eastercom anyway i'm
sure that is in the works because they must be talking to each other a little bit um you'd think
so we will wait and see it's not that long now is it no it's true it's not six months six months
terrifyingly we are halfway since easter con and halfway to easter con yeah no it's it's kind of
terrifying how quickly it comes around yeah things come around faster and faster is it october already
what happened to the year just before we move on from easter con one other thing is that
applications for the art show
for dealers and for fan tables are open
and we will also have a link to that in the show notes
dear listeners
what about for suggesting program items
if for example you have some kind of podcast
that you might want to do a live show of
at eastercom
I... that's a great question
yeah iridescence right in
I'm not sure I've seen that yet
I don't think that has gone out
and I suspect it won't go out for a little bit
but I suspect it is coming
But yes, because I haven't.
I think the programme team is like beginning to spool up in earnest.
So stuff like that, I think, will come in the near future.
And when it does come online, we will, of course, request Octop Live if you want it through the appropriate channels and not by...
Asking on the podcast.
Wishing it into existence on the podcast.
Definitely done that before.
Exactly.
Because we're good people.
Yeah, but as a programme person, you know, it winds me up something chronic.
Indeed.
I'm not a member.
Ah!
so uh we're gonna talk about some other forthcoming conventions as this episode drops the next
imminent conventions are bristol con world fantasy con which is in brighton and armada con which is
in plymouth so um if you're not already planning to go then it might be a bit late although maybe
not you might still be able to get your act together and head to those but if you do please
write in and let us know what you thought of them and we're already we're always very interested to
hear uh from listeners who go to conventions we're not going to so we can live vicariously through
you i've never been to plymouth so you know just write and tell us about plymouth if you like
i've been to plymouth liz uh i went to see the world fireworks championships oh well yeah i can't
of what year it was the British Firework Championships I've been to see the British
Firework Championships I saw the World Firework Championships when they were on Scaveling Beach
in 1990 right next door to the Worldcon which was also in Scaveling in 1990 so that was very exciting
that is quite a good co-location it was if any future people are thinking about Worldcon bids
and want to look up the calendar yeah yeah yeah because you could just we all went down to the
each to watch fireworks at the night and that was one of the things that was good about the Dutch
Walk-On. The other thing that was good about the Dutch Walk-On was the Rice Staffel. I remember we
went to see the British Firework Championships were in Plymouth I think almost every year and
when I went there was square fireworks and I don't know how you do that but it was very good.
Ooh yeah they had all sorts of magical stuff in 1990 but I mean that was
that was a very long time ago so it probably wouldn't be quite so magical now.
I believe Bristol Con is happening the day after I get back from cottaging.
So I think, so Hispania is going, but I am not.
So maybe she will write in and tell us all about it.
Rare opportunity to hang out with Hispania without having to also talk to John.
Yeah.
I mean, it is a pretty big, pretty big opportunity.
That was a bit mean, but I thought it was funny.
So I thought you were just like noting entirely seriously that this was a good opportunity for listeners.
I was going to say, we talked a little bit last time about Pictcon and Novicon, which are both in the same week in mid-November.
Pictcon is in Perth and is being run by Pharah and looks to be quite successful.
Pharah who?
Pharah Mendelssohn. Pharah tells us that it has met its membership targets, so that's quite good.
And Novicon, I think lots of people are going to be at Novicon, including John and me, but not Liz.
we will be doing octothop live and we will have a stunt liz on sunday morning and we've been
promoted we are not in the off-piece program this time we are in the main program we're very excited
yes and our stunt liz befits the change of locale yeah that's what i was going to say i think it's
not so much that we've moved into the main program because octothop is more popular than it used to
be it's more that our stunt Liz is more popular than we are our stunt Liz is I would argue more
popular than Liz oh oh that's harsh I can tell you that I am I am hopping mad that I don't get to be
on the podcast with the person who is stunt me yeah that was Tommy Ferguson right also I I mean
I think it says more about the stunt Liz is a profile than it does about Liz's profile I didn't
think i was being too mean but um but yeah sorry liz it's fair i was quite mean about you john
uh but yes we will be doing we were doing uh ultra thought live which will be on sunday morning
because we didn't actually say we just mentioned it and then didn't say anything about it last
episode uh so it's good that we've mentioned it again this episode but yeah that will be good
have we got we got another episode before that because we can just drop progressively more hints
about who the stunt leader is.
I think there's going to be one more episode, isn't there?
I think so, yeah.
Otherwise, I am also on programme.
There's a panel about Morris dancing,
which might actually involve a workshop on Morris dancing.
I think the full details of this have not been worked out yet,
but there will be sticks.
So that's my other programme item at Novicon.
Excellent.
I think I'm moderating some mathematicians.
One of the mathematicians, I believe, is Nicholas Jackson.
But I don't know if the programme's set in stone yet,
so I shan't say too much more in case it's in flux.
Oh, no, maybe I shouldn't say.
Maybe I should say that next time.
I'm sure that...
No, we're wetting the listener's appetite, Alison.
It's good.
We're getting them excited.
There will be something about Morris dancing, I'm pretty sure.
Yeah.
Even if it's just Alison drunk in the bar.
Taking a Melodian with me.
I don't normally take Melodians to conventions for obvious reasons.
not for not for any program item she just wants to hold a melodion it's not just also playing it
they're quite loud you know i do know oh yeah no you would know wouldn't you i i keep forgetting
that you you were brought up in this community and did at one point one point uh make a brief
attempt to learn to play the melodion and then stopped probably to the you know happiness of
everyone in the same house then the other upcoming one which is a little bit further in the future
is Satellite 9.
So it is the 18th anniversary of Satellite this year, I believe.
It's been going for a while.
And I think it turned 18 as we record.
But the next convention is in May, so it will be 18 and a half.
Old enough to drink.
I am also planning to go to Satellite.
That's the plan.
It's not very organised yet, but that is our plan.
I'm looking forward to it.
It should be good.
It's a lot closer to me than it used to be.
That's not because they've moved venue to the Clayton Hotel in Glasgow, it's because I've moved venue from Southampton to Newcastle, which is quite a lot further north.
Those of you who attend WSFUS business meetings, which I assume is all of you who are listeners now since we've introduced you to them so much,
you may notice at the end of the WSFUS business meeting agenda are financial reports from all the past WorldCons and NASFICs,
which I suspect most of you have not read.
So we thought we would go through some of them and pull out what we think is of interest about convention finances,
because we may be slightly more interested in convention finances than a lot of you.
It's not impossible.
I find it interesting, right?
If you want to know how much money it costs to put on a Worldcon,
we generally put out a big public thing about how much money it costs to put on a Worldcon.
Some conventions break it down into a lot of categories, some don't.
But I think we're probably a little bit more public about the funds that are needed
than some kind of cons of equivalent size.
Yeah, I'd agree with that.
I think that's probably true.
But yeah, and there are some interesting things.
So one thing is that you have to keep or you're supposed to keep sending accounts until you have spent all your money.
And I noticed that Sasquan, who did pretty well in 2015 because they had a lot of supporting members because we're going back to sad puppy times, still have over $20,000.
And last year they spent $500.
So at this rate, they're still going to be sending reports to the World Cup until about 2065.
it sounds like they might just be putting all their money basically into a scholarship fund
for sending people to com-running conventions which is good but maybe you should just do this
at this point and not have to send in accounts every year yes i mean i think there's a general
point here which is that well-organized one-off events wrap up their finances and close their
books and are done with it in reasonable time keeping chunks of money around yes they fester
right stuff happens to the prime candidates for things not going in a good direction yeah and i
in an ideal world i think if you want to um if you want to have this money go forward for longer
You do something like the 2005 Worldcon did,
where they gave a lot of the money to the League of Fan Funds to get that started.
And that meant that that convention could wrap up,
but the money could continue to be used.
There's no reason you can't form a subsequent organization
called the Spakan Conrunning Support Company or something
and have that take the funds from the Worldcon,
but that would let you wrap the Worldcon up
in a way that just having it go infinitely is not quite as good.
Well, they have given all their funds to the parent organization.
So, I mean, part of this also is I do not fully understand
how US convention finances work and all this stuff you have to do to be like 501c.
But it sounds like they have basically got a parent organization
and SaskOne now doesn't exist.
The parent organization has the money, but they still fill out reports.
So possibly they're just doing this because they're very conscientious
and you could say, look, we gave the last bits of it to this other organisation, they're doing it.
But maybe we should have a thing saying like, once you get down below like, you know, $20,000,
you can just submit a final report and be done.
But that seems strange because, you know, things like the trip report bounties that are given by
Skiffy, that money is funds from an old Worldcon that ended up back with Skiffy for that purpose.
They're not still reporting that through the Worldcon business meeting.
but they do say that they keep the sasquan fund separate from the rest of the seattle westacon
committee so maybe that's why so i guess it's nice they did send a report because uh like san antonio
did not send a report and mid-american 2 did not send a report possibly they have finished
i didn't go back far enough to check if they sent something in previous years so they didn't send
anything in 2024 so probably they they're done and finished mid-american 2 did but they only had
five thousand dollars so probably they're done and finished as well yeah and so there was not a more
updated version of the agenda that i could find i could be missing one but there were no reports
from con zealand or from chengdu submitted to 2025 um they did submit reports to 2024 and of the end
of 2024 con zealand had an amount of money which i'm just gonna have to go and convert because i
think this might be in New Zealand dollars. Okay. So I cannot do any sort of conversion from New
Zealand dollars to like regular dollars or pounds in my head. That's fair. Yeah, about half, aren't
they? Yes, they're about half. Okay. Yeah, 43p. So as of the end of 2024, Con Zealand appeared to
have about 140,000 pounds left. That's quite a lot. That's a lot compared to how much money is spent
on science fiction fandom in New Zealand.
Presumably, I don't know for a fact,
but I assume that because it was literally impossible to hold the event,
they got refunds and were allowed to wriggle out of contract commitments.
So maybe that reflects the fact that they had some money
that didn't need to go to the venue.
I don't know.
Intriguing.
I think I remember that there was quite a lot of uncertainty
and so they probably kept a lot in reserve in case they had to pay out for certain things they
contractually obligated to but at this point yeah they gave quite a chunk of money to Glasgow 2024
but we don't know what they've done with it since so yeah it's just generally interesting that
they're obviously cons that made um you know have ended up with quite a big surplus and some of them
like Dublin 2019 have kind of slowly passed it out for good causes and wound down and they are done.
Whereas 2020 still has quite a lot left to go.
I think last time we looked, the 2020 Eastercon also had quite a lot of money sitting around as a surplus.
So we're not sure what's happened to that.
So, I mean, we're on the same theme here, but of interest is that Chengdu also did not submit accounts to 2025.
And their accounts are interesting because they show that, you know, Glasgow declined their pass along, but they did then basically, I think, give extra pass along to Seattle.
And their accounts look pretty standard.
But the main thing that's of interest to Chengdu is that they've managed to get $132,000.
And I say dollars because they're basically $132,000 overseas.
And then I think about $900 in China.
So this is probably because of all the difficulty of moving money back and forth and how many memberships ended up in being bought overseas and ending up in the US somewhere.
But basically, we just ended up with this big surplus, which is sitting in somewhere in the US, presumably, which must be an interesting accounting challenge.
They could use it to pay Dave McCarty's legal fees.
Maybe they could use it to just, you know, buy a load of new trophies and pack them all individually into...
Maybe someone could hand-carry each one over in first class.
Oh yeah, I can imagine how dispatching a bunch of people to China to smuggle things back from China to the US in the current climate.
I mean, I just think there might be the odd logistical problem there, Liz.
I'm not saying you're smuggling it, I'm just saying you carry it. Have you never carried anything weird on a plane, John?
yeah but do you want the risk of having i don't know i don't know i guess my point is i'm not sure
i'd want to explain that to the ice agents or whoever it is at the border no fair enough you'd
probably have to send a u.s citizen yeah but yes no it does seem like a lot of money and i i imagine
there are some quirks with how that money needs to be dispersed but i wonder where that money has
gone in china like i wonder where the chinese pots have gone is that related in the documentation
um i don't think there are large pots of money i think the chinese world can't cost a lot more
money than the amount of money it raised in ticket sales maybe maybe that's the answer i mean if you
look where they've been spending things like um i mean these are the 2024 accounts we don't have
2025, they gave $60,000 of pass along to Seattle. So they're obviously doing well enough that they
were planning to send 30 to both, I think. And there's quite a lot of stuff on there about trophy
shipping and customs, which were presumably incurred after the con. Yeah. So I can't really tell where
all the, like where in particular money went right. It's not like these things are incredibly
detailed. And so the nice thing in 2025 is that Glasgow's account is not only their accounts,
but quite a long note about how they plan to disperse their remaining funds.
So I thought this was quite interesting because basically they're saying,
if you would like some money to sort of, you know, fund something that needs some seed funding,
you want bursaries to attend con running activities,
you want to need seed funding for an event or to do a publication
or to improve inclusiveness at fan activities,
then they will take applications for spending small amounts of funding on that,
which I think is a really good idea.
And they've also said like how they will judge it as well.
So I think that's quite nice and transparent.
And it will be nice to see what they come up with in future years.
And when they kind of say, okay, well, actually here are the 10 things we spent small amounts on in the next few years.
They also have very detailed accounts if anyone wants to dig a bit more into what the accounts look like for a WorldCom.
Except they're so detailed that now I can't find out how much money they've got.
It's good to have process.
Like, it's good to make it clear, because I think if you don't have process and if you don't have a process people can follow, it would be very easy to disperse all of these funds to people who are already known to the higher ups.
And I think this way, groups who might not be as known or who might have been inspired by Glasgow can potentially read this and be like, oh, we could apply.
I mean, I guess the counterpoint to that would be, I don't know how many people are reading the WUSFUS financial reports, but I think it's better than not.
I mean, I think it's a lot better than not having these procedures written out.
So that's really good.
Yeah, I mean, I presume the main person reading these financial things is me at this point.
Liz, what money are you applying for?
It does say that they should be focused on UK and EU con running.
So sadly, I cannot apply to fund the Bangkok Convention.
And that's it.
Basically, there's like Buffalo Nasfik, but I don't care about that.
One of the things that Glasgow have done with their surplus is that they have put together a bursary scheme for Smofcon.
So I applied to that and I've got some money to go to Smofcon, which is very lovely because I probably wouldn't be able to justify it without that.
And so I'm off to Sweden.
And yeah, I'm looking forward to sort of working on all that.
Listeners might. I think I mentioned on a previous podcast where I was intending to work with Tammy Coxson on the Hugo team.
But I've stepped down from that because I don't think I'll have time to do that and some professional commitments and also be a Clark Award judge and work on programme.
So unfortunately, something I had to give.
But I'm looking forward to talking to people about programme and stuff at SmothCon very much.
It will be good.
I'd love to be able to go to SmothCon, but I think it's just not quite happening for us this year.
I did love the one in Lisbon, and I'm sure the one in Stockholm will be equally lovely.
There may be a bit colder and darker.
We can always sneak in a discussion of seasons.
Oh, always.
Even when Liz says, it's dark here, don't get distracted.
We can manage.
Sorry, I got distracted by something and wasn't really listening to you.
Or did you get distracted by more financial details, Liz?
Yeah, I wondered if I was missing an updated one, but I wasn't missing an updated version.
Of which one?
Well, I wondered if there was a new version of the Seattle report, which might have some
future stuff in, but the note actually is on Glasgow saying they added something which
I could see.
So, nope, I apologize if I have missed an updated one that one of your treasurers submitted
after the business deadline, but I can't find it.
that is fair yeah it's it's it's interesting to read them because you one you get to see
an idea of how much it actually costs to put on world cons and where all the money goes and also
an idea of like how differently they sort of approach spending their surplus funding yeah
thank you very much for doing that deep dive liz it was honestly my pleasure although john is going
to court to smothcon so what are you two volunteering for over the next while allison's
doing Eastcon merchandise. Doing a little bit of Eastcon merchandise, but I'm also doing the
newsletter for Eastcon, not that we've actually sorted out any of the details yet. I might also
not be volunteering for LA. I'm having a think about it. I keep finding things that I have
volunteered to do and go, oh, I'll tell you one thing I'm volunteering, which is that I have been
past part of the archive for a very long running APA, and I am in the process of scanning that.
And as always with scanning, it turns out to be significantly more trouble than you think it's going to be.
So there's 300 issues and I have scanned two and a half of them so far.
That. So you are a solid 0.8% of the way through.
Yeah, something like that. Don't tell me that. It'll just distress me.
Oh, sorry. Ignore that I said that.
No, no, no. It's fine.
When you get to this bit in the edit, just put your fingers over your ears.
No, I'll cover my ears. No. So I got so far with it and went, oh, no, this is clearly going to be more work than I thought it was.
I mean, I knew it was going to be quite a bit of work.
I mean, I'm hoping that the process that is currently extremely non-automatic will become much more, much more automatic once I've got the hang of it.
But at the moment, it's taking a lot of fiddling.
I think all of this is evidence that I've been doing too many different things and should probably not do as many things.
And the way to do that is to not do as many things.
I advise not doing anything. It's very relaxing.
Yeah, that.
Shall we do picks? Liz, did you do any reading on holiday?
Yeah. Guess what? I'm going to pick a book.
before you pick your book tommy picked a sequel to a previous liz pick so he did have you got any
messages for tommy or um you know thoughts on the sequel uh he's a man of good taste but i haven't
read the sequel yet so no but it was framed from you two as uh oh nick harkaway that's someone i
should get around to reading and i my comment is yes you're only like 15 years late onto the nick
carquay bandwagon there's no there's no time that's too late to get acquainted with a good
author that's true i've read the second um speaking of previous picks i have read the second robert
robert jackson bennett a drop of corruption also liked it a lot continue to like the series
fortunately that is not my pick it is one of the books i own holiday but i wasn't about to pick it
which is good because i couldn't could i yeah you could have i just not have said that you do you
we'd have taken that bit out and then you could have picked it and then i'd have gone oh by a
strange coincidence i'd also say that i mean i can't pick this because john basically picked it
but i did read the third agent chaykoski book in the time philosophers it's good isn't it i mean
it's hard read but i'm enjoying it it's very good it's best one i think i just want i just want
everyone i i it's really difficult to read because oh my god there are a lot of people making a lot
decisions in that book yes but i love where it is going or where i think i think it is going anyway
but no spoilers so that's very good and you should read it and then nominate for things but actually
i'm going to pick a book that i did not think i would like but i did so i'm going to pick it
as part of my trip for why i was missing last time i took a train overnight a mere 16 hours
and basically on that train I read an entire giant fantasy book. Giant fantasy books especially
the first book in a series which is all about an empire where there is mysterious competition going
on for who gets to be the next emperor and they're all from like different houses represented by
different animals and there's going to be intrigue and collusion between different candidates and
lots of trials and then the last one will obviously be surprise ending or something
which sounds very much like not my type of thing but actually it's great so i read the raven scholar
by antonia hodgson which i think is a debut novel and is the first of the eternal path trilogy but
yeah it is a an empire where the idea is that empire emperors are term limited and then there
is a competition by kind of the best warriors from each of the different houses to decide who replaces
the emperor but it's actually really really good there's lots of intrigue it's a very smart
protagonist i really like that kind of the protagonist is really good morally good or
well written well written because she basically she is from one of the lower classes and has risen to
a great height and therefore like a lot of people dislike her for that even though she's really good
at her job which would make her insufferable if she were not also an extremely fallible protagonist
who is aware of the choices she has made to get there
and that this is not a case of everyone was against her
so she did all the right things to prove them wrong.
It's like everyone was against her
but some of the things she's done,
you can see why they think she is kind of cutthroat
getting her way to the top.
So I did really like the protagonist
and if you don't,
then you're not going to want to read
a 650-page fantasy book about them.
That, yeah, fair.
But also there is like a murder mystery
going on in the background
and I like fantasy murder mysteries
and the murder mystery is strong enough
to be an interesting part on its own
and what kind of the plots
and all the clues that get unraveled from that
mean that kind of the contest is a little less
the contest becomes less important
than figuring out what is going on
at the heart of the empire
Cool
And it kind of comes to a conclusion
I'm sure there are going to be
books two and presumably two and three
and how many
but I think if you only read one
you would probably be satisfied.
I think that's a sign of a good first
a good first
instalment in a trilogy, right?
Like it should probably work as its
own book as well as the
first part of the trilogy. That sounds neat.
It is very long. I mean
a little bit too long, but I regularly
say that 300 page books are too long and this is
a little bit too long but not like 400 pages
too long, so. Yeah, it's fair.
Yeah, that's reasonable.
Alison, do you want to do your pick?
I am picking Here East
which is an area of East London it's not quite Stratford it's about a 20 minute walk from the
Stratford stations and it's about 10 minutes walk from Hackneywick and it is served by
exactly one corporation bus and and kind of a local it runs its own bus service where it
gleefully says you have to pay even if you have a London transport travel card so we didn't try it
we just kind of looked at it um here east has a lot of interesting things but i want to pick out
two one is the new v&a east storehouse which is the v&a's attempt to kind of explain to the public
what museum stores do and why they're a good thing when you hear that such and such a museum has a
million items in storage why that's not just a terrible idea they should sell it all off or give
it all back in the case of all the stuff that was acquired under strange circumstances. And they have
quite a lot of items on display. It kind of looks like a cross between the Ikea warehouse and the
final scene of the Raiders of the Lost Ark. They have some enormous installations in corners. So
you'll kind of turn a corner and instead of more crates, there will be like an enormous stage
backdrop or a piece of a Moorish palace roof and things like this. It is very strange, very
interesting, free, well worth going to have a look at and it also serves as a place where you can order
things from the V&A's catalogue to have a close look at. They don't actually make all of their
collection available for this purpose. The lady said oh the other things for storage that you
can't look at are in a vault which seems likely I am going back in a week or so to view a live
performance from the National Video Archive of Performance where they record theatre shows and
this is one which was not made available for DVD but I want to see it because I did not see it in
its live run and you can arrange to go and watch it at the V&A storehouse you know obviously they
could just send you a they could just send you a link but they don't do it that way they do it by
making it available in the vna east um and then we kind of had a wander around here east after
looking at that and came across a sign saying umbilical conrad shore cross free entry and you
know one of the things about wandering around places is it's always good to follow up signs
like that and see what it is the chap on the desk said do you know what this is and i said i think
It's an installation. And so it proved.
Shawcross is a sculptor, I guess, artist, who is fascinated by rope making machines and has been making successively larger ones.
And this one has some 250 spools of thread which are being formed into a massive rope that then trails across the floor in real time.
except when we actually went, it was not working.
It had broken earlier that day.
It is a commission from the University of Tasmania
and it's going to be shipped to the far side of the world.
So if you're a listener and you're in Tasmania,
you'll be able to see it next year.
But in the meantime, you can see it in its kind of trial run
in here east until the beginning of November.
So you've just got another week or so after this episode goes out
to go and have a look at that.
But I'm mentioning it.
I'm mentioning it because it appeared last week's cover art was the three of us,
Tommy, John, me and Tommy as Norns.
And the Norns are weaving the rope of fate.
And in this case, I made it to the rope from Conrad Shawcross's Umberleichel.
And it made no sense.
So I thought I better explain it on the podcast as part of my pick.
But well worth going to see if you like giant installations of semi-industrial art engines
making a point about something.
I'm not quite sure what.
But the idea is that it will spin rope forever, only requiring new spools once a year.
And the rope will gradually create a massive quantity of rope in this atrium in Tasmania.
So well worth seeing for nothing.
And there was also a pinball.
The other thing here East had was a pinball, an arcade bar called Four Quarters, where they would sell you 18 US quarters for £10, which is the worst exchange rate of all time.
And we played 18 quarters worth of pinball, which did not take us very long because we're not very good at pinball anymore.
Here East, a part of London, a new part of London, a new neighbourhood that's not quite finished yet.
That sounds very interesting.
And yeah, if I am in London, I might try and go and see it.
We shall see.
Is this the first time we've picked a neighbourhood?
I've picked an entire country.
I'm not sure if I've ever picked a neighbourhood.
Could be, couldn't it?
I don't think I've picked a neighbourhood before.
No, I think you've picked, like, the control room of Battersea Power Station and so on.
Yeah.
I don't think I've picked a neighbourhood.
I might be misremembering.
John, you've got to pick.
I'm going to pick a video game.
I'm going to pick Tactical Breach Wizards,
which was one of the finalists for the Hugo Award for Best Game or Interactive Work,
and is quite good.
So this is a game that is only available on PC, which is slightly annoying,
but I played on my little brother's laptop, which he gave me for free because it's knackered,
but it will play this, so that's good.
and this is a game in which you play wizards who are basically on a SWAT team and you play a turn
based game to try and defeat the enemies in various situations and do good stuff it's basically x-com
but with wizards and it's really fun and it's kind of also quite funny I did there were a
real especially there's a point in the game at which you start to play anxiety dreams so um
there's a mission for each character where you end up teaming up with yourself and you go through
missions with two of you and they're the anxiety dreams and in one of them um the character the
main character jen asks her dream doppelganger why she's being so mean to her and the answer is
because you're the only person you can't have any compassion for and um and i was like oh that's
that's quite real um but i like that very much start out with two playable characters who are
jen who is a witch who is very good at pushing people around quite literally uh and then you've
also got zan who can kind of do an overwatch sort of thing called predictive shot which is very
useful but he can also make clones of himself that kind of shimmer into life and then when they're
when they're shot they shimmer away again but you end up with this thing where you can start sending
armies of clones or armies of like projections to their death because there's a couple of perks you
could unlock that let you do some really quite degenerate stuff which was very fun i just really
liked it it's it's funny it's kind of poignant um it's it's it's it's really the gameplay loop is
really solid um and yeah i just thought it was wonderful spent about 20 hours on it i think
and i'm kind of like oh they should do more of that because that was very good i don't know if
They will do more of that.
But if they did, I would probably play more.
So, yeah, I recommend it.
It was very good.
And I think Ed Moreland recommended it when we asked people to write in with Hugo's suggestions.
Must have been about six, eight months ago now.
So, yeah, thanks, Ed.
You were right.
Honestly, I think you could have just said, like, XCOM with wizards.
And I would have been like, yeah, all right.
I mean, it's fair.
It's fair.
So it's also on Steam Deck.
So you can play it on PC or Steam Deck.
Do you have a Steam Deck? No.
I do not. I have an old knackered laptop.
Is Steam Deck a Linux?
Steam Deck is, yeah, they're Linux machines that have like a open source translation layer on them that Valve contributes to.
Doesn't that mean you could put it on other Linux boxes if you were?
I mean, yeah, but I think we've talked about this on the podcast before.
Life is too short.
It was much easier to get an old knackered laptop off my brother and install it on that.
Yeah, I have an old knackered PC, but I'm not sure.
I think it might be too old for this purpose.
Yeah, I guess there's old and there's knackered and there's old and there's knackered.
So, yeah.
I was considering, well, I saw someone selling a secondhand Steam Deck
and was vaguely considering to get through the Steam backlog of games I don't play
because I don't have a PC anymore.
yeah uh yeah listeners if you have a steam deck and you really like it right in or if you hate it
right in as well but you know we're gonna get a lot of we're going to get a lot of letters liz and
you're going to read them out oh no i don't think that many of our listeners have a steam deck
do any of our listeners have a steam deck if you have a steam deck write in i bet ming does
at least one because someone wrote in about it didn't they that was the odd thought podcast
and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me
no i mean i think the solution is to actually eat more carrots my eyesight is great john
because of shooting lasers into it yeah um but carrots are specifically for night vision right
and do the lasers help with night vision the lasers do not help with night vision to be fair
fact the opposite you know it's all a myth don't you what everything you are all figments of my
imagination carrot supporting your night vision may be propaganda ah it's big carrot so in the war
they wanted people to meet they wanted people to eat more carrots
listen carefully children auntie allison's talking about the war again
no no they wanted to eat more carrots so they did proper guarantee saying that carrots would improve
your vision and simultaneously they wanted the germans not to know how we were finding their
airplanes at night which was radar and so they put it about that the pilot's night vision was
being improved because of all the carrots that they ate that was not true it was radar i see
it's because it's because if you have if you don't have enough vitamin a you lose your night blindness
and carrots contain vitamin a so they don't let you i think there's like they don't let you see
like infrared but if you have a vitamin a deficiency they can help restore your night
vision from the vitamin a deficiency yes but anyway i'll give you a link the propaganda was
that it let you see like an actual cat which is untrue but then i don't think anyone seriously
thought that was true because i've never been able to do that and i've eaten carrots for a lot of my
life and i feel like if carrots did give you literal superpowers we would have noticed but
radar does is the point maybe i'm wrong um if i had if carrot if eating carrots gave me radar
then yes that would also be fair comment yes i have got i i have got a but if you are i guess
the key point is here if you are struggling enough that you need under bed lighting to get to the
loo in your hotel room you might need to eat some carrots because you might have vitamin a deficiency
or you might need to go to the optician okay i don't have vitamin a deficiency eat lots of carrots
but John, I'm 60 now.
Yeah, I was astonished by how much my,
the kind of edges of my vision knocked off in my 50s.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space
by Kevin MacLeod and Competech.com
used under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.