Amazingly, creating VR social spaces is one of the things that I am particularly interested in.
You'd never guess.
It turns out I was born to run parties without having to tidy up the house.
Either before or afterwards.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very seventh episode of Octothorpe,
a podcast about science fiction and science fiction fandom.
We are sponsored this week by Stow Shirts.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
For those listeners who are reading the news and Twitter and Facebook and sort of generally staying up to date,
there have been widespread protests against police brutality and the treatment of black people in the United States of America
for most of the last week.
Here at Octothorpe, we are aware that a lot of you may be listening to us to get away from the terrible and awful news happening out there in the wider world.
But equally, we as a trio feel quite strongly about social justice.
And we are very much standing with the protesters.
As we are all white, we are not necessarily the best people to tell you where to go to educate yourself.
So if the listeners of Octothorpe have any suggestions for literature or for places to donate money,
then please send us locks and tell us where we can donate money and what we can recommend to our listeners in order to help them educate themselves about everything that's happening at the moment.
If you want to start educating yourself about black writers of speculative fiction, you could go and look at FIRE magazine and we'll put a link in the show notes to that.
And there's also the Black Specfic report, which reports on kind of the state of the industry.
The writer's survey, I think, is quite American-centric.
I'm not sure about the contributors to FIRE MAG, but I believe it is based in the USA.
So if anyone knows of any equivalent initiatives in the UK, I'd like to hear about them.
And I should say I've had a couple of people, as always happens when there's anything trending, getting in touch with me and saying,
have you made this badge or this T-shirt or this thing?
And I would suggest that you should go and get your protest gear from black and minority ethnic owned businesses.
In letter of comment news, we had a conversation of comment with Lillian Edwards at the first Thursday pub meeting,
in which she told us that Ian Sorensen says that my microphone is better now, which is true.
It is. Hurrah.
Last time we recorded was in the middle of Balticon, which was being held virtually.
It is the Baltimore SF Group's convention.
It's held every year.
And they did a variety of programming and social spaces on the internet.
We decided not to talk about it last week because it was still happening.
But what did we think of Balticon?
Did we go to Balticon?
Liz, it's rather the wrong time zone for you, I understand.
Yes, really everything is in the wrong time zone for me.
But see, many, many podcasts previous to me complaining about this.
So I didn't.
It's like I keep meaning to go to things, but it's one that they're in the wrong time zone.
But also that every time there is a convention, I have to then work out what is its local time zone?
And how does that compare to my time zone?
And what time actually is it?
And usually I never get to the third stage.
So I have to say one thing I would implore virtual conventions to do is to maybe put somewhere in small letters their time in like UTC or something, just to make it easy for us all to work out what time it would be in our own time zone.
That is a good idea, actually.
That should be a thing that happens.
I'm sure people from Con Zealand are listening to this podcast.
I am not sure people from Con Zealand are listening to this podcast.
I was intending to spend quite a lot of my weekend at those conventions, both at Wiscon and Balticon, and it mostly didn't happen.
And I'm not entirely sure why not.
I kind of dropped into the discords a bit and they were fine.
But I never found like the buzzing Zoom party of my dreams or anything of that kind.
And I didn't go to any program items because I have a problem with my life at the moment, which is that for all that I'm locked down and can't do any of the things I would normally do, I am incredibly busy all the time.
I have no idea how this has happened, but it clearly has happened.
And I'm surrounded by things I should be doing all of the time.
Yes.
And so I didn't get to a lot of it.
I did talk a little.
I understand that Balticon was an enormous success and I talked a little bit to some people who had had a good time and they really liked lots of things about the way that it worked.
My wife, Espania, also attended Balticon and she wrote a very excellent blog post about it.
And she basically sent me a text message saying, I didn't lock, but here's a blog post.
So I will include a link to the blog post in the show notes and you can go and read her thoughts on everything.
Espania did an awful lot of socializing on Discord in the text chat.
So she had quite a different opinion of it than me and Alison did, which is interesting.
She, I think, thought it worked very well.
But she also went to some of the Zoom parties and she thought that that was that was good.
Right.
And I also talked to the Glasgow in 2024 team who said it was a lot of fun, but not very many people came to our room party.
So we're now worried about room parties at Con Zealand and will you run them all?
And I said, no, I would not run them all, but I will run one.
And they said it won't be very difficult because only a very few people will come.
And I'm like, not if I'm running it.
So I'm telling you now I'm going to have an awesome and enormous room party at Con Zealand.
And it will be timed at like, I don't know, eight o'clock in the morning UK time.
But, you know, just day drinking.
It's the best.
I will say that the problem I think the Glasgow in 2024 room party at Balticon had was that I did not know it was on.
So I did not attend.
And I feel as someone who is a pre-supporter of Glasgow in 2024 and man who was at Balticon,
I perhaps should be in the middle of the Venn diagram of people who heard about this room party.
So I do think there might have been a slight problem with the communication there,
because I would have been there with bells on had I realised it was happening.
I think you had to look down a long chain of information on Discord to find the Discord channel that was Glasgow in 2024 and then go to that.
And I think there was an issue with multiple nested Discords and possibly rather too many of them.
I think part of the problem is that, like, I don't know why they didn't advertise it on the Glasgow in 2024 mailing list, for instance, which I subscribe to.
If it's a virtual thing that anyone can come to, you can make it buzzing by advertising on your mailing list and then people will come.
I do think that there should have been, and I don't know if there was, I suppose I could double check as we record.
There should have been, like, a room party slash social notice board equivalent on the Balticon Discord.
If there was one of those, I'm not sure I really noticed it, but that probably should have been, like, quite prominent.
I will say, so, I went to Balticon.
I did not go to any Zoom parties because they all started after I went to bed, and I am some sort of lame person who goes to bed before 2am.
But I will say that, generally speaking, I enjoyed the panels I went to.
I went to three or four panels.
I went to a panel on Star Wars, the end of the saga, which I thought was going to be a super great panel, like, looking at the nine-part thing and, like, how it went and what they should have done differently and what they could take away.
And actually devolved into people just talking about their favourite parts from Empire Strikes Back, which, if I'm honest, wasn't quite the angle I wanted from the panel, and I eventually gave up.
I do wish that panellists would read the panel description.
Like, it's my biggest bugbear.
Just, guys, there's a description of what the panel's about.
Please discuss that, because that's why I clicked.
The other two that I went to were both on Tabletop Games, and they were actually really, really, really good.
I really enjoyed the way that the Zoom kind of webinar mode lets you ask questions and stuff.
And then people from those panels were hanging out in the Discord text chat after the panels, and you got to talk to them a bit more there.
And you also got to see people talking about other gaming panels you might not have been to.
And that actually worked really well.
So I think from my perspective, I kind of mostly ignored the dealer's room, the artist's alley, and the fan tables on the Discord.
But the little gaming segment with the different channels worked quite well.
I think next time I would probably advise condensing the Discord channels for the dealers and artists of fan tables a little bit,
because I think there was just way too much variety there.
But I could see why they did that, but I'm not sure it was what they should have done.
But I think these things will be things that we get better at over time.
And I think Balticol is the first place I've seen do this with what I would say was quite a high level of success.
So I thought it was quite good.
I was quite encouraged.
I will say, harking back several minutes at this point,
Glasgow in 2024 did put it on their Twitter feed.
And I wonder if they're trying to do the sort of thing where they keep their mailing list low volume announcements
and announce things like an upcoming party in two days on their Twitter feed.
So that might be part of the issue.
OK, so Twitter is a terrible way to announce anything unless you announce it every half hour.
Because how people use Twitter is that when they're on Twitter, they dip in and a Twitter stream rushes past them.
And nobody's actually reading everything that the 9000 people they follow posts every single time.
It's even worse than Facebook for that.
And at least if you put something on Facebook and lots of people say they are going,
then eventually Facebook will go, oh, yes, that's an event I should probably show you.
Well, and the other thing is that I like the Glasgow in 2024 page on Facebook.
So if they had made it into a Facebook event, presumably they could have invited me and I would have seen it that way.
But I will agree that Twitter is great and I think it's very good for many things.
But the thing I think it's absolutely awful for is announcements.
Because as Alison just said, like the algorithm means that I don't see posts in the order they were published anyway.
And if Twitter doesn't show me that tweet, then there's no way for me to see it.
And the thing I love about mailing lists is that when someone sends me an email, I read the email.
And that is a one to one correspondence, which Facebook and Twitter are sadly algorithmically eroding.
Which I fully understand why they're doing that.
But it does.
It frustrates me when stuff is announced on Twitter.
And I'm like, but I never could have seen that.
Because I have run mailing lists, I now know that when you used to send things to people in the post, you never really understood how many people were reading them.
But when you email people, you do learn how many people are reading them because MailChimp or whatever you're using will give you a read percentage.
And if you're doing well, that read percentage is somewhere in the margin, in the order.
Like a convention mail app will probably get a 40% open rate.
And that's the reason why conventions are kind of going, we'll mail you less.
We'll not use the mailing list.
People just aren't reading their email.
No, and I understand.
I do think it's probably better not to pepper people with emails.
So I do.
I understand the tensions.
But what you actually do to announce things is you have multiple channels.
You get in touch with the people that you want to be at your fantastic buzzing party and say, will you be there?
And they go, yes, of course.
I wouldn't miss it for the world.
And you go, can you tell all your friends on your podcast or whatever?
Yeah.
And you actually, you know, it's like any other event would be that you do have to market things a little bit more aggressively than just sticking up your hands saying, we are running a room party at Balticon.
And of course, you busy people all over the world who are overwhelmed by the amount of stuff you have to do on the Internet at the moment will immediately think of our party as being the first thing that you want to do.
It's become clear that that in fact, Facebook marketing for conventions is quite effective at has been effective at pulling in people who would not habitually have gone to the Easter con.
The Easter con, the makeup of the Easter con has changed extremely dramatically over the last five years.
And although Lung Kong gets some of the credit for that, it's also the fact that we accidentally reached out to a broader community by just doing very basic social media stuff.
And also by the people who go talking about it and and raising buzz for it.
And I don't see any reason why you can't do that with the online conventions as well.
You just have to make sure that you've got a value proposition that is compelling at times when people have a lot of other things on their plate.
On the topic of value propositions, Con Zealand have announced that they are also going to use a mixture of Zoom and Discord to run their convention.
And one question we had when we read this is what is the value proposition of this, given that Balticon has done this seemingly free at the point of use?
So, Alison, did you want to start talking about this and then me and Liz can jump in with our excellent opinions?
I wanted to 100% make clear that I am pontificating from a complete state of ignorance here.
And I wanted to say that I guess that Balticon probably wasn't free.
That they will have had their convention that doesn't that runs every year.
So they will have things like a corporate structure and a bank account and a set of and they would have been able to put some money into this in the knowledge that they will have future physical conventions in a way that conventions that only run once like a Worldcon may not be able to.
So it is possible that it was not as free as all of that.
These will all be tied together with a single sign in point for authentication.
So I feel like Con Zealand is planning to wall off its garden.
And I guess that Balticon, because it was free, didn't need to wall off its garden.
And my guess is that the process of saying only Con Zealand members are going to be inside the loop here will make this more expensive.
And if you can spot the flaw in that reasoning.
I think you're right.
I think that Balticon almost certainly as a continuing convention has a reserve that they can probably call upon because they are an established organization that has been going for a while and will have a continuity.
The disadvantage in this sense that Worldcons have is that each Worldcon, for those who don't know, is a separate organization.
And so there is no continuity in the amount of money on the organization that you have available to you other than what other Worldcons have been able to donate to you.
And I don't know how much Dublin did in donating to Con Zealand, but I wouldn't be surprised if it was relatively low because I suspect Dublin spent quite a lot of money on running their convention.
And so it might well be that this is mostly driven by the fact that Balticon might have a source of stability that Con Zealand doesn't.
And so it might well be a slightly unfair comparison to make in some ways.
If you look at the Easter Con, Easter Cons pass along money between Easter Cons and these pass alongs can often be quite large compared to the relatively small budget of an Easter Con.
And they've been getting bigger.
And we intended when running Folly Con to reduce the size of the pass along deliberately because we thought they were slightly too large.
But we did end up passing along quite a lot of money.
And we will use, I think, it is likely that most of that money is going to get used up dealing with this year's Easter Con, refunding where it needed to and incurring the expenses it couldn't get out of.
And then next year's Easter Con, coping with what is likely to be a very disrupted Easter Con for a number of ways.
And I would suspect that between those two, we will probably not have very much pass along at all left at the end of it.
So it's kind of like, oh, yes, Easter Con has been saving for a rainy day.
And that is a thing that that it's done now.
I imagine that Con Zealand has an enormous amount of incurred expenses that it cannot get out.
I think there's also one extra aspect that Con Zealand will have to deal with.
I think Balticon in a way could have sort of open zoom and open discord and largely fly under the radar.
And I didn't hear anything about any problems they had.
But I think a World Con is a much more visible entity.
And also the World Con has had problems in the past.
Well, you know, World Con is a higher profile thing and it has, you know, had the whole thing with the puppies and the Hugo nominations.
And it's possible they also feel that, A, they need to be a little bit more of a walled garden and to put some effort into making sure that no one disrupts their higher profile event.
And also into more people points to do moderation and to try and keep things as safe as possible for everyone when they do have the event just because of numbers.
So I don't think any of these open events have had problems.
I think that segues quite nicely into a discussion about what the relative strengths of Zoom and Discord are in this space.
My understanding is that one of the reasons Discord has gotten more popular recently is because they've recently introduced an awful lot of features to allow for that kind of effective moderation to be more easily implemented.
And I saw that there were to get into the Balticon, you had to agree to a code of conduct before you were allowed to enter the Balticon Discord.
And there were moderators who were able to step in.
But I think you're right that ConZealand will have a harder time with that.
It will be a much bigger enterprise.
But I think it's interesting that the way that you see the way that Discord can be used to facilitate that kind of code of conduct might be one of the reasons we're seeing that as the like spokes in between the Zooms, which are the kind of panels and room parties.
And I think that's a really good use of the two technologies, really playing both to their strengths while minimizing their weaknesses.
Discord strength being like the fact it's always there and you can always go and it's got the moderation.
Zoom strengths being that the video quality is higher.
It's a lot easier to get started.
Like you just click a link and it appears and you can do the webinar mode stuff, which is all kind of baked in.
Very much playing to the strengths of both platforms.
Yeah, I mean, I think it's quite clear that a combination of Zoom and Discord is very good.
very good for all this stuff.
I mean, I haven't, I've not thought about running a party in the form of having the, having the actual party going on in Discord with a set of video chats.
But that might be a better way to run big parties.
I don't know.
I'm still, I'm still amazed that nobody has really solved the problem of running big parties.
Given that it's been months now and given that big parties are one of the things that humans like to do a lot.
I know I just keep talking about parties all the time.
When we get to what I'm doing to stay sane in the apocalypse, one of the things I've been looking at is whether there are any really good VR party apps,
because it feels like VR parties ought to be totally a thing that could solve all of these problems.
But you know what?
They're not.
Or at least if they are, I haven't found one yet.
And actually, one of the things that we were talking about, I'm almost certain it was on one of Alison's Interminable Zoom parties.
Possibly after a taff, possibly after a taff Zoom, maybe at the London Pub meeting, maybe a Thursday.
They're lovely, but there are many of them and they all slightly blur into one, which I enjoy about them.
And also, I've just Googled Interminable and they are endless.
You are always Zooming, Alison.
It is 100%.
I do not believe you will ever stop partying.
I am actually slightly less Zooming than I would like to.
I feel like I'm not running fewer events than I'd like to, but I kind of find I get to the beginning of weekend and goes,
who's running a party this weekend?
And there are never quite enough of those people.
So maybe there are great parties going on to which I am not being invited.
But there probably are.
But I feel like I never was going to invite me to loads of things now.
I'm going to have to go.
No, no, no.
But I would like there to be more things out there that I could just kind of drop into if I feel like it, where people will be having buzz.
But I will say that Jerry was saying that Balticon also had a presence on Second Life, where you could go and interact with people in Second Life.
And I was like, and it gets back to what you were saying about, yeah, about VR.
Like, party like it's 1999.
Liz, do you use Second Life, avid Second Life user?
I have never used Second Life.
Me neither.
I used it in 1999.
Was it actually 1999?
I'm just checking.
But yeah, no.
And I think that gets back to what you were saying about, like, it would be, it sounds like what you want is a VR world where you could go and, like, more realistically interact.
And then I heard that they were doing a Second Life thing.
And I'm like, oh, no.
Because I think that's the attempt to do something like that.
But I just don't think it actually works or provides that experience in any meaningful way.
And hopefully one day, but not today.
But kudos to them for trying.
I don't think Con Zealand has announced their aggressive Second Life utilisation yet.
And obviously I think I speak for all three of us when I say I'm waiting with bated breath to see what they plan.
I am actually wrong.
Apparently you can party like it's 2003.
Excellent.
Octothorpe is sponsored this week by Stow Shirts.
Stow Shirts makes political, science fictional and nerdy apparel and pin badges for a whole range of different interests.
Whether it's a virtual hug badge to tell a loved one you're thinking of them.
A shirt with an in-joke for SF fans or nerds.
A pronoun badge to wear on your work lanyard.
Or a political slogan for your next protest.
They're likely to have something for you.
Podcast host should speak here about their personal experience with the sponsor.
Erm, podcasts with her every week.
She's quite nice.
What's more, they can do custom badges and shirts.
Amend existing designs to suit your needs.
And they're happy to work with SF conventions and fan groups to help organise their merchandise offering and reduce stress on the committee.
Visit them today at stowshirts.com and use the code Octothorpe for a 10% discount.
We should talk briefly about the Nebulas and WhizCon.
Which we, I think I speak for the three of us, did not attend.
But Alison got some sneaky gossip before the Nebulas happened.
So, erm...
Well, it wasn't really sneaky gossip.
Stephen Silver said he'd been running Zoom parties along the lines of the ones that I've been running for up to 500 people.
Although he'd been running them for up to 150 people with a plan to run for up to 500 on Nebula weekend.
And I've heard nothing.
I feel like if 500 people had gone to the Nebula party, I would have heard about it.
But they were probably all American science fiction authors.
So maybe not.
But if you were at the Nebula Zoom party, do let us know how it went.
So he was using the same system as we do where you have a lot of breakout rooms.
People move between them.
He was doing a thing very cleverly where he put everybody into a lobby and then he had moderators in the lobby trying to divide people up into smaller rooms.
I slightly worry that that leaves you with hundreds of people in the lobby.
And he was leaving people in the waiting room until he had a bunch of, say, six.
And then he'd bring them all in at once and give them the spiel about how it was going to work and things like that.
But I don't that was all in the practice, which is what we talked about.
So, Stephen, if you're listening, then that would be a great thing to know about how it went.
And yeah.
And if you're not listening, if anyone was at the Nebula Zoom party, I really, really want to know how it went.
The one thing I must say I really dislike about Zoom is the bit where you wait for the host to notice that you want to party.
And they eventually let you into their party.
But it's, I guess, a bit like queuing to get into a room party at a Worldcon.
So it's a pleasing recreation of a Fannish tradition.
It's replicating that bit of the party where you decide to go to party and you get a drink and you sort of hang around at the edge trying to work out if you know anyone at this party or if you're just going to stand around looking like you are a cool loner.
It's actually replicating the part where you're standing on the doorstep and your host has had a, has engrossed in conversation.
And the last thing they want to do right now is open the door.
The other thing we did not attend was WizCon.
Do, Liz, do you know anything about WizCon?
Yes, I have been to WizCon quite a long time ago now.
2006.
And I enjoyed it.
But I've never managed to go back.
So I was sort of thinking about trying to go back when it was a virtual convention.
But I completely failed to do so because of inertia and time zones.
But they, I think they were paid as well.
So I would have had to make a proper commitment to working out if I could go to things really before.
You couldn't sort of dip in and out.
But it is the, of the ones that were running on Memorial Day, that was the one I would quite have liked to go to.
Registration for WizCon cost $10.
You could pay $0 if you could not afford the $10.
And they also had membership levels at $25 and $55 for those who felt able to more support the convention.
So it wasn't, it wasn't sort of Con Zealand levels of money.
But it was sort of a small tip.
I hadn't realised it was only $10.
I think I must have seen one of the higher numbers and decided I need to think about it.
If it was only $10, then that is within my realm of, yep, I'll just take a plunge on that.
And if I don't end up going to any of the events, well, I like WizCon and they can have my $10.
Yes.
No, that is fair.
I was, I don't know whether Balticon had a tip jar, but it does occur to me as well that you,
you really need to have some sort of like PayPal or, or drip or whatever other service tip jar on your,
on your convention website to allow people to contribute to the costs, I think.
I'm still very much looking forward to Con Zealand.
I am.
I think part of the thing about the virtual trip is trying to get myself into a headspace where I really am focusing.
When you, there's a focus thing.
When you decide to go to an actual convention in actual life, you go, right, I am going off.
If we ever have these again, I go somewhere for the weekend and I spend my weekend there and I do the convention.
When a virtual convention comes into your life, you're kind of like, oh, I'm doing everything else I'm doing else.
And then also there's this convention going on.
And I think actually saying, no, I'm going to block out three days and the convention is going to be what I do for those three days is a very different way to think about these.
And I'm not sure how many of us are doing that just yet.
Did that make any sense?
That did make sense.
Because I think when I was thinking about, oh, should I try and get to any of these online conventions over the Memorial Day weekend?
I was thinking about it in, oh, I might dip in and out of some events if they're in the right time zone.
I wasn't thinking I will take the plunge and commit my weekend to it as I normally would for a convention.
Yes, I think, I think that's fair.
And I think that was very much the thing I did with Balticon was I signed up for the panels that I was interested in going to and were in the right time zone.
And then I didn't really think I was attending Balticon, but I got to go to some cool panels, which is the way I was thinking about it.
But I think if there was going to be a convention I usually attend happening virtually, I would be taking that as a I will block the time out and do this as if I am at the convention.
And the next convention for which that happens is probably going to be the Virtual UK Games Expo, which is being held in mid-August.
They have cancelled the physical one and they are holding a virtual one and I will be thoroughly and enthusiastically attending.
Oh, how much does it cost and what are its dates?
So it's the 21st of August to the 23rd of August.
I have found the part on the website.
We've decided to make Virtual UK Expo freely available to anyone who wants to join in.
So there are no entry tickets, but there will be the option to donate.
And some activities such as role playing games and tournaments will still require individual tickets and will attract a small fee in order to participate.
So free to attend the sort of show floor, but perhaps small amounts of money to attend some of the events happening.
They're using Twitch, Discord, Zoom, YouTube.
It's being sponsored by Pezo and Weyland Games and Warhammer and Catan.
So big sponsors.
I had not heard of UK Online Games Expo and because gaming conventions are one of the things that I very, very much enjoy, but have had to decide are a piece of life that is too much for me.
You know, I can't manage to squeeze them into my life.
I'm actually extremely excited about the idea of a virtual one and I might well come along to that.
So that's quite exciting.
It's going to be very interesting to see how some of the tournaments are run because Asmodee, which is one of the big, big board game companies in the world, has been clamping down on methods to virtually play their games in recent weeks.
And it will be interesting to see how you run a tournament for a game that has no official digital client and the parent company of which has been strongly discouraging online play.
So I don't know whether those will actually happen or what they will look like if they do.
But, you know.
Which games are Asmodee?
What games are they famous for, John?
So they do anything with the Arkham Horror branding is Asmodee.
Anything with the Star Wars branding is Asmodee, unless it's Hasbro.
But there aren't any tournaments for Hasbro games.
Anything with Legends of the Five Rings branding, Game of Thrones branding.
Catan is Asmodee.
Like, if it's not Hasbro and it's not Wizards of the Coast, it's probably Asmodee.
It's basically how it breaks down.
Ticket to Ride, Pandemic, Carcassonne, Small World, Mysterium.
I'm not sure they originally developed all of those, but they've sort of swallowed up some smaller companies at this point.
So essentially, huge swathes of games are now Asmodee.
They've been eating companies and then they recently got sold to a venture capital company.
And, you know, capitalism is great, obviously.
You wouldn't hear a word against it, but yeah, slightly sad.
Oh, so they're basically the electronic arts of board games.
Oh, jeez, that is a particularly good comparison, which makes me very, very sad, Alison.
So essentially, the bit where you're starting to spend too much money on Arkham Horror, you have no idea how that's going for you.
Right, let's move on.
We should talk about the Hugo Voter Packet on the subject of things which are terrific value.
I signed up for a supporting membership to Cod Zealand after the last episode of Octothorpe,
and I have downloaded my Hugo Voter Packet.
Alison and Liz, have you downloaded Hugo Voter Packets?
I have, but it took me so long to download my Hugo Voter Packet, which is enormous.
I had to have a little lie down after that, so I haven't really looked at it very much.
But you have told me that it has the whole of The Wicked and the Divine in it, and I am very excited about that.
Because The Wicked and the Divine is an excellent graphic novel that everyone should read.
Yes, it has the entire of Wickediv, The Wicked and the Divine, and it also has the entire of Monstrous and the entire of Paper Girls in it.
So all of the back issues for those comics are available.
And I think Liz is particularly excited.
Well, I have already read all of Wickediv as well, so I do not need that from my Voter Packet.
I basically haven't signed up to Cod Zealand yet, but I am considering signing up for a supporting membership.
Basically, I will sign up for a supporting membership in a very mercenary way if the amount of stuff I haven't read,
which is in the Voter Packet, makes it seem like a worthwhile proposition,
and then I basically get to vote in the Hugos as a bonus.
Okay, I'm going to put my grumpy old fart cap on now and go,
I believe in the Worldcon community, and I think that it is worth buying a supporting membership to the Worldcon each year,
even for years in which you could not possibly travel to it,
because we are one, if you can afford it, obviously,
because people have to spend their money on different things,
because we are one community,
and having the membership every year,
and voting in site selection and the Hugos,
and being part of the Worldcon community is a bigger thing than any one Worldcon,
and you understand that sometimes the Worldcon will go to places that you cannot possibly get to.
Don't go where I can't follow!
Yeah, like that.
I do buy supporting memberships to the Worldcon every year for exactly those reasons.
The reason I bought the Con Zealand one very late is because I thought I had voted in site selection at San Jose,
but I can find no evidence that this thought was actually based in facts or anything approaching evidence.
So having reluctantly conceded I might not have done that, I eventually bought a supporting membership.
But yes, usually I vote in site selection, and that gets me my supporting membership without me having to do anything else.
But this time it does not appear to have worked, which is probably my own stupid fault.
It's true. I sound overly obsessed with free stuff at this point.
I have bought quite a lot of supporting memberships in various conventions and Worldcons in the past.
I don't know why I never got round to buying one for Con Zealand.
I think it is now clear that putting your things in the Hugo but voting pack
does encourage people to pay attention to them and maybe vote for them and certainly increases the chance that they will win the Hugo,
but probably is also quite good advertising for things generally.
I worry slightly about the tendency for people to buy Worldcon memberships just for the Hugo pack,
because it's not quite that's what gave us the sad puppies,
but that's what gives us a group of people who are interested in the Worldcon
only for what it can provide as a reading service.
And that seems a bit of a shame.
Yes, I don't want to suggest that the only reason to support the Worldcon is the Hugo voter packet,
but obviously the Hugo voter packet is a pretty fantastic perk that one gets if one is in that community.
And I will say that I have oftentimes used the Hugo voter packet as a way to try to encourage friends
who are perhaps less in the Worldcon fandom to support the Worldcon
and maybe bring them slightly more into the fandom,
which is, I think, also a kind of good carrot to use, if that makes sense.
It's true. I also feel that I am sufficiently embedded in Worldcon fandom
and have given quite a lot of my effort in kind to Worldcons in the past,
but I don't feel I always need to support them with my money.
That's fair. For those who don't know, Liz has deputy department headed,
well, sorry, no, Liz has deputy division headed at Worldcons in the past,
a job which is very difficult.
Alison has also deputy division headed in the past, a job which was very difficult.
And I have also deputy division headed in the past, a job which was very difficult.
So we are all speaking as deeply entrenched members of Worldcon fandom
who have never been quite daft enough to rise to the position of full division head,
which would be insane.
This is where Alison is like, I was division head of something.
And I'm like, oh, no, why?
No, no, no. I've been area head.
I was area head at 1995 and 2005.
And I was a DDH at 2014 and have no further intention,
have no ambitions in that direction at all.
Yes. The only one of us who will ever chair a Worldcon is, of course, Liz.
I've been going down in responsibility.
I've gone from deputy division head to area head to person who hangs around a bit
because they know how the programming database works.
So clearly my next role will be just hanging around for no reason whatsoever.
Excellent.
I think I should say that it isn't a progress.
So I have been, I did area head jobs at two UK Worldcons and then a DDH job.
But at other Worldcons, I have also taken quite dull staff roles,
like, for example, the person whose job it was to inject jokes into the newsletter
and that sort of thing.
That's a pretty vital role.
Shall we move on to staying sane in the apocalypse,
aka Alison attempts to bring the entire world to her house?
So what have I done?
I've run some more Zoom parties.
One of the exciting things that happened this month is that Facebook included a checkbox on events
for this event is happening online,
which has stopped the repeated messages that I and all my attendees were getting,
saying, are you really going to an event with 50 people?
Don't you know that that's not allowed under the lockdown rules?
So now it has a little checkbox where you can say my event is happening online.
But being Facebook, I slightly worry that what Zuckerberg is doing is trying to,
because now I get a lot of advertising from Facebook about how wouldn't I be rather using Facebook's social media,
Facebook's video conferencing tools, to which the answer is no.
I am still using a combination of Zoom and breakout rooms because I've not yet found anything better.
But I could be persuaded into Discord instead.
And yes, I'm running big Zooms.
I'm running small Zooms.
I've not gone into the enormous.
I kind of think once you've got about 20 or 30 people,
that's probably enough for me to have a fantastic time.
And there's an extent to which I don't necessarily care about anybody else.
And I have bought a VR rig.
That's why I bought an Oculus Quest.
My child stopped working for me on the completely spurious excuse that she was studying for her finals
and therefore did not have any time to make badges for minimum wage.
So you'll notice that she does have time to run a turnip empire on Animal Crossing.
But, you know, people make their own priorities.
I mean, to be fair, Alison, you're benefiting from the...
I was about to say you're benefiting from the fruits of her labours.
But obviously you're benefiting from the vegetables.
All right, that's it.
Stop the podcast.
Episode 7, we're peaked.
There's nowhere down...
Nowhere but downhill from here.
Right.
So instead, I basically had to do all the minimum wage badge making and shipping work last month.
And at the end of the month, I looked at what I thought I would have paid for the number of hours I had spent doing it.
And I bought an Oculus Quest.
And also because I had said when I decided to buy nothing that I would spend my money on experiences rather than things.
And if I still can't get out of my house to do anything, then clearly sticking a headset on and going and swimming with dolphins or playing some VR game is as close as I can get to new experiences.
And they are new experiences.
It was like utterly science fictional.
It was completely sensor wonder for me.
Now, I mean, I'd obviously used some VR stuff before, but there's something about the fact that it doesn't use wires.
So it's just wherever you happen to be.
So you can take a tiny patch of your house from which you've managed to clear clutter and then you put this headset on and suddenly you're in a gorgeous geodesic dome that has been tastefully furnished by somebody else.
And you go, oh, I can see how we might all be doing this.
And it's equal parts of, oh, my God, this is a really futuristic feeling.
And, oh, my God, the world as I know it is going to collapse.
I look at what has happened between when I bought my Nintendo Game & Watch in 1980 and the Oculus Quest.
And I extrapolate forward and I'm like, we are going to get to the point where real life does not necessarily have a lot to offer that is better than these systems.
It is the opinion of the Octothorpe podcast that we should all live in.
Small pods plugged into some sort of central computer where we socialise without risk of pandemic.
And is this how the Matrix starts, Alison?
Is this how the Matrix starts?
That was literally where I got to.
I was like, I can see a world where actually people do this an enormous amount.
And that's the Matrix.
Yeah.
And that was kind of weird.
That was a very weird feeling.
And yet, when you sort of go, well, if, say, Facebook's creating avatars now, and you can see that one of the reasons that Facebook's creating avatars is if you want to do something that's like Second Life but works, getting people to have realistic, consistent avatars for themselves is one of the ways in which you make that happen.
So you go into your virtual space.
And you go, oh, yeah, that's John, because I recognise his avatar.
And this is all quite the weird thing.
But, you know, when you're saying, well, we can't actually go to see, I still can't see my family.
And I feel like there's going to be attractions to this sort of thing.
Also, Beat Saber is a lot of fun.
Beat Saber is fun.
Beat Saber is the only VR game I have played.
And I like rhythm games because they're the only games I'm actually any good at.
Every other game, I have to put it on easy mode and die a lot.
And Beat Saber is just like, yeah, I'm going to go for this.
And it's fine, although hard work.
So Beat Saber is great.
Have you played any other VR games?
Because do they make, and someone should have made this, a sort of like Matrix crossed with Half-Life, crossed with Inception style game where you can do the Matrix and run up walls and re-shift reality?
I think my feeling about games, Beat Saber is fine, but Beat Saber feels to me like a tech demo rather than a game.
I feel like we are, so there's a set of games that are coming out now that are set of the Star Wars universe where you get to run around with a lightsaber.
But I feel like we are only at the very beginning of exploring what you can do with this game space.
There is a game called Superhot VR, which people talk about where you only move, the bad guys only move when you do.
You're in a kind of weird Matrix-like environment there, and there is bullet time.
So as long as you're not moving, the bullets aren't moving.
And if you start to move, then the bullets move.
And that is quite freaky.
And it also is quite intense.
When they talk about intense VR experiences, they mean roller coasters.
They mean things that set off your balance.
So it's not intense in that way at all.
But I found it intense in a gaming way.
I am five foot tall, and it didn't seem to have any height adjustment.
So these guys that were coming towards me, but only when I moved, were much bigger than I was.
And that was quite freaky.
I've only played the demo, and I'm not saying I won't buy it.
But it felt like, and I've heard other people talking about VR and saying that some of the really intense first-person shooter games are not working for them because it is just all too much.
So other people really like that sort of stuff.
But it's just early days.
Early days for all this stuff.
And there is a game called Star Trek Bridge Command, I think, that Ming pointed me at.
Ming has a headset.
Ming is in New Zealand.
Ming and I could play.
This is a cooperative game where you work with other people on the bridge of the Enterprise or some Federation starship in order to solve problems.
And I haven't actually played it yet.
But that's something that feels to me the sort of thing that I am actually looking for, which is cooperative games in VR between people who are not located in the same space in the real world.
To make up for a thing like board game.
I like cooperative gaming generally.
There's apparently a version of Keep Talking and Nobody Explodes, which is a game which my family has played endlessly to the death.
We have absolutely wrung all the love out, all the possible joy out of this game at this point.
But apparently there's a VR version of that.
So that one of you is sitting with headphones and the quest and the VR set on with the bomb in front of you and actually physically manipulating it.
And the other people are sitting with the decoding manual trying to tell you what to do.
But I have not played that either.
So I've played a bit of Beat Saber and I've done a few.
I've done some things like.
I have done some VR.
I have played the Star Wars VR game on PlayStation 4.
And it made me feel a little bit queasy.
I had to spend some time looking very fixedly at a planet in the distance in order to avoid feeling very queasy.
So I am.
But I'm very much looking forward to VR becoming a bigger thing.
Because one of the things I really am finding very difficult about the apocalypse is that I have a weekly role play in which we do quite a lot of highly cooperative storytelling.
And part of the problem with Zoom and Discord and all of these things is that it's very difficult to pick up on other people's social queues in a way that means that everyone can join in without having to sort of go round the room pointing at people saying,
Now it's your turn.
Because louder voices dominate and quieter voices find it difficult to get a look in.
And this can really disrupt the dynamic.
So I'm very much looking forward to VR as a mechanism for role playing games.
Because I think, I hope, that VR will be a better way of doing that that doesn't fall prey to the same problems that video chatting falls prey to.
So I am sort of optimistic and hopeful about the potential for VR chatting as a replacement for video chatting.
But I don't know what time scale that's a realistic proposition on.
20 years.
Like nuclear fusion, right?
It's 20 years away.
No, I think it depends really on how pandemic goes.
Because if we are still here in a year, not really going to the pub, then I think at that point, a lot of this stuff will have happened because there will be so infinitely much money in it.
I also did see, and I've been looking for the link for ages, which is why I've been super quiet, someone developed a sort of top-down 2D chat room idea where you wander about a 2D space and you can talk through your microphone.
And people who are closer to you can hear what you're saying more clearly and people who are further away hear you less clearly.
And you can wander around an actual kind of physical space talking and it replicates a bar in 2D.
And I am looking for the link and the name of this and I cannot find it.
It's very frustrating.
If I do find it, I'll put a link in the show notes.
But...
So they've got to get...
The problem with all of these systems at the moment is that they have to get over the level of adequacy
that we've established now with the Zoom and the breakout rooms, which is clearly not that adequate,
but it's still a lot better than a lot of these systems are quite managing yet.
And the other thing about the VR rig that I was going to say is that although my house is not small, really,
it's got five adults in it.
And I've been...
And I don't think of myself as the world's greatest introvert.
But when I put on the quest...
We don't think of you as the world's greatest introvert either.
No, you're a terrible introvert, Alison.
Yeah, indeed.
But when I put the quest on, I'm alone in a way that I never am in my own house at the moment.
And I quite like that.
It's quite isolating.
And I have been missing feeling...
It's odd in a time of self-isolation.
I have been missing feeling actual time alone to do things I want to do in comfortable spaces because my house is lost.
I've made that many comfortable spaces and they're awful.
The name of the service I was thinking of is Calla.
And I will put a link in the show notes.
It is C-A-L-L-A.
Is this a thing you're planning to use on your virtual guff trip, Alison?
I am hoping that I will be able to do some of my tours virtually.
I have a really whizzy idea that I am going to do VR stuff whilst streaming it to Twitch.
Streaming both the VR stuff and me using Twitch streaming tools, which I already use a little bit.
And so that people will be able to come along and watch me swim off the Great Barrier Reef in real time or something.
And that will be hilarious.
Please get in touch for recommendations for ways we can support and learn about the Black Lives Matter movement
and also BAME people in the UK and in the community in the UK in general.
And please also write in with your experiences of virtual conventions.
We would love to hear from you.
Thank you to Stow Shirts for supporting our podcast this week.
That was the seventh episode of the Octothorpe podcast.
So it's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod at incompetech.com
used under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 licence.
Is this the point where I can say that Lillian and Christina are hoping to do a podcast?
And when they first told me about this, or rather when Lillian first told me about this, I said,
but you'll have to find someone to do all the work.
And they have now found Ian Sorensen, I believe.
So he is investigating other podcasts, which is how he's paying attention to John's microphone.
So I'm very much looking forward.
I am waiting with bated breath for that podcast to appear in my podcast feed.
I will be listening avidly.
Yes, no pressure, obviously.
The fact that we've announced it doesn't have any ramifications for whether it has to happen.
And Alison's decision to do that was entirely her own.
One of the things I always liked about fanzines back in the day was that they could be...
Relentless piss takes.
You know, a little bit edgy about the community and the things the community were getting up to.
And I feel like we should capture some of that flavour in our podcast.
More antagonism.
I do feel if I was going to pick some adjectives to describe our podcast, edgy would be quite a long way down the list.
Oh, okay.
No, I maybe don't mean edgy.
Are you indicating that you think three middle class white people during a podcast are not at the forefront of edge?
We talk about things we like, Liz.
What could be more edgy than this?
My 19-year-old son did call me an edgelord this week.
Right, well, we're going to come back to that later, 100%.
And I was like, what do you mean by edgelord, dear?
And he explained.
And I said, you mean like Kylo Ren?
And he said, yes.
Oh, dear.
Oh, Alison.
And I said, that's unfair.
I said, what I actually said was, that's unfair.
Whash, whash, whash, whash, whash.
But we'll come back to that.
I would like to reassure people that Alison was miming destroying a control console with a lightsaber and not miming beating her children.
That's important to note.
The context of the video was key in that particular interaction.
Before we descend...
Also, your lightsaber noises are terrible.
Yeah, everyone knows it goes vwom.