So way back in episode one, um, this is the point where you can put the way back music, John, that you've got on the...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[
I'm Alison Scott. And I'm Liz Batty.
Good Lord, you all have a lot of opinions about Monster Munch. We are not going to go through all of them here, but we really respected the amount of attention you all gave that on Facebook.
Apparently you all like Monster Munch a lot.
Um, over on Twitter, someone sent us a chart of comment or a cock.
[laughs] No, no, no, no, no, no.
Too far, John. Too far.
So Hugo Book Club wrote to us saying a very quick note for accuracy.
Um, I think I said that Fancast was the category with the lowest participation, and they sent a graph showing participation rates in the at-risk categories, and Fancast is sometimes the lowest, but is not always.
I do recommend going and checking out that graph, and we will put a link in the show notes.
I discovered that Peter Sullivan once used a Monster Munch as an engagement ring because the bar didn't have any hula hoops.
I'm just feeling sorry for the Americans who are like, "What does that mean?"
There's not a nouns there, but I know what.
Uh, so yeah, if you're listening, Laurie, and the Hugo Girl people, uh, we will explain it to you at Worldcon.
Yeah, I might manage to bring some hula hoops in my luggage.
It won't make more sense, but you'll know what it means.
I almost want all the details from Peter, but I also kind of want it to remain, you know, the rest of the story to remain a mystery.
Except Peter, please write in to say what you used as a wedding ring.
[laughs]
Well, he used Rose Bee for the engagement, so presumably we'd pick old onion for the wedding.
Both Kevin Stambly and Tammy Coxon wrote to us about NASFIC voting.
Thank you very much both. Kevin basically noted on Twitter that there have been previous cases where NASFICs have selected NASFICs
because the lead times for Worldcons used to be different, which is something I don't think we picked up on.
But basically it didn't used to have to be that there was Worldcon consecutively, because obviously the bid process used to take three years, not two.
And so it happened in 1987 when voters at CactusCon in Phoenix chose the site of the 1990 NASFIC.
Thank you both for writing in.
Yeah, Chris Garcia sent us a letter of comment. Thank you very much.
Chris, he says he is the gloomy dark rain cow, cloud, hanging over fandom, old bother.
Sorry, Chris, try eating some pickled onion, monster munch, and you'll perk right up.
We'll bring you some, Chris, don't worry.
Oh yeah, and he also mentions sci-fi London short film program, which is fantastic.
And yes, I don't think I got a word in on this one last time, but I went to many sci-fi London short film programs when I lived in London or thereabouts, and they were fantastic.
Maybe I'll even put a link to some of my favourites in the show notes if I can remember which ones they were.
Also, he is surprised that Alison is short, so apparently either Chris is short and doesn't know it, or maybe Alison's personality just makes her seem like a tall person
through sheer force of will.
Poor Cain, no lost doors.
Chris is, Chris is like, he's not a tall man, I wouldn't say, but Alison is also taller personality than stature.
Not a tall man.
Alison is also not a tall man, that is true.
This is something that people are often very surprised to discover how short I am, but I make up for it in a width.
I wouldn't say volume, but...
On Friday, I was on a Zoom with Alison, and there was a point at which Steven took a phone and recorded Alison doing something, and I had not seen Alison from Steven's vantage point before, and it is bloody brilliant.
I highly recommend anyone get Steven to carry a camera around when he's with Alison and watch, because he is 10/10, would win a Hugo.
And what was I doing and why was I doing it, John?
You were making a Zaziki and beer smoothie with ice, because I said I'd pay you a favour if you did it and drank it, and you did it and drank it, and then I'd say, "I'm not a fan of it."
And then I owed you a favour.
And it was, "Let me tell you, spending a favour for that level of entertainment, highly recommend."
It was pretty good.
Anyone who's at a convention, bring a favour and some Zaziki and corner Alison in the bar.
World's calm.
You know?
Please don't.
Are we good?
Everyone do that, please.
Please don't.
But secondly, I did eventually watch all of the Sci-Fi London short films.
There was a brief hitch.
I think we might have mentioned it on the podcast last time, where the website had broken on the day.
I was going to finish them off.
But it was back up when running the next eight, so we watched them, and it was very good.
And I generally enjoyed all the others I watched as well.
But we already talked about it in some detail.
But Liz, I forgot you used to live in the UK and went to UK things.
I was like, "Oh yeah, Liz was near London once."
I was.
I've never done, I've kind of ignored Sci-Fi London, except once or twice I've been to things on the Sci-Fi.
London programme, and it's been good.
But I feel like I should do more of Sci-Fi London than I do.
But that's, I feel like I should do more of everything than I do.
How do people find time for things, people?
It's difficult.
Leicester used to have a great film festival every year, which was zombie-focused.
And so I have seen a surprising number of classic zombie films, especially considering my view of cinema in general.
My view of zombie cinema is much better than my view of almost all other cinema.
Run by a book called Zombie Ed.
The thing about Sci-Fi London is some of the longer films could be hit and miss.
I mean, the short films can as well.
But in the short film programme, you usually got kind of a mix of quite good ones, some terrible ones, some mediocre ones.
Whereas if you picked randomly four films, you might randomly pick four mediocre ones.
So I thought it was a very good chance to see something really good.
But then of course, if you did see a really good film, then it was brilliant.
One of the things that is great about short film programmes is that if you absolutely hate something, there'll be something else to log in ten minutes, and I like that a lot.
Exactly.
One other thing Chris mentions in his lock is that we definitely have a listener in South America, which is very exciting.
So Chris says that his friend, Jules, lived in California for decades, but has moved to Brazil and says he listens to the podcast last time.
Chris spoke to him.
So we have a South American listener.
Yes.
Hello, Jules.
So now we need Africa and Antarctica and Asia, who is not Liz.
And then we get the full set.
Yes.
To be fair, I do have colleagues on Antarctica, so I could ask them to listen, but is that cheating?
Do you have colleagues on Antarctica, John?
Like sporadically, because obviously you don't just live there, but yeah, like I've got colleagues who have went to Antarctica.
They have great photos.
So yeah, you should definitely do that.
Do you ever have colleagues in space?
Not yet.
If you're listening to what's a thought from space, we really, really want to shout out.
Thank you.
So the Brigitte Bradshaw wrote to us, she put the phrase cover art for Octa thought podcast into the artificial intelligence image maker, Dali.
And she describes the result as weirdly pleasing.
We have used it as our show art this episode.
She says, I don't know what it's drawing from, except for the Sumason, which I think is probably the left, the left column in the middle.
I think might be coming from the punctuation art in part, because it's that black and white.
It was very cool. So thank you very much, Brigitte. That was a great lock.
It is, I find it strangely beautiful.
And it's all, it's gone very much with a sort of pink and yellow and blue colour scheme somehow.
Apart from one which is black and white.
And sometimes we're like shadowy figures.
Yeah.
If they're supposed to be us.
Like the Illuminati.
If you just put Octa thought in, Liz discovered you basically get C-n-n-me.
I don't know what about us is C-n-n-me like.
But.
Yeah, I mean, I was thinking I'd just get, you know, hashtags.
Yeah, yeah. It's very clearly keying off Octa and not off Thorpe.
Hmm.
Interestingly.
But I don't know why.
But yes. Thank you very much, Brigitte.
Oh, and my Brad W. Foster original arrived in the post and it's very nice and I get very, very much.
And obviously it's at home and I'm not.
So I can't show you it. Sorry.
I'll show you the next time.
Oh, and also there was a lock from episode one we were going to deal with and I'll let Alison introduce it.
So way back in episode one.
Um, Catherine Crockett said, please can you do transcripts of Octa Thorpe and we took that very seriously and so now here on episode 60 of Octa Thorpe we now have transcripts.
We've got transcripts of episodes 57 to 59 and we're going to do the rest in our copious free time.
If you listen to Octa Thorpe on the Podbean player, it's got the embedded subtitles in SRT format.
They don't work propagated to your podcast thing.
So if you need subtitles, you can either download the SRT subtitles and put them into your podcast, your listening solution or you can listen on Podbean, both of those work.
We sync transcripts will normally be about a week after the podcast or up to a week after the podcast.
We'll see how it goes because it's still a very manual, despite the fact that auto auto transcribes the episode, it makes a lot of mistakes and we like to correct the most egregious of those before we put it online.
And we have a new Octa Thorpe page on efansies.com and the link is in the show notes and you can find there the text files, the transcript and also the subtitle files so that you can put it into whatever you use to listen to the podcast and also the second edition, a mended edition of an immutable artifact which is a Hugo Verti Packet submission.
And all of this is thanks to Bill Burns, who has put the page up for us.
I mean the transcripts are thanks to us because we've done them.
We think transcripts are important for accessibility.
So thank you for nudging us, Catherine, and we've done it now and it's great.
You say, wait, it's mostly Alison doing the transcript. Thank you, Alison.
Alison is doing most of the transcripts. Thank you, Alison, because this is a hugely tedious job that would drive me absolutely mad.
So I'm very in awe that Alison has taken it on.
So thanks to John for doing the editing, which is a hugely tedious job that would drive me mad.
The key in any successful partnership is to find people who like different forms of tedium.
My dad has a theory of this with marriages. He's like, you need someone who likes cooking and someone who likes washing up.
And I think that you can generalise that into creative partnerships in a number of ways.
And Liz's favourite form of tedium is sitting on beautiful beaches whilst reading books.
Oh, shots fired, shots fired.
Liz, do you have a response?
Look, if we need any octa-thorps spreadsheets doing, I'm totally on it.
Oh, that is true. Liz has. And you have done spreadsheets for us previously.
You've knocked up a graph or two in your time for previous issues.
Episode.
So listeners, if you could think of some data you'd like processing for octa-thorps, do let us know and we'll get Liz on it.
There.
Johnathan Cowie sent us a letter of comment which we are going to treat as a full segment.
We think it was an interesting question.
And he asks, what special Hugo Award would we introduce if we were in charge of doing that at Glasgow in 2024?
Assuming, of course, touching wood that Glasgow were to be successful in becoming the world con
when we vote for them in Chicago.
I think Glasgow is now the air presumptive for the world con, isn't it?
Or maybe even the air apparent?
Yeah, but I could still get a right in bid going for Alison's house if I wanted.
Do not even think about it.
Yes, listeners, you heard it here first.
Wolfamstow 2024. Right, but...
I feel like Bangkok 2024 would be a lot more fun.
Oh, that's true actually Liz. Let's put the world in world con.
So the question is, what special Hugo would we introduce if we were in charge of Glasgow 2024, which we're definitely not?
And my suggestion is best transcript.
I think it's just 10/10 idea.
I think there needs to be more recognition of transcripts in the podcast space and we have better art in our transcript than some other transcripts.
So I think we were shoeing.
Well, we did do. Yeah, maybe sort of.
I've now discovered that it's much better to have your transcripts as a plain text file, so that's what we're doing going forward.
But yes, the only use of a lot of factors of fanzine.
But it is not eligible for the best fanzine, Hugo, obviously.
Hugo, Liz.
Chicago. So I should say here I am assuming that between now and 2024 we have already passed the proposal to have the best video games you go, because if we haven't done that, then I would tell you.
The best video game in my head would be an awesome Hugo, but you probably don't want to know.
Can I have a Hugo for Best Vivid Dream?
No, don't tell us.
Liz, you made us out like...
I had a very vivid dream the other day that Stuart Prawns, and I was like, "Oh, I'm not going to do this."
I was like, "Oh, I'm not going to do this."
Liz, you made us out like...
I had a very vivid dream the other day that Stuart Prawns Dad was very old.
That was the end. That was just the dream.
Just a single, super vivid image of a very old man.
I mean, presumably Stuart Prawns Dad is quite old.
But I was imagining him in like 95, and Stuart Prawns Dad is actually what I would describe as a dillf.
See, this is getting into the disturbing regions that I was not going into.
Yes, exactly. This is why we're not doing it right.
This is both disturbing and cricket content, so I think it should be banned on two grounds.
Yes.
Liz and I discussed, um...
Liz's views on cricket content on the podcast.
Er, I have views. There should be more of it.
Yep, she was absolutely... she was like, "You and... you and Josh should start having a cricket segment."
Yes!
Yes, assuming we only have a best game Hugo on the list, and assuming that I could come around to the position that there should be even more Hugo's,
because the moment I'm not convinced we shouldn't have any more, it's getting out of hand.
But assuming all that, I would then have one, I think, for best nonfiction.
Mmm.
Since this is my own, you know, make believe Hugo, I would probably define that quite broadly.
So you could have essays, you could have books, you could have reviews, you could have academic works.
I mean, you could probably have nonfiction video essays in there as well.
Basically, the whole thing, a lot of the stuff that ends up kind of in-best related, but maybe make it more specifically focused on non-fictional content.
A bit more like the kind of BSFA awards nonfiction award, which I think works very nicely,
although I would exclude podcasts maybe from the Hugo non-best nonfiction, I would say that.
So I'm thinking of things like, you know, I often look in semi-prosines and I enjoy, you know, voting for strange horizons.
Maybe not even primarily because of their fiction, but because I really like a lot of their nonfiction essays and reviews,
and it would be nice to have somewhere to reward particularly good examples of that form.
Mmm.
So would you do best non-fictional best criticism?
I don't know. I think I'd have to look up how I kind of defined it because the other problem is with a Hugo.
You kind of, the problem is that best related work is a big grab bag.
So you'd want to be able to carve off a chunk of what would be best related work and make it best non-fictional best criticism.
I might make it best criticism and then like the voters can define criticism.
So that could include like straightforward reviews or it could include, you know, critical essays and things like that that aren't focused on any specific work.
But it could include, you know, things like strange horizons around table discussions, you know, or long form.
There's a lot of long form video essays out there out there now about generally criticism of various media properties from different angles.
I think it kind of includes all of those in it. But maybe try and avoid non-fiction things like, you know, author interviews and certainly things like that do fit in better-related art books and so on would not be in this category.
I'm not sure why. I mean, I feel like professional non-fiction podcasts on the theme probably would fit in here.
Yeah. I mean, I'd say like...
I mean, I'm not sure if there are any.
Yeah, I'm trying to think of an example of one. I'm sure there are ones that I would fit in.
Like, I mean, Hugo Girl in a Way is a critical discussion of a different book each time and therefore would fit in.
But I mean, I might try and say, well, there is already a thing for fan podcasts that would fit better in there.
I mean, it's not a professional thing though. I mean, I think there isn't really a good space for professional podcasts, which is one of the things that I'd be getting to in my suggestion when we get to it.
So, yeah.
Oh, sorry. You said specifically professional, didn't you?
Yeah, I'd just say professional.
Because I think fan criticism is definitely covered by fan cast because clearly it's part of what we do and it's part of what lots of other fan casts do.
I mean, one possible professional thing is, you know, you get TV shows which have accompanying podcasts,
which I've quite enjoyed, and maybe some of those would fit into that sort of area.
One thing I would say is, like, on the subject of professional criticism,
obviously, the lines here are slightly blurry because, like, I would argue that, for instance, upcoming conversation guest of honor, Neil Harrison.
If Neil Harrison had a podcast in which he criticized books, like, I would say that's probably more on the professional end,
despite the fact that I don't think he'd be getting paid for it because, like, obviously he was editor of Strange Horizons for ages and he is incredibly knowledgeable in a way that when I talk about how much I like moon night, I'm maybe not.
And so there's, like, there's a semi-pro kind of problem here, isn't there?
But basically what I want to say before Alison responds is, Abigail and Neil, please do a criticism podcast. I will listen to the shit out of that.
Uh-uh. Sorry, going.
Oh, God, that would be so good.
It would be very, very good.
You should have to edit it, John.
Ooh.
No, I don't think I think that would be difficult.
Edit down someone else's three-hour argument, John.
I would also say, yeah, one thing I did think about is suggesting this for Glasgow is I think there's quite a lot of interesting work coming out of, you know, from UK-based writers and things like, you know, Vecta for the Biersefais got a lot of good stuff in recently, so it would be a nice one to have at Glasgow, assuming there was a slightly more British
tilt to the nominations, which may be completely wrong.
I mean, best criticism would be great because I do think, and I know this is my patriotic prejudice that a lot of the particularly good critics are British or have come out of British fandom.
I think it's something we do quite well.
Oh, that's fair.
Well, I think, maybe I'm talking about my butt here, but is there an equivalent?
I feel like the science fiction foundation and the BSFA both do quite a lot for kind of science fiction, criticism and commentary, and is there a similar American body to those two that focuses on that side of SF?
I'm blanking on it if there is one.
I mean, something like New York Review of Science Fiction, right?
Or the...
Yeah.
I was thinking of New York Review of Science Fiction here.
I lay review books, there's a bunch of good stuff as well.
Oh, no, yeah, no, that's true, but there's not a... like, there's SIFWA and there's ASFA and there's like WUSFS itself, I guess, but I can't think of a nationwide American body that does science fiction commentary.
National Fantasy FALFITERATION.
I've never even heard of that.
Yeah, there's a reason for that.
Do you know what I mean? Like, I just wonder whether this is partly because of the structure of... I wonder whether this is because British fandom has this as kind of a national thing that we do, and maybe that's why?
Because even if... because it might even be true that it's not better in Britain, but we're better at concentrating it into a place where people know where it is, like BSFA, because like, it might be there's loads of great stuff in America, but there's no body that's kind of working to represent that on a national level.
I don't know, right in, Americans and Brits, tell me what you reckon.
Yes, I think this is exactly the heart of the matter. I think we have the BSFA and foundation, and both of these things are national organisations that are taking science fiction and fantasy criticism very seriously.
But I just want to say before angry people from IFR, right, in, there is the International Association of the Fantastic in the Arts, which I think is worldwide, but has quite a lot of Americans, I think, in it that runs the annual International Conference on the Fantastic in the Arts, so you've got that going.
And Rita Khan, of course.
Oh, yep, no, that's true.
So there are some things, but I think this all comes back to remember that British, the remarkable cohesion of British fandom, this is about to generate a massive split.
And there's also the Finnish one.
Oh, cool, I didn't realise that.
I think, I think this is actually, like, so I was going into this thing and I was like, we'll have an amusing chat and I probably won't have any genuine opinions, and now I'm like, oh no, I'm not.
Oh no, they should definitely introduce best criticism.
This is very well argued and it ties in really well with British science fiction fandom, like, this is a good show, actually.
So related to what I just said about tying into British science fiction fandom and its pursuits and tying into something I tried to get off the ground when I was very young and didn't really know how any of this worked.
Something that Emily Arrow and I chatted about years ago, my ham could well be a decade because I think it was before "Luncon".
Was that neither of us was particularly happy with how the best dramatic category works in that it doesn't reward short film.
So if I was allowed to pick a Hugo category and do it as a one year thing, I would pick best short film.
I would probably say films of 25 minutes or less.
And if I was going to do this at Glasgow, I would work with chap who does Sci-Fi London and I would have a kind of Glasgow sponsored program of shorts in the year that showcased eligible shorts from around the world and encouraged the Worldcon members to watch and vote for their favorites and have that as a Hugo.
It would tie in well with Sci-Fi London, which I think is a great British thing and also tie in obviously I know that other countries do this as well so I'm not trying to say Britain's better, but like I just say it ties in with a fan pursuit in Britain which I think would be cool.
And yeah, and I think short films are underrepresented in the Hugos and probably are not as influential on the genre as short stories are, which is probably why, but yeah, Liz.
I would say the Sci-Fi London man, I think it's still Louis Savvy.
Do you think there is a danger that your category would be dominated by essentially the five minute shorts that picks up out before the films and the kind of five minute MCU short films and maybe not kind of get those less commercial short films that you may be aiming to to include?
Maybe you might have to do something like restrict them and say like, you know, there can only be one film by any given studio.
Maybe so you only got one Pixar or one Marvel.
I don't know if that would work. I don't know how you would do that.
Because I guess for a special Hugo category, do you have to hammer out the wording in as much detail as you do if it's going into the Constitution or does the Hugo Administrator get to sort of call a spade a spade a bit more?
I don't know how that works.
What did they do for Best Video Game? Did they have a very kind of rigid definition? I assume they did probably.
Yeah, they had a rigid definition that was very different from the one that here Alexandra is putting forward for the actual suggestion, which was slightly annoying, but there we go.
So no, you have it. It's done the same way as anything else.
You just announced the committee announces the wording that people are supposed to work to.
I don't know if you could definitely include just one from a studio or anything like that. It's very, and they don't even have to have voting. The welcome could just reward a Hugo.
I'm going to talk about that a bit later.
I had forgotten that that's true, but that is true, isn't it?
Yeah, 100%.
Wow.
Badger is the best cat Hugo.
Yes, yes.
A couple of months ago, John said fan art is hilariously undiscoverable, but I don't think it is as undiscoverable as short film.
We've been talking about it in the context of the sci-fi London Film Festival, and some short films are on YouTube, but an awful lot of them aren't.
They're not distributed. They are dependent on film festivals around the world, and I hope that there are more online film festivals where we can see short films.
I think we might try to surface them a bit on octa thought when they happen, but it's incredibly difficult to survey the ground.
One of my concerns with this is that it's going to be hard for the Wussfuss members to access short films to nominate, because there's just so many of them, and they are so undiscoverable.
But presumably, you'd end up with the same sort of thing as you get in the other categories of general release. So if something was playing the Film Festival circuit and then after it had finished the circuit, they put it on YouTube in the next year, presumably it would then count in that year.
It depends.
But everything has to have special, everything has to have special dispensations, doesn't it?
Yeah, so it has to be voted on work by work, but also if you are going to, in my proposal, you'd be doing some sort of magic portal that Worldcom members would log into to watch the movies.
And so I would argue that even if something had had a limited release Film Festival, if it was widely available to the Worldcom membership, I think laying people nominated for best film.
Like, I think that is one of the big problems, and I think you'd need to address it by making sure that you worked with the filmmakers to get a lot of these movies into the sphere of the votership.
And I think that's why I wouldn't necessarily advocate again for it to be added as a permanent Hugo, but I think doing it as a special Hugo and really putting a lot behind it to increase the profile of short films in that year, that would be really cool.
And I think there might be scope there.
So Esther, if you're listening to this, I think you have a volunteer for curating your Film Festival.
No, I think if you're going to do it, you want to work with Louis Savvy because he's done so much great work for Sci-Fi London.
And I think, firstly, I mean, it should be his right refusal because I don't know if there's anyone else in the UK that's done more for science fiction short film, but I'd rather suspect there isn't.
So he should probably get the kudos, but also he has the contacts, the drive and the know-how, and also they've started doing the online films now, which means that maybe the technical expertise is there now, too.
Again, started this out by not really thinking it was a coherent idea, and now I've set out loud and I'm like, "Ooh, they're interesting.
Do you want to do best audio presentation, Alison?"
One of the things that's happened this year is that last year, the Hugo Awards Study Committee was asked to go away and have a think about best audio book as a Hugo category.
John and I are both on the Hugo Awards Study Committee, mostly because we wanted to put some oomph behind Best Game, and whenever anyone mentions Best Game, we're like, "Yes, this must be a Hugo."
But I have been chair of the Best Audio Book Subcommittee on that. I don't think we're going to recommend Best Audio Book, which I think is there is not a compelling argument for having it as a Hugo category, but I thought, and got some encouragement from other people, but one way to push this into the long grass would be to think about best dramatic presentation and whether there was scope for splitting out audio from video.
If I ever take this to Wispus as a proposal, I will call my proposal Video Kill the Radio Star, and I think that there is an argument that there's a lot of good work being done in audio, and it all gets completely in audio dramatic presentation.
So that includes things like fictional podcasts, it includes audio books, especially audio books like Sandman, where more has been done than just reading out the book.
It includes things like the Big Finish audio dramas, and quite a lot of other audio stuff that is very good, and that we are a professional podcast that are dramatic, like, "Welcome to Night Vale," and "The Lovecraftian Ones" that the BBC do would be eligible and would be good.
And, like, for example, the adaptation of RUR that I had as a pick a couple of months ago, as somebody who likes a lot of audio content, I feel like it's being completely overshadowed in the Hugos in much the same way as short films are.
There's a real discussion here, and I think it impinges on both of our categories, which is basically like, "I love short film, and I love audio dramatic presentations."
Like, I mean, I'm a recent convert to short film, I've been watching Science Research in London for two years, so, like, you know, that is the extent of my short film knowledge, really, but I've really enjoyed being in that, and I'm really glad that they've put it online so I can.
And I've listened, I've been listening to dramatic presentation on the radio since the next day of the show, it's a galaxy when I was a kid.
But I think there is a problem here, which is, I love both of them, I think it would be cool for them to get recognition, but I'm not sure they're a big enough part of the genre for them to be part of the Hugos every year.
So I think doing them as special categories would be a really good way of kind of squaring that circle as it were.
Yes, and I think we have to have disclaimer for this entire segment, which is "No More Hugos, Upper Brackets, Apart From The Best Game Hugo, Obviously, Close Brackets."
Yeah, and we can make room for Best Game Hugo by getting rid of best editors, so it is fine.
Oh, John.
Please write in listeners, please write in.
On the subject of Hugo voting, it is now open until the 11th of August.
So you've got a little bit more time, listeners.
Keep reading, keep going.
Don't, whatever you do, stop reading on the basis you've got loads of time, because that is the way to miss a deadloy for phowing in the hugos.
Ask me how I know.
In what order should we do picks?
Should we let Alison hang on about Abba for a bit, because then we won't, she won't go on past like 10.30.
Ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha.
Yeah, let's let Alison hang on about Abba for a bit.
She's put like an essay in the show notes.
Go on, Alison.
Go on, Alison. Get wangin'.
No, all I've done is put to the show notes.
It's what, it's the...
No, I mean, I'm genuinely interested to hear about Abba, because I missed the Zoom meeting immediately after you went.
So I've not really heard the story yet, so I am paying attention.
Yes, tell us about Abba.
So I am going to wang on about Abba, and this is because as regular listeners to what to thought might know,
I'm not really a science fiction fan at all.
What I am is a futurist.
I really like things that are about the future and of the future, and about three miles from here.
Abba has built a purpose-built arena where they're doing a light show, where you think that you've got Abba from the 70s on stage,
but obviously you don't really. It's just magic done by the industrial light of magic people.
Now, they've had a thousand animators working for several years on this sort of spend of vast amount of money.
Tickets are quite expensive, and six of us, all science fiction fans, went last week and we had a lot of fun.
So if you didn't know that it was a magic trick, you just wouldn't question.
You just assume you're watching a life-bad.
It looks exactly like watching a life-bad except better in some ways because of all the money that's been spent on it.
And it was fantastic. The sandals are very, very good.
They've done the voices by recording Abba now, but blending the voices using machine learning with Abba at the height of their vocal skills.
So that's quite good too. So it sounds amazing. It looks amazing. It's very, very good. It's quite expensive,
but I mean, I think they got spent 140 million pounds on it, and you can see where that was spent.
They gave us free pin badges, and I'm just afraid some of the massive cost of our tickets by immediately flogging the Mollie Bay
for not inconsiderable amounts of money, not as much as the ticket's cost but plenty.
And I went to something a little bit like this at Disney World in 1979, but this is quite a bit better.
That was quite a long time ago, so it was great. I thought it was amazing.
It's probably Pepper's Ghost, which is Victorian-like trick.
Yeah, I was going to say, what thing did you go to like this in Disney World in 1979?
A Pepper's Ghost stage show where, oh no, it was actually an animatronic stage show where they'd got heads of presidents speaking
and declaiming things about the US Constitution. It was not as good.
Oh, it's the Holy President's. Yeah, but there's no Pepper's Ghost in the Holy President's.
No, no, it was just like heads, I think.
It's full presidents, and now a bit worried that you've kind of conflated it with future armour heads in a jar.
You did also go and see a Pepper's Ghost probably as well.
I've seen Pepper's Ghost on many occasions, but this is just fantastic, and apparently.
This is where you take a lot of the best people in the world at doing this thing and put enormous amounts of money on it,
but also it is quite futurey because this is not creepy because actual abba, all four of them were involved in the motion capture for this
and the stage management and how they walk and look.
And so it's a lot less creepy than it would be or that it will be when they do this with dead pop stars,
which I'm sure is going to be in the works for some people.
Oh, yeah, it's coming. 100%.
Because you can see a lot of bands looking at this and go, oh, this is a thing.
And I think this is the thing where I go, I go to a lot of festivals, and one of the things that happens at festivals
is that bands from the 70s and 80s come on stage and do all their old hit.
There's normally a couple of people from the original band and a load of session musicians come on stage
and do all their old hits.
Like, what, like that? It's quite good. This is a lot better than that.
If you like Abba at all, I would recommend, if you like Abba of Futurism at all, you should get on to see this.
It's good.
But I'm not right in thinking there's no actual requirement for Abba to be there when it's happening.
It's just like there's a hologram and, you know,
no, it's a film, right?
Yeah, it's a phenomenal money maker. I mean, if they're charged, I mean, I know it must have cost them a lot of money,
but, you know, there's no reason they couldn't run this for, you know, 20 years.
Well, they have a live band. One of the ways they make it feel really good is that they have a live band,
about a 12-piece live band on stage.
Okay.
But that is because you'll be all session musicians who can just be fired and you can just hire new ones when they retire and stuff.
It is. Yes. They're not going to be paid a lot. If you look at this and go, oh, they've put it in London.
Could they do this in every city in the world?
And there's a bit where they introduce the band and they say, and I'm going to introduce the band.
And they don't actually introduce the band in the way that a live band would where they say the names of the people in the band.
And I was like, aha, that is because they have a film which they can roll.
And they worked with Abba for six weeks and they can be playing this all around the world until the money runs out.
So I think you will see Abba.
But it's a purpose built arena. This is a very spendy activity.
People have spent a lot of money on it. It's very exciting in a kind of weird way.
So my mum and dad are huge Abba fans and they were entirely unimpressed by this because they were like,
it's just a film. I don't understand why it's good.
Oh, no, it's great.
And so I'm interested by the disparity in the reactions.
And I must admit, I think I'm more...
I think it's really impressive technically. And if it was a band I liked more than I like,
I'm not a huge Abba fan. But if it was a band I really liked, I don't know, the Eagles, I'd be like,
"Ooh, interesting." But I do wonder whether...
If a band does this that I like when it's still new and shiny, I'll be like, "Oh, I'll go and see that."
And it'll be like magic. It'll be very science fiction. I'll be very into it.
But in like 20 years time where there's loads of machine learning concerts,
replicating old bands at their heyday, I think I might be quite a lot more jaded about it
than going to see actual live music. And I did because I went to see the Eagles on their farewell one tour
and it wasn't, you know, they were older and they did not sound how they did on the records
and there were a lot more horns and stuff. But it was still amazing and the energy in the room was still brilliant.
And to be fair, the energy in the room must be brilliant at Abba too, because you've got like, what,
20,000 Abba fans, all of whom really like Abba.
No, three. Three. That's the other thing is that it's a small arena. So all the seats, all the...
Ooh.
It's purpose built and it's small. So all the seats are amazing and they're standing at the front.
I'm going to go back on a standing ticket so I can get right up to the front. Very excited by that.
And I think that if you're...
Well, that's interesting. I hadn't appreciated that.
If your folks are Abba fans, they would probably enjoy this a whole lot.
And I would commend it. But obviously people could do what they like, right? You know.
So those are the two reactions though, which are... Oh yeah.
Oh, God, this is amazing. This is fantastic. I'm so excited. I never got the chance to see Abba in the 70s.
I'm really excited to go and this will be great and I don't care that it's a light trick.
And why would you want to do that? It's just a film.
No, I mean, that's exactly it. I did see. I just remembered because I was like, you were like, I never got to see them.
I never got to see Injuri in the blockheads.
Oh, I've seen them.
But I did get to see Phil Jupiters and the blockheads and that was really good.
A festival like Little Day Long festival thing in Stanford. And that was nice.
I also understand that this is the technology that was used to do that performance of the Queen on the balcony on the final day of the Jubilee weekend when a holographic version of the Queen came out and waved to the crowd.
The difficult thing with that is that obviously it's much more difficult to do this sort of hologram for a lizard.
My pick is Moon Knight. This is not particularly current because Moon Knight wrapped up a few weeks ago now, but I did quite like it.
So Moon Knight is a character I got into through broadcasting because there's a podcast called The Incompable and they did a summer long tournament of superheroes.
And Moon Knight made it to the last 16 in that tournament, beating such little known characters as Thor.
And so I kind of read the comics because I was like, oh, this is interesting.
They're all talking about Moon Knight a lot. He sounds kind of weird.
And I got into the comics which kind of starts to explore his character much more in the sense of like dissociative identity disorder and stuff like that.
And also the mysticism of the character was much more focused.
Whereas originally Moon Knight was a bad Batman rip-off and originally the different personalities were basically just alter egos he had while being a bad Batman rip-off.
And so I was really pleased that Moon Knight, the series, lent very much more into DID mysticism than it did into bad Batman rip-offs, which I thought was very good.
In general, I very much like Oscar Isaac. I was a little bit uncomvinced by the accent, but then that gets like specifically addressed in the universe of the show, which I thought was brilliant.
And it, I think, kept me engaged as someone who likes the character. It kind of gave me enough to be like, oh, I think I might know what's happening there.
And then I was like, oh, that was right. And that was very exciting. But also a lot of the supporting characters were really good and I liked Ethan Hawke a lot.
I understood a lot better why they cast him as the villain after about episode 3 or episode 4. And yeah, just really, really enjoyed it generally.
I think it's much more character driven than plot driven. I have a few friends who found a couple of the episodes a bit lacking in plot.
And I was like, that was so full of stuff, but it was a lot kind of, it wasn't much plot stuff. It was more kind of internal stuff.
But I kind of think that makes sense for the character anyway, because the character is very much about, well, because he has multiple personalities, they do tend to focus on that a lot in some of the comics.
So that kind of made sense to me. Anyway, but yeah, I really enjoyed it generally. I think it is probably my favourite of the Marvel shows so far beating previous favourite Hawke I.
Alison, you haven't seen Moon Knight yet.
I haven't seen any of it. I know nothing of it. I have zoned out through your description in case I am, in case it was a bit spoilery for me.
I mean, I am excited to watch it. If you could send me a note saying which bits of the Marvel Cinematic and Television Universe I need to have watched before I start watching Moon Knight, I will put them on my iceberg.
None.
Yeah, it's probably probably okay. I could start from the beginning of Moon Knight. In that case, I'll do it after Severance. I'm not finished with Severance yet.
To the point where one of our friends was like, I don't really understand the point of this because how does it tie into the rest of the MCU, which I think is like the opposite reaction to Alison of things so interesting.
Well, only because I'm in MCU bankruptcy.
Liz, what did you think of Moon Knight?
I think I since you give up and just start watching the MCU in Random Order. Just go for it. Just pick what looks fun.
Yes, to it.
I kind of have had that experience because that's how I did comics as a child because we only got comics kind of randomly when we were lucky and we just really didn't.
And we just read bits of the Marvel Universe totally out of order and not understand anything. I still quite like them a lot.
Yeah, to walk both ways or pill in the snow to get your Marvel comic.
Yes.
I've seen Moon Knight. It's pretty good. The plot is... I mean, the plot's not very good, is it? So it's a good job. It's not particularly plot oriented because the plot is basically a bit...
The plot is a bit of nonsense with some fighting and so on. But Oscar Isaac is very, very good.
He somehow manages to pull off having these two identities, one of which is a mercenary and one of which is a museum nerd.
And somehow Oscar Isaac manages to pull off looking like a nerd.
Yeah.
You know, kind of looking completely unremarkable in a way that I didn't...
You wouldn't think he would if you sort of saw him in the other persona.
And yeah, so I thought he was very good as a central character.
And I think the supporting actors in it are also pretty good.
It's just, you know, the plot was kind of a "Let's Find Out About this superhero" and "Oh, there's a threat to the world and there's a villain's person and we have to resolve it."
And here's a little hook for maybe the next season.
And I was not particularly engaged in any of that, really. But I did like Oscar Isaac.
I do very much like... I do like F.M.A.R.E.R. and portrayal of this god who is not really a benevolent force on Oscar Isaac character.
But it was not... I don't think it's right up there in my favourite MCU ones just because it felt like the plot was a bit like an MCU.
Oh, there is a superhero and a villain and a threat in the world.
And I couldn't tell you anything that made it stand out particularly from the other 27 iterations of this plot.
But I quite enjoyed it anyway. Especially the hippo.
Yes, yes.
Sorry to anyone who was champing at the bit to find out what Liz's pick was, but I have to go to brunch now because it's Father's Day.
And so I am cruelly cutting Liz off in order to not annoy my family.
But that was the Octa thought podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me.
Does that mean I wanged on about Abba for too long?
No, you aren't going to about Abba for as long as I expected.
[Music]
I just finished the last graduate by Naomi Novick, which I was good.
And then I was a cliffhanger and I was just...
I got to the end of the book and I was like on the train and I was like, "Oh no, I want to know."
Anyway, I have to wait for the next one.
I think the third one is out this year though, so you should be okay.
Yeah, people have said the second one ends on a massive cliffhanger.
It's an entirely predictable cliffhanger, really.
That's all I said in my pick.
Entirely predictable cliffhanger in hindsight.
So the first one also ends on a giant cliffhanger, so it fits with the series, I think.
Yeah, but in the case of the first cliffhanger, I knew what it would be from like page three of the book,
so I wasn't very surprised.
I'm pretty sure I know what the second one is going to be as well, not the time for the second book.
This is one of the things where I'm kind of like, I have to grade these things on a curve
because when books are as predictable as this, you go, "Oh yes, but it's young adults."
You probably wouldn't have spotted it when you were 16.
I mean, I didn't spoil it by never try.
Whenever I spotted a twist in a plot coming, I'm like, "That was extremely obvious because I noticed it,
which is why I really hate that Miles episode of Doctor Who, because I saw the twist coming at the beginning,
and I was like, "That is bad writing if I notice."
Yeah, so the problem is that the more science fiction you read, or the more books you read generally,
the more inclined you are to spot where writers are doing things are then you.
And you're correct that if you're insisting on having fun when you read,
it's more fun to read without spotting what's going to happen.
Thanks, I think.
And I remember this from reading the first book of a song of ice and fire,
and I did not spot the big reveal, despite the fact that my friends were like, "This is a thing."
And I was like, "Oh, that's so obvious. I did not spot it."
And of course, it's the big reveal for the entire series, not just the first book,
but it's very obvious from the first book, if you're paying attention.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod in Com