Worldcon if you're listening please have a silent disco you've got to call this out job is it too late for that suggestion yes.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very one hundred and tenth episode of octa Thorpe a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom which is winging its way to you on the 23rd of May 2024 I'm John Cox and I'm Allison Scott and I'm Liz Batty and we have letters of comments.
We heard from Tammy Coxon who wrote to say she thinks if we don't want Chinese corporate or government involvement in Worldcon we can't ever have a Worldcon in China regardless of who's bidding it because as we saw in 2023 the leadership organizing committee venue and dates are all subject to change based on external factors such a sponsorship and she would not trust that a group entirely composed of Chinese fans would be able to avoid being thoroughly co-opted.
And we had a little bit of a discussion about this on Facebook so if you're interested in seeing the full discussion do go and visit our Facebook I think I would be willing to reach this conclusion if there had been two separate groups of fans that had been thoroughly co-opted but I am hesitant to assume that one point makes a line equally I do understand the concern and I do think it is something we'd have to go into eyes wide open.
I don't really know how to make this better I don't want to just conclude that we can't ever have Worldcons in China but equally I don't want to have been the situation again where the Worldcon gets co-opted for the money and the prestige so it is a hard one and I do see the concern.
It's a tricky one because you don't want to say no more China bids we think it will be co-opted but I also don't want to have a second one that gets co-opted in the same way because you know for me once shame on you.
I mean we could do something like you know and I think this will happen to any future Chinese bid is when they come to the vanishing position they're going to get sorry when they come to the future Worldcon question session at Worldcons and smothcons they're going to get a lot of questions about this and quite rightly I think there will be questions like what involvement will corporate
sponsors have will you consider changing your date so you're going to change your venue how set in stone are you on this but I mean they might say look this is generally how things run we are a bit more beholden to corporate interests who also give us a lot of money for this convention and other ones.
Then we have to decide if we're happy with that I think I'm also a bit less bothered by corporate sponsorship than a lot of people at Worldcon it doesn't bother me too much if you have like a corporate sponsor who you know and they say oh such a body kindly contributed the closed captioning for the Hugo ceremony until we mention the beginning or whatever.
I think you don't be careful but I'm not totally against that I mean I guess the Chinese one was not so much sponsors is other we think other corporate interest but you know if you want sponsors then they want something in return and then you have to decide if you're willing to give them what they want in return.
But if we don't have an attractive offering then we just want to get their money and we have to live with that.
So I also think there's an interesting thing here which is I'm not opposed to sponsorship I wasn't bothered that like so San Jose the Hugo ceremony like had Google sponsorship and I wasn't all that bothered by that.
I mean not withstanding Google's military contracting but like that's a whole different kettle of fish but the thing I'm worried about is the committee being dictated by the sponsor right.
And I don't know how because I think it's fair to say that sponsorship is a big part of China and we're seeing that but I don't know how much that extends to it's a foregone conclusion that any WorldCom would have its committee dictated by the sponsors.
And that's the thing right I don't know and I could make an assumption based on one data point but it is tricky right because if we do it again and the same thing happens again then that is going to feel real bad but that I think the reverse option which is kind of never letting a Chinese
bid again or you know I'm not suggesting we ban the bidding but like never never kind of voting for that bid again. I don't know if that's better I don't know it's really hard.
I don't know if I have a good answer.
I think it's yeah it's one of those things where we don't want to borrow them entirely but I think there are also maybe other things will make this moot if they do decide to not they.
Yes if we do decide as a WorldCom to have certain minimum standards for bidding that China can't meet then we might not get a China bid for a long time anyway.
I'm remarkably comfortable with the idea of just banning China for a while and hopefully this sort of thing will sort itself out in the meantime.
And if not then the fans at the end of the ban can have a think about it or people can reverse the ban if they'd like but I'd be 100% up for a thing that just says China aren't allowed to bid the WorldCom for 10 years because they screwed us up the last time.
I mean I guess the thing is normally Spanish pressure is what does this right like Japan bid again in 2017 and I when talking to people kind of heard a lot of negative sentiment that they wouldn't win because people still remembered that 2007 had terrible
budget issues but that doesn't work when you have enough people that you could probably just win the bid anyway.
But yeah we have to decide kind of yeah do we ban China for the actions of WorldCom and then you know do we say okay five years and then think again but then they might just plan for a bid in six years time.
We heard from Jonathan Cowie of SF concatenation who is is a very useful news publication but is only kind of annual so you know and also a website.
I suspect even catch up might be subject to the colossal clean crawled corpus and therefore any video might be used to pay an I.A.
Maybe not because I think they're behind a paywall so perhaps not but I don't know I'm not an expert.
It just takes one solitary nefarious pod to create a deep fake of someone and therefore mischief.
I've discovered that my own work has been used without permission to train chat AIs and I'm not comfortable with that.
I am very surprised by the many SF fans willingness to embrace the cloud use things like Google dots etc.
Yes it is impossible for average folk to prevent big hitters from getting our data but to give it to them on our plate on a plate having such folks read the likes of Brunner Gibson Orwell and others my flabber is gassed.
I'm going to say that there are two sorts of science fiction fans right there are the science fiction fans who are science fiction fans because they believe that technology is wonderful scientific progress is amazing and the future is
the future is beyond our wildest dreams of wonderfulness and there are ones who believe that science fiction is telling us about terrible disasters that will be flawless if we so much as touch the modern world and I'm always going to be way over towards the first camp
rather than the second camp obviously that it's actually both but I still think that on the whole we get more from the stuff that we lose.
I can't I kind of like a and I think we're just at the stage of ironing out the bugs in the early implementations and it's going to be phenomenal and change our world in ways we can't even imagine yet.
I think I think I have two reactions here which is firstly I think it would be very sad if Jonathan hadn't started as a concatenation because he was worried about nefarious actors scraping his content and so I do take the point that that is a problem
but I hope that we don't let that fear get in the way of making a vibrance scene which we can all enjoy. I am much more skeptical about AI than Alison mostly because I have trained machine learning models and I'm like they're fine.
Like it's just complicated regression I don't think it's going to change the world. It's quite useful when you want to fit a line to some data though that's good.
I think I'm also more in the middle of well firstly I mostly like SF because SF lets us put people in situations and imagine how they react realistically I don't really care if that's anything to do with technology. I like the people.
But also I like the SF that's course of retail as much as I like the SF that's like since a wonder I like 2001 as much as I like 1984 and you can't take either away from me.
Yeah I think most people are in the middle right and a lot of books I would say are in the middle. New ones.
Recent example right like thinking of things like the Terraformers by Anilene Uitz which has both corporate overlords running a colonialist system and also people rebelling against this and finding their own way.
Kind of a lot of things have both of these right. I would say personally yeah I think the benefits of the Google Cloud currently outweigh the potential disadvantage that someone might steal my recipe lists and train an AI with them.
I think I'm also skeptical about AI because I keep asking it simple questions and it absolutely cannot do it.
Like it is not to me like an intelligent thing you can so see that it's just like predicting the next thing.
So I don't currently think it's going to either destroy the world or bring us unlimited prosperity.
I do worry about the scraping of all human knowledge into it and the fact that it's now kind of polluting its own.
Everything is now being polluted with AI output which is scraped from past output and I worry that it's going to ruin a lot of things on the internet.
And I worry that a lot of people are planning to try and use it to automate all kinds of things that's not very good at.
But I'm not personally worried about EasterCon recordings as you say they're behind the paywall.
But I think it is something to think about for future EasterCons to say look the recordings are they're going to be locked away so you can see them with a membership but otherwise we're not going to save them and upload them to anywhere they can be scraped.
I mean there's also I think I can't remember if this was the most recent one that some of the recordings are going to try and go into like an archive of recordings and that's potentially something that could be scraped by AI.
So I think we do need to think about letting people know what will happen to these recordings both in the short term and potentially in the future.
But I don't think that's a big enough worry for me to stop me being on panels.
So conversation has given its archive to fanact.org and the science fiction foundation library both with donation letters attached that say we'd like you to use it like this.
Obviously you can't really constrain libraries or archives quite as much as you might like but we thought that the value to individual researchers is probably greater than the risk here.
I wanted to pick up a second point from Joel's letter which he says is the good news is that within a few years you'll be able to generate three AI audio clones of yourselves and then create an AI edition of OctaThorp.
We've already done this and it was in episode.
No I have no clue.
It was about two years ago somebody said to us an AI version of OctaThorp.
Andrew January sent one.
Although it was a transcript I mean at this point you probably could feed all the OctaThorp into something in deep fakers all.
That would be funny slash disturbing.
I think this is a really good example that Jonathan has at the end of the email though right which is should we have let our fear of that prevent us doing this podcast would that have been better.
And I mean probably there are some people who are like yeah I would have been much better like we'll listen to them we're on.
But like I think that really any time you put anything out into the world it's a risk right and I don't want to end up in a situation where I don't feel able to do that.
But I think I would like to thank Jonathan he was the only person who wrote in and he wrote a very eloquent description of his reasons which were very thought provoking as probably evidence by the fact we spent quite a long time having our thoughts provoked by them.
So thank you very much to Jonathan.
Provoke us any time Jonathan.
From thought provoking to thought provoking here is Chris Garcia who missed locking last time and is sorry and is doing his own penance he's wearing a hair shirt or a sweater vest.
I cannot believe we didn't notice I'm really sorry.
I did but I didn't want to you didn't want to ask him for not locking up after 109 continues.
We don't want to call him out now.
I thought I would give Chris Garcia the space to announce that Chris Garcia had not written a lot.
I mean I think this is the end of the podcast I think it's all downhill from now.
True.
Chris writes in on the same subject as Tammy saying the thing he wants is a Chinese fandom world con not a business opportunity world con but does note that China will do what China will do.
So comments on the wealth topics that we talked about last time the money money money he's priced out of all but his local conventions these days and it's looking likely he won't even be able to get a virtual membership for Glasgow.
We need to address costs and there's no easy way to do it.
It's one of the reasons he's big into us getting sponsorships and that's actually a good point.
We did not discuss how seeking sponsorship might make this burden slightly loiter for people who are less less able to attend these things.
And yeah I think that's a really interesting discussion that we didn't touch on hardly at all but maybe we should, we should loop back to that in the future.
We heard from Sandra Bond who said "Well this one's thoroughly depressing or is it just me?
I have a terrible pain in the diodes all down my left side."
She didn't say that bit.
I don't know we will try to be less depressing Sandra we're very sorry.
I realized that Sandra sent her very depressing look at a time when she was about a week away from finishing the latest novel and now she's finished it and it's off to the editor so congratulations Sandra.
I just want to go back to Sandra's thing which is yeah we should have.
I think I am as noted on the previous episode I am quite privileged and I think one of the examples of that privilege is that it had not occurred to me that last episode could be really very depressing if you were in a position where money is a big problem for you.
I do think we probably should have made that clearer up at the top and that is an example of my privilege blinding me to some of these discussions.
We did put it there are content warnings in the show notes and we did have a content warning for all privilege but that is why we have that is why we have content warnings and trigger warnings because yes these issues are potentially very gloomy if you are affected by them.
I am sorry that anyone who found that that was a gloomy episode but I will say thank you to the people who said it was interesting.
There were few people who said it was an interesting discussion so I'm hopeful that the interestingness and the value of having the discussion outweighs the gloom we may have caused.
I think it was quite depressing episode well it could have been quite depressing episode even if you were quite privileged because we were basically saying you know here or what is in which is to comes might just not be feasible anymore which is quite depressing.
Yeah that's also true.
Sorry will be more cheery we promise.
Yes.
Before we start being more cheery.
Johnny badly wrote and said another area of economic privileges transport if you have a car then going to a convention over the east weekend is not a concern.
I would just put an aside here which is this is said by somebody who's never sat in the on the M6 for four hours on morning Thursday afternoon but.
Whereas I waited until I saw the planned railworks list this year before deciding not to go but that does mean I get to go to fund con one and I will see you there.
I think I want to say I've been to every east concert 2007 I've taken the trade to all of them and it's always been fine and I don't know whether my I think I might just be a trained unicorn because a lot of people care by car this year.
Oh that is true we did drive but that was mostly because I could get left.
I mean lots of people came to east con by train and they all got there and it was not brilliant but no form of traffic is ever great on east weekend.
I mean I would say this is another another bit privileges often the rail work start on the Friday so if you can travel Thursday to Tuesday you will sometimes miss out on the train works.
Okay John's can't relate it now. I've been to 16 Easter cons I've traveled to to by car which were the first one of the last one I've been to all the others have done train and the vast majority have done Friday to Monday and it has in general been absolutely fine.
I think by I have a very different perspective of trains to other people because I because a lot of people say you shouldn't travel by train on Christmas Eve and I've done that bunch of times and it's always fine.
So I don't know I just wonder if I'm like I maybe trains just love me.
We would go to east con by train routinely were it not for the fact that we are almost always carrying a load of Easter con related crap in our car and in fact we are going to Glasgow by train and we are already 12 weeks out going.
How is all this stuff going to get to Glasgow that you know and we will find mechanism.
I would say I've definitely had problems on trains where the railworks mean maybe instead of it being one or two trains it's some kind of complicated for stop for change journey which is a problem for some people more than others.
It is obviously harder if you're disabled.
Oh yeah no that's true.
I do love trains though.
And I think the other thing is that we have had as we have previously noted there have been a lot of Easter cons in Birmingham International and London and it is true that I think when Easter cons are in less well connected venues the risk of trains going haywire is much higher.
And that I think is something worth bearing in mind.
I also think it's Houston I think Houston always just has railworks like they love having railworks every year I think right in if you have facts.
I bloody hate Houston I'm very glad I've never lived anywhere that needs me to go through Houston.
Yeah it is an armpit.
I'm very fond of Houston and I have kind of softy romantic reasons for why because I used to spend quite lots of time catching trains to or from Houston to see Steven.
So you know but it is a hole I mean obviously it's a big 70s hole it is also a good time to remind people that while we are talking about trains the train timetables for August are already up.
And so you can go and buy your trains to Wilkham and I have indeed done that for the Princey some of 28 pounds I think which seems pretty good.
28 pounds from Thailand because that is good.
Sorry we do like being absolute bananas on this show.
You say the most sober voice possible.
No that is from like in the Northwest to Glasgow but it seems like pretty good there are some pretty good deals out there.
Do you want an under pressing update?
Because we got a letter from Farah Mendelton so you may remember that last time I read out confidently Mark Blumner's letter saying there were 450ish people who were there.
And Farah has in fact sent us the four membership numbers such that we can say that there were just under 600 members of which 50 were virtual but that would be 550 people on site if they were all there not 450.
So apologies to levitation for making them sound like the smallest used to come for a long time when they were in fact bigger than that.
Mark I think your research skills have let you down.
I think it's beyond the record that this is the opinion of Elizabeth absolute wrong ed batty and does not reflect the opinions of her two to hosts.
No you were to cut that out that's too harsh it's too harsh.
It's going in.
I'm partway through my my next times pick and and one of the things it's talking about is a bunch of people who were very fans who were very argumentative and I'm like oh oh am I like that am I the batty.
Have I have I just started a fan feud and I'm the bad guy I hope not sorry Mark I'll buy your beer or several.
Did it feel like a 550 person will come that's question.
Easter con hmm it's got there.
No it did not feel like yeah it but I will say it did not feel like 550 person east con but it was in a much bigger venue than usual so like that is kind of tricky because I it's because it's a venue very unlike any venue with a lot of people.
It's really unlike any venue with previous we've had in a while and that makes it hard to work out what it felt like really.
These are the full stats of levitation there were 586 members of which 53 were virtual which if you assume that all of the people who bought memberships attended would mean that there were 533 attendees.
I don't know how many people who buy memberships usually attend.
90%
So that's what high 400's or not that far away from Mark's number.
But in fact fewer this year because quite a lot of people bought memberships and they decided they couldn't afford to go so it probably was about 450 was that what Mark said in the first place.
Yeah I think this is sick burn notwithstanding and I'm very happy that Farah sent the stats but Farah has notably not done is sent the warm body number.
It may be that they don't know the warm body number but I'd be very interested to know you know there's enough error on both of these numbers to make me think they're probably the same number.
I guess is my point.
Farah do you also know how many membership packs were not picked up?
I've got to say normally I would pick up the warm body number from the newsletter was it in the newsletter? No okay.
We were never told the warm body number.
Alright we heard from Bridget Bradshaw who when I'm talking about combining Eastercon things into one room says all four how soon we forget.
So I have two comments one is that I wasn't talking about putting all the program into one room and two all four how soon we forget is a reference to the 1995 Worldcon.
So yes we forget things that were twenty nine years ago.
I don't.
I didn't know what this meant so I'm very glad the older members of the podcast have explained it to me thank you peeps.
I know about it I wasn't I wasn't there John how old do you think I was in 1995.
For the listener Liz made a face which I think is Liz is I might quit the podcast now face so if this is the last episode I apologize.
It's been great we've had a lovely time thank you all for listening.
I just know my fanist history John.
Yeah it's fair because you're a much better researcher than Mark Plummer.
So I was at 1995 and my experience of the 1995 Worldcon was that a lot of people were complaining about the fact that there were program rooms with no roofs in hall four at the SEC and although I remember people complaining I don't actually I didn't experience it directly because that was the program.
And even in 1995 I had largely my my Worldcon enjoyment was not mostly delivered through the medium of program.
So Alison what you're saying is we should free up space at at conventions by just putting all the program into one big room with the divider in.
What did they do in 2005?
They did not put program they did not put program into it especially also use the armadillo and the crampola I think.
Program space.
I don't know if we use that much in the armadillo but they definitely were like no we are not doing what we did in 2095 but they had there are some other holes in the SEC which did not have to be subdivided and they had one giant program room which was one of the holes I think.
And we also heard from Androzzan who says yay Ian.
Do we know who Ian is?
I was going to be know that because I don't remember.
This is all three of us are mystified and so we're very glad you listen very attentively but hang on I'm just going to go to transcripts and Google for Ian.
Are we in McDonald probably?
Hopeland.
It's probably Hopeland.
Yes.
Okay.
And finally Ming wrote to us and said another factor when deciding which program items to watch live and which to do on catch up is which ones I am most likely to want to ask questions in.
And it is certainly true that it's very annoying to watch something on catch up and have I have a trenchant question which you cannot put to the panel.
Sometimes I email them.
So I was actually alerted to this by a quote tweet ex whenever calling him by a Sats culture which was a picture of RF crying's Babel winning the Chinese Nebula award for best translated work on the same stage that the Hugo's were presented.
So yes it doesn't appear there's a big problem with giving awards to Babel in China.
But it was awarded best translation because of course it's a totally different book once the translators have finished with it.
There is an interesting thing of supposedly the three body problem.
The start of the novel in the English translation is not where the novel starts in the Chinese version so that was kind of the part about that period of history is kind of hidden inside the novel but obviously we haven't read the Chinese translation of Babel.
There are many other textural changes in the three body problem and in some other Chinese works that have been translated into English. I don't know if the same thing happens in reverse.
But it might do because part of the job of translation is making sure that the thing is you know will work culturally for the intended readership.
So translations always have explanations and so on.
I mean the three body problem translation is by Ken Liu isn't it or at least he translated I think the first and the third and he does very interesting presentations that I've seen a convention of how he does translation, how he approaches it.
So I was talking to Josh Connard Lee at Eastcom and one of the things she said is that translating Chinese is very interesting because there's usually too much in the Chinese translate into English in a way that makes any sense.
So the approach she usually takes is like pick two or three of the themes that are in the original text and try and convey those in the English.
I do think I think this is just final clinching proof if anyone needed that China has understood shitposting.
Well done China.
Yeah we will link to the rest of the winners but I haven't personally read any of them because they haven't been translated I don't think.
Anything on Beaebel Alison before we move on to the clock list.
No but it is very interesting that it won a major award for science fiction in China isn't it?
Other circumstances.
This is particularly interesting because I think the Hugo's might get their own charm in the sense that Dell magazines have asked the Hugo administrators to extend the eligibility window in the astounding award in the case of Jiren J Zhao.
Yeah I mean it's only a minor you know it's a minor fuck you compared to what could have been but yeah.
Oh yeah why not I do love her books.
Right in other award news the Clark award finalists have been announced and they are Chain Gang All Stars by Nana Kwame Adjay Brigna.
I'm so sorry. The 10% Thief by Levania Lakshmi Narayan.
In Ascension by Martin McKinnis. The Mountain in the Sea by Ray Leyla.
Some Desperate Glory by Emily Tesh and Corey Fad does Social Mobility by Isabel Waidner.
This is interesting because there is one book that overlaps with the Hugo Awards which is the Emily Tesh but there is also a book that overlaps with the Nebula's which is the Ray Nailer.
But very interestingly it overlaps with the 2022 Nebula's not the 2023 Nebula's so the Mountain in the Sea was nominated in the year that Babel won the Nebula.
I really hate that the Nebula's do it differently to other awards.
So the Nebula's actually do it differently.
The 2023 Nebula Awards are the Saint-Brite Doors of Water Outlaws, Translations State the Terraformers.
The 2024 Hugo's Correspond to that year and the 2024 Clark Awards Correspond to that year.
So it is the Nebula's that are the odd one out.
So interesting shortlist I think. I've heard of, I've not read any of them yet but three of them are on my iPad waiting to be read.
How are you guys?
I'm very excited about this shortlist because there's one I've read, one I already own.
One that I've borrowed from the library, one that's on my library hold list.
One I hadn't previously heard of.
But I've read some desperate glory, it's the only one I've said far away.
The reason that the Mountain in the Sea is in the Clark Awards for 2024 but it was in the Nebula's in 2023 is because of the UK publication date being a year afterwards.
So the Clark cares about UK publication date whereas the Nebula's do not.
I have read three heard of two and never heard of one before it turned upon this list which is always nice.
I've read the Mountain in the Sea and I think I picked it a while back.
I quite enjoyed it but it's probably third on my personal list of the ones I've read.
I'm pretty sure I read it ages ago in ebook and the Clark counts paper publication so that's also another weirdness because it came out in ebook first in the UK before paperback.
Yep, that is about like, sentient octopuses.
I think the thing I really liked in the Mountain in the Sea is it has this thread essentially following a group of, a group of sailors who have been enslaved onto ships and are basically being trafficked around as slave labour on these ships.
Which I think is more interesting than it's kind of main thread which is about hyper-evolved octopuses and stuff on an island of Vietnam.
I've also read In Ascension. I read it like nearly a year ago I think but it was very good.
I remember it being, it's a book where kind of the characters are quite hard to like but still interesting.
The main character is kind of a sort of very single minded person who ends up putting a co-work above all else and that is quite interesting and it's an interesting science fiction novel.
It's beautifully written. I'm not super surprised to see it turn up on the Clark list and the other one I've read is Some Desperate Glory by Emily Tesh which we spoilers for shadowing.
We'll discuss in a few episodes because it's a Hugo book. I've also now bought the 10% thief so I've got that queued up and we'll try and get hold of the other two so I can be fully educated in preparation to you know violently disagree with the jury as it's traditional.
But in this case the jury occludes Nick Clark who is friend of the podcast and someone we can argue with in the bar.
Indeed and will.
The other thing to mention I guess is that these six writers none of them have ever been nominated for the Clark before.
They're all new to the Clark list which is interesting. I mean Martin McInnes has written other books but I know the nailer and the Tesh debut novels.
I'm not sure about the other three. I don't think they're wide no is a debut novel.
But that is interesting and I mean it is also interesting I think if you compare the 2024 nebula's to the 2033 nebula's and compare the 2024 Clark finalists to the 2033 Clark finalists is notable.
I think that the 2024 finalist rosters are stronger than the previous year.
The same was true of the Hugo's I think but obviously that was much harder to talk about because of all of the kafafu with the Hugo's we don't know how representative the Hugo finalist list actually was.
But yeah I think it's a sign that 2023 was a very good year for science fiction and we are seeing that recognized in the 2024 short lists.
What do you guys reckon?
I mean I agree.
Ayyy.
I read lots of good books in 2023. I'm not sure I've read lots in 2024 yet but you know I've got another seven months.
I think also 2023 was an incredibly good year for debut novels because you can put the same to bright doors on there as well as a you know an exceptional debut novel which bodes well for future years.
Neil Harrison in anonymous Claire gave a huge long list of fabulous books that were shortlisted only one of which was shortlisted for the Hugo so lots and lots and lots of good things.
Oh wait did we discuss the locus wards because the locus wards got announced or did was it just a short list got announced?
No the short list got announced.
Okay.
Oh they don't pay any attention to the locuses.
I'm going to pay attention to them only in the sense that I think they've got a very very strong debut novel list because they have a separate first novel list.
It's also worth mentioning that the locus wards announced their finalists which essentially the votes already happened they just announced the top 10 in each category and then announced the winners later.
They split novels essentially into five categories because they have Sans Fiction Fantasy Horror, Young Adult and First Novel and I think you can only be in one category.
And their first novel list is also very strong and in fact does contain Changanol stars that is a first novel but also there's Emily Tesh there's Inklook Sister Scribe which I've heard good things about these burning stars, Shigidi and the Brass Head of Obalufon which yeah like there's loads of novels that I've heard really good things about as kind of contenders for just best science fiction or fantasy novel rather than best first novel.
Yeah we will put a link to the locus wards in the show notes.
I would also note that Adrian Tchaikovsky managed to get himself nominated only twice I think but you know he will eventually be in all categories.
Are they saying that you can't be in best novel best science fiction fantasy or horror novel until your second novel then?
I don't know whether they're saying that.
I assume you decline whichever one you don't like but I don't know I don't know for how they work.
I'm not sure how they do that I don't think they do it that way.
If you're locus writing.
Now that is interesting now I'm curious.
There's a novel in there by Monica Wollblak-Gus who is also a finalist for the Astounding Award in their first year of eligibility so that must be their first novel.
Okay so maybe you can be in more than one category.
So now I'm wondering if first novel is is best first novel that doesn't appear on the top ten lists.
Maybe.
If you're locus writing or if you understand how the locus awards work writing.
I don't know how they work you get more votes if you pay very wise.
Hang on I want to quote something from locus if I can find their thing.
But remember John the locus wards are the longest standing democratic major awards for writing in science fiction fantasy and horror because everyone can vote.
You just get more if you pay them.
Right.
Is that what the word is that is that hang on right is that what the word okay.
I'm actually quoting from locus is indiegogo they do call themselves the longest standing democratic major awards for writing.
Right which is you know factually inaccurate because it's like 20 years younger than the hugos but whatever you do you locus you do you.
Not everyone can vote in the hugos John you have to pay the money.
If we gave all welcome members like voting power of ten and then let everyone else vote as well then they will be democratic John.
There's lots of things going on for the Glasgow world call it's all getting busy I think they've got a stuff we can next weekend so if you're heading to the stuff we can when you're listening to this.
If you're heading to the stuff we can when you're listening to this then have fun.
I'm not going but there's a lot a lot of people trying to get things done in their areas before the stuff we can.
Lots of activity going on lots of different fronts if you are a program participant you are getting emails from the convention and if you want to program participant you probably can't be now because I know some people who kind of wrote in and begged as I suggested and they were told to go away.
We also think that the Hugo packet is imminent.
I mean we know the Hugo packet is imminent because we sent them all stuff.
So that's very exciting so it might even be out by the time you get this listen to this podcast but it is not out yet at the time of recording.
We are also at the point where people are working very hard on the world card so if this is you that we appreciate it very much thank you very much and make sure to look after yourself because you know.
World cards are not can be unfun in the last few weeks before the event take care.
Yeah I've got to go and pick on my program participants after this.
I'm supposed to do it by tomorrow.
Oops you picking us you picking us pick us list pick us.
Did you fill out your program participant form?
Yeah and probably I can yeah okay I mean I literally haven't done it yet I'm not going to like I'm not going to put an up to the podcast on there with three random people although that would be very funny.
What does anyone else I say anything else about World card I am very excited about World card already.
I'm going to do the whiskey tasting thing and we are going to yeah we're going to plug Joel's whiskey tasting.
So the members of the Joel's whiskey tasting group have organized a whiskey tasting at the Caledonian distillery in Glasgow I think it is.
Clideside distillery so they are they have organized a whiskey tour distillery tour and tasting for the Friday night of World con August the night and they would like some more people to come along because they organized a group deal and they don't have quite enough people yet so they would they've asked people to plug it and we said yes we'll plug it that's going to get you welcome drinks food or calipers.
Some single bolts and then later the cash bar and the opportunity by personalized bottle of whiskey and we will put a link in the show notes if that sounds like the sort of thing you would enjoy.
Mm-mm yes probably talk about the Glasgow work on every episode now until Glasgow so I'm looking forward to it it'll be good.
Picks picks.
Alison's just going to make me mad jealous so you can go ahead.
Oh I have so I don't believe a bucket list I think having a long list of things that you want to do before you die reduces your ability to enjoy the things that you just get to do by walking out of your front door.
And so I don't really have a bucket list I don't go oh I have to go and see the Taj Mahal or whatever however on Friday night I had a very quiet night and I didn't do anything this is a week last Friday now as you're listening.
I didn't really do anything very much in the evening and I definitely wasn't online and so I went to bed and I picked up my phone just before going to sleep and I saw a picture that my brother had taken in his back garden of the Northern Lights of the Aurora Borealis and I kind of sent it to John because I know that John is a professor of the
and John sent me back the picture that he'd taken of the Northern Lights from his spare room and at that point I kind of kicked Stephen and said oh look there might be a Aurora outside and he was like there are not Aurora outside we live in London don't be stupid.
So I went to Twitter which I feel quite embarrassed about but therefore it was definitely the right place to go on Friday night or X as I suppose we should call it.
And there were actually pictures from London at that point I said oh no Stephen we should get up and get in the car and drive to somewhere dark.
And we drove to the darkest place that's near here I saw the Aurora Borealis pretty clearly actually though I will say that on Monday morning I described this experience to John Cox and Professor of Aurora's and he said oh it's not good enough you really still need to go to New Zealand to go to Iceland and see proper Aurora those really fake Aurora's like it's pretty time good actually
I was there I was going I can die happy now because I don't have a bucket list because if I did seeing the Northern Lights would be on it.
And so I'm very very happy because I'm 58 years old I've wanted to see this since I was a tiny child.
I'm going to protest that this was in the context of people on that call saying that the Norwegian tourist industry would surely be destroyed by the fact we had had Aurora in the UK and I very gently pointed out that it is possible
that it is more spectacular if you go on a holiday to see it at all.
Though I do have multiple friends have said I spent X000 on an Aurora chasing holiday and the Aurora that I saw on Friday night were better.
So there is that.
My half-brother and my parents went on an Aurora chasing holiday recently and my half-brother has 3,000 pictures of the Aurora and each of them makes me incredibly jealous.
Because it was like just so spectacular.
They are not as good as the ones you get on your phone.
No you are right that they are they show up better on the phone because obviously your line exposure time means you get more of those pesky photons than your eyes can pick up.
So photographs bring it out more.
Yeah though if you if you can go somewhere darker than we managed so that you have absolutely no sources of extraneous light and if you can avoid looking at your phone for about 15 minutes.
I think you are going to see you would have been able to see a lot of very good Aurora very clearly on Friday night.
And apparently we are going to get more.
So this is the sort of thing you like getting a Aurora app on your phone and get it to tell you when there is a red alert.
Because apparently there is going to be more for the next year is that right Professor of Aurora's?
It is not right no.
Oh okay Boo.
The Aurora we got the other night was the strongest event we have since 2003.
So I would be skeptical that there will be anything that good again for a big while.
Obviously the problem with all of this is it is predicting the future which is impossible.
So you know it could be that the sun belches out some stuff tomorrow and like we might get lucky.
But certainly you are looking like this is a kind of one every decade level of event really.
I am also going to acknowledge at this point my car ownership privilege because when we bought a car we were very on the borderline of should we have a car or not at the time.
I had elderly relatives we had to be able to visit quickly and so we bought a car.
And we in fact did not use the car for that.
You know we did not have an emergency that needed ever needed to us to jump in the car until Friday at which point we had a bona fide emergency that meant we needed to jump in the car and go in see Aurora.
So feel very glad that we had a car to do that with but also know I am quite lucky.
If you did not have a car you could still go and walk to places like Holopons or Waltham's Doe Wetlands and get a reasonably good picture.
I think Vicki Hartle got some nice Aurora pictures in Waltham's Doe which is a very very loomy sort of place with a lot of bright lights.
But anyway so sorry I was so excited.
I have to talk to you about it guys.
I was so excited.
It was like so we so I got I was traveling home from London that day because I had been at a conference and like my phone started blowing up at about I don't know 10 30 ish.
I was like oh I really hope that I really hope that it's still happening when I get back and then I got home and I took a lot of exposure photographs to the north and I was sad because it showed no Aurora.
And then I expressed this to my wife and she said I yes but they are to the south and that is a sign of how much activity there was the Aurora Loval expands when there's more so activity and I could go on about this great length.
And if you're really interested I have a thesis which discusses it.
I think we're actually up for a minute or so in fact given that it is the most it's your professional expertise and it's the best show that we've had for 20 years right so I think a minute or two of of nerdy detail would be fine.
And then my link to your thesis in the show notes.
The son of the earth both have magnetic fields.
The Aurora happens because of charged particles which go along the earth's magnetic field and hit the atmosphere and they happen on closed magnetic field lines that is field lines that go from the northern hemisphere background to the southern hemisphere and then around again.
And what that means is that the more field lines on the earth that aren't closed that is to say it connect up with the sun's magnetic field, the further the Aurora gets from the magnetic pole long story short as the sun is more active it reconnects with more of the earth's field lines
and it pushes the closed field lines further and further away from the poles and that means the Aurora get further and further away from the poles.
And what that means is that typically speaking the Aurora line northward of the UK but I think on Friday night they must have been roughly above the northeast because when we were lying on our spare beds and looking up we could see basically straight up in and we could see like the lines of Aurora meeting in the sky above us,
which is called a coronal Aurora and it was very good but I have a photo of the house where you can see the Aurora but I'm facing south which is very strange and there's nothing at all to the north presumably because of how active that period was but it was amazing.
It was really cool.
Do you get to see Aurora a lot in your job or is this the first time you've seen it? This is my second time.
I will eventually let there are, it will not surprise you to learn conferences are often held in spots where Aurora might occur so I will eventually probably go to one and see it there.
I have friends who go and install instruments on an island, well there's an island called Svalbard which has a lot of instrumentation but there's also a place called Trumpster in Norway and I have colleagues who have gone there to install instrumentation
and they also send back phenomenal photographs which are very envy generating.
I will link to the XKCD comic on Aurora because I was in the bit where it says it's basically what it means if you see an Aurora by latitude and I was in the latitude where it says a bunch of open questions in solar terrestrial physics are about to be answered.
Nobody living with London Loom ever expected to see the Aurora in London but in the boroughs of London this is bad.
Yes but I'm pretty sure you will never see it at latitude six self unless you're about to die probably.
Yeah I mean probably not. One done like obviously if the poles flip maybe.
But that does fall into the open questions thing. That's going to be a bit of a problem though if the poles flip isn't it John?
I think it's odd though maybe you just multiply all the sums by minus one Liz and it will be fine I'm pretty sure.
That is untrue there's not my professional opinion that is a shit posting.
But the suns the sun switches polarity regularly I learn or I read something the other day.
Yes so the way so the earth's magnetic field points north because the earth's north pole is the south magnetic pole so the magnetic field points from the southern hemisphere to the northern hemisphere.
The suns magnetic field can be in either direction north or south and is basically 50/50 chance which one it is.
You get the activity when the suns magnetic field points south so that's a good if you've got nap that shows you the bz component you wanted to be negative for.
The thing if the earth's magnetic field rotates and basically just like there's a day where everything's mad and then it's suddenly the other way round that will really not do much.
But I think it's far more likely that you'll get a period of sort of years to decades to perhaps centuries where it very slowly goes incredibly strange and then re-orient.
So I imagine that intervening period will be lots of interesting physics.
Obviously the problem is that no one's ever seen it happen so we don't know.
Doctor Thorpe nerdy science corner.
I'm very glad I get to do this for a job. It's very good.
Yeah I mean I think your job is always cool but I think it might be a bit cooler than average this week.
[laughs]
I also don't know how often we like I don't know if you start listening to old Doctor Thorpe.
I don't know how long it is before you found out that like I'm an oral physicist and this is a bio statistician.
Bioinformatician.
Close.
We did mention that quite a lot in the episodes from 2020 to 2022 you know.
The second of those.
Yeah if you've been listening the whole time I think you know both of these things but I'm curious for new listeners how long it takes before they retell them.
Oh and like Ditto how long before you work out Liz lives in Thailand?
Because we mention it in episode one but we do recommend people not go back and listen to the whole thing from the start so I don't know.
Yeah I don't know.
You make a joke about it like every week I think.
That's true.
Is it dark where you are Liz?
No.
[laughs]
Because we haven't been recording for six hours.
My pick is basically all my reading is going on Hugo's stuff and all my TV watching is not very good.
And so I'm going to pick a book I reread actually but I haven't read it for years and years.
The book is A Man on the Moon by Andrew Chakin which I'm going to assume John has read and probably Allison as well.
I think I've read it.
No.
John?
Really?
Okay.
Books.
It's basically a pretty exhaustive history of the Apollo program.
Well it kind of focuses on the astronauts a lot so he managed to interview I think all of the surviving astronauts at the time he was writing except for Jack's Waggad I think he passed away before that.
And I really enjoy it so it's pretty broad overview so we talked to kind of all the astronauts.
For the later missions there's a lot of emphasis on kind of the lunar geophysics and geology and why they were going to different bits of the moon and what they were hoping to get there.
And talking about you know how they got the astronauts interested in geology and that kind of thing.
So I guess there are definitely books that kind of go into individual parts in more detail.
And it's definitely not kind of about the politics of how the Apollo missions came about or were ended.
But it is just kind of a really nice overview of what happened on each mission.
Lots of stories from the astronauts.
Quite a bit about kind of the personalities of the astronauts and how they're very different and how they felt that affected maybe whether they got selected for missions and so on.
So I have now read this twice and I kind of really enjoyed it.
But I mean I enjoy all books about the moon and sort of slightly depressing you know we haven't been back there for many many years.
But I would recommend it to anyone who is interested in the Apollo program.
It's basically what got turned into the From the Earth to the Moon show that was on HBO a few years ago.
Another book, another book people should read if they edited the moon is Jim Lovell's book which is called and was the basis for Apollo 13.
It has quite a lot more detail in it than Apollo 13 did. Jim Lovell's Wikipedia page is massive.
So I would say that the copy of Man on the Moon I read has an introduction from Tom Hanks about how I read it in preparation for Apollo 13.
So I think that was also you know it's quite detailed.
But I mean yeah Lost Moon is Jim Lovell's book which I haven't read.
It is I think the best one I have read.
It is very very good. It is very very funny.
It kind of has a good it has a good short overview of rocketry and then kind of the rocket program in the United States and then kind of a lot on Apollo 13 itself.
But it is there are some great there are some great little tidbits in there.
So I would highly I would highly recommend it is it is a good good book.
The one I would recommend is the Hanes manual for the Saturn 5 if you really really like rockets.
Oh that's nerdy.
I found it if I'm honest a little bit much but it is if you really like rockets.
Ho ho!
I think that's probably a bit much for me.
And it can save you quite a bit on your Saturn 5 servicing.
I will also say a man on the moon is currently 99p on ebook so.
That's probably why I bought a copy. I probably thought it was like a well give that another read.
And what I would like is kind of an equivalent book that gives a good overview of the Russian space program if anyone wants to suggest one.
There is so that is much harder for obvious reasons but I have a book called two sex.
I return Alexei Leonoff was the person who trained to be the USSR's first man on the moon.
And David Scott was on Gemini 8 with Neil Armstrong and they wrote a book called Two Sides of the Moon which is their memoirs of the US and Russian programs in a single volume and it is supposed to be very good.
I'm really at some of the bookshelf. I'm brandishing it at Liz as we speak listeners with a forward by Neil Armstrong and an introduction by Tom Hanks because Tom Hanks bloody loves the moon.
He does he loves face now. I did pick moon walking the other episode in time.
Yeah that was a Tom Hanks thing as well wasn't it.
An entire show about how Tom Hanks loves the moon.
I'm going to pick short films. So I went to the Sunderland short film festival which is a big old film festival.
We watched a lot of films so we didn't go to the whole day and it runs over like a week and we did not go to the whole thing but there was a science fiction track so we rocked up for that and we watched those and they were very good.
Well they were mostly very good. I was actually pleasantly surprised and I don't know whether this is just because it was much more focused so you could be much more selective or what.
But I felt the hit rate was much higher than the sci-fi London shorts I've seen which I was intrigued by and the names of the films we saw were soul mates beautiful things in sold finger food bisected own home Rico and the first time I never met you.
And especially soul mate finger food bisected and the first time I never met you were really really good.
There was like a wide range of things kind of touched on in these movies but a lot of a lot of stuff about feelings for one another and how those feelings can be reciprocated or not reciprocated and how those feelings can run awry.
After the last movie is found your turn to me and said some men will literally invent time travel instead of going to therapy and that was basically the moral of that film.
It was incredibly heart wrenching because he accidentally he accidentally takes his relationship with his dead wife out of time by trying to go back and relive it.
It's enormously sad and a very effective rumination on grief and appreciating what you have.
I think I'm going to have to look out for this festival because I think it's every year.
If anyone wants some short films they could actually watch the rolled out adaptations by Wes Anderson on Netflix are also very good and I enjoyed all of them.
They're not really genre.
I guess one of them might be genre.
Henry Sugar is arguably genre.
Yeah that's the one I was thinking could be.
I think I described those as really high budget jakonori.
I don't have a problem with really high budget jakonori that sounds very good.
They feel like plays. Instead of feeling like movies they feel much more like an audio book of a short story told on a theatre stage but I quite like how Anderson subverts that in a couple of years.
It's that in a couple of points by doing things that would be impossible to do in a theatre in a way that kind of catch you out.
And that I found very good.
And also the cast is amazing.
It's Rupert Friend, Benedict Cumberbatch, Richard I.O.R.D, Dev Patel and Ben Kingsley.
Ah it's just that's a good collection of actors.
Cool men.
Oh yeah I mean Rold Dahl.
As perz.
Do you remember the Rold Dahl books about women?
I remember some of the short stories about women.
Matilda.
The one about the leg of lamb has stuck with me all these years.
Yeah I think there's no women in Henry Sugar. I've also watched the ratcatcher which I think similely, manly.
Haven't watched the other two.
Yes.
When deciding what works you're going to choose to adapt in 2024.
You can go own I will adapt an author who is notable for hardly writing any women in and then I will not choose to do any of the stories that do involve women.
I mean I recommended like a man on the moon where he talked to maybe two ladies and 375,000 men.
So I mean I think what I'm saying is I like the fact that modern art tends to be, tends to be, to work hard to overcome this, this tendency of the pastor.
And my biggest criticism, my biggest criticism of Fantastic Mr Fox is that they have Mrs Fox in it.
The character is just so insubstantial and it's a real waste of metal street.
Because Anderson is clearly fascinated with dull and you can see why, especially in all of the ones he's adapted, they're dull playing with story structure in exactly the same way that Anderson likes playing with story structure.
I have not read all of Wild Dahl's short stories and I don't know whether the ones which you could choose to adapt that had women in are the ones that play with story structure in a way I suspect Anderson finds interesting.
But equally like presumably there are other authors in the world who did this and Anderson could have chosen to adapt those instead.
But basically like you know Wes Anderson's side project he really wanted to make and Netflix gave him some cash to have a go at it and then you know his other films are much more even I would say.
I'm gonna have to take a month of Netflix aren't I?
Maybe.
That was the old podcast and it's goodbye for me.
It's goodbye for me.
I would be up for a thousand person worldcon if I could pick a thousand people.
That's a gatekeeping and I'm gonna have a completely different thousand person worldcon at the same time probably.
Oh no I bet we have people in common.
I think we do we might have to have a Venn diagram.
The only one you both invite is me.
That was my immediate thought.
I mean I hope I mean maybe not though so.
I'm Mark Plummer.
Yeah no there's definitely I mean I can there's definitely 20 or 30 aren't there?
All the listeners of this podcast.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod in Computech.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beat.
Keep.