The podcast of science fiction, science fiction, fandom and cake etymology.
I am glad that we said we'd speak a bit less about cake this episode. That's going well so far.
Hello everyone and welcome to the 35th episode of Octa Thorpe which is coming to you on the 8th
of July 2021. I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott. And I'm Liz Batty.
And we are recording early this week because it's coming home. It's coming home listeners.
It's coming home and by it I of course mean Liz. Yes, the reason we are recording early is because
it's coming home. Fingers crossed, you know, don't want to jump the gun. But should I test
negative for coronavirus on Saturday on Sunday I will get on a plane and come to the UK.
And how long are you going to be in the UK? I don't know. I haven't put the return flight yet.
Probably mid-August. That's crazy. I didn't realise you'd not put the return flight yet. That is a level
of free-wheeling spontaneity I have never achieved in my life. So I'm slightly in awe.
Yeah, I don't think I've ever managed to not book one leg of the transportation.
I mean, you know, obviously there could be like a day or two between all the bookings getting
sorted because it's such a pain but no more than that. I don't feel comfortable about holidays
until I know how I'm getting through place to place for the whole time.
And to be fair, often if you don't have a passport for the country you're going to,
the people at the border don't feel good about your holiday if you don't have the return
leg book time. Yes, this is only possible. This is only possible because the UK are basically
obliged to let me in and they're not allowed to tell me a date I have to leave again,
which is not true of any other country in the world. Take that, pretty. It's coming home and
there's nothing you can do about it. Please, please don't do anything about it if you can.
Don't. Is it too late to give me COVID? So I test positive? It probably isn't. So yeah,
don't do anything, listeners. There are boring technical reasons why I've only booked one way,
which we do not need to expand on in the podcast. We have some letters of comments.
So Chris Garcia sends a lock which contains 100% cheese and cake related content.
And he's right. A bit like our convention, really. A bit like last week's podcast, really.
Yes, yes indeed. Yes, I think we should apologise to anyone whose first episode of Octa thought
was last week and alike. What are these people on because they have just whitted about
cheese and parties for an entire hour? And we would like to apologise to anyone who is coming
to this episode as their second episode and has the opinion that it is not nearly enough about
cheese and cake. Both opinions are entirely valid. Yeah, now I read Chris Garcia's
comment which said 100% cheese and cake related. And it said Trevat shows us the best of all cakes
trailing only red velvet and carrot cake. And the thing that struck me about this is that I like
cake very much except for red velvet cake and carrot cake. So I'm worried now.
Oh, I forgot that you don't like carrot cake. I feel like I have a spectrum of cake and I really
don't like those cake. I mean, I much prefer my perfect cake is maybe a brownie or a lemon drizzle
cake. I'm kind of into the solid Scottish cakes with not too much frippery type cake.
I'm about to get us some letters of comment. So just regard the mastery with which I do this.
But I think you'll find brownies are not cakes. So, you know, well, that's a load of bollocks for
a start off. You can't disagree with me too much on the podcast, Alison, because then people won't
write in. What makes you think the brownies are not cakes, John? If they were cakes, they would be
called brownie cakes or, you know, chocolate cakes or something ending in cake. Because it is my
observation that things that are cake have the word cake in them. Okay, so no, right. No, you know,
as this hill, there are many hills I'll die on. And this is indeed one of them. I'm like,
I'm like the Rome of podcast hosts. Jesus, you do understand. So you'll probably say that a pie is
a pie if it had pie in the name, rather than or at a tart if it has tart in the name, rather than
pies being pies and tarts being fundamentally determined by the amount of pastry coverage.
I will say bloody love me some carrot cake cream cheese topping. Mm-hmm. No, no, no, no.
And I don't put beetroot in brownies either before you ask. I think Alison, Alison, I think
is on record as being anti-vegetables in cake. Exactly. That is, if I had to nail you to a personal
philosophy, that would be it. What I'm going to say is that I have a long history and fandom already
of having discussions about the classification of baked goods. And I'm going to shy away from
starting any completely new ones. But I will say, what about, say, uh, Madalins? They're cakes,
right? But they're not called a Madeline cake. But that's because they're French, they're gato.
She's called that an exception. She's called you that. What about banana bread?
Yeah, banana breads are cake. There we go. And in fact, all of those breads like Dayton
Walnut loaf, they're all cakes along with brownies. But banana bread isn't a cake, it's one of your
five a day. Different. That's not true. Okay, that is true, but totally if you eat like half the loaf,
at which point you have other problems, it's not five a day related. Swiss roll. Far. Swiss roll.
That's a very complicated sandwich. Or alternatively, it's a cake. All right, all right. Right, onwards,
onwards. Spike has sent us an email with a poem in it from a poem a day service she subscribes to.
And I have found the poem on the internet. So I will put a link in the show notes. And it is entitled
Commerce by Miller Oberman. So it is very related to our recent convention. Thank you very much to
Spike. Faram Mendelsohn tweeted to show a picture of Freddie, which is far as cat listening to the
podcast with Farra at the live recording at punctuation two. So if you like pictures of people's cats,
why will put the link to that tweet in the show notes? And Peter Sullivan emailed during the live
recording as well, I think, or perhaps the day after saying that there is a US diplomacy games
convention called the Boston massacre, which is going online this year and is going to have rounds
at eight AM, four PM and midnight UTC. And if you play in all three, only your best two scores count.
So that is another way of doing international things, which is basically force everyone to stay up
for 24 hours. And then no one can sleep. And that just seems like a wizard scheme. So yes.
Nesumdorma. Wait. Nesumdorma. Bless you. And then hello Brian tweeted as to say also why the bleeps.
What is this the **** bbc? It is not the bbc, although you know, if the culture minister wants
to give us any money because we're a public benefit, we're always in. I also do a mean line in PPE,
but I understand that gravy train has come to an end lately. Don't worry, there'll be more gravy
trains, but you're not a mate of anyone relevant. So not for you.
Why? Some of my friends are very relevant. I'll have you know. And finally we had another email
from Fran Dowd, who wrote us a lot about PIMs. She is researching the history and perception of the
PIMs brand and recipes and her conviction that you should add more gin appears to be a modernish
blip that came and went. I would argue it hasn't gone Fran as long as you and I sustain it. I always
add gin to my PIMs because well it's just better that way. I highly recommend anyone try it. And she
also says that she's going to be experimenting with making her own PIMs, but she doesn't mention
anything about Hooker's nor Blackjack. We had one final comment from Graham Slite who said that he
was awaiting eagerly the tell me what to think about Discon and the Hugo's Octa Thorpe. And that
is what we call listeners a segue. Now I'm a member of staff for Discon 3.
I am a member of staff for Discon 3 and Discon 3 haven't told me anything about what I should or
should not say about this because Discon 3 do not have a clear promotional voice that they insist
all of their staff adhere to. On the other hand Glasgow in 2024 set out some very clear rules.
Oh wait you've got some clear promotion so wait Glasgow have some clear promoter rules
about what you were allowed to say about Discon. Yeah yeah yeah. Interesting I mean it made sense
makes a lot of sense. Yeah they basically said do try not to spout off the mouth about this.
I mean I'm slightly paraphrasing the comments. Did they email it just to you personally?
So Meg if you're listening I'm very sorry I do not speak officially for Glasgow in 2024 which I
think everyone knows at this point. Yes. Liz would you like to explain about Discon and the Hugo?
Okay I'm going to suggest to anyone who wants to know further details of what I'm about to
summarise. Read Jason Sanford's genre grapevine primer which he wrote on the 25th of June and
there's also a follow-up post. But essentially the Hugo administrators which is Discon's second
set of Hugo administrators resigned on mass. A little later there was much discussion on the
internet of the fact that Worldcon had said that they would limit finalists where there were more
than four finalists for a single a single entity to only being allowed for four people and a guest
in the pre-Hugo reception in the reserved area for the ceremony. They have now changed their mind
again and will now allow groups nominees to send as many people as they would like.
And of course this all takes place on a backdrop of you know last year's Hugo ceremony being very
long and mangling lots of people's names and a kind of history of Worldcon's not doing very well
by large groups of finalists or pronouncing their names. So I recommend that you read those two
posts and all the links that spin off for them if you want to know more. As an even more follow-up to
this the chair of Discon 3 Bill Lohan resigned this week. This was obviously the second Discon 3
chair to resign after his co-chair already resigned over a previous Hugo finalists discussion.
So yeah it doesn't seem to be going super great for Discon and the Hugo specifically
but there have been some signs of movement and they have a new head of the Wispers division.
Linda Dennoroff and there's been some more communication now from Gaddy everyone who is the
head of events and appears to have taken charge of getting some communication going with the Hugo
award finalists in order to try and put things straight. So I'm actually one of the very few
members of the Hugo team that did not resign because my work does not affect the related area
and because we've almost done we've still got a few little bits and pieces to tidy up but we're
basically finished so we're carrying on. Wispers division now has a new division head which is
Linda Dennoroff so thanks very much Linda for taking on a poisoned - it's like it's a
poisoned chalice and you know that the previous two people who picked it up have kind of keeled
over a bit later go "Ahh I know it really was poisoned"
But no I'm sure it'll be fine now. And our best wishes with Nicholas White's family.
Nicholas is fine but Nicholas and his team resigned and then the chair resigned so Bill Lauren has
resigned. So there's a process by which Discon will appoint a new chair. I think Bill sent a
note round thanking everyone for their work and giving some sort of final thoughts and express
wishes for what might happen now that he's no longer chair and that included a possible name
for a chair which seemed pretty sensible name to me but I think it is in the hands of
whoa whoa whoa whoa whoa whoa whoa whoa whoa whoa whoa whoa you could do with the sound of that
as well done i think i've got one uh please. i have no idea what's going on right now
i think it's the hah. oh you've been sent from bone okay you think central bone is the official
the name of the um parent organization is boston washington association for willcon
administration oh whoa whoa whoa whoa whoa oh i see okay so it is what what what what it kind of
works quite well i mean it's a good acronym turn out ten to have a came up with it i like a lot
mainly because it is a little bit silly in a way that i enjoy whoa whoa whoa but i don't really
know anymore than than has been publicly stated which is that there was a big route and now they
have reversed their previous position so um i am on uh i am i am a hugo finalist
and uh so i've been in a couple of days or i've witnessed a couple of discussions i don't want
to say i've been in them because i don't really feel like i've contributed to any meaningful way
but i've witnessed a few discussions around this from the finalist's perspective and i know that
there have been discussions between the finalists and the events division at discon which have led to
some of these things being um kind of rolled back slightly i think a lot of this is coming from the
fact that the finalists are after the big buster when collet fozard resigned um there was quite a
lot worry around kind of the relationship between discon three and the hugo finalists and that led
i think two strange horizons putting a um 80 person um team in to their um category uh in the awards
and so i think and you know that they did that in order to try and make a point and to make that
point forcefully but i think the problem with that is is it did make that point forcefully and i've
seen a number of people not just on the disc on three side of this saying well that was not a
particularly diplomatic thing to do and i think part of the problem here is that dc are worried
that there are finalists acting in bad faith with regards to naming lots of names and the finalists
are worried that discon three is acting in bad faith because they want to strike back against
finalists having lots of names and i am worried that but basically at the moment both parties in this
discussion are coming out this from the perspective that the other party is acting in bad faith and i
think that is one of the reasons we're seeing this blow up very quickly when there are problems
um and to be clear i don't think that i don't think the discussion we've had has been a bad thing
but i do wonder whether that has not helped deescalate as it were i think that this assumption that
people are trying to be difficult or are acting in bad faith or that the reason where that lines
have to be held is because otherwise everything will come crashing down in a year or two is
i think because nobody's had a chance to get together in a room this is everybody is very
touchy people are touchier than you'd expect them to be normally i did talk about this a bit
in michael's bar talk but um i think it's more generally true that you're seeing
situations that would have been resolved by people hanging out and having a chat just not
getting resolved and just getting worse and worse over the last 18 months and so probably got a
little bit more to get worse yet because i don't think necessarily the oh yes we will give free
passes free day passes and to everyone who's listed on a hugo ballot um and we will list everybody
who's involved in the production of a finalist work on the hugo relative they wish is a is a
permanently sustainable option so eventually that is going to cause problems down the line probably
but it might not might see because i think there's probably quite a lot of other things going
on the hugos that involve large teams where the large teams are kind of looking at this and going
oh maybe we should expose the size of our team a bit as well just want to ask when you say
because people haven't got together in a room for you who specifically do you mean
like the the discount hugo team or people in general or i think at the moment because of the
pandemic because we are all uh at the tail end of 18 months of extreme stress and haven't had much
into personal contact we are all doing badly expressing ourselves to everyone else and so i
i think um and i think that i've been seeing that work with people being more irritable with each
other than usual as well um so i i don't think it's just fandom or like discolony is like humanity
as a species well i think we've underestimated the extent to which a business gets done in side
conversations in coffee shops in parties at oh i heard you the you know somebody's talking about
strange horizons putting 87 people on the ballot can i introduce you to so-and-so who's a member of
strange horizons editorial collective and then 10 minutes later they're fast friends under at the
bar you know that sort of thing doesn't happen doesn't happen very much on zoom so i think to
push back against that a bit one of the things that have come up in the discussion is strange horizons
are saying you know they have a very large number of people on the finalists listed as finalists
but they never expected more than a handful to come to the convention because many of them are not
regular congoers partly because they're an extremely geographically dispersed team so they're not people
who are going to be in those conversations anyway um so that may not be like it just feels like we're
saying explanation is oh well they were not sort of there having these discussions but i guess the
chances that people would be introduced these people are low if these people are not feeling like
they can make it to our conventions anyway yeah i think some of those people who were
speaking for them would have been there as well yes and i mean i think another part of the problem
is i think people have been speaking sort of four strange horizons or assuming things on behalf
of strange horizons or suspecting that really any of the issue with the number of fuga finalists
was caused directly by strange horizons when it doesn't appear to be because they seem to be quite
happy with only having four people at the actual ceremony because that's about the number they
expect to attend but i would say sorry i think there's actually sort of three sides to it almost
which is there's a people saying you know if it seems weird to me to list as many people and you
know you can't expect to get more than you know four into ceremony then there's the people saying
well we want everyone to be listed we know not everyone will be able to attend or be actually present
as a finalist but we do definitely want them all to be listed but then you also have a third group
who seems to be saying very much that if you are a hugo finalist you need to be treated as a hugo
finalist and that has to encompass everyone which means in a way you kind of have to give all of
those 87 people the same opportunity to be there and be on the stage and you know what if they what
if more of them did manage to attend then you thought might attend then you necessarily need to treat
them in in that way and that i think is not something that's trying to try in terms of asking one
to say it's coming from other groups who feel very strongly that if everyone is a hugo finalist they
have to be treated in in the same way as a hugo finalist so i think almost somewhere at the intersection
of those three is where we're getting the issues coming up hmm there's definitely also a thread of
and and furthermore the world con doesn't make enough of hugo finalists that the experience of
being a hugo finalist is fundamentally bad and um i've been a hugo finalist quite a lot times and
i didn't find it so but it also it's fair to say it really only consisted of here's an envelope with
a ribbon and a pin in it so we'll see you on saturday so i think recently we have seen more
and more discussion of using hugo finalists more and more in the world con and there's been discussions
about you know if your program doesn't reflect enough of the finalists um then is that okay i do
wonder whether part of that is a gradual shift or or shift in perception um away from conventions as
a place where fans talk about their experiences two conventions as a place where you know prose
talk and fans listen and that's something we've touched on on octa thought before and i don't think
there's a right answer but i definitely think there are multiple scores of thought and i think
where you stand on some of this stuff will be very much a function of where you stand on that
question um from my perspective i find value in both i like listening to people who are very good
at doing things talk about those things that's very interesting but i also like listening to fans
talking about how they relate to the genre i find that interesting and i i do wonder whether
there has been no room for nuance or for kind of acceptance that there might be um perspectives
here that are very well intentioned perspectives which are logistically very difficult to accommodate
i think this is a bit of a red herring argument in some ways in that i think there are very few
i think there are very few cases of a hugo finalist who is attending world con that you would not want
to use on program somewhere whether it be a fan attendee or a pro attendee um and i think there's
very there's very rarely sufficient numbers that there are going to overwhelm you know going to
constitute such a huge amount of program participation that it pushes out other people is my feeling
now again if you did have a an entity which nominated its entire staff and there were significant
numbers of them and they were going to attend then that might be a problem but at the moment i don't
think it is a problem because they basically don't you're going to win these don't attend
insufficient numbers to be really overwhelming the program and many of them will make fairly
last minute decisions and they're usually very accommodating if you say okay we'll try and
start you in for something but we can't promise anything uh at this point so at the moment it
doesn't seem like that is a a really big logistical problem my experience from world con is that
fan programming even extremely good fan programming that's really well thought through
does not draw the audiences of even minor writers um so you will get a bigger audience for
four writers who are as dull as toast talking when you will for incredibly interesting funny
fans and um that's i think just the way it is in the demographic we've got now um might less be true
might be less true in the us um than it is in european world cons my primary experience of
this in european world cons and when we kind of say oh we're not sure we could put everyone who
asked on the program i think we probably can almost everyone apart from the people who say oh i can
only do things you know between the hours of 12 and 2 on thursday and saturday and that's always
going to be difficult um i was on a program i didn't come to zero and nobody should go back on and
check with a kind of random fan from the midwest who really didn't have anything interesting to say
on the topic and i think not just to be somebody who was you know was not like a hugo finalist and
i kind of take that as my standard for if a world con has room for people like that on the program
or people like me it's definitely got room for the hugo finalists all of them every single one as
long as they get their programming form in yeah pretty early yeah i think i think that's probably
true i mean i know but i do wonder whether so for example one of the big controversies about
conzeland and is that the program didn't have enough content from the finalists and mary robinette
coel was parachuted in with like two weeks to go this was san hosey it wasn't it what was it san
hosey i think it's san hosey she was but conzeland also had the same i mean conzeland did have some
of the same issues so i think so i think just to be precise i think which is that i think conzeland
specifically had a problem with the hugo finalists i'm pulled in some help but it was san hosey which
had a problem in general i think i'm pulled in mary robinette coel to help successive world con
programming teams have struggled to make the diversity of the program reflect the diversity
of the genre and participants and in particular hugo finalists and there's more that we can do here
and some will cons are better than others yeah i think it's definitely fair to say that we are saying
that you know we we don't think it is usually a problem to accommodate hugo finalists on
welcome programs there have definitely been examples where it has not happened in the way you would
want it to happen and of course from the outside the difference between like if it is actually
difficult to accommodate someone and you haven't really made an effort to do it look pretty similar
so there's two things here so one is that normally when i've been involved with program what happens
is at some point you go to the hugo team and say can you tell me like who's attending and then we
can cross check them on our list of program and if they are attending and we don't have the
damn program you know can you send them an email asking them to get in touch with us
but the other thing is there is a kind of distinction here in that sometimes for pros it's very easy
to add say a reading or a signing or a cafe clatch at the very last minute that gives them a way to
meet their fans the way to participate in the program that can be quite difficult for like
fan category no one is because usually you want to put them on a panel or you want to say give
them an item or you know about you know a live recording of their fan cast or something like that
and there was a much more difficult to sort of wedge in at the last minute it's much easier to
say okay i've got a spare reading slot here are four slots can you do any of them fine we've got you in
but i think the other thing here is obviously that you know world cons need to be doing their part
to make sure that their programs do reflect the diversity of the genre and if that is through
making sure that you go finalists you you might not have usually put on program get on program
then that is a very good way of doing that but also kind of from the the general membership like
i think you know we went through this and i think to a large extent have now been through this with
with with making sure that panels reflect gender diversity and it's about time we start working on
the other aspects that we can work on and you know i appreciate that's hard i think hopefully we start
to see younger people in the community step up to that kind of role in order to wield their ability
to re-examine some of the assumptions in this field in order to bring those more diverse programs and
i'm hoping that that will happen and that's one of the things i was impressed by when when this was
deputy dh in london three was that the pool of people working on that program i think was a much
more diverse pool of people than you could have brought on and that's you know one of the things
that you can do is make sure that you've got a diverse group of areaheads who are presumably
going to be better identifying diverse people to speak and that's something i think Glasgow is
trying to do i mean obviously gazco don't have their programming team together yet but they're
clearly trying to bring people into their organization who are not necessarily the usual
suspects and i think that that can only work to help world cons become more diverse and more
reflective of the diversity of the genre which i think is great um so uh yeah hurrah for that
there may also be a need for world cons to think about what a world con program looks like
from the from the ground up because i think it's easier for a new convention to come in and say
well we want we want to have a diverse program and we're going to do it by getting getting these
voices in from all of these different places if if world cons start from the point of view of
we know what a world con program basically looks like and we can obviously change it up a bit each
year it's much harder to get to the end point of a of a modern program i think but they do get to
try again every year it's true just one last question before we move on to other topics um
do we think that this is something that's easier or harder for world con as an organization that
doesn't have that or doesn't have as much institutional memory because it feels like it should be easier
but the fact that both san jose and conziland had difficulties with this might put the light of
that assumption will cons are not as different as you think they are particularly us ones as yes
i think the question of world con institution memory could probably take us long as just
seeing how we would do a world con program from the ground up oh i just want to say one other one
last thing about disc on three which is they cannot get a break they are having an incredibly
hard time i do feel very sorry for them yeah bless them i mean a lot of it or maybe not a lot of it
but there's quite a lot of it there's own goals but it doesn't make it less painful to watch
yeah we didn't even talk at all i mean i feel like we may have underdone it by not talking
all about how rubbish their communication was did we talk about how rubbish their communication
was the hugo finalist maybe we're out of time we probably did a bit oh yeah no we probably should
talk about that disc on three's communication two finalists was um somewhat deficient um i think a
lot of finalists only found out that there was this limit when it was announced uh and although i think
disc on three talked about a consultation and none of the finalists felt that they had been
consulted in advance of the announcement being made and i think some genuine consultation
would have helped now i'm going to say something which might be slightly um off topic um but i do
wonder to what extent this is because the job of organizing the hugo ceremony falls under a
different division to the job of organizing the hugos and i have always wondered why the hugo
ceremony is under events and the hugos are under wasphus that i i think the hugos are a big enough
temple of a world con but they probably deserve their own division um and that would be something
i wonder whether that would make the communications a little bit more joined up and maybe help avoid
this in future but maybe i'm maybe i'm incorrect there i don't know um but does anyone have any
thoughts on on how disc on three communicated with the finalists um and how that went well i mean i
don't get the finest communications but uh it seems like you know judging by their action many of them
did not feel that they were you know being honored as a hugo finalist but you know seems like treated
as like something of an inconvenience because there's too many of them to fit in the room
um which is not a good look um and as for communications i can see the argument for a hugo
division but i there's also a lot of places where divisions in wollcons have to interact and maybe
don't do a great job of doing it um and lots of areas you can improve that i think we shouldn't
merge events at wisface well we know we could have merged events in wisface it just be really weird
fundamentally events is about how you put a big thing on a stage and every day of the convention
yeah and there's there's too much similar i think there's too much between like the few
girls in masquerade to split them into any distinct chunks without then basically doing the same thing
twice yeah divisions have to work divisions have to work together effectively and boards have to
work together effectively and and clearly discom did have some issues may still have some issues on
that front um i didn't see i was obviously not a finalist this year and i did see some
some stuff coming that i was copied into that i had to say i didn't think that was perfect so yeah so
if you've got the two divisions and they don't really get the chance to um sit down and work through
the issues properly and then get it to if it needs to go to the chair or to the board for a decision
get that happening at early enough stage that's when the sorts of problems that arise here in
retrospect at the point where collet resigned and they issued a note saying we will work individual
we were finalists on things around the ceremony and attending the convention and so on that at that
point they should immediately install to the process of making that happen and that clearly
didn't quite happen in the way that they'd planned probably because they were busy fighting other
fires around the hotel going bankrupt you know and and that sort of thing you can see how that
would cause the problems with the hugos to kind of get pushed down the road until the point where
they then blew up and i don't think discom's problems are entirely confined to the hugos i think
what we're seeing is we had a convention that had a problem overall with its divisions pulling
together and the hugos was it has been the touch paper for it um if you had a hugos division you've
put the rest of wasphus into it because the rest of wasphus is relatively tiny so it would just be
the wasphus division plus half of events but i do wonder whether if this had been under nicholas
this would not have happened and so if it was up to me i would say the hugo administrator
administrates all of the things to do with the hugos especially at times when they have come in to
fix problems with your communications about the hugos but maybe so i take your point i just wonder
whether the hugos are high profile enough that it might be wise not to introduce potential points
of miscommunication within your own organization around them um but i don't know at some point you
have to have a consistent view of what the convention believes and what its policies on things are
that there's a there was a problem with the division heads and the board actually communicating
any useful way and i don't know where that problem rests obviously what i said about having a hugo
division rather than different divisions each of which in direct with the hugos does presuppose
that the problems that discom three had came from disparities and miscommunications between
divisions and not from the chair the chair has resigned and they are currently looking to put
a new chair in this is the second well so collet fosard resigned and she was the co-chair of
discom three and now boulogon has resigned and and he was the the remaining co-chair who had become
there for the chair of discom three um and so like i suppose the other argument is if these
decisions were taken at the very highest point restructuring the divisions wouldn't have helped
and then that explains why um boul has has resigned because this is presumably a fundamental
difference of opinion between um the hugo team and the chair rather than the hugo team and other parts
of the discom structure and there's no way for us to know um but the fact that the chair has resigned
might be suggestive or why not in that regard i think the fact that the chair has resigned and
the policy has been reversed might be yes uh we stress dear listeners that this is speculation
if your head of hugos goes to the chair and to the board and said well you can hold this line as
long as you want but it's not sustainable and when it gets out into the public it's all going to fall
apart the director of communication should be there saying either no my view is it's manageable and
this is the line that we will take on it and this is how we will hold it or they say no i'm with the
i'm with the head of the hugo division here or the withers with division here and it's not sustainable
now i would say that that's why you have you know why head of communications is a board level role
on the worldcon because you are going to have um things that come up that are going to require
the entire board to speak coherently with one voice on a line that the members of the convention
will tolerate and i don't think they'd i don't think they'd be doing that i think don't think
discana's done that very well at all well they don't have one they don't have a communication
director and that gets back to why i've asked easter con to merge basically merge
parations and communications because i agree with you there needs to be a consistent line of
communication but i don't think any fanish convention actually does that because they don't
have communication they have outreach and i would argue the outreach division is not i mean i think
probably it is doing a lot of the communications the role of a communications division but like
it's not geared towards that it's geared towards advertising effectively and so i and then you've
got publications which are the other half of the voice of the convention and you probably need to
merge those two into a communications division that does what you just said because i completely
agree someone needs to be on the board doing that generally speaking it's the chair so if you look
at dublin for example the voice of dublin was james bakins voice i think we are so far off topic
this is actually a different discussion especially there was a job supposed about the
vote like what is the voice of a convention and conventions with individual voices that might
be interesting for a future podcast do you want to kind of draw this to a general conclusion oh a
general conclusion of discana yeah i've got no idea how to do that no i'm either yeah it's got virtual
memberships and they're seventy five dollars which is an absolute steal because you'll be paying
fifty dollars for the hugo packet anyway which is an absolute steal so an extra twenty five dollars
for hanging out with fans online for five days in the week before christmas when you won't be
busy at all does seem like i mean twenty five dollars is nothing it was seventeen pounds i mean
if i go into town and go for curry and have some beers it's going to cost me more than seventeen
pounds i mean i i feel like this is this is now so cheap as to be a no-brainer everyone should
join discol three and have a big faddish party and they will definitely be excellent social
spaces otherwise i'll kill somebody no um sorry on the topic of virtually attending world cons there
is a post on dreamwith from and k grey who says that she is looking for people or suggestions uh
people to join the working group to address the question of remote attendance and or
participation in the wussford's business meeting and suggestions for the same so if anyone is
interested in being on that working group or suggesting things for that working group uh then
please do uh get in touch we've put a link to that post in the show notes uh but i'm sure if you
can't work out again in touch with an if you don't want to comment on her dreamwith post then we
can put you in touch as well and was the taf administrator when i won taf and she is a good egg
and it's good to know that they're working on it she is but why would you ask people to do that
in a dream-ruth post rather than say on joff or file 770 or something like that see also problems
with communications uh at world cons no but i mean i i had not seen this and as someone with i think
quite defined views on this uh i'm glad that liz spotted it um liz how did you find it i got it off
twitter last weekend we went to conspire where allison was the guest of honor it was one of the
guest of honor along with john clute and tardotomson at conspire which was the one day um sites
which i can mention for the bsfa and the science fiction foundation and i did a talk and we're
going to put a link to the talk in the show notes which is ideal for anyone who quite likes octa
thought but would like it a lot more if it didn't have john and liz on it yes and for those who have
not been listening to octa dot vlog conspire was the combined bsfa and science fiction foundation
agms and had panels alongside and allison ran an afterparty because i texted her and said are you
running an afterparty and she did and it was great and we all got a bit too drunk had it was very
interesting because i put put it on not only the places where i would invite friends to my parties
but i also put it on the bsfa discord and said anyone who fancies an afterparty after conspire
come along so we had a mix of the normal sort of luscious and people who might otherwise have
thought they were getting serious science fiction talk who would seem to be quite surprised to be
exposed to graham chana kennick farrey saying get off my lawn like a good surprised or a bad
surprised and allison's talk was on the topic of her year in virtual fandom and um was i think
well received my friends liked it that is true i don't know if anyone who wasn't my friend liked
it it's now available on the internet so you can laugh at me oh nice well put a link in the show notes
anything else to say on conspire i spent the first half of it panicking about my talk so i hope it was
good and then i listened to tardis talk which was immediately after a while and he was interviewed
by caroline mercy and that was pretty interesting that's probably also available online um we will
put a link to the best bsfa discord in the show notes uh where you can go if you'd like to see
what people said about conspire while they were there uh and you know chat to the sort of people
who attended that was the octa thought podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me
and it's goodbye from me
yeah the day uh i think the day before yesterday as we record possibly yesterday uh it was announced
that there is going to be a second season of good omens gosh wow oh boy oh boy oh boy i would have
been mildly excited about this i think maybe you know plight intrigue to a general feeling of vague
positivity if it were not for the fact that they have announced that john finamore will be a writer
on the project my excitement went from vague to specific and intense so i am super excited about
this because john finamore is a writer of some repute he has made many radio programs which i love
and worked on television programs which i also love and i am hugely excited to see him uh being on
a science fiction television project uh it's going to be very good or a fantasy television project i
suppose uh delete is applicable depending on your views on genre i feel like having Neil Gaiman
partner with a co-writing partner who is much funnier than he is can only be to the benefit
of the project because that's obviously how the good omens original good omens worked because
gaiman has great strengths as a writer but he's not really a humorist um go on i'll just stand
here while i are in tahr audience right so it tells me i was going to say direct letters of comment
to octa thought cast at gmail.com come on i don't think that i just don't think that's too i mean he's
he's kind of whimsical and has a sense of of the absurd and the the liminal spaces between
um reality and fantasy and all of that stuff but i don't think he's funny whereas pratchett is one
of the funniest writers ever to live and as john says john finamore's pretty bloody funny that's
kind of good and and i think the best bits of the previous good omens were the bits that came from
the original and they were not the bits that that gaiman kind of padded in later because those bits
were less funny it's very strange to me because i remember getting good omens out of the library
when i was maybe oh i don't know 12 and i read it and then i closed the book and i went back to
beginning and i read it again and i've said that on the podcast already but i basically loved it
and so it's very strange to me to find that they're they're saying they're making even more of a good
omens tv show and i'm not immediately jumping up and down with joy i very much enjoyed the first
series of good omens but i did think it was a bit too slavishly devoted to the book in that it took
jokes that work on the page but maybe not on tv and then forced them onto tv like a lot of narration
a lot of narration and i think there's also a few bits of the book that maybe haven't age well or
don't work um so well on maybe don't work so well it's on tv because you know all the
perspectives but all the bits with um chadwell and mr. stracy like were strangely not funny
anyway i'm sure they used to be in the book and i don't know whether that's yeah because i have
changed all the book because that the tv doesn't work as well as a book that was a bit rambly um
so good omens too i am tentatively hopeful because there isn't a book there's just discussions that
no gay men terry pratchett had about a sequel that they never wrote so there isn't sort of a
uh a book that they will follow very very slavishly and maybe insist on keeping all the funny lines
in from it because they'll have to write the funny lines afresh and i think this could be good
because it might mean you get something better suited to tv it sounds like they got john finamore
who the small amounts john finamore i've listened to were very good and everyone tells me i should
go and listen to more john finamore so maybe i will go and spend three hours on a plane listening to
john finamore souvenir program um so i'm tentatively hopeful oh there is one thing i would say Liz
which is how much do you enjoy laughing until you cry in front of strangers on a plane oh that might
be a problem because i can't take no ask off to blow my nose so maybe i'll have to wait until i'm in
quarantine so you see i'm sort of tentatively optimistic but i'm not like jumping up and down
and being very excited yet but i did think david tenant and michael sean were very very good
sorry i i will echo everything you just said um in the same position that good omens was one of
my very favorite books is i discovered it in the school library and and yeah like you reread it
multiple times um and loved it and also i i enjoyed the first season of the tv show um but i think i
was i am in the same boat as you that when i heard that season two was happening which i actually
heard of punctuation it did not film me with joy i was like oh cool i probably watched that and it
is very much the news that that finamore has attached that has taken me up um but i will say i do find
your game and funny i i find um especially um oh god what's it called the one in london never where
especially never where i i remember finding very funny when i read um so i don't know i mean he's
nowhere near as funny as pranjai i think that is it would be ludicrous for me to try and hug you
otherwise um even if it meant we got letters uh but um but yeah i think i probably find it more
funny than us and it sounds like i like game and well enough i just don't think that his humor is
the primary thing that's good about his work um i am enough older than either of you that
i was an actual adult at the point where good ermans came out i i saw you i saw you reacting very
sadly when me and liz were saying that and i was like sorry alla said that was an accident
and i i enjoyed it i enjoyed it very much i thought it was a very good novel i
but it didn't have the same formative influence on me that it did for people who read it as a
as a young teen i'm fairly sure it was my introduction to both game and and pratchet
i might be wrong about that but i think it it's solved very well
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud at ncompetech.com
used under a creative commons attribution 3.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep