I mean your living room is right here with you.
We've had a question in the chat.
Lily in Edwards asks,
"Why are you running the hospital radio in an open prison?"
(laughing)
- I am assuming that this is a reference to my
blue snowball and clamp and pop filter set up.
- Well and also the fact that
she thought that your background made it look like
you were in an open prison.
So she thought, she thought you were recording
from the sick bay of a prison.
- I am recording from, this is balcony.
That's, this is balcony with, as we discovered earlier,
pigeon proof netting.
- Yeah, it's to keep things out, not to keep people in.
- It does keep Liz in though.
Liz have you ever jumped off your balcony?
- No, because I live on the seventh floor John.
(laughing)
Yeah, so I'm like, I am not jumping off this balcony
while in her lovely flat with this gorgeous view
of the Thai skyline behind me.
(dramatic music)
- Hello everyone and welcome to the very 11th episode
of the Octa Thorpe podcast, a podcast about science fiction
and science fiction fandom.
I'm John Coxon.
- I'm Alison Scott.
- And I'm Liz Batty.
- And we are coming to you today live from Liz's house.
Alison is on the balcony and Liz and I are on the sofa.
- Well, I'm on the coffee table.
- Yeah, you're basically purchasing the coffee table
in the middle of my living room, but that's fine John.
You do you.
(laughing)
- I shall and thank you.
And the beer here is excellent.
So I'm drinking Nocturne by Unity,
which is a lovely oatmeal porter
and I'm surprised they sell it in Thailand.
(laughing)
- I am drinking two tribes Metroland, a session IPA.
I am surprised they're sell it in Thailand.
(tongue clicking)
- Liz, are you drinking beer?
- I mean, I'm drinking water,
which they also sell in Thailand.
So.
- Fair enough.
And yes, we are here.
This is the last stop of Alison's guff trip
on the way back from Worldcon.
She's coming back from New Zealand via Thailand
back to Wolfham Stowe.
Are you tired, Alison?
- I believe I now have a title for my virtual guff report,
which is Time Zones, Our A Social Construct.
(laughing)
- That doesn't mean that is true.
- So yes, I am quite tired.
I feel, I think I feel less tired
than I would after a regular convention,
which is interesting because I do feel very tired,
but I do not also have some kind of low level
gastric disorder and a majestic hangover.
And I think that's a win.
So normally at the end of a convention,
I'm kind of quite poorly as well as being physically
and mentally tired.
And I do not have any of that stuff.
I'm just tired.
I am, I do not know what time of day it is.
I do not know what day of the week it is.
I have no idea whether I can move back
straightforwardly from New Zealand time.
I don't even know what New Zealand time is.
Oh, I do have to go and visit the Chatham Islands for half an hour.
So I'm gonna do that.
So there is one more stop on,
there's one more kind of New Zealand stop on my tour.
So I wasn't aware that there were any talking pigs in New Zealand.
Talking pigs?
Yeah, if you're going to chat to ham.
I make this joke every time I go through Clap Ham,
I'm like, we're applauding the pigs at Clapham Junction.
And Hogg the first time I did it laughed entirely too much.
And so I've never stopped.
So basically I blame him.
So this is basically a brick joke for some different fandom.
A mean, I guess.
Maybe.
So, and you are, you may be channeling Ian Sorenson.
I again regard this as a great compliment.
So I have no regrets.
Oh dear, Douglas Spencer has said he does the same
whenever he goes through sheet wash.
Fair enough, fair enough.
I have also been at a convention this weekend
and a spina has been at Consi-land.
And we have been getting increasingly greasy takeaways every night
and drinking entirely too much.
So I do have the traditional lack of vitamins
and over-emboying of alcohol feeling
and feel very much like the Sunday morning of a convention.
Liz, how do you feel in terms of vitamins and stuff?
I feel pretty good because I think at the end
of the last Worldcon, I had quite a big hangover
and that was entirely due to Alison Scott
spending all her growths on beer in Martin's Bar and Dublin
until they literally closed and turned the lights
on and kicked us out.
So I don't have that this time,
but I will be having a beer later in solidarity.
I have two comments to make on that.
The first is on a point of order.
I should say that as well as spending my own personal growths,
I also went round the bar finding if anyone had growths
that they did not expect to spend
before the end of the evening
and collecting them up and redistributing to them,
to people who didn't feel they had enough beer
to last till the end of the evening.
And I also, at least one point in the evening,
hung the treasure of Dublin 2019 upside down
by his ankles until quite a lot of growths fell out
so that I could do more redistribution of growth.
Is that the only reason I was not at Conzeland
until the point at which they shut the door
and turned off the lights is that I had to leave
the dead dog about 50 minutes early
so that I could come here and set up for this pog car.
So I think they have actually shut,
I believe that the last parties at the Conzeland,
I think the discord is still open for another three hours,
but I think the last parties have closed now.
You'll still be able to watch the videos
and things for a week.
So what are we talking about this week, John?
- Conzeland.
So we're going to note at the top of this episode
that we are going to talk to Alison
about how much fun she's had at her convention.
And I might talk a little bit about how much fun me
and his panel have had doing conventions this weekend as well.
We are unlikely to have a coherent
and nuanced discussion about all of that,
what happened regarding George R.R. Martin
and the Hugo's and general things that were on fire
as a result of that.
We will be discussing that next episode
where we have had a chance to come up with
coherent thoughts, sensible thoughts, nuanced thoughts,
good thoughts.
But critically, thoughts that we can edit
before their broadcast.
- Let do.
(dramatic music)
- How did you find shifting time zones
on your guff trip, Alison?
- I do not know what time of day it is.
I do not know what day of the week it is.
I do not know.
- Sunday.
- It started out quite good.
So I thought it was going to be quite straightforward
and it was straightforward.
And then we went camping,
so I was combining a actual holiday in the daytime
with virtually touring New Zealand and Australia
in the nighttime and there weren't any hours left
at that point.
And then it went all went quite wrong.
And since then, it's been a bit chaotic.
- How was being in New Zealand and Wales simultaneously?
Did that go well?
- Both these places have sheep.
- Okay.
So I got out of the, you know,
it's dawn in Pete Crump's farmhouse garden
'cause we were camping in his field.
And there's like these rolling hills and sheep.
And I was like, you could almost believe you were in New Zealand.
- Oh, you know, it's a good point.
Okay, for enough.
- So this is quite like,
but then there was some kind of really weird things.
So I was going virtually touring
where Ming and Smitty were taking me around Wellington
on a, as a telepresence, on their phone
and pointing me at things so I could see them.
And it was about two o'clock in the morning.
And this sort of thing is quite strange.
So, and yes, that was the point
where it all went completely wrong.
But also when I got back, even though I was here,
once I was on New Zealand time,
the notion of being expected to fall asleep
at one o'clock in the afternoon
when it's very sunny in the house is very active.
It can no longer be explained away
by going to bed late or very late
or getting up very early.
It really was just that you were on the opposite time
and it's much harder.
- So I kind of ended up with a couple of sleeps a day,
neither of which were at all adequate
and which taken together,
did not remotely add up to eight hours
or even probably five hours.
- So a proper convention sleep cycle then?
- I don't normally sleep in the afternoon at conventions
unless I have got so exhausted
that I just drop where I am.
And I met Kristin, Kristin Sybert, I think her name is,
who is the head of parties at Conzilas.
So we spent quite a lot of time together over the weekend
as I spent all the time working the party room.
She was basically the party host for the Zoom parties.
And the parties ran in three hour chunks
every eight hours all weekend.
So you basically had...
- I really like that.
'Cause this fan you mentioned that and that's a good idea.
- That worked really well.
They should have done it with the panels as well.
So what they probably should have done
was have a three hour slot of parties
and then five hours slot of panels
and possibly just a three hours slot of panels.
And then a three hours slot of,
then an hour for lunch and showers and physical exercise
and actually not spending your time on your ass
because the hugest difference between a five day
online convention, at a five day work on,
I hit 10,000 steps every day,
I hit 20,000 steps most days.
I get plenty of physical exercise.
I normally get plenty of fresh air.
A Dublin, I got so much fresh air.
I was often at severe risk of being knocked over
by the bloody wind.
And at this convention,
I literally, it is not wrong to say
that I have dragged myself from my bed
to my desk chair back to my bed.
And one of my dear friends was talking about her
extremely aged and infirmed mother
and said she just, she spends all night in her bed
and then she spends all day in a chair
and she started to get bed saws and we're really worried
and I'm like, okay, yeah,
I should be checking for bed saws at this point.
So, so I have not had very much exercise this week
to put it mildly.
- I have been in a similar boat from Thursday.
I basically spent, well, as I've told Liz,
I've spent roughly 12 to 15 hours a day
playing Arkham Horror of the Card Game on my computer.
- Don't look so happy.
You look so happy.
For people watching this,
- It's been really great.
- John just has this, he has the exact same grin
that people have when they've had sex
for the first time with the new partner.
(laughing)
- I mean, I would like to say two things.
Firstly, España laughed, could hear it.
Secondly, I would like you to know
that I look less happy than this in that situation.
I am definitely glowing right now.
I think we can all agree.
- Yeah, no, you really, really is looking very contented
right now.
- It's been so good.
It's been so good.
I had a hugely great time,
but it has necessitated doing stretches at my computer,
which is fun.
- Yeah, I've had to do stretches at my computer.
Sometimes I've had to stretch for beer
and sometimes I've had to stretch for two two chips.
- I see, I'm weightlifting right now.
So Liz, yeah, we've talked a lot.
How are you?
- Well, I'm good and I haven't been to a convention,
so I figured I would just stay quiet
and react to Alison's stories of Consiland.
- Does Alison's story of Consiland make you wish
you had time shifted and attended Consiland?
- It does a bit because the time shift for me
would actually have been not too difficult.
I think basically I could have time shifted
by just getting up very early,
but I'm not naturally a morning person.
So the idea of having to get up at 6 a.m.
to attend the convention seemed really grim,
so I didn't do it.
- I was on the program at 8 a.m.
New Zealand time on the first day of the convention,
which is like 9 p.m. UK time.
So I had to time shift to get up
to be on a program item at nine o'clock in the evening,
as if it was the start of the day.
And oh my God, anyway, I blame Laurie Mann,
who tells me it's not her fault,
but I blame her anyway.
So I never, I never,
that day I was on program at eight o'clock in the morning
and 10 o'clock at night.
(soft music)
- So I have a question about the Consiland program,
which I didn't look at in any great detail.
I saw people doing the traditional,
I could have done it better on Twitter,
and I sort of mostly ignored that.
But did you find that it was programmed
like a traditional Worldcon in terms of like the times
and how many panels were in each slot?
Or what did you think changed compared
to a physical Worldcon?
- I think it was programmed very much like a normal Worldcon
in that a lot of random people were put on panels,
sometimes the great effect,
and sometimes the slightly less good effect.
It mostly ran in the daytime.
So compared to a British con,
Worldcons and American cons generally
do not tend to have the programming into the evening
on a range of increasingly frivolous subjects.
That for me is the entire point
of attending program at conventions.
So, and I understand that it's important to have
an important topics about the important things of the day,
but I would have liked to have seen,
I'm sorry I haven't a clue and things of that kind as well.
But I know that I'm not going to get that.
So with the day was programmed pretty thoroughly
with exactly the sorts of panels,
probably rather fewer than you would get at a real convention.
But nevertheless, people went to a lot of program.
People worked out that you could go to program
and slip out very easily if you don't like it.
You could go to program and kind of be in the bar,
having a, people had worked out that you could like man
your convention table in the bar,
whilst also watching things on the program,
whilst also snarking to people in another chat somewhere.
And I think people like that a whole lot.
That was very popular.
So that was that.
I was on a fair number of program items,
vast numbers.
I saw some more because I promised people
I was not going to work at the convention
because they thought that if I was being the guff delegate
and also running a dealers table
and also being on program, I might die.
Also working the convention, I might die,
but it became quite clear early on
that some of the areas of the convention
were not quite coping.
And one of these was the Zoom host role
where you have somebody in the Zoom
making sure that the exact thing we're not doing
in this Zoom actually.
We probably should have arranged somebody to do that.
But anyway, but.
- Do as I say, not as I do.
- Yeah, exactly.
But they needed that role and they,
and they knew they needed that role
and they trained people for it, but they didn't have enough.
So I did a few shifts of that.
So I did actually do some work on the convention,
which got me to see a little bit of the kind of
how things work backstage.
And then the only other work I did was that
there was one point where they wanted to,
they had a party room set up so that ordinary members
of the convention could meet Hugo finalists.
And we met somebody who was very senior at the convention
who had been working for like 102 consecutive hours
at that point and that he just looked at us and said,
I now have to go because I have to run this room
for random people to meet Hugo finalists
in which there will be random Hugo,
random people and no Hugo finalists.
And Tammy Coxon, who's the Hugo administrator
and me who was the gof-goer that said,
"Well, why don't we sit in your room
"and you could go and actually get some sleep
"or do whatever else you have to do?"
And we can man that.
So that was the only other work I did.
And I think if there was gonna be another con like this,
I would actually get in touch and say,
"I'm very happy to host parties for you
"if you have like official party rooms that need hosts.
"This is a thing that I'm prepared to do,
"provided you don't mind me being drunk when I do it."
- I'm actually curious, Alison,
how well did it work with all the participants on Zoom?
Because there's a huge variation in whether people
are sort of, you know, sound like they're on a panel
from underwater somewhere or like,
you can hear every single thing that's going on.
- (speaks in foreign language)
(laughs)
- Three to people with quite good setups.
So how well did it work for ConsiLint?
And were people like on the whole, you know,
audible and compensable or was that a big problem?
- The items I was on as a panelist,
we had all our panelists and I believe they were all audible
and it was completely fine.
And this was a non-issue for us.
One of the rooms that I was in charge of as a Zoom host,
we had an author who is in the class of people
who probably should never be allowed near a computer
and who could not get her Zoom set up
and who had had quite a lot of individual tuition
to help her get Zoom set up and they'd finally got it working
and that, but the set up that they managed to make work,
she couldn't get gallery view working on.
So she insisted on loading the app as well as the website
and it all went spectacularly wrong.
So the poor viewers of whom there are about 30 or 40
who come in to see this woman read,
who's going to be nameless because this is absolutely not her fault,
got 25 minutes of me trying to coach her through Zoom instead.
So I think there is a,
we should probably be a bit more dogmatic about
we are, if you're going to be a program participant
at this convention, you need to do Zoom training
and we need to know that you have done it.
And that Zoom training could be very short
if you're obviously competent,
but for the people who take longer, they need quite a lot
of personal love and attention.
In general, it was amazing.
I think people forget how difficult it is to hear panelists
and see panelists in program items,
particularly big program items normally.
I think for a lot of panels,
you get a much better view of the panelists on Zoom
and you get to see them in their native habitats.
You see them in their studies and with their cats
and this is kind of nice.
I thought I quite like panels on Zoom
and you can leave.
If a panel's a bit boring, you can just tuck it away
in a corner and do other things.
And just when the person who won't stop talking,
I think moderation is probably slightly harder on Zoom.
I was in one panel that was terribly moderated
to the point where I as one panelist said,
I think it might be nice to hear from the other panelist
who isn't speaking at all.
I mean, and I hadn't spoken very much at that point.
- Oh, Jesus.
Like, 'cause I've moderated panels with people who talk a lot,
mentioning their names.
And like, it can be difficult to interrupt someone
who's in full flow and it is more difficult
if there is an audio delay.
But like, yeah, if you're the moderator,
you really need when there's a pause to be calling
on the people that haven't been speaking as much.
And if you're not doing that, that is what,
where did you learn to moderate?
This is the one concrete improvement
I have made to British fandom.
I suggested that Eastercons should run workshops
that like did moderation roleplays for new moderators
at the start of each con.
And that is a thing that has been adopted.
And I think it's a good idea
because when I fly moderating, I had no idea how to do it.
I just let Neil Gaiman talk, which as I said,
that was the right choice
'cause most of the room was there to hear Neil Gaiman talk.
And fewer people there to hear Dave Haddock talk,
although in some ways Dave was more interesting.
But yeah.
- Didn't I have to keep coming
and frantically waving the time up signs
that you've that pedal to try and get you off stage, John?
- Yeah, I'd had two hours of sleep
and I was still drunk
and I was moderating a panel with Neil Gaiman
about the hitchhiker's guide to the galaxy.
Like, I'm a standard, I voluntarily stopped moderating
that pedal.
I am surprised that people didn't have to drag
to be from the room.
I was having my, I was living my best life.
It was so good.
I have to say that if I'm slightly surprised
that at the point where you came in and frantically waved,
the audience didn't hunt you down
and beat you up really less.
I think I could--
- It was a good.
- 'Cause it seems unlikely that whatever was on next
was going to be more engaging
than Neil Gaiman talking about the hitchhiker's guide
to the galaxy, presumably a few years ago.
- 2008, it was, it was the,
not Olympus orbital, orbital,
Eastcom in Heathrow.
- I mean, he was guest of honor.
So he probably had his schedule like,
planned down to 10 minute intervals.
So quite likely if he hadn't stopped his hand load,
if had to come in and then try and get him
to go to whatever he was doing next.
So it was good for us already that John wrapped up
because I was being like, what do I do now?
What do you do if your panel doesn't actually get off stage?
I guess in Zoom, if your panel is running over,
then presumably you'll just get the, you know,
this Zoom chat will shut down in one minute sign
and it goes away.
I went to a panel yesterday,
there was a item that was scheduled for,
it was originally scheduled for 10,
but I think that was a mistake
'cause when I looked at the schedule again,
it had been moved to 11 and it said it would run 11 to 12
and I was like, really?
Like, what's his power?
That's the last power of the day and then I can go to sleep.
And then at 12, they were like,
oh, we're supposed to wrap up now,
but like, there's nothing else on the schedule for a while.
So we'll just keep going because there's no,
there's no one to stop you.
And that meant I was like, oh no,
I want this to go to bed.
So I ended up like, it's finally asleep next to me,
like on my iPad with my earphones in,
in the dark, wishing they would stop doing up,
well, no, 'cause it's a great Arkham horror trivia,
don't get me wrong.
But I was like, I always hope it could go to bed, guys.
But it was a very good stream, so.
- I have to say, there are some things
that Kansilin did quite bad.
So they, I think they'd fail to realize
that you can't just uncontrolled,
I can meet you like this where you're working
on a Zoom basic account.
So you've got 20 or 30 or 40 people in,
but it's a panel with a discussion angle.
That really needs to be set up with, you know,
everyone else with video off an audio off
and questions in chat and quite formalized,
because the sort of quite come and go discussion
that you might have in a program room in that circumstance
is not gonna work on Zoom,
because Zoom, as we all know, Bob,
fails from groups of more than about 10.
It stops being fun.
- Turkler Spencer says in the chat
that big group discussions on Zoom are very bad
for hard of hearing people, and I can imagine that being true.
But I think that the other, the flip side of that
is obviously small group discussions
where people aren't talking over each other
are presumably much easier.
I am not, I am very, very slightly hard of hearing
in that I don't, like, if I go and get a hearing test,
I won't be recommended to get a hearing aid,
but I can't hear stuff like crickets,
like it's brand new, you can hear things,
I just can't hear when we go walk.
She's like, listen to that.
I'm like, there's no sound there,
it's brand new, what are you talking about?
- I was going to say the good thing about Zoom meetings
that Conziland did was that they were quite focused on,
this is how long the meetings will last,
this is how long you've got until the next meeting comes in.
They slightly, they made it a bit hard for reading
because the readings, the readings were 25 minutes
with five minutes to turn the room round
and I can tell you that was quite the tricky thing,
particularly as you have one author
and if they can't manage Zoom, it's very hard.
But for the panels, it was mostly the things
that they expected to attract a lot of people
running webinar format with an understanding
that the webinars could run over if they liked
because there was only one webinar every two hours.
- Yeah, so there was a program in each time slot every hour
but they had two separate Zoom accounts
for each program room.
So you do webinar one and then webinar two in the same room.
Yeah, so it looked seamless to the members
that they just went into a room.
But in fact, as you went through the door to the room,
you were seamlessly transported to one of two rooms,
one of which contained a lady
and one of which contained a tiger.
No, different rooms.
Okay, neither of you got that joke.
Hopefully someone in the audience got that joke.
I can hear that someone in the audience got that joke
and I think they were in front.
- Because Paniya says that we're young.
No, it was a span of your chuckling
and coming through my mind.
- And Roman has said, "Nice joke, thank you."
And some of Joe has said, "I want the tiger room."
So okay, it was a, I promise you it was a good joke
even though you two didn't get it.
This is one of the problems with Zoom
for people who do any sort of comedy
is that that lack of reaction is very distressing
that you kind of go, was I just not witty?
- No, and you can't, 'cause I've given seminars
on Zoom professionally.
And I think the problem is with,
yeah, the problem with that
of audience reaction is you can't tell.
And especially like, I'm just looking at my slide.
I can't see any of the faces of the people I'm talking to.
And I'm like, I have no idea
if people are struggling with the concepts
I'm going through.
No idea if they're enjoying the little bits
of daffness I'm putting in.
Like it is really hard to give talks on Zoom.
I imagine as an author doing a reading
it must be even more difficult
because ultimately on my slide,
I got some pictures of graphs
and people could look at the graphs and be like,
"It's a graph."
But like as an author, you gotta convey emotion and stuff.
And that must be tricky.
- Yeah, it's really hard to try and teach people over Zoom
because you can't see if they're falling behind.
I'll see if they're sort of looking worried and like,
"Yes, and Zoom's kind of got some reaction things
"with like go faster and go slower."
And yes, and it's possible that those could be used for React.
Facebook Live has little React emojis
that float up the screen as you're doing your Facebook Live.
But I just want you to know that I have now done a Facebook Live
and it was very horrible.
So I'm not sure I'm gonna do another of those.
- Zoom has them as well.
I can click on go faster and go slower.
- Yeah.
- Oh, we have votes for go faster, go slower.
- Yes, me and Liz are telling you to do one of each.
So please say each word very quickly,
but with long pauses in between.
- Like this, maybe this is really...
- Yes, excellent.
I'm gonna turn off my go faster 'cause this is not.
- I turned them on off.
- Okay, that's a bit better, right?
- I like the fact that you went high pitched
like I was fast forwarding your audio
in an old rubbish music player.
That was excellent.
- Yes, that's how I do fast forward, obviously.
I'm thinking I'm perky.
- This is gonna be very confusing to our listeners
who listen on three times speed.
I just wanna point out.
(laughing)
- Yes, yes.
Oh my goodness.
Yes, no, please.
I'm crazy Dave and Max right in and tell us of 3X speed
whether or not Alice in talking fast forward
is comprehensible.
'Cause if it is, you are super powered.
- They can always slow it down for those bits.
They're slowing it down for my bits anyway, I'm sure.
So one of the problems with parties at Zoom,
so they had a party suite and what they did
was they created a 500 person party room
for which each party had one breakout room.
So that meant that if you were, say, running a party,
and I ran two parties in these spaces over the weekend,
you just had a kind of uncontrollable room.
And as anyone who knows of me knows,
I run Zoom parties quite a lot,
and I run them as a managed set of breakout rooms
so that with the idea that each room ends up
with five to 10 people in it,
and when it gets bigger than that,
we kind of encourage people to break it into smaller rooms
because we find that those are the,
I find that those are the optimum.
Somebody asked me what was the optimum number
of people in a room?
And it kind of depends how many of the sort of introverts
who like to sit in a corner and not say anything you've got
because you can have quite a lot of those in your Zoom room
as well as the loud-mouthed people who want to talk all the time,
but you could probably only have about five or six
of the loud-mouthed people who want to talk all the time.
Or two if they're Lillian.
- Oh, is Spania as one of the Lillian group
or the Alison group?
Maybe they're all women, there must be some men.
- Oh no, yeah, it's Spania came down and said,
"Alicein's first party at the Zoom was like 50, not 50,
but like some huge number of people are like,
how did that work?
Did anyone get a word in it?"
And well, I did, obviously.
I was like, "Oh yeah, that makes sense."
(laughing)
- It was actually, so I went to, I said,
I thought we had 37 at peak.
- Blindly.
- And the party team said, "No, no, no,
you never went over 25."
And I was like, "I had 37 at peak."
But I, yeah, it's fine.
It's still clearly too many.
But people were happy, people were fine, I think.
And then we went down to a manageable number
and it was all good.
And then the second party, which was not the Guff party,
it was the Fanny McFanny's party had fewer.
It had a kind of very stable, agreeable number
of people all evening, so that was quite good.
I still felt that I would have been happier
if I'd had three or four breakout rooms to look after.
And then I could have moved people around
and then popped in to make sure they were happy
the same way I would normally do it.
- So were there any absolutely colossal parties?
Like, I'm not sure which one you hosted
other than Fanny McFanny's, but you know,
I did like Chai Khan or Glasgow in 2024
have colossal parties and how did they work?
- No, I ran, oh sorry, I ran three parties
'cause I ran a party for Glasgow.
And again, we had about kind of 20.
I think a lot of the members of the convention
did not find the party spaces.
- Right.
- Yeah, that's a problem.
- And some of the members of the convention
who did find the party spaces kind of
were expecting more structured parties.
I don't think they'd realized that parties
assisted of people sitting in a room drinking beer
and chatting about random stuff stuff.
And then there were a couple of parties
that were almost like book discussion groups
put into a party space.
And then I think eventually the filters
took a kind of a filming space to kind of do
the sort of film that you can do on Zoom,
which is where everybody shuts up
and listens to one person sing.
- So I have a question about how Conzil and diddle this.
So I know that like several of the parties
were basically just a single breakout room
for anyone who is in that party.
So like Glasgow in 2024 had like one breakout room
for the Glasgow in 2024 party,
which is not necessarily how I would have got
about a stroke train there.
But on the, so the convention I am attending
does not have a Zoom component.
It has a Discord and then it has the different panels
and stuff are streamed on Twitch or YouTube
and you just like go along.
So there's no Zoom stuff happening.
But it has a feature where in the Discord
you can create new rooms in the Discord to hang out in.
There is a basically you draw a voice channel
and it automatically opens a new voice channel for you
and kicks you out into that.
And you can put video on, you can play a game.
So it's really good for like playing pickup games.
Is that something that Conzil and would doing?
And do you think that would have worked better?
- How many people were at the Arkham Horror Convention?
- Like much fewer, many, many fewer.
- Yes.
So this is what you would do
if you were running a small friendly convention.
What happened was that they experimented briefly
in one of their test runs with letting people
make their own Discord chats
and it all went wrong for them.
They, their quote was it got very, very messy, very fast.
And part of this is that Conzil and had a notion
that they needed to have a way to police Conzil and space.
So party rooms had to have a moderator
and if you had a, if you had a table,
I.E., a Discord chat for your fan group,
you were supposed to moderate what went on in there.
They could have done a lot more there
to make it easier for people to create,
do things with their own tribes.
And there were many Discord video channels in the bar
and I think by the last day they'd,
they'd opt that to about 20.
- Okay.
- So those video channels in the bar
did kind of act like bar tables
'cause you could see who was all in them
and you could spot somebody you knew
in one of those conversations and then join it.
- So we, we speculated when we were speculating
several weeks ago about how Conzil would work,
about how is it gonna work for the sort of people
who if they come into the con bar might find it hard
to sit down and have a quiet chat
because there's someone that everyone wants to talk to.
Now, how would that work?
How did that work in the Conzil and Discords?
Or did you see someone join a table and everyone,
ooh, and suddenly join their Discord chat
and they had 50 people?
Or in practice were those people
just not joining the Discord beer chats?
- Okay. So there was a lot of different,
there were a lot of private zims going on.
A lot of the people who you think of as being more famous,
well, for a start off a lot of the people
who think of as being more famous
weren't actually at the convention.
So there's some of that.
I think quite a lot of US and UK authors were not there
for whatever reason somewhere.
- I guess if your primary reason for going to WorldCon
is to hobnob a network professionally,
I can see why an online convention
would not represent a good opportunity to do that.
- I think you can still form good connections
with people at online conventions.
I think I've been doing that.
Both on my trip and at the convention,
I've made lots of new friends. It's fine.
I suspect that there were a set of zims
to which we, Hoipaloy, were not privy.
'Cause I wasn't getting access to,
obviously there were less and less of Discords
I wasn't necessarily seeing.
I obviously have chats with some of those people,
but I suspect there will have been
like the Zoom equivalent of the stuff was sweet.
So just in the same way as it's a real WorldCon,
you might find that authors don't tend to be in the bar
the way they would be at the EasterCon.
I think that's also true.
- How many WorldCons have you attended, Alison?
- Are you counting this one?
- Yes.
- 11, this is my 11th WorldCon.
- Where did this one rank on the list?
- Oh, that's such a good question
because not at the bottom.
Right.
I think it takes a little while to get into WorldCon
and really get a hang of how to do them.
So I quite, I quite enjoyed myself.
I've had a really good time and it's good.
I mean, last year at Dublin,
the convention where I only got,
there was one night that I didn't get thrown out of the CCD.
The previous night I stayed up drinking
with Caroline Mullen and her daughter until 4 a.m.
And as a result, the following night
I could only stay up till midnight
and couldn't, couldn't get thrown out of the CCD.
But that was the only night.
I did get thrown out the other four nights of the convention
and I feel that that's all you really need.
What more than you want is that every night you go,
you're having sufficiently good a time
that at the point where they round everyone up and say,
"Ain't you lot got homes to go to?"
You go, "Oh, I suppose I do really, I'll see you tomorrow."
- At the Dublin WorldCon,
we had a slightly,
it's spany and I had a slightly different experience
'cause there was a great like,
deli/bakery place around the corner from our digs
and they shut at 3.30,
but they sold pizza out of a whole little wall at like 3 a.m.
So we would leave slightly early every night
so we could go and eat delicious, delicious pizza.
I like, yeah. - Absolutely.
- And I will put a picture in the chapter out
'cause I do, I took a picture of the pizza.
- I have been being rather glass-hoft full
for the last three weeks
and people have kind of gone,
"Oh, this is all right, but it's not like a real con."
And I keep thinking,
"Have you forgotten how much time you spent in Dublin in a queue?"
- That's fair, it is fair.
- So that's a really interesting question
because queuing at normal world cons
is a very powerful motivator in saying,
"Ah, sod this, I'm not going to programme
"and returning to the bar to drink more with your friends."
Did you find that your like ratio
of socialising to programme changed
and do you think that people like went to all the programme
they wanted to go to as a result
didn't socialise as much as they usually would
and ended up being like,
"Oh, I didn't see my friends as much."
Or do you think that's not?
- I had a, well, a lot of people,
people's friends weren't necessarily there as much.
- That's true.
- I had a theory that before this started
that the convention would not quite get the social spaces right.
I think that theory is confirmed.
I getting those social,
so they did some things right, for example.
They had a programme-discord chat
for every programme room,
but not every programme room, but many programme rooms.
There was a discord chat
that afterwards to match it.
So you would get thrown out of your Zoom
and then there would be a place in the bar
for you to go and have a text chat.
And unfortunately, they could probably have done
with a video chat associated with each of those as well,
but they had a text chat associated with each of those.
And I think that was quite good
in terms of carrying on discussions,
exchanging links, forging friendships.
I think they could have done with more
kind of generic meet-up things.
I said, I don't think we haven't got the social spaces
sorted yet, especially for such a big convention.
And I think there is a risk
that these online conventions will get bigger.
I spoke to numerous people over the weekend
who were there because they had always wanted to go
to a worldcon, but their geographical location means
that it is impossible for them to ever get to one.
Social spaces, it got better through the weekend.
So I found, and I think that's often true at the Worldcon,
that you kind of don't quite know how to find your social spaces
at the beginning of a Worldcon.
And then it, after a bit, you know where you're going to find
the people you want to chat to.
I had to work quite hard to find social spaces at this con
because a lot of what I think of as my bread and butter
social life was not at the con.
So all the people that I automatically end up
in a bar chatting to because they're my mates,
none of those, I think, sorry if you were,
but the, I mean, there are a few in here,
but the vast majority of the people who I think of as my
regular mates were not at this con.
So that meant that they weren't there to talk to.
And so you have to do more work.
I think we need to say this every week,
the fact that they managed to turn the convention
into a virtual convention, the time they did
with as few things going wrong as did go wrong
is an absolute bloody marvel.
They stitched together a ton of different stuff
to make it happen.
It all more or less worked.
Those of us that went, well, I certainly had a fantastic time
and I think a lot of other people had a fantastic time.
I wanted to say something else that was much better
than we could possibly have imagined,
which is that we ran a fan fund auction.
We were like, we are not going to make any money.
It is going to be a bit of a disaster.
We ran it in Zoom.
- Yeah, no, I saw that.
You made like a thousand pounds?
- We made 2000 New Zealand dollars.
A lot of which was due to some very marvelous lots.
I have to mention Esta McCallum Stewart and James Shields.
Esta gave us two shawls.
I think we're going to have Esta knitting
for the fan funds for the rest of time now, if she doesn't mind.
So she had two shawls that they went for a lot of money.
And James Shields custom printed us dice
with convention logos.
So like a D20 with the Conzila logo instead of the 20.
And oh my goodness.
You know, if he wanted to set up a business doing this,
he could probably do this at this point.
There were loads of people in the auction
just for that one lot.
And then Erin Underwood, my Duff counterpart,
had hit up a load of authors for like story critiques
and Zoom calls and things of that sort.
The fan funds auction ran so well
that I have a plan to run a kind of golf party
at some point.
So you're on warning here.
It'll be like the other golf parties,
but it'll be a party.
Everyone will be invited.
And then after about an hour of drinking and socializing
on Zoom, it will seamlessly turn into an auction
where we spend an hour shaking you down for money.
And then we'll go back and party
for the rest of the evening.
Does that seem like a reasonable way to spend a evening?
- Oh yeah.
And it's very important we get people drunk
before we ask for their money.
So that is a sensible order of operations.
- So it was sufficiently, and we'll do the same thing there.
We'll get a load of lots and we'll get them on a website
so that people could go, oh my goodness,
I want to go to that
because I want to bid on this thing that is unique and special.
- Do you think that a future real world con
should have an online track?
- I think it is much harder than people think.
The reason this convention was a success
was that everyone was at home and we are all nerds
and we all pretty well have jolly good internet
and all the equipment we need at home.
And if what you did was put everybody into a hotel
and then said, oh, and we've got a hybrid track,
then at that point we would destroy the convention's
Wi-Fi in a spectacular way.
I don't think panels made up of three people in real life
and one person online would necessarily work.
I mean, I think it's worth thinking about.
I think every convention, I will say this right now,
if you're running a convention, you should have a Discord,
you should open it today,
you should encourage your members to join it,
you should have chat rooms,
you should start to create the social space
for your convention straight away
or certainly well before the convention.
I've never understood why conventions don't.
I mean, initially I assumed,
but initially I never understood why they didn't have slacks
and now Discord has become what Discord has become.
I now wonder why they don't have Discord
'cause I'm like, this is like Twitter,
but it doesn't have a lot of awful stuff
about what's happening in real life on it
and it doesn't need me to be on Twitter.
I can actually read all the messages.
So I just, I think in so many ways
it would be a very good idea.
And you could have an announcements channel
which could be the new?
- Less that sees, not zero Nazis.
Oh, and also you could just say
that the code of conduct,
the code of conduct applies to all the spaces
in the Discord all of the time,
which you cannot do with Twitter.
- I think that actually is not necessarily an issue,
but certainly if you decide to bring everything in-house
on your Discord, then you have to commit
to maintaining the code of conduct on your Discord.
So you suddenly add a lot of work for yourself
where essentially you need people watching
all the messages on the Discord.
- I have a question about that,
which is do you think that policing your members on Twitter
where you don't have any power is easier
than policing them on Discord where you do?
Because I think if you had a Discord,
you would be able to say the COC applies to our Discord.
We actually have the tools to enforce that.
But as Doug pointed out,
the code of conduct for resisting conventions
already cover their Twitters and their Facebooks.
So you're already having to do that.
So I'm not convinced it adds a lot of work
that's not already being done.
- Also, you just have a listener function.
You say to people,
"If you see anything that's troubling you,
"tag listener and we'll come and have a look at it."
And that's, so it's actually,
it's not that you have to read everything.
It's that if somebody sees a problem,
they can bounce in a mod.
And that doesn't seem to me to be ludicrous.
And before the convention, you can say,
"It might take us 24 hours to come and look at your thread
"because it's before the convention
"and we're all very chill right now."
- When everything is in-house,
people will have an expectation
that you will be able to react much faster.
- That might be a good point.
I will also say that I think the Discord
is a very good opportunity to finally do something sensible
with virtual or digital or online newsletter.
That isn't just putting a PDF on a webpage.
Because I think making an RSS feed or a blog
of the newsletter doesn't really work
in the same way that having a physical newsletter
at a con does,
and I wouldn't advocate for removing a physical letter
at a con,
but being able to have a Discord announcements channel
where you can have the newsletter team posting
in real time as they get news items
would be a revelation for how
at con communications and publications are done.
And as someone who's always been a little bit
a nerd about those sorts of things,
I would very much like to see this happen.
And in fact, I will email Diana afterwards
and volunteer to do it for 2021's EasterCon.
- Can I just check?
Are you saying your
actually offered to run the Discord?
- For a Eastern Con 2021.
- Yeah, if you're gonna set a Discord up for them,
yeah, that would be great.
I think everyone would love it.
I think people would love it right now
while they're all kind of a fallout from Concealand.
I think it would be great.
Anyway, so I want to say something about
the Concealand newsletter, which is,
oh my God.
(laughs)
Oh my God.
So they did this thing where they basically said,
how we're gonna run newsletter is,
if you want something in the newsletter,
you write it to this thread
and we'll put it in the newsletter.
So the newsletter was a bare dump
from a random Discord chat.
And it reads like that.
And it's, this is actually shocking.
But I mean, I think if you had a Discord and you got,
so I don't think everyone was on it.
I think maybe only 60% of the fans
that Concealand were on the Discord, maybe.
And the number actively on the Discord
might have been a bit lower than that.
So there's a kind of getting people to take the technology,
to actually get involved in the technology there,
that we need to help with.
(laughs)
- On the subject of letters of comment,
we have some letters of comment.
We have a meme of comment from España Sheriff.
If you are listening to the podcast,
I will have put this picture in the show notes
so you can go and look at the meme.
But yes, this is her based on us getting very meta
in our last episode.
So, yup, that is a fact.
- Ah, I just need to say this is much more what I'm after
in a podcast than the people talking about books with movies.
I'm sorry about that.
(laughs)
- So, Hog sent us an email, or sorry,
sent me a text message,
asking if I'd heard of the New Games Journalism.
So, the New Games Journalism is a thing put forward
by Kieran Gillan about 15 years ago now,
in which he kind of talked about
what is the added value that you get
from having someone who is actually good at writing,
talking about, in this case, video games,
as opposed to just getting someone random
to play the game and write what they thought about it,
and then move on to the next game that you give them to play.
And he made an argument that actually
the missing link there is when you review games
or talk about games, you need to be linking,
you need to be linking what you're talking about
to what people feel when they're playing games,
and contextualizing it in how they might have felt
when they're playing other games,
and actually linking it to the human condition
in a way that just playing the game
and then talking about what the game is
doesn't necessarily do.
And that kind ties into what we were saying last episode
about the difference between a podcast
that just literally reads a book
and then talks about the plot,
and a podcast that kind of contextualizes the genre
in terms of reading different books.
And I had used the example of Shabbat sit down
in the gaming world as a way of doing that.
And that is an example of the new games journalism.
So there will be a link to Kieran Gillens' manifesto
in the show notes.
- I am going to say that both Liz Batty and I do know,
I hope Liz will remember this and not look blank,
but we do know about Kieran Gillens' new games journalism
because about 2017, how long ago was in the autumn of 2017,
about three or earlier than that, 2016, 2015,
about five years ago, we were sitting around
in a living room and I think Michael Abbott said,
it would be really good to get Kieran Gillens
as a guest of honor at FollyCon.
And I said enthusiastically yes,
and the reason I said yes was because of new games journalism
rather than because of his comics writing
with which I was not familiar at the time,
I had been an inordinate fan of Kieran Gillens
for games journalism rather than,
because I am, as everyone who listens to this podcast
probably knows by now, a very considerable games addict
and nobody was writing sensibly about games
except for Kieran Gillens, I slightly exaggerate,
but not much and that was really important to me.
And I think that games are not well-loved by,
are they not well-supported by EasterCon
despite the fact that most EasterCon members
are actually quite into gaming
and it's a thing that we probably,
not, it's not that we should have more games at the EasterCon,
it's fine to have games at conventions,
but I think that we don't do enough,
I'm always after talking about what it is
that we're doing when we are making the thing.
So deconstructing things in greater detail
than just, oh, the plot stuff that I talked about last week.
And I think that games journalism is one of the core,
you know, talking about what it is that people are doing
when they are playing games, it's a lot interesting
than saying, and I liked this game
because it had interesting characters
or because the cards were nicely cut.
- Yeah, so I remember that slightly differently
'cause I think I said, maybe we should get Kieran Gillen
and Alison went, yes, for his game journalism
and my club went, yes, for his comics.
And then we were like, okay, well, then he definitely
like fits the bill.
So I would be delighted if we were to end up as a podcast
in the new games journalism style,
although I think we might need to be a bit weirder.
(laughing)
- Challenge accepted.
- My thinking of new games journalism
is it was digging into those things,
but it also wasn't afraid to kind of be a little bit
strange while doing them.
- Yes, I think the surrealism of Sharpe sit down
is definitely part of that.
- Yeah.
- And I know that Kieran Gillen is a friend of Quins
and Matt Lee's and has written for Sharpe sit down
on occasion himself, mostly about Warhammer.
So we have two more letters of comment.
Firstly, Malcolm Hutchison,
which he signed his letter as Chockey Monster,
which I already did not know was his pseudonym,
but I'm gonna use it.
So Chockey Monster asked whether they could have
comped Hugo finalists today membership.
I believe this did eventually effectively happen.
I believe Hugo finalists were given the ability to attend,
or as a Hugo finalists did not take them up on that,
'cause I was attending a Arkham Horror Convention this weekend,
but I think that was done.
And I think we will be talking a bit more about
the nuts and bolts of Consi-land next time.
The final lock is from one Claire Breiley of Croydon.
And she has written a poet.
- So the Octothorpe Poetry Corner.
- On rudeness.
The higher minds of Octothorpe have made it very clear,
clean up your dodgy poetry.
They want no rudeness here.
We've checked and so it now appears safe topics can include
seeing comments leaping even with a naked eye,
and it seems it isn't rubber, so it's also not too rude.
If your only need for latex is transliterated tie,
they nonetheless put in themselves really very sinister,
a sudden and quite unprovoked terrible prime minister.
So avoiding offence is just more mark protection,
and listeners too, all those blushes to spare.
Yet when Alison Ponder's sports body perfection,
John Waze her words and concluded, that's fair.
So sing double standards and don't try your luck,
even if you think it's just a comedy, ah, yes,
this isn't gonna get featured either, is it?
And it's the one I like most, despite the complicated meter.
But maybe this one will be more accepted.
- Going down under.
Alison wants more subscribers and rest,
and maybe a pie is a float of the best.
When did today start?
Who can say where it ends?
Adelaide site seen by phone, held by friends.
Western Australia, then nullable.
Friday night drinks over Zoom, not a pub crawl.
Discord with Erwin while watching the football.
Don't say the city name if you're not sure.
Canberra, Sydney, the beaches up north,
Hobart, Tasmania, Capitol radio,
then just the whole of New Zealand to go
and finally sleep going home on the fourth.
Guff passes the 21st century test,
the modern fan travels by Oculus Quest.
Coming up, the live broadcast.
Octa thought live what to drink, what to wear.
John needs to check all the settings in Zoom to record it,
and Liz needs to tidy the room for Alison
not to be there.
This is not a podcast for fan technophobes.
John leave out the magnetosphere,
but speed up the sound and it still seems quite clear
unless they're talking to Tobes.
Liz has no thoughts on all French aristocracy.
John is still pondering Hugo democracy,
and where is the fun at a virtual comm?
Join us with Octa thought, fan nerd or geek,
then Alison's hoping to sleep for a week.
Right then, I do need to let you get on.
(clapping)
Okay, thank you very much Claire.
We love them.
Keep sending poetry guys, we're never gonna stop.
So that was the 11th episode of the Octa thought podcast,
and for today it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me, and it's goodbye from me.
The theme music for this episode was fanfare for space
by Kevin MacLeod at Ncompetech.com,
used under a Creative Commons attribution 3.0 license.
(upbeat music)
I should say I came upstairs, I said to my family,
I should explain that my daughter is moving out of our home
to go and live somewhere else for the first time
during the recording of this podcast,
due to what I think I would say
is a cock up on the catering front.
And so we had this sort of tearful farewell,
and I said I have to go up half an hour.
(laughing)
I was actually gonna be first.
Oh my goodness.
She didn't say, she didn't say,
could we move the podcast?
This is, I did not know that.
They're pointing.
Oh dear me.
I really didn't, when you say you didn't know it,
I didn't know it either.
I didn't know it until I was in the dead dog at Colzila,
and I was like, I should probably leave the dead dog.
And Marianne said, yes, you probably should mum,
'cause I'm gonna move out while you're on the podcast.
I was like, you what?
And so anyway.
So I came upstairs and I said,
I have to start the podcast early.
We're starting half an hour before we actually go live.
And Marianne said, that's so you can work out
before you start broadcasting exactly what you're gonna say
about George RR Martin, isn't it?
And I said, yes, you have got it right in one.
And the answer apparently is nothing,
but bits might slip out around the edges,
in which case we're terribly sorry.
Right, anyway, so yes, Marianne is moving out.
She isn't really moving out forever.
We've had her girlfriend stay with us for the last three months,
because they didn't really want to not be able
to have any physical contact.
So they wanted to be living in the same household.
And so they are now going to go and live in
Kirsty's parents' house for a few months.
So at some point, probably, things will go back to
a state of normal where people who are partners,
but do not live in the same house
are allowed to have physical contact,
at which point they will probably,
Marianne will come back and live with us.
Kirsty will stay living with her parents
until such time as they both have
gainful employment and can rent a flat.
Yes, I just assumed she was moving out
because sharing a house with you time shifted
had gotten to her to the point that she was like,
I'm out of here.
Is this how...
So what extent do you think this is true?
It's perfectly plausible.
Are you gonna add at all these berry burps out of the podcast?
I can't hear them.
I'm not going to edit you mentioning that.
We will edit your berry burps.
So have fun with that.
That's gonna be the title of the episode, "Berry Burps".
We're gonna remix it into the Octopiquilida,
the "Buttery Biscuit Bass" song.
"Berry Burps", "Berry Burps", "Berry Burps",
"Burps", "Burps", "Burps", "Burps", "Burps".
Excellent.
We're making music here.
If you're tuning in now,
you're listening to the Octopodcast,
a jam podcast for people who like music.
We were talking about something that wasn't this
and I don't really remember what it was.