So Alison, if you could look confused, I'll just take a sneaky screenshot of the zoom.
How does it have to look confused?
A bit like that.
Hello everyone and welcome to the 10th episode of Octa Thorpe, a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom. I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Betty.
And we have several letters of comment this week and we have Max, who has written in to tell us that she beats Crazy Dave. She listens at 3x speed.
And she says that she wishes we could speed up pub chats too.
And this gave me the idea for a panel show, which is to have people listen to podcasts at various speeds, see how much they understand, and then have them drink alcohol and then repeat the process.
And so they're too drunk to understand any words and I think this could be funny to do at a convention.
Okay, so I have a theory that we should speed up tobes and see if anyone can understand him at any speed.
Yes! Yes! 100% yes.
Because I once had a conversation with tobes where I was drunk and he wasn't and I understood everything he said perfectly.
And I felt that I'd been, and he talked a lot of sense, and I felt that I might have been missing something for all the previous years of my life.
España will tell you that she doesn't understand tobes even when he's sober.
But she lies, she does understand really.
Also, happy birthday tobes, because it was tobes' birthday the day before yesterday as we record, which is the 19th of July 2020.
We should say here that we mean, when we say tobes, we mean "tobes valwa, scion of the valwalkings".
Right, fucking of France. Liz, any thoughts on French aristocracy?
I have no thoughts on French aristocracy.
Okay, it's always worth checking. On the subject of Crazy Dave, he sent us an email and he basically says that he doesn't tend to vote in the PSFA awards,
and he wishes that the number of Hugo finalists would go back down to five now that the puppies have gone silent because he finds he sometimes doesn't get round to reading all of the books and he doesn't like voting if he hasn't read everything.
But he thanks us for reminding him that you can actually just not finish the things you're not enjoying because that probably has ramifications or implications for whether or not you'll think it's the best of the punch.
But he does know he has mostly managed to finish all of the Hugo finalists in recent years because of his commute, but notes that the lockdown has somewhat hurt that method of keeping in touch with the finalists.
At the time we go out, you'll have about minus one days to vote in the Hugos.
There is a slender chance this will go out on the day of the deadline, but it might well be the day after.
So if you haven't voted, it's probably too late, but you know, you could get reading.
Sorry.
So, Mark Plummer has sent us a poem which I will now read to you dramatically.
Shouldn't we each read our own?
Oh yeah, we could each read our own stanza.
Yes, please. We do have to note before we do this that Mark has written this in an order which is different to the order in which we say hello.
Please do not be alarmed. This is artistic choice and it is valid and important.
Are you going to explain why he sent us this?
So, last episode we asked all of our listeners to send us poetry and Clara Hughes about members of the podcast,
and me and Alison and Liz, and Mark sent us two poems in response to this challenge.
One was a Clara Hugh about me, which is not going to be broadcast, but we all thoroughly enjoyed.
And Liz came up with a reaction, Clara Hugh, to that.
Liz, do you want me to read your poem or would you like to read your poem?
I'm happy for you to read my poem because I have lost the email with it in,
but I think it may be a limerick rather than a Clara Hugh because I don't know what a Clara Hugh is.
And here we go.
This is Untitled Limerick by Elizabeth Batty, age 34 and a quarter.
Is that how old you are?
No.
Close?
Recently close.
On the flattering side, so we're okay.
Yay!
The poems of Croydon found Plummer and to tame Octothorpe for the summer,
though his rhymes are first class, they're too rude to broadcast, which is really a bit of a bummer.
Thank you, Liz.
And now, have we all got the email from Markup?
Excellent.
So, Dr John the Boy Coxon didn't notice several locks on Octothorpe because he hadn't checked,
and thus he failed to Mark protect.
Liz Batty, also doctor, didn't know so many people had locked her.
Octothorpe's a fanist gestalt, but in this respect, it's all John's fault.
Guff winner Alison Scott has several novers and she has also got two hugos for the fanzine
plotter, but unlike John and Liz, she's...
From you, lon.
Shh, not a doctor.
This ends Octothorpe poetry corner.
No, but you know, we're happy to do it again.
Please send us more poems. Yes, absolutely.
Oh yes, please send us more poetry.
Please keep sending us poems.
Ideally, you go for faintly rude, but not as rude as Mark's previous one.
I have to say, if I was responsible for editing this podcast, we'd have broadcast it, but that's just me.
Alison, you are currently on New Zealand time.
That's not so. Or Australia time.
I am currently on Sydney time, which is nine hours ahead of the UK.
It is therefore currently 9.36pm as we record, which is significantly later than we usually record.
So I wasn't quite sure.
I sort of said I will do a virtual guff trip and I would have loads and loads of brilliant ideas
and I would make them all happen.
And then I promptly forgot about it until my diary was like, "Oh, you have a first John and Liz alike.
This is what Alison is like."
And my diary was like, "Your virtual guff trip starts today."
And I was like, "Oh, I suppose it should."
So I started setting up meetups and I now have meetups in Seattle on a stopover and in Perth,
a couple of times in Perth and in Adelaide and in Melbourne, where we spent most of the time
with the Melbourne fans, oh whoops, the Melbourne fans, schooling me on how you say the word Melbourne
and me not really quite getting it.
And then this morning Canberra.
I still have to go to Sydney and then up the east coast of Australia to like all the bits that
have lovely beaches and I want to do things.
And then I also want to go to Hobart Tasmania, which is kind of a capital radio joke and doesn't
really have anything to do with an actual love of Hobart at all, but I am going to get to Tasmania.
And then I've got a couple of days in Turing, New Zealand before the actual Worldcon starts.
Getting on to Australian time was really hard, but I'm on Australian time now and it's fine.
When I've not been doing chats, because it's not just Zoom chats, I have obviously had
a lot of appropriate Zoom backgrounds.
I have started sketching, I should have started sketching earlier, but I didn't.
But I haven't started sketching, so there are going to be some sketches of some of the things
I'm seeing while I'm there.
The primary thing I'm doing to experience the country is that I used my Oculus Quest,
which has starred in previous episodes of OctaThorp as a way I was staying sane in the apocalypse.
And now I'm using it.
I create YouTube playlists of 360 degree videos that I shove my headset on and watch
all these videos.
Oh my god, it's like being there.
It's not always like being there, but sometimes it's like being there.
And this is very exciting to me.
And as a result, I've got to experience a load of authentic,
tourist experiences like going on a dolphin watching boat trip around Rocknest Island and
walking around botanical gardens.
So there's some things about Australia.
Space is very big, but it doesn't have anything on Australia, which is absolutely bloody enormous.
It's huge.
Everything in Australia appears to be very big everywhere.
All Australian cities have a set of things, and they seem to me to reflect
colonial history to some degree.
So they all have, apart from Canberra, they all have historical buildings,
which seem like, to Brits seem like very ordinary Victorian architecture,
that in the UK would be in severe danger of collapsing into disrepair or being torn down
in order to make flats.
But, but are kind of these are the exciting historical buildings in, in Australia.
They all have a botanical gardens.
They all have masses of park land, and they all have a jail which has been lovingly restored.
Weird, weird detail.
And they also have, they have a kind of big thing about colonial guilt and debt,
which I'm just kind of getting my, my head around seeing as I feel like the British do not have
as much of this despite the fact that we kind of cause, but in our psyche it's not such a big thing.
And, and Australians are lovely and loads of them have come out to see me.
And I've done, I've done some actual telepresence things where like going out into the Adelaide
hills with Damien and Juliet while on Juliet's phone and wandering around the centre of Adelaide
with Roman Ozutsky on Roman's phone.
And I'm trying to think, do any of you have any questions about it?
So overall it's going much, it's both better and more interesting than I expected.
That's excellent.
But I'm very tired now and it's only been a week.
I have questions, so I am curious as to have you met anyone through this guff trip that,
you know, were fans you didn't know previously or has it been hard to get people who don't already
know you to come and join in? Whereas if you were there in person it might be easier to get them to
come out to meetups, do you think?
I'd say about the meetups have been half people I already know, but in some cases I only knew very
faintly and half people I didn't know at all.
That's a terrific ratio.
So roughly even and lots of people I don't know.
Some of them I feel I know quite well now.
So I watched them not really properly well but a bit and this is how relationships form over
long times don't they?
So it's not just I had dinner with them and then now we're bussing friends forever normally.
You kind of build these things over years.
So there were people I'd met once or twice who I've now spent some more time.
I watched an Aussie Rules football game of Erwin Hirsch said you must while you're out here,
you must watch an Aussie Rules football game.
So I discovered that you can stream them online.
So I at one o'clock Sydney time or 4.05 am UK time I was watching
Carlton play Port Adelaide.
I think it's okay now to say the result because it will have been a few days but I've been quite
careful which is that Port Adelaide won that at the point where the final whistle blew they had
a free kick so they are allowed to take that free kick and they kicked it into the goal and
and beat Carlton who is Erwin's team by three points.
Oh that sounds good.
So that was devastating for Erwin but I was like oh if you're going to watch a random game
from a sport you've never seen before you could not have asked for a better one that is how sports
should be.
As far as I can see Aussie Rules football has everything a sporting a sports ball activity
could require it is it is very fast pace a lot of points are scored nothing is properly in control
ever and it is played by extremely beautiful people.
There's a limit to what you could say in 2020 about bending two and a half hours
ogling gorgeous men whilst talking to equally gorgeous Erwin Hirsch on discord.
Oh this is how we get locks we just call our listeners gorgeous.
This is how we get locks so I don't think that's offensive quite but I mean they're just lovely
to look at and it's just very entertaining it's a good game I enjoyed it a lot.
I am not much into sports ball I did have to pay I thought that was reasonable that's one of the
biggest expenses I would say touring places virtually is very cheap compared to touring them in real life.
Are you saying that your monthly broadband subscription costs you less than a flight
halfway around the world? When I'm costing up the virtual guff trip which I am going to do I'm going
to put things like my order for authentic New Zealand meat pies into the list of expenses but
I'm not putting in either my broadband subscription which I was paying anyway or my Oculus Quest
which I did not buy with this in mind at all it had never occurred to me I'd be using VR goggles
to wander out bits of Australia and I've done some video diaries so um we should probably
have a link to the video diaries on the show notes for people who feel that octa-thorp every
two weeks is not enough allison for them. Yes Alison will now put the links in the show notes.
I have six subscribers at the moment it's very exciting I'm kind of demonstrating how you fail
to monetize. Yeah if you'd monetize this channel properly then you could actually be raising money
for a guff while on your guff trip probably not really much maybe enough to cover your pie.
That seems fair. That would be great that would be quite funny yeah I actually have more
subscribers to my other channel to the channel I have under my under my Bohemian coaster name
despite the fact that they're just totally random things I see that those subscribers are all bought
so there's two videos so far one of them is saying no views which are a bit depressing.
I think I really have no views. The the virtual guff report which you'll be very pleased to hear
Claire Barley of Croydon has volunteered to edit for me is going to consist of a vast stack of
bits and bobs thrown into an electronic carrier bag and tossed over the wall to her with a kind
of if you can make any sets out of this you're doing well dear. Yes but it's gonna have an appendix
on what the technology I've been using is and and to what extent that has worked. One of the things
I've done is gone for a flying trip with the flying doctors because I am of an age where British
people learned only a very few things about Australia growing up and one of the things we
learned about was the flying doctors serve and now of course I live in Wolfham stow where we have
our equivalent to the flying doctor service because it can take so long to get people the two miles
from where they've been injured to a hospital they send a helicopter yeah so so it's it's much
the same sort of thing except on a much smaller scale and it turned out that David Cakes wife
Karen who I don't think I've met on this trip but I don't think I've met before spent a year
working she she's an emergency doctor by trade and she said he spent a year in Alice Spring working
for the flying doctor services this is the closest I've got to anyone who lives in the interior of
Australia at all who is actually also an active fan um if you are listening to this podcast and
you live in the interior of Australia and you're an active fan then please please get in touch
because I would very much like to talk about what it's like to live in the desert yeah that's good
sounds like you're having a good time on your guff trip I'm exhausted so tired
Liz has posted a link in our show notes with a tweet that expresses some concerns about the
Conzeland program and an open letter to Conzeland outlining and detailing those concerns
Liz would you like to talk a little bit about what's going on here yes I mean I just happened to
see this tweet retweeted on my feed today with a link to the open letter the discussion seems to
be about essentially Hugo finalists and the use of Hugo finalists on the Conzeland program
and it sounds like quite a lot of Hugo finalists have not really been offered things that are
relevant to their expertise um or they they feel their panels do not have a diverse enough
participants or a diverse enough framing of the topic of the panel and also it's it's not clear as
to where the people can participate in programming without a full membership
extension where they have to buy the full membership and of course this is all especially
difficult because this is the first virtual world con and so there are going to be extra
difficulties and problems associated with that but it sounds like coming this letter although
not public are some suggestions for ways in which these problems could be mitigated yes and the
tweeted question was posted by Alistair Stuart who is a nominee for sorry who is a finalist for
best fan writer and people may know him as well for being a host on the escape pod family of
podcasts my thoughts on this are good job mark protecting there John protecting the Hugo finalist
mark yeah well you know you've got that bit sorry I just got because I was like Alistair's not
called mark which is like mark plumber has done a number on my ability to accurately
talk around by role on the mark protection committee um so the um I have thoughts about this I am a
Hugo finalist as has been previously mentioned um I am not on the Conzeland program because I am
not attending Conzeland I did get a program participant survey I think but I didn't fill it in because
I'm not going um I in general can see the point that the signatories of the letter are making
but I think my thoughts on this are neatly encapsulated by something that listener Emily
January said to me it is in another place and another time which is that I understand the
representation is very important and I want people who are not traditionally attendees of the world
Conz feel like they're being invited in if they get nominated for Hugo's and I can see why having
Hugo finalists on the program is really important but however I think that there is also an argument
that the world con is by and for the World Con membership and so if someone is not a member of
the world con it is not necessarily the case that they should be invited to be on the program if
they haven't signed up so I think there is in some ways a clash here between um World Con as a thing
that is put on by its members and the expectation that you will be invited even if you are not a
member um and I think that is a complex discussion that kind of runs up a little bit about um the
World Con style of having members instead of tickets and I wonder whether conventions that are more
ticket-based might be skewing this conversation slightly in a way that is a little bit antithetical
to how World Con's have traditionally worked and I do think that there is another um element here
which Emily pointed out which is that she has chatted to newer conventionality attendees at
Eastercons who she has said oh you'd be great on program and they've said oh I can't be on program
I'm not an author and I think this idea that to be on program you need to be a professional or
need to be recognized in some way is dangerous because I think in general programming is about
putting interesting people on panels but having said all of that obviously people who get nominated
for Hugo's and become Hugo finalists are perhaps interesting people who it would be good to have
on panels so maybe those aren't antithetical concepts um so my thoughts on this are all very
wishy washy and nuanced which is unhelpful for polemic allison before thrite I agree with everything
that john said so I think oh dear some of the wishy washy stuff there is fine I also note that people
are kind of like I got offered program but it wasn't the exact program item I wanted to do
to which I would say that's the thing you can suck up yeah and but I also note that they say the
program is not diverse enough and it doesn't feature die it doesn't have enough diversity in its
range and scope and it doesn't have enough diversity of participants and that I think
conzeland if it had got its act together four or five weeks earlier would have done well to have
a think about it's now clearly too late for them to do that um some of the australian and
new zealand fans i have spoken to have said you need to remember as well this is a new zealand
wilcon and they are and I think 100% correctly for grounding australian and new zealand creators and
fans in the program and that is that is absolutely the right thing for them to be doing part of what
you do when you have a local wilcon is showcase what you are doing both professionally and fanishly
in science fiction for the world and I think that's inevitably going to lead to some voices
particularly voices from american participants not getting as much attention as they often do
i might have no idea where alice to do it comes from he's he's british i should say the spread sheet
is a private sedition of spreadsheets which i think is correct it was a correct way to do it
there's an open letter and then they have probably sent a set of helpful suggestions to the program
team which i think is absolutely the right way to do it well it's a good way it's a good way of
doing it because it doesn't turn it into a giant muddslinging flight but it also implements concrete
exact suggestions i think there's a few aspects of this one is i think it is normal or at least
the normal when i've been involved to get in touch with all the qgo finalists who you know are
attending to say hi would you like to do some program but part of this is about the hugo finalists
who are not attending who do not have a comped membership but part of the issue is that usually
because the expense of attending a wilcon is way more than just the membership it ends up being
that even if you gave three memberships to every hugo every hugo finalist many of them still wouldn't
be able to attend i feel like if they comped membership for every hugo finalist who was not
already an attending membership they would have a much bigger problem on their hands than the problems
that they currently find themselves because all the hugo finalists who that maybe at some
considerable expense themselves because it's not cheap join the convention um this is another
argument for why you should be eurocon and charge 10 euros for your membership i need
still have a joyjip but i must do this or uk gave's expert charge absolutely nothing i mean i have
had discussions about whether we should just be giving comped wilcon memberships to all qgo finalists
like as a matter of policy and you know refunding the ones who already had memberships but it it does
in any normal wilcon end up being quite a lot of your members there are quite a lot of hugo finalists
as well and they're in fact increasing numbers of hugo finalists because we have a lot of multi editor
um podcasts and and magazines which is great but it just just increased those numbers again so i
think we worked out that you'd have to comp like a substantial fraction of the membership which would
be an issue but with this being a virtual wilcon that issue is partly side step because you don't
have a membership cap you don't have the physical facilities your costs are not as high so in this
case i think they could consider comping every hugo finalist so my thought on this is effectively
something that allison knows i have strong strong feelings on which is i i i i generally think
this problem is being caused by the fact that the membership is far far too expensive um and
the fact that we have seen like zero other science teaching conventions charged in excess of about
thirty dollars and this one costs somewhere in the region of five times that is tricky and i
sympathize for the consilent uh committee and there must be reasons they're doing that and i suspect
those reasons are things they can't easily get out of but honestly i think the whole thing is being
caused by the fact that this is a hell of a value proposition for a for a virtual convention um
and i think it's difficult because you're quite right that in general comping hugo uh members uh
hugo finalist memberships would not enable them to attend the convention anyways there's not much
point doing it but this year it would be necessary to do that for most of them to attend and also
it's the one year that doing it would mean they could participate so it changes the conversation
a lot compared to normal um world cons and other virtual conventions running alongside the world
con i have two thoughts that the first is that one of the things that has been a little less nice
about my guff drip has actually been a bit sad is that i keep having conversations with people where
i say and are you going to conziland and they and people are saying no it's it's far too expensive
i can't do it and i was i kind of got used to those conversations in britain but i i have been
quite sad and surprised by the extent to which i'm having them in australia and i think that's that
it's really interesting because i had assumed the reason i was talking to a lot of british people
who weren't going was because those people were not planning to go anyway but if people from
australia and new zealand are not planning to go that says something quite significant i think about
conziland's pricing structure because i would have expected anyone who had been planning to go to the
world con to have been attending the virtual world con the people who already had attending
memberships have kept them they did their their kind of partial refund system has worked in terms of
keeping their attending members to the most part i don't think a lot of people who had attending
memberships have have scrapped them but people who were were hoping to go or have not picked up the
virtual membership just the same way that they haven't in in the uk as well so i thought that was
bit sad um my second point was having said that they clearly cannot routinely conz membership for
every hugo finalist because that enormous number of hugo finalists i think they might manage to
conz membership for every hugo finalist who is not already an attending member and is from a
marginalized group and suggests that they may have financial problems managing the cost of
membership because i don't suppose that's actually going to be that many people so that that would
have been a thing that they could do and certainly i don't know if this is true of world conz but in
the uk we have an honorable tradition of having an un waged membership level which is available to
you if you feel you need it rather than uh making it sort of a thing where you have to be able to
prove that you need it which i think is in general a good model for doing that sort of thing we don't
it's not a lot cheaper but it is something you could have the same system here where you say look
if you are from a marginalized background and you know you you would like us conz membership we will
do we're not going to ask questions you know we're not going to ask you to prove anything about it
we just will uh so my other thought is that having only very briefly looked at the conz
elan program because i'm not going it's it's got a lot of program items but i think it's still got
quite a lot fewer than at a regular world con which i think makes sense i don't think you want
like 15 to 20 program item running simultaneously i think you probably want five to 10 but it means
there are many fewer spots on the program and i also wonder if they're having an issue of time zones
because one of the things that has become increasingly difficult when programming
world conz is trying to do the scheduling it is like a you know multi-week nightmarish jigsaw puzzle
and that is with everyone in the same time zone to try and get everyone on items with the right
people and the final time when all those people are available and at the con and you know there
will always be commitments people have though people you don't like doing late evening panels
people who don't like doing morning panels and so on and sometimes you do go okay this would be the
ideal set of people for this panel but there is no time slot that actually works and so i have to
change it up and i wonder if time zones are causing even more of a problem because if your ideal
panel would have someone who's in europe someone who's in new zealand and someone who's in the usa
that's going to be very difficult to do so i wonder if sometimes the way that they have solved
problematic scheduling issues is to drop people who would otherwise be good on the panels and
replace them with someone who just has more availability i i think i'm sure that the time zone scheduling
has been an absolute nightmare and they can't you know i basically told them i would be on
australia in uzland time but i've been given at least one panel on european time and luckily it's
that it's at um ten o'clock at night New Zealand time because i'm kind of a late bird will probably
be okay um but it's quite a serious panel and normally it's at a british convention i go on panels
at ten o'clock at night and they're all the kind of lighter-hearted ones so i don't know whether
how it's going to work in practice one other thing i wanted to point out uh so i was complaining about
the cost of gonzeland relative to other online conventions and we mentioned that the euro
gone this year is ten euros i will say that there's the opposite um the opposite problem occurs to me
which is is this partly because we as a community are not devaluing our time as volunteers enough
and we actually should be charging more than ten euros for what is probably really quite a lot of
work um is this something where consi-land are actually charging an appropriate amount of money
for what it is they're planning to put on and other conventions are so severely undervaluing their
their offerings that consi-land is suffering as a result but we always undervalue our volunteer
labor because we essentially put thousands of hours of volunteer labor and for no money all the
actual cost that you pay for worldcon is going to the physical facilities and the paid staff of the
venue it's not going to anyone organizing it so it would be a completely different model if you
started charging for virtual conventions because of the volunteer time you're putting into them i
can understand charging in order to make sure you have you know a sufficiently good zoom and
discord license on so on but if if we're going to actually start saying okay and then we will
somehow compensate people for volunteer labor you put in then you are one changing the whole
model and two you're probably going to get yourself into a very sticky situation because of then
employing people that's a good point i'm not sure if that was what you were proposing not as such i
i guess i wasn't trying to argue that they should pay volunteers as if their employees but i do
wonder to what extent conziland are using more services which do this sort of thing professionally
because they partnered with the fantasy.network and people like that and i do wonder whether part
of this disconnect is coming from this is an appropriate amount i need to spend for this sort
of event but most other places are much more relying on volunteer labor to make it work okay so
we always rely on volunteer labor to make things work i think collet conziland decided
possibly correctly not possibly not so correctly that they didn't have the skills within fandom
to do everything that they wanted to do and so would need to use paid labor for something that
that would normally be um volunteer labor but in fact their primary things are you know we're
going to send you an email with your zoom links in it we're going to be all discord i mean this
doesn't seem to be that much different from what baltachol did and baltachol managed with its
existing volunteer knowledge you know we've built up some knowledge in this area in the last few
months i mean i don't i don't want to criticize conziland too strongly for a decision that they
took under pressure i feel like they're doing their best job they can to run a good convention
under extremely difficult circumstances but i feel like considering that we are all volunteers
and we are generally happy to you know we muddle along in slightly good less less good hotels than
we might and slightly less good circumstances than we might generally at conventions because
we're actually after the volunteer feeling of it and and the relatively cheap thing i think that
the model the models that we see going forward will be cheaper than gonziland they may not be as
cheap as eurocon we'll have to see how that goes there are a lot of the professional conferences i
might consider going to uh have gone online and their virtual registration rates are usually
somewhere between sort of maybe 20 to 60 pounds so they are a cut above eurocon but they're not as
much as conziland well and so this this actually neatly dovetails into the next point i was going
to make which is is the other mistake potentially the conziland has made not relying on sponsorships
because like the uk games expo is doing everything for free but they're being sponsored by some of
the largest companies in the industry and a large part of the money they'll be spending to make
their convention go is being provided by those companies now world cons have not traditionally
relied on sponsorships and there are contentious discussions to have a power back and i have been
present for some of those discussions even though i have a baby fan world con has an interesting
sponsorship history which i think we should take another time but it is fair to say that in general
but not always will cons have happily taken some money from publishers and anti-stikons for that
matter but it's not normally there's not normally the amount of money flushing around in the industry
that there can be if we were taking money from television or movie studios say so so publishing
is more marginal generally however i remember having a chat with patrick lee lson hade of taut
where the taranto world con was called talk on talk on two or talk on three and tour books basically
went yet that will spot i see you have this range of possible sponsorships and sponsorship
things can we have the biggest one please which i think is quite good they they weren't called
talk on because of that but in general there are issue there are some sponsoring issues we we are
not very good at at acquiring sponsorship and then finding appropriate ways to use it that don't
worry our membership i think another good example of recent sponsorship is just san jose's sorry world
con 76 colon san jose 2018 they had their hugo ceremony and it was sponsored by google and they
gave a free google home to all of the hugo reception attendees that year and because google does not
have an obvious conflict of interest with any of the kind of hugo finalists that went entirely
unremarked upon and i think was generally a very good idea so maybe that's the other thing which is
science fiction fandom in theory leans towards friendliness to technology and to other such things
so perhaps going to a technology sector which is increasingly flush or maybe even going to somewhere
like wetter who are obviously a homegrown New Zealand institution but aren't necessarily
explicitly competing for any of the hugo categories there might have been options but it's very easy
to quarterback these decisions when you're not the one making them under incredible pressure and i do
i do think allison's point about that as well i realized one of the other things i do is the
mit puzzle hunt and the mit puzzle hunt is the sponsor is entirely paid for really
by sponsorship from tech companies and when these tech companies talk about why they sponsor the
mit puzzle hunt it's like there is no better place to recruit in the world than by the sort of people
who like spending three days of their weekend solving very hard puzzles for fun is it is it too
soon to say easter con needs to think about going virtually we're back to normal by christmas
allison don't you remember and we'll play football against the germans on on christmas day i've
just been i've just been struck dumb by that thought that's so good sorry to anyone who does
come to us for escapism for the sudden and unprovoked mention of boris jonson for which we can only
afford choice oh i thought this was like off the record for planning for the next podcast so i'm
not i'm not cutting that joe karl the podcast liz and now i think that bit about never gonna be
playing we're going to play football with the germans on christmas day i thought was amazing
we're going to turn the we're going to turn the virus off for an hour
so we can all go out and play football
yes fantastic but in fact i i i don't know if i'm the only person but i felt a real chill in my heart
when johnson said we will have normality by christmas because i just went oh well we're not going to
then clearly clearly that's his way of saying this will be the 2020 to 2024 pandemic
i've done some reading i don't think we've got time to go through it in quite the detail
of our previous episode which we talked about hugos i've read the hugo finalists for best novel
with the exception of uh the light brigade which is the last one on my list i haven't quite got two
yet and i'm about two thirds of the way through giddy in the ninth and i have read the other four
i've been enjoying them generally i thought they are very high quality and i would be happy to see
pretty much any of them win so far my favorite is maricold empire i was on a zoom yesterday
with some friends in which i was decrying giddy in the ninth but it turns out it gets good about
40 percent of the way through and now it has got good i am really enjoying it i will say that the
beginning is a little bit of a slog and my wife keeps asking me whether it has gotten good yet
i keep saying no be patient it gets there um i know that a lot of people think that's going to win i
don't know if it will uh i think my favorite is as i said maricold empire i have uh read city in the
middle of the night um and middle game so i think city in the middle of the night is probably my
least favorite i liked it but um didn't quite do what charlie jane and does previous novel did for me
quite a little game uh really liked maricold empire and the ten thousand dollars of january both of
which i thoroughly enjoyed and thought were really really good and as i say giddy in the ninth i
dike i think i like it better the middle game and city in the middle of the night but i don't think
i like it quite as much as the ten thousand dollars of january or a maricold empire i'm wondering
whether i'm going to enjoy the light brigade because my wife bounced very hard off it um but i will
be reading that and hopefully next episode i will have some thoughts but yeah so far those are my
thoughts about best novel i'll just want to very quickly outline them to show that i do read
yay even when i'm not on trains that's probably a little bit longer than three minutes but that's
mostly because i got our dc fontana episode mixed up with the challenge in anders book i thought
you were going to do all the hugo categories and i was like shit jane i need dinner at some point
i i have read some of the hugo stuff but nothing like enough um one of the
i accidentally found myself in a discussion of best novella at one of the zoom chats i've been in
the um a critical mass um and they they found it quite interesting because they said we all
like this one the best but we don't think it will win we think this one will win and i thought
that's very interesting they kind of had this notion that the hugo voters are voting as a as a
conglomerated agglomerated mass that do not vote for the best thing but whenever i voted in the
hugos and be really really keen to see something amazing win it's either one or or or come second
to something else very solid so i'm not sure i agree with them but i am i have stored their
prediction away and i will i will be watching the hugos carefully reveal in an envelope after the
hugos next episode and i'm giving out a hugo i'm so excited i i had forgotten that that was a thing
they make guff delegates do how do you how do you give out a hugo on zoom no it's great i when i gave
a hugo to claire it was brilliant even if i did pronounce the name wrong i am i am very excited
about handing out a hugo even though it's obviously going to be a virtual thing which category are
you handing out i am handing out best fan artists oh excellent that's a really yes excellent i did
get around to listening to episodes of at least one but mostly two or three episodes of all six
of the best fan cast hugo finalists and i wrote an article about it which is is compliment is
reasonably complimentary about all of them i think it's a it's an overview article at Glasgow
2024's blog um and i was quite interested in them i wanted to say a little bit here about them because
it turns out that most of these um fan cast are people talking about books or movies or
television shows and sometimes that could be very interesting but generally while it is all very
well it is not my primary interest in science fiction fandom i realized what i was listening to
these um so hence i'm i don't notice that um lillian and christina and diana are out there doing a
fan fan cast about everything else in the world now so maybe we can encourage other people to do
theirs too so we can have a whole network of people do fan cast that aren't just talking about the
books they'd be reading uh so this never happens is the name of an excellent fanish podcast done by
lillian edwards and christy lake uh and they may be sad because they reminded me that my duo lingo
street could gone away um i had a multi-hundred day duo lingo street and it went away over christmas
uh because i was very busy and i forgot to do it two days in a row and yes it went way very sad um
but i now know the spanish pre-to-write tense because i have been learning my spanish with an app called
Anki so um anki which liz recommended to me and it's very good for learning languages and whatnot
and other things you could do for later uh mark up i i use i use anki for many i mean i don't actually
but when i am trying to learn thing i set up anki deck for the things that i'm trying to learn
so for example i have an anki deck where i just the anki deck shows me the name of a dance that
our morris side does and i play the tune for it on my melodian so that i can remember how all the
tunes start so that we don't have that embarrassing thing where the dancers are standing around going
okay musician please play the eightteenth of may and i go you can't see on the video on the audio but
but but that that is a very embarrassing thing for musicians to be doing but it's not uncommon for
musicians what we will do is we'll take a photo of allison looking confused and we'll put it in
the show notes now so like look at you look at your podcast app look at it now it's got away now
look at my fully functional latex using anki deck there whoa you're gonna have to take a screenshot
of that and send it to me please oh is that latex tie well no it's latex for transliterated
tie because this is from back before i could read but the transliterations require me of the
method my school uses requires more than just a standard alphabet so it's got a you with a line
through it which represents the ew vowel okay so when you said latex i was like oh i guess you could
use that for learning how to write maths but i learned how to write maths by just writing the
latex when i needed it and looking up things to find out the next bit of latex i needed
for the next bit of math it had not occurred to me that anyone used latex for anything other than
math i use it for work obviously uh well that's maths did it i'm doctor the boy who who go
finalist coxern yeah but you you use long words like magnetosphere and magneto hydroton alex
but drichrag is kicking and screaming back to the topic which is it's interesting that i think
allison has reached i don't know maybe there's like a first level of fandom where you actually spend
lots of time talking about the books and the television and the movies which may be where the
start of your fandom and then at some point you move on to this this higher level i listen
as reached where you're now sort of meta fandom um because you're sort of wanting fan
fan cast that talk about fandom oh i i i think one of the fan cast sometimes the fan cast get into
the material business of science fiction so what it is that we are doing when we do science fiction
and i find that a lot more interesting and all of the all of the fan cast do this sometime it's
not that some of them do it but but so a fan cast will go almost seamlessly from in this book there
are a boy and a girl and one of them turns out to be the the hero in disguise and the book tells
of their adventures through the planet nor um i'm paraphrasing but not as much as you might want
and then they'll suddenly go into and it's very interesting the way that this book compares with
the same sorts of themes being talked about 20 or 30 years ago and at that point i'm riveted
and i can't quite find a way to get please stop talking about the plots of the books or why you
find them exciting and stop talking about what it is that is what it is that is going on critically
so for people in board game fandom this this reminds me a great deal of the difference between
the dice tower reviews and the shut up and sit down reviews on youtube because the dice tower does
great reviews in which he goes through the rules and explains what he likes and dislikes about them
which i find very dull and shut up and sit down talk about games and how they make you feel and
how they can paint it how they compare to other games that might have made you feel similar things
or different things and what the differences are and the latter is fascinating as something i thoroughly
enjoy listening to in both science fiction and board games and the former is is not something i'm
as interested in guys because i think of it as a difference between a book report and a book
review in a way and that they are aiming to do different things and and giving me a different
a different interpretation i think part of the reason i like panel discussions at convention so
much is because you tend to get that kind of wide ranging discussion of themes and juxtapositioned
and and it helps you contextualize your um your reading and the reading you've done with reading
you haven't done and like draws parallels and and helps you explore the genre um whereas a book
report talks a lot about a book which is valuable but i don't find as compelling i think that's fair
i hope that's fair i want to also mention when you're talking about um gaming podcasts i like i
like tabletop which is a a video a youtube series rather than which is the will-wheaten thing because
they just play gay in an entertaining fashion so i assume they play games for hours and then edit
it so you only actually see the good bits but i feel like i end up with a sense both of
these people are enjoying themselves which is always quite engaging but also whether this game
is worth playing or not which is something that i'm quite keen to get out of out of gaming podcast
next time we recall this podcast we are inviting all of you to join us for episode 11 of the octal
podcast that will be being recorded on the second of august at 12 noon british time that's british
summertime and we will be putting a link to that on facebook and if you're clear and mark we will
be emailing you a link because we know you're not on facebook and if there's anyone else who's not
on facebook um get in touch and we will email you as a link as well it is not just clear and mark
but we don't want to put the link just openly on the internet because you know how it
so if you'd like to come send us send an email to the email in the show notes or find the
event in our facebook group and i would expect that after we finish doing the proper recording
part of the podcast there will be a trivial chat part of the podcast because those seem to work
quite well as well and you'd be very welcome to stay around for that or in fact come to that without
coming to live podcast that would be fine yeah we can't tell you when it starts it will start
sometime between 45 minutes of three hours to true true true true okay so that was the 10th episode
of the octal podcast and it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me but it's good a from me i'm in
australia the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud at ncompetech.com
used under a creative commons attribution 3.0 license
and i'm like well there will be written you know there is some written stuff and i have
i've written up a couple of anecdotes about the trip like when i got off my zoom chat today at 1129
1129 uk time i won't say where it was in the place i was um my daughter said to me did you really
have another chat to go to at 1130 and i said no having forgotten that we were recording octa 4
but prior to that she said because it's really interesting because you said oh i need to let you
go because you have her you've told me that you've got a draft to submit to before world cod and
you have a load of work to do and you said oh i really should be spending i only get a couple of
hours to spend with my family before i fall asleep those are the couple of hours i'm currently
spending recording the podcast but let's let's move that away and you said oh and and she she just
reeled off the many increasingly fretful excuses i'd use to try and get this lovely but but ever
continuing person off zoom chat without success before going no gotta go 1130 is this by any chance
not for the podcast i feel like i feel like it's probably okay because i don't think the person
in question is going to realize this was them and if they did do then we're very sorry
but i'm just gonna say here's it's one of these british things if a british person says i need to
let you get on or i'm taking up too much of your time it means we're done now can we can we stop
or if you say briskly right that that means goodbye like and it would be very useful if everyone was
aware um no i i know but sometimes right means i'm thinking of leaving and i'm gonna look like i'm
leaving but actually i'm gonna stay in chat for another half an hour maybe have one more beer and
then go yeah no i mean i think i use the word right and enormous about right just generally means i've
actually had a thought then i'm like i'm not gonna tell you um so the the i have i have become very
good on zooms uh just put it in the chat i have to go down by and they're just collecting which i
view as the zoom equivalent of an irish goodbye and i feel very useful um but yes an irish goodbye
where you leave a party without saying goodbye that's an irish goodbye right i think so yeah you
just leave because you know it would take you half an hour to go and say goodbye to everyone you just
kind of duck out we shall put a link in the show notes i believe i was i learned a couple of years
ago that there is great merit in not saying goodbye to people but just leave and i think that's
even probably even more true on zoom i mostly do that at conventions with a few adorable exceptions
i usually say goodbye to liz because she's from far away these days um so anyway other questions
about the guff trip yes now you're going to be camping in whales while on your guff trip how does
that work we decided that while we have this window where it's possible for us to see our elderly
relatives we should do that and so we're going to be camping close my in-laws so you're agal
so you're going to go camping with your relatives while on your guff trip no no we're camping near to
where my relatives live but do not have enough house space okay for enough i mean that's not that
exciting so i think what i'm going to do is get up dawn there is a problem i there's a not a lot
of time after that and before worldcon starts i think the start of worldcon might be very hard for me
that so my current plan is to rise at first light which is about four and go to go to sleep or maybe
slightly before i am determined to see this bleeping comet just look which i've kind of like i'm up
in the middle of the night i ought to be able to see a comet but my my house and garden and location
have other ideas i'm going to need to move a little bit away from borford stone i managed to see it by
just going to our local park which is not particularly unlike polluted but i imagine that
salamton's light pollution is less than london's in general no i mean i think
Simon bison had no problem in puttney but anyway north whale should be no oh yeah you'll be fine i
mean it's it's next week rather this week but i don't think it's going anywhere i know that comets
are slightly they do move obviously i mean you're you're professor the boy coxor must know all about
comets right yeah the big balls of ice and stuff yeah no that bit i do know um so yes
comet neo-wise is visible closest approach to earth is on the 23rd of july which is in four days
time as we record probably the day or the day after we um released this episode um if you're listening
to it uh so yeah you should be able to get good views then but i was able to see it with the naked eye
before last um and i managed to take a very good photo on my phone so i was very happy and i'm hoping
that i will be able to use my phone to take an adequate photo just before dawn in north whale
you'll be fine you've got the same camera as me i have a brand new phone i mean it's an old phone
but it no you don't have the same camera as me you've got the one before mine but you should still be
fine i've got the i the new iphone se it should be perfectly up for taking photographs of comet yes
just take a tripod or something because of their second exposure will do you wonders oh yeah no i'll
just probably push on a bean bag that works i put it on one of those trees scaffolds you get for
very young trees and that worked fine i mean i'll i'll sift on something so so no i am just home
and see but otherwise i'm trying to just get up at first light or just before first light to
take pictures of comet and then go to bed mid evening and not enjoy my evenings but you know what
i mean we're staying with we're staying in the field of peat and carol peat crump and his wife
carol and carol and tops i'm not crump and um and i i the whole part thing about sitting in a garden
enjoying a beer with some is a lot more fun before it gets dark this is an activity that stops being
fun at nightfall so i think if i just kind of stay awake from sunrise to sunset it will it will be
reasonably okay for for australia in new zealand i'm not i'm not doing the bits of the tripway
you'd be traveling or hanging out in people's houses doing your laundry or did this one to
ask me any questions about guff singers i love nothing more than talking about myself that bit
is really not for the podcast oh that's going in that's a hundred percent going in that might be the
episode title no i think i'm curious to talk to you in another two weeks when you will presumably be
almost completely dead oh yes we should plug the live episode the live episode yeah we need to talk
about our live episode coming from um lizz's house where you're going to send me some backdrop photos
that i can use as my virtual backdrop yeah well of the idea of your hair and your hair i'm going to
have to tidy my house it's not it's not very exciting though i mean it's just a house i could
could probably steal some photos off the internet okay so what would be even better
might be a coffee can you go out for coffee with people at the moment yeah so i could like
have a photo from a coffee shop in tylor lizz you need to send me an allison virtual
backgrounds so that we can all be in the same place when we do our live recording all right okay
okay is that the view from your house do i have a number of foot uh this is the view from the
training station so i've for those of you cannot see which is everyone because this is a podcast
i've been changing my virtual backgrounds to different places in tylor and this what happens
be a nice sunset from the train station near my house lizz is going to send me these images and
if you look at your podcast app now you will see them stop looking they're gone i never see the photos
in podcast i know that most people don't so that's why it's funny it's quite funny i mean i i'm just
like how could i see them i'm i'm not watching your audio show you're right we should we should
call that because it's for it's like meta podcasting which we will cover in the live show anyway
oh no i i will i will cut it down to just my joke which was on point fine that's a
your channeling is sore and so that's what you're doing i do not mind that is a great complement
that is also staying in the podcast Ian you're a champ