[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 96th episode of OctaThorp, a podcast for
Science Fiction and Science Fiction Poundome, which is coming to you on the 9th of November
2023. I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
So Chengdu was a shower or was it? But it's definitely past tense because I think today is the last
day or is tomorrow the last day. By the time this comes out it's past 10.
Ah, yeah it's gone. It's closing now. There were lots of very shiny things.
Yes, I think if it was there it was probably quite shiny if you were there.
I get the impression the online aspects were kind of hard to interact with
from other people that went past on my socials. I've heard nothing good about them.
No, okay. I've heard it's like oh they've they basically learned nothing from all of the
experience of doing things online. That's sad. That is, you know. I mean yeah, did either of you
do any online stuff or? No, I tried. Oh Liz, Liz tried. Did you? What happened? It didn't work.
So you like, I should say that my home internet is broken so I'm on my phone internet at the
moment. But my phone internet is really pretty fast as in we are doing a live as a podcaster it.
And so you log in and you like pick a little avatar and you should be able to wander around
in a full 3D environment and so on. And I did that a bit and then I tried to teleport to the live
programming room and I did teleport to live programming room where you get your little avatar
sitting in a little chair but then I couldn't actually get any programming to load. So I gave up.
That's very consistent with reports I've seen. I mean some people have had it working audio only.
Some people have had it working audio and video a bit but mostly we've not really had any
output from the work on. It's just been reports. We've had reports and the reports have been,
well, you know, this is amazing. I mean the report's been amazing. I get the feeling that they
only did the online stuff because they kind of felt they should have an online component because
we have the last few World Cons and people generally like it if they can get something out of World
Cons that they attend remotely. But I think they should really just have ditched it all. Maybe
just stream the opening and closing and the hue goes on some platform and just not bothered
with the rest of it because there wasn't a lot of stuff going on. Some of it was kind of panels
being attended remotely by people doing them remotely which I kind of didn't really see the
point of. And there wasn't a lot of like items that were interactive between the people online
and the people in the audience which is what kind of you want to do to bring people in. So I think
honestly they should have just scrapped it and not bothered. I mean they sold attendance to it for
like $10 or something or $2 for first World Cons. $10 if it's not your first World Cons.
So it didn't cost people a lot so they hadn't lost a lot by signing up to it. Like if it
was a con where I paid $60 for a virtual membership then I'd be annoyed. But it's kind of like
well I'm as well have a go and it didn't really work so I think they should have just skipped it
and had a great time in person which it looks like everyone did. So I can only go buy a report
of what's coming out. File 770 has a lot of stuff. I think our occasional correspondent
Sats Culture has been collecting a lot of stuff together. Honestly like the in-person experience
looks like it's an amazing spectacle and I am kind of sad I wasn't there.
Yes and I just want to say one thing which is thank you to one man cultural liaison at Sats Culture
for basically rendering the entire thing interpretable to Western audiences. Like I think without his work
like I would have so much less idea of what was happening and he has been doing a lot. So I will
just want to call him out and I will say I believe he is eligible for best friend writer in the next
Hugo Awards and I for one should be very glad to see him as a finalist because I think he probably
has earned it. Ooh there are a set of official program photos. Ooh. Instead of just posting the
links in File 770 they've posted the QR codes but not actually said well these are the links.
Yeah I think you're from a less QR code using society but yeah I mean the pictures look amazing
they're venue. The venue which was yeah the venue was amazing. The Hugo's themselves look amazing
I'm sad I don't have a panda Hugo. The Hugo's a beautiful yeah I would have liked a panda Hugo that
would be good. They released just a few days before the convention a promotional video which I
kind of linked to and was like well what is this for and people were like well you know they want
to do nice things. It's not a 2D video it's a 3D animation that has taken professionals hundreds
of hours to do. What's going on here? It does seem like a lot of effort has been put into Chengdu
and it does surprise me a little bit. I'm not sure I would have deployed the hours where they
have deployed the hours which is not a criticism so much as an observation like clearly they had a
vision and they have it seems like they have executed on that vision. But also we we don't in a way
know what they got offered. We don't know if they said right we've got a chunk of money and you'll
you'll get the spoilers for future episodes but you'll get us at some point discussing a little
bit more about you know how you best spend your money and your people points at conventions
spoiler for future episode. We don't know if they had a ton of money and they were like shall we put
a bunch of this money into making a really attractive promotional video or if someone came to them
and said hey we would love to sponsor your convention by doing you a really great promotional
video and they were like yeah fantastic. Yeah no that is true that is Dye's Fair. Yes it probably
is something like that and you know I'm sure it was played at the com. I'm sure it's played at the
com and then you get this kind of like great thing for the author. Yeah it was just in English.
I mean there may be another version of it. Yeah I had very little dialogue at all it's not like it
was the one with a voice over. You could really easily change that one entirely to a Chinese
language. Yeah that's probably right. I'm sure it would have been amazing to have been there and of
course had I not been on my guff trip I probably would have been there so you know it's kind of weird.
There's so many photos of like school children as well and young people and like kids sitting next
a panda photos. Oh so many young people. I just can't help but find that just really cool.
It's not what we see at World Cons usually. And also Nicholas White signing autographs.
Don't they probably thought she was the science fiction author? Maybe I don't know.
It's just it's very good. I got us from autograph once and I found that even funnier.
I haven't seen pictures of Nicholas signing autograph. He posted them on the internet somewhere.
It's supposed to be a bit of one-time. I think he posted autograph. So we don't know if it's plural
but I think that's just going to be there's not that many people there from outside China and so
some children are collecting the autographs of every single one like children who go around
collecting a million ribbons. I will put a link in the show notes listeners so you can you can see
all of this. Yeah I mean how many people are there from outside China because some of the people I
was expecting to be are not. I don't know. I genuinely don't. It's hard to tell. I mean I could listen
off but I reckon I've seen reports from maybe 30 or 40 some of whom are like invited guests on
the program some of whom are just fans who are there. I've seen reports of some fans like
not from the US or UK kind of going there. There's an Indonesian fan there I think.
There's people there from the Uganda bid. I think there are people there from Saudi Arabia as well.
Plus the head of wetter workshop. He's gone all the way from the New Zealand.
Yeah he probably didn't have quite such a tight timetable New Zealanders me.
I mean that seems bizarre but. We know Gillian Pollack did a online program item I believe
for Chengdu and I don't know I assume other people did as well. I assume it wasn't just Gillian
although you know yeah we know it would work. If you are listening and you did please write in
because it would be very fascinating to hear how those went from the horse's mouth. Yeah well
what happened to Lucianco in the end? Was he just kind of there and hanging out? No one knows.
Don't think he's there? Like he seems to have been massively downplayed and yeah I'm not sure
if he is there but I don't understand why you'd uninvite him without announcing you'd uninvited him.
I mean it may just have been logistical difficulties and actually maybe he just literally could not
attend because he cannot get there. I watched some of the replay videos of the opening ceremony which
are on YouTube which are worth watching and I think there is one where they list all the guests
and he's not listed as a guest so maybe they just decide they had to drop him because he couldn't make
it. Maybe maybe yeah fair enough very strange well I mean not very strange but notable.
So the other thing that people have been posting pictures of is pandas because they've got to see
pandas what they really check do which is quite good and don't you aren't you really looking
forward to the pictures of everyone who goes to Glasgow and takes pictures with the haggis in the
same way. Oh that'll be adorable. I mean they have to do a bit of work because they actually have to go
up to Loch Ness and then they have to go and hide out on the mountain with their bait. Yep yep yep
I'm sure some of them will be up for that because it's not like pandas in like a
the pandas are in a big preservation thing whereas when they go to Glasgow they're going to have to go
out at twilight into the wild yeah to get there yeah to get pictures of wild haggis so it's a bit
harder because they're crepposcular they are crepposcular but also I'm just looking forward to the
Hugo Award rocket base having the tiny haggis mascot on it. Okay so so you heard it at first it's
gonna be it's gonna be a haggis but because haggis have two long legs and two short legs is everyone
knows this right? Yeah yeah exactly yeah. So haggis is a lot they're designed for mountains so they have
two long legs and two short legs so so the the hot because the base is going to be shaped like a
haggis the the hugos go to be offered a jaunty angle because because the haggis bit lopsided
but it'll be fine if you put your Hugo on a mountain when you win it or maybe the haggis is running
around the Hugo. Oh or scaling the Hugo they kind of like a series of Esther can you write in and let us
know when the base design competition starts because I believe we're going to want to submit one yeah
because we've got one we've got one we've got a plan little talking little ton haggis is going
up side of the Hugo with crampons. Do we want to talk about the business meeting? What happened
at the business? Hang on no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no no
badliss. So we didn't have an episode where I could talk about it but there were quite a lot
of amendments on the agenda for Chengdu. I'm just loading them so I can have a look. Where's my
amendment for all Hugo designs should incorporate a funny animal? Can I have that next year? Yeah so
there were tons of amendments we don't actually have a report on everything that pasten failed so
it's I'm going to have to wait to give a full report but according to file 770 they did pass a
few things they ratified the ones that were up for amendment which is the 0% solution and best
game and interactive work apparently so yes we'll have a best game Hugo from next year. Good!
And also we will no longer no award a category if it's on a 25% of the total which I think we were
in favor of. Yes please. So that's pretty good. Was there anything that wasn't ratified Liz?
So those are only things that were for ratification but then there were things that were like this
year's business. So there was nothing that passed at Chicago that needed ratifying that wasn't
ratified. I don't think so because there were only two things that were passed on and they both
passed. Nice okay cool cool cool. And then there was a bunch of new business some of which appears to
have passed on some of which I don't know yet because we don't have a report from the
appropriate business meeting so probably we'll before then but it looks like they've referred
to committee the one about whether you should be paid for fan casts or whether that should disqualify
you basically. What is clear is that there's a lot of people who have taken the opportunity to
propose constitutional amendments because the World Congress in China and this is their year when
they can propose constitutional amendments and some of them I think do make sense and some of them
it kind of depends do you think that fan casts should be analogous to fanzine or do you think
fan cast should be analogous to kind of both fanzine and semi-prozine in terms of its limits of
professionalism? Yeah I think the wussfuss nerds would say that this has been gone over endlessly
including at the point where the category was developed. Yeah but I don't think you can blame
people for saying it's weird that fan cast is different from fanzine and we should make them
the same when kind of all the debate took place 10 years ago at a business meeting they weren't at.
Yeah and also I think this has largely been answered by the fact that escape pod, pod castel and
writing excuses all got nominated in categories that weren't fan cast and so my argument would be
that the way the hughos have been treating these is very much in the sense of fan cast is the equivalent
of fanzine and if you are doing a semi-prozine in audio it goes in semi-prozine and if you are
doing a professional podcast it goes in best related work. So my gut feeling is we should respect
the voters and codify that in the constitution so that it continues forward and I think that is
usually my opinion about the hughos. I'm usually of the opinion that if that if the voters are
treating something in a certain way it should be codified with the very very strong exception
that I don't think conventions belong on hughos finalist lists and I would be quite happy if
that never happened ever again. Yeah well it looks like that runs the committee for more discussion
which actually feels like a sensible way to do it because I think there is some discussion to be
had there and also you don't want to make it so strict that if your podcast has you know a patreon
that gets you a couple hundred quid a year that you spend on hosting a microphone like that shouldn't
automatically make you a semi-professional podcast but as is written maybe you can't get any money
at all. Anyway that is up for discussion they failed to pass one for best young writer this was
a proposal for basically a new category for writers age between 15 and 24 which hasn't been passed on.
Firstly that's just ageist because people can come to writing a later in life and that is okay
and secondly we have an award for new writers already we have a sounding yes we have an award for
new writers and this was specifically you know the person proposed it said it's a try and encourage
young writers in their creative endeavors which is fine but they'll do it some other way that's
not a hugho and then the other thing that passed is there were two basically conflicting proposals
for what you put on site selection ballot and they have passed a slightly more restrictive one
which basically means you have to have now a postal address and it's mandatory and if you
don't put a postal address in it may be a no preference ballot. Interesting. It doesn't explicitly
say what a postal address in the other amendment said it should be addressed including at least
country and province/state but then otherwise left it as is so you wouldn't have to put a full
postal address in. So I interpret this to mean that site selection will now require people to put
their full street address on the site selection ballot which is the situation that came up a
couple of years ago during the vote for Chengdu. I don't know if I have a I think about whether
I have a strong opinion about that it just seems like fiddling but yeah. I have a fairly strong
opinion on it which is that it's it's of parochial. It just doesn't take account of the way the
world works. Lots and lots of people don't have addresses that a street address is including
incidentally many people who are traditional voters of for the WorldCom because they have
post office boxes and they aren't going to put their post office boxes they're just thinking that
their post office boxes are street address which is not they mean post they think postal address.
But it doesn't specify didn't specify what a postal address is so I assume it can mean
wherever you would get post. Yeah so the point is that in lots of places you don't get post in the
way that you think about it if you come from a western world in which post is delivered in the
way it's delivered in Britain right? Yeah no no no no I appreciate that. Lots of places deliver
post to your name and a bursi at the village shop essentially. But then that would count on the ballot.
Yeah potentially that would count as a postal address. I think that's an argument you can have later.
Yeah maybe it would count as the postal address rather than a street address so so some of these
things have asked for a street address and that is hard because lots of places don't have those lots
of people don't have those. It did need clarifying because it just said address so it hadn't been
updated since we invented the email address basically and this has never previously been a problem
and it has come up as a problem so I agree with clarifying it but I guess you know maybe they need
to include what is an example of a valid postal address and I so I felt like the one that was just
like at least put like your country in province in maybe was clarifying that better because then
you could say okay it's got a province and a country it's an address so I don't know if this will now
basically leave it to site selection administrators to determine what counts as a valid postal address
and potentially leave us with more problems but that's the one that passed so there we go.
I will go on record as saying that if a site selection administrator disqualified a ballot for
a postal address that is a completely like crombulent like one of those in whatever country the vote
was for I'd be very angry so we're like if you know if you are a decision where your postal address
is effectively given to Bertie at the village shop and the site selection administrator got angry
I'd be like well that's just parochial nonsense. We'll see. I guess my point is it doesn't seem like
it's solving a problem it just seems like it's being driven by the wussfus nerds need to categorize
and I'm not wholly behind constitutional amendments that I feel are being driven primarily by a
desire for neatness rather than a desire to actually address problems which but that is a take I guess
which you go ahead and have your takes done. Oh thanks Liz. I'm happy about Best Game and I
can nominate things for Best Game. Have you seen Don Eastlake's report on the main business meeting
from the wussfus business meeting Facebook group? No I don't really go on Facebook very often. No
not on the wussfus business meeting group. Right so that's included independent films has moved
up the agenda amended to add sun setting and past. Oh god yes yes this is what I was getting to
which is the independent film were moved up and was passed so if that is ratified next year that
adds two new hugos. I will be going to the Glasgow business meeting and voting against
ratification. Yeah don't it's got zero chance of getting ratified I would have thought I think
there'd be actual pitchforks. In theory I don't mind the idea of a category that tries to represent
represents things that are not massive TV shows and massive blockbuster movies and like indeed I
have some sympathy for that but I think the way you do it is firstly run a trial category so you
ask Glasgow please could you use your special hugo to run this category and see if it works because
putting a hugo on the ballot without the test is insane and then secondly you consult with the
community you don't just spring it on people like I am not against the category in principle but
even I will be voting against ratification because like and I will be encouraging lots of people to
come with me because I'm like you don't know if this is going to work like the game hugo was
carefully crafted over years and like that's on the ballot and that's how it should be done. Sorry
but also this is a this is a this carves independent because we have a general rule of not having
one thing eligible for multiple hugos this carves independent films out of the hugos
out of the best dramatic pro inflation long form so it's it's incredibly controversial in the same
way that the load star was and it's gonna take if you want to have something like that it's
gonna take decades to get it sorted or at least a decade and also everything everywhere all at
once is won you know it's it's definitely definitely or the indecided happened to be a massive blockbuster
but there was no reason to expect that to be the case. How do they define independent film Liz?
I don't think this is particularly worth discussing how they define it but what I would say is we
have complained a lot on this podcast about the business meeting and how difficult it is to
figure out what's going on at the business meeting and how difficult it is to work out what's going
on so when this amendment is brought by two Chinese members of the world con a world con which seems
to have had a ton of stuff about like independent films and small films in the film industry
generally it may just be they thought the best way to get people discussing it was to put it
forward as an amendment it's hard to know kind of from the outside exactly how much work went into
best game yeah no that is fair to get it up there and how many years that took so I'm gonna give
them a pass I mean I think they're gonna probably fail to be ratified I just think it's people
saying well this is the things we're interested in can we have an award for them and if you don't
you know spend a lot of time reading business meeting minutes then probably you think that's
the best way to get them get them on the agenda because maybe it isn't other places but it turns
out if there was a best way to get something passed is basically now to build you know spend a lot
of time building support before you actually bring it to the business meeting which is not
immediately obvious if it's just like would you like to pro some business send us an email I'm
not opposed to the two people who brought the amendment I will say and there was a little baby
faced Cox and who brought an amendment to Chicago 2012 Chai Khan 7 with Emily Arrow I think
reporting a best very short category for dramatic presentation because we wanted to see more
short films get hoo-hoo's so like I genuinely am sympathetic to this the thing that annoys me is
that they passed it yeah like I'm not disappointed with the two uh proposals I'm disappointed with
literally everyone else in the room there weren't that many people in the room maybe 40 and that
might have included quite a few Chinese fans who had never had any previous experience with the
business meeting when this opens up a really big can of worms right which is like if the Chinese
fans got one thing through an iO Western fan I'm like boo is that good of me but equally I really
don't think this is a category we need but also this is why you want to have online presence at
your business meeting so you do in fact have a permanent group of people are interested in this
I can come in from everywhere so hmm maybe this is the best argument for actually sorting that
problem out which is do you want best independent film hoo-hoo's because that's how you get best
independent film hoo-hoo's is it called best independent film or is it called best dramatic
presentation independent it's called is best independent short film award and best independent
feature film award there are two oh yeah there's two soon there'll be more hugos than cacopos
now i'm transitioned to thinking this is very funny and if we can get a ratified that increases
the number of hugos by three in three years and and that would be that would really like if if
if that makes people angry enough to sort out online participation with the business meeting
which I repeat should be a doggle uh then we can just do this and that'll be good but they're
trying to actively prevent it they're actually going further in the other direction so you know
everyone go to the business meeting at Glasgow and propose to ratify have you reversed your
position completely in the last five minutes of the podcast because if you have yes because if
ratifying these two makes the nerds angry enough that they finally open up the business meeting online
that is a concrete win no they won't no no they won't and then and then we just propose ever more
bizarre things when the world comes not in North America best fresh language film
yes when it's in nieced best film involving a man who surfs and lives in a landlocked city
yeah okay anyway thank you for bringing this to our attention Liz this is sparking lots of joy
convention time bracket was amended to replace preferably between first august to the 30th of
september we and past as amended that's just to say no more discons isn't it no more christmas
worldcon well I think this come would have been all right because it's not quite that late but
yeah it's all kind of like it's it's nitpicking things and cleaning them up yeah I mean there are
other things that passed some of which are quite sensible basically the thing about works appearing
in a language other english being eligible um in the year its first issued in english has been
tweaked because it makes more sense to not say english but say the language of the convention
that year because otherwise you kind of block I think this would actually have blocked some
things which came out in translation but came out you know in in in tina in a particular year like
there was some edge case that they wanted to fix and it sounds like this went to committee and
they did something sensible and that and they fixed it so we'll go with that does it basically
add the language of the hosting convention and english or is it does it replace english with
the language of the hosting convention it replaces english with the language of the countries of
the administering and previous year worldcon and here it is just today translated to a main
language of the country the ministry in previous year worldcon I think it covers things that were
published in english and then translated into chinese not being eligible in the year they could
be read by them what what it means is so like obviously this year it would have been fine the
thing i would say would have been fine because it went chicago chenghu so that's english and chinese
what it would mean is that if last year it had been held in france and this year was in chenghu
any chinese language science fiction that had only just been translated into english wouldn't
have been eligible and that feels like a shame to me because a lot of the voters are still reading
in english and so i do think that building in support for works which are translated into
english in the year of the worldcon does make more international works eligible for the award
which i think probably benefit international science fiction more than removing that does
so from the perspective of having more international stuff on the ballot i kind of wish they hadn't
gone that way but maybe i'm wrong i don't know it's a very nitpicky point because it will
i think i haven't i think i haven't quite got my head around this because it changes the language
requirement but also changes the works immediately published outside the usa to
countries of the ministering and previous it will come again i think i'll need to
really sit down and think about it that's interesting yeah because that means that like
if something had been published in if it had been london then chengdu well and it's about to be
chengdu then glasgo so anything that's published in the us for the first time in 2024 won't be eligible
and it would used to have been if this would if this had already been ratified so i i think
this is a well-meaning amendment that on the face of it seeks to make the constitution less
parochial but i think will probably actually make it more parochial by by basically meaning that
a america fans can't vote for things that haven't made it big in america yet i think it's designing
language for the worldcon we wish we had rather than the worldcon we actually have and i think
that's very laudable but this all still just gives stuff an extra year of eligibility it doesn't
mean it's not eligible it just gives it an extra year based on slightly different criteria right
i think maybe we should hold this over and really i need to think about the different you know this
was published here in this year in this situation and we can discuss that asfic another time asfic
can fuck off that's my opinion yeah i just like the idea of it be called asfic well because i do
want to say i think ispania is right about asfic it's time for ispania's opinion
dah dah dah dah dah dah jingle ispania has always pointed out the reason that nazphic is codified
in the waspus constitution is that if the worldcon is held outside the us and that means that the
main convention which is often held in the us is not in the us that incentivizes us fans to vote
against foreign world cons and the reason that nazphic is in the constitution is so that you don't
have an incentive for north american fans to vote against non-north american world cons and so that
provision is there mostly to encourage there to be world cons outside north america which is another
example of how what looks like on the face of it a pro-keel provision in the constitution is actually
acting to try to make the organization less pro-keel if we had like a truly egalitarian society we
wouldn't need any of our affirmative action policies because all of the jobs would go to the best
people regardless of like gender or ethnicity but because we do not have a truly egalitarian
society we have to have lots of very tedious things that like try and make it more egalitarian
yes so you're saying that american fandom is even more pro-keel than we had thought
no i'm i'm saying i'm saying that you need to incentivize the behavior you want to see in your
society i think not incentivizing that and crossing your fingers you get it anyway is a bad way of
going about these things no that's often fine but i mean if you're saying that the reason the
nazphic is encoded is embodied in the constitution is to discourage american fans from voting against
foreign world cons which they would do otherwise um that's basically saying oh we accept that american
fandom is ossley xenophobic and we've had to do something to deal with it no that's that's bullshit
you told me you weren't going to see janelle mene and manchester because you couldn't be
asked to go to manchester and she should play in london thank you it is exactly the same thing
people tend to go to things they can go to and voting for the thing you can go to or the thing
you can't i don't think it's unfair to vote for the thing you can go to for much the same way
that if there's like well i mean firstly there's vanished been vanishingly few eastercoms in whales
on northern island which is partly due to venues but also partly because there are bugger for most
eastercom attendees to get to it's 100% to do with venues and zero potential you know lots of people
have tried this multiple times it is not 100 to 0 i will guarantee you that i so put it this way
if they ever said let's have the eastercon at the um at that hotel that novicon uses i would vote
against it because i don't want to have to go to buckston because it's ages away and i don't think
that makes me xenophobic i think incentivizing the behaviors you want to see is sensible do we think
the nazvik really incentivizes people anymore well no i don't think it does nail but i definitely
think there was a period for a long time where that did work in the right way and so it might be
time now to get rid of it but i think a lot of the discussion about this ignores ignores how
things used to be and how they have changed for the better um but i do i do think having metrics
like the constitution has always sought to make sure that the constitution can't just stay
so sorry that the convention can't just stay in one place and that it has to travel and i think
the nazvik is part of that attempt to force it to travel and so like i'm not saying it should
still be there because i do think at this point the world con has become properly i mean maybe this
is just my bias as like someone who's only come into it sort of in the last sort of 15 years but
it seems to me like it's much more international that was like in the past and i would be surprised
if that went backwards again and i think it's probably slightly more fragile when you think i think
the cost of getting around the world is going to shock a lot of people over the next few years
klaska is going to be a real wake-up call well that's the other thing right as as travel was getting
cheaper i think the nazvik became less and less relevant but now now travel is getting more
expensive again post pandemic i do wonder whether you're right and it's often very it's very alluring
i think to think oh i've won the argument i can stop worrying about this but so in general i don't
support the waspus implementing asvick because i think it's cultural appropriation that wouldn't
do anything to help the world travel worldwide which is but that that's to say that's not in contrast
with my opinion that likes the fact the nazvik is in the constitution i actually do think it might
be important that the nazvik is properly codified in the constitution despite the fact it looks
pro-kill and and that's why i have that opinion about the previous thing liz was talking about was
because i also wonder whether that's something that looks pro-kill but removing it will actually
work in the opposite way to what people think it will and this is something that worries me
sometimes when we have these these discussions i think hopefully that's all useful and reasonable
insight and not just the wafflings of a lunatic could go either way though couldn't it
i think we should do asvick at a different time asvick asvick nazvik and also it's got changed so i
think we should yeah probably hold over some of this until we can properly discuss it so it might
have been a bit of a waste of time but just because i think there'll be a full business meeting
report an asvick is now like also generalized to regional stuff not just ajour anymore but i can
see why again i can see why someone submitted it you're like why is there a nazvik why does a nazvik
exist why don't we have one no yeah no exactly exactly yeah i i think that's right i i think
this could be a long discussion yes we we will come back to this on future episodes listeners
if you have opinions right in yeah um somebody something else that people have said on
about apodcasters that we talk about world cons way too much so that's the thing we did just have
one well i mean it's difficult it's it i mean that's a difficult criticism to respond to the
episode that happened right after world con isn't it i haven't even done hugo stats yet because we
don't have the hugos that's it yeah i did we can't do hugo stats the one thing i did want to do that
we haven't mentioned yet is site selection voting because they were 168 ballots cast wow yeah that's
not many it's not knowing we were some contestants and no one could be bothered when also it was
really hard to vote that's not why it was it was no harder than usual to vote from like well it was
harder than it was harder than in the years that they've managed to implement online voting but it
wasn't i'd say it was easier than the health sinky vote which is only about well eight years ago
that was hard vote yeah but there was a reason to vote for health sinky because it was yeah multi-way
contested i guess what i mean is it's an uncontested year and it was harder to vote than it could have
been and i it's slightly harder than it could have been pdf scribbling a pdf to send it to hell
and Montgomery i think was the way you think who then printed off your ballot without looking at it
and put it in a sealed envelope and took it to China with her um yes and the face palm emoji you have
just demonstrated is how i feel about this i don't know that wasn't a face palm that was me pretending
to be Helen covering my eyes as i was printing out the ballots don't look don't look don't look
but in fact i voted i very have to say that i voted for Seattle what do you think it was though
Alison Seattle was not offering a discount for voters which is why the vote count is so low had i
known that i would not have voted so there we go i feel like i put a lot of work into voting that was
not a lot of work but slightly more work than maybe necessary into voting that that wasn't really
very much rewarded and they did it because they thought that generating a vote would involve
giving people's details to China and some people didn't want to do that so they made a direct decision
i believe not to have a voting discount you couldn't because you had to get a membership in Chengdu
to buy the site section token but i wonder whether they could have solved it by saying we'll offer a
voting discount or a pre-support discount i wonder if they could have sold like some pre-support tier
which converted into a supporting membership in the same way that a vote would have done
because the thing is that i guess the reason i say that is that they're not they don't have
much money then like what's 185 times 20 like i i think if i was them i would have thought quite
carefully about how i was going to replace that revenue stream because it doesn't seem like an
obviously good thing to incentivize people not to join so i might have thought about how to
incentivize people to join but you know i've never run a world con so who knows a lot of people
will join now right and also i'm a sucker who voted i did not vote i think people will join now
but also there have been issues with getting like pre-supports and money around to because of
tend to get them into Chengdu right and they had to set up like a holding company in the US so
it may be that all the finances are just weird and also that some pass along that couldn't get to
Chengdu because of logistical issues may now pass on to Glasgow and Seattle it might be that they
know what they're doing and they've got new branding which is no longer which is no longer
riffing off a major corporations logo that's probably a good a good thing yeah i mean i did like the
it was cute yeah i would say it's time for it's time for his spani is opinion
da da da da jingle um so his family was happy about the guests of honor she says Bridget Landry
is a good value space and cosplay guest and is a regular at los cons and Alexander James Adams
is a bay con uh was a bay con guest and is a noted fillker apparently so she is very excited for both
of those people um the other guests are nissy shawl k-tempoest bradford denato jian cola and
martha wells so it does seem like a good seems like a good ballad something for everyone perhaps
um i'm excited about you know quite a few of those guests so who are and i might go to Seattle because
i like Seattle although i might also not because i might be poor we'll see
and now it's time for picks uh it's been ages since we did our last picks uh i think you're both
agree so i am going to pick i'm going to pick a movie i'm going to pick the movie halloween
by john carpenter which i watched for the first time so this is a slightly delayed
belated pick but this is the first episode post halloween uh so it seems relevant
it's fanny and i have a rule that during october all of the films we watch have to be horror so
we went to watch for friday the 13th on friday the 13th which was great and then we watch halloween
halloween is amazing a young jamelee kurtis absolutely smashing it out of the park uh in every way
genuinely scary and unsettling just yeah really enjoyed it and i also enjoyed the trivia that
ispania delighted in telling me that the mask that the main antagonist wears uh was basically
the cheapest mask they could find at the local um store spray painted white and it turns out the
cheapest mask was a william shatnam mask so under his terrifying visage there is a terrifying
visage good good movie uh obviously not if you don't like horror but john carpenter um just
obviously a fantastic director and uh really good really good film we watched it on lion's
gate plus oh god is that another thing to subscribe to yeah we only survived for a month we tried
watching on pluto tv but firstly it had adverts and i don't know if you know this adverts detract
from the sense of terror in a horror movie like you know premiere in and it's like that is quite
terrifying but not in the same way uh and also there were no subtitles and uh and i really i was
willing to pay five pounds to be able to work out what the dialogue was uh because for those who
don't listen regularly i am slightly deaf i like a good premiere here i put one for glasco no
premiere ends are good it was a cheap joke i am also in a premiere in for glasco cheap joke at
the expense of premiering are we all in the same premiere in for glasco i think the premiere in
a gla yeah basically liz allison and i have a rule that whatever hotel we stay in for a convention
must match the octa thought logo and so we are all obviously in the premiere in which is naturally
purple how did the heart regency how did the heart regency match the octa thought logo i spray
baneid it purple oh that explains it don't worry boo i got you john is just making a
cheap joke a cheap joke a lot of them today um liz what's your pick my pick is a tv show that i
largely watched on a plane just breaking allison sort of watching things on planes uh it is poker
face starring natechelyon and created by natechelyon and ryan johnson of you know glass onion fame etc
um it's really good what streaming services at all i was on it was on a plane
i will do a google but i think the answer might be yarr
i really wanted to watch this because because natechelyon is like a murder mystery series about
a woman who has a psychic ability right liz yeah she knows when people are lying nice which is
great but she's essentially like she's not operating you know as a law enforcement officer
anything she's basically operating i don't want to give too many spoilers but basically she's
operating outside this and trying not to attract the attention of law enforcement and also it's
really clever with how it uses a gift because she can't literally go up to people a lot the time
and say oh you're lying or you know sometimes she picks people up because they've done like a trivial
lie and sometimes people do trivial white lies for all kinds of reasons but sometimes they're
doing a trivial lie because it's actually covering up that they committed a murder and it spends a
lot of time in each episode kind of setting up the other characters in the show around
a tashley aunt she's basically a different place every week and it's setting up kind of that that
weeks cast and and murderer and murder victim and supporting cast and they're all really great and
there's some amazing like guest actors in there as well i'm looking at like the list of
Wikipedia Ron Perlman, John Ratzenberger, who's the other one i saw that i thought was great,
Nick Noltee, Joseph Gordon Levitt, like yeah that is some Rhea Perlman who doesn't get enough work
Tim Blake Nelson, yes! Jamey Lidrimet, I'm going to stop reading names now Liz and let you get
back to your segment. I am also going to say for the benefit of listeners sky, sky and now tv
is how you can watch it in the UK. So for that month that you decide it's worth taking now tv
that's the thing to watch. And there's 10 episodes all about an hour long there is a kind of overarching
plot in kind of that you know the last episode refers back to the first and sets it up for like
the next series i think there will be a future series yeah you should just go and watch it it's
good. Yeah the tashley aunts very good. Alison, at the time of release you're back from your
golf trip you've had loads of time to watch films and movies what's your pick? My pick this week is
New Zealand. Hey! New Zealand is a country it's it's very attractive it's full of
lovely and interesting wildlife and lovely people and you should definitely go there and visit there
and i was there for about 10 days and i had a brilliant time and i would strongly recommend
New Zealand yes um do i need to say any more about it it's on the other side of the world it's
quite a bit to get to unless you're already in New Zealand in which case it's right there.
Yeah but in that case we really are fansplaining to New Zealanders about New Zealand aren't we?
Like have you heard of this place called New Zealand? Yeah yeah it's good.
At some point there will be more reportage of New Zealand after i've had some sleep.
So at the moment my all my reportage is in like huge piles of notes most of which have been delivered
in in the form of text to Claire Bralley and also some to my husband and to other people.
I don't know John, have I texted you at all? Probably not much. People have had a few texts
and and i've got to collect all this stuff. I've been trying not to text you too much because i'm
worried i'm interrupting your lovely time. You won't because i just i just only look at my phone
but i have time to it's all right. That's fair. As Alison said last episode there's nothing quite
i've never done anything before since that was quite like my TAFT trip and it is the only people
who really get it. I think other people who have done it. I should say that i have not found a life
partner on this guff trip i just want to make this clear. I mean Stephen's going to be given that
you were with Stephen for three weeks. I took one with me. We had one day off
Stephen travel with me for three weeks. We had one day off guff where we kind of sat around
circular key and at dinner with like the the Sydney Opera House and the and the Harbor Bridge and
and kind of said how we'll celebrate our 25th wedding anniversary because fun fact our actual
25th wedding anniversary is tomorrow we're going to be well it's today now apparently but not for him.
We're going to be 12,000 miles apart which is almost as far apart as you can get without
actually going off planet and that was the Octa Thought podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod in Com
[Silence]