[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome to the 91st episode of Octa Thorpe, a podcast for Science Fiction
and Science Fiction Founder which is coming to you on the 31st of August, 2023. I'm John
Coxin. I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty. And we have some letters of comment for you
all. We got some letters of comment. First off we got letters about, oh no yeah we got
letters from Chris Garcia and Abigail and it turns out that Chris Garcia and Abigail
Nussbaum are going to have to have a cage fight. Oh that sounds good. This is news to
both of them. But we basically got various letters about AI. Thank you everyone who wrote
in about that. Chris says he's looking forward to Asteroid C and Abigail said that Liz would
not succeed in baiting her with praise for the last blade priest. So your attempt to
hook an Abigail has failed Liz. Well has it failed or did she write a letter? See because
I was like it's a bold move to put a PS about not being baited at the start of the successful
reeling in. I think it is a bold move. I think Liz has caught and that's a fishing trip that's
gone well for you Liz. Yeah to be fair to Abigail she has read other things on the kitschy's
red tentacle shortlist and I have not so I can't say if they're better and for I know they may
well they may well be better but I still enjoyed it so they're... She also explains that sub-length
that I was being to one note about Luddites. So I think when I talk about Luddites I do know
something of the history so I was including the fact that the Luddites weren't totally
daft about their protests. It was it was reasonable. I still think they're wrong and Abigail thinks
they're totally reasonable which is fine. I think we can we can have differing opinions.
Laurie Anderson also says "Hugok to Thorpe girl" so that's good. Liz has done a thumbs up and a
triumphant facial expression Laurie so um... I mean I can't hug them because on the other side
of the planet but you know metaphorically. Yes. I still haven't got over the fact that she's
Laurie Anderson. I just want to go oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh every time. I assume that's referencing
something I am too young to know about. Yeah yeah it's a superman. I see.
Alison will provide links for the show notes. No I found a link that's actually uh huh huh.
Well there's there's a joke for all of our older listeners. We have plenty of older listeners.
I'm gonna clip I'm gonna clip that out. That might be a useful thing to have all the self-force.
Just it might be useful if I have a button that I compressed that just says in Liz's voice there's
a joke for our older listeners. I can be useful at conventions. Okay guys look you don't have to
remind me of my impending senility all of the time. What we've done here listeners is we've kept
strictly on topic and we've not digressed so that's good. Right then we did get letters about
six wakes. We heard from Christopher J Garcia. We heard from Laurie Anderson. We heard from
Edward Moreland and then we heard from Ali Brooke, Ali Baker Brooks and David Curry about
problems they have with the representation of their expertise in culture. So yes I think it's fair
to say that some people like the book and some people didn't. You've just summarized the whole
episode, child. Why are you gonna be bothered by this? But I did hear from at least two people who did
who had not read the book, who did then really enjoy it. So I was glad because even if you read
it and you hated it I'm very sorry to you but if you read it and you loved it, hooray hello.
Yeah Emily January really liked it so that was she read it because of our episode and she really
liked it and I was like *sigh* and also having just finished the spare man this is a spoiler for
a Hugo episode. I actually need to make this joke in the Hugo episode which is I think I may just
not like books with food bridges in them. Fair enough. Fair enough.
Shall we talk about the Clark Award? Yes, we can talk about the Clark Award.
On the topic of books, so the Clark Award was awarded.
Liz do you want to tell us about this? So the Clark Award was awarded this year
in a nice ceremony that I did not attend that was in the UK. Do we want to explain what the
Clark Award is for our new reviewers? New listeners. Oh I suppose I could do that. So
the Arthsee Clark Award is an award for the best science fiction novel first published in the UK.
It's been running for, ooh I don't know how long it's been for now since about 1987 I think
and it's a Judgement Award, a jury award, so there's a jury which is made up of judges from the British
Science Fiction Association, the Science Fiction Foundation and currently the Sci-Fi London Film
Festival. And so these judges read nearly every single science fiction novel published in the UK
in a year. They do have to be submitted so of course for publishers who don't submit them but
generally they're getting a submission list of kind of up to 100 books and then they pick a
shortlist of six and then they get together and pick a winner. And the winner is, it has been
announced previously I think earlier in the year kind of in May or June when that was when the
Sci-Fi London Film Festival was but this year it was announced in August and the winner was
Venomous Slump Soccer by Ned Bowman as I believe mentioned by John as his sort of stealth pick on
a previous episode. But as it happens I managed to read all of the Clark shortlist before although I
did not read every single one of them before the award was announced I fell slightly short.
Were you on a long intercontinental holiday involving a lot of reading Liz?
I did go on a long intercontinental holiday involving a lot of reading which is why I've read
about 20 books since our last episode so I've got lots of material for picks now really maybe for
the rest of the year. And so I did read I think I read three or four of them while on that holiday
which was very nice thank you to Neil Harrison who lent me all of those and then I read the other
two myself and yeah I would. So the Clark award always comes up with a shortlist where I don't know
it's interesting because there's usually some overlap with other awards but quite often there
will be kind of some left field books quite often ones that were published by more literary
publishers or not marketed as science fiction quite often something completely out of left field
where I have no idea at all why that book has been nominated. Sometimes it's quite fun because you do
know who the judges are and then you can you know try and wonder what they saw in a book you think
was terrible but I think it usually picks a pretty good book as the winner. And this year I would
agree I really liked Venomous Lumpsucker by Ned Bowman which is about you know the the titular
Venomous Lumpsuckers are a type of fish which you know being studied and maybe more intelligent
than previously thought and this is a big thing because we are in this sort of climate change dystopia
where part of the economy now involves extinction credits and you know paying if you drive a species
extinct and kind of the whole market that would just horribly inevitably spring up around this
like okay so if I was predicted to make 15 species extinct but actually only made 10 extinct do I
now get some some tax credits back for not making them extinct. How do we incentivize companies and
nations not to top down forests? The price of these extinction credits fluctuates which means
there's a kind of really comedy segment where they go to a place where the last known example of a
species is being kept and when the extinction credits weren't worth very much known was really
paying very much attention to it because they didn't get very much money for keeping them alive and
now extinction credits have become extremely expensive and so they're all like yeah we're going to get
lots more money but oh wait some of those species maybe are not quite as alive as we hoped and we
thought no one was checking. It's basically a kind of funny dystopian counterpart to I would say to
Kim Stanley Robinson's Ministry for the future because they're which can kind of posit a sort of you
know different credit system and incentives and things and have them work as intended this is like
how you get all the credits and systems and have them work in a kind of the way you can imagine they
might do under a current capitalist system. So I really enjoyed it. Don did not like it as much
think sorry Dom. My reaction to this is actually very similar to Liz's reaction to six weeks where
I liked the ideas and I thought the execution was quite poor. I think my main problem with it is it's
a book that posits that the UK is completely irrelevant and yet the entire world knows the UK
by a special name and the UK turns out to be pivotal to the plot and it's like you've got a pick one
either we're special or we're not but he kind of has his cake and eats it there. We've been not
doing that for a long time. No I know and I'm like you can't criticize British exceptionalism
while also practicing British exceptionalism that doesn't land for me which I found very frustrating
I'm a bit worried at one because I thought it was okay and I'm a bit worried I'm gonna like all
the others even less. I haven't read the others yet so we'll see. You have read at least one of
them right? Yeah I like the anomaly a lot. I understand why it didn't win but I like the fact it doesn't
commit to an interpretation. It's a very it's on the very literary end of science fiction I think
in that it is much more idea interested in the ideas than the mechanics of the ideas but also
it's a what they called the oh oh hang on if I go to the anomaly to Wikipedia page it will tell me.
From there a Lupien work which is one where you basically firstly it's very French and secondly
it's one where you like adopt faux constraints on your writing as your writing and so like it is
also a literary experiment which I could see some people might have gone with. This is the same
group that like writes books in palindrones or without using the letter E or stuff like that
but I haven't read the others. I've heard mixed reports. I'm looking forward to the coral bones
because I've heard good things about that. I believe that one of the things about the way that the
Clark Award is structured is that the judges always come from very different perspectives so
judges meetings are allegedly extremely angry but kind of they've got a lot of they've got a
they're not angry they're just disappointed. They're disappointed. I think that's individual
judges are in fact disappointed because they come in going one of these books is much better
than all of the others and then and then it turns out that all of the judges believe that but they
are picking different horses. Yeah I mean I enjoyed the anomaly but it is basically like a sort of
I like its sort of character extrapolation stuff of what would actually be the effect on people if
a certain thing happened but it's science fiction feels like it's got the middle bit where it sort
of lays out a bunch of potential science fiction like explanations for why a particular thing has
happened that just feels like a big info dump in the middle of the novel in a way which I wasn't
very interested in. It has the same problem as six weeks that Edward Moreland was annoyed by
which is the other problem it has is that all of the people from the religions basically agree
and Edward Moreland says that he feels that this is unrealistic. I think it is but I think that I
feel part of the problem there is if you try to do a realistic take-off all the religions would do
in reaction to certain very difficult uh ecumenical questions that that would be and you'd end up
wearing a 26 novel epic it's a lot to grapple with I could understand why authors don't like doing so
but yeah I mean you're going for plausibility here that they have managed to kind of pick a
representative per religion which would probably be a whole novel in itself of like who would you
pick as a representative for each world religion. It especially has like as someone who grew up in
the church of England like you can't even there's not I mean there's not even just two different
groups in the church of England with opinions like it's fractal right there's disagreements all
the way down. I think that's all true about the anomaly but I think I liked it better than Venomous
Lumpsucker but I still didn't think it was great I thought it was solid. I think that's my main
the 2022 list has so many books that I thought were great on it and the 2023 list is like oh
I was excited and now I'm not so I don't know we'll see maybe after I've read the bar I have a
different opinion. So I would say they break down into the three that I would recommend you read in
this three where I'd say you probably don't need to bother or I was less excited by them and
the anomaly is one of the three I enjoyed along with Venomous Lumpsucker and The Coral Bones by E.J.
Swift and then the other three the Red Skullers Wake by Alette Bodard I already talked about a
few episodes to go there's Plutishine by Lucy Hissick and also Imagine on by Tom Watson and I
would say they're all kind of flawed in one way or another and I would have been a little
disappointed if any of them had one but they didn't so I'm pretty happy with that. I think we
talked about Plutishine at all we talked about Plutishine before I'm surprised it was on the
shortlist and I would have been quite a stylish difficult one it would be a remarkable departure
for the Clark Award judges if it had won. It is interesting because the 2022 shortlist had
two I detested and three I loved and one I thought was okay but I understood why it was the winner
but this one just seemed to be much more it seems to be in many ways a much safer shortlist
I don't think there's anything I will truly detest and I don't think there's anything that
will completely capture me it seemed to be much more kind of regression to the meme
than previous ones and I don't know whether that says something about 2023 or 2022 as a year for
the genre because the other thing is the I mean spoilers for our Hugo book discussion episode
listeners but I think the same could be argued of the Hugo finalists this year as well where I don't
think there's one that really astounded me. A lot of people are saying a lot of people are saying
gosh isn't it a week year for the Hugo shortlist we are if we conclude that we will not be alone
in our thoughts but I've only read two of them so far but I've read two of them that's amazing
yeah no well done well done and the one that I've seen a lot of people say should have been on
these shortlists was the moon day letters which as we previously discussed I liked a lot but I
thought it had flaws I don't think I've read any books that I would give five out of five on good
reads from 2022 yet maybe there's one lurking I just haven't heard about Sea of Tranquility by
Emily Cindre-Mantle oh yeah I haven't read that one yet it is on my it is on my radar as is
I don't give book star ratings really because I kind of think well a lot of books are just kind
of not not a book that's being written for somebody like me but um Sea of Tranquility is
absolutely a book that's being written for people like me and if I gave star ratings I'd
give it a five stars because it's short and thoughtful the other one that I'm looking forward to reading
which I think I will love is the spear cuts through water which I have not yet read yeah you'd love
the Vanish birds I did love the Vanish birds but it was very good people say the spear cuts through
water is better than the Vanish birds I have not read either anyway books in it but I'm glad you
liked I'm glad you liked the numerous love sucker Liz I um yes hoorah and I would just say yes the
final the final book that we because we haven't mentioned it on this podcast at all yet is metronome
by Tom Watson which is very much your literary science fiction pick but two people who have committed
some mysterious crime and their sentence is to live alone on an island or is it and every day
they must take pills that get spent three times a day to keep them alive basically and it's about
what happens when they come up to supposedly the end of their sentence and relief does not arrive
and you learn more about their backstory and why they're on the island and it's fine it just feels
a bit like not very new not to spoil too much but it does turn into a fairly standard dystopian
reason for why these two have been exiled to an island and then it all goes a bit off the rails
at the end I wouldn't recommend seeking out unless you're being a clerk shortlist completist this year
and then on the topic of awards the Hugo voter packet has been released yes so a lot of people
said that they were having a lot of trouble downloading and that was because
Chengdu hadn't sorted its certificates out but they have sorted that all out now and I found it
straightforward to download some of the downloads are huge and I'm you know I always cut slack to
the best graphic story category because if you significantly reduce the size of those files then
you also reduce the quality of the past probably what people really want but there's two enormous
files one of which is I think the episode of the expanse that has been this is a finalist has
been included in full but I wouldn't recommend anybody watch that if they haven't watched the
previous 197 episodes of the expanse or how many have ever been in the hour so I'm not sure what
used the two and a half gigabytes there is for you but in best related work there's a four gigabyte
download that is the uncompressed audiobook of Terry Pratchett A Life with Footnotes by Rob
Wilkins it's narrated by Rob Wilkins and it's lovely to have it in the packet I think that might be a
first supply the audiobook edition as well as the print versions love it but they could probably
have compressed that uncompressed audio is quite big yeah yeah I can see so I can see what they're
going for so I would say also I had a problem downloading the packet at the start because the
links would not automatically open when you clicked on them you had to basically go and open them in
a new tab because the HTTP HTTPS was messed up but I also had some very slow downloads and I'm not
sure why but it meant I actually haven't downloaded best related work yet because
I know it's going to be a slow download and I don't listen to audiobooks so I am thinking look in
future if you're going to have like anything which is or maybe over gig for a certain thing
then make it optional I don't need two and a half gigs of the expanse it's very nice but I've
seen it I don't need no new book I'm never going to listen to and it'd be fine if they were you
know hosted somewhere incredibly fast like previous ones I think have been hosted on Amazon's like
hosting system and I've been very quick to download but these were quite slow and so I don't
want to just sort of sit there downloading a bunch of files I don't need also all the downloads are
called Hugo packet so I have like Hugo packet folders one through 20 or something but on the
contents of the Hugo packet I can link to it but um our occasional correspondent
uh a Sats Culture has put together a page which tells you what is in the voter pack
for all the fiction categories so not for every category but I think just for
the fiction and some of and I think that's dramatic or is it or it might be everything it
might be everything but it basically tells you what you get in there is it a partial version a
complete version pdf e-pub what language is it in and then a few notes and that is quite useful to
see what has been what has been presented in every category you can see that basically you get
complete versions of all the novels but only if you go to netgalley and request one of them and
also some of them are only in pdf and not e-pub which is a tiny bit annoying to me because I
would much rather read things in e-pub and I can't think it is that beneficial to stop piracy to
give me a complete book in pdf but only part of it in e-pub so it seems a bit strange I don't
understand the logic where you put it in pdf and not in e-pub I can understand the logic of not
providing it because you think some of the Hugo electorate might buy it and I guess by putting it
in pdf and not e-pub you think that people who are annoyed enough by pdfs will buy the e-pub instead
but like it just seems very strange to me I don't I really understand the logic and if it is piracy
based that makes even less sense to me because they must be aware these books were already out there
they're out there as soon as they're published like the Hugo's is not how these works are making
it into into the seven seas I mean I would buy the e-book if I thought they were books that if
they were books I would otherwise gonna probably buy anyway then I would go and buy the e-pub but
I think they might be books which I may not otherwise have bought so I'm not going to go straight
out there and buy the e-pubs when I can I can read the pdfs I just prefer to have them in e-pub
so they can go on my e-reader that's exactly it right like I'm gonna read the e-pub I'm gonna read
the pdf and be grumpy I'm not gonna spend money I'm just gonna be grumpy and that seems like the
the weirds you shouldn't want me to be grumpy whatever you read your book I will get it some of
the books you get to the long end of the long extracts and it says do ask for the whole of this
book on netgalley and I have asked for some of these and I have not yet been sent any this is one of
these when I was doing the Hugo packet thing one of the reasons we just like netgalley is that there's
a kind of secret if you are in the US caveat to netgalley because mostly if people are not in the US
the publishers will not give it to you so so you're disenfranchising your non-us photos I don't
I mean I don't like netgalley very much so I don't too much mind the netgalley thing I think the problem
with the netgalley thing is that you can't just log in and make an account now you have to make
an account and fill in your whole profile and say whether you're like a reviewer or what and put
in like the website where you post your reviews like you can't just sign up as a Hugo voter who is
interested in only getting Hugo voter packet things you have to sign up like as a full member
to get it and I did get the one I requested but like it's just quite a lot of extra faff because I
had to basically log in and say oh well I'm a I'm a podcaster and I might podcast it we do in fact
talk about books on our Hugo finalist podcast now so if anyone would like to send me books please
feel free but that's kind of what annoys me about the netgalley thing which is they're like
requests us on that galley and it's like but how if you're just someone who is a Hugo voter and does
not have a broadcast and does not like have a blog where they talk about the books they read
I don't get the impression you're likely to be accepted so they're basically saying if you're
an important member of the community click this button and we'll give it to you but if you're one
of the plebs you can't have it sorry and I'm like the whole point of the Hugo voter packet is it's
good because all the voters get the packet and so I would rather it didn't have this bifurcation
so when we did the packet we basically if people said oh they can ask for netgalley we were like
well you're gonna get up to everyone right and they were like absolutely oh that's good when people
wrote to us and said this has not come through from netgalley which wasn't variably because they
worded to the US we would write back to the publishers and say right you're gonna send him a deep
pub then here's their email address and and I did quite a lot of because one of the reasons that the
Hugo voter packet was a ton of work was that we did quite a lot of managing round the edges
through the Hugo packet help the other thing we did was stick um whatever they ended up download
was over a gigabyte we just stuck it on a streaming site and pointed people at it we're not gonna we
we didn't let people download 4 gigabytes of you know expanse episode I mean I I know that I think
the download should be optional but as someone who always downloads all of the massive things um
I'm quite glad that they uh they are there because I like downloading them so just to say
some of the other things so Vincent Best Novella is there entirely an e-pub which is nice and
therefore I'll probably read that entire category quite excited by that um one story in Best Novelette
has a full Chinese translation one novelt that is uh was in the Chinese languages only available
in in Chinese unfortunately so that's a bit of a shame but in Best Nove's short story it looks like
five out of the six nominees are available in both languages which is very nice so actually
this is this is gonna be really nice I was worried that I would not be able to have any
opinions on some of these categories because of stories I couldn't get to but actually I will
be able to read most of the nominees in these categories I think it's worth saying I think
for once in future the graphic story where volume four has been nominated I think the entire work
is in there and I read the first two volumes while on holiday and pretty enjoyed it so now I'm
gonna read the benefits that he goes and read all the rest everything else in graphic story
seems to be there completely best related work there's a bunch of stuff I guess the only one
where it might be hard to judge is Best Series you get complete works for two of them and for three
of them you have to try and request copies on net galley and for one of them you there are any net
galley requests links so it'll be interesting to see if that has any well I bet we can't really
tell if that has any effect on the voting but I think that is very nice particularly as tiny
spoilers for our Hugo episode but I read uh terms and mirrors known of the ninth and if you have
not read Gideon the ninth and Harrow the ninth I think you will be completely confused by
Nona the ninth so that's going to be an interesting one does having all the material you need in the
Best Series packet help you in best novel if your novel is quite a difficult entry point
John have you read Gideon the ninth and Harrow the ninth yes obviously uh brilliant um
I'm sorry you could be a guinea pig I want someone who hasn't read him to read Nona
it's time for our new segment which is called what does my wife think about the state of the field
of science fiction da da da da da hey jingle it's basically it's fanny was going to read Nona the ninth
because she was very unconvinced by Harrow uh she I think she quite liked Gideon but she did not
really get on with Harrow she went to download Nona the ninth and then she read in the thing this
is the third book in the four book series and she was like no this is not what Best Novel is for this
is why we gave you lot Best Series push off with your series is and this triggered a run and that
made me laugh quite a lot yeah I don't know I don't think Nona Nona didn't I just want half an
hour of his spanias opinions can we just have you recording episode with a spaniel one day
what spaniel thinks about the state of science fiction I think it would be fun yes I only report
the things that I think that will make you laugh there are things that would make you argue with
her and that's where the problem would arise so one of the things that's interesting about the
voter packet is that it's not complete and for example best fan scene where people did submit
uploads to it has not appeared in the packet and there may be more but I'm not sure so it seems
quite strange to me that it's complete in most areas but not in others did one of you just say
there's the whole rivers of London nine books as long as you like PDFs yeah that's what I said
I am I'm on net galley as we speak uh which is bad form I know I shouldn't do these things
but uh I am doing so you know there's that and I am requesting the books but I had to update my
account so I created it before you needed to give them loads of information but they have
basically when you log in they're like oh you have to give us all the information so I am now
listed as john c/media-comer-journalist which is ludicrous yeah I'm a serious book reviewer
there's no option for I just quite like books I think that's what makes me I think that
what makes me a little bit sneer about using net galley which is you shouldn't need to be
anything other than someone who quite likes books to engage with the Hugo voting you should not
need to have an outlet I should not need to give a URL of where I am going to discuss this book
and I understand why net galley does that because it is a book for reviewers to ask for copies of
review books but that is not what the Hugo's there's no there's no implication of a quid pro
pro of like I will read this and might review it in the Hugo packet you read it and might vote for
it so like put it in or don't put it in but the net galley thing is daft imho I'm feeling very
punchy today sorry I'm very opinionated I mean it's a net galley thing because they can
do one of those like watermarked e-pubs that has all my details in or something
I haven't actually opened my net galley one yet but if they did that I guess that would kind of make
sense right like if you buy books or for so books then they're all DRM free and they email them to
you if you go to request short and requires books on net galley you can just download them you
don't actually have to request them they're just there so like if you have been thinking about
reading those they just have a read it link rather than a request access link um so that that and that
I think is that I'm fine with is the requesting bit that I find odd I haven't read those and I
think they're the only ones in best series I haven't read hmm maybe I read one or two Rosemary
room is fine it doesn't take long and it's not like it's not so terrible you throw it across a room
but equally I don't think it's good enough to merit winning an award
site selection uh Liz has written in the show notes
site selection voting has started if you can manage it Liz do you want to talk about that
well I I have not personally tried to vote in site selection because there's only one bid this
year so it's not like they need my vote especially and it seemed like quite a lot of hassle because
all the emails like went into my spam folder I basically interactions with the Chengdu website
are basically oh yeah I'll do them if I have to but they're normally like oh maybe the certificate's
broken or or maybe this page isn't load or oh maybe I can get a reset email for my password but I
can never actually manage to log in in the time the password reset email is actually valid um you
know basically it's with a hassle and so I haven't voted in site selection because
I can't build it but there is one bid it is for Seattle a place I have never been but sounds
quite nice Seattle's amazing um it would be in the brand new expansion to the conference center
in downtown Seattle it hasn't been settled since 1961 it seems like a pretty good bid for a world
con and a pretty interesting place to have a world con and they've got a fun logo which is
presumably as close as you can get to the Starbucks logo without getting sued what a look good on
t-shirts and so you can now vote for it and I also got some emails which said that there would be
like a Q&A session with the Seattle bid unfortunately this Q&A session was held yesterday and I
fished the emails out of my spam bucket this morning but it's the thought that counts right
it's just changing the end of the problem right this is a perfectly reasonable email
but the problem is that the registration link obviously goes through doesn't go straight to
a zoom page something it goes to some kind of like link thing through their email which
presume you used for nefarious purposes and so Google thinks all of them are trying to steal my
information and so they always end up in spam and I just don't regularly tip my spam enough
so I'm very glad it's not a contested bid actually because I think it was a contested bid and people
were having lots of problems logging in and lots of problems paying I think you can only pay using
credit card not like buy check or cash this year but I can't be long let me just check that one
I think this is 2023 right it is 2023 but potentially people don't want to give their credit card
details to a Chinese welcome yes so buy yourself a throw away prepayment card and use that yeah
probably but I mean I've never tried doing that in the US and I don't know who easy is and okay
bit it's a bit different because you've always been able to like hand carry a ballot with some
dollars in it basically if you really wanted to and that year that's not going to be an option
yeah and I think like yeah probably yeah you could say okay we're not going to take any cash
or checks for site selection like I think if Glasgow wanted to say now we are not taking cash
or checks for site selection you have to manage to pay through our online system or at the comm
could announce it now but maybe you need to announce that one a little bit in advance for those people
who don't have credit cards or don't wish to get a credit card but I mean then they get a friend
to pay for them and pay them back presumably there are ways around it and I'm sure they will
figure them out so I guess it's good it's not in a contested bid year but I have not joined it
I'll join Seattle when they actually become the seated bid
[Music]
I need to before I go on my guff trip spoiler for the next section I am going to get a bra
that contains no wire oh yeah get one for traveling you need a wire free bra anyway
it was a pandemic yeah obviously I don't know why I hadn't worked this out before
I just like people feeling my tits in public on the subject of Alison's tits let's talk about
guff what's your guff plans Alison so yes it's happening it's really it's really really
really happening now I have booked almost all of my flights I've booked almost all of my accommodation
though it's all the accommodation is cancelable so if fans come out of the woodwork in the places
where we've where I've ended up booking hotels and say no no no I can put you up do not do not stay
in a hotel there then booked a very exciting train up the east coast of the south island of New
Zealand and I've booked a very exciting ferry across the cook straight which is supposed to be the
best beautiful ferry journey in the world or my New Zealand friends say when the weather is good
which is apparently a bit random but you know I used to live in Scotland I understand this
I have lots of plans to meet up with people if you are in Melbourne, Sydney, Canberra or if you're
going to Conflux which is the Australian netcon Adelaide, Christchurch, Picton or Nelson which is
quite near Picton Wellington Auckland or Perth get in touch I mean not if you're already in touch
because obviously a lot of these things are already sorted but I'll be in all of those places and in
most cases I'll be in those places for long enough that I can be fairly flexible about when I meet up
and I'm very excited by all of this and I've got like side trips and where there's one side trip I
don't want to talk about because it's so exciting that if it happens I'll be like oh I can talk about
it out and I'll go to islands and I'm going to tourist places and I'm going to Faddish
Haultsard I'm going to hear Justin Accroyd singing Acapella music with men
and wow it's just amazing it's gonna be amazing guys it's also going to be incredibly expensive
oh I mean I'm sorry for the person who's going to come north in 2024 because
there's going to be any funds so I guess I'm going to have to start fundraising
massively for that immediately after I get back from the trip
them are them are the rules I mean this is a serious thing I think is that as far as I can tell
flights in the post-COVID flights in this kind of weird semi-post pandemic flights of resumed time
are drastically more expensive than they were in the pre-pandemic era so just for that
basically more we're going to need more fundraising for every every fanist trip
internal flights don't actually seem to have gone up as much as I thought but I think the
actual flight to and from Australia is about it's not quite doubled it's about 80% more than I
thought I was going to have to pay for that flight well when I ran in 2020 and hence because
Stephen's coming with me for three weeks his flight is also his flight's not quite as expensive as
mine because I'm going by one airline to Sydney and I'm coming back by another airline from Perth so
oh yeah that'll get you one of my expensive things about this trip is that it's going to be the
first time we think that a guff delegate has taken a non-stop flight from Australia to the UK so
that's quite exciting oh god that's going to be a long flight do you feel do you like long flights
Alison 17 hours 45 minutes I believe that I am going to test whether it's possible for me to sleep
continuously for 17 hours and 45 minutes and it might be because I mean I kind of look at the
things I've packed into Perth on the grounds that I can sleep when I'm dead or rather when I'm on
an aeroplane for 17 hours and 45 minutes I well I hope it I hope it's a very good trip you're going
to need a squishy bra all I can say I am going to get a squishy bra but also I quite good at sleeping
on Forbes and public transport so I hope it's going to be okay this probably can't go in the
podcast but one way you could raise funds is by auctioning the squishy bra at the end having
not washed it that's disgusting and no and also the squishy bra would have been washed on multiple
occasions during the trip you can't you can't tell me you don't think it might work it could there's
a chance it would it would work I mean you probably can push to the podcast but though I have never
I have never ever ever ever ever ever ever ever you know because I do quite a lot of eBay and
so Alison will you be reporting on your goth trip on you know live journal or twitter or your only
fans I tell you what that is a good way to raise money for the fan funds that is the only fans
with discussion of the exact nature of the squishy bra only fan funds
so shall we do pics yes we're going to make Alison go first on account of how
she's got another non-Sf no pic it's totally a sf no oh hello oh hello come on now yeah no actually
that's that is fair that is fair all right Alison do your very very relevant pic so so my pic is
several crates of unsorted lego which is where my decluttering has got to and I was like I can
take these what I should have done was go I have several I found several unsorted crates of lego
what I should do is put them to us to one side until much later in the decluttering process where I
could then sort out the lego but in fact I went oh lego let me sort it out this will not take it
long and I will generate order out of chaos it has it is it is it is one box of lego what
great lego belonging to one of my offspring one crate of lego belonging to my other offspring
and two castles which I thought were in two separate crates but appear to be in two crates
each of which have bits of each castle in it in that helpful way and also a box or a crate of
bionicle which has never been sorted it was given to us as I was kind of here have a crate of
totally unsorted bionicle and it has stayed in that way and I thought I would generate order
out of chaos but in fact what I have done is generate several slightly smaller heaps of chaos
which is not necessarily a good outcome but I have made one of the castles and and I was like
because it's very straightforward you could buy the bits if there are a few bits missing I will
sort everything out sort of to two sets work out which bits are missing get all the spare bits
profit and it turns out that one of the bits that's missing from this castle is a piece of
hose lego hose that only existed in this castle yep and somebody in Denmark will sell me for 14
pounds that's not happening so I don't know I'm leaving this as a maybe later maybe it'll be
somewhere else if I like my child's bedroom but I think what happens is that although we'd be very
assiduous about not throwing away lego ever a random bit of plastic tube could easily have
got thrown away are you sure that it is hose and it's not hose hose have you considered looking for
any tiny letter o's in lego in your house this foreign listeners is a two ronnie's joke well if
you cut it very fine with a knife because one of my one of my options for this hose is to get
the same hose in roughly the same color and a bit longer and chop a bit off the end of it that
might happen and then when they're like she did this they'll be like there's no proof and they
will direct people to Oxford episode 91 hello future lego police it's good to have you with us
yeah so of course it is science fiction because the castles are from the 2006 to
2008 fantasy castle era of of lego which is fantastic the castle I have built is the dwarf's mine
which is way better than any 40 pound lego set has ever been it's wonderful it's got like
it's got like little tippy crates full of golds that you tip and and many like double-headed
axes and just fantastic stuff Liz you got any lego? I mean not anymore I did have a lot of lego
I'm not entirely sure whether lego ended up I mean it wouldn't have been thrown away right
because yeah no I mean it'll probably have been donated to some younger children who wanted lego
I think oh yeah I had tons very organized filing system as well the lego knight's castle
which is the one that like uses all the iconography for when I was a child is 344 pounds 99 yeah it's
about four times the size of the original knight's castle oh yeah but it's also four times the
and a lot of the new lego they've got a lot of like small little bits but they don't they don't
necessarily have the stuff that's so you know exciting about the about the dwarf mine the dwarf
mine's the dwarf mine's an awesome set um it's amazing how much of it is still there actually
given you know given the fact that it has got things like projectiles sorry Liz I interrupted your
you're about to tell us all about it's all right no I've got I've got distracted by looking
lego pirate ships now yes this is the way yes so one of the problems of this is that I don't feel
I don't really want to give children crates of unsorted lego but also my my offspring feel like
there is probably money in there them their hills and they are probably right even but I'll know
how much money after I finished all the sort of Liz yes oh do you want my pick or I'm gonna talk
about lego yes please you want my pick oh okay so I read a lot of books and now I'm like oh which
ones do I want people to to to use my pick I am gonna go with the mountain in the sea by Ray
Naylor which was a Hugo nominee at the time which was a nebula finalist and also one of those
books where I thought people were thinking it was a nailed on Hugo finalist and it was not
along with Babel or that was even more nailed on so the mountain in the sea is I believe a
debut novel of Ray Naylor and it is about octopuses yay more specifically it is about it's kind of a
book about kind of the nature of intelligence and what it means to be intelligent and what it means
to be conscious in a sort of near future setting a lot of it is set on these Condal Islands which
are set of islands in Vietnam which have now been kind of cordoned off from the world by a large
tech corporation and the scientists get sent to investigate what is essentially an extremely
intelligent octopus species living down there but there's also kind of the nature of artificial
intelligence of AIs it's near future you've got the hacking of AIs you've got human slavery on these
giant fishing ships run by AI that are sailing the seas and it's a bit of a slightly dystopian
future and I quite enjoyed it I think its main floor is it it does feel like someone read a lot of
books on octopuses and was like yeah octopuses they're super cool I'm gonna write a book about
super telling octopuses yay and there's a bit much of that and I'm not quite sure it gets the DNA
and evolution stuff quite right but I mean that is my problem with like all novels with DNA and
evolution as we've been through on the podcast before but it's good enough and yeah I quite
enjoyed it it's a very good start and I would read more by Raynaylor nice I've not heard of that one
so that is interesting is it as good as Agent Tchaikovsky's book about octopuses um no but it is short
and standalone intriguing I mean I do like octopuses so you know that could work anyway now that I've
started reading books I have I have um Paul requested it from the library I guess a lot of these books
are going to come in while I'm in Australia you can always let the lapses expire and then just
re-request them right but yeah but it's 65 pence every time John so you're five pence you
place a hold yeah that's almost when I place a hold for a physical book it's 65 pence online I think
it would I think it would be free if I place the holds at the library on a book that was in
Walthon Forest but I never place holds at the library always place holds online because it's
not really worth 65 p to me to queue up at the library desk and then I should do my pick we're
in the sequence of the year where almost all of the reading I'm doing is for the Hugo episode
and so I have no good recommend it like I have nothing to report there really
realize I picked Lego and I could have picked the world I've left this I've left this for picks
because it's not I guess it's not really directly Oct Thorpe's remit and also I've been accused before
of wanging on for too long about stuff I've read or played under the guise of not picking so this
time I'm going to do it under the guise of picking them so I have played the Spilled Eora's nominees
for 2023 I have not to be fair this is a slight lie because I have not played fun facts because I
cannot find an implementation of it or a copy of it anywhere I can access it which is like you
know it happens but it is very slightly irritating but I have managed to play the other five so I
don't tend to bother with the Kinder Spilled Eora because that's like for younger games and they're
not usually my speed so I have played challenges and Icky and Planet Unknown and then I've also
played Dothromantic and Next Station London Dothromantic and Next Station London were up for the Spiel
and challenges and Icky and Planet Unknown were up for the Kenna Spiel and I enjoyed all of them
actually so Dothromantic is based on a video game which is out for PC and Switch and I actually
think the board game adaptation is better than the video game because the video game is infinite
and you basically just keep going until you fail but the board game is a bit more structured which
I like and I kind of hope they will add a mode to the video game which recreates the way the board
game works because that would be neat I would be interested to play the board game more the
the TTS mode I used to play it does not have the campaign elements in the mod and so I would
call it go to a board game cafe and see like how it unfolds as you can see to use play
because I think that might be quite interesting and Next Station London is a lovely little roll
and write it's very vaguely themed around London like almost non-existently but it's got bright
colours and it's about making trains on a little pad so I liked that one quite a lot that's the game
I played of all the board games I played in 2022 Next Station London is the one I played the most
about 12 times I think it takes about 10 minutes right and you can play five games in a row yep
now those are both true facts I don't neither of those games would be good enough to end up in
my collection I don't think they're both like probably Dothromantic is probably a six and Next
Station London is probably a five like I would play Dothromantic again but I can't see myself
playing it a lot and Next Station London like I'm glad I played it but I probably won't go back
because it's very light I have better role and write so I think Next Station London's on board
game arena and that's a very good way of playing it I was gonna get to that at the end
the other three games are played with Challengers Icky and Planet Unknown Icky has a terrible rule
book but the actual game is lovely my friends really disliked the game because of how bad the
rule book was and this is a salutary lesson in if you are designing a game make sure the rule book
does not make the game feel like a chore to play because I think the core gameplay loop
Icky is really good and I think the rule book does a terrible job of introducing you to it but
it's really nice it's got beautiful art again played that on a tabletop simulator and then Planet
Unknown is fine it's got a lazy Susan and I can't remember what Susan stands for but it's an acronym
and it's something like space utilization sort of system something something anyway and that's
okay it's like a tile playing game into your drafting tiles but where the tiles you can draft
from changes because of the lady Susan and it's kind of interesting but but a lot of plastic and
kind of gimmicky and then finally Challengers which won the Kennespiel and that's a game where
you draft a deck and then you play a tournament with your deck every round but the tournament is
basically you're just turning over the top card of your deck and doing what the card says there's
not really any you're just kind of running your engine and so most of the game is building your
engine and then you run it to see if you've got a better engine than your opponent and that one
and next station London are both on board game arena and so it's really good because once you get
the hang of what's going on it's very easy the problem with board game arena is that unlike with
CTS where you have to read the rules and understand what's happening to manipulate the pieces
board game arena you can just sort of start going and start clicking and sometimes it can be
unclear what is actually happening when you're clicking and this is this is something I think
I think they could stand to address in slightly more detail. This is the Scott Kane family
approach to board game arena so every Tuesday night we pick a game that's not too complicated
and we just start playing and at the point where Stephen is like oh god I have no idea what I'm
supposed to do everyone else rolls their eyes and reads the rule book while they're waiting for him
to play. But anyways yeah good good group of games um good little group of games and and would highly
recommend looking out for them. Challenges might end up in my collection I haven't decided yet but
it is quite an interesting little little game and especially like because I like I've got sushi
go because I like drafting mechanics but obviously like challenges kind of takes the drafting to the
place where like magic has taken it but without needing to know how the game you're drafting for
works. Oh that looks right up our street complexity two out of five plays with four. That was the
thought podcast and it's goodbye for me. It's goodbye for me. It's goodbye for me. Okay and then
we should stop recording and start again. Yes.
[Music]
I started reading the Lewis McMasterful Joel books with cryo-bum.
[Laughter]
Because that was the one that was in the packet and it worked fine. It worked fine.
It's like people get very confused but it's just it turns out most authors don't expect you to have
read literally everything they've ever read in the or written in the order that they wrote it.
No and even when they do part of the job of their editor is to make sure that there are.
So that's that's kind of brilliant actually though I do like it because the thing with I think the
thing with cryo-burn is and I hope I'm thinking the right one. Cryo-burn is basically absolutely fine
but like the long-term fans would read like the last page and cry and Joel would be like yeah.
Yep this is the exact conversation I had with Claire. She was like isn't the last page sad and
I'm like not really. Yeah no the the the last page of cryo-burn is an absolute knife in the gut you know
and it's like and it's like a knife in the gut that you you've been knowing for some books
was gonna come anyway. Actually no so okay so it's time for another segment which is
"My Mum and Dad's approach to Marvel movies."
Da da da da da da da. Hey Jingle um so basically Mum and Dad are going to go see
the Marvels very excited about this they think it looks great. The MCU movies they have seen so far
are Ant-Man and the Wasp end of list. They liked Ant-Man and the Wasp a lot they thought it was really good.
Why did they go and see Ant-Man at the Wasp specifically? Got Paul Rudd in it.
But why don't they go and see Ant-Man? They were probably busy.
The theme music for this episode was Surf Shimmy by Kevin McLeod and Combertek.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license. This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.