every time you eat a new food at
extencialife by 45 days.
I don't know if this is a real
proper morality and I don't like to
check too hard because you know,
you discover that when you check too
hard, you just go to the Coca-Cola
does not own the world's second
largest submarine fleet and things
like this.
Who was living a world where
Coca-Cola is not a meaningful
naval power?
They're not a meaningful naval power
because none of the submarines
they own work, I'm told.
That's not the reason I thought.
That's not the reason I thought
they wouldn't be.
So that does make me happy in its own way.
Hello everyone and welcome to the
16th episode of Octa Thorpe, a science
fiction and science fiction fandom
podcast.
This is the episode for the 15th of
October and those eagerly waiting
our emergency episode dealing with
Trump and the coronavirus will be
disappointed because it has been
delayed but we promise it's coming
soon.
I'm Jon Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
We have had two letters of comment.
We have a letter of comment from
Karen Schaeffer who says that with
another episode of Octa Thorpe comes
another puzzle which is also
wooden and also has hidden figures
but this one is in Russian.
We will attempt to put pictures or a
link in the show notes.
Karen has a neighbor who puts the
edge pieces in a separate bag and
then when he passes on to what else
he passes on with the edge pieces
already in the separate bag which
seems like removing a part of the
puzzle making process to Karen and
to me.
What's your opinions on this?
My view is that if you do that you
might as well be one of these people
who puts the puzzle very carefully
in four constructed sections back into
the box so that the new person doesn't
have to do anything at all with it
apart from separate all the pieces
whilst being quite annoyed but I
think it's probably quite thoughtful
to put the edge pieces back in the
box because people do find sorting the
edge pieces tedious and if they do
want to do the puzzle properly and not
cheat they can just kind of tip the
edge pieces back into the box before
they start and shuffle them around and
that will also be fine.
That is the thing that Karen notes you
can do and she says that she dislikes
what the previous puzzle puts the
puzzle back in in big chunks which I
would assume is a fake punishable by
or sorry an act punishable by death but
I'm not in the puzzle fandom.
You just get the box and shake ups up
and down quite a lot.
Oh maybe not if you've got a nice fancy
wooden puzzle that wouldn't work.
Life hack.
Yeah and also fairly expensive puzzles
it did.
Yeah I think that the advantage of having
the puzzle provided in section is that
it demonstrates that the puzzle is
complete which as acquiring puzzle
second hand is a kind of magic pastime
roulette.
I mean I suppose roulette is a pastime
roulette but a kind of Russian pastime
roulette where you never know until you
finish the puzzle whether it was
complete or not.
I mean my mother and father do an awful
lot of jigsaw puzzles and his spannier is
a fan of them as well.
In our how to stay sane in the apocalypse
thing one of the things I've been doing
after Caroline Mullen said she was doing
jigsaw puzzles online and I said oh that
really is a waste of your time dear you
know that that's a really a really bad
way to spend time.
I am a I should not really rag on what
other people are doing to stay sane in
the apocalypse but also I started doing
them because Colin Hins has been posting
lots of puzzles on a website called
jigsaw planet and it turns out that I
quite like doing puzzles that my friends
have made I find it quite fun and sort
of connective and so if you're on jigsaw
puzzle jigsaw planet then I'm behemian
coast look me up we'll put a link in the
show notes.
Yeah and we have a little community of
science fiction fans doing each other's
puzzles that are not particularly
science fiction all that there are
photographs so so I became equally sad
to Caroline and this is a chance to say
that I have found websites that allow you
to do large jigsaw puzzles collaboratively
online and punctuation will probably have
a jigsaw puzzle that you can do with other
people because that's one of the things
we liked. One of the things I've been
doing one of the things I did on Facebook
was that I asked people what sort of
things they like to do and how they were
doing them online and I got about 300
replies many of which were things
activities I had not thought of and my
next task is to go through that list
collating them and thinking about how we
might do them at punctuation. Oh yes that's
a good idea. No I have thought for some
time that the fan funds need to do custom
jigsaws of fanish bookshelves because
Catherine and Colin have a great bookshelf
and obviously Clara Mark have several
great bookshelves but I just suspect
that you could have a good line in
different fans bookshelves and that and
that could be something you could sell
for money a fan fund auction but I've
never got around to seeing if it's easy
to get custom puzzles made. Neil and Nick
also have extremely nice bookshelves you
want extra bookshelves diversity. Yes I
want as many as we can get. Many many of
them yeah. We would need the problem is
that if you go ahead Zazal and look at
how much it costs to get a thousand
piece jigsaw made it costs 60 quid so I
think I think you do you need to go to
a company you don't want to do it print
on demand you need to go to a jigsaw
company and I actually do it properly
and I have no idea what the minimum
like numbers are required to make it work.
Yeah a thousand John come on now it's
not going to work. Oh but you know what
would work if you got like Neil Gaiman
and George R.R. Martin to give you photos
and then did them as one-off jigsaw
puzzles like you can have this one-of-a-kind
jigsaw puzzle of Neil Gaiman's bookshelf
and you did that a fan fund auction at
a WorldCom that would go from more than
60 quid 100% especially if they signed
it if they did the puzzle signed it broke
it up and then you got to complete it.
Have you just asked Neil Gaiman to like
do a thousand piece jigsaw puzzle? I mean
we would have to find an author who
likes jigsaw puzzles. What you would have
to do is get the jigsaw puzzle do the
jigsaw puzzle put it very carefully
back in the box without breaking it so
that it was in four sections ship it to
Neil Gaiman. Ship it to Gaiman have
him sign it send it back that would work.
No no no no we only you only have to do
like the the modern corner of the jigsaw
ship it to him get him to sign it. Oh yeah
that's true. Have you ever done jigsaws
you two? Yeah I think it's pretty easy
just to do a specific corner Alison I
don't see. No it's not. No no no no you
you do the whole jigsaw but you'd only
have to ship like a tiny corner. Better.
Yeah no I mean I'm just saying though
I the more I think about that idea the
more I think that could work in a
financially lucrative direction. How
long did it take us to get irretrievably
off topic? I mean and the great thing is
there's literally no way. I guess I could
put this in the podcast just to see if we
get any locks because if people say that's
a great idea and I'd spend 300 quid for it
we know it's a goa. Right in if you would
spend more than 60 pounds on a jigsaw
puzzle of a famous author's bookshelf
right in and let us know because that is
useful information. Anyway we now move on
from this emergency fan fund planning
meeting to Liz's hand up. My I'm still
commenting on Karen's letter of comment.
Oh yeah we're still on Karen's log like
it's all nested. Okay that's fine. Octa
thought a podcast of jigsaws and fandom.
It's because she says you know a puzzle
may take up more than a
painting but has the advantage that it
goes back in the box afterwards and I
cannot deny this is the advantage but
what's actually going to happen to my
paint by numbers is I will finish my
paint by numbers. I will look at it and
go yeah that was fun and then I will
probably throw it away so it won't take
up much space at all. Oh poor paint by
numbers. I am made sense though. It's a
journey not a destination. Exactly. I mean
speaking as somebody who's got a build
at yourself, Erdie Gurdie in the study
that I can't quite bring myself to
sling but has actual no merit. It has no
Erdie Gurdie related merit because it
it sounds like a cat being strangled.
Karen wrote to us about puzzles and it
was very good. Thank you Karen.
Claire writes to us to say that Mark has
Claire Breyerley of Croydon writes to us
and tells us that Mark has also been on
holiday this week and they have not been
away and she notes that
Waltham so hearing that Waltham so is
great for holidays is really nice because
it means that she might try it one day
but she then asks whether she should
believe everything she hears on podcasts
and then she tells us off for not letting
her join punctuation. Sorry Claire. We
have never rectified that. I think on the
basis of the last week I cannot
really claim that Waltham so is great for
holidays. Oh yeah. No I mean it was fine.
Hey here.
Far and on that very enthusiastic bombshell.
So last weekend was Fyerturicon which was
the virtual Eurocon membership was 10
euros um Alison through a party and gave a
talk which I missed because I was playing
Arkham Horror of the card game with Liz.
Oops.
Okay I'm I'm not feeling even a little bit
hurt.
I wasn't a member of Futuricon so I'm not
sure I would be allowed to come to your
talk. Well I'm I'm very much hoping that
I'm going to I thought I was recording
it but apparently I wasn't recording it
but they were recording it and they're
basically like we will put the recordings
up and I'm like yes but I want the
recording because A) I'm hoping that
somebody in fact somebody is offered
Richard Bredger is offered to transcribe
it so that it gives me some text towards
the virtual GuffTrip report but also I
wanted to just like shove it on the
GuffTrip's Facebook page and it will be a
bit past its prime by the time they
actually get around to send him with
the recording so I know they've got it
but they haven't sent it to me or put it
anywhere that I can grab it. I used I
used software called Mm-hmm which we can
put a link to in the show notes which is
in beta and for Mac only but was very very
nifty and it's just basically software
that allows you to to manage your slide
deck whilst having you as a little
disembodied head in front of it and it
worked really quite well after I rigged
up the green screen in the study so I
gave a talk it went down I think quite
well but it was very talking into the
void because I couldn't see any of the
audience I did have some people on chat
but I didn't have anybody with their
faces and I am not used to that and I
had a party because apparently that's
what I do. Futuritcon pre-recorded a lot
of its content which made it easier for
them to and then they streamed it they
used Jitsi as the back end and then they
streamed it through OBS I think so that
as a member you just kind of clicked on a
stream and that sort of worked quite well
but they had it set up in a way that
they for pot they made it very easy for
participants by giving them one click
link but their one click link for me
didn't it only it only put my camera onto
their Jitsi it didn't allow me to choose
different cameras and of course I wanted
the combined feed from the software I was
using this is probably a bit more
technical detail than we need for this but
I think there is a big takeaway for other
online conventions here which is that
saying to your program participants
we will send you a link you can click 10
minutes before your item is going to drop
certain sorts of people anyone who is
kind of nervous about how their tech might
work into a flat spin and I'm here to
say I am not very nervous about how my
tech would work and I was absolutely
bricking it before that presentation
because I had I was like I can kind of
contacted them a couple of days in advance
and said can I have a tech run through
for just five or ten minutes to make sure
the tech I'm using all works with your
system and they were like no he will send
you the link 10 minutes and advance and
it will work and I mean it did but I mean
it's reassuring that it did just work
it didn't just work it worked because I
kind of shouted at them and said send me
the direct link so I can launch Jitsi and
feed by um um feed through it yeah yeah
that is a stupid day for an app it's uh
I've put a link in the show notes so if you
are wondering how the f*ck do you spell
mm-hmm then look at the show notes and it
tells you it's spelt exactly as it sounds
it's spelt and well yeah but then the
question is like how long is the mm
and how long is the mm and that is the sort
of question that we really do you into
here on the old thought podcast indeed
okay but you also threw a party how did the
party go I went to the party because the
party did not require that I be a member
of Futuricon it required that I ask
Alison for a zoom link yeah that that
technique did actually work for a couple
of people at the um at the octagon
parties but it was I had explicitly told
people I wouldn't do it for octagon but
for for Futuricon I just ran a party
it was at an official convention item
the convention didn't have any parties
and its only social space was discord and I
find um somebody who should be
nameless but who is lily and edwards
said "Ha ha!" discord is just clunky
i-r-c isn't it and she's kind of got a
point so so text chat is all very well
but it is only text chat and I find it
is not an adequate for me it is not an
adequate substitute for actually getting
together and hanging out with people
in a way that zoom is also not an adequate
substitute for getting together and hanging
out with people but it's a much for me zoom
is a much better substitute for that than
any amount of text chat i'm not convinced
discord has any functionality that's not
possible in IRC gift sallison
gifts oh no okay you know IRC is kind of
I mean you could do a lot with IRC so I
mean discord IRC is extremely flexible
the problem is that IRC's got a kind of
roll your own vibe to it that discord
doesn't um though I will say the thing
that I most hate about discord which is
that it is incredibly difficult to export
text from discord and I I really this this
actually gives me the heebie gb's I do not
like working in platforms that don't
want you to export the things you write
in them I don't I like that that is a
valid christ you know and that and I'm not
I think it's a deliberate design decision
and I I hate it with a fiery passion I am
all about the capturing the things I write
for posterity um I think um so but I think I
think there's two things where I think I
think saying discord is clunky IRC like I
think is the other way around I think IRC is clunky
discord I know I know that discord came
after IRC and it turns out like a proprietary
software where somebody is making a profit
though they probably aren't actually and IRC is
a big old open source thing that nobody owns
and is out there for the whole world to use as they
as they need which is why it is hello clunky
oh yeah discord came about to replace a
piece of software called mumble and I say
replace and like people who know more about
this are yelling at their podcast playing
device at the moment but effectively like
mumble and team speak are both things where
you could host a server for mumble or
team speak and you could invite your friends
to your server and they could voice chat on
that server with you while you're playing
games and they were very good and um the
Mac app for mumble um is very very very bad
and I dislike it intensely um and team speak is
quite expensive because hosting a team speak
server is not cheap and they're both very
good and discord basically came along and
said we're going to do this thing where
we will offer you voice chat in an application that is
nice instead of massively clunky and it
will be free and in exchange we will sell
you discord night throw and access to more
emoji and try and make money in this way
and in some ways that's a very compelling value
proposition and I do and then as times gone on
discord has started to compete more and more with
slack so I think slack is the original um
IRC replacement um proprietary platform
um and then discord had text channels alongside
the voice channels but it was more of an
afterthought at the beginning and it has
become discord has become more and more used
for text chat primarily driven by reddit
but it's a really interesting landscape and a
landscape that i've seen developed from both
ends because i use slack professionally and
discord for leisure and um yes
as so does everybody else so one of the
things about zoom that we see one of the
reasons i run all the zoom parties is that i
don't use zoom at all professionally i mean
i do very occasionally but basically i do
not have to do video meetings with my
colleagues regularly so you see quite a lot of
people who don't like zoom parties because
they associate zoom with things that they
don't like like interminable meetings with
their colleagues and you see and the
the different although the slack and discord are in
many ways i don't they aren't in many ways i don't
at all but they have an awful lot of overlap
and you see a lot of people who are like well i
don't really want to be doing things socially
and slack because i have slack the entire
service in my work part of my brain is where i am
on slack when i'm on slack i'm working
when i'm although obviously there's a there's a
queue in the name people lots of people slack is
quite a good place for not working with the
people that you work with um and then discord is
is an entirely social space it is primarily social though of
course some people who are using it for work
and um and we're seeing so we see some of that with zoom as well
and i think this is actually a huge um
misstep on slack spark so i think slack if slack had had a more coherent
mechanism for monetization at the low end
slack would have much of this market and discord wouldn't really have had a
look in but because slack has this model where
if you want to upgrade to the first paid tier you have to pay 10 pounds per
month per user it's basically the gulf between
free and the lowest paid tier is so gigantic if you're not
in enterprise that there's just no way you could possibly do it
it's quite possible that slack dude just just do not care about trying to
monetize low end users they're quite happy where they are
which is providing paid services to businesses because they're more of a
Microsoft Teams competitor than they are a discord competitor
this is point leads on to something i do want to talk about and indeed put to the
show notes which is that next week zoom is um
holding its annual conference which does every year called zoom topia but this
year it is free and online and i am going to take two days out of my life
and go to it and as lis says these companies are not really aiming at the
social market but zoom has a big social market
and i want to go and be extremely difficult to them and talk to them a lot
about what they should be doing um to nurture all the people who are
having fun on zoom i feel that their conference
thing doesn't really include enough about fun and i feel that it's actually
would have merits for their corporate business as well because
the big thing that businesses are losing as they go online as as people
work from home much more is that that sense of collegiate fellowship
is being lost in many workplaces and i actually did need that it you do better
job work if you like and get on and have fun with the people that you work
with who knew um so anyway i'm going to go talk to them a lot about that
and i will come back and report but that's all happening before
this episode goes out so by the time you hear this i will have already done it
um and i want to mention their dress code because it said what is the dress
code for online zoom topia and they said
business on the top casual on the bottom well okay that works which i thought
was quite funny and and i think zoom topia
although there's nothing on the website about it having social space
um the email gives me some hope it's kind of saying oh it's got lots of
um different spaces that you'll be able to go and explore and get
virtual virtual tokens and if you get enough of these virtual tokens you can
cash them in for prizes such as virtual ribbons or
merch or even a conversation with the a half az zoom with the ceo of zoom and i'm
like oh that would be funny oh my goodness can you
imagine allison getting to talk to the ceo of zoom
recording for the podcast allison do it as an interview
i mean obviously if i talk to the ceo of zoom i will be recording the
meeting if i am allowed to do so and if i'm not allowed to do so i'll just be
recording the meeting but not in zoom um
don't tell them don't don't put that we can't put that out of the podcast
i'm gonna bleep it so going back to future a con
how did you so the reason i did not join was because i did not see a coherent
social i think for me like i think the way conventions are using discord at the
moment to kind of be the backbone of the convention and offer
kind of a place to talk in between program items
is like a good one and i think running the convention through the discord i.e
having links to the parties and the panels on your discards
on your discord server is a good way to kind of
unify everything and and have people have a kind of
central place to get information which is i think cool
but i will say that like i didn't join future a con because it didn't seem to
have a story for like social zooms or anything like that
so what do you think about what do you think about that because like for me
the big appeal of like oh there's a convention this weekend is
i get to like you know beyond zoom in the evening and talk to interesting
people and future a con other than the party you ran us and didn't seem to do
that very much it didn't do it at all and it was
really strange because they started by having a very sad
little video of kind of what what future a con was like last year when it
wasn't the year con and i'm sure it had lots of panels and
events and things but nearly all of this
the of the video shots from this convention with of people
hanging out in a space and having fun together
and i felt that they didn't really do anything like enough of that and the
reliance on pre-recorded content made meant that quite a lot of their
programming was less interactive than you would want it to be as well
so although there was chat going on and they were
they they basically had a chat in the live stream on the internet which i think
is not a terribly good idea and they also had a chat
in the discord which i think probably work quite a bit better i think twitch
might give us the best of both of these worlds because twitch chat
would work perfectly well and in fact has worked perfectly well for octagon
um it does mean that people need to join another service but you know
twitch is another good service that you should probably be a member of already
um twitch i don't think twitch has quite realized yet that they're um
they're going to be used as people suddenly realize they can be used for
everything they will be used for everything and not really for
streaming games i'm the fucking internet historian today
i do apologize but twitch was originally a service called justin.tv
which is a bloke called justin who just bloke quite like streaming random
things and then twitch came about because everyone
latched on to justin tv for game streaming and he launched twitch
as a um companion to justin tv that was specifically for games
and then eventually justin tv died because everyone just went to twitch
and i think i think it's interesting to see that kind of coming the other way
but i don't know whether twitch i don't know whether twitch needs to
i don't know the extent to which twitch needs to take action is not clear to me
because it might just be that they can carry on in the way they are and still
kind of attract multiple groups i don't know
and of course twitch is amazon speaking of evil evil corporate
overlords so octagon avoided the fact that zoom webinars are expensive by just
streaming out twitch and then encouraging people to chat in twitch
which i think is it's a good way of doing it perfectly sensible i mean
i have a vision of what twitch chat is like which is very different from my
vision of what the chat stream at science fiction
conventions is like so i don't know whether they've ended up somewhere in
the middle but i normally think of twitch chat as being like a
continuous stream of of unreadable copy pastor and memes
well i mean is that meaningfully different to an east con bar
mahingi liz how did you find futuricon programming
oh i did not go to futuricon i thought you'd been to like a panel
that was at the right time no okay no i didn't because it wasn't
free it was like some small amount of cash but it didn't really seem worth it
for the one to two panels i would be able to make
and while i do believe you party hard you did not party hard enough to still
be partying in my time zone we have been failing to do that
did not attend any of it well it does require you to party essentially until
probably at least one or two a.m we party till one o'clock last night
yeah but but we were very we were very tired at one
exactly well it's because we'd also party till
one the night before and i had gotten drunk at noon yesterday
so realistically i just made a series of bad bad life choices
but i actually have uh liz i don't know if you were to see this
i actually have a widget on my phone that tells me the time in bangcock that i
can look at when i'm partying to see the likelihood that liz will be there
oh that's sweet that's so thoughtful oh that's very nice
but you don't it's very thoughtful though when do you think i get up in a
morning john ah i um i think you get up at
nine thirty that is on a weekend not far off well done john
nice but it's fine because the i mean the reason to have that widget also is
because the the time difference is not fixed
hmm yeah because of daylight savings time
by by the time of punctuation it will be seven hours which means i will be more
likely to wake up in the morning when you're partying but actually i'll
probably stay awake far too late anyway
yay list list list list um so yes so fair enough um
and i i meant to go to octagon programming and then completely failed to
do so because i was busy doing social things
which pleasingly replicates the experience of real convention so that's
good i was interested in the fourth way feminism panel
and i'm hoping that it might be recorded although i suspect i will be hoping
uh in vain because i don't know if they're recording anything
some twitch in it oh maybe make a good twitch yeah
because that sounded really interesting and alleybakers great so
yeah i kind of think if these things are on twitch then
then you just get recording free and it keeps it for 30 days or something which
feels ideal for me and you know i'm thinking stuff will be
and you can export them out you can export them out to youtube as well from
twitch um no twitch does it twitch increases the
technology load um and it increases it like i think appreciably
but it does seem like quite a good way of doing some of these things and i'm
basically a very jealous of octagon because they're doing all the things i
thought would be neat to do at punctuation but they're doing them five
weeks earlier yeah so so octagon had i known octagon was
existing and was doing a lot of the stuff i thought
the convention should be doing um i mean i think that we will have more of
it and more of the social stuff and that will all be fine
um but i think um i think they are doing they are coming a lot
close to my platonic ideal of what online
convention should be like than any previous convention that i've been to
they have a thing which i've not been to any of yet which are called fan chats
which are essentially zoom get-togethers on a theme which is obviously like the
kind of workshops we're planning to have um and and they have quite a lot of
space that's thematic in the um in the discord's got quite a lot of kind of
themed channels and things so you can hang out and talk about
the sorts of things you'd like to talk about like pets or crafting
yes whatever else that fans talk about book recommendations and things about
these seem like the right sorts of things to be doing and i am having
quite a good time um but i i did run both the parties
which was kind of accidental because because Glasgow said can you run a party
for us and i was like well of course Glasgow that's what i do um
that's that is my the thing that i'm giving to the Glasgow 2024 World Cup bid
is that i sit in zoom and then we thought it would be fun to have a punctuation
party on the friday night so so we ended up having
two parties with me doing both of them and um they have i believe they are having
a dead dog tonight the john de_labelle the punctuation party
and there are plenty of Glasgow people who would have helped the Glasgow party but
so James Shields at the punctuation party was excellent because he brought
some punctuation to the party and he was awarded one point
and for those who don't know what points do
firstly respect Bruce Forsyth come on but secondly uh you'll find out when you
come to punctuation i think it's highly likely that
points don't mean prizes unless you mean by prizes some kind of virtual badge or
ribbon or some kind i'm not saying it's a good prize
yeah yeah full disclaimer we make no guarantees of quality of
prizes on this podcast or our convention i always take no
vicon as a guide because um whenever i hear the police dog
hogan's song which is white wine it makes me think of no
vicon and the prizes for events oh i have no comment um
liz what did you think of octagon programming uh i am in 20 octagon
programming no i tell a lie i went to one piece of octagon programming
which is they popped in this chord saying that they were randomly gonna stream
the chair of the convention playing untitled goose game between panels and
so i watched someone run around trying to play goose
game uh on twitch for 10 minutes while people in the chat tried to give helpful
suggestions about you know maybe carry some carrots or something
and it was great um and then i meant to go to some panels
but uh i was watching the cycle racing ah okay for enough for enough so yeah
that is your other problem it's clashing with the attempts to put entire sport
seasons into a two-month window yeah and then of course
you know half the programming is too late for me
so i didn't go to any of that and i failed the party as well
it's very sad but i'm quite enjoying the discord and i think what i have seen of it
is well set up and i do like their twitch streaming
yes all right i hadn't realized they were doing untitled
goose game in between but that is most excellent
that was spontaneous i think they spontaneously just decided
hey we've got some time let's have some goose game
which is the kind of programming that one day i will be able to play untitled
goose game you can play it now you got a switch
you got a switch yeah on my ipad just get out of your switch
allison is like 13 pounds okay i don't i should say i don't
actually own a switch oh you're son owns a switch
my son owns a switch so i mean i can do it and in fact
obviously jonathan doesn't play switch all the time
that's not i don't believe you that's not that doesn't tell you with any of the
things you've ever said about jonathan or his switch
um he is quite often playing on his laptop
ah is he okay i mean it you know there are lots of hours of the day and
switch gaming does not fill all of them it does if you try hard enough that's
what i'm saying not if you have a knockulous quest
yeah okay so is that so what are we what are we going to steal from octaton
for punctuation everything i've sorted out with kathryn that we'll have a
debrief middle and next week and can i come
nickelling stuff i haven't had to sort it out of time for it but that's
kind of that sort of time oh cool okay no because i do think and i do
wonder whether this indicates that there are people
because i mean obviously so not to disrespect the
the fine and distinguished nuances between
irish and british fandom but i think in many ways irish british fandom share
uh quite a lot of dna in terms of like a general approach to
program and social spaces at conventions perhaps
and um i do wonder the extent to which like octacon is a sign that
this end of the world are thinking about virtual conventions and beginning to
come to the realization that perhaps they do need to be a bit more
you know octaconne or east connie on over connie and um
and yeah i've been thoroughly enjoying octacon in a way that um previous
conventions have not quite been doing it the same way for me so um
hats off to the octaconne career then they've been doing a fantastic job
no it's been very good and of course octaconne is free which is making
five pounds look terribly expensive but it doesn't look as expensive as
some conventions i could mention a segue allison
well what what are these other conventions to which you refer
so in a in a move that i think will um as pleased a lot of us actually we're
very pleased congratulations to confusion for um
announcing that they are going to hybridize their
convention that they will have physical elements if they can but they will
also be planning for an online convention for easter 2021
it's very good stuff very very good stuff i think
that when we say we are hoping to have a hybrid convention it's a bit like when
they say your dog has gone to live on a farm with
all the other old dogs when it's going to be happy and play all the time
i still think there is no chance that we will have anything that is at all like
a convention in at easter though i i still i held out a tiny amount of hope
that we might be able to gather locally in small groups by then
and there's a thing that you could you might be able to say
actually we're going to say we're going to tell you who else is a member of the
convention is your area if you want to meet up in a
pub or something which i think would be quite a cool thing
if we're allowed to do that in atista which i think is
you know possible possible maybe not very light yeah i mean if you assume by
if you assume easter will have hopefully relatively pleasant weather then it
could be like okay well you know ten of you are now
allowed to go and sit in a beer garden and drink beer together
and we are encouraged and so you could do things like say we're encouraging
everyone to do that yeah and maybe at a particular time
and that would and then we could have like a photo like a photo stream of
photos for all of these gatherings and i think that sort of thing could be
very agreeable and foster that sense of the
of the community that the the community getting together so i think there are
some things that they could do that are short of
we will actually have a thousand people in a room
in at the n_e_c_ because i don't that that doesn't seem
terribly likely um and they've announced a price which is 50 pounds
and yes and that was the basis of your segue
ooh it was and what they said and there is a quote which we should probably use
but i paraphrasing they've said doing this properly cost money
um and and in that they are they are they are not wrong
but they might not be right whether or not it costs 50 pounds is the tricky
thing right i i'm curious to see the thing with
the thing with consieland was that they said doing this properly costs money
and they charged money and then they did it the same way as all the
conventions who don't charge money did it or the
conventions the charge 10 quid did it oh no they had lots of stuff so
so one of the things that certainly costs some money is putting a paywall on
your convention yes no and that is a good
point that is a that is a very good point and and you clearly do want to have some
sort of paywall on the easter con i think um
octagon's not charging but as a tip bucket do do throw a fiber into that tip
bucket if if you're enjoying the convention by the way
but at the moment there's no clear evidence to me
that using the free services or the very cheap basic services and then
stitching them together in kind of with
vanish gaffer tape is producing a result that's any worse
than what you buy if you buy an integrated events solution
and integrated events event solutions are expensive they are
i i've kind of i'm not suggesting that that 50 pounds is not a good amount to
charge and i have had at least one conversation with
john tord who's working on um the easter con about something i kind of
wanted to do for punctuation he was like oh yeah that takes service and lots of
money and i was like oh yeah no i can see how it might
and i and so that sort of thing they can easily do well
with a budget of 50 quid ahead you could get a lot of
good stuff for that and and anyway 50 quid ahead is still less than i paid
for the easter con by a very long chalk and i have joined and i have totally
forgotten the 50 pounds by easter so i'm perfectly happy with that
but i would like to see their budget i just want to know i want to know
where they think they're spending the money because i think actually starting
to have that conversation about what things are really worth spending this
money on and what things are maybe not worth spending the money on
it's good i have joined easter con i joined um before it was online so i don't
know if i'll get my 20 quid back but oh well 20 quid
literally by half a board game um i think and i think you're right i think
there is a there's a compelling argument to be made that you might be able to do
some of this stuff better if you do charge like serious money and like
i didn't go to conzeland um and i know that they did
use things that they wouldn't be able to do had they not charged money so that
is a good point i think that um i'm just i'm i'm still curious about the value
proposition but i am rooting for them i will be
attending because it is my home convention i've never missed an easter
con don't plan to start now i i'm i'm definitely going to be there i
mean i i i i was somebody when i was with bells on
in with bells on somebody is a thread that i
announced this in said and i think this is a very reasonable question is that
per person or per household i assume per person but it is a reasonable
question and it is of course per person but i think i think there's a real
question for online conventions whether you should be saying
we are going to charge you x amount per household and then extra people are
a little bit extra but your your basic membership gets you that one stream
because you're not i think so i think the problem i mean it's okay if you're
john and his spannier and you have two totally separated offices
but lots of households essentially sit on a sofa and do the zoom together
i think i think what it needs to be is it needs to be per
um account it's like if you are planning to be on the sofa together and just
usually what account then paying once i think is fine and i don't know
this is not the obviously this is not the opinion of confusion the 2020 what
is to come because uh i am not um involved with that
convention um but like my my assumption is it's basically per
account and i think i think that would be the
sensible way to do it if you were going to be doing it per household and like
trying to implement some sort of like oh you know if you've got multiple
accounts but you're in one household will give you some sort of discount
that's enormously complicated you don't need the extra mental load
but equally like if say me and his family decide we're just going to pay
once and then everything we do at least call we're going to do together
i kind of don't really think that council's ghosting i wouldn't feel bad
about doing that so like that that would be more
instinctive reaction but i don't know i don't know how they'll do it
but by the time somebody raised this i had already bought two memberships for
myself and my husband despite the fact that you know
Stephen really doesn't do this online convention stuff he just kind of hangs
around in the background of parties sometimes but i mean i think in that
case i think you could yeah you could definitely get
i've got away with one membership for that but i mean i think
if you do have it never even i mean i did say to him do you want me to buy you a
membership but i i was kind of doing it in a kind of
because of but of course you do dear because it's the easter con and
we really want to express lots of enthusiastic and vigorous support for
our home convention which we which we love in
ordinarily so there was a bit of that but it's also yeah it should be one account
because it should be one account where you know
then you can't be watching two panels at once and you get one account for the
discord otherwise it seems a bit unreasonable for those people who can't
split the prices though i do feel quite strongly that with
whether i'm one membership i should be able to watch two panels at once if i
want to say you know
well i want to eat screens well one on each of my several screens i
you know especially if they're not recording like like that scene from
serenity where he's just watching the whole universe's news all at once
because he's so good at news i love that movie but there are some
haunt choices yeah my thinking is i'm just not sure at this point it's even
worth aiming for a hybrid convention because
i think that'll be really difficult it is an interesting one right because
i think it's laudable but if it's going to cause a lot more stress and a lot more
hassle and it's going to be unlikely to come off
even even if you put the work in i do i do wonder at which point you just say
like i i think it's still very likely that they have
contractual obligations to the hotel that mean that they cannot
ditch at this stage i think you need to be very
soothing and kind to conventions that are supposed to be running online
further yeah yes so liz are you going to
timeshift and attendees to come i might um i'm trying to remember when
easter is this year yeah i think if i'm gonna
uh it was a while ago well next year is late april so i think we may have gone
back to s no it's april of the fourth april of the
fourth april of the fourth year of the pandemic no it's
fourth of april is eas sunday because sometimes the clocks go back in the
middle and that makes it slightly more complicated for me on account for the
clocks do not change here um i probably will like
if it's going to be 50 quid then like the only rational thing i think for me to do
is to go okay in which case i'm going to do it i'm going to timeshift for a few
days like i don't think i want to pay 50 quid
for a thing where i sort of drop in and out and you know get to see
roughly half the convention none of the parties i think i'm going to have to
fully timeshift so let's see i mean if it turns out that i also can't go outside
then that is a much more appealing prospect
yeah then voluntarily staying indoors they've also not talked about
day memberships but conzeland didn't have day memberships
punctuation isn't having day memberships because a day membership would do two
pounds 50 and that's just dense no we we are having day memberships they
just cost the same as the weekend and give you a free extra day
yes so conzeland didn't have day memberships i think
because a lot of stuff for conzeland got sped up
quite fast in a world where there wasn't really time to think hard about these
sorts of things but easter con could have day memberships
and i feel like that's something they should be talking about because i think
liz may have said in chat that you wanted a two-day convention really
rather than four full days of front of frolics and i think there are quite a
lot of people who might like just one or two days of an easter con rather than
the entire four-day thing yeah it's more that i i think i i mean i very much
enjoy having four or five full days of frolics at easter con than
will cons but i'm not sure i actually want to have four
full days of what is effectively mostly sitting
with my laptop open on discord and zoom and maybe streaming some twitch to the
tv if they can go up with some way that i can sort of be engaged with the
convention but also out and about a bit which i think is one of our aims
of punctuation we're going to try and do something like that i think that makes
it more appealing but even if there is a sort of hybrid
well we're going to have meetups in these places with as many people as
possible like obviously that's not much use to me
as possibly the only easter con fan yeah you and Pete's family yeah it would be
me and me and Pete's family who are in fact
yeah who are in fact two hours away so yeah no so i think it's going to be
interesting because obviously like there is a question as well as to whether or
not it makes sense to offer day memberships because i
assume most of their costs are going to be super like
not it's going to be based on total people rather than like how many people
you have at once so like i don't know to what extent they're going to be able to
do that but like it's something they could definitely look at
and like hopefully hopefully they can make all that work i mean
i am planning to go with bells on um i'm very i'm like happy that they're doing
it and like i say i haven't i haven't missed an easter conces so i started
going um so like yeah i'm not gonna start now um
but i am hoping that it will be great and like i think it is important to say
that although for all of the like you know
probably not gossiping smoughing cob running doesn't sound right because it
sounds like you're actually doing it smoughing does sound much more like
carping carping carping i mean it's it's like
we're a podcast about fandom we're going to complain about the easter color
we that's kind of what we're here for but we are all of course obviously
rooting for the easter con we all uh definitely want it to be great
oh yeah even if we can't root at the easter con anyway
ha ha that's for our Australian listeners i assume that's for our
Australian listeners anyway are you familiar with the word rooting
Liz no it's Australian for f*cking oh okay
but they still call their Wi-Fi routers routers and that makes me so happy
is this something you learned on your guff trip it's Australian slang for
not practicing careful social distancing
is there anything else we want to say about easter con um
i mean i as well as asking the easter con committee for a budget i would also
like them to be thinking hard about compelling social spaces i'm sure they
will be anyway i think the announcement they um
released made it seem like they weren't of the opinion that this was a solved
problem whether or not that means that they will have a compelling
solution is obviously like slightly different but like i'm hoping the fact
that they don't think is a solved problem indicates that they are
kind of thinking of our how to you know improve um
upon the current situation so so i'm kind of like cautiously optimistic
that that is um i think that's happening
upcoming conventions so um upcoming conventions fire fire the magazine
uh that george ron martin can't pronounce uh is running a convention
uh that is next weekend and at the time of writing everything except for
the friday assault out by the time you hear this almost certainly the whole
thing will be sold out but uh congratulations congratulations to them
on running what looks like a great convention and hopefully it'll be brilliant
for everyone who's going and um finland the all and islands are bidding
for the 2025 euro con which is all very exciting
um that might be in a country that doesn't have any coronavirus in 2025 so
like that's gotta be good right and then um i wish you i should say i went to the
2015 archipelago and this would be archipelago 2
and it was great although it's very easy to stay up drinking till 2 a.m
when it doesn't really get dark at night so a recommendation and a warning
whereas of course if it does get dark at night it's very difficult to stay out
drinking till 2 a.m
we also have a note in the show notes that by the time we record the euro con in
2022 will have been decided but i can't find anything about it
during my quick googles on the internet so listeners if you know
where the 2022 euro con is going to be please write us a letter of comment
so we can be more informed next time
we maybe we should talk about punctuation remind people it's still good we're
still doing that guys right um so john here i'm recording a quick
pickup because liz asked whether we were going to mention punctuation
and then me and Arson agreed but immediately got distracted
and then we didn't end up mentioning it in the podcast so i'm rectifying that now
punctuation is a convention you can join for five pounds you can join today
and it's happening at the 13th to the 15th of november 2020
we would be very keen to see everyone who listens to oak to the up come along
um we are super hopeful and super enthusiastic about some of the stuff
we've got planned um and we are very much looking forward to welcoming you all
to our idea of an online convention so head on over to punctuation con.uk
and join now
that was the 16th episode of the octa thought podcast and it's goodbye from me
and it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me the theme music for this episode
was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud at ncompetech.com
used under a creative commons attribution 3.0 license
anyway welcome to octa thought the podcast about the movie serenity um
very topical i was told that you could watch serenity without having watched
far flight and i believe this to be not true i met someone no no
alice said i said you are going to blow your i'm going to blow you right now
right i met someone at my 30th birthday party i was in the bar and um
someone was like oh you're having a birthday party like you know
and started a conversation back in the days when there were bars you could talk
to people less than two years apart you didn't know
and he was like oh you know like he was here and i was like oh there you know
they're french for university when i was at the university i was an engineer and i was
like brilliant so i was like who's there i was like ah there french
science fiction you went ah quite like sci-fi uh one of my favorite movies is
that movie serenity have you seen that and i was like yeah and he went yeah i
really wish that it was a sequel and he said and i said well obviously you've got
firefly and he said what's firefly and i said sir you are about to have a very
good week because i'm going to tell you a thing that is going to make your day
and i told him that serenity was the follow-up to a series show called firefly
and he was like what and i was like i have just i have just done such a good
deed definitely getting into heaven now okay i i had not seen
firefly when i watched serenity and i thought it was
incomprehensible um and not at all good so imagine how excited you'd be about
firefly if you'd enjoyed serenity yeah i think that's the issue actually
because it's never occurred to me to go watch firefly though you know
maybe one day when i get to the bottom of my television backlog
queue i mean i will be honest i went back and rewatch firefly
and there are some ways in which it has not aged well
especially the first pilot rewatching it it is slow and it does take a
long time to induce the characters and it is a little bit
it takes us up a little bit too seriously and actually and don't tell any firefly
fans i said this i think fox might have been right to make him
shoot a different first episode because i think the train job works better as
an introduction to the characters because it does everything in subtext
instead of like as explicit exposition and i think show don't tell
is a is a thing that's good um but i would recommend it because he's very good
well this is certainly a change from our usual mcu based movie chat
yeah now that we're discussing movies for 15 years ago so that's good
uh well this is the after show sorted we're just going backwards in time
that's because i have watched no mcu movies in the last fortnight
you know next week 12 monkeys right oh yes 12 monkeys because it's all right
player yeah 12 monkeys a movie i have no particular
desire to watch right now for some reason i do like it i do love it
are you saying you don't want to watch depressing apocalyptic movies
in which time doesn't seem to have any meaning i i love 12 monkeys i i mean i
quite like the the weird french short on which it's
based but i um i really like 12 monkeys i really like the fact that it's
uh hugely successful big budget hollywood film with
that nevertheless has quite a lot intelligent to say about its topic
because you know as you know i find that big budget movies are often
not that thoughtful about the subjects that they discuss
this podcast will end at the beep beep