Oh, we've got a seam tune there! I forgot about the seam tune!
Oh shoot, yeah, we have to do that.
We've got a seam tune?
Ah, long story Liz, we'll tell you later.
Ha ha ha! In the vloggast!
Did you get drunk and make a seam tune?
No, it was in the morning and it was Carrie.
It was Anne de Graeben.
Anne Graeben.
Shall we do it now?
Hang on, yeah.
Did you do do do do do, you find wherever I put it.
It started with me going...
Octa thought. Octa thought.
Does whatever an octa thought does, which is like obviously classic,
theme tune stuff, I'm a visionary.
And then people started filming in the chat of the zoom that we were in
and Carrie posted.
Octa thought. Octa thought.
You can listen to us and talk.
Anne de Jon, Anne list two.
Octa thought is here for you.
We discuss, we review on everything we have of you.
Talking cons and talking fans, if it's Fandome Octa-Corkan.
Look how, here comes an octa thought.
And then Graeben says,
Octa thought. Octa thought.
Fourth dimensional space-time warp.
And, and unfortunately at that point, we never finished the next verse because...
Because of Pat McMurry.
The podcast spent 15 minutes discussing whether
Thorpe rhymes with warp or not.
And Thorpe, Thorpe absolutely rhymes with warp.
This is my contention and I will take it to the grave.
And I think it's fair to say that rhyming octa thought and warp
is evidence that you're part of the cultural hegemony of the south of England.
I'm from the east.
The mysterious east.
Pete, that's the first time Peterborough has ever been called the mysterious east.
Are you saying I'm from the south of England?
Liz, say octa thought and warp.
Octa thought, warp.
This, this alright?
Yeah.
Yeah, so you're doing the thing where you put, you pronounce the R in warp.
Warp. Warp.
[Laughs]
No, you're thinking of corn wool.
Yeah, I'm not from corn wool.
Warp.
[Laughs]
Anyway, all of these will be available on the Patreon OctaThop Soundboard coming real soon now.
Thank you very much to everyone who is in that Zoom call for Filki long.
And if anyone has any suggestions for additions to the OctaThop theme tune in terms of verses,
please do write in and let us know it's been too long since we did any poetry.
But critically, if you're a filker and reading this,
because I'm sure some of you are, if you'd like to work that up into an actual thing that we can use the theme song.
500 episodes later we can still be playing it to the great annoyance of a certain proportion of alliculus.
[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome to the 43rd episode of OctaThop, a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom.
This episode is coming to you on the 28th of October 2021.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
And it's almost Halloween, so we're in a really spooky mood.
Yep, I've got my pumpkin coloured microphone muffler on to celebrate the season.
Are there any of you doing anything for Halloween?
I think I might have, I think I might have a movie marathon on my own.
I have got a pumpkin dremel.
Oh.
So yes, I am going to be carving a pumpkin this year because I didn't cover pumpkin last year because
there wasn't really Halloweeny stuff that needed pumpkins.
So I decorated my windows instead so that children could stand outside and look at them
in a non-contact way.
But this year we're going to have a pumpkin and we're going to wear masks while we dish out the
candy because that's the thing you could do on Halloween at nobody's sixth word.
Yeah, we might dress up.
We'll be doing the candy and we will be carving a pumpkin.
It used to be tradition when I was an undergraduate that we would marathon the
saw movies on Halloween and I might do that again this year because there's a new saw movie
out which I haven't watched yet.
I mean the problem is now that there are nine saw movies when we launched this tradition
there are only four.
It was easier back then.
Could you just like pick three random saw movies and binge them?
No.
Okay.
Can we have this talk?
Are the saw movies good?
You wouldn't like them.
I don't think.
No, just checking.
I like them a great deal.
I quite like that.
I think the first one is good.
The third one is the most critically well received but it's also the worst so I don't
really know what that means.
Your critical faculties are on tilt which we knew in fact.
I think I saw the first one and it does involve someone doing something with a hacksaw
to themselves which I did not enjoy so I will not be watching saw movies and also trick or
treating is not a huge thing and you know you can't trick or treat me.
I live inside an apartment building and the only pumpkins we've got are green
so they would be slightly non-traditional pumpkins if I tried to carve one.
Nice.
And I don't have a pumpkin dremel.
I mean I have actually there was one year when I thought about carving a watermelon
because pumpkins had disappeared from the shops at the point where I wanted to cover pumpkin.
Carver papaya.
Less additional but they are orangey so.
I can think of a number of reasons why this is a terrible terrible idea.
Try carving a peach.
Just get a very unright very large peach you'll be right.
Like a giant peach maybe.
Yeah I'm like John is this this is not this is like the plot of a children's book I think
rather than actual real life.
John and the giant peach.
I mean all I'm saying is it could work if you squint a bit.
Okay so all of you people who haven't actually made a habit of carving fruit vegetables
it kind of needs to be something of the squash family.
Like a pumpkin or a melon and not a peach not stone fruit or whatever papayas are.
Yeah crucially it needs to not have a stone in the middle right.
I mean if you want to put a light in it then you need to be able to hollow it out and so
you know you're not going to be hollowing out a pomegranate I should say.
You could hollow out you could hollow out a papaya I think because they've got kind of like seeds in the middle.
Yeah but but but the problem with papaya is going to be that that it doesn't have enough structural
integrity to to whack it with a dremel.
If you don't believe me then google I carved a papaya with a dremel videos of the um.
No I mean what we're going to do is Liz is going to do it and video herself and that
that is going to go up on YouTube like come on.
I do not own a dremel.
This is even better if you do google papaya carving it is actually even better than pumping
carving it is like ornamental fruit carving.
Yeah that's because yeah maybe I'll learn to do that instead of the dremel one.
That's so pretty.
Yes do a scary one.
They are pretty yeah no okay apparently you can carve papayas and that's amazing.
Yeah brilliant.
All right well I know what I'm doing for for Halloween.
I need for papaya and a very sharp knife.
And it's a Thai thing apparently.
Yeah it's fruit carving.
So I was totally wrong and in fact papaya carving a papaya is something you can do.
I admit I made a mistake.
Right click that out John.
That's going to be the episode title yeah.
Good excellent.
Before we go into let us a comment a reminder to everyone that we are doing
Octa Thorpe live at Novicon at 1pm on Sunday.
This will be episode 45.
So come along and shout things at us.
I would like to state that a correspondent in Discord, one mr Andrew Hogg did call it
forkeda thought live.
Does that work?
F-folk to Thorpe.
F-folk to Thorpe yes like it's not quite full octa Thorpe.
Hogg also says I was replaced by an actor at some point after seeing the ZZ9AGM video
and Andrew January said that he's approaching that point where he's not confident he's ever
known what John looks like.
So yeah I'm glad to have sown confusion and doubt.
We got a letter of comment.
Yay.
From Chris Garcia.
Hey.
Who says it was another good episode and one that provided an eye opener.
Alison lived in America.
Does she still know the secret handshake?
Alison do you still know the secret handshake?
No.
Don't.
Well that was less funny than I was expecting.
Yeah sorry.
Stimulance not yet coursing through my veins.
Right.
I mean I know that I've had several days to think of a funny repost.
Have another go.
Chris says Alison lived in America.
Does she still know the secret handshake?
Yes but it's not a handshake.
Oh.
Is that better?
It's got an air of mystery about it.
Interesting.
He also says that the next drink tank is all about Lego and I should write about the Lego club.
And instead of writing about the Lego club I've told you all that he said I should.
Nailed it.
We also got a tweet of comment from Richard Bradshaw who tweeted a link to
a itinerary for traveling from London to Thailand and Liz responded.
Yes so crucially there is currently one missing link which is basically you can get as far as
either the Chinese border or Hanoi but there's no direct train links at the moment through any
of the countries that border Thailand to the north and east and west but it looks like they're
going to open a railway from Vientiane and Lao to coming in China which means that missing
link will be solved and it will be feasible to take a train I think all the way from Bangkok
and go all the way around through China, Russia, Mongolia if you want to you know and then from
Moscow you can get a train to Paris then from Paris you can get the train to London and you'd
be sorted you could in fact come all the way to Novakom on the train but you'd have to start like now.
So my first question was but can you do it in 80 days bearing in mind the location of the
international state line and my open brackets spoiler for a novel published in 18 um tm.
Secondly it would be really funny if it turns out the difficulty with getting from Bangkok to
Buxton by public transport was in fact the terrible train service to Buxton which would not be
impossible. We also heard from Alibaba and Sea Dave and Androsin on Facebook you too can comment
on Facebook if you join the Optorpe Facebook group there's a link in the show notes. You also have
to sell your soul to Mark Zuckerberg which you might not want to do and if you don't do that we
are available on another a number of other fine platforms that are not owned by Facebook. Yes so
Anne said in response to um my discussion of the hit checkers guide books I had as a kid which had
the four covers you could arrange it for different ways she said I have those book covers but not
the box if it was a box set which is typical rosin behaviour uh don't worry and I don't think
they came in a box that was it.
A couple of conventions have announced their covid policies in what is rapidly becoming a
feature of octa thought in the covid policy roundup it's the covid policy roundup it's the covid
policy roundup. The octa thought covid policy roundup. Like my jointly tuned um yes so smothcon has
announced their covid policy and Alison is going to tell us about it. So smothcon we're waiting
apparently until Portugal updated covid regulations on the first of October which a lot of countries
have. So as of the first of October in Portugal mask wearing at conferences is mandatory
mask wearing in bars and restaurants is not required digital certification of vaccination is
required by bars but not hotels or restaurants. Smothcon is doing all of that plus they're
additionally ensuring good social distancing and ventilation in their program spaces.
All members need to either be vaccinated before attending or have written to the convention
to tell them they're not vaccinated so they can arrange to give them a test on arrival and at any
rate everybody has to come to the convention having either had a recent lateral flow test
and or have some evidence of having had that or take a lateral flow test they'll have lateral
flow tests on reception to test everyone they're going to have sanitation stations. Portugal has
a strong uptake of vaccination and has 70% of the population vaccinated. I don't know if that's
70% of adults or 70% of the entire population which sounds pretty good if it is. Yeah Portugal
has astonishingly high vaccination rates isn't it? That's like tick vg isn't it? I mean that's what
you want. Yeah yeah no it sounds good. Well I do have a sorry I have a question when they say that
you need a digital covid pass to get into bars do we know what that entails? It's the EU parcel the
NHS pass I think. I've seen something because prior to the first October I was worried that my NHS
pass would not do for me but in fact in practice I believe that carrying everything on paper also
works perfectly well in Portugal people say. Okay but obviously not all countries have a
vaccination certificate that will work in Portugal. Yes I have a digital vaccination certificate but
it is not interoperable with the EU digital covid pass so I assume there is some wiggle room there.
You're not coming to Smofcon though are you? No but I could feasibly come to Smofcon.
Yeah so I think there are people coming to Smofcon from around the world and I think it would be
interesting to see what happens there but obviously Portugal doesn't want to trash its
conference trade from the United States so they'll be doing something. Yes! Alongside Smofcon
core flu concord has released their covid policy in PR5 and they'll be linked in the show notes.
So basically as far as I could tell they are saying that masks double vaccination and regular
thorough hand washing are not compulsory but very strongly encouraged. They say also that
Novacons guidance is excellent and they've reprinted it and Novacons are saying that members should
be vaccinated where possible so yeah I guess basically do what Novacons says and then go to
core flu. I'm kind of like what I really require of these things it should probably less than John
does is that conventions have a policy and publicise it and obviously we slightly prefer more
stringent policies but actually the important thing is having is that the committee have thought
about it and written something down and I'm quite glad that all of the conventions that I'm going
to in the next few weeks have got these hopefully I won't catch covid whilst gallivanting around the
world. I mean it's a bit like a code of conduct in that my minimum is that I require one but I do
have slightly higher standards than that for what I would expect to see in it but mostly I want
you to have one and have thought about it. Yes core flu is a very small convention though and in fact
all three of these conventions are quite small so Eastacon we're looking at you to set standards here.
Yeah Novacon full? Novacon are I believe close to full. They're closing memberships on the 9th of
November you're not going to be able to buy memberships if you rock up on the day that will not be
possible. I believe last time I looked at the membership list they're coming up on 250 members
and I don't have a feel for how many people usually go to Novacon but I have a hunch that is
towards the top end of attendance. Yeah they're at 254 members at the moment. Yeah that's quite high
for an Novacon for but it's because it's Novacon 50 they were always expecting it to be a big one.
I don't think it's just that though I think it's also because it's the first
in-person convention in the UK like four. That's not core flu. Oh fancy come. Novacon's the first
general science fiction invention that's not not specific I think that's a better way to say it
apart from BristolCon. No because BristolCon's the one day con. So Novacon is the first full weekend
general science fiction convention. I think Novacon will probably be the biggest that will have been
held for a while so I don't think fancy con was 250 people. If they have 250 people at anything
I think that will be bigger. Anyway yes so we will link to the core flu covid policy in the show notes.
Core flu has 69 members. Nice of whom I think about 50 are attending so it is much smaller than
Novacon. Yeah it'll get some more at the last minute and we have some Americans flying over
which is quite nice so there's going to be a nice small international fancy focused crowd for
core flu and that sounds pretty good to me. This episode of OctaThop is sponsored by Stoshirts.
Here we are in the season of mists mellow fruitfulness in-person super spreader events and holiday
planning and what better than to get unusual shirts, mugs and other paraphernalia with
fanish and nerdy themes from Stoshirts. Stoshirts designs are unique and targeted closely on the
sorts of people who listen to OctaThop. I for instance have a punctuation hoodie which keeps me warm
at times of year when it is not as warm for instance in a minute. Admittedly I bought it in the summer
and so I haven't really been able to test it but I'm assuming it will work because it is a hoodie.
You can visit octaThop.stoshirts.com for a carefully curated range of goodies including our own
OctaThop merchandise by which we mean we have a t-shirt and you can use secret code OctaThop
for 10% off. Thank you to Stoshirts for sponsoring OctaThop and enabling amazing sound effects like
this. So we're going to talk today about guests of honour and how they're announced and
I thought we were talking about bidding for Eastercons and Worldcons so there is a tradition
amongst traditional science fiction conventions by which I mean really Eastercons and Worldcons
and conventions in that vein where there is a bidding process and you might not be the seated
convention of not announcing your guests of honour until you are until you have won the bid
so that people who are voting for you do not know who you are planning to have as guests and that
cannot form part of the voting process. So the reason for doing this and the reason it's a tradition
is that the conventions have argued that we're not having guests as some form of marketing strategy
the guests are there because they're being honoured and as such if you give people the
opportunity to vote on those guests it's not an honour they're kind of going oh do we like that
person do we not like that person however that has a major downside as John will explain.
So there is a there is a potential negative here which is obviously if everyone is very happy
with your guests of honour then it works super well but if you have picked a guest of honour
who is problematic for any reason then that can mean that when people find out who your guests of
honour are they have concerns or issues and those can be concerns or issues around kind of the
Me Too movement and Code of Conduct violations in Day Gone By but it can also be stuff like
we saw with Discon 3 and Tony Vyskoff where she was uninvited as a guest of honour after it turned
out that the Bayon boards had been involved to some extent in the January the 6th insurrection
in the United States and so there is like a potential issue there and so it's kind of it's
kind of there are I think good arguments that either one has its ups and its downs.
Recently the astounding and the otherwise awards were renamed after it was realised that there
were potential issues with the people for whom they were originally named and this has spilled
over I think into discussions of guests of honour in recent times where there is a concern that
honouring certain people might be problematic from certain angles. This is something that I think
hasn't yet been addressed by the mode of keeping the guests of honour secret until the bid wins
because it means that any problems with the guest of honour also can't be challenged as part of the
bid process and this is I think potentially an issue that hasn't yet been discussed in the genre
and I think it is an issue that is going to be shortly addressed in the genre because of the
current push towards trying to avoid honouring people who are who have problematic aspects.
So okay so the problem here is that there are two ways of doing this one is to do your due
jillindance before you invite people and say aha we want to invite this person to have any
skeletons in their closet and ask around and people will tell you and then you make your judgments
and if you say oh no we're going to invite them anywhere and in the case of Tony Wyscop that's
what happened they knew perfectly well what people said about Tony they invited her anyway
and then as a result of the insurrection part of which would be fermented in the spaces that Tony
you know encouraged and didn't discourage they decided that position was untenable so it's not
quite the same thing but they certainly knew about the issues at the point where she was invited that
was part of the point um discon is in some respects a southern convention and that was a thing that
they were doing I mean I think I have some so the problem is that the question is really do you want
to do a thing where you go oh we're thinking of having so and so as a guest oh community tell
us if they're good enough because that's essentially what you're saying and I kind of I kind of hate
that idea I think if you're going to say we're honouring people then it is it is incumbent on
you to make sure they're worthy of being honoured and then announce them and then follow through with
that I think in practice you have to do your due diligence and decide what you're doing in private
whether you announce them with the bid or you announce them with the con because if you announce
if you announce your guests when you announce your bid then and people don't want them as a guest
of honour then they will basically tell you why this person should not be honoured by your
convention and then your choice is either to stick with them at which point the vote becomes not just
a vote on the bid but a vote on the bid's guests which you know is is something we is something we
could consider doing or you might be in a position where the bids are then saying well actually should
we change our guest of honour mid-bids as some you know disinvite them as conventions have done
so I think you kind of move you just kind of move the whole thing to an early affair
but a phase where there is a potential for people to say actually we really dislike this decision
you've made on guest of honour and therefore we are going to vote for the other bid and in a
case where there isn't another bid people would then say actually we feel so strong about this we
are going to mount a rival bid and I think I think there is an argument that that could be a desirable
thing that you give people that that chance to vote but it also brings in the fact that people
are then just going to vote for cons where they don't have a problem with the other bids guest of
honour they just like this set of guests of honour more and then you do turn it into kind of a
popularity contest between the different bids I think that's both the advantage and disadvantage
of doing it that way which is firstly it means if you pick someone problematic who people do have
a problem with they have some agency in pushing back against that that isn't asking you to uninvite
the person and I remember at the time that Discon was uninviting Tony Allison and I had a big
argument about whether or not that was acceptable I was very much on the side off they should disinvite
her and Allison was very much on the side off you don't disinvite a guest once you've invited them
and I think the problem with that is it's much easier if you if you are making the guests of honour
part of the bidding process it means that if people don't like a guest they can vote against the bid
and then the bid never has to disinvite someone the bid can be defeated and there's no issue of honour
there but there's still a mechanism by which the guest of honour can be not honoured and it means
the community can express opinions about problematic guests without asking conventions to go back on
invitations which I think I think would be a positive the the negative obviously is like if
you have a world con that announces like three local authors from the country that the world
con is being held in or from the state that the world con is being held in all of whom are not
quite as famous and then you have a world con that goes for massive like well-known global authors
that is going to sway things and that would be I think a disadvantage and I think that is a difficult
thing I don't know if I think either one is clearly better but I do wonder whether
if we're not going to make the guests part of the bidding process convention bid committees need
to think very carefully about what their procedure is should there become a problem with a guest
after they've won and after that's been announced let me backtrack a bit when you say a problem with
a guest clearly there's some cases where there are major problems with guests but there are also
cases where what you actually have is a load of twitter people going off on one and we are
too quick to say people going off on one on twitter without having thought through issues
matter more than the considered opinions of people who have thought through the issues and
come to a conclusion and we need to be much better about saying people's immediate reactions on
twitter in some cases because somebody one person has fermented a row where they said get a thousand
people to write in we make these knee-jerk reactions and actually if you took a step back you go well
you know yes in this case there is there is a case to answer here in this case maybe not
but also how do we know because I think this business of judging the behavior of people of the past
we have some cases where people did do all right things where we absolutely know they're problematic
and we can look at them and go oh yes we would never we would never accept this thing now but we
have other cases where we're actually it's just not that there's just not that much evidence people
are just going off on one I think it's hard to discuss this without like going into the evidence
and the merits of specific cases I mean I do agree that generally if something is on twitter it
that a lot of people express very strong feelings about it very immediately and I think we've discussed
before how that can kind of pressure cons also into taking very quick judgments because there is
that pressure weighing down on them but I think in certain case it has been like the only route
I'm going to bring up here Frank Miller who was invited to Thought Bubble this year as a guest
and now Thought Bubble has no bid process it's just a convention and they announced their guests and
they announced Frank Miller a lot of people said we would prefer Frank Miller as not a guest because
of his extremely islamophobic works and it turned out that basically the person who brought this up
had contacted Thought Bubble privately and nothing happened and so they were forced to take it public
in order for something to happen so I think it is good that we we do have this route
where people can bring public pressure especially if the convention seems unwilling to take their
concerns seriously and the outcome of this is that Frank Miller has been
disinvited as a guest which is something I think I would personally agree with
I think I think that's a very good point which is if you don't have this being part of a bid
process and obviously with Thought Bubble that wasn't something that would ever have happened
but if you wait for it to be part of the convention there's an enormous amount of
inertia on the sense of convention not to have to say oh we have goofed we're going to go back on
that and one of the only ways to make that equation swing in the in the sense of because if you're
a convention you've you've invited a guest disinviting them looks bad and so the only way for people
to exert pressure is to make it look worse if they don't and that's where you get the big public
things coming from and you see the same thing with with private companies like someone complains
through the official customer service channels and nothing happens and then someone posts on
Twitter and retweet starts happening and suddenly the company goes back on it and and so it and it
is annoying it is annoying that that's how it works but I don't think it's necessarily
I think it's very understandable why it ends up working like that quite often and I think it's
all to do with kind of perception and pride and and sort of those kinds of things as Liz says.
I want to take this open a little bit more broadly because you did touch on the fact that some
conventions choose their guests because this person is a stalwart of the community and we want to
one of them and some people or they write very very good books and we would like to bring them
to a wider to wider notice and some people choose their guests on the basis of who will put the most
bums on seats and I don't know are these equally valid approaches? Wilcon has an internal I don't
know if it's formally a rule but they have an internal notion that people will have spent 25
years in the field before they get invited as a Wilcon guest and that means that we often get
complaints that all the Wilcon guests are very old as a result of that and that's why you get
and that's why you get people like Charlie Jane and Charlie Jane Anderson and Lee Newitz being invited
to be Toastmasters right because you don't need to have done a certain amount of work to be Toastmaster
but it does let you celebrate let's you celebrate kind of younger members of the community because
the Toastmasters not a Wilcon guest and actually that's a really good point because it does
I guess it does mean that especially with Wilcons you do end up with a with a pool that is more likely
to have perhaps said things in the past then or proud of and wanted to to change although I can't
remember many yeah but there's different there's different ways there's a very standard way of
dealing with this which is somebody says oh in at such and such a time you were saying such and such
a thing and you go you're right I should never have done that I am terribly sorry I have given a
proportion of my income to the teddy bears protection league or whatever because of the terrible things
I've said in the past and and everyone goes oh right then mostly I obviously don't people can't do
that which is important if you're thinking of honoring dead people and there are some things
for which that's not considered be adequate but that's not mostly the case for the people in our
community no and I think I think like obviously most world cons the only world cons that have
honored dead people I think are people who died after they were announced with I think there's one
exception right but I can't remember what the one exception is there's a ghost of honor for one
world con right yeah I can't remember who it was there have occasionally been guests of honor at
world cons and Easter cons it's a great pun and then it is normal for world cons to um continue to
want a guest who died in the who weren't tended to be guests and have now died um I think I'm back
to um you do need to do your work though so I also because I'd slightly prefer to see guests who
may not be 100% perfect people but are towering figures in the community and again that there's a
borderline there because there are things I don't want to you know I don't think we should be inviting
Islamophobic American comic artists you know that sort of thing um but or because one of the
alternatives to that is to invite people who nobody has ever heard of and and it is certainly
true that if you do that the chances that people will have things to say about them is much reduced
but it makes your convention a bit less exciting I mean obviously there is a middle ground in between
inviting racists and people no one's met there is but I mean so uh to take for example some years
ago now a primarily on live journal which tells you all it was there was the whole um race fail
thing right yeah and a lot of names in science fiction and fantasy were involved in it and many
of them are subsequently invited to conventions as guests as I know and I'm sure some of them have
discussed it and discussed their feelings better at the time I mean I think certainly like my
you know I think I'm certainly like my opinions and thoughts on things have definitely changed
like in the that 15 year span or whatever and I'm sure a lot of theirs have as well but in some cases
we now have like these discussions that were taking place online and can be you know we're there
for everyone to see and I think the key thing to get to think about is like if you're inviting
this person as a guest and there is something in their history where you feel like this could
be a problem for many attendees and the thing to do is to look at it and see you know what kind of
magnitude was it and what is their response now to you bringing it up to them is their response to
say yes that was you know a mistake I made in the past and I have done this to you know make up for
it or is it them to say you know that's the thing I did in the past it's all ancient history or is
the thing say yes it's something I did in the past and I would stand by those opinions now and I'm
thinking again of wisc on who is the wisc on guest of honor so this is the like the first one I can
think of where someone was disinvited as a guest of honor Elizabeth Moon that was it
I remember this and this was way back in 2010-2011 she was disinvited essentially for saying things
on her blog that were not acceptable to membership so you know this is not entirely a new thing that
is happening but obviously I would guess at the time that this happened because they were online
and it could spread around whereas previously that might have been in a fanzine with limited
circulation I think race fell is interesting because it did two there was two things going on
there so first of all plenty of people who really shouldn't have been were were on the the wrong
side of that argument but also some of the the argument was not just being advanced by people
of good intentions and character it was also being stirred by an agitator so not an agitator because
somebody who who was um oh I want I think science fiction fandom really needs to address this which
it did and has done now I think a lot um but also somebody who was like I can increase my personal
store by making this a bigger argument than it would otherwise be so and that that turned out to
involve a lot of quite bad behavior so it's complicated when you're when you're making arguments you might
not also want to make death threats that sort of thing that's true Alice and I originally
disagreed on disinviting Tony vice-cough but then when she doubled down and said to the
main forums were fine and didn't need any um work that was the point of which we both very much
were in agreement of oh no like she could start off and if she had launched a widespread program
of reform I would have been like maybe they should re-invite her because she's clearly
because there needs to be an incentive for people coming around to a perspective that the community
finds more compelling I think and maybe that doesn't need to take the form of honoring them but like
I don't know like if you are showing that you're like in the case of race fail if you said things
that you then reflected on and are no longer representative of your opinions I don't think
that should disqualify you from being a guest of honor necessarily if if you've done that work
but if you if you're Elizabeth Moon and you've stood by the things you wrote that got you disinvited
from Wizcon I'd be surprised if a world con then invited Elizabeth Moon as a guest of honor
because I don't think she has done that work and that Wizcon disinvited invitation was a decade
ago now which is terrifying yeah so this has all been going on for quite a long time yeah I I must
admit and I'm really glad Liz brought that up because I had forgotten that that had happened
but but that is actually a really good point that this I was I was very much thinking of this as a
kind of recent discussion but it but it isn't as much as I thought it was I think it's gotten louder
but I don't think it's new in some ways I think it's got less loud I think science fiction fandom
reflected after all of that and to a very large extent put its stall in order
and one of the things that we're not bad at is taking the being a global community seriously and
and making the sorts of changes to our behavior that you need to do if you are a global community
we are not perfect collection of individuals individuals never perfect but I think you do see
over and over again in SF that we have these sorts of arguments and then we go oh well does that
mean we have to change and change itself people it takes longer than it should we're not as good
as it might be I don't think race fail which I wasn't really involved with but was reading at the time
is a thing I can really put into context but I can link a couple posts in the show notes which do
I want from NK Jemisin in 2010 talking about it and you know what good things might have come
out of it and there's one from Jamie Go last year in Strange Horizons thinking about definitions
of whiteness and Eurocentrism and how they end up post-race fail so I will put those in the show
notes when he wants to go and read up on it more I want to those links to a primer on it on fan
law in case you missed this discussion entirely which you may have because it was in 2009
on the topic of race fail and I'll sort of go of ethnicity and privilege I think the other
thing that's worth knowing is that we are obviously all coming at this from a kind of
European white perspective and I don't know the extent to which like if you're a person of color
in the States I don't know how you viewed Tony Vice-Cough's invitation kind of before the
controversy in January you thought it was terrible and you thought it told you something about
disc golf and what sort of convention it was I mean not all of them but many of them because
people are not coherent block and I suspect that many of our listeners are in fact in the same
boat as we are so so I obviously like our perspectives are limited and we we I think are all mindful
of our privilege but if you are if you have any thoughts on this from that perspective please do
write in because I'd be interested to hear them I think this links is background which is if you
are a convention and you are thinking of inviting someone as a guest of honor and you are trying
to do your due diligence and talk to people then you have to talk to people who have a different
perspective than you do and yeah you also have to think about what it means if you do decide to
invite that person because I suspect yeah what it meant was a lot of fans looked at this con and
maybe said this is not the convention for me and they have alternatives they can go to other
conventions they can go to firecon where they know they're going to feel much more comfortable
and I think you have to think about what this says about the ethos and the nature of your convention
and the people you want to attract and what sort of convention you want to be and your
guess of honor are like the one of the public expressions of the convention you would like to be
which doesn't mean you can just invite diverse guess of honor and have done with it but you do
need to think about who you invite as guess of honor as part of it I will also say that although I
absolutely accept I am dripping in with white privilege Liz and I are both women and all sorts
of things are continuing to demonstrate that people have not learned the you know I'm still
watching new movies I am reading new books where the notion that women are people and
should not therefore example be given as prizes to the hero the notion that women deserve to have
equal roles in in science fiction is still kind of out there and um frankmiller is not just a
lamaphobic you know um so so so it's not just about race um I would like you know you want people
who demonstrate that they take well essentially the the humanity of women as as a critical part of
what they're doing as well please and I think this is all just about thinking about your guests and
why you're inviting them and what what the honor believes and should you do it when you bid
convention committees bemoan the fact that you want people to bid on the basis of how competent
the people are to run the convention and what you actually get is people bidding on how much they
want to visit a Winnipeg rather than Shendue or whatever um and so all you do if you add guests
into the bidding mix is that you give people another thing to vote on that isn't how competent
the committee is so I want to say two things which is firstly and this is something that's been
happening in the I listened to an actual play podcast and they had someone right to them basically
saying like actually you've got this thing in your kind of basic and seat which is super problematic
in terms of like ethnicity and they hired a cultural consultant to come on and kind of um
talk it through with them and they made changes based on that and I think that's the thing it is
not about not making mistakes but it's about when you notice you've made the mistake taking the
actions you need to take as a result and I do wonder whether conventions like I wonder whether
cultural consultants might be the sort of people that might be able to help out with that but I don't
know um to what extent that's true on the topic of the difference between ethnicity and gender I do
notice that all three of the examples we've currently got in the show notes are examples where someone
was found out to have problematic views in terms of um white privilege or ethnicity and were then
disadvantaged and as far as I can tell we haven't mentioned any examples where people have been
disinvited for things connected to sexism or things connected to me too or things like that
so I wonder whether that will be when I was saying this is a newer discussion I wonder whether the
thing that's newer is in fact the more gender component to the conversation because I do think
gender has been something we've we've kind of come on a little bit on in the last few years with
discussions like me too. I am going to just mention that there was a lot of
disquiet about the Saudi Arabian bid for WILCON and it's complicated because the a lot of the
disquiet was focused about around LGBT rights um and I'm kind of like and that is all very well
but they have half the population enslaved and you're not doing anything about it so you know
again I feel like I feel like the gender issues are often not um not quite as um
probably because they ought to be um but you know we have common cause there but so the Saudi
Arabian bid despite the fact that the the fans who are bidding are absolutely lovely had people
expressing a great deal of concern and I think also there's a great deal of concern around um
the Chengdu bid because of the Chinese government's um record on human rights um
so I just want to say one more thing which is in googling for ghosts of honor and I didn't find
anything on ghosts of honor so if either of you do have good links please pop them oh I found it yeah
oh good good but pork or nail back in 2011 suggested a um suggested the concept of the um
ghost of honor future so as well as the ghost of honor past and the guest of honor present you
have the ghost of honor future uh and it was you have an unknown individual listed as a guest of
honor and then you have a vote at like the world con 50 years out to retrospectively decide like
who was born that year who would have been who has made the biggest contribution to the genre
and I like I think obviously because the point of the guest of honor is to impact the programming
so I'm not really sure whether it works as like a logistical con running concept but it is kind of
cool I do quite like the idea of of of trying to have like the person for each world con who was
born that year who had the greatest effect on the community thereafter um so I've put a link to his
blog post in the show notes because I made me smile. Beckon H7D Succon had hg wells as the ghost of
honor and they had um Ian Watson dressing up as hg wells and we had a plan and giving a very good
very well received ghost of honor speech in the body of hg wells and I'm sure hg wells was problematic
but you know it's quite a long time ago for both hg and um hg wells and of course um the plot.com
in 2000 had was expecting to have a lot of fetuses at it because um because Caroline and I were both
very pregnant at the time of the convention and as was Laurie Meltzer but in fact Laurie couldn't
come to the convention because her baby decided to come seven weeks early so there we go.
Shall we do pics? Yeah yeah let's do quick pics quickly. Quick little pickles. Quick pics.
Alright I went see shong chi and the legend of the 10 rings I enjoyed it a lot. In the cinema did
you go to the cinema? I went see it in the cinema on a Tuesday at 1045 there were two other people
which honestly was busier than I was expecting. That's what I'm planning to do for dune? That's
fair um the I quite liked it. It cheats for sort of two key reasons which is firstly it's got
aquafina in it and I love aquafina so I was always always going to be partial to this particular
movie and she is very good in it and secondly it's set in san francisco and I do love san francisco.
Unsurprisingly listeners I enjoyed it. Yeah no I'd accidentally got the impression it was set in
china so there you go but I learned that this is about the chinese american experience and chinese
americans often love this movie. So the beginning of the film is set in san francisco and then by the
end they are in china. It is it is very good. I enjoyed it a lot and I was glad I went see it.
I think it might be in my top five marvel movies because I really did very much enjoy it but as I
said it is it is very much my cup of tea and it reminded me weirdly of always be my maybe which I
also love and it's also set in san francisco and it's got aliwong and rundal park in and they're
very good and I would recommend that film as well. So you know cheeky extra pick.
It is it has lots of chinese culture in it lots of the dialogue is in mandarin and people from
around asia have commented on how it's got it's a superhero with a chinese backstory that is
not racist. This is good. I mean I might say there's quite a low bat there's quite a low bar to
what are you what are you quoting there though? I'm the new york times.
Alison do you want to do pics?
Yeah I it has been a week since we last recorded and I believe that I have done
no genre reading or watching in that week apart from a bit more foundation.
I have instead watched more of the new season of tus master very funny.
I have read a book called the how not to die diet which is kind of related in that it was given to
me by the science fiction fan who runs publishing company but other than that it doesn't really
have anything to do with science fiction. Spoiler immediately adopt a plant based whole foods based
diet that is very low in processed foods. Bit depressing really and and I started to read a large
book about the fact song of england. I thought you were doing quick pics Alison.
I've said I waffled for five minutes and that isn't even five minutes.
Yeah I don't think we need five minutes on.
On things such a lot genre.
So no genre for me this week.
I also I mean I did consume some genre things this week but I didn't like
the very much and I don't really mean about them on the podcast so I'll go with the genre thing
which I finished consuming last week. I mean I'm going to call it genre. I basically finished playing
the fourth uncharted game. They are basically what if you were playing a video game but it was sort
of Indiana Jones but with more pirates and stuff. So basically they're fun action ventures and they
also get much better as the series goes on because in the first one the protagonist is really
just a dick and by the fourth one he's become a likable dick.
You know the fourth one is the sort of I've given up the treasure hunting business and I've gone
legit but my brother comes to visit me and he pulls me back in for one last vital mission etc.
But by the last one they've just become incredibly slick experiences and it is kind of as close as
you can get to actually playing a movie and I'm pressing the buttons at the right time to leap
off the ledge and so on. Alison's making a face at me because Alison's saying these are sort of
games she'd hate but they're lots of fun. I mean I'm good I don't know if I mentioned Baba as you
last um Octa thought but I am playing Baba as you. I am completely stuck in multiple different places
so I like the sense of a game that makes you think a lot and where you get stuck and
preferably without any cutscenes or if there have to be cutscenes can they make them short please.
There are a lot of cutscenes in this but I mean this is an orchy dog game and they are
basically spectacularly better at cutscenes than most people because I think they literally
have the actors do them and you know motion kept the face to make it look like it is actually a
person rather than sort of an assembly of polygons in some way but their actors look
incredibly good and so when you're watching the cutscenes it is like you are watching a scene
from a movie and I think they can do that by only having like five characters and they spend
lots of time lovingly getting the mocap working for those five characters basically.
I put some YouTube vids in. It's just a movie isn't it it's a movie. Yeah but it's a fun movie where I
get it's a movie with buttons yeah it's basically a movie with buttons where I get to climb up the
cliff and stuff. Why isn't it a movie where you can play Crash Bandicoot in the middle? Oh you do
have to play Crash Bandicoot and that's really annoying but it's over as soon as you die so.
And it is genre because any universe in which someone can kill that many people and still be
charismatic must not be set in our universe. I mean the other counterpoint to that is James Bond
whose body count in the latest James Bond film is astonishing. That was the 43rd episode of the
OctaThought Podcast. Thank you very much again to Stow shirts for sponsoring this episode of
the podcast and it's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me.
OctaThought, OctaThought. You can listen to us and talk and to John and list two. OctaThought
is here for you. We discuss, we review on everything we have of you. Talking cons and talking fans if
it's Fandor, OctaCork and... Look how here comes an OctaThought. We will not be doing
OctaThought live at Corflu but that's because we're doing OctaThought live at Novocon. I mean
effectively you will be doing OctaThought live at Corflu it's just it will be at 1am and it will
be in the bar and it will just be John and it's talking loudly. I've got a microphone on my phone.
We could record a little bit of OctaThought. We could record a little segment for OctaThought
live from the bar at Corflu. We can ring Liz. We can ring Liz a record and all to
thought which is just us leaving messages on Liz's voicemail. No no no what time what time
are we staying up to? What time will it be in Bangkok? If you stay up late enough I will have got up.
It'll be six hours ahead. No I will be seven hours ahead because the clocks have changed.
Yes so it'll be seven hours ahead. Yes brilliant. So we could do that thing where we are drunk
in the middle of the night and Liz is having breakfast and she's like oh we're like high Liz.
Yeah pretty much. It's Alice and Johnny the bar.
Drunk but it's just the morning and I am sober but I haven't on the max. If you could have
raged to have an on the max at that point that would be really awesome. Okay let's let's not get
too ambitious because I am going to have to get up early for this. I'm not sure I'm going to get
up early enough to go out and buy an onalmon max but I will try. How early is it? Well how late are
you going to stay up? I don't know. At least 2 am. I don't know John is a lightweight so these days.
Well I stay up later at conventions as I do on zoom. We'll see and you'll have a couple of goals
at it I guess. Let me see when the quest on shop opens. I think we should probably aim for Friday
night. We are going to be there Thursday night. I might be very drunk by Friday night though.
We I don't think are going to be there on Thursday night and also on Friday Liz will have work
and doing it on a day that Liz has work seems a bit unusual. Yeah we can't do it Thursday night so
Friday night Saturday morning. I'm just glad that all of this is going in the podcast so that
people can hold us to it. Well the quest on shop where they serve the onalmon maxis which
I will not we have not explained on the podcast yet so maybe that could be the pick for whenever you
phone me up drunkenly. They open 830 so I might have to go and get one the day before just to be ready.
Okay. You might have to stick it in your oven. That's okay. Almond questions don't really like
being kept overnight. What do you mean? What do you mean? That'd be fine but I think I will need
Almond Quest on a coffee to cope with you guys. The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for
Space by Kevin MacLeod and Comfatec.com used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.
[no audio]