I got distracted and was looking at that website, putting.cool.
Putting.cool?
And so therefore I've missed the start of this section of the podcast
and have no idea what you guys are talking about.
I'm sorry.
Let's just move on.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 101st episode of Octa Thorpe,
a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom,
which is coming to you on the 18th of January 2024.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
We had some letters of comment.
We start with competition winner Christopher J. Garcia.
Oh ho.
And it pleased me to listen to Hugo Girl the other day
where they read out Goodreads review by Chris.
Laurie was like, I'm going to read this out like John Reed's on Octa Thorpe.
Christopher J. Garcia and it may be Giggle.
So hello, Hugo Girl people. That was great.
So Chris is our competition winner.
He wins a copy of All These Worlds Reviews and Essays by Neil Harrison.
Chris, I will mail it to you when I'm in LA
because it will be cheaper than mailing it from Newcastle.
When are you in LA, John?
For galley.
Oh, we'll get back to that foreshadowing.
Congratulations on 100 Episues.
I do think I prefer it issue codes, but Episues is good.
He listened to 23 books, which according to Audible is 14,049 minutes,
which is quite a lot of minutes reading.
How many hours is that?
I'm going to put it to Liz that even though she read 96 books,
which is four times more than Chris,
she may have spent less minutes reading.
What do you reckon Liz?
So it says that 14,049 minutes is about 234 hours.
Now, I reckon I read about 100 pages an hour.
So the question is, did I read 23,000 pages?
No.
So no, it was definitely Chris,
but I would point out that I cannot multitask while reading,
whereas maybe, well, I know that John, not John,
I know that Chris can definitely multitask while reading
as he is abitually doing seven things at once before breakfast.
He can actually listen to an audiobook in his left ear
and octothorp in the right ear, which is a pretty magical skill.
He also notes the amazing thing about California libraries is that they no longer have fines.
Newcastle also doesn't have fines, which makes me much more likely to return things on time,
which is weird psychology.
It used to be when it was, I paid some money and if I was late,
I was just like, oh, I paid the money, it's fine.
And now it's like, no, don't be late because you're being inconsiderate.
And I'm like, but I don't want being inconsiderate.
I'm a nice boy.
So I return things on type.
And it's very curious how that psychology shakes out.
Can anyone tell me if Cambridge County Library system still has fines
because I think I might sit over them a fiver?
Is that your library fine, Si?
I can't find anything on the Cambridge Library's website about fines.
Oh, no, hang on, charges for late renewals.
25p a day, Liz.
Well, they weren't 25p a day at the time, but I think I dropped some books back
and then never went back into the library at one point.
So sorry, I probably owe them a fiver.
I hope they don't put interest on that.
Chris also said, "Romanticy dates back a long way.
He remembers Gale Carriger calling Solus back in 2009 or so."
Well, 2009 is a long time in internet time, no?
I think that was a long time.
I was 20, seems ages ago.
I think the genre has been around a lot longer than that,
even if it didn't necessarily have a name.
You know, I think there was a lot of that sort of stuff
knocking around when I were a lass.
Yeah, let me find the blog post I want to quote.
Carry on while I look for it.
Neil Harrison agrees with Chris Garcia.
So Neil says, on the marriage genre,
"He's looked into the matter and we can't blame
"or credit Goodreads for imagining romance.
"It's been at circulation for at least five years,
"although Goodreads has popularized it.
"But then he follows up with, but maybe Goodreads
"should invent new genres."
Spotify does this.
There's someone whose job is to look at the emergent patterns
from listening data and give names to different clusters,
which is how you end up with playlists for things like
Catstep, Chamber Psych, and Solip Synthum.
The fact they are based on actual listening behaviors
makes them fascinating.
Goodreads could do the same sort of things
and who knows what they'd come up with.
You cannot see on the pub,
but I am nodding vigorously to that suggestion
that Goodreads should be using its data in this way.
Step one, it wouldn't work very well
because your data set is so much smaller.
Like the number of tracks a music listener listens to
in a year is orders of magnitude higher than the number of books
most people read in a year.
And so I do think this probably works way better
for Spotify than it would for Goodreads.
And part of the reason I say this is because if you are interested
in doing this kind of analysis, I have a PhD project available
on using K-means clustering in order to evaluate
GMM and SS storms and hemispherek symmetries
in the Earth's magnetic field.
You can go to northumbria.ac.uk
or find a PhD.co.uk and search
and you will find the project.
So if you're interested in this kind of science,
come work with me.
New Castle's great.
I'm great.
Yay!
But what if I'm more interested in micro genres
of science fiction and fantasy that I have?
My recommendation is to do a PhD in clustering machine learning
and then go work for a company that does it.
It turns out many people who do PhDs on ML
end up working for companies doing ML rather than in academia
which is shocking.
Yeah, go and do a PhD with John
and then you can call yourself a data scientist
and machine learning specialist and earn quite a lot more money
than you would continuing to work for John.
Sorry, John.
Anyway, romantic.
Because having complained about it,
I think there's two things.
One is that yes, it clearly does exist as a category
and has existed before Goodreads started picking it up,
although maybe was not often called that.
And in fact, Adam Roberts had a blog post in mid-December
which I missed precisely about this and talking about
Jacqueline Carey's books as maybe one of the kind of first things
you can point at and say they are romantic.
The other thing is really I see it as Goodreads
adding an extra category into their awards for a thing where there are
maybe lots of books in this area, but it also feels a little bit like
let's take all these books out of fantasy and give them their own box
and I'm not sure how I feel about that.
Good.
I think you feel good about it.
Is that helpful?
Possibly.
I mean, Goodreads are reflecting what a chunk of readership is reading
and looking for in fantasy.
You see, when I'm kind of looking at a fantasy book to read,
I'm kind of looking at all the ones that aren't that.
So it's quite useful for me to have them offered a genre.
I mean, I guess I do read things that you could call romantic but just not that many.
Tell me if you think this is an untarable interpretation,
but I suspect you would find, my guess would have been that you'd find
the distinction useful because there are certain books.
So for instance with Legends of L'Arte's, right?
Like if that was in romanticity rather than fantasy, you'd be like,
"Oh, brilliant.
That's in the bit that I can safely ignore or dip into when I want to cosy read."
And these are the bits where I might actually nominate them for Who Goes.
But I don't think romanticity is kind of not romantic, though.
Yeah, I don't think romanticity is cosy.
What? What's the point?
The point is the romance, right?
It's the strong central romance as the thing, whereas when I read a fancy book
with a strong central romance, I go, "Oh, God, let me get back to my fantasy world."
And what's interesting and different about it?
Because if I wanted to read a romance book, I'd go and read a romance book.
In what way does Legends of L'Arte's not fill the description you just set?
Cos it's to me.
The central romance is wet and doesn't take up very much for the plot.
I mean, in that it has that in common with everything else in the book, but yeah.
I prefer the wet romance.
Well, what you want, Jon is smot talk, which is also a category apparently.
Smot talk.
Oh.
Yeah.
Hang on, smot.
Smot has in the Tom Lera song.
Yes, Jon, obviously.
It didn't have any smot.
Like, I'll put it this way.
I thought it was a lot more romance than I did smot.
Yes, but romance has a lot more smot in it than you think.
Yeah, so, romanticy probably has quite a lot of smot in it, I would think.
I have not that I've read a lot of it, but on average.
Listeners, if you are bigger readers of, like, romanticy than I am,
and I think I've read a handful of books you would pick as romanticy, but not that many,
please let us know kind of how you would define it.
Fair.
Shall we move on?
Yeah, I suppose so.
I think this is the living rights in saying that this is thoroughly insufficient as a letter
of comment, especially given how long it's been since they last sent us one.
Now, there is no minimum quality of lock required.
If we start getting into minimum qualities of products, some of our previous episodes
would be ropey at best.
So, yes, feel free to write us with any inane thoughts you like.
But Jerry notes that I forgot to credit one of the scenarios in, if I ran the zucon,
which is the BNF scenario by Priscilla Olson and Fred Isaacson, there's a joke,
so I'll put that in the show notes in a minute.
When that was a good one?
Yes, it was.
And then also went back to episode 98 and offers a small correction to Mark's lock,
which is Mark wrote that LA was in 1994.
And of course it was in 1984.
So, yes, unless it was time travel.
Mark, how was the 1994 LA WorldCom?
It would actually have been unallowed.
So, in the parallel universe when there was a 1994 WorldCom, it would have had to have been
after a change to the Constitution.
Or 1993, San Francisco didn't happen for some reason.
No, no, that's one of them.
What's names?
A fixed point.
That's the badger.
Alright, does that have to exist so that if Spaniel comes along so that you may later
meet a Spaniel at another WorldCom and get married?
Yes.
Oh.
Very important.
Bridget Bradshaw sends us a letter of comment saying, congratulations and thank you for 100 episodes.
You are most welcome.
Thank you for being here with us.
She says she is sad to hear unsung stories of Step Back from print publishing.
She messed up her plan not to buy books faster than she reads them when they offered 18 books for 50 quid.
And she sent us a photograph of a very lovely looking shelf with lots of very lovely looking paperbacks on it,
including the Corobones by E.J. Swift.
But she notes that the Corobones is out again in paperback, this time from Joe Fletcher Books.
And we will put a link to that in the show notes.
Thank you for pointing that out, Bridget.
What you could do is put that bookshelf in as chapter art.
Yes, I could do that.
That's a good idea.
Yeah.
For the two people who see the chapter art.
On the subject of 100th episode, congratulations.
We also heard from Fiona Moore and Johnny Badley and Dave Mansfield congratulating us for 100 episodes.
Thank you very much, folks.
And Trishy M. on Blue Sky also said that.
Yes.
We're on Blue Sky, by the way.
You can follow us.
I might post on it if I remember.
Bad at social media.
Edwin Mooreland also said not only a rare time, all of our picks were books, but also a rare time that he'd already encountered all of the picks.
We should announce what our next book club pick is going to be so that people can read it before we talk about it if they want to.
We should.
We also heard from Dave Mansfield, who said, "Dear Octagons, as an influencer on the Podbean socials, we'd love to get a shout out to your audience of Science Fiction and SF fandom.
The opportunity to hear about FunCon 1."
So this is a very excellent reproduction of emails we get on the regular from people who are like, "Hello, will you please influence on this thing?"
And I'm like, "No, go away."
But Dave is lovely, so we have not told them to go away.
So FunCon 1 is a weekend convention at the end of May, which is in the Palace Hotel in Buxton, and it is called Space Leopard, probably.
Won't eat your face.
Wear fun, meet science, meet fiction.
This is one of a number of conventions which are coming up in the next year, which we will henceforth talk about.
And FunCon 1 is in the hotel that NovaCon is in, usually.
So if you like that hotel, do go along. Or if you like fun.
I thought you were going to say this is one of a number of conventions which is happening this year in the Buxton Palace Hotel in Buxton.
It's a big weird if the Buxton Palace wasn't in Buxton when it happened.
I can open the Buxton Palace in Stafford just to confuse everyone.
So I'm going to mention very quickly that Contable A Triple Time, that's the 34th Film Convention, is happening on the 2nd to 4th of February in the Palace Hotel in Buxton.
So if you were a Filker, I don't know if we have any Filkers listening if you're a Filker.
Hello?
And that is also going to be in the Palace Hotel in Buxton.
And they haven't had an in-person film con for a few years, so this is quite exciting I think.
Emily January is a Filker, so we've got at least one.
And I hope all the Filkers already know about it because it is in like two weeks, so you've probably got a week to sign up for the day of this pod.
Yeah but somebody out there might go, "Filk, what on earth is Filk? I should look into it."
And Filk is science fiction and folk music guys, everyone knows that right.
And if you want to listen to it, I knew you'd like Buxton.
Yes, if you like Buxton.
I'm sure it'll be a lot of fun.
Uh, Filk is where you f*ck.
[
There is also probably PicoCon, which will probably be in February.
Probably. PicoCon is organized by undergraduates, and therefore the lead time on the announcement is not always what you might want it to be in an ideal world.
It's organized by the Imperial College Science Fiction Society, who may or may not be OntoGrads.
There may be grad students, which is probably a tiny step up in organizational capacity and busyness, but yeah.
It would be nice if they would let the world know when they're going to have PicoCon.
Something about now.
Do you want me to do my provocative people should stop complaining about this so you guys can vigorously disagree with me?
It can if you want, unless you're bored of that rant already.
I think that there is a segment of British Science Fiction Convention fandom who would quite like PicoCon to be a lot more organized than it is and have forgotten what it was like to be undergraduates.
So, I think that John may be talking out of his hat here because the thing about PicoCon is that it probably doesn't pay for, but books out the Imperial College Student Union for the whole of the Student Union for an entire Saturday.
And my theory is that this date that they're going to do this on is not actually still under negotiation, but it has in fact been in the diary for some considerable time, possibly since the day after PicoCon last year.
And they could perfectly well tell us what it's going to be. We're not asking for a lot.
We don't need you to do a whole thing with, you know, where do you have to go and what you do and just tell us the date it's going to be on so that we can turn up at Imperial College at 10 o'clock in the morning, or if you're me about 3 o'clock in the afternoon.
And come to a convention. It's normally about the third Saturday in February, but people like us. And I guess Dave Langford, who does the indispensable news fanzine answerable, would like to know before our deadlines.
If PicoCon is going to be before our next episode, please tell us so that we can publicize your convention. That's all we ask.
I suppose the question is, who is PicoCon for? If the thing of PicoCon is to try and get a bunch of people to turn up and pay a small entry fee and, you know, that helps the society have some money to do fun stuff, then you probably want to advertise it in time to have people turn up.
Whereas if it's just sort of like a day when we're going to spend a day talking about science fiction and being in the bar, then it's probably less essential that you advertise it early enough to get people to come in potentially from out of town.
I only ran one convention when I was an undergraduate, which was a convention called SabreCon, which we ran at the University of Leicester Students Union, but we did not run it to make money.
We spent all the money on things for the convention.
Possible they spend all the money, I don't actually know. I think we may all be too out of date to really speak to modern undergrads and what their lives are like now, though, but yeah, it's quite possible that they are all very busy frantically trying to get their money is worth out of their thousands of pounds they've spent on university.
Yup.
Yeah, and indeed last year PicoCon, which is always in February, was in March, so it's possible that that will happen again.
[Music]
Hello everyone, John from the future here. We heard after we'd recorded that PicoCon will be happening on the 23rd of March.
There is also going to be an EasterCon, which will be at the end of March, 2024, in a place called Telford, and will probably be good.
I'm going.
Liz isn't going.
Yeah, so, so not, it's going to be quite a small EasterCon, which I guess we probably knew because...
It's a WorldCon year.
The small ones are more juicy.
[Laughs]
I quite like Easter, a small EasterCon, because, you know...
I like all Eastercons, but small Eastercons do definitely have, they are definitely good Eastercons.
They have a vibe.
They're all good Eastercons, Brent.
We could discuss which were the good Eastercons in one of these.
Have a, have a, have a, what's the name of draft, where we draft Eastercons.
Oh yeah, can we have another one of these, please?
In the order we enjoyed them.
[Laughs]
Last thing about conventions, you can never go back.
Which convention would you like to go to again?
Though, I mean, I have a clear top of, clear winner of that, which is LugCon 3.
I would like to go again as a punter, rather as somebody who wore a high vis jacket for 17 hours.
I would like to go to LugCon 3.
I am as previously referenced going to a convention called Gallifrey 1, which will be in mid February
in LA, in the United States.
So if anyone is planning to be there, hit me, hit me up.
Say, say so, and we'll hang out, it'll be good.
Are you going to have Octa thought ribbons to give people John?
Errrr.
Don't know, probably not, but we'll see.
We are working on our cosplays, which will be very good.
They are British, genre, comedy, but they are not Doctor Who.
Ghosts?
No, better.
Ghosts, oh no, that was a little sad of me there.
She was.
Hmm.
British?
No, I am going to go as Garth Merengi.
Oh yes.
[Laughs]
I have brought a bull belt buckle and a pair of gold like glasses like the ones he wears.
Er, and we've got lab coats and it's just generally going to be great.
Nobody's going to realise you're cosplaying, are they?
That's brilliant.
I think they will.
I hope they will.
We haven't yet fully completed it, but we are working on it.
So I might have to have ribbons that say, "I know writers who use subtext and they're all cowards."
Yes.
Which is one of my favourite Garth Merengi quotes.
Absolutely.
Can I ask who is España being?
She's going to go as Liz Asher.
She's going to get a blonde wig and she's going to wear the beads.
That's the problem.
I, because she can't go, she can't go as Dean Learner, because I think it would be not obvious enough.
And she's not really got the frame from that berry.
She's definitely got the attitude.
Yeah, that's it.
I mean, I think it would be great if she was Dean Learner.
But, yeah, maybe not.
The one problem with Garth Merengi's Dark Place is that it was made in a time.
I think if it was made today, it would have a lot more women in it than it did at the time.
Are we sure España can't pull off Matt Berry?
Can she do the voice?
I'm sure she could pull him off.
And there will also be a world con.
I don't know if people are aware that Glasgow 2024 is occurring with maybe unturable, but we'll be
banged on about it a bit.
But we do have a couple of tidbits of Glasgow news.
And Liz put one of these in the show notes.
Liz.
Yeah, I put one in saying that Glasgow Hotel Bookings opened January 22nd, which I got off the Glasgow Welcome Facebook page.
Intrepid researcher Liz.
I'm going to go and check it and enjoy these typing noises.
Yes.
20 seconds.
Keep an eye on their socials for further information.
Nice.
If you are staff, you will have already had the link for Hotel Bookings.
Like it goes as Liz says, it goes live on the 22nd, which if you're listening to this on the day of release will be on Monday.
So look out for it on Monday.
We have booked in the Campanile or the Campanile, depending on how that word is pronounced.
Oh yeah, we're in the moxie I think.
I was going to go for the village.
John, I will just say I would check the recent reviews for the Campanile Campanile on TripAdvisor because they are a bit of a thumbs down.
Oh, they were right when I say their last time, but that was a little bit ago.
Yeah, they were fine when I stayed there in 2005.
From the reviews on the website, it sounds like they may not have updated the hotels since 2005.
So I'd have a quick check.
I think I'm going to go for the village, probably, which is a little bit pricier, but not much pricier.
The village also has a swimming pool.
That's really nice swimming pool.
Village hotels are kind of like swimming pools with hotels attached to them.
It does, but how, I mean, I thought about that, but then I also thought how much am I going to go swimming during your World Cup?
Yeah, that was why we ended up on the right side of the river.
Yes, in case anyone has not been on Worldcon staff, generally what happens is they let the staff book a little early,
so they can break the booking website in all kinds of different ways before we let the general public loose on it.
But that does mean you get to book a little bit early.
Yes, which makes sense.
Yeah, it totally makes sense, but it is also a nice tiny perk if you think your preferred hotel is going to sell out.
I'm not sure they will, but all the hotels are quite big.
Yeah, now in Indeed.
And then there's also a other thing.
But do you like to be more specific?
Or would you like one of us to people?
I would love to be more specific.
There is also some news that they have some new special guests.
So they have the hosts of three black halflings, which is a TTRPG podcast.
They are going to be doing live shows in Manchester and London in April in 2024,
and they're coming to Glasgow as well.
Presumably they will do a live show at Glasgow, but that is not stipulated.
We will put a link in the show notes to the final 770 story.
But yes, this is really interesting because they also announced Tanya DuPasse previously.
And so I am excited by the number of gaming related editions from recent times.
You might also think that the chair of Glasgow 2024 was a professor of games.
I would also say if you said what is like an area of major, major interests
that Worldgons have typically not covered very well, it is gaming.
So it definitely makes sense to beep things up there, beep things up there, not beep things up.
John will beep things up later.
Beep things up by getting some special guests in that area.
We have altered our booking.
And where have you gone to?
The village.
Ha ha ha ha ha ha ha.
Oh John, we can have breakfast together.
Did you look at the reviews for the company?
It's probably company because of French I think.
I was going to go to the village and I had said that, but then when I thought about a choice
between over the river and not over the river, I went for not over the river.
I'm not.
Yeah, I don't know if I think I don't really care.
Is that bad?
Depends if you like to pop back and forth your hotel room the extra five minutes, you know,
becomes quite an obstacle if you want to pop back five or six times a day and leave things
there or nap or whatever.
But I think if you're going to leave your room in the morning and then go back at two in the
morning, it's not a big deal.
I'm not sure it's closer.
What's that?
I'm not sure it's actually any closer.
It's closer to the bits of the SEC we're not using.
I think the village may be, they're very close.
Oh is there a bridge somewhere?
I'm going to look at it.
There's a bridge that goes basically like right by the village.
You have to walk past the premiere in.
So Alison just doesn't like crossing running water?
She is a vampire.
We do know this about her.
I am vaguely, vaguely worried that something might go wrong with the footbridge and leave
you with a long walk at the middle of the night.
I see.
You've got to bear in mind that Alison lives in North London and so places south of any
river innately scare her in ways that as non-landiners we can't even begin to grasp.
That is 100% true.
How do you feel about Gates said John?
We're going to be talking about things we might nominate for the Hugos over the next few
episodes and we would like your help.
Please email us your favourite things from 2023.
Please do not email us your favourite things from other years.
We're interested in 2023 specifically but please do let us know and then we can read them and
maybe shout them out on the pod if we think they're good or watch them or listen to them
or other things.
And in forthcoming book news, China Mayville and Keanu Reeves are doing a collab.
It's a Keanu Reeves created universe that started as a comic and he invited China Mayville
to write a book in that universe.
And say what you want about Keanu Reeves, he has very good taste.
Like I've never seen a thing that Keanu Reeves was in where I've been like oh I don't understand
why he did this project.
He is, yeah, no, his presence in things is usually a good sign.
His acting in them, not always a good thing but his presence indicates that it had merit
on the surface.
Is that too harsh?
Um, no, maybe it may not be harsh enough John.
Well like, because every time I see him in a movie, very often I think he does not bring
much to the text but very often I think the text has something really interesting about
it and I can see why he agreed to do it.
It's like the opposite of someone who does terrible things and elevates them if that makes sense.
[laughter]
I think he's very good in films where, like there are obviously films where he's really
well suited to them and they work really well.
And then sometimes he's in a film where I'm like this film was not super well suited to
you, what are you doing?
Which I would pick, 2005's, Constantine.
I think if you didn't know much about Hellblazer Constantine was quite good because relevant
to the rest of genre movies in 2005, I think it was quite imaginative.
It's just relevant to Hellblazer, it was not relevant, relative.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
This is just staring at me.
Yeah, I mean I think we may be going on about Keanu Reeves a little bit too much now.
I suppose it's fair, I am okay, there's too much Keanu Reeves but yes, it's true, I was
thinking of Hellblazer as he kind of has written in the comics which is very much not like
Keanu Reeves.
Oh yes, that is true, that is 100% true.
But he is great and always be my maybe, so.
He is so good in that movie.
Yes, it's so funny.
I have not seen that movie, should I see that movie?
Yeah, John has plugged it before on the podcast.
Okay, hang on, hang on, hang on, hang on.
Bye, yeah.
When I get Netflix back it's one of the things I might rewatch.
I'm not on Netflix because I've got Netflix back.
Yes, yeah, it's like a Netflix original film.
So I'm slightly pre-empting the conversation about things we might nominate in best dramatic
presentation long form with this pick.
But I am going to pick poor things, the new Jorgos Lanteos directed film starring Emma
Stone, which I went to see yesterday.
It was released in the US in 2023, so it is eligible for nomination in 2034.
It's Emma Stone, Mark Ruffalo and William Defoe, sorry, William Defoe.
And it's just great.
It's not a movie to watch with family.
You should definitely not watch it with your children or your parents.
And it really, the 18 rating at the start says that it contains strong sex and I made fun of
it.
What does that mean?
And then it became very obvious through the film exactly what that meant and it was.
Gosh.
But it's very, very interesting.
It's very, very disturbing in the way that Lanthamoss' films tend to be.
I liked it more than I liked the favourite, I think.
I definitely liked it more than the lobster.
It was very good.
And Emma Stone is absolutely fantastic in it and thoroughly deserved the Golden Globe.
Ruffalo also doing his best Matt Berry impersonation, which is something I never thought I'd see,
but I am very glad I have seen it.
Basically, he plays Toast of London.
Like if they ever need to do a Toast of London, whether a tour of them, I feel like Mark Ruffalo
would be great casting.
Have I had to review seen this or read the book it's based on?
I read the book poor things a very long time ago and yeah, no, I'm going to look out for
this.
I should go and see this.
Yeah.
I haven't read it and I don't think it's out here yet, but it's hard to find kind of upcoming
film release dates.
So I'm just hoping it might come out in February or something.
We went to Finsbury Park over the Christmas break for a thing and discovered that Finsbury
Park has a picture house, which is probably our closest decent cinema that's accessible
by public transport now.
So that was quite exciting.
I can actually go to the movies again.
I will also say I didn't understand all the controversy about Scotland.
It seems fine that it's set in London.
He's kind of like a national hero, right?
I saw a bit of trivia on IMDB.
So, Yourgos Lanthamos approached Alistair Gray about adapting poor things.
Apparently in 2009, and Gray took Lanthamos on a personal tour of Glasgow.
Can you imagine if we could have done that as a Glasgow 2024 programme?
I am just following Yourgos Lanthamos on a tour being given by Alistair Gray would have been
great.
Lanthamos said he was a very lovely man.
Unfortunately, he died just a couple of years before we made the film, but he was very special
and energetic.
He was 80 something when we met, and as soon as I got there, he had seen his previous film,
Dogtooth, and said, "I had my friend put on the DVD because I don't know how to operate
these things, but I think you're a very talented young man."
Which is freaking excellent.
I like that.
That is good.
He came to a Mexican.
Oh, did he?
Nice.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Um, Mexico 3, Mexico 4, one of them.
Um, somebody will write in.
He was good.
I mean, Mexico doesn't have guests, but obviously he was guests, and yeah, no, it was great.
No, highly recommended.
Um, presumably we'll be coming to Disney Plus because it is, I believe, a Disney film.
Ooh.
Ah, okay.
Well, Dodd.
That's the most likely place I will see it then.
Yeah, it's not a film that shies away from uncomfortable subject matter.
I will say that.
Um, probably, probably content warnings for underage sex and problematic power dynamics.
I, yeah.
Um, so if those are like things that are likely to bother you, I might think about whether
or not you should see it.
Um, but I think, I think it's deconstructing the power dynamics between men and women in
relationships in a way that's really interesting.
Um, but it does so by portraying some of them.
Yeah, I wonder if it's still going to be on next week when we don't have plague.
Ah, possibly.
Hi everyone, it's John from the Future again here.
There is an exhibition of costumes from poor things being shown at the Barbican until the
26th of January, which I meant to mention during the recording, and I forgot.
Right, so I've gone back to the safe territory of movies for my picks.
Everything is right with the world.
And now I confidently predict that one of my co-hosts will pick a game.
Yeah, yeah.
Um, it's not me.
Wild.
This is because I wrote "It's a game in the show notes."
So it's not like John has developed precognitive abilities or anything.
I am picking a game which was recommended to me by Abigail Nussbaum.
I think she's just quite good at finding like little indie games it turns out I might like.
Oh, it's a video game.
Every time this has happened, I've then lost a significant portion of the following week
to completing the game that has been mentioned.
It's quite a short game.
So it's a video game called "Cance of Sinar", which Abigail compared to another game called
Heaven's Vault, which I haven't played, which I might then go and play.
Anyway, "Cance of Sinar", you're basically kind of thrust into a world which it turns
out is a tower.
And on each level of the tower is a different people's and you have to basically figure out
their language.
Usually by listening to them, reading written materials, listening to what they say, and
you're sort of figuring out, okay, well, the first example is you go to a place with like
a couple of levers and you push one and a gate moves up and the other one, you push it
and the gate moves down and see like, okay, well, this is the words up and down then.
And then you go through to the next area and someone says, you know, mystery character
up and then mystery character down.
And you figure out these must mean me and you based on who's supposed to be doing different
things.
And it just does that for the whole game.
You're trying to figure out from context what the unknown words mean.
And it's quite clever.
So at some point it will offer you the chance to kind of demonstrate that you understand
some words and then it will lock you in and give you the official translation.
And until then you can put in your own like unofficial little notes and translations and
things and it will translate what people are saying.
And the languages are clever.
Like, you know, you'll figure out that some of the characters and maybe two other characters
put together to form a particular word in a way that makes sense.
And it all starts to come together, what's going on in this tower and what has happened
as you learn the languages of the different people going up.
So it's really neat.
And mostly puzzles, it does have a few sort of like stealth bits which are not very difficult
but a little bit annoying.
And I will say I played it on my nice new Nintendo Switch which is probably not the
best platform because the, at least you've put on the handheld one, the screen is a little
bit small.
And there was one stealth bit I was having difficulty completing and I watched like a
little video walk through of someone doing it.
And I was like, ah, you can like select a particular thing that I don't seem to be able
to select with the controls on the Switch.
You have to click point and click on a mouse to do it.
So I think like it's a little bit more difficult on the Switch just because you can't see some
of the stuff on the small screen but otherwise it seems perfectly playable.
And so I happily sat there playing through this.
I would say it takes maybe 12 or 15 hours.
So it's not super long but it is quite moreish when you're like, oh, I've only got to figure
out another four characters and then I'll have this whole language.
And then you move the next floor and there's another whole language and you're like, I'll
just play a little bit more, a little bit more and it's quite moreish.
So sorry, Alison, for telling you about it.
Oh, I love that sort of thing.
I'll bear it in mind if I come down with plague in the next day or two, which is not
unlikely.
Do you mind if I post a spoiler on Discord because this is 20% off on Switch until today
and it is 20% off until Wednesday on PlayStation and Xbox in the UK?
Yeah, no, can you put that down?
Because I might go and buy it as soon as we finish the pod.
It's like 12 quid or something on Switch.
So it's probably cheaper on PlayStation.
I should have gone on PlayStation.
Same price.
Yeah, but probably not in Thailand where PlayStation prices in Thailand tend to be significant
be below the UK and US ones and Switch prices are not because I have to use the UK store
and Switch because there's no Thai eShop.
Ah, right, possibly.
Which probably explains why the Switch is not very popular.
You know, I can imagine that.
Listeners, I will put links to the UK stores in the show notes because I'm pro-keal.
Right, I think so.
You'll pick Alison.
Can I do my pick now?
I'm slightly sorry because I may have poached this pick off Liz who did recommend this to
me.
But in my defence, when I went into the show notes to write my pick down, her pick was
already there.
So it's clearly all's fair in love and picking things for OctoThorp.
So my pick is a graphic novel.
It is Why Don't You Love Me by Paul B. Rainey.
And I think I saw some conflicting evidence.
Suff, somebody said it would be published on his website and then collected into a book
and somebody said, "Oh no, it's always been a book and that's all it's been."
So I am not sure which of those is correct.
Each page of the novel, the comic is like one page panel comic of the sort that if you
ever saw Posey Simmons in the Guardian or numerous other Guardian comics or Sunday
strips, that sort of format.
But it has more in common with the Guardian strips than it does with the Sunday ones because
although there is some humour in quite a lot of these strips, they're not kind of roll
on the floor laughing funny at any point.
And indeed the graphic novel is not roll on the floor laughing.
You are introduced to a couple.
A couple with two children and they are clearly very unhappy and they are having massive fights.
And as long as as well as having massive fights with each other, they are also neglecting
their children very substantially for, and you just don't know why at the start.
So you're very much thrown in in media res and obviously gravidually over the course of
the graphic novel you find out why they are unhappy, why they are not looking after the
children, what is going on.
And it does kind of pick up a bit so it is not quite as relentlessly bleak and depressing
as it seems at the beginning.
But this is not exactly a cheerful graphic novel so you might want to go and read it when
you're in a imperturbably good mood rather than when you're already a bit grumpy.
It seemed uncomfortably like my own experience of raising children which was kind of a bit
distressing.
I used to have a fridge magnet that said who are these people and why are they calling
me bum.
And so it was quite resonant in that sense.
I thought it was fantastic.
It's going to be on my Hugo ballot and I appreciate it.
I've not yet told you enough to understand why it will be on my ballot.
And I don't really want to because saying why it might be on a Hugo ballot is in itself
a little bit of a spoiler or even the fact that it could be.
But it's good.
Go read it.
Thought it was great.
Would like to see more graphic novels like this getting attention.
It's a graphic novel.
It is a graphic novel.
Oh yes.
So I have a question then which is did you read it in paper or in e?
I bought it from the library.
My library had a copy?
I...
In paper or in e?
From the library.
My library had an e-book of it and I read it on my iPad.
Was it good in e-book?
It was slightly irritating because in fact, I mean I may have been able to sort this out
but in fact it was presented in two-page spreads.
So I had to zoom in and then read one page and then swipe my finger over and read the
other page.
This is not very irritating in the grand scheme of things but it was just I would have preferred
it to be one page at a time and that may be something that I could have sorted out in
the Libby software but did not bother to do so.
Read us right in.
No, I'm very suspicious of...
I love reading comics in electronic format but I'm very suspicious of reading them.
I used to love comicsology but that's gone now in its Kindle and ebook versions of comics
are awful and so I'm like I don't want to buy it if it might be awful and the lack of
delineation between comicsology and Kindle now makes that very difficult and so I'm like
well I might just buy it in paper.
Or you might be able to get it from your library thereby cutting through this.
Possibly.
I mean I read it in paper and I borrowed the paper copy so I'm not really much easier.
That's right can you lend it to me?
No because I borrowed it from Naughty.
You can ask him for his copy.
Naughty if you're listening can I borrow that comment from you?
But I would say that it is presented in sort of landscape format.
They're kind of rectangular pages that seem like they would be perfectly oriented to be
read on an iPad or similar.
I just don't know how big an iPad you need for it to be sensibly workable.
It's fine.
It doesn't have a lot of tiny text or anything.
It's fine at my 11 inch.
I prefer reading comics in landscape on iPad.
It's my one criticism of the Marvel Unlimited app is that if a page isn't designed to be
read as a two page spread you can't read it as one which annoys me because of reading
comics that I've acquired like in other formats and I can read them in a different app than
I will read them in landscape preferentially.
So maybe the pub would be fine.
I've decided for 2024 I'm going to try and consume all of your pics because I'm a good
person.
Can you get the sample guys?
Can you get the sample?
On Kindle just get the sample.
If it works the sample will work and then you'll know it works or not before you buy the book
because one great thing about Kindle is that they give you a few pages to read and you
can find out whether the formatting is terrible.
Very important for cookbooks this.
But I do need a Kindle to do that.
You need to get the Kindle app if you're going to do that yeah.
Or the Kindle Cloud Reader.
But actually this one might not be readable in the Kindle Cloud Reader now that I think
about it.
So can we have an after show which is Amazon and comics?
Because I used to know how it works and then Amazon did a lot of things and I don't think
I know how it works.
But either of you know how it works.
Because it says on the Amazon page that I can read it on Comixology.
Is that actually true?
Is it just that they've gotten rid of the Comixology store but the apps still exist?
I thought the app had gone away.
I remember getting an email saying you must move all your stuff into Amazon from Comixology
which in theory I did.
But I've got that there are a lot of comics in there that I don't remember buying.
So I am reading it.
I am current.
There is an app on.
I am reading something on Comixology right now.
Oh no.
Yeah.
I've just opened Comixology and it says as of April 2023 this app is no longer available.
So the Amazon the Amazon website I guess hasn't modified that little string for the last eight
months which my impression is that Amazon has not been taking their comic arm as seriously
as comic fans might like and certainly maybe that's unfair but it seems to be the case.
So I think everything I own on Comixology is now just coming up in my Kindle library.
Okay.
And also some comics I don't remember buying.
Right. Why do I own a bunch of issues of a 2011 on Canny X-Men?
Can anyone tell me?
I don't think I bought them.
Yeah no.
The comic that turned up when I opened Comixology wasn't what I remember buying.
If you open Comixology do you have a bunch of on Canny X-Men from 2011?
I do not think I do.
Alright.
I have a lot of Hellblazer.
I have a lot of Sam Mann.
I have The Psycho Path Club by Sandra Bond.
But I don't have any X-Men.
I mean this is a part of what I also say that my pick is also a 2023 game and therefore
potentially eligible for a Hugo.
So we're getting your Hugo stuff done early.
Yes I'm going to try and make sure all my picks are 2023 for the next few weeks.
Yeah I mean it's not going to win but it's good to have alternatives to Tears of the
Kingdom so that there are other games alongside it when it inevitably wins.
I feel like Tears of the Kingdom probably will win and it very much annoys me but there
we go.
Not that I've played it.
Ha!
No because I hated Breath of the Worlds sufficiently.
It's not that I hated it's that it has no forward momentum for me.
We have a letter of comment on this episode from Andrew January because I posted a link
to Liz's pick in Discord.
Andrew January writes in to say on Switch and he assumes other platforms too.
If you play the demo and then buy the game your progress will carry over which is useful
to know.
Thank you very much Andrew.
And then he says he assumes on the episode that Alison talks about the Sudoku Boys and
their playthrough.
So you didn't talk about it.
Yes.
Oh so the Sudoku Boys have played through this one as well.
I mean I kind of do like all the games they play through.
They do pick them.
But that also means I can link to that in the show notes for people who do not want to
play it but do want to get an idea for what it be like.
So yeah we'll do that.
Thank you very much for writing in Andrew.
And that was the Octa Thought Podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
I almost exclusively play my Switch on the TV because I don't like playing it portably
because I either use the Joy-Cons which I find are too small for my massive old man
hands or I have to use a like pro controller which I have to take with me as well as the
Switch.
And then if I'm going to take the Switch and the controller for the Switch I might as well
take my iPad which I've got anyway and a controller for the iPad and then play things
on the iPad.
So like almost all the time I'm playing my Switch it's docked which I know is like
highly atypical but I really wish the controllers were more comfortable.
I designed for kids I completely understand why but.
Well I have a kind of regular human sized hands and I find them okay.
It's not the most comfortable one.
Well I have fairly small hands it was what really stopped me taking piano seriously and
yeah no I really like Joy-Cons they work really well for me.
Oh that's true I can easily do an octave and a second so make a little person hands.
I get RSI if I play the Switch with the in portable mode or if I play it with the Joy-Cons
slotted into the holder thing.
The thing yeah.
So I had to buy a pro controller so I could play without getting thumbain.
Because the Joy-Sticks are too close.
Which like you know most controllers designed for men so like I'm not begrudging the fact
that they did one that wasn't.
And it must be pain in the arse if this is the other way round so I sympathize for all
you ladies out there.
It's a penny arcade joke about Xbox controllers isn't it?
Have you seen that?
No.
It's very old now.
Yeah there are a lot of controllers I just can't use but I'm fine with the PlayStation
one and I'm fine with the Switch one I'll probably prefer the PlayStation slightly smaller.
Oh dear god I just went up to I just went to look up the penny arcade comic I was referencing
and it's from 2002.
Oh my god.
Are you cracking up the finger at 21 year old penny arcade comic?
21 year old penny arcade.
I would have sworn I had read all the 21 year old penny arcade comics but apparently not
or maybe I just forgot it and could read it again.
[BLANK_AUDIO]