Hello everyone and welcome to the very 74th episode of Octothorpe, the podcast of eldritch
poetry, which is coming to you on the 5th of January 2023. I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison
Scott. And today we have something a little bit different for you. We asked you for poetry
and Sandra Bond has delivered! She has sent us this lovely pastiche, thanks very much Sandra.
And I'm not sure we can do it justice but we'll have a go.
There's an intriguing Lovecraftian hellscape where fumes make the fetid air glum: And Alison
Scott and Liz Batty went there with John Coxon, their son.
A broth of a boy was young Coxon, all dressed in his best like a swell and he carried a
plastic lightsaber, the best one that Woolworths could sell. They didn't much rate that dimension,
though the angles looked wonky and wrong, and Alison thought her accordion sounded better
than Dagon's old song.
So seeking for further amusement they paid to go into the zoo, where they'd shoggoths and
deep ones and serpents, not to mention Almighty Cthulhu.
Now Cthulhu was peaceful and passive, his tentacles twitched as he slept, he lay in a
somnolent posture, as he dreamed of the secrets he kept.
John Coxon had heard about Cthulhu, his unspeakable nature and that, and it made him a tad disappointed,
an Elder God, lying there flat.
So Coxon, he took his lightsaber, like Skywalker or one of those, and ere Alison or Liz could
stop him, he shoved it up great Cthulhu's nose.
It was certain that Cthulhu di'n't like it, for giving a kind of a roll, he opened his
cavernous mouthpiece, and vacuumed out John Coxon's soul.
And Alison fled with a gibber, and Liz she fled too, with a wail, and they dragged little
Coxon behind them, like a Tindalos hound with its tail.
They made it out of that dimension, which I think is more than they deserved, and decided
to record a podcast about all the things they'd observed.
And Octothorpe came out as normal, and it's pretty good fun on the whole, but the funny
thing is that John Coxon seems to get on just fine with no soul.
The
theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod at incompetech.com, used
under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep. Beeeep