- John was frozen. - He has.
That's why he's not mocking us.
He's got a kind of...
It's got an interesting look he's got on his face.
I'm going to screenshot it for him.
Yeah, we're the screenshot for sure.
Yeah. I wonder when he'll come back on.
Yeah, it's gone away though, yeah.
Hmm.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 71st episode of Octa Thorpe,
the podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom.
This episode is coming to you on the 24th of November 2022.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
We did get some letters of comment
and the first one is from a man named Christopher J. Garcia.
He says,
"Dame it, Coxon. Where are the graphs? I was promised graphs."
And this time I do categorically promise that there will be graphs.
Have you done them already?
No.
Then don't categorically promise.
Categorically promise that there will be graphs.
Chris also said that the Hugo ceremony is way too short
and it could definitely go longer.
I think Chris may be the only person in the world who believes that.
I would be interested to know if Chris's perspective is skewed
from usually being a nominee.
Like if you're a nominee,
do you want the experience to last longer?
And if you're not a nominee,
you want to get it all over with so you can find out
who won best novel and go to bar.
No, Alison.
No, I mean, we were finalists this year
and I would have been entirely happy for the ceremony to be noticeably shorter.
No, it was alright.
I didn't think it was overly long.
Chris also says he lives about 30 minutes for the beach
but doesn't like swimming in the ocean
because it has great white sharks, jellyfish and surfers.
Yeah, to be fair, I'm going to speak
but probably not going to swim in the ocean
because it's not a particularly nice ocean swimming beach
and it does have jellyfish
but I will walk along the shore and panel my feet in and so on.
Anyone else got anything on Chris?
He'd like to give more awards,
best dramatic presentation audio, best game and best cat.
Badger just winning a Hugo every year would be great
but I'm not sure we could just make Badger our own Hugo.
Can we have a Badger badge?
Can we have a Badger's best cat badge?
Yeah, definitely.
Also onto Esther.
He also says, "Space shuttles are okay.
Mars rovers are much cooler.
I've actually licked one continuing the pattern
of Chris having a much more interesting life to me."
And he also says he's got 32 and a half megabytes of zines
over the last 15 years, which is quite a lot
although less than I would have guessed.
I mean, is that just a text file?
Because that doesn't seem like a lot of zine, right?
Can't be like full issues of journey planet or anything.
Chris, write in and clarify.
"I've edited journey planets that were bigger than that."
Maybe that decimal points in the wrong place.
That would make a lot more sense
because there would be 32 and a half gigabytes
and I think that might be right.
Yeah, that sounds a lot more likely, yeah.
Oh, yeah, that makes more sense.
Okay, we also heard from Phara Mendelssohn who said,
"Oh, Pemicon is the NASFIC."
You never actually said, that is correct.
We should have said.
So Pemicon is the NASFIC.
Thank you for pointing that out, Phara.
And we can confirm that Phara was in New Orleans
as a support for Karen Fishick's big,
Phara is taking on the roles of communications and tourism.
And possibly very helpful synergy there
with all the other conventions that are happening in Birmingham.
Yes.
Get some good tourist guys going and you've got the tourists guys done.
This segues neatly into Raj's tweet
where Raj says that they're not going to the Eastercon in Birmingham,
but they are going to satellite eight and worldcon.
So we will see you at worldcon, Raj.
Worldcon 2024, presumably, Raj.
Yes.
Worldcon 2023.
Yeah, we will definitely see you then.
I probably won't be at satellite eight following a long tradition of me
never quite getting to satellite.
Sorry, guys.
It's a very long way from London.
Oh, so you go to Scotland for worldcon, but not any other con.
It's complicated.
Conversely, I might will be at satellite eight because it's quite close.
Oh, yeah.
Equally, I didn't know.
It's not on their website yet.
So I can't, I don't think I can join yet.
No, they were definitely taking memberships this weekend.
There were several conventions at,
they've gone there for shadowing.
But speaking of Winnipeg, which we were before,
John Segway'd away from it,
I'm not sure if we mentioned the TAF race last time,
but even if we did, we can mention it again,
because fandom needs a few good people.
And by that, a few good people, I mean, at least two,
and you do not have to be good.
We would like to have a TAF race.
Well, the TAF administration was like to have a TAF race.
It's going to be East West Race to go to Pemecon 2023.
Yeah, I think this is a really great opportunity,
because one of the things about worldcon is that they're enormous.
And you as the TAF delegate probably get a bit lost in the crowd.
Whereas I think at NASFIC,
it's going to be a convention of exactly right size
to have a really, really good time as a delegate.
And don't just go to Winnipeg,
go to other places in North America as well,
at somebody else's expense.
Yeah, so if you're listening to this,
and you've always wanted to run for TAF,
and you are European or resident in the UK and Europe,
this is your chance.
Is it a flip?
Have we flipped the direction of races?
We're doing two Westbound races.
So we did Westbound to Chicon,
and we are going Eastbound to Glasgow,
rather than having an Eastbound rate to conversation.
I see.
They're going Westbound to Pemecon,
and then Eastbound to Glasgow.
I mean Canada's very nice,
so I'm thinking I might run.
Haven't you won TAF already, John?
Yeah, but it's more of a guideline than an actual rule.
Yeah, you just try running and see what happens.
That's my plan.
I'm still waiting for Chris Garcia to launch his Duff campaign,
Chris for TAF 2 this time for Duff.
Which I think will be very good.
If John did run it would probably kindle in a fan-ish outrage
to get a lot of donations to whoever was running against John.
Yeah, I'm basically just doing the fan fund a massive solid.
I'm an altruist, Liz.
Maybe not the best way of raising money for the fan funds.
Yeah, by massive solid you mean a great big enormous...
There was also a tweet of comment from Peter Sullivan,
who notes that Space Shuttle Enterprise is actually named after itself,
because in Star Trek, the ship that Captain Kirk captions is named after
the Space Shuttle Enterprise,
and when they were naming the Space Channels,
they called one of the Enterprise after the ship from Star Trek.
So it is one huge recursive loop in the great tradition of good time travel stories.
Johnny Badley wrote twice in the Facebook page,
wants to say, "There's a Canadian embassy, did you know?"
And in fact, I did know that because it's the picture I used for my art references for that cartoon.
And he would like a best publisher Hugo category,
which I think is not a bad idea,
to reward the publisher who put out the most interesting,
new exciting or republished out of print books,
or was in general the most interesting genre publisher.
Doesn't Locust have a best publisher category?
Yeah, but Locust is about to go out of business,
so we should probably get on with finding a replacement for their awards, right?
Ooh...
Not for podcast!
Apparently, apparently that is too far from his listeners,
because she made a very paint set on.
No, obviously it would be very sad if Locust was to go under.
*laughs*
It's not for podcast, go on!
There's um, isn't there like a crowd funder or something at the moment?
I just thought it was a bit harsh to kick them when they are, they are down,
but they're struggling, yeah?
I did have a good point if you give me one moment to look it up, which is...
Oh...
So the best publisher award for the Locust has been won,
well, for the first 15 years of his existence it was won by...
Sorry, it's had at least three winners.
*laughs*
That's what we like.
Tor.com and...
No, so the thing is it was Valentine and Valentine Del Rey,
and then Pocket/Timescape for a while,
and then Back to Valentine Den Rey,
and then it's been Tor or Tor St Martin's since 1988.
So for longer than I've been alive.
*burps* Chon!
Sorry, if it's only won by three people,
and one of them has been winning for the last 33 years.
Is that helpful?
I don't know, I don't know if it is.
So have a best small press award?
Maybe that would be good, that would be good, perhaps.
I looked at the vast range of books on Elswen presses stand at Novicon,
and I was like, "When do you stop being a small press then?"
Look at all these books and they said...
Apparently we stop being a small press where that turnover goes over 50 billion dollars a year.
So we've got a little waltz.
That is, uh...
That is reasonable.
Quite a bottle of money.
I mean, I think if we were going to take anything from the Locust Awards
that we thought should go into the Hugo's,
I would probably pick something like the anthology award.
Readers, write in what awards from other awards should be adopted by the Hugo's.
I mean, I do like, I do actually quite like the way that Locust splits a novel into multiple different novel awards,
but I think just because I like novels, I like giving them all prizes.
I think if I was going to poach one, I would poach best magazine,
and then I would ditch best editor short form,
because you could reward it all through magazine semi-pro-scene front-scene.
You know that Mark Plumber's going to write in again, don't you?
Good.
I like it when Mark writes in.
I secretly say things, hoping he will.
Because it all comes around again.
Speaking of awards that have been won by four different groupings.
Oh no, has it?
Okay.
So I can't, I think it's changed over time.
So I'm not sure it's always been magazine or anthology.
I was just looking up in the internet, but it was like it's been tour.com
as involves FNSF and Locust.
I would now, so if I was ever going to run an award,
like for instance, say we did the Octa-Thought Awards,
and there was a category for Best Podcast,
I would make it very clear that Octa-Thought was not eligible.
Yep.
Because I don't want to win an award I give.
Like, I have a pretty low bar for,
I feel like I've not got very rigorous standards around self-motion,
certainly nowhere near as much as some other people in British fandom.
But like, I'm not going to give myself an award.
Come on guys.
Reader's writing for the first annual Octa-Thought piece,
what should the categories be?
Ooh.
We are crowdsourcing these.
Please also all nominate yourselves for Best Letter Hack.
But obviously if you write in, there's a good chance you're going to get
a nomination for Best Letter Hack, because there's not that many of you.
Oh, there's literally a handful.
That's loads.
Put it this way, there are more people who would be eligible for Best Letter Hack
than there are people who have won Best Publisher in the Locust Awards.
It would be a more vibrant award than that.
But would it be more vibrant than the purple colour of your office John?
Nothing could be.
Please also write in to tell us what voting system we should use
for the nomination and voting system of the Octa-Thought piece,
which we will then completely ignore and pick them by editorial whim.
Oh, I'm thinking that the number of votes for each person,
you print out that many slips of paper with that person's name on
and you put them all in a hat and then you jiggle the hat about
and you pick one at random.
So everyone's still got a chance of winning.
It's just biased in favour of the first one.
It's like a worse version of First Past the Post.
I'm very proud of it.
That's terrible.
That's an extraordinarily terrible voting system.
It's basically a raffle.
If you've got people to pay to vote as well.
I'm quite proud of it given I came up with it on the fly.
Because I was trying to come up with a terrible voting system
and I feel like I've nailed it.
You might have.
So yeah, on to our main subject for today,
which is I went to Mote Novicon.
Did you guys have fun at Novicon, guys?
I lovely time not being at Novicon,
but I feel listeners may be more interested in your lovely time at Novicon.
So maybe we should focus on that.
So Novicon was back at the Buxton Palace for a second year
and we've now heard it will be back again next year for a third year.
Why did it leave the old hotel?
Sorry, I forgot.
Can you explain that?
The left the old hotel because Covid.
Because they were using it as a coronavirus court.
They were using it as a temporary court to catch up with the backlog.
It was a Nightingale court.
Ah, okay.
Yes, and they couldn't host Novicon 50 there
and I guess that means that they're not going to go back.
So when they had Nightingale hospitals,
I think everyone was like,
"Oh, Nightingale hospitals."
They're called that because of Florence Nightingale being a famed nurse.
But of course, it turns out that it's actually Nightingale anything
and it's because Florence Nightingale was actually a famed water-timer
administrator who was very good at setting up things at short notice.
That's what happened to the old hotel and they moved
and having moved, they decided they liked
being in the center of a really nice town
that's the right size to be in the center of when you're at a convention.
And they really liked the public areas of the hotel, which are amazing.
The rooms at the Buxton Palace are a kind of mixed bag.
Our room this year had a double bed in it,
which sounds fine until you realize that we normally have a room with it.
We normally sleep in a room with a super king bed inside it.
So it was kind of far more intimate than my husband and I are used to.
Hello.
And there was no heating.
The heating didn't work.
There was hot water the first morning we were there and there after.
We had to basically crack the ice on the bath, had there been a bath,
which they wasn't.
So it was very cold.
I quite like it cold.
I woke up after they fixed the heating,
I woke up in the middle of the light thinking I was suffering from a terrible fever.
But I wasn't.
I was just, I just wrapped up in the way that you do if you're in a hotel.
They were working, eating.
The public spaces of the Buxton Palace are amazing in that not only do they have quite
a lot of quite nice function rooms as a right sort of space,
but they have a couple of bars and also quite a lot of sofas just randomly
strewn around the hotel in different places.
So I quite like sitting around on sofas all weekend.
So I like hotels that have lots of sofas for me to do that.
Back at the palace next year, it's a Britannia hotel.
They had actually improved that last year I was worried I might die walking up or down the steps.
Outside the lead from the hotel to Buxton.
And this year they've got some new lighting on them.
So presumably either they suddenly decided that would be a good thing to
spend some maintenance money on or somebody sued one of those.
So that is that your Novacom reporter in nutshell,
last year thought I might die this year just nearly froze today?
Novacom, the UK's second convention.
It actually has on the website the UK's longest running
science fiction convention, which I think is a bit of a bloody cheek actually.
I know what they read.
Sort of.
Yeah.
If you real squint.
It's kind of always run by the same people, but obviously it's not the same people.
Basically sort of if you lie.
So are we not counting Easticon because it's in different places, different people or what?
Well it actually says the UK's longest established science fiction convention.
So what we are actually arguing is whether or not Easticon is established.
And I don't know how you define established to mean that Easticon isn't but Novacom is.
Yeah, you don't. It's nonsense.
Novacom was lovely.
The public areas of the hotel are so nice that it rather makes up for everything else.
The rooms were not actually bad apart from being a bit cold,
which was not entirely anybody's fault.
The hotel did.
Worked extremely hard to get the heating back working again.
And they were just very unlucky that they had very great difficulty getting a heating
engineer in who could sort it.
And they were very lucky in that the total climate catastrophe that is going to destroy
all of our lives in short order meant that it was the warmest mid-November weekend on record this weekend.
So there's a wall that's called as all that.
There are even more lovely brew pubs and little craft pubs with interesting beer
and nice restaurants all within about five minute walk of the hotel than they were last year.
Though I think if you want to go to one of the nicest restaurants,
it is best to book before the Novacom weekend because as they said
to one person, "Oh, we have had a lot of large bookings for Saturday night already."
And the banquet was quite good, which after last year's banquet,
which was one of the worst convention backwhits I'd ever been to,
and I've seen a few doozies.
It was pretty good this year, so that was quite nice.
The food was good.
It was hot.
There was plenty of it.
It was people were not allowed to serve themselves.
That being the problem.
I was in the dealer's room.
The dealer's room was small but perfectly formed.
It had several conventions, including satellite,
which we've already mentioned.
Core flew crack, which we have not mentioned enough yet,
but which is in Belfast in the week before the Eastergone.
I want to say something about satellite,
which is that if you go directly to the likely URL for the convention being
satellite, sorry, 8.satellitex.org.uk,
the website is there.
But if you go to satellitex.org.uk, the link to it isn't.
So you just have to extrapolate that it exists and go there directly.
We will put a link in the show notes.
Satellite had a game at the convention in the dealer's room,
which consisted of throwing sperm into a bucket.
And I thought this was an odd choice.
Did you have to provide your own sperm?
They were saying, "Start life on earth."
Right. Okay.
Now, I may just have a biology degree,
but I'm not sure life on earth actually started
when someone threw some sperm into a bucket.
Although there is that episode of Star Trek,
where it's all about that like galactic panespermia hypothesis or whatever.
But even then, I'm not sure there was an actual bucket.
Oh, before you do, I want to talk about last year's banquet.
Last year's banquet was terrible.
I am very glad that they fixed it this year.
What was the problem last year?
There was not enough food.
Oh.
And the food that there was wasn't amazing.
And so it basically is spannier when and got a kebab
before our table got our turn to go up to the table.
And the kebab was much better than the banquet.
It was all organic.
The problem was 99% organizational.
They didn't call up tables.
So they called up the first table,
and then they forgot they were supposed to be calling up tables,
and everyone sat around.
By the time we got there,
it had all been eaten and it was called.
And I took the day off to go to the banquet,
and I have to do that far enough in advance.
I will never do it again,
because even if I turn up and they're like,
"But this year it'll be fantastic."
I'm like, "Sure, but I got work on Monday,
so I'm not going."
But didn't you take the day off to have another night
at the convention with your friends?
Well, yeah, but all my friends will be at the banquet.
So if I don't want to go to the banquet,
it's a toof of the convention will be dead,
and I can go and eat a kebab on my own.
I mean, to be fair,
it sounds like you might have had some other takers
for your kebab plan just in case.
But I did see the cheesecake,
and it looked quite nice, and I thought,
"Ooh, cheesecake's pretty good."
No, it did. It looked good.
It's not a cheesecake.
It was all the food was nice.
But anyway, it's program.
Did you enjoy all of the program you saw, Alison?
So the only bits of the program I saw
were a very brief amount of the book launch with free wine,
but I didn't really see any of it,
because I was busy trying to find the hotel's trolley
so that I can move my stuff in,
because the hotel only has one trolley,
and we need to take wine to the book launch.
And then immediately after that,
I'm told that there was a ZZ9 party.
But when I asked people who you might have thought
would know something about the ZZ9 party about it,
they were like, "Apparently they just kind of assumed
that if they put ZZ9 party on the...
on the main... on the program, it would happen."
But we just dragged the free wine
that was left over from the book launch, so...
So it did, basically.
Those were the only things I saw apart from the banquet.
So I'm sorry.
Lots of people went to the Serious Scientific Talk,
which was apparently a Serious Scientific Talk,
rather than a Serious Scientific Talk.
Who gave the Serious Scientific Talk?
I can't remember. There's a little bean one on.
That's why I wanted to have the program in front of me.
I would have given you things about the program.
I wonder if it's on the website.
They don't put the program on the internet.
I remember this from last year.
I had to take pictures of it and put them in along with Claire,
so everyone could have it.
So basically what I'm getting from this is that ZZ9
assumed if they just sort of put apart in the program,
it would happen.
But then actually they turned up...
ZZ9... it's not ZZ9's fault at all.
Oh, no, the comp put the ZZ9 in the program.
I think the convention assumed that if they put...
Oh...
I see.
Yes, there was a ZZ9 quiz hosted by Satellite,
and that was supposed to be very good.
But Alison was in a bar.
Now I think Alison went to the quiz.
No, no, no, no.
Was there anything else in the program that looked good
that you didn't go to?
I didn't tend to open the read,
look at the program.
I mean, the thing about Novocod is that it's got like
some very nice beer bars.
So, I mean, my program was that I went to Red Willow,
the Boxter Brewery Tap, and a nice...
Oh, that's what I did on Saturday night.
We spent three hours in a French restaurant
eating and drinking.
And then by the time we got back,
I could hardly move,
so I just kind of sat in the lobby for a while
chatting to people on some of the comfy sofas.
It's quite hard to get me out of a comfy sofa
or did to the program.
Sorry.
I had a really good time.
What you're saying is we should put comfy sofas
in program rooms.
Ooh, I quite like that idea.
Ooh, I do.
Or beanbags, although I can't care for beanbag.
Couldn't get out out of one of these sofas.
There was one where I just went to stand up and went,
"Oh, oh no, apparently this sofa is not constructed
as I had expected."
And I had to elicit somebody's help to get me out of the chair.
And then, when the next time I needed to get out of the sofa,
they were like, "No, my back will not put up with that
another time."
Leimproven was there with his partner,
Yana, and their daughter, Ada, who was extremely cute.
It was quite nice to meet her in the flesh.
Anything else on Novicon, guys?
Any questions about Novicon?
Oh, did you want to talk about masks at Novicon?
About what?
Masking.
Wasn't any?
Um, well, yeah, you had to wear masking in program rooms,
except obviously when the program item was a banquet or a book launch or a party.
Which is, as you know, many of them.
And you had to wear masks while moving around in the hotel,
but not while seated in bar areas.
Now, this, as I said earlier, is a hotel with maybe 32 comfortable sofas.
In various places.
And, um, so that meant in practice that I spent almost no time wearing a mask.
I also didn't notice very many people who were ill.
This is the first time I've been to a convention that I haven't noticed lots of people
showing signs of having viral infections.
So that might bode well.
I'm not saying the word, Teddy.
I'm not much about COVID.
So either nobody caught COVID at the convention,
or nobody's got sick during the convention or immediately afterwards,
or, um, I just haven't heard about it yet.
And I would like to congratulate the convention committee for doing such a good job on squashing
all of those COVID stories.
No, but that's, that is good.
I mean, I do think, so I think this time last year we had an argument about whether
or not there would be a wave in time from overcon.
And I can't remember whether it ended up in the podcast or not,
but I think it doesn't look like there has been really.
I haven't heard, I mean, either that means,
I mean, like Alice has said, either that means it's not coming up in the news,
or it means there has a blue one.
I don't know which is, but yeah, no, I haven't noticed as many ill people
around as I did this time last year.
So anecdotally, I think Liz was right.
I can't remember what I said, but I'm glad that I was right.
You basically said it was impossible to extrapolate whether or not there would be
an autumn wave every year, or whether or not it'd be like less predictable than that.
Yeah, I was smart, wasn't I?
Yeah.
I mean, and beautiful modest, all these things.
Yeah, I mean, the only way I look at all these things now is I look at the UK ONS survey,
and it looks like there was a little kind of blip up in September that's on the way back down again.
So...
Did you catch Covid?
I don't know.
Awesome.
That's better than knowing that you did.
I certainly don't, what day is it today, Tuesday?
Might not know yet, but I'm quite boosted at the moment, so I'm probably good.
I had Covid fairly recently.
Oh, yes, you, yes.
I mean, I had a cold which might not have been Covid quite recently,
and then I got boosted, so hopefully I'm in reasonably good Covid-free shape.
I wish that I could pay for a booster.
If I could pay for a booster, I would get boosted before a recubvention.
Yeah, no, I think I might too.
Though, Stephen was really sick this time, so it would be kind of like
taking several days of ill health as a kind of prepayment on impossible more Covid.
Come and get your pre-con crud.
Pre-con crud.
Do you fancy guaranteeing your pre-con crud with low risk of post-con crud?
Have we got the jabs for you?
I'd be great at advertising.
And your post-con crud might be worse, but might also not be worse, so it's complicated.
Octa Thorpe, Covid Roundup.
I've done one of those for a while.
Oh, one last thing, did I say, Gen Williams?
Gen Williams is the guest of honour of the next Nova Con,
and incidentally, she was the person who did the interstitial art for the fanzine The Lid,
edited by Alice's Stuart and Marguerite Kenner last week.
So I was like, "Oh, that's a coincidence."
I don't know whether that was on purpose or not.
But yes, and she writes, "Fancy and crime fiction, I understand."
And Claire Breuerley says she's good.
Yeah, the friend of the podcast, Claire Breuerley says she's wonderful,
and I discovered I actually own the first of one of her trilogies,
because Claire told me to buy it when it was on Kindle for 99p.
So hopefully I'll read that quite soon, certainly before Nova Con next year,
because it gives you something with...
Nova Con is a convention where your charts,
if running into the guest of Oder in the bar, are very nearly 100%,
so it's very useful to have read one of their books,
so you have something to talk to them about.
Though this time, I was expected Gareth Powell to be at the convention on his honeymoon,
because it'd be reported that he would be,
and he ended up there on his own and had quite a long story about that.
So I did have something to talk to about him about in the bar,
but it wasn't necessarily the joyous.
I understand you're here on your honeymoon, the tired.
I hope to talk to him about.
I have read some of Gareth Powell's books,
and I have read the Akak Macak, which was good, fun nonsense,
I would say.
It is not what I'd call high-concept sci-fi,
but it was like an enjoyable, rollicking read.
But he also wrote a book called "Revelation",
which I did I remember quite enjoying.
And I need to read more of his stuff,
but this goes for almost every author in British science fiction,
because I read two of their books very enthusiastically,
and then I read two of literally everyone else's books very enthusiastically,
and then it takes me ages to get back to the first person again,
which is bad, I should do better.
What was it called?
"The recollection", and I gave it four stars,
and I said I loved the antagonist and how ambiguous the morality was.
I loved some of the ideas.
I read it in 2018.
I do like knowing all these things.
I had dinner with Ian McDonald on Saturday night,
and was very glad to be able to say everything I've read of yours is fantastic,
which it is.
And I don't know if every other book he's ever written is fantastic,
because I've only read a small proportion of them for the reasons that John mentions.
Mostly we talked about walking holidays in that way that you do.
He was one of the people along with my ex who's just had a comedy accident
who went walking the Camino with Carrie Spearing for the last several months.
They'd, I mean Carrie, we spent several months over at other people,
just kind of dropped him for kind of mini walks of only 100 miles or so.
So is Carrie doing a 100 mile long walk as a guest of honor item at the 2023 Eastcom?
I will ask her.
Okay, thank you.
Yeah, 100 mile walk with the stars.
Oh, I'm not going to get on a Sunday morning.
Departing on the Friday morning, getting back on the Monday night.
Oh, what we should do is set up a pilgrimage to,
you could have pilgrimages to the NEC, right?
So we set up a pilgrimage and say, plan your own walking route at all,
put your things and walked.
We will to enhance our sustainability policy for the 2023 Eastcom.
We will all have people walk to the convention from different locations and blog
and have a kind of discord thing about all things they're doing on the way to the NEC.
This is perfectly rational, right?
They can all time the finish to be there on Thursday when I will be there
stamping anyone who's walked at least 100 miles.
I will stamp their walking passport and stand them up into a beer.
Right, so Caroline, I'm sure you're glad to hear that that is your convention's transport policy.
And I look forward to your lock next episode.
Well, they were asking for sustainability policy.
Hello, Caroline, let's chat on Friday.
Right, but does it involve everyone walks 100 miles to the whole convention?
How far is the NEC away from my house by foot?
Same distance as it is by other routes, really.
I mean, probably.
Not, there won't be much in it.
Walking directions from Newcastle to the Hilton Birmingham Metropolitan.
It's 320 kilometres.
Quite a long way.
Carrie walked about 800 kilometres on the Camino.
I said, "So you really would walk 500 miles."
And she was like, "Oh, yes."
Shall I do my pick?
Because it is genre fiction, the roaring years,
which is a collection of Peter Nichols' writing that Peter himself had always planned to do.
But never quite got round to.
And really quite a long time later, Dave Langford has lovingly put together
with the help of Peter's family and many of Peter's friends,
and also friend of the podcast, Claire Barally.
And so quite a lot of it is serious writing about science fiction.
Peter had the ability to look at his own writing and say,
"It wasn't very good until about 1970 or '71, and then it stopped being good in about 2000,
so we're going to pick that central period."
And I think there's a degree of self-awareness in that, which is very impressive.
And so many of his longer, more thoughtful pieces about science fiction books
and also some more light-hearted writing conventions,
con reports, things about science fiction fandom, all sorts of great stuff.
And I haven't actually read all of it because I just formulated the idea that I would read it,
but everything that I have read so far has been very interesting indeed.
I particularly love the conventional reports of the finisher me a new chiai and so on,
like raking over the coals of conspiracy 87, the sponsorship deal with new era publications,
something which would have been very useful reading for the discount committee,
I think, before their convention, because it might have helped them make slightly different
committee decisions in advance. I read a review of this book by Adam Roberts,
and he really, really hates all of that stuff, so horses for courses,
but I like the fact that it's a mixed collection, and we get to see different facets of Peter
Nichols' writing. It's very good collection, and you should all go and get it, and we'll put a link
in the show note. It's available on e-pub, it's also available as a paper book, and all the
profits are going to support the science fiction encyclopedia, which is a good course,
even if they don't have an entry for OctaThorp, the rotors.
I mean, I wouldn't expect them to. Have an entry for Octa? Oh, fuckers.
I see how it is. Liz, do you have a pick?
It's a very big to come up with a pick. I don't know, I seem to have,
I seem to have been in the middle of watching and playing things, and therefore want to finish
watching Andor playing them before I can pick them as my pick, although I suspect.
Once the thing I am watching finishes, Joel and I will have to fight about who gets it as their pick,
foreshadowing, spoilers, etc. Anyway, what is it?
Star Wars Andor.
Oh, it's good.
Yes, it's really staggeringly good.
What do I have to see first?
Nothing really, if you have a vague background knowledge of Star Wars and that there's an
empire and it's maybe not great, then you're probably all right, but Rogue One would probably
help.
Seem Rogue One.
Anyway, that is not my pick because it hasn't finished yet, and it might completely
fuck up the landing. But speaking of things which don't fuck up the landing,
I read the third Naomi Novik Scolomant's book.
I think I've picked all three of these as picks now, and I don't know. It's not that I,
I don't feel like I love them so much that I was instantly wanting to go out and pick all of them
as my picks. They've just come at convenient times. Anyway, it's the third book, it is the
last one of the trilogy, and I think if you remember, I wasn't super keen on the first one because I
felt it was a bit too much of a kind of school story where people were falling into particular
roles that they play in a school story.
Yeah.
And the second one is kind of about them maybe subverting that a bit in that without doing
going too deep into spoilers, instead of it being school rivalries, it becomes kind of like how
the students themselves can basically unite against this school system, which is screwing them all over.
And in the third book, they are out of the school and back into kind of the real world,
or this is a magical world, and it's kind of about how they take the kind of teamwork and
cooperation and work together that they had in the school and try and kind of put that into practice
in this incredibly unfair magical world that is outside the school.
It's kind of interesting. It's very dark in places when you work at what people have been doing to
maintain this system. It is essentially about a kind of corrupt system that is only maintained by
the suffering of the few for the benefit of the many, although it's not even that many in some
cases and about what choices they make when presented with this.
I think if you really are into the kind of romance of books one and two, you probably
will be a little bit disappointed because I don't think that's not as big a part of this book as
you might expect, but I was never super into that anyway, and it really just has those two characters
there to kind of be opposites to each other as they have been all series. And you find out a lot
more about why they are the opposites. They are. It's not an entirely random coincidence.
I'm trying to do this without doing too many spoilers, but it's quite hard when it's the third
one in a trilogy. Anyway, I liked it. I will almost certainly put this as one of my picks for Hugo
Best Series and possibly for Load Star Award as well.
I'm quite excited to hear that the third one's out.
Yeah, it was out like a month ago and it just popped up as though, oh you might like to buy this on
my Kindle list, bought it and read it in a day. It's one of those books.
What you said about them leaving and going out into an unfair magical world reminds me a little
bit of Lev Grosman's The Magicians, but it sounds like this sticks the landing better than that book
did. Maybe? Didn't love the second half of The Magicians, if I'm honest.
I mean, what the whole trilogy?
Oh no, I don't like the second half of the first book.
Oh I see. Very much. I thought it was a bit flimsy, I guess. I quite like where he goes with it in
books two and three, but yeah. Yeah, interesting. There's some things I prefer about The Magicians.
I think The Magicians kind of get that young adults figuring out what adults they're going to be.
Yeah. Better. Oh yeah, 100%. They're like 100%. I agree with that.
I know I think Scallamance is kind of a more traditional, not being more traditional, but
where it goes at the end of the trilogy is possibly a more obvious place to take it than where The
Magicians kind of venture at the end of the trilogy. Okay, yeah, I can see that.
Yeah, it's kind of a, just more of a first book they're in school, second book they're figuring
out how to survive the school system and third book they're on the outside.
So I decided not to read the second one until the third one was out because I thought I would
find that Lefanga rather irritating. I'm so quite excited that the third one is out and I will
probably read them now because I did really enjoy the first one even though there was
something about it that really annoyed me. Ha! Okay, I am very bad at telling whether you enjoy
things because the way you talk about them does not portray your level of enjoyment in a way that I
can, I would have guessed it was a two out of five for you. I think I said, you know, I think I've
finished my review by saying, "recommended for people who like this sort of thing and really
who doesn't?" So, you know, very entertaining books. Yes, I am going to pick another extremely
timely thing. I am going to pick Star Wars the next generation there. I am going to pick Star
Trek the next generation, which quite good. It has rough spots. One notable rough spot is
the entirety of series one to four. That's quite rough. But once you get to the good bits,
it's quite good. It's got some great science fiction in it. It's got Darnock, which is
possibly one of the best episodes of science fiction television ever made. And also Chain of
Command, which is an amazing episode. And especially in season seven has some really
quite good bits, although it does still have episodes where it's like, "Waf is concerned about
Klingonism and Riker is a bit horny." And you're like, "Yes, but we've seen this episode quite a
few times now, so it'd be good if we could have a different one." The end, the last episode,
is stupid. Like, it completely fluffs the ending in the tradition of all long-running,
well-known genre TV shows. But because it's not really building up to that end, because it is not
particularly an arc-driven show, it does matter. And the penultimate episode is very good.
I'm glad I have watched it. I have now watched All of Star Trek, the original series, which also
has a terrible last episode. And all of NextGen and I've moved on to Voyager. And I'm quite
enjoying Voyager so far. It's quite good. Certainly better than early Next Generation and early Star
Trek and early Discovery, which are the other three Star Trek shows I've watched. I went lower
decks, but that starts brilliant and stays brilliant, so unfair comparison.
Have you guys seen Star Trek the Next Generation? Remind me who the captain is? French.
Sounds extremely French. Jean-Luc Picard. Yeah, I've seen some of it then. A very long time ago.
Played by noted French actor Patrick Stewart doing an amazing French accent.
Yeah, then I've definitely seen some of it.
By it is my quest to have watched All of Star Trek eventually. And it's slowly getting there.
It's all still on all, no, sorry, no, all of it. At least NextGen, DS9 and Voyager are all still
on Netflix. So I am taking advantage of my brother's Netflix before they clamp down on the account
sharing next year. Yeah. Oh, right. Are they going to do that? Yep, they've announced it.
So how much of All of Star Trek have you watched now, John? Uh, I've watched all of TOS,
all of TNG, like the first five episodes of Voi, um, all of Lower Decks, first three seasons of
Discovery. I haven't watched Strange New Worlds, haven't watched Enterprise. I think I've seen all
the movie. Picard, the animated series? I haven't seen the animated series. It's on my list,
but I suspect it'll be on Paramount Plus rather than on Netflix. That was The Old
Law podcast and it's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me. It's goodbye from me.
John, why is it? Why is it very purple in your room? I got new bulbs. I actually know I got new lamps.
I already had the bulbs. Oh, do you have a sign on saying on air? I would love to. I'm going out
to that be yet. So the Taspania knows not to break in except with pancakes. The cats, however,
well, the cats haven't managed door handles yet, right? No, they have not because we don't have,
we don't have like door handles. They have door knobs. They are tricky because they don't have
thumbs. I believe once they have thumbs, you have to report them to a kind of special
special secret service that deals with the cats with thumbs. Well, that's the episode art.
I don't know how you can do that as a all being secret cat detectives, but that is absolutely it
and I look forward to Octa Thorper's secret cat detectives. I was just gonna say we want a
picture of like a cat hand creeping up towards a door knob with a thumb, preferably one of John's
cats and John's door knob. Maybe it should have been old bebades in special octa Thorperple light.
It is quite good in here when it's purple. It's quite purple. It is.
You did it like a professional YouTuber, whereas I look like I'm in a basement somewhere.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod in Competec.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license. This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.
[MAIN SOUND]