Hello Oct though, listener, it's John here. Just a very quick note before you listen to the rest of this episode,
that in between recording and releasing this episode,
Discon 3 did in fact rename their promotions division, the communications division.
So, to whoever at Discon is listening to our podcast records, please stop, it's scary.
This is an aggression my grandparents life was ruled by food, so the half of the lunch dishes
washed up. My grandmother would sit down with a cup of tea and two chocolate biscuits,
and that will keep her going for the period between immediately after lunch and property with
sandwiches and cakes and tea, which was at five o'clock. What I loved about that was this is deep
and heartfelt sigh, which is why listeners, you heard me lose my **** halfway through Alisson's
anecdote. It didn't go in the direction I was expected. I thought Alisson was going to send us
into an argument about which meal times happen at which time of day, and we have neatly side
step that and let us never go back. Hello everyone and welcome to the very 36th episode of the
Octa Thought podcast, which is coming to you on the 22nd of July 2021. I am John Coxon.
I am Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty. God, it's only the 8th of July. Yeah, it's weird, isn't it?
Yeah, we are well in advance here. And we are recording early because it is the summer of fun,
summer of fun, and at the time of recording it has been six hours, approximately, since we last
released an episode of Octa Thought, and we have had two letters of comment. And this is mostly
because I said things about cake, which is, I think, very good. Chris Garcia says, "Alice
in is right, so very, very right." Right, anything else in the locks, guys? Alison, I think you might
have done that thing where you read someone saying Alison is wrong, but you you fuzz it up in your
head again. No, I am merely selectively quoting from Chris Garcia's lock. Chris agrees with me on cake,
and well, no. Chris disagrees with Alison on cake, but agrees with Alison on Neil Gaiman,
and also gets a plug for my fanzine lulzine in there, which I appreciated. Thank you, Chris.
Chris also says that brownies are not cake. Brownies were cookies, and then they evolved into their
own category. And the key thing about this is that brownies have never been cookies because,
well, cookies is just the American name for biscuits, and as we know, don't write in,
I mean, do write in, obviously, biscuits have a nice snap to them so that when you pick up a
biscuit, it goes, snap. So this is, um, this is in fact wrong. You pick up a biscuit and it sort
of crumbles apart, or it's very soggy because you had gravy on it, and Chris will know what I mean.
No, no, those are American biscuits, which are scones. No, they're not. Basically baked goods are
hard. No, no, if they're hard, you're doing it wrong. They should kind of be soft and fluffy.
No, if they're hard, they're biscuits. We've been over this. No, no, no, biscuits are crispy,
but they're not hard. They're just kind of yewy a ginger nut. Okay, ginger nuts will break your teeth.
I love ginger nuts. Liz, what's your favourite biscuit? What are they called? Those, uh,
chocolate oleum nuts that are like a sort of rich tea underneath, but they got chocolate on top.
They're even better if you just eat all the chocolate off the top and then throw the rest of it away.
Well, the other option is, uh, Marks and Spencer's, uh, very chocolatey, uh, rounds.
Which, as they say, are more chocolate than biscuit. Marks and Spencer's dark chocolate ginger
biscuits, which remind me of my grandmother because she used to eat two of them every afternoon with her tea.
Chris also says, "Let us all rejoice that a Merry Robinette Coel option for chairing has been
activated." And, um, yes, this is something that happened after we recorded our last episode,
and by the time you hear this, we'll be old at. Yeah, it happened about 20 minutes after we
recorded our last episode, and I did tell John to record a pickup and slip it in, but he didn't.
Nope, I didn't. He also has a question for all of the Oct thought people, which is what is the
best way to get things to us. So, um, said it to me, Chris. I want it. Whatever it is, me.
Email. I assume he means physical tat, but I could be wrong. And then, and Rosin wrote to us with a
letter of comment, um, saying that she too did a slightly sad face when me and Liz spoke about
reading Good Omens as teens. She would have been 19, but only started reading, uh,
Toprech it the year. It was published so probably, uh, 21 before she read it. Um, so yes, and she
agrees with us that John Finnenmore being involved is good. Uh, and she notes he is an excellent
observer, and that is true. And I don't think we've mentioned it last episode, but his, his
observational sketches are amazing. So, um, that is a very good point. Um, and she has joined
Discon 3, and she blames us for this. Sorry, she has bought a virtual membership to Discon 3,
and she blames us for this. She says that listening to Oct thought is an expensive pursuit. Uh, so,
um, sorry about that, and, uh, not that sorry though. Hashtag sorry, no, sorry. Um, and then she
tweeted ours to say forgot to mention in my lock, not all of those things called cake, a cake,
see pancake. And that's a good point, pancakes, not cakes. They are, in fact, biscuits.
No. So, and mentions that listening to Oct thought is an expensive pastime, and I think we can combine
this with Chris Garcia's letter to say, if you would like to send us stuff, obviously get in touch.
We are going to talk about something that we started to talk about last episode. We want to
touch a little bit on how conventions communicate and, and how it might be quite rooted in quite
old-fashioned assumptions about how communications actually work that haven't really been reconsidered
in the modern age. A crude model of how world communications work is that the role of communicating
with the outside world is taken by two of the world contributions, which are promotions and
publications. And this is for good reasons. It's basically because in the old days, most of what
happened in terms of kind of communicating with the outside world was done by writing things on
bit of paper and sending them to people. The key issue here is that obviously the advent of the
internet complicates this model, because it basically means that you have a lot of opportunities to
talk to your membership. And there's a lot of opportunity for potential miscommunications if
one division is communicating on the internet with the membership in a way that is not consistent
with the kind of view of your world con as an entity. And so this is something that I think has
gotten much more common is that now any division can directly interface with the members in a way
that I don't think was anywhere near as possible before the internet was around. But what this means
is that now, instead of having two divisions who are the public facing divisions and the rest kind
of being either public facing but at con or being internal, you have divisions all of which are
effectively public facing. But we haven't reconsidered how world cons communicate in light of that.
I think that best solution to this is to have a communication division whose job it is to come
up with the opinion of the world con on certain issues and to make sure that the world con actually
hues to that line. And I don't mean this in terms of, and so I'm not talking a kind of draconian
controlling the message thing, I'm more talking about a way of making sure that if you take a high
level decision, the communications of your convention actually reflect that high level decision.
What I more mean is if you've decided that it's important to consult Hugo finalists on things that
affect Hugo finalists, you make sure that every division is aware that that is a decision the
convention has taken and you provide support to divisions to enable them to do that well.
I think the same thing is also true of East con but I think East cons have less rigid
organizational structures which are more changeable between East cons. So I think it's less of a
problem there. But one of the reasons I've volunteered to be the head of communications
for the 2024 East con is because I do think some of these comments are applicable to East cons as
well. Now Alison who has made a variety of faces through what I've just said will come in and
disagree with everything and tell me why I am wrong. Liz might want to go first though.
That's very nice of you. I mean I do think John is wrong in some ways. So
John is wrong and then you can follow up with why John is more wrong. So I just say I haven't run
a convention in the pre-internet era because you're going to go back to sort of the mid 90s I would
guess before you go back to one which was not doing things on the internet. So I'm not sure if it's
that more divisions are communicating as much as more divisions can communicate more and they
look faster. The program division would always be communicating with program participants. It's
just now instead of sending them a letter you have like a whole series of back and forth emails and
an awful lot more communication going on. And the same thing with you know like member services will
be communicating a lot more with people. Access for instance communicates with people an awful
lot under an awful lot of like direct sort of member facing communications. So I don't think it's
that it was all it all used to be confined to certain divisions but I think it's just that it
all happens more and faster and in some case it happens in a much more public way.
So but I also think some of this is you can't split communications into kind of public facing
and sort of private communications. Oh you can. I don't think I know that you can because nothing
you know because it gets out yes it does. Yeah I mean I'm thinking you shouldn't do that you
shouldn't think of things as being private and public just because anything you say on behalf
of the convention could be quoted somewhere or revealed even if you didn't intend it to but I
think you can draw distinction between things which are official con communications happening
on those channels and things which are essentially discussions happening in emails between
warm member of convention staff and some of the members and things like that because those I think
maybe don't need to be in such a strong branded voice as maybe your public facing communications do.
I mean and it also depends I mean if it's something you're going to send to like a thousand of your
members you probably do want to think about how it comes across whereas if this is you know someone
sends you a you know a query about where's the nearest pharmacy to the convention center and you
send something back that doesn't maybe need to be quite so strongly thought about. So I think
John's wrong. No I think John is most right in some parts but also wrong in some other parts.
That's what they said when I was born. He's right in some parts but wrong in others.
Yeah it went wrong. So I think we touched on one of the part things that I think last week which is
that the voice of the chair is very important in determining conventions overall tone and that
is not cited in either publications or promotions division. I have a kind of general rant which is
not really necessarily a rant for this particular discussion on the subject what are the publications
of a convention for and if it's not for communicating your conventions philosophy or telling people
information they need to know then then I'm kind of like well why why have them and that
does flow through into things like if you choose to do special publications or something like that
why are you choosing to do those particular special publications and I would include the
program book or souvenir book within that because I think a lot of the stuff a lot of convention
program books are very bad and a lot of the stuff that goes in them is of very poor quality this
this kind of links to a lot of fanish fanishly produced material for a purpose
to order is often quite bad and I think that that that just is an example of that.
And John didn't really touch on on the social media specifically which is kind of an area
ahead within promotions division most of the time but has which has two jobs for most conventions
I think one of which is to again impart the conventions lines to take and philosophy to the
membership but also it's got this reactive role of spotting not only when the internet has come
down on your head and you need to deal with it but also the when bits of your convention are not
worth working properly the way you find out about it first is through your social media team and if
you're lucky it's in direct messages to the social media team where somebody says I've been trying
to raise so and so in bug-f*** division and they haven't really got back to me for four months and
is there a problem there but sometimes it's actually that that conversation is quite public
which is why every every company on the internet is always busy going please please send us a DM
so we can deal with this where people are watching and I think there's a whole thing there about the
process by which we set up effective and rapid communications with members in a way that doesn't
cause volunteers to get extremely tard and stressed out all of the time it's kind of so this is why I
think both outreach and promotions are not a great name for that division and that is where John and
I are in agreement because it's clearly a communications division and that bit I would agree with I think
the role of promotions is increasing as the role of publications should be shrinking I tried to get
rid of them for EasterCon I didn't try to get rid of all of them because we wanted to have some
ACON publications that were good and I think we did but it isn't necessarily shrinking and I think
we should be doing more to think about what it is that each publication achieves and what it does
for members particularly if you're going to put that publication into the post because post
global post is now very expensive I wanted to get rid of progress reports for
follicom in 2018 because I thought they were very outdated and not a very good use of people's
time but it turned out that Eastercons have a kind of flow and rhythm and there's an expectation that
certain pieces of work will have been done by certain dates and those are the dates of the four
progress reports so even if you don't have progress reports it's quite useful as a
kind of planning structure for your convention to say we will announce the following things at the
following times so even if you actually get rid of the physical progress reports you need to be
quite careful that you don't get rid of the work that you should have done by Novocon or whatever
and if you make your overarching communications division like with any other machinery of world
conchangers as us all civil service lags would call it you have to be sure that the jobs you end up
with are sensibly sized and that's something we touched on a little bit last time on progress
reports I think I completely agree that I'm not sure of the merit of posting progress reports to
members but it is definitely helpful to have those milestones and I think you're right that you have
to think about what certain publications are doing so I think for instance I support having
physical readmees physical newsletters at conventions and I quite like the artists showcase that world
contents to do and the reason I like those publications is because I think they each occupy a they each
fill a role at the convention which I think is not necessarily easily filled by other things and I
am even though I am someone who is very technology forward I think being able to have a copy of the
program that doesn't run out of batteries is useful being able to have newsletters that you can wave
people or put in places where people notice them as they're walking rather than having them on a
website that people might not check is useful and having the artists showcases a way to kind of
give people a tangible reminder of the artists that were your convention and a way to connect
with the artwork after they've gone home I think is useful so I do I'm not saying that there shouldn't
be a role for paper publications but I do think you do have to think quite carefully about what the
what the things you want to do with those are and why you're doing them and if the answer is because
we always do it that you might want to have another thing and it might well be that you come up with
reasons you're like oh actually no this does still make sense like physical newsletters and I agree
with you as well I think you are right that effectively what's happening is the promotions or the outreach
division is the communications division but I think that's one of the reasons why I want it to be
renamed because I want it to be I think there's a tendency for Worldcon not to consider the role
that that division has in shaping the message and the personality of the Worldcon and I think
giving it a different name and perhaps refocusing kind of some of what it does would be very helpful
in that regard to make it clearer that they do have that role instead of calling your promotions
division say promotions division or outreach division you could just call it the Worldcon fire
service yeah I think that works also unrelated I have a art request that's just come to my mind
for some reason if you try to control the message too much you are probably doomed but there is a
happy medium and there are certainly things about which the convention should say this is what we've
decided and this is what therefore everybody in a senior role on this convention is gonna say about
it and I don't think it's wrong to have that expectation but I think at the point where you're
going oh we require everyone down to the person who is stuffing um flyers into combags has to have
exactly the same line on everything the convention is doing I don't think that's necessarily the case
but I think it's reasonable to say you'll be generally positive and here are some topics that
we have some standard things that we say about them and we'd like you to say those standard things
yeah I think it can be standard things but it can also be like in a fast-moving situation where
you know things could go in multiple directions like for instance a thing you know with the Hugo
finalists where things are obviously moving very fast and they could have resolved in multiple
different ways I don't think it would be helpful if you ended up with conflicting messages from
different senior members of staff on that one or even kind of senior members of staff just like
disagreeing with each other you're better off kind of you know deciding who is going to take
the lead on communications for the convention for that and backing them up on it.
I help reminding people that they don't necessarily need to weigh in all of the time on every
argument on the internet that concerns the convention that they're working on especially
arguments that are about live issues that don't have resolution yet is not a bad thing to do
which is the thing that I joked last time about Glasgow doing but you know it is sensible.
I was going to ask did has at the time of recording has Meg listened to episode 35 yet that's the
question. It doesn't seem very likely does it because it's been like six hours you should either be
doing practical things that people need to know or things that support your overarching
convention philosophy. So for example for Follycon producing work by I guess Savannah was supporting
the overall sense of what it was that we wanted to do with the convention and for a world con you
might say well producing the art show is is producing the art showcases is expressing our philosophy
about what the art show should be like at this convention but but all too often you kind of get
a thing where you go well here we have a a chunky souvenir book what does it have in it oh let's
look at what last years had it. I'm much more going let's what what is the positive what are the
positive things you're going to try and achieve with this. Yeah so I think that's interesting
because I've been wondering if whether there's also another sort of role now for social media in that
this was some some discussions I was having with friends about non-convention things but just about
like how you try and grow your social media presence and how you try and attract more people to your
social media which is like an increasingly important tool for bringing people to your convention
and sometimes it seems like the strategies for growing your social media presence are not always
going to be completely aligned with keeping your communications just to kind of you know things
that are practically important about the convention or sort of things that relates to philosophy of
the convention. So I think you do need to balance how you can have a sort of engaging social media
presence that actually draws people in and also hopefully posts on a regular basis and is there
to answer people's questions and tell them practical information but also to try and do a bit sort of
outreach just through social media and I know personally I'm not very good at doing social media
for conventions because I'm not very good at getting that balance between you know posting
regularly and posting interesting stuff without kind of just posting things for the sake of it that
are maybe not that related to your convention or its philosophy you're just sort of randomly
posting things on the subject of science fiction fandom for the sake of like trying to pull in
more science fiction fans and I think that's quite a tricky balance to make and I wonder if there are
you know I wonder if there are social media experts that we should be talking to you more about how
we run our social media effectively or trying to get on board on board with us just because I think
some conventions are not regulated and also like there are more and new forms of social media that
we're not really using like I felt I don't think I've seen many conventions with sort of Instagram
or TikTok presences it's all kind of still Facebook and Twitter and I think I would just say I echo
all of the things you've just said about what you find challenging with with kind of doing
timely social media so I think that is a good point Glasgow does indeed its Disability Pride Month
that posted two hours ago on Instagram so Glasgow very much has their social media strategy is we
will be wherever we will have a social media presence wherever we think that the fans are that
would be would enjoy our convention so they for example have social media presence on Ravelry
which is the knitting social network oh that's clever and and also in fanzines because that's
where I think that is just me so I'm not sure if that really counts um I hesitate to say well
we should get people who are professional experts in this in because that's the sort of people who
are professional experts in particular roles aren't always the very best people to run those
things for a world con yes we need to be in more places but that doesn't necessarily mean that
Eastercods suddenly need to have a big top presence yeah I maybe don't mean TikTok but I
may also just be a sign that I am old now and don't know what the good social media platforms are
I thought your point on the the giant logistics document was interesting though because another
aspect of convention publications is making sure they do like move with the times and I'm sure
there's lots of stuff we used to put in convention publications like exact details of how you get
to the hotel that you don't need to anymore often still very useful yeah it's not so very useful
but in a way it's like are you putting in here stuff which is already out there do you maybe just
need like one copy of this at the convention info desk rather than posting it to a thousand people
or similar I mean not not directions hotel yes I guess that is useful because people need to get
to the hotel um but I think restaurant guides have moved from being you know here are all the
restaurants around to more of a sort of like here is how you can pick a restaurant that is going
to suit you and your your party because of you know different accessibility needs or different
dietary requirements rather than you know because people can look in certain ways just like look up
more easily how to get to places they need a slightly different set of information and
want to make your publications change with what people actually need yeah you don't want to abandon
everyone who doesn't have ready access to a smartphone but you can consider that a lot of your convention
that does well and restaurant guides is a really interesting one because I think the merit in a
restaurant guide now is much more tapping into local knowledge than it is giving a kind of dispassionate
summary of what's about because you can get the dispassionate summary from TripAdvisor or Google
Maps wherever you prefer to get your information but if you've got someone who lives in the area
who loves eating out they're going to have the information like don't go on a Tuesday it's the
wrong chef you won't enjoy it or if you go on this day like the queues will be awful going this day
it'll be much better or what that that kind of personal information is really useful and something
that's really difficult to get by just searching but the opening hours you don't that is not useful
because it's it's trivially available yeah I think I'm near near a list that in fact it's the things
like accessibility and dietary requirements which the formal restaurant guides on the internet are
still very poor at often whereas fans definitely need that that's true a lot of convention social
media presences are still quite bad it's this thing that Liz mentioned about talking about stuff that's
kind of random science fiction stuff without it anyway relating it back to the site or the
convention or the people who are likely to be there or or the memberships I mean I kind of I guess
I think of conventions as being a little bit like a fancy that there are a community of people or
a podcast there are a community of people and what you're actually trying to do is find stuff that's
going to be of interest to that community and tell them about that and get and get some engagement
going about that because otherwise the only things on your social media sites will be everybody
whining at you but yeah I think actually the thing is that generating the content for social
media is really hard work and I'm going to bring up Glasgow again as example of you know how for
Pride Month Glasgow had a whole series of posts ready and things to discuss and things that they
could put on their social media feeds so they weren't really you know tweeting happy Pride Month
here's some rainbows it was actual interesting content of interest to their members and Glasgow
specific but that takes an awful lot of preparation and work and you know cohesive communications
strategy and I see too many things that kind of don't do that and just post happy May the Force
be with you today and this is actually a really good point because it kind of gets to something
that Alison was saying earlier where you know there are two schools of thought with the publications
you make you either think well what did the Worldcon do last year or you think about what it is you're
trying to put out into the world and you reflect that but the problem with social media is that if
you take the kind of we'll just do enough that people know we're here you end up with that kind of
just tweeting every two weeks saying happy happy Pride Month happy Star Wars day whatever and you're
not that would be better than the average um convention social media strategy but it I will say
that I think doing what Liz is describing and what Glasgow is doing where you are having that kind
of um sustained program of interesting content is is probably more work than the traditional um
than than assembling the content used to be for the traditional suite of of publications because
you've got vastly more content you need to put out now and so it is I think a real it's a really
difficult thing and Glasgow are making it look very easy so well done to Glasgow Glasgow working
very very hard Esther said at conspire that the things that they were doing in terms of running
panels at conventions and having a lot of blog posts on their social media site and in general
being extremely engaged in all the ways they can be for a bid are kind of what they're doing because
they can't be in all your regional conventions running parties because those those conventions
aren't happening they are running virtual parties as well but they're not you know they're not
serving whiskey to the denizens of Chicago or whatever and um and I feel like that's that's
they've actually directed bid energy they've actually thought quite seriously about well where
can we direct our bid energy if it's not into running parties at regional conventions it's going
to be really interesting to assess how well that works because first I'm interested in in how it
works if you have a communication strategy that relies less on going out and and meeting people
the more on doing it or online but also I think it's a really hard thing to assess because how
well do you how do you judge how well your social media is working do you judge it purely on the
number of people who are joining your bid and you know giving you money I mean that's one way to do
it but also it's clearly like raising awareness and maybe getting you into you know corners of fandom
that you wouldn't otherwise be in or you know getting people engaged from different groups and I'd be
really interested to know if any conventions have tried to kind of assess how their different outreach
methods are working you know can you use like you know different different URLs in different
places to see if you can work out where the referrals are coming from and that kind of thing
John tell me about analytics so um I think this is a really interesting point which I think
I think you can do that it is not clear to me how much of that you can do for free
yeah you can do little bits of it for free but the question about whether you really want to
um yeah I'm not sure how many people either Eastercons or Worldcons are attracting especially
at the bid stage who are not already known to the community through much more traditional
outreach methods like we know those people I just wanted to come back to something that Alison
said earlier about how she was worried she might be repeating herself the other key thing about
Confu-convention communications is you need to repeat yourself because people especially on
on on social media where the things you see are not controlled by are you looking at the right
time but are controlled by kind of what does the algorithm decide to show you it's vitally
important that you tweet things multiple times in different formats if they're vital information
because if you don't people might miss them uh and so you can't assume that if you tweet something
once everyone who you need to read it will read it and that's another really important thing
this is why it's important that everything that people actually need to know is also on your
website in a way that they can find um yeah because literally every piece of information that people
are likely to go looking for needs to be you need to be have either have it there or tell people
how they can get it or when they're going to get it and did we do anything of these things for
punctuation not really but it was fun anyway and we're going to do another oh no that's secret
no we did we did it eventually make sure we put the program on the website it did take us a while
one of the things i find very frustrating about conventions is when they put a piece of
per- a piece of information in one place rather than putting it in many places because that's the
other key and the thing and so there has been examples of conventions in the distant past and in
the more recent past which which have kind of said oh well it's on our facebook and it's like that's
not helpful because i mostly check your website your mailing list and discord so if you've just
put it on your facebook i have missed it despite the fact of following in three different places
and the thing we did do i think quite well for punctuation is that when we wanted to tell
people something it was on our website it was in our emails and it was on our discord and it was on
our social media now i don't think we did a great job of continually pushing those things and i
think we probably could do that better next time but i was there i think punctuation two
much better job than punctuation one where we were like everything's on the discord why is no one
checking uh and something that we did iterate quite quickly for punctuation two to make that better
and so it is one of those things that if you don't think about it it's very easy to fall into that
trap but um put everything you want people to know in as many places they will read it as possible
we did forget to put the punctuation two program on the website for quite a long time though until i
told people it was on the website and then had to go john put the program on the website
look right we're clever listeners so there's room for improvement
but also if you think that we are holding world cons to a higher standard than easter cons which
we're holding to a higher standard than the convention we've run in six weeks flat for a bunch of mates
then you are not wrong i think i gave john my air table for folicon and suggested he might like it
for 2024 and i feel like if you don't have a grid system for your communications as if you
were like number ten or something you do need one even if you're quite small certainly regionals need
one you need you have to have a calendar and know when your big messages are coming and know
when you've got fallow periods and you're going to have to have the summer of fun or something to
to find things to tell people because there's nothing going on and and you need to have that
stuff quite early and in quite a boring way and although john says make sure that everything is
everywhere you need you often need to have the same message in multiple different formats and you
need to you need to have art and and pictures that you could use to go with your messages and
you need to know places that you could get them and all of this stuff is a lot of quite i mean it's
not really like professional social media work i mean it is like professional social media work
but it's like the most boring and basic type of it but you kind of need to do that stuff and
if you are just still at the phase of oh this has happened we should tweet something you probably
should take a step back from that and i think a lot of conventions are still doing social media in a
very seat of the pants sort of way that's not necessarily helpful
did i say last time that having a Hugo division that both administered the
Hugo's and ran the Hugo like ceremony was probably a bad idea yeah oh well i won't do that again
then although if you did i have a new thing which might be good which is that Nicholas
Nicholas White wrote a thing about the Hugo's and what he's voting for in best related work
and one of the things he sort of buried as a nugget in that bit was his emotional reaction to
watching the Hugo ceremony at Conzeland because he felt quite strongly that the Hugo ceremony at
Conzeland did not reflect what he was trying to achieve as the administrator of the Hugo's and i
thought that was quite an interesting example of an area in which a failure to have a clear
convention line on what something was had basically meant that the eventual public facing
Hugo's from Conzeland were something that the Hugo administrator was sad about
i think i think the things the set of things that went wrong with Conzeland's Hugo ceremony
um it's quite big and a lot of it's related to failing to cope with the pandemic and therefore
failing to keep George under control which they might not have been able to do anyway but certainly
couldn't under the circumstances and yeah but i think i think that happens maybe to a lesser
extent across the whole of the convention like it's perfectly possible to put together a great
program and then find that the advertising of it by you know the promotions or communications
division is kind of really disappointing and in direly not focusing on what you want them to
or to put on a set of really great events and find that you know the
publications vision managed to not list them in the right way in the program like i think there's
lots of ways divisions interact where basically you can cause there's a point with to one division
because of what the other one does but i don't think that's an argument for kind of reforming
them in different ways i think actually what you're arguing for is better communication between
divisions rather than reforming them in a different way yeah i think so i mean essentially what you're
saying is that you have to take this set of division heads who are and possibly deputy division heads
who are very global come come up the world come from very different perspectives often have very
little in common and sometimes actively hate each other and form them into a cohesive team despite
the fact that everyone's working on a voluntary basis and it's all a big set of baronies so
um yeah quite hard i mean it's it's not trivial but i mean you just get done better at some
conventions than others no one and i will just say i think i think you and lissey both right i think
that is the answer but i just um i thought it was worth bringing up just because i think it
it kind of got a little bit while i was trying to get to that last week but i do agree with both of
you i mean there is something here too about the actual job of chairing a worldcon which is
sufficiently in order to get it you have to kind of you have to be very single-minded about it in
a way that is not necessarily doesn't necessarily require the same skill sets as the building a
cohesive happy team skill set and at least in at least a couple of cases i've watched as conventions
kind of jockeyed around who would end up with the chairmanship of the convention and have not
ended up with the person that i would have thought would be the best at pulling the team together
and and i think that's the sort of thing that does play out down the line yeah i i think that
goes with the very when we were talking about conventions which have a very strong chair's voice
versus of the don't sometimes having a very strong chair's voice kind of just sets the tone for the
whole thing and so when you are if you have the kind of the chair in place when you are recruiting
the division heads then they kind of know what they're what they're getting into you know they sort
of know what the tone of the convention is going to be and i think you can also mitigate this because
you know which divisions are going to have to work more closely with each other and which ones are
going to be at kind of more arms length and so you try and make sure that the division heads and
divisions that are going to work really closely with each other are you know more on the scale of
working well together rather than the hating each other side of things you know you know like
programming events are going to work very closely together i think you know that sort of facilities
and member services are going to work very closely together and that kind of thing i and by the
same tone it's clear that wuss was division is often quite detached partly because of the hugo far
wall but in general is often quite detached from some of the other areas of convention and that
is an issue for things like the hugo ceremony where obviously they should be working very closely
and tandem with events i mean wuss was basically kind of rins almost three separate things that
don't actually go very closely together because it runs the hugos it runs site selection it runs
the wuss was business meeting and those three things just kind of go together because they're
the things you sort of have to run because wuss was exists but they don't actually sit together
that neatly oh they sit together neatly and that they're the precise set of things that the world
can't be required to do so um alie baker who is um someone who will be well known to
east con fans uh she has run programs at east conlan is running the program with vajena
preston at the 2022 east con uh has started a new podcast it's called the fantasy book swap and the
basic um concept for the podcast is that a guest picks a favorite fantasy book from their childhood
alie picks a complimenting contemporary book and they talk about them the first episode is a
dela terelle and alie talking about the magic far away tree and the dragon in the library by
louis stowell and they will be recording that um in between now and when this episode comes out
and there will be a link in the show notes i think this is a really cool idea and i'm pretty sure
alison is excited too yeah so so i i the magic far away tree was my favorite book in the whole world
when john was minus 15 years old or something like that i don't know the magic far away tree is the
first book i remember reading i have a lot of of fondness for that yeah i mean it's it's it was
my first not necessarily my first chapter book and certainly not my first book because i i read
a lot of very short books but but certainly the first book that i kind of had that reading
experience fanish reading experience of reading the same thing over and over again and go this is
this is amazing i should i want to read this all of the time um i i grew out of that phase
the last time i finished a book of wet i must start this again from the beginning um it was
wolf hall and it's sequels by hillary mantel and i got over it pretty quickly because it's like
a hundred and an eighteen hundred pages long anyway um so i have read the dragon in the library
and i really didn't like it very much at all and i haven't reread um the magic far away tree but i
suspect i wouldn't like that very much at all either and i think this is because i'm not eight
what i think both of these books are really aimed at people who are quite a bit younger than me
now but i do have lots of interesting thoughts about the dragon in the library so i'm going to
pre-lock alleys podcast and i think if you also have a lot of interesting thoughts about these
books you should pre-lock it as well so she can start the podcast with a load of a load of letters
that say this is a this is more an opinion than a question and i think you are right i don't know
um i have not read uh the dragon in the library and and i i'm probably not going to because i'm still
chewing my way through the hugo voter packet um thank you very much allison i am also chewing my
way through the hugo voter packet um i think i've read about eight percent of shawnan maguire's series
uh so you know there's work to be done i am super excited to listen to the podcast i think it's a
really good idea for a podcast it plays to alleys strengths both in genre and in her academic expertise
really well and i think it's really cool that we're getting more podcasts coming out of the british um
science fiction fandom uh and i think that is just that can only be a good thing so um well done alleys
and i look forward to hearing episode one and i really love the way that it's speaking directly
to this way that people have fond memories of the books that they've read in childhood and so
believe that they are much better than they were in fact and are in fact and and hopefully that's
something that will come out i i have suggested a book which i still think is quite good that is one
of my favorite books for childhood so hopefully i'll be a future guest on this show and i did not
suggest but somebody else might like to i did not suggest journey to jupiter by a few vultures but
i didn't think about it quite hard which would have been which is possibly a book that was even
more influential on me than than um the book i have picked oh is this is this is finally the
all going to be on a future episode i'm hoping to be on a future episode yeah i i i i i i saw i
nabbed the book so so she has somebody else talking about that book i'm going to be very
sulky what book did you pick alison i'm not going to say because you know i want it to be a surprise
when the podcast comes out but i mean anyone who knows me and knows the books that i cite as
influence such a children's books would probably have a good guess um somebody else in that thread
grabbed carton quidder which is another book that i might well have chosen but i didn't read it when
i was a child so i don't think it would count this is one i did read as a child because it was a
television series when i was a child i think i have not i have not asked alie whether i could be or
no or not uh i don't know if i will but if i did ask or if he invited me the book i would pick would
be rebekah's world by terry nation which is a phenomenal children's book as the only children's
book terry nation wrote and it is the same terry nation from the dalex and it is about a world in which
ghosts are repelled by wood and that's why there are no ghosts and we don't realize that until we've
chopped all the forests down and replaced them with gleaming skyscrapers and modernity and it is
i i just loved it when i was a kid um i thought it'd brilliant i have no idea how it holds up i have
no idea what alie would say about it um but but yeah it's my kind of i have always loved that book
it's a great choice liz what would you pick if you went on the podcast i don't know i'm thinking
about this now i think the problem is i was probably reading books that were age group inappropriate
when i was uh you know too young for them and so i'm now trying to think of what fantasy books i
read that might have been like actually age appropriate rather than an macafrey which was not uh and
very much not i mean maybe i will um who i think it was uh false meadows who read a bunch of early
and macafrey and just highlighted all the immensely terrible stuff in them oh some of which i picked
up on even even at the time so you can tell how kind of egregious it must have been um that's
made me it's maybe a digression but i'm trying to think i'm trying to think of what i would have
read i must have read stuff i mean i read i read like every book in the library so this is probably
the problem is i read so many books as a child it was basically whatever was in the library and
nothing has stood out as i read it 27 times apart from i read a lot of books about girls going to
ballet school or going to boarding school or boarding ballet school or that kind of thing
did you read any about girls going to magical boarding ballet schools
no i don't think i did that's the thing they're all going to sensible boarding schools and except
for one who gets like consumption and then has to go to a special boarding school i feel like this
is not this is not john's reading experience if nothing else we're learning we're learning a lot
about formative liz which i thoroughly enjoy there's a there's a there's a group on facebook
called finishing school which is a a group of people who chat about um all fashioned all
fashioned children's books so so things like angela gets it off and you know
she'll enjoy her pody's oh i will no i i actually know i know what it would be now
i think what it would be is actually i started reading all these point torah and point fantasy
books that are you know probably when i was at primary school so actually yes
they'd be a great choice it's a lot of terrible books about like american high school kids getting
murdered on on demonic roller coasters and things excellent well there's our children's book so i
think that's a good i think that would be good great choice yeah yeah definitely oh jesus so jon
do you want to know how much the audiobook of rebekah's world by terry nation narrated by paul
darrow will set you back on amazon i don't know but you should do it 894 pounds jesus
i mean not these are what we're saying here is that rebekah's world is a rare book at this point
that was the octa thought podcast and it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
[Music]
where are you at the moment liz i am in the uk in captivity next to the nicest garden in the world
it is a very nice garden i don't think it's the nicest garden in the world but it is lovely
some very nice garden she was like i'm in captivity she showed us this photograph of
a beautiful garden do you bet john said i was in captivity and i said you were in captivity
oh no i listen said i was in captivity and i thought i should point out that actually i have an
entire house with a nice garden to myself so it's it's really not that bad the theme music for this
episode was surf shimmy by kevin mccloud and combatec.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.