Lizbati, Lizbati, does whatever a lippity can. Can she look at the stats? Yes she can, but she has no cats. Look out. Here comes the Lizbati.
Hello everyone and welcome to the 100th episode of Octa Thought which is coming to you on the 4th of
January 2024. I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott and I'm Lizbati. It's been 100 episodes. 100.
That's quite a loss isn't it? That's a lot. When did we get to 100? I don't know. How did that
happen? Yeah number go up. And so we're carrying on. We're not stopping doing more in 2024 because
2024 is going to be a super quiet year for British science fiction fandom in which nothing important
is going on. I mean if you end up murdered in your bed with a horse head made of Glasgow tartan
on your pillow I will not be surprised. I nearly, it was midnight and I thought oh I could text Esther
and say "hoping you have a peaceful and uneventful 2024". And it's time for letters of, hang on a minute,
there's someone at the door. Oh it was the postman and he had a telegram. Oh now so non-
non-British listeners may not be aware but on your 100th birthday you get a telegram from the monarch
and we have a telegram here. Below two pieces of weetabix it reads
"I am so pleased to know you are celebrating your 100th episode in January 2024.
I send my congratulations on best wishes to you on such a special occasion."
Claire Briarley of Croydon.
I may have solicited this particular lock.
John is screen-chairing it and yeah very good telegram.
Thank you very much to Claire for sending us our birthday telegram.
I thought it was apt given as Claire is obviously the reigning monarch of British fandom.
Absolutely and then I'd like Mark's the Prince chord sort right?
Yeah I think that's apt. I think that makes sense.
Yeah they better have thrones for the McGlasko that's all I can say.
*laughs*
Thank you very much to Claire for our birthday telegram.
We will see you at East Con and Glasgow variously.
I'll see you on Thursday.
Yes, that's fair.
Christopher J Garcia emailed to say "barreling towards 100.
What sort of special will you all be unleashing this, this?"
It's the hangover special.
Yeah we are recording on New Year's Day.
In the morning.
With very few show notes.
Yeah but alcohol.
It's afternoon for Liz.
Yeah I don't have show notes or alcohol.
So anyone who is
minded to complain that this is a slightly short slightly disorderly episode
should look to last year where we put out a two minute episode for New Year.
Did we?
Yeah we do have so he says is this the first chapter of a trip report
appearing on a podcast?
Yes we believe so.
If you know differently listeners write in but I think so.
And he says Sandra is indeed a good egg.
Thank you again Sandra for standing in for Liz who was on assignment.
I must say something about my assignment.
You can if you like but there's no obligation.
You pause for meaningful length of time.
Are you an unassignment Liz?
I will actually briefly say thank you to various bits of Bay Area fandom
for showing me various bits of the Bay Area and also John who is not part of Bay Area fandom
for showing me various bits of Bay Area.
Well John are you like on a remember of Bay Area fandom did you marry into it or something?
Does that count?
Yee so sort of yes and no.
Yeah.
A Bay Area in law.
Because I it's because I like actively work to take his fan you're away from Bay Area fandom.
I'm not sure whether I count as a member or whether I'm like an agitator.
Mmm are you their nemesis?
I've been to a bass for meeting which for someone first in pub meetings in the UK was
utterly bewildering.
Oh all oh god everywhere they're all like this.
Seattle and Toronto weren't?
No but um Nesva is and I think Lasvas is and the Australian some of the Australian ones are.
The critical what's it called critical thing?
I should know this.
Critical thing yep very enough.
And Novamob and yeah the meetings it's really weird.
I guess from that perspective like I guess the BSFA and the nine-plus alpha like are more
meeting focused sometimes but like yeah it was weird to have like a uh uh city group
be chaired uh odd but yes me and Liz went to a board game shop and then we went to
a book shop and then we went to another book shop and then we had pizza and beer.
It was pretty good.
And Brussels sprouts.
Yes Brussels sprouts with daka and pomegranate molasses which were
frigging great.
JC was at the party I was at last night and um he was wearing a t-shirt with a picture of a
Brussels sprout and the words not just for Christmas.
I agree with that I do agree with that.
Chris also says we have half of the Hugo stats numbers look like voters were voting in
patterns that he thought they would although Journey Planet did better than he'd have thought.
So yeah we know the voting for we know the voting but not the nominations.
Yeah so we know where we came in the stats.
Third.
I think I was fourth or fifth and we were third we're third.
It's pretty good.
And Journey Planet was three votes off winning.
Really?
Oh.
Which I was I was surprised by because like it often comes second which I think is the
dichotomy between traditional fanzine like effect basically people who like PDFs and people who like
websites.
And I think basically the final two end up being all the people who like PDFs are very
for Journey Planet and all the people who don't haven't.
But yeah it was closer than I expected.
But but actually the Chinese the Chinese fanzine that won is PDFs.
It was it was quite a good year for traditional fans of.
But also congratulations to Hugo Girl again for if you look at the stats
knocking all the rest of us into a cockid hat.
They got significantly more votes than anyone else.
Excellent.
Yeah they crushed us they crushed us all.
Fear their domination.
I'm kind of like Hugo Girl could crush me any time they like.
We should get badges because we have t-shirts.
Crushed by Hugo Girl.
We're not that sort of podcast.
Come on.
We were fourth, by the way, not third.
Oh, I thought we were ten, oops.
You were fourth, I thought we were fourth, I thought I was fourth as well.
But maybe I was fifth, I don't know.
I don't. You were fourth.
I was fourth.
You can tell I paid a lot of attention.
As our official Hugo Statz mayven, Liz.
Yes!
What is the deadline for Dave McCarthy getting his figure out and getting the bornated zaps up?
Oh, I meant to look this up and then I forgot.
Nom, nom, nom, nom, nom, nom, nom, nom.
Liz bat.
OK, so one of the things I did in the last week is read the six Warren Ellis written.
Declan, Shavy, Drawn, episodes of Moon Knight issues.
Hey!
I can't distinguish the words issues and episodes in my mind anymore.
They have become one word.
Yup, ish, ish opponents.
So, and they are, they are very stylish.
Yes.
And I kind of understand some stuff at the end of them, but I'm kind of like,
"Should I go on and read the rest of the run written and drawn by other people or not?
Or should I just go and watch the TV show?"
The current Moon Knight run, I think, is better than the rest of the Ellis run
and has extremely good art, but also has a really interesting,
it's got some really interesting mystic concept.
So if you wanted to carry on reading Moon Knight comics, I would read the currently
running Moon Knight, which I really enjoy.
I would say, what do they say about these things?
I mean, the story is fine, but the art is fantastic.
So that, and there is in particular, a bit of sequential art,
which I think is fantastic that I have not seen used before in episode issue two,
the sniper.
Yes, yes, another one you mean.
So I thought that was a magnificent and, yeah, not a pick,
but that was one of the other things I did over Christmas in the year.
So I might go, I might do some more Moon Knight.
It is the reason Moon Knight's relevant people is that over in another place,
doing the Moon Knight game book as a kind of collective thing.
Choose your own adventure. Yeah.
So I was like, how do I know nothing of this character?
I still don't understand why the character totally passed me by,
despite the fact that Bill Cinkovitz drew it in like 1980 or something.
And I was quite the Cinkovitz fan for a while.
I would say I think the current runner
moonlight also has great art, which is one of the reasons why I'm really
enjoying it, like some of the art reminds me of that Ellis run.
Liz, you return.
Yes.
What did you find out?
What did I find out?
So the full Hugo stats must be released by January 19th.
So we are at most kind of two weeks away from stats, full step.
Whoo.
Well, not quite.
There is a chance they won't be out the next time we record.
Yeah, I mean, there's a chance they won't come out on January 19th,
because what happens if you don't do the stats on time, basically, nothing.
But I think they probably will.
Dave McCarthy, I'm going to sick moonnights on you.
I mean, Jeff is phone number.
You're just going to call him up.
That's just helping job with his editing issues.
Yeah.
Do you want some like stats?
Fingers, though, from what we've got so far.
Oh, yes, please.
Yes, yes, yes.
Yes.
And I mean, I also say that Nicholas White did a blog post on this as well, which we will link to.
Basically, there were quite a lot of sort of just first round winners, right?
Like you don't have to redistribute them.
They've just got a ton of votes.
So they are over 50 percent of the votes in the first round.
So, for instance, Nettle and Bone was a runaway winner for novel.
You know, some of the others are quite close, but that was a runaway winner.
Surprisingly, to me, children of time was a runaway winner.
I thought that was going to be quite a contested category.
Yes.
Isn't that fantastic?
Nobody was just like everyone was like, no, this is clearly brilliant.
Give it a hugo, which is correct.
Correct, I say.
I mean, it's correct, but I did spend at least two years
bigging up Robert Jackson Bennett's trilogy, which came last.
So you can still read it.
Still there. It's still good. Yeah.
Yeah. No, that surprised me.
Some of the ones that came last were almost more surprising, right?
Because like, no, no came last in novels.
So clearly a lot of people did find that book enormously frustrating and it was not
just Alison. Yeah.
So like the Terry Pratchett biography again, runaway winner, everything everywhere,
all at once, unsurprisingly, pretty much a runaway winner.
I'm not all of these were in the first round, but they were like well ahead of
everyone else, Neil Clark, best editor, and J.
Now, absolutely smashed it in a press professional artist, which I was not
expecting. I mean, I thought their art was great, but I wasn't expecting them to get
kind of over 370 out of 710 votes.
So that was pretty impressive.
Stranger Isons were in the lead for five rounds and lost on the very last
redistribution of votes by 20 votes.
So that was really close and it must be, I think it must be a bit
going for the Stranger Isons team who have been second a lot and they're kind
of almost there and never quite make it.
Yeah. Best Fanzine was incredibly close.
Best Fancast was not best fan writer, one vote in it.
Hmm. Yeah.
So if you didn't vote in Best Fan writer, you could have swung it.
Well, you could have made a tie, which would have been very interesting.
Who could you swung it for?
Well, you could have saw it was Chris Barkley by one vote over Riverflow.
So if you were playing for Riverflow and didn't.
Yeah. Yeah, don't tell them.
Yeah. So that's the Hugo voting stat.
We're still in letters of comment.
This has been a very oddly structured episode.
That's OK. I mean, it's that time kind of between Christmas and New Year.
Time has no meaning.
Bitwixtmus.
It's not between Christmas and New Year, Liz, because the New Year happened already.
Kind of. Yeah, but it's still in that that
Interregnum before anybody does any work spiritually.
It's in the 12 days.
Do you think we can do this entire episode without ever leaving the letters of comment
segment? Maybe that could be episode 100.
We've only got one more letter of comment.
So, yeah, let's let's go go.
Why not? We have a letter of comment from Erwin Hirsch.
I have to explain that I was joking about thing, which is when I said it's
quite a coincidence that both of the fan funds are sending delegates to the World
Con. No, of course it isn't.
I ran a fan fund for two years.
I understand how fan funds work, people.
And I thought it was weird that Alison and Sandra both treated me as if I was
like being completely on the record.
So I didn't say it out loud.
It was a joke.
I'm not saying it was a funny joke, but nevertheless, Erwin Hirsch has written
to enumerate some stats on this happenstance.
But we do love stats.
Thank you, Erwin.
Stats are great.
Yeah.
And what I actually need to do is work out whether the stats disprove the null
hypothesis or whether it's actually impossible to reject the null hypothesis
that this is a coincidence at the 5% level because it would be quite funny if
actually the evidence doesn't prove the hypothesis.
But unless Erwin has lost count since 1979, there have been eight World
cons in Europe and at seven, Guff and Taff both had delegates.
The only one that missed out was 1990, which was the Hague.
Yeah, it was a conviction of the Hague.
Yeah, which there was no Taff race.
And actually, I am genuinely surprised that that is the case.
I would have assumed they all had one of each.
And if it hadn't been one, I would have assumed it was Guff.
So yeah, I'm surprised that it was Taff letting the side down.
Yeah, I think Taff might have been in slight.
Oh, was that just after Abbey Frost?
I don't know, but a slight disarray.
Don't maybe to the Taff website.
I'm already on it.
No, it's pre Abbey Frost because I was I feel like I was quite an actor fan
at the point where Abbey was running and and in 1989, I kind of wasn't, you know,
I was inter-fandom, but I wasn't.
I didn't, I wasn't really into Taff and stuff.
Yeah, so I don't know why there wasn't one.
I mean, maybe they just didn't have enough
funds or maybe they just didn't have enough support at the time to manage to run
two races in the same direction in consecutively.
But basically they skipped 1990 in Thailand.
Yeah.
So also Erwin says in 1984, Rob Hanson was
LA con two as the Taff delegate and just an
aquoid went to LA con two for a lot his guff trip, which I do feel is a slight
kind of stretching the boundaries of what guff is for.
But there we go.
I mean, it's yes, it's good looking back at the history, isn't it?
It is.
And I think we should thank Dave Langford for having a website that basically
has every single race and like all the newsletters online.
So I can actually dig into this.
You're showing your showing guff up a bit on you, Dave.
Because I've got a whole string of emails in my
intray inbox that are basically shouldn't we do something about the Guff website,
to which the answer is definitely oh, yes.
Like should go have a website.
Guff does have a website.
It's Taff.org.uk/guff.html.
Yeah.
That which, you know,
and there's also Oz fans dot A.U or something like that.
Oz fans, Oz fans.com.
I can segue here, I think.
Speaking of world cons Glasgow in 2024,
the world con that will be happening this year in Britain announced a special guest
who is games related.
Tell us about her.
Yes, they announced Tanya de Pass, who is, I mean, I know her from,
I think her blogging and Twitter and else was a founder of any diverse game.
So a game, you know, a project to diversify gaming.
And so she's done a lot of work on video games and on RPGs.
And yeah, I'm not going to go through the whole biography, which is on the Glasgow
website and we'll link to it.
But she sounds like a great guest and I think she feels maybe a gap in the guest
and a line up of someone who is deeply, deeply involved in games and has done a lot
of interesting work in the field of games.
And that will be really nice to kind of have have that filled by an expert special
guest. So I'm quite excited about this way.
No, it's good.
Glasgow are going from strength to strength.
No, she's a really good choice for guest.
This is brilliant.
Yeah.
Erwin also talks.
He says the only conventions where Guff and Daff both sent delegates that were not
World Cons were the 2008 and 2012 British Easter cons, although I think that's wrong
because Sue Ann and Trevor Klark, Sue Ann Barber and Trevor Klark attended
L.X. in Bradford and that was 2009.
So I wonder whether it's just 2012.
But did we have a tough delegate that year?
Chris, we had the he says that Sue Ann Barber and Trevor Klark and Chris
got here both went to 2008 and I know Chris was at 2008, but I remember Sue Ann
and Trevor were at L.X.
So I don't know whether that's true.
I wonder whether the list of past Guff winners says that Sue Ann and Trevor went
to 2008 because they did not know.
No, the Guff website is correct and backs up my memory.
And then the 2009 TAF trip would have been to the States.
I can't remember who won it.
2009 TAF.
Yes.
Who was oh Steve Green.
Steve Green won it because he was administrator when I was running.
So Erwin, I think it's just the 2012 Easter con because the 2008 Easter
con did not have the Guff delegates and there wasn't a Guff race in 2008 at all.
But the 2009 TAF race was the to the States.
So there's there's no way Sue Ann and Trevor were a convention with a TAF
and Chris wasn't a convention with a Guff.
So I think that's incorrect.
But thanks for writing in Erwin.
On the subject of writing, have you guys read any books recently?
Mate, I've read a lot of books.
I feel like I feel like 20,000,000,000 was a much better book reading year for me
than 22,000,000,000,000.
But good read says I read fewer books.
So I'm confused and I still did not hit my 52 books in a year read.
But I have read the Coral Bones by E.J.
Swift, which was one of the nominees, one of the finalists for the clock award.
I thought it was pretty good.
And this novels tells the story.
It's three interlinked narrative.
I mean, I'm a sucker for this, right?
Three interlinked narratives by women past, present and future.
And they are all connected to coral reefs.
I understand that Swift had not visited Australia when she wrote the book,
but she definitely had visited Australia by the time she wrote the
acknowledgments in the book.
So because she did actually get out and go snorkeling.
So there is a little bit of a this is a holiday book about it.
I didn't really interested to see whether actual Australians like this book or only
or only people who have recently visited Australia, for whom a lot of the
scenes and events in it were quite resonant.
There's a kind of current story about climate change destroying the Great Barrier
Reef. And there is a past story in which a woman who is the daughter of a
explorer successfully managed to get out to go on one of her father's expeditions
in a way that is not necessarily all that convincing.
This is a that's I thought the least good section of the novel.
And there is a future world where people are dealing with the consequences of climate
change and yes, it's another climate novel, but I thought it was quite good.
Really enjoyed it.
I also really enjoyed Liz's pick for Shadowing.
Well, I really enjoyed your pick, Alison, which I think I've mentioned at the time.
So it's a good book.
We should read a good 2022 book.
Haven't started talking about good 2023 books yet.
The Coral Bones is the Clark Award nominee that people thought was good that I
haven't read yet. And I am it is on my list of things to read, but I am hoping I
will very much like it. It sounds like my cup of tea.
Also, it is beautifully produced by a small press called "Unsung Stories",
which differs from other UK small presses in that it has extremely strong design
views and they've packed it in because they can't make any money and it turned
out that they were, you know, they were doing it a little bit of work for for the
return and eventually it became too much for them, but they've published some good
books in the meantime.
This is one of the ways that small presses go.
So that's a bit sad.
But anyway, this is a good book and it would be nice to have small presses who
are publishing very good books like this.
So what I'm hearing is I need to hurry up and buy it before I can't.
Oh, I know they've packed they've not gone bust.
They've just stopped doing publishing new books.
OK.
I mean, I think you have to buy them as ebooks now.
I keep their old books in print.
Probably won't be able to get a paper book very easily, I don't think.
No, you can only get a handful of paper books from them, but I think they're still
up as ebooks on Lee Summer's doors.
I'm just going to check that out, actually.
Fair enough, fair enough.
Yeah, you can still buy on Kindle.
I don't think you can buy the ebooks.
And I can buy ebooks through their website and there's a hand full of paperbacks left.
So yeah, it is a shame.
No, it's a great shame.
And I think I think it will be more up your avenue, John, because I think you
like venomous lump sucker, I think there is more to kind of either really like or
dislike about it.
It's a bit more marmighty.
I think the coral bones is just kind of
yeah, reliably good, but maybe the highs are not quite as high as venomous
sucker if you like it. Yeah, I mean, I can see why both why the club judges gave
the award to venomous lump sucker over this and also why people might think that
was a terrible thing to have done.
Liz, do you have read any books?
It's a simple question.
Do you have read any books?
I do have read books.
Wait, apparently in 2023, I somehow read 96 books.
Wow.
Hold on, hold on.
I don't know when I I don't know when I did that on the beach.
It was on the beach.
I've only been to the beach a couple of times like this year.
I need to go to the beach more Liz.
Oh, you set us photos of the beach more than twice in 2023.
I don't think I did.
I think I may have sent you pictures of a couple of different beaches, maybe,
but they're all in the same location.
I had one beachy trip, so obviously I need to go to more beaches so I can read more
than 96 books.
But yeah, I think in a future episode, we can go through some 2023 books and things
we would like to nominate, maybe for the Hugo's.
But I will make a start by picking some desperate glory by a standing award winner
Emily Tesh.
I've got to confess I didn't really pay much attention to the novella that she
won the astounding award for, but this is her first novel and it is really good.
Nice.
I'm going to say more John.
I'm not finished yet.
Oh.
It is basically a space opera about Kia who is essentially a child soldier
training to avenge the destruction of planet Earth.
And so she's been raised by kind of the last bits of humanity on a space station
in a very regimented environment ready for the time she will go out and kind of
take revenge on the aliens who destroyed the Earth.
And I mean, it doesn't take you long to realise what's going on, which she is
basically being raised as this fascist soldier by these renegades humans.
And the novel is about her figuring out that maybe, you know, everything she's
been told is a lie, but it's not all a lie.
So it's it sounds like a very kind of bog standard, maybe why a space opera.
Oh, she's a child soldier, but fish figures out.
So what's going on and has an epiphany and it all ends up going OK, but it kind of
almost like speed runs enough block to put into about three novels and it's got
alternate universes and kind of alternate versions of her and alternate ways.
Things could have gone and it sort of sets up this little squad and you think,
she's going to have this squad of disparate individuals who all come together to
save things and no, not really.
It's much more interesting than that.
So I can say is like, if you read the blurb, you might think this sounds like a
very not an interesting twist on a story that's been done before, but it is a really
interesting twist on a story that has been done not quite like this before.
So you should all go out and read it.
Interesting.
That sounds really good.
I really liked it.
And I thought it did a very good job of both making it very clear that she was
she was well read in the genre of young adults books that that had done these
sorts of that had dealt with these sorts of themes, but was obviously doing a fresh
take on it, but also doing a book that would be perfectly accessible to somebody
who had not read all of those books.
And I thought that's quite clever.
Yeah.
I think it was absolutely perfect, but I think it's generally pretty good.
There are lots of things I liked about it all through.
And it's one of the books for 2023 that is getting quite a lot of buzz.
So thank you.
The library systems of the world.
I was going to talk about libraries because I had a library crisis.
I forgot to renew my library books when I was in Australia and unfortunately there
were 10 of them.
And by the time I found out I had incurred a fine of 65 pounds.
And then when I returned to Britain and said, Oh, no fair dues.
I will pay this fine.
I discovered I was caught in a cat,
a cat, a grass nightmare where I could only pay the fine by going physically to a
library and paying on the machine.
But the first time I went, the second machines were down and the second time I
went, it wouldn't let me pay.
It was like you're blocked.
You're blocked user.
You cannot pay a fine.
And I was like, well, can I pay a fine another way?
And I was like, well, you can only pay the fine on the machine and took five library
visits and about 40 emails before this got sorted out.
But the resolution was that they waved my fine.
I'm reasonably happy and my library card works again.
But it kind of told me not to do my former habit was to take out 10 endless
live paper library books and keep them renewing them until the point where I
finally got around to reading them.
And this was probably this is probably a mistake.
So I'm going to try and reduce my dependence on actual paper library books.
And in honor of this, I have found a couple of libraries that you can join,
despite not being a resident of the relevant place so that I can increase my
library reach.
And I don't want to kind of broadcast them.
But thanks Emily January who told me how to do this tomorrow and tomorrow and
tomorrow, which is a previous pick from Liz.
I had a 498 day waiting list on Libby for London libraries consortium.
And it has been delivered to my e-reader,
the California library that I joined.
So I'm quite pleased with that.
So because that's a 2023 book.
It's not.
So because this problem with very long wait times from libraries is that you cannot
read books in nomination season unless you buy them.
But you know, I mean, I do appreciate your enthusiasm, but it was published in 2022.
So what's it?
A bollocks.
That tickled me.
OK, I am also going to discuss a book that I read that is from that is from 2022.
And that is The Spear Cuts Through Water by Simon Jimenez.
It really good.
Two thumbs up.
Didn't I pick it?
Nope.
Oh, I thought I did.
Maybe not.
As not as far as I can tell.
Oh, maybe I didn't.
I should have done.
Yeah, you should have done because it's great.
I have not yet read this book, but it is on my list.
I liked his first book.
I didn't like it quite as much as another book by a different sounding
finalist that year, which was the one you really liked Liz.
What was that called?
About the dimension hopping space between worlds by Mackay and Johnson.
Yeah, that's the badger.
Yeah, I like that slightly better, but I thought him and his first book was good
and like really interesting, like probably more interesting than the spaces
between worlds, but like probably less well executed.
This one is even more ambitious in many ways and is just amazing.
I tore through it.
A lot of people said the framing device was really confusing.
And I found it fine, which makes me worried.
I missed something, but like is I guess is on the confusing side, but like I've
it, you know, I just went with it and eventually it turned out that things
were happening and you found out what they were.
But yeah, but I mean, as someone who primarily reads for vibes,
the vibes are strong with this book and I very much enjoyed the vibes.
It's about two people on a road trip.
Plot summarised.
Because Liz is laughing.
I mean, technically correct, but pretty useless.
My aim with all my plot summaries is episode 100.
So I can now finally reveal this.
My aim with all my plot summaries is to give technically correct, but utterly
useless plot summaries of everything I encounter.
Oh, are we, um, is that the first time we've ever all three three of us picked
books because that is weird.
I don't know if it's the first, I can't be the first, surely not.
Hang on to the list.
To the list.
We have a list of picks now so that we don't repeat ourselves too much.
Thank you, John.
No, it isn't.
We did it on episode 47 where I picked the psychopath club by Sandra Bond.
Alison picked Sibilant Frickative by Adam Roberts and Liz picked The Witness
for the Dead by Catherine Addison.
Yeah, I've just finished The Grief of Stones, which is the sequel to The
Dead, The Witness for the Dead.
And then we did it again on episode 50 where I picked Leviathan Falls.
You picked the actual star and Liz picked Elder Ace.
It is definitely true that I am the least likely to pick a book, which makes
me slightly, uh, feel slightly weird, but a lot of movies.
Yeah, I have also got Leviathan wakes out of the library.
So you see 2024 might be the year where I fully engage with the expanse and its
books. I will say Leviathan wakes his following, but push through because
episode books two and three are better.
Certainly I'm.
We returned to the expanse when we ran out of For All Mankind to Watch because
we're now on the drip feed of one episode a week for For All Mankind, which is not
enough. So the expanse kind of gives me a a a science fiction television vibe.
This is quite good.
Thank you, Erwin, for writing in.
Did we get any other letters?
We got some toots from Raj.
So Raj wrote us two toots.
Firstly, he put up the Liz bat signal.
He wants to know, can he nominate the whole of ghost season five for best
dramatic presentation long form?
It's no longer than Oppenheimer.
Yes, I should think so because it's television series.
They often go into best presentation.
I'm not Liz. I am obviously not an expert.
Hang on, breaking news.
I mean, I don't see why not.
But yes, and I think ghosts was one of the things in people happy mentioning it in
the giant Hugo spreadsheets of doom.
Yes, I need to watch it.
I haven't watched it yet.
I've only watched one and a half seasons of it.
So I think we probably just finished Lower Decks because we kind of have a comedy
slot in our television rotation.
Fair enough for enough.
And then he also says that we need to make room for him on our soapbox because he
also doesn't like it when there's a when novels have the subtitle a novel.
So, yep, you are welcome to stand on this soapbox.
Raj, anytime.
Just to be clear, I believe that is John's soapbox.
I mean, it's a large soapbox and I welcome all comers.
I'd like, yeah, but I'm not sure I've owned the soapbox with you this time.
I think that was your soapbox and my soapbox is the TikTok made me read it.
Yes.
Which today's prime example was the Virgin Suicides TikTok made me read it.
Apparently I was in and I might well have told this story on the podcast already.
I apologize.
It was a long time ago, but when I was in, I was in Maryland over a part of March
and I went to a shopping mall to do some shopping and I went into a bookshop and
they had a shelf which was labeled TikTok made me read it.
So it is not just the online booksellers that are employing this strategy.
Oh, no, it's not.
So I don't know if you guys saw the Goodreads choice awards where they have
invented the category of romanticcy.
Nice, which I think is explicitly designed to be books.
I just want to read.
Goodreads is I've been having trouble with Goodreads all through this podcast
and this will not surprise you, the Goodreads servers are overloaded on the 1st of January.
Isn't all fantasy basically romance because it's all about falling in love with a different world?
No.
This.
Oh, OK, fair enough.
Goodreads is currently recommending that I read the book called Dungeon Master's Guide,
Dungeons and Dragons, 5th Edition.
And there's no button to say on no account do I want to read that.
Thanks, Goodreads.
Do you know what Goodreads thinks I should read?
No, tell me.
It thinks I should read China,
Mayeville's Introduction to the Communist Manifesto.
Do it, do it.
Oh, God, that does sound good though.
I mean, yeah.
That does sound good.
You should do it and then pick it on the pod and we can talk about communism for an hour.
I feel like I've learned a lot, yeah.
Yeah.
No, I've got to I'm reading 2023 books for nomination purposes for the next month.
So yeah, so tell us what we should be reading.
All these worlds reviews and essays by Neil Harrison.
Oh, yeah.
So I'm already on my list.
I think I mean, I think this is a whole future episode, right?
Should I be reading some things before I start?
Basically, what should I be reading the next couple of weeks?
Hmm.
All these worlds reviews and essays by Neil Harrison.
Is that helpful?
I've read about half of it, actually.
Wait.
I'm looking for possibilities.
You could try titanium mar by Nick Harkaway as picked by me on the podcast.
Oh, I know.
Hopeland by Ian McDonald's is on my list.
Yeah.
That's on my list as well.
Well, it's on my list.
The Saint of Bright Doors is on my list.
I've read that.
I don't know why I didn't pick it.
I do know why I didn't pick it.
I don't think I'll clever enough.
All right.
I did try to review of it on Goodreads.
You should read Walking Practice by Dulce Minne as picked by me on a previous
episode.
I think there's a theme here.
Yeah, no.
It's almost like Liz has been picking the books that she thinks people should read.
Yeah.
Crazy.
It will never catch on.
I'll come up with some more later.
But that's a start.
Oh, have we got any more letters, John?
No.
So we finished the letter column for today.
Do we have any other content for this episode?
Because I've got things to do today like play board games and drink.
I mean, you've already started one of those.
That's true.
That is true.
You can multitask.
You can podcast and drink.
I mean, it's possible you can also podcast.
You probably could have podcasted in the gaps between turns and terraforming
Mars, probably.
Oh, God, that would be quite funny.
That was the ultimate podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me.
And also happy new year to all our listeners, especially those who stuck
with us for 100 episodes.
Yes.
Thank you to anyone.
Yes. If you've listened to every episode, write in and I will buy you a
pint.
Read all the names out next time if it's not too many.
Well, the first one to write in, I'll send a copy of all these worlds,
reviews and essays by Neil Harrison.
Really?
That'll be Chris Garcia, you know.
How are you?
And international shipping.
Oh, the second one to write in.
Well, I hand carried a copy of all these worlds reviews and essays by Neil
Harrison to the Bay Area.
So possibly we can facilitate some kind of loan to Chris.
Oh, maybe, maybe, maybe.
Yes, but thank you to everyone who has stuck with us.
We enjoyed doing the podcast.
We hope you enjoy listening to it.
We do.
And it is a lot more enjoyable because you write in and tell us when you
agree, when you disagree, when we're completely wrong, etc.
So please keep doing that for 2024, especially if John's wrong.
Yeah, no, I asked somebody at the party last night whether they listened
to the first thought and they were like, it's not in my rotation,
which I thought was a nice way of saying that's dull.
That is a very diplomatic way of saying now.
All right, shall we stop recording?
Yeah, yeah, we can do that.
Okay, okay.
I have played.
I did play many board games.
Oh, which ones?
So we played, we finished off our advent calendar.
Oh, yeah, Marianne had that.
The exit one.
Yeah, I really like them.
They're great.
So I'm like, that might be enough future.
Played a lot of herd mentality, which is a popular choice around the holidays.
It's a very popular party game, yes.
Yes, it's very good.
I like it a lot.
And what else do we play?
Played to Kaido, played Paleo, played legendary, played Monica's, played Scout.
And played final goal.
Okay, apparently we played Bannanza quite a lot, which is a classic, I understand.
Yep, it is.
Uve Wrzenberg.
Yeah, and we played three player Bannanza and it was kind of pretty good.
And I was getting to the end of the three player Bannanza and I was like, oh, I probably am getting, you know, we played about three or four games and I was like, okay, I probably had enough of this there.
And then, and then we played it with four players and at that point, I went, oh, this is the,
this is how it works.
And then Jonathan, Jonathan hated it.
So, you know, that's the problem with having a single gaming group is that you find that people go, oh, this doesn't work for me because it's much, it's much crunchier with four.
You're putting a very difficult positions all the time, which I really like.
And then we played Pandemic Iberia, Iberia, which was one of the games we got from Emily and Andrew, shout out to Emily and Andrew if they are listening, but they gave me a whole sack of games.
In a kind of decluttering Santa.
It's the old adage and listeners.
This is words to live by.
The easiest way to declutter is to give it to Alison.
Yeah.
Because and Alison has employed the reverse tactic with me.
The easiest way to declutter is to give it to John.
Yeah.
Has also worked.
Yep. Yep. I mean, I guess more generally what's old and stale to you is new and exciting to other people.
So it can be it can be very good.
I got three games from Emily and Andrew.
I was very restrained.
Oh, yeah.
Which ones did you get Scotland Yard, Kalico and Kitchen Rush?
Yeah.
So so we have about, I don't know, six or seven games from Emily and Andrew and we've played Pandemic Iberia, which obviously will keep and carry on playing and Mary Ann and I have played the mind, but we want to play it with all four of us.
So that's definitely one of the things we're going to do today.
We're going to read each other's minds for you as day.
Marianne and I lost the mind catastrophically.
So, you know, and then I've played shot and Tottenham with both Stephen and with Marianne.
Anyway, this is games over Christmas.
This which is off topic for the podcast probably.
So, yeah, who knows?
Well, if we're short, John can use this filler.
Um, how many board games did you get from Emily and Andrew Liz?
I got zero board games from Emily and Andrew.
Oh, boo.
New conspiracy theory.
Do Emily and Andrew hate Liz more on this as it unfolds.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod in CompeTech.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.
[BLANK_AUDIO]