Liz, do you fancy a quick game of our comp
horror before Alison's ready to?
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty and we are coming to you two weeks after Easter at
which we had our first live show which had many comments in the chat as some of our
favorite podcast posts say. How did you feel that the live recording went?
I thought it was full of drivel and distractions and people not really keeping on topic and
it went on far too long and then when I listened to the editor it sounded more or less alright
so I think that's what we're aiming for right?
Yeah and Liz was good.
Yeah I think we've peaked and it's just going to be downhill from now on but maybe we can
hope for a very slow decline over some time.
So EasterCon had a variety of virtual components this year owing to gestures out of window.
How did we think the Zoom bit session?
I think they put a load of work into it. I think Keith Smith and his team essentially
stepped up to the plate and worked out how they would do it and make it work well and
it did work well.
It seemed to run very smoothly. I think it was obviously a very different sort of experience
for the people presenting especially poor Phil who's being sick with the plague and
sort of came off his deathbed in order to do his presentation for 2022 but I think the
actual mechanical running of it in many ways worked better than our regular bid session
which I think is something that parliaments around the world are finding as well that it
turns out that when you stop people cat calling and interrupting and generally acting like
lunes you get a better democratic outcome.
I think in some cases it was quite hard to do the questions by text because if you're
doing them live in the room people can get a lot of context from you and the way you say
it and I think there were some questions that maybe got misunderstood or we did not get
quite the answer that the the questioner was looking for but other than that it was pretty
good. It was a good start. It meant I could go to the bid session which otherwise I would
not have been doing so that was quite nice.
Did you vote for An Easter Kong?
I did vote for An Easter Kong. Yeah I mean essentially it's back to Birmingham again.
I don't mind Birmingham Hilton. It's a perfectly reasonable place for An Easter Kong. We didn't
go this year so let's go next year.
For those who don't know the 2021 Easter Kong will be confusion in 2021. It will be held
at the Birmingham Hilton Metropolitan. The guests have won as far as we remember were
Don Appnite, Nick Vincent and Dave Lally but the list is not on the website yet so we
apologize sincerely if we have forgotten one.
I am excited about confusion but one thing I do want to touch on is that my understanding
is that the Birmingham Hilton Metropolitan Metropolitan was chosen as the location before
the COVID-19 situation arose. It's interesting that this I think was the first time we would
have gone back to a hotel in back-to-back years for a long time. I know I think it's
happened in the Dimondistant past but what do you think about having Easter Kong in the
same place two years in a row?
I think it's becoming increasingly difficult to find hotels. The other thing that was announced
at Easter was that Phil Dyson is kind of a bid presumptive for 2022 but didn't want
to bid because he hasn't nailed a hotel down yet and I think some of the sites that we
might have used in the past are not acceptable to us now. Some of them are out of our price
range now. The Easter Kong becomes more demanding in what it needs every year.
But Easter Kong is kind of stable in size. You have to actually work to prevent it from
growing but it's around about a thousand which is quite a difficult size to put into
hotels in the UK. They just aren't that many sites and I think Liz said, 'Oh, the Hilton
Birmingham Metropolitan Metropolitan Metropolitan', 'is a perfectly good site'. In fact, it was
quite a lot better than that last time we went. It really did have, apart from being on
a motorway junction, pretty well everything you would want an Easter Kong site to have,
like local shops and restaurants and beer and good cheap food and plenty of function
space and plenty of bedrooms to the extent that they don't have to use an overflow. Everyone
always gets into the hotel and I think that's quite compelling. I can see that having negotiated
it once, I can see that Vanessa would want to go back. The other thing I wanted to say
about Confusion 2021 is that the other thing I want to talk about Confusion 2021 is that
although Vanessa is chairing again, it's otherwise a different committee. I think a couple of
the same people working on the convention but the overall committee has new people on
it and in particular I don't think it's got its program head in place yet. It's a different
committee to the committee that would go to give us the East Kong this year.
Yeah, you're right. I'm probably a little bit unfair to the Hilton. It was noticeably
better last time we went than the time before because a lot more shops and restaurants and
everything have grown up around that development. So it's less kind of in the middle of nowhere
and there's nowhere else to go and eat and more in the middle of other things and I think
that made the hotel more competitive about feeding us because we actually have other
options. They're not the only game in town. It also has extremely good transportation
links as well. Yes, it does and I think one of the things I remember about the first time
we went was that the food situation was not really very good and the most recent time
we went it was a lot better. So I agree with you that the growth of the complex nearby
it's called a Nando's and a pizza express another chain restaurant. So it's nothing
particularly to write home about but it just gives you a lot more option than you had before.
It also has one of the best restaurants in the Midlands. So it actually as well as having
its cheap restaurants it's also got a couple of really high-end restaurants. So it was
filling that niche for people who wanted to go do a bit of fine dining as well. Excellent
and it does have very very good function space. In fact it's got more function space than
a Easter con can use which is unusual for a hotel. The other thing that had changed in
between our two more recent visits is that they'd had the furries I think a couple of
times and I think the furries are more or less exactly like the Easter con except with
more fur. And so they really knew how to serve a crowd that was like that.
Yeah I think as hotels get used to conventions they get more and more keen to have conventions
because I think conventions are usually relatively well behaved group of people who will spend
in orders amounts of food and drink while being very polite and quiet. I think that
was clear in the difference between the Hilton the two times we went. And I think it stands
as stark contrast to the Radisson Ed Wardian which was one of the common East con hotels
of yesterday because they got progressively worse and always treated the convention attendees
as a lower class of hotel guests than the non-convention attendees which I think left
a very poor taste in the mouth and led to an awful lot of dissatisfaction with that as
a venue. So I think that the Hilton Metropolitan does a much better job from that perspective
too. I'm happy we're going back. I really like that hotel. I find it very easy to get
to because it's a direct train from Southampton. There are lots of hotels around if you don't
want to stay in the con hotel but there's plenty of room in the con hotel if you do.
And it's generally a very good location. So I am excited to go in 2021.
I just want to go to an Easter con anywhere anytime ever again. Oh sorry. Not Easter?
I mean one of the things that surprised me about the bid session was there was a question
about what would happen if COVID-19 meant that there were still travel restrictions
in place at Easter next year. And the con con said that they hadn't really thought about
that and hadn't put any plans in place. What do you think about that? Do you think that's
sensible? I was appalled by how little planning they did this year. I mean obviously Cavendish
Councilor Easter con is terrible but I feel that they could have done a lot more in the
four weeks or five weeks between when they cancelled and the original dates to make sure
that virtual events were happening and were encouraged even if they hadn't done all the
work of organising them themselves. What they actually did was sent out a thing saying please
don't organise any events because we're going to let you know which was the exact opposite
of what I think they should have done. I understand that if it'd be my Easter con being cancelled
I might have been too busy crying into my beer to think about what alternatives we could
have but it would have been quite straightforward to have set up social spaces to have set a
system in place so that panels could have happened. To say we're going to have some
chats about some topics you might be interested in that you could sign up to be on a panel
on or something like that and they could have done all of that and they didn't do any of
it and that was for this year. So I was very keen to say Easter cons or all conventions
in the future should have some planning arrangements for this sort of thing and should be planning
to do virtual things so that they could switch if they need to and I was surprised that they
didn't. I feel that they missed an opportunity. I feel that although as they said doing it
properly can be quite expensive you can do it improperly with not a lot of work as we've all
discovered in the last six weeks. I think I'm not surprised that they didn't do anything because
I think that it was very clearly a big shock to everyone that this developed as quickly as it did
like intellectually I knew it was going to but sort of emotionally I think it really hit me that like
this is the first Easter for a very long time that I've not gotten to an Easter con so that was a bit
of a shock to the system and so I think I can understand why they might not but they would
arrange anything this time round and I appreciate that's very hard thing and I appreciate that
that could have been very fought. What I am sort of hoping is that if there are still travel restrictions
next year we don't end up in a situation where again we have no officially to come provision because
I don't want to end up in a situation where this kind of thing happens again with no
official panels or official social spaces or anything like that. I think I can understand
and sympathize with what happened this year. I think if you are planning to do Easter con next
year it is just prudent to assume that you are not going to know until close to time how it's
going to work. I think it's just prudent to plan for if you have to do a remote Easter con or if you
want to even include some remote options because clearly the last thing that's going to come back
is large gatherings of people and the last thing that's going to come back is like long-distance
travel. So you might be in the position where we can have a full Easter con. You might be in the
position where you have a reduced Easter con or you might be in the position where you have no
Easter con and I think it's at this point you just have to have contingency plans for those
and if you don't then you're going to have another year of planning to run a great convention
and then being extremely disappointed if you can't do that. I think there is a fourth option which is
that they may have a lot of members who even if travel is allowed and the Easter con is allowed
have decided for themselves that it's not safe to do so and I think the notion that we might
disenfranchise our oldest and in poorest health members not because they can't physically get to
the convention but that we don't think that they don't think it's safe for them to do so and that
even with a year's warning nobody's doing anything about that and when they were asked the question
we're kind of like well we've got no plans to do anything about that. I feel like there's a lot
more that could be done here. I agree and I think it will be really interesting to see what does
happen next year because obviously I think all three of us are very much hoping that Easter
Cop will happen and everything will be normal and there will be none of this that needs to be worried
about that I am keenly aware that me hoping that happens and it's actually happening are two very
different things. I think the other interesting point here is that especially with WorldCom but
with Easter con as well I think the idea of having panels one can access virtually from the
perspective of being able to buy a supporting membership and do that is something that has been
being talked about more and more in recent years and I am wondering whether this will be a shove
towards trying to start making that happen and I am hoping that this is the shove that starts making
that happen because I often find myself in situations at Easter con where I end up missing a panel
that I would love to go back and see a recording of or I end up being on a panel where I would love
to watch it back because I think there were some really interesting points made and I am not
able to take notes as thoroughly as I would like to while talking so I think it would be really
nice if we could develop that capability and this seems like a good almost like a good excuse to
try and do that. Do you two think that this will be an impetus towards that? Do you think I am being
overly optimistic? I think you are right I think that everyone would like more things to be streamed
live broadcast recorded for later consumption and this could be got an opportunity because
what the benefit here is that you could plan your convention panels so they can either happen
live at the Easter con with a streaming broadcast or they can happen live from people's houses with
a streaming broadcast and then in either situation you are already prepared. I think the best way to
do this is to have some of the panels planned that way so rather than saying we're going to try
and recreate the 420 items at an Easter con or whatever we've got a lot which includes all sorts
of items which nobody in their right minds will put on the internet along with all sorts of things
where actually the the audience for them is is very small. I think the latter sort are fine
you know you may only get 10 people tuning in but those people really care and they're all over
the world so I think there is something there about you could do certain sorts of things better
in small groups including an internet presence and if you just said well we won't be doing all of
it but we're going to focus on a cut say half a dozen really high profile events that we'll do
online and a few small and very specialist events that you that will do online and the rest of the
stuff will happen if it happens and not if it doesn't. I think that's very true and actually I spent
two days this week doing two full day training calls which all took place on zoom and it was
incredibly tiring and I would never voluntarily do that for an Easter con so you don't need to stream
420 items you need to stream 20. Maximum yeah because I think if I was going to do that I would
be streaming the big guest of honor panels and talks because oftentimes what happens is I'm torn
between an interesting little niche item and the interview with John Scalzi and if you stream the
interview with John Scalzi John Scalzi is already going to be on his best behavior because he is in
that kind of work mode as a guest of honor anyway and it means I can go to a small little niche panel
that I otherwise wouldn't have been able to attend so I do think there is an argument there that you
can get around that by only streaming the big panels where you're already hedging your bets a bit.
The other thing I will say is that I think that at the moment we have panels that are more intimate
because we know they're not being recorded and I think if you start recording panels you will get
a slight shift in what people are willing to say if they know they're being recorded which I think
would change the complexion of the panel slightly. It is interesting to note I think I saw one of the
people who worked on Conzieland saying that prior to the announcement they were going virtual
only five people who had filled out the program survey could set that they did not want to be
recorded so I think most people appearing on panels are willing to be recorded I think as long
as they know it's going to happen in advance and can tailor their presence on that panel
with that knowledge. I do think in some ways you'd lose a lot if you streamed the entire program but I
wouldn't necessarily think that would be necessary although I will say if it was only available to
supporting and attending members I think I wonder to what extent I would be worried about guarding
my speech because if I know that anyone of the Eastcon can watch my speech back that's not much
more public than anyone of the Eastcon being able to come into my panel but I don't know.
Anybody at the Eastcon who has recorded technology can then pass it on. In practice everyone can
record all the time anyway you know we've we've not really people are very polite about asking if
they can record panels but anyone with a phone can record a panel so we don't really we've not
really been able to have the sort of freedom to have the late night drunken panels that we that
were once a feature of conventions that's not necessarily a bad thing but I do miss them sometimes.
Well you do still get a couple but I must admit I always prefer going to parties than panels but
I want to have a drunken laugh. So the last time we were at the Birmingham Hilton I went to a late
night panel on I think administering the Hugo Awards which sounded like an incredibly dry panel but
was actually a really great one so sometimes the unexpected panels are the surprisingly great
slightly all the audience are drinking late night panels. That's a good point and certain
panel concepts like vote with your ass would work very well as a drunken late night thing
although you'd have to be quite careful not for it to become a contact sport I think.
You may have to explain vote with your ass John. You have a room in which there is either
sort of a one-dimensional line or a circle of chairs and the moderator of the panel will pose
questions to the audience and the audience will divide themselves in the room according to their
opinion on that question so oftentimes it'll be like which is better the 10th or 11th doctor
and everyone who thinks the 10th doctor is best stands on the left and then everyone who thinks
the 11th doctor is best stands on the right. Where do you put the people who can't remember
which is which? It's a good panel item for a light-hearted kind of group argument format
which can be very fun especially if everyone has had a drink so as a late night panel idea it could
work quite well. The people who think the fourth doctor was best just rattles Emma frames.
Another bid that was mooted at the bid session was the 2022 bid led by Phil Dyson who has
Covid-19 at the point he was presenting the bid which is truly heroic. He still did a pretty good job
I have to say. He did an excellent job. I think for somebody who was plague ridden he really did
step up to the plate and give a good bid. I think he probably did better than I would do remotely
without the plague so. Smash it out of the park. I've got a lot of time for Phil. I think he's an
excellent com runner and I think his bid was very well put together. There was a kind of
take the temperature of the room vote for whether a lot of people thought what he had announced was
fair but he did not put his bid forward for a natural confirmation vote because they do not
yet have a venue. They are still in discussion with a few different places as to where they're
going to end up. I think they heavily hinted that they were trying to end up in the north of England
somewhere. Are you excited about the 2022 East College and what you heard at the bid session?
It's actually much easier to bid at East Decon if you're not doing the whole package.
So if you don't have your whole committee together, if you don't have a site to announce,
if you don't have anything for people to really say, well, actually we hate some of this idea.
So obviously it was, it's very positive but that's because it's not a complete bid yet.
I'm still very excited about the idea of going to an Eastergatan and meeting my friends. You have
no idea. I'm very excited about the idea of going to the pub. I'm actually quite excited about
the idea of going to the shops, you know, not to buy essential items but just to kind of
hang around an apple store for an afternoon. You know, I might like... What excites me as
really gone downhill at this point? You heard it here first folks. And to like stop at those
pretzel stands where they give you a bit of pretzel to taste with germs no doubt.
All of these things, I'm just very excited by anything else that's sitting in rooms.
There's how excited are you by bits of pretzel and going to apple stores?
There's a knot to things which are really high on my list to be honest. I'm quite excited by the
idea of having an Eastergatan in 2022. I think Phil's going to do a great job and I look forward
to seeing the rest of Phil's team and his guests and also location. I think it's also worth noting that
we really don't know what the hotel market is going to look like in 2022 and what will be available
and it might completely have changed. There might be far fewer in-person gatherings and
prices could change and hotel chains could completely evolve. So it's going to be a fun year for Phil
sorting that one out. I think we may have a significantly smaller Eastergatan or a significantly
bigger one. I think one of the things we do know is that it takes a lot for hotels to actually close.
They just they kind of go down market and shabbier and shabbier and shabbier when times are hard
until they end up as the Adelphi and it seems likely that when we do decide we want to get together
again we will find somewhere we can do that. I think going a bit down market and shabbies really
are on target set of hotels. Okay so one of the reasons that Eastercons are hard at the moment
is that shabby hotels tend to be quite bad for access and we have increasingly complex access
needs. That's I think a big part of the problem. I mean the Adelphi, I still love it but it is a
nightmare of stairs as well as being a nightmare of a hotel to work with. We had a stair problem at
the Majestic that I think that they've looked at again for 2022 and concluded is not ever going
to be soluble. I think that's a problem with a lot of the shabby sites that if you're shabby you
don't sort out these access problems and although we talk about fans liking slightly shabby spaces
as we've grown older we've kind of liked our creature comforts as well. So in fact we don't
really like shabby hotels any more than anybody else does. So what we're actually hoping for is
hotels with great access to become shabby. I think it will be interesting to see if some of the high
end conferences do go virtual whether there is scope to use the sorts of hotels that are just
completely out of our league at the moment that do exist. Yeah that's fair it will be interesting
to see how that happens I think. Over the weekend there were a plethora, a myriad, a very civil
smorgasbord of virtual activities arranged by a host of good people including our very own
Alison Scott. So what virtual pursuits did you go to? I think we mentioned a lot of them on the
podcast but what did you go to and what worked and what didn't. I didn't go to any of the program
but I did go to a party every single night so it was a lot like a release to come for me.
I did go to the bidding session but apart from that I didn't get to any program. I don't think
there was any program actually I think that that's the problem and I discovered that drinking a very
large amount of beer in the vicinity of my extremely expensive work computer is probably a terrible
mistake and I may need to some kind of beer ingestion system that doesn't involve leaving it
leaving open cans of beer on my desk in future. You need one of those hats with the two cans of
beers in the store. For example I'm not sure how that would go with the whole headphones and
microphone and pop filter. Now this is a new market headphones with built-in beer holders.
Yes we have invented a thing well we have the idea for an invention we will we will
patent it and octa thought what we forever remembered as the inventor of the podcaster beer
romantic 3000. I also went to parties I don't think I went to as many parties as you.
Did you go to the dead dog? I didn't find out about the dead dog until afterwards.
I did go to the dead dog because I did find out about it but one of the things I established when I
set my party up was that you have to be quite assiduous in telling people that events are on
in Facebook. I got to the point where I was worried that Facebook were going to cussend the police
round because every time I went into my Facebook event for my party it flashed up increasingly
strident warnings saying you're not supposed to be gathering you should not be having events of
many people and there didn't seem to be a box to tick to say it's on zoom you idiots.
I kind of publicised my party very hard much more than I ever would a real party where essentially
you have to be chatting to me and then I give you party invitation but I kind of told everyone
repeatedly about it and including people who were not on on Facebook and I think other people who
ran parties rather relied on Facebook to show the party invite to their friends and Facebook's
terrible at that so I think a lot of people didn't know about it but there were parties every night
I think and some nights have more than one party. Yes I thoroughly enjoyed your room party or
sorry your zoom party. I started the party at night I had some beer that I had bought from the pub
across the bridge from me which I believe I was talking about at the live recording and then
I had some beer and then I had some more beer and then I had some gin and then I had some more gin
and a midnight oiled with pizza and a some pizza and I went to bed at 3am and then I woke up the
next morning with a stonking hangover and no hotel breakfast so it was almost exactly like a real
Saturday night at least con and I thoroughly enjoyed it it really took all of the sadness out
of my weekend it was absolutely fantastic so thank you very much for organising it it was great that's
very kind I that was what I was hoping for I was hoping that people would drink too much and stay
up too late and have hangovers there is a slight problem with zoom parties which is it turns out
that if you drink too much and stay up too late then gradually people from Australia and New Zealand
and indeed Thailand start to join your party and and these parties could theoretically just kind
of continue on in a never-ending cycle of debauchery through this method though I think eventually
zoom throws you out going you lotter a load of dirty stopouts ain't you got homes to go to
but then you could just start start the zoom again so it's not too bad so basically you're saying
that zoom is going to recreate was it the longest party anyone ever had that flies around in the
hittakers guide yes randomly attacking places for party supplies you're basically going to recreate
that I had a great time I was reminded of I think it was a few years ago John when you decided to
stay up all night drinking at an Easter con and then we had breakfast together the next morning
while you were extremely kind of passing from very drunk into slightly hungover and the hangover
was going to appear and I was like just woken up and having breakfast and I very I definitely
recreated that experience at Alison's party but it was fun because if it was a party actually at
an Easter con then I would not have been able to go was that that must be 2008 maybe no is it the
park in so it must be oh okay no I do remember uh well we we had breakfast with Shordon Maguire
who was the guest of order because she turned up in the bar and me and Alison and Claire and Jerry
and a couple of other people who I don't remember had been staying up drinking at about 6 a.m.
Shordon came down and asked please tell me that you have gone up early and you're not here
from the night before we said we got up early she said that's a lie isn't it we said yes
and then she saw it and we eventually had breakfast but that might not have been the same type
the problem with all of these stories is I was very drunk so my memories are hazy
the park in is a remarkable hotel because it's at Heathrow it is possible to get caffeinated beverages
made with actual coffee machines 24 hours a day without any difficulty at all so at that point
at about three in the morning where you go you know unless I have a double espresso I'm probably
going to need to go to bed soon you can have a double espresso and carry on it is pretty fantastic
was that the one you were thinking of it or was it a different one I think it was that one but I
think what happened is you had like three or four different separate breakfasts I think you had
that breakfast I like 6 a.m. I think then you went for a nap and then you got to have breakfast again
about 10 o'clock I mean I'm not saying I'm a hero but I'm heavily implying it I remember that
it is possibly the most fun I have ever had at Eastcott every time I've got to the stage in my life
that I every time I stay up all night drinking I think is this the last time I will ever stay
up all night drinking and it never is or it never has been so far way well that's that is a result
I think it and it was good because later on we were talking about it and you were right at about
2 a.m. UK time and by that time I was half a pizza and many beers down and it was very good to see you
I very hazel you remember that that happened and yes but it was it was it was properly it did
properly feel like at Eastcott it it was it was truly excellent in other news things that have
happened since last time we recorded one of us needs congratulating congratulations to Alison
Scott for being this year's Guff winner yes I'm very pleased and I am quite pleased that it wasn't
close that there that lots of people voted and lots of the voter for me and I do appreciate that
that is that is lovely I'd been a bit worried because I I ran because one of my nominators kind
of twisted my arm up the back and said you should really run in this race and that was
because I was worried that there wouldn't be candidates or and then they ended up being
sick so I was like and then there's a whole lot of complexity around this because given my
this is the first guff race since my youngest child turned 18 and given my
drothers I wouldn't have chosen to go to a worldcon in Australia and New Zealand I've chosen to go to a
national convention because worldcons are kind of more the same anywhere whereas if you go to a
national convention or a large regional you really get to meet fans in the area doing doing
fanish things but because of various personal crap that's going on in my life I wasn't sure I
would be able to run in a couple of years or three years or whatever so I am now committed to virtually
attending CODZYLEN which I'm very much looking forward to and I'm going to talk a little bit
about how I'm going to do that in a second but also I will make a real trip to Australia and
New Zealand hopefully next year I mean I'm not going to go until it feels like it's safe to go
so that might end up being I mean I hope it'll be next year but it might be 2022 you know but
I'll go when I can and I'm I'm really excited to have won and thank you everyone very much for
for voting for me and putting your faith in me as a fan fan delegate and it's particularly
sweet because I really don't think I was ever going to be able to afford to travel to without
the fanfums so I'm really very thrilled I am planning a virtual trip so what I'm going to do
is I was going to go for three weeks ending two weeks in Australia and a week in New Zealand plus
travel ending at the New Zealand Worldcon so I'd have had the Worldcon and then one rest day and
then flying home and so I'm going to take that exact period of time and if you are any part of
any Australian or New Zealand or somewhere who can reasonably visit it on the way as a stopover
fan group I would like to have a virtual meeting in your area and I'd also like to do
the virtual tourist attractions in in those areas in the period leading up to conceal and so I'm
hoping to meet with as many fan groups as possible and as many fans as possible and do as many of
the experiences virtually that I would actually have been able to do if I'd visit it so that's
that's kind of the plan. Excellent stuff. I'm going to go on to Australia and New Zealand time one of
those I I assume they are not all in the same time zone as it's an area about as big as Europe
or maybe even a bit bigger so I don't know but I will I will do I will be on their time zones as
well for three weeks which is kind of night shift. According to timeanddates.com there are eight
total time zones in Australia and New Zealand and it's one of them a half hour time zone.
Yes there's a half hour time zone. Yes Adelaide. So you can you can really go go off-piste and
set yourself you know 10 and a half hours away. There's a quarter hour time zone. There's a
quarter hour time zone Alison you must go there. On my tough trip I went to St John's in New
Foundland on my way to Toronto and that is a half hour time zone and I'm like very excited because
that's a cool thing to do. Mm-hmm. N.B. may not actually be cool maybe heavily dependent on
Nurtory but yes there is a part of Australia which is a quarter hour time zone and I don't know if
there is any fandom there but so there are eight time zones in Australia and New Zealand and my
challenge for my virtual trip is to visit all of them. I will have the worst case of jet lag.
I think I'll go to game for the worst case of jet lag ever without leaving your own home.
Excellent. I'm not sure there are eight time zones I think they span eight hours technically.
Ah maybe. But we might be too fine to time zone Nurtory now. Australians and New Zealanders please
send us letters of comment about why we are wrong about your time zones. So we said those two
Alice and Dot's got no. I confidently predict that somewhere in a very small
listenership there will be someone who is nerdy at the about time zones then we can believe possible
and they will be in touch. Excellent. Please. For people who have not looked at the voting statistics
there were six candidates for Guff one of the candidates dropped out and the other five were
comprised of individuals and couples so it's like six groups of people I suppose rather than six
individuals but Alice in one with over 50% of the first preference votes and when will you
write your trip report Alison? Well I'm going to write a virtual trip report this year but I'll
do a real one as well. You're not going to get my trip report for a while are you? I'll have to think
of a more of another new format to do it in. Maybe it'll be the first zoom zoom. No it'll be the
second zoom trip before I did. Me and Anna Raftree have been doing zoom videos in order to do Anna's
TAF report so Anna went to Mid-American 2 in 2016 which was in Kansas City and she was the TAF
winner and so I interviewed Anna on Friday as we record that was two days ago talking about the
first leg of her trip and her reasons for running for TAF and how she found the experience of running
I think that went really well. We had about 20 listeners live and the video audio and transcript
thereof will be made available for a small donation to the fan funds when we've done
the whole trip in conversational form. I wanted to explore what the format of a trip report could be
because obviously the original trip reports came out of Van Zeen Van Dung in the early to mid-50s
as the fan funds have gone on for longer and longer they have become less and less tied
specifically to fanzing fandom and have become a much broader thing that reflects a lot more corners
of our fandom which I think is really good but one of the flip sides of that is that not everyone
who wins necessarily has the skills to write edit and produce a 80 to 100 page document
so I think some people are you know much more conversational or have different skill sets
and so I wanted to do something with Anna because I thought she would be very good in a kind of
more conversational video audio medium and I think it went really well I hope it went really well
I found it interesting but I was obviously interviewer and Liz could not attend because we held it in
the evening which was about three in the morning for Liz but Alison very hopefully let us host it on
her zoom and sort of did introductions and then we had a bit of a party afterwards so that was also
very I think I am learning that when you're doing something like this formerly using zoom or another
video conferencing solution it's extremely helpful to have one person whose job is only
managing people in the room and letting them know what's going on and telling them how to do
things and and all of that stuff because if you're trying to do that plus also run the interview
if you're me you'll get distracted all of the time and because I don't have webinar mode because
it's an extra 40 quid a month I'm we're doing this thing where whenever anyone turns up we have to
we have to quickly turn their video off so that it doesn't appear on the eventual recording but
hopefully that will all come out in John's beautiful edit um I think your fine video editing is much
more complicated than podcast editing maybe the videos I think will probably be less highly
edited than the audio so my my plan with the videos is basically just to cut out moments where
it was someone else's camera coming up because they were joined and we hadn't managed to blank
them out yet with the audio I will go through and kind of cut out the ums and errs and that will be
available as a kind of audio book and then I will do transcripts of that on top um which Claire
Breiley is assisting with in her capacity as person who does lots of work for very little thanks
which is a thing that she is very good at and I try and make sure that I say her name and give
her thanks wherever possible in order to address that balance I think it is good for uh the fan
funds to move with the times a bit I think it is good not to exclude them from being fan fund
candidates if their attitude is not for producing a giant rich and report but for doing something
in audio form or video form or photography or whatever medium they would like to report it
basically and I think you've got everything covered you're going to do it by video and audio and
unfortunately not everyone will be able to watch live but there will be recordings and there will
be transcripts so you've got all the bases covered yeah we are I think also going to try to do it
different times to make sure that different recordings can have people from different time zones but
I think I suspect most of them will be at times that US people can turn up because obviously
TAF is most interesting to Europeans and people in North America and so obviously tailoring the
time zones to the evening in Europe means that you hit that better but I think we'll try to at least
one that is suitable for people who are in times zones ahead of London in order to make sure that
they can have at least one experience of coming along just for you Liz and also for other people
who live in far off places yeah I realize I have brought this upon myself by moving to a time zone
which is either six or seven hours ahead of the UK but yeah you're not the first people to have to
grapple with the problems of time zones virtual events and you will not be the last we will not
and I suspect we will come on to discussing that a bit more when we touch upon Conzeland in the
next episode do either of you have anything else you'd like to say about the fan funds I think this
is probably a good point for you to mention your trip report your imminent trip report John so
I have written a trip report it is 90 pages long and somewhere in the region of 25 000 words
and it is very almost finished it only needs two more pieces of art and one of them is being
constructed by a Alison Scott of Wartham stone so if Alison if you could sort of get your finger
out a little bit and I can get my trigger while okay so there's a slight catch which is that
this weekend a lot of the time that I might have done that has been doing things like
helping with that as TAF thing and recording octa thought and in fact I've had I've had four
kind of very work like zoom events where I've been responsible for managing the
structure of the event this weekend which seems like more than you should have to have in
I feel like I've discovered a new skill that's apparently a paying job skill in this new world
except that I don't really want to do it for pay because I was very happy selling crap on the
internet so you know anyway so yes so I'm sorry I will get my finger out but possibly still not
this weekend so you know soon soon soon soon real soon now um as you've missed the east
content line you don't really need to get a chat before comes elan do you?
My new plan is probably to do it next year because next year will be the 10th anniversary and
that seems like if I'm going to do it late I might as well do it properly late um but Anna
does report so for those who don't know who aren't as red up on the various TAN funds as I am having
been an administrator there are bounties available for submitting trip reports there is a bounty from
a american organization and there is a bounty from a Canadian organization and when I have
remembered their names I will put links in the show notes the Canadian one has a five year deadline
and the American one has no deadline so I will get the American one which is five hundred dollars
and there will be five hundred dollars for TAF the benefit of doing Anna's this year is that as
long as we get it finished by the end of the year she will come under the deadline for the Canadian
bounty as well so that will be a thousand dollars I believe for TAF. Is that five years from the date
of trip or five years from winning the fund this this seems more relevant than it might be?
It would be as long as we do it by the end of 2020 they are the same that they both of those
will be true I actually don't know I assume it's from the date of the trip yeah I'm just slightly
worried about this for my guff thing though projects that are left do fester so I kind of think I'm
going to have to do it within a year of actually making the trip or all of those things that you
remember I will have forgotten though I am when I do the proper trip I am going to take a lot of
recording devices with me I'm going to try and make notes and scribble things onto Facebook and so
on every single day otherwise yeah you know what it's like the words in my trip report were mostly
committed to foundsings within the month after I came back and it is only the kind of written and
nicely formatted trip report those day good ages I wrote all of the words as I was going along
and editing it turns out is is effort I was trying to ask Claire to do it Claire did a proofread
run on mine which took me about three days to go through because it was 500 comments on 25,000
words okay I could beat that I did a poster I did a poster for Dublin it was a big post-scour
on the wall Caroline gave me the words I did the layout I just happened to give it to Claire to
proofread at a party and I think there were 500 comments on that and it was one poster Claire is
a proofreading machine if you ever need a healthy proofread Claire is a good person to proofread
it I actually think she should probably at some point start charging for her services because she's
very good and also some of the comments may be laugh and I'm a bit sad no one else will ever get
to read them you could definitely put an appendix to your trip report that is the funniest bits out
of the proofread there are footnotes in my trip report which are the thing that Claire said about
that thing and I've just put that in a footnote how are we all feeling about staying sane in the
apocalypse I have to say I'm feeling several degrees less sane than I was a couple of weeks
ago if this were Call of Cthulhu or Arkham Horror or something my insanity would be rising or my sanity
would be dropping precipitously so actually that's funny you say that because one of the ways me and
Liz have been staying sane in the apocalypse is playing Arkham Horror over a tape drop simulator
sort of simulating our lapsing sanity in order to prevent it happening in real life
but I must admit I do I can feel my sanity slipping slightly I think I am getting less productive
and slightly more frustrated to be indoors I bought a new portable telephone oh what's portable
telephone is it it is an iPhone SE so it's exactly like my old iPhone SE except bigger and much flash
ear and very much faster and I'm not quite used to it yet because it feels very big and flashy and
and it's too slightly too big for my hands which is the reason why I didn't have a phone in that
form factor before phones have got too big for me I might have to go back to one of those little
Nokia things and then I realized that it was stupid buying a phone because I'm not going out
anywhere or seeing anyone or doing any of the sorts of things for which it's quite handy to have a
phone on you I ride the review finding that you are turning to retail therapy to stay safe because
I am definitely I'm spending less money because I'm obviously trapped in my house and I'm definitely
buying more stuff than I was well I've said two things I've said first of all that my mother always
told me to save for a rainy day and this day seems to be pretty rainy as days go so my habit of buying
nothing in my life has turned into a buy everything in my life so for example during this podcast I
have bought a clamp on microphone stand for a blue snowball microphone from eBay so that next
time we speak I will actually be able to have the snowball right in front of my face Liz how are
you staying sane and what's the what's the COVID-19 situation like in Thailand are you
allowed out or are you under curfew what are the what are the restrictions you're under?
I can't go out between 10 p.m. and 4am which is fine because all the restaurants are published
at any way so you're not going out drinking you also can't currently buy alcohol but fortunately
I laid in a stockpile of gin I'm doing okay it turns out I'm quite well suited to sitting in the
house all day and not talking to anyone but I have just got a very exciting message saying that
people are coming around to deliver cookies to me this is not a joke so I will have to leave the
podcast shortly in order to go and collect cookies is that okay that is okay we can use that as our
impetus to ramp up so from the three of us thank you very much for listening to the
Auto Thought podcast and it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me
the music used in this episode was Pam Faire for Space by Kevin MacLeod at Incompetech.com
licensed under a Creative Commons BY 3.0 license
Excellent! While we will speak to you soon Liz I hope the cookies are lovely please send me a
picture of them so I can put it in the show notes