I should say this is that we've done Oxford Live before, but when we've done Oxford Live
before, you've all been on Zoom. How many of you have been to one of our Zoom Oxford
Live? Cheers, yeah. Cheer if you haven't. But we've not actually... I was under the impression
that I was going to have to plug into a soundboard. You were in the backboard. So I brought with
me a fist full of dongles. And now I have nowhere to plug into anything. Yes. Hello everyone
and welcome to the very 45th episode of Octa Thor. Yay! I'm John Coxon. I'm Alison Scott.
I am definitely not Liz Batty. Who are you? And why are you not Liz Batty? I am a secret
intruder who is invited to this podcast because we are here at Novocan and I am Margarit Smith,
wearer of many hats and doer of too many things. And we shall be talking about all the podcast.
And why is Liz Batty not here? Because she is rubbish. So did you go to Google and do
the how long does it take to get from Bangkok to Buxton by public transport? The thing is
the main problem is the train from Stockport to Buxton. I could get to Stockport with that
last leg for a while. But no, Liz is indeed not here. Because she is in Bangkok. Because
she is in Bangkok. But he is young is here. Yeah, yeah. And there is a Thai restaurant.
They don't have teleporters in them. They will look happy to ask. True, I haven't asked.
The Thai restaurant from Mr Ben. Right. But yes, so we are going to talk about things.
We are not going to do letters of comment now. But we are going to sit low-eave letters of
comment at the end when you have all the things to comment on. Such as what was that? You idiots.
So yes, Marguerite, now you are the vice chair of Discon 3 and you are also bidding Dublin
and Glasgow. You were talking about Dublin in 2019? 2019. 2019. All of you, all of you.
Excellent. So we are going to talk to you about all of that. So we are actually staging
an intervention here. I did wonder about that. People, people do stay, friends don't let
their friends run World Cons. And I wondered what that said about me. It's a good question.
It's a very good question. But first we are going to talk about Novacom. We are talking
about in-person conventions, they are fun, aren't they? Yes, they are. We are having
quite a good time. Is anyone else having a good time? Is it lovely to be out of the
house? Players just like. Is it nice to be in the bar with actual people doing bar things?
Yes. I think three people enjoy that. Everyone else is like, "No, we are here for the programme."
I will programme some significantly better in person. I don't know the answer to that.
I think some can be. I think a lot will come down to the person themselves. This is my
professional how to consult it. It depends. There are certainly differences. I know some
people who absolutely adore online programming because it gives them access that they wouldn't
otherwise have. That includes not just accessibility items but access to people that they wouldn't
otherwise get to hear from or to talk to. That is just inherently more difficult when
you are in person. But there is something about being in the same space as other people. And
particularly for this, as a performer, if you like, having the energy flow back from
the audience in the room is very different from the online experience, even though they
both happen. I think there is some of that as well. I mean, I've got two relevant anecdotes
from this very weekend. Two from this weekend and one from previous weekend. This weekend,
a program I was on yesterday and a spike brought me a pint of porter. That hasn't happened
to any of the online conventions I have been to. That has been great. A punctuation we
did, no, no. I was about to say, Esther brought me several beers of punctuation. That was
because we put it in the scavenger hunt because we are dicks. When I say we, I mean me.
I was a thing in the scavenger hunt of punctuation where we would buy things for the committee.
John's idea and I was like, oh no. I can't get very improper and I was like, I have
cake. I indeed also kept getting cake through the post. I just want to show off hands. How
many people in the audience have said publicly that when this is all over, they really like
to buy me a pint of beer for all the good I have done for family. Right. What if you like
to go to the bar and get me a pint of porter? Thank you very much.
I just get my nitty as well. Okay. We've driven with now an audience member down because
we made to go get them a beer. I don't know whether that is that a good podcasting time
will tell. I don't really like us. I'm going to get a porter.
The other thing is I went to the Christopher Priest panor item and I'm sure it would have
been very good had I had subtitles and I could hear it. And that was a definite negative
to not. And I just sat there thinking one of you say something. One of my online regular
acquaintances very much prefers online program because as he says, you can start it halfway
through and then speed up through the boring. And the other thing you can do at an online
program is leave in a way that turns out to be really embarrassing for anyone who is wondering
how to skip through the boring bits of this episode of Octa Torp. If you skip to about
the 40 or 45 minute mark, that's when people from the audience will start shouting at us.
Yeah. No. Have you seen the fine apparel that Ang is wearing today? Oh, yes. Ang is going
to model that. We might need to use this chapter art darling. Yes. All right. Ang,
I'm also wearing apparel by hiding it beneath the jumper. But I am cosplaying my podcast
with my purple jeans and purple t-shirt. Ang is modeling our fetching Jesus t-shirt. Yes.
We were an original swear by Liz Batty. Yes. But we, so when we were talking about spot
discount at one point, it was pointed out on the podcast that the blah, blah, blah,
sounded a bit like a sad talk about. And so I commissioned a piece of art from Alison,
which is a kind of like marching band logo or like patch. It's a patch. It's like a
fire. No. Oh, no, it's the word confine. Yes. The word confine. Yes. The patch. We did.
Yeah. The satro burn. I've done a lot of art for you. So we have some worlds also. So
considering, yes, considering that this podcast is entirely audio, I seem to have made an
awful lot of art for it. That's my fault. And I don't apologize. Yeah. That's the story
of my life. But yes, no, and also there are people here who do not usually come to the
Novocomp. There are a lot. There are quite a lot of people at this convention who, because
when they said last night, who was here at the first Novocomp? There were a lot. Is that
one in the audience that they first never come? No. No. No. Okay. I guess. Spite. Yeah.
I thought spite was. But this is Bill Burns's first. First Novocomp, for instance. What
have you enjoyed most about Novocomp? I think that, to be honest, one of the things that
I have enjoyed is simply walking around and seeing everybody talking to each other. Because
that is something that is very difficult to do with the technology that we currently have.
I am still extremely socially awkward. I won't necessarily go up and join in. But, you know,
knowing that people are having a good time is part of why I do pop-allowing. So it's a
good thing to see even when I'm not running this one. I've run into people in hallways.
I like running into people in hallways. I haven't done that for a while. Because I
have seen people. But I don't, it's always been people that have made a particular appointment
to go and see. I think that habit of just going somewhere and running into a load of
people you know, but you wouldn't necessarily have the not appointment people. I will say,
you know, one of the things that I've noticed here in particular is an increase in the number
of people who see my name. And finally, I can tell, associate the name with the face.
They're like, "Oh, I've seen you around. I know." I have an anecdote from this convention.
I have an anecdote from this convention. I've heard that you've just felt this anecdote,
which is a Friday night. You've heard the anecdote, I've always given you. I like that
you've had in your face already, even though this is on you. On Friday night, I was in a
restaurant and I saw a number of people eating dinner together. And I went up to one of them
and said, "Because I knew that she was being asked up, there's hello, Marguerite." At which
point everyone fell over because it was in fact Meg, Meg and Darnell. And then they explained to
me that Meg and Marguerite, neither of whom I knew at all well before the pandemic to be
fair, I mean, I had met them both, but not in a kind of, you know, they were both baric maitresses.
And I had met them both, but I had not met them in a way that associated their kind of three
dimensional actual human beings. I kind of had a notion of these are nice women with long hair who
are doing stuff on the Worldcon and are a bit baby Celtic.
Just in case any of you have not met Meg, she is tall and thin and very graceful and I have
none of those things. So when Alison told me this, I also felt about the place that I had because
it's like, "Oh yes, please keep confusing me." Yeah, what you need to do is get Sue Mason to draw you.
Anyway, I finished the end of that because at the following day, I was happened to be by the
Glasgow table as Meg and Marguerite were both there. So they did a kind of comparative thing.
This is Meg. This is Marguerite. I mean, that's also the horrible way, but you know, you're different
shape people. Those are appropriate gestures. Yeah, sorry, this is Meg. This is Marguerite.
This is one of those things that will not translate to radio, but yes.
That would be actually not chapter art, but you'll find a gift.
So Meg is very tall and shapely. Marguerite is very shapely.
I've also got a beer list.
Esther is, well, this is very good. Alison now has three different ingredients in front of her.
I've only two hands. Oh, balanced diet. So moving, I was going to say swiftly on, but moving slowly
on with the digression into a punchline. Is this your first mobile corner? How many
of you know the ones you've been to before? It is actually not my first mobile corner,
but I have not been to many. I think I've only been to one other. It would have been 2018, I think.
I've been nodding. I was there representing Donald Clinton as it was, and did not then make it in
2019 before the world changed. So how many people, when they asked how many Nova Cons you'd been to
yesterday, could not in fact remember? There's more than half the room.
Because very fortunately, they kind of went to more than 10, and then they went to 50, and that made
it quite good. That's how you do good stats. It will be incidences.
Isn't that accounting system one, two, many lots? I have definitely been to lots of Nova Cons.
Have you been to one, two, few, many or lots of Nova Cons? I think I've been to four, then it's my
fourth. I don't make anywhere near as often as I make it to EastCon, but yeah, I wanted to make it.
I had another anecdote about program at conventions, which was that when
Alison and Spike and Tom and everyone else nods off in program, you can take selfies of yourself
with them, and it's very funny. You can't really do that on Zoom, and it's a shame.
So should we talk about World Cons? Oh yeah, no, because we have... I see those eyes on me already.
Well, Margry was working for Nicholas White on the Hugo team at... You would like
Deputy Division Head for... Correct.
...Gusvus for just gone, and then you resigned from that role, and then just recently, like,
a couple of months ago, so start of September. Yeah, you became one of the vice chairs.
You're the first ever Irish vice chair of the Baltimore World Cons. I think that's a
same assumption. So that was for people who didn't know the disc on, which has... I don't mean to diss you,
Com. That was too well planned. Yes, you should have told me what for doing puns, but that one was...
That was bad. It was there. I don't want to diss your Com, but it has had a bit of an ability to
not always say the perfectly right thing. Correct. So what convinced you to take on this? Because
it's very reasonable. When you said... When you said...
...you might let friends run a Com with, say, Esther or Nicholas, but friends really should have
stopped you from going, "Yeah, I'm going to step up and do the disc on things." So what made the
difference? For me, a lot of the difference, and since Nicholas is here, he can verify some of this,
part of why the entire WIS15 resigned. It was not just refusing to work for Nicholas anymore.
The personal decisions was a point of principle, and we thought it was very important to say we were
not willing to build that particular world clock. Well, there were other changes that happened after
that, including a new chair, and from what I saw, that was much more the World Cons that I thought
I was going to. I am seeing internal correspondence from the new chair. It's really very encouraging.
And it has been... I think Mary Robinette seems to be doing a really fine job, and so you thought,
"Well, I've got that one." I did. I did. I thought, "Here is my chance to make some of those changes
that I want to try to bring in." I mean, it is... It's not even turning one of the giant ships.
It's more like trying to turn the iceberg itself. It just takes so much effort, and sometimes
still doesn't work, but this was a good chance to continue trying. And the more that we can all
continue trying, the more likely it is to actually actually happen. Thanks, Barida. We're very much
taking the option of not trying and just complaining about it on the radio instead, which... What
you have is the difference, because usually it's social media. Well, I think we usually, you know,
we usually make sure we argue. Like, we don't... We present both sides. We also present both sides.
I mean, I think... Usually because two of us disagree and we have two. I think just gone to be quite a
troubled Worldcon, even by the standpoint. I mean, obviously all Worldcons have a load of
crap going on behind the scenes. It doesn't necessarily... It kind of... There's always a load of things,
and then every sort of something bubbles up and there's a little flurry, and then it goes away.
But just gone and seems to have had a very continuous thing of it, and it's kind of coming together.
Now you've got how many weeks to go? We have... I'm sorry, I should... I...
That was... For the listeners, that was four and a half. I do actually have a pile of sticky notes
at home, and the only thing it is is a countdown of how many days I pull one off every day.
Should you be like rocking Xs on a calendar?
Want to see Promise? Yeah. Or maybe a gold star for every day, we make it through...
Yes. That's a great idea. So you said like you kind of decided to go on board the
Disgrom ship, because there were things that you thought you could achieve. So what was the kind of...
What was the kind of thing you were like hoping to do? So some of the things that I was hoping to do
were coming out of previous Worldcons, which in hands up I have worked on those as well. It's not
somebody else's problem, but I know there was quite a strong reaction to, for example, the
hero ceremony last year. And people felt that the finalists were not getting the recognition they
deserved, in part because traditions have changed. You know, I know that George RR Martin, who was the
Toastmaster last year, and who designed that ceremony, those were the things that he enjoyed
as a young writer. He liked the anticipation. He liked that, you know, sense of not knowing and
drawing it out. And boy, it was cruel, but then wasn't it fantastic when he found out. And that's
just not really how it works anymore. You know, things have changed and that wasn't recognized.
So by being able to come back and say, these finalists are our sort of celebrities in a way,
you know, everyone who is there is their unequal footing. But we as a body have decided to
honor these people. We should honor these people being able to come back in and say, yes, there will
be, you know, a party, there will be pictures, there will be space for everyone to bring a plus
one. We will just make sure that this kind of stuff happens was important. Some of the other
aspects that I was hoping then to change, or at least to be involved in along the way were
things like making sure that it's a DC worldcon. I won't say that any old asshole can run a
worldcon because that's not entirely true. It takes a very particular type. There is a difference
as an attendee and as somebody who's worked on them between this was a fun worldcon and
holy shit, that was, you know, this locations, worldcon. You know, I know it was one of
the things that I was hoping to do. Do you have any connection with DC? No, no. So what have you
done to immerse yourself in kind of DC culture to try and get that sense of the local, I can do
an anecdote which is that we did the news letter for Dublin and none of us are Irish. What?
It's Irish. Not Irish. Not quite Scottish. I'm vaguely Celtic. There it is. But we did, so we did quite a
lot of things that we thought as English people would make it more Irish, bearing in mind James's
injunction that we would not put any leprechauns in it. We did put a leprechaun in the spoof, but
you had that. But we also had an Irish sensitivity reader who was, he was lovely. But, you know, so we
did kind of our assistive to just, but we also thought, what do we like about Irish culture as
the Irish represented? So we had a lot of folklore and we had the drop capitals and things like that.
We did quite a lot of stuff that was designed to make the news letter super Irish, just by the
fact that we are super not Irish. And I think it was fine. I think. Yeah, definitely. And so we're
doing, we are doing similar things, but the biggest thing that we're doing is bringing people from
DC in to tell those stories. Yeah. We've made sure to have DC-based writers, you know, write the
script for our Hugo ceremony. And actually, we've done a slightly different thing in that we have,
for lack of a better term, a writer's room, you know, has actually been announced. And we're having
them write all of our majors ceremony so that we can get some of those references throughout the
weekend repeated. You know, it's not just, here's the opening ceremony. And here's the Hugo ceremony,
and here's the closing ceremony, and here's the masquerade. Here's this, that, and the other.
So where we can, we're trying to bring that only one piece, but it's also, and Mary Robinette said,
this very flatterably when she was, was asking me to join was her job as chair is to find the
smarter people and let them go do their thing. And I think that's very much true of how do you
bring that location sense as well? You find the people whose location it is, and let them go.
You build the stage for them to do their thing. Yeah. Yeah. I think that makes a lot.
So do you think that part you get involved, there was a strong sense of DC place in
this culturally? I did not get that from the original workings that I had. There were certainly
DC aspects to it, and some of those will become more obvious as things are announced, but there
wasn't that real sense of this could only happen in DC, where I think some of this stuff we're
doing now could only happen in DC. And I think that's, that's the difference.
So, and I think one of the things I've liked about the World Curves, the World Curves are
particularly stick in my mind. I've been to 10 World Curves, and the best of them have really
had that sense of place that could not have been anywhere else. Yeah. For example, Reno,
when I left the kind of mountain doing, Chris Garcia's car, and when I got back it was too hot to touch,
that was a very, you know, experience. I remember that. And there was also like program, I think.
I've, I've friends don't let their friends drink a American mountain,
because look at them honestly. So you're also involved in Glasgow.
So can I just check, are you doing any World Cons between this gun and Glasgow?
Technically no.
So I was part of the executive team for Chai-Kong 8, which is coming up next year.
But Helen Montgomery and I, who she is the chair, she and I had agreed ahead of time that
coming into 2022, because that is the year of the vote for Glasgow, I would be withdrawing from
Chai-Kong. I don't think anybody's a song. So, so yes, I, and again, I don't think anybody would
have raised any objections, but I just wanted to remove any possibility of that. So I sped that
up a bit when I took on the DC. Yeah, kind of went. I kind of went. Hello, hello, hello,
yeah. Hello, hello, yeah, hello, yeah. I think it's reasonable. So what is it you're doing from
Glasgow? I was, I was wondering, I was wondering what it is. Sorry, can I just check something?
It's Friday, it's five o'clock. It's...
So what, what is it you're doing for Glasgow? I am the chair of vice for Glasgow.
Or the vice chair? Excellent. Do you just have one? Do you have like a Latinx
Covice chair? Not for Glasgow. Not for Glasgow. Do you have like a Scotts Gaelic
Covice chair? No, or not yet. I thought you meant it. Certainly.
Looking at each other. Well, then they're going, oh, yeah. I was like, oh, hey, there's an idea.
I think you should get Helena on the side, because she's like, she could bring in the Glasgow
element. You know, when we're talking about getting the authentic Glasgow voice, because we
were saying in the bar last night about what the authentic Glasgow voice is like. See you, Jimmy.
No, you, me, man. Stop that.
She's not the asker. She sees four broadies.
I think you can accept this as prime content. Yeah, yeah. So which, which voices are you the chair of?
Everything that Esther does not wish to handle. Actually, indeed, indeed. Actually, I was
some white who seemed to do this at Peoplepong in 2020. Just before everything broke down.
My job is actually to protect the chair.
Like this. Excellent.
We're taking our bullets. We'll talk some 2020 at Peoplepong.
Oh, there was a quincy.
We're just being a botches. Oh.
Because what I do, I haven't added it about Peoplepong.
Yes, but we've told it on the podcast before.
Perhaps you can't hold it to. Yeah.
You have shit. Okay. Sorry.
Oh, there's a limit.
Well, Alison workshops her jokes.
So friends don't let their friends workshop their jokes before.
Yeah.
Hey, this never happened.
Hashtag a week.
Oh, yeah.
We can have the question for now.
So, the name Christina like.
Yes, very nice.
She's late.
So how long have you been involved with Glasgow?
Oh goodness.
But yeah, just about five years.
Oh, thanks.
Sorry.
This is a very recent acquisition of mine at this time.
Goodness.
I suppose you and I spoke about this particular position 2019.
So two years of this.
And has it been filled so far?
Yeah.
Pretty much.
It is.
And I say this with all love to my Irish con running compatriots.
The certainly the most frighteningly competent it's been.
OK, so what I see because I have a very, very tiny role in Glasgow,
which I do mention occasionally on the podcast.
I have an interest in my role in Glasgow is to get all the old thoughts come along.
And that seems to be going pretty well.
Yeah.
People are pretty positive.
It's going to be fantastic convention.
Very purple.
Yes, but it's a slightly different shade to all to talk about.
Yeah.
If I do use some print on demand t-shirts while you're in a dry spell,
then they're going to be that car.
So, you know, that's how it works.
You're OK.
How did you know?
I was not right.
I think that's a good question.
I was drinking with your wife.
I'm not used to it.
So, yes.
So what is kind of, so you have a year now until the vote, a try con.
Are you confident you're going to win?
What do you think there's going to be a Royal Inn?
And they're just going to...
Yeah, when is it?
Everybody's looking at Esther now.
As representative, I'm protecting my chair.
Listeners, audio description at this point,
Mulgory Tcontorted herself in interesting ways.
That is probably the benest I've been all weekend.
Like a wicky face.
I will never say 100% confidence until the vote is complete,
just because so many things can happen.
However, no, I don't expect a writing vote at this stage.
I believe that for the most part, writing votes
they're like sharks, they sense, weakness.
And we haven't shown any or maybe just real...
So we could maybe find the weak spot or we could be noisy.
Yay!
We, um, you haven't shown any weakness.
So what's happened with this year's writing vote was clearly
that there was a sense of people not wanting to go to Chengdu
and thinking wholly accurately that Memphis might not quite have got its sugar together.
We are a family-friendly podcast.
Yeah, I probably should have checked that before swearing all through it.
No, no.
No, I mean...
We may be stopping B because John can't be asked.
Yes.
We're mostly family-friendly as long as you don't mind the word fuck.
As long as your children swear, that's yours.
Yes.
And so you're also involved with Dublin in 2029.
I am.
Now, I have two questions and there is a few...
I don't know, I'm going to lead into that.
I actually had a segue.
Oh, you have a segue.
So speaking of world compits that are 100% not going to lose,
I understand you've launched a bid for Dublin in 2029.
That's excellent.
I like that.
Although I worry that you've jinxed us.
No.
So how it works right is that...
Is this Allison's predictor?
This is my predictor.
I don't think...
Because the smoths like to think they organise the vote.
But actually, there's a lot of ordinary American fans who vote.
And my belief is that America...
They're kind of potty for the Irish.
And fundamentally, you could be like,
"We're going to hold it in a bog in a...
In a tree."
I'll be able to ask.
As someone from Cambridge,
if you hold it in a bog, I will be there.
There has not been enough bog-based world comps.
It's a terrible shame.
There are actually bog diving competitions.
We could bring some of that in.
But they were circles and we could just...
Yeah, I can bet you could get people to do that.
I was going to ask two serious questions.
First question.
One of the strategies that has been employed by British and Irish bits
over the last few years is announcing far enough in advance
that it is unlikely that other bids will contest.
Is that something you are hoping will happen again in 2029?
That is part of why we weren't announcing early.
Yes, we want to make it clear that we are intending to run for 2029
being a nice crossroads year since that's sort of how I'm thinking about it.
And that Brian Nisbitt and I bid for 2029 as the anniversary of 2019.
But it's also the 10 years until the 100th anniversary of the first world comp.
Okay, so that was 1939.
So 2039 will be 100 years on.
That's a perfect spot for lots of activity.
So you are in 2029?
So we're going for 2029.
Right.
My serious question is, so if there were one complaint that anyone must make
about the excellent previous Irish World comp,
2019, which I have told everyone I loved,
I'd be to 10 World comps of that push.
That was my favourite by Niles.
For reasons that maybe it had more to do with me personally than...
I mean, it was a lovely, lovely con.
But it was the first convention when none of my children were under 18.
So my question was, if people had one complaint about the W World comp,
it would be that the CCD was absolutely stuffed full to the gun.
So what are you going to do to get some more comfort space?
So one of the things that we are already working on is planning to work with the NCI,
which is the college that is in the building's next door to the CCD.
Because they do have quite a lot of suitable programme space,
lecture halls, amphitheater style seating.
They also have a relatively large atrium that we can use for exhibits or displays or other activities.
And the biggest thing that we're doing is planning that in from the start.
I mean, when 2019 started,
nobody ever expected that it was going to be as big as it was.
And the CCD holds, notionally, 5,500 people.
Turns out that might not quite be true in the way that a World comp distributes people through the
building. But I know from seeing past emails, from seeing past projections,
people were saying, "We'd be lucky if we got 3,500, 4,000 people."
They fit fine in the CCD. So one of the things that we're doing now is obviously,
as World comps as a whole, get bigger, as we now have this experience of a convention within the CCD,
to say, "Okay, this is what worked. This is what didn't. How do we start trying to solve some of
these problems? Do we start getting NCI space? Do we find other additional space nearby?"
Ireland and the UK in general do not have the US model of a giant convention center
immediately attached to a hotel. You know, Glasgow is very lucky that we do have that.
But it means that our World plans have to look slightly different.
Most of the time, we will not be lucky enough to have everything within one contained building.
But that means that we have to plan for what that means in terms of accessibility and
size. You know, I saw a comment shortly after Brian and I announced that was, effectively,
that this person would not attend any Dublin convention unless we promised that we would
cap membership in order to keep numbers down. And it's not something I heard.
We won't miss them. But exactly.
You said about 3, 2, 3, 9 being a crossroads.
And I always sort of assumed that at some point someone would try and work out how to hold the
bolt con in New York again so that it could be in New York in 2039. Are you expecting that to happen?
Are you expecting to bid Dublin for 2039?
Well, I would never say never. Very unlikely.
It's not, no. It's not, no.
2039. Because I will be another 10 years older at that stage.
I wanted to make sure that the possibility is open. I would love to see a New York anniversary of
the World Con, but there's always that debate about which was the actual first.
Where was the first science fiction convention?
Everyone, please.
Yes. But even within the US, even within the US, there's debate about was it New York,
was it Philadelphia, was it? But the first official World Con was part of the World
World Con, the first World Con was definitely.
Which is why it's a big world.
You know, so I think it might be a bit difficult to take a batch of New York.
I'm sure people would love to.
Yes.
It's not impossible. I think it would take an awful lot of work from people who are
extremely busy at the moment, or an influx of new people and a huge reduction in prices.
Unfortunately.
That's very fair. That was my other question.
Excellent.
We're now going to open for letters of comment.
Please submit your letters of comment through the medium of yelling from the audience.
No, please raise your hand.
Oh, right.
Yes.
Are they allowed to make a letter of comment?
The letter of comment is not finished with a question.
No, no, no.
Letter of question.
How do you want to?
Do we have any letters of comment?
Sit your hands up if you do.
If not, we'll do picks.
Do you have asked, ask, or thought questions?
Don't all shout out once.
I don't know.
I should warn you that if you say anything, it might be recorded and used in the podcast.
Against?
Oh, yeah.
No, it's the podcast.
We can do picks for people who are ruining.
No, we can do our picks.
Oh, but we have a question.
Nicholas White.
It is I.
Oh, we have to leave.
I'm going to have to be bad.
You're going to have to leave.
Will you blue-tash?
You promise.
What have you voted for in this year's Hugo Awards?
Ha ha!
That was going to be my pick.
My pick was going to be, and I've written in show notes,
I was going to pick voting in the Hugo Awards because I'm insufferably smug
about having done all the reading.
How many of the reading have you done, Harrison?
I read helicopter stories.
Right, and who?
And the years?
Some Hugo voter packet, Alison.
Caroline.
And so Caroline and I submitted.
I, my primary Hugo reading is that I have put, I put 300 hours into Hugo reading
for this year's Hugo Awards and it was all Hades.
Yes.
Have you, have you enjoyed the Hugo roster this year?
Have you?
She's my chair of the book.
She hasn't read a book since late September.
For the listeners, Marguerite is making a face.
I will let you imagine the face.
I have enjoyed what I have partaken on,
but I am, you know, working on the World Council.
There are two things there.
One, I am actually busy.
Two, I am, well, can I say two things?
There are several things.
One, too many, whatever.
So she's not going to actually say what the quick picture he goes on?
Probably not other than, of course, I will vote for all of my friends
because everybody knows that the he was a root.
Please don't take that out of context.
But I am not part of the Hugo's up.
So could you say that again so that you won't get tung-looted by the future?
Yes, it might be quite useful.
Thank you very much.
Yes, I am putting spirit fair above Hades, I'm sorry.
Yeah, I understand that.
That's the likes of a fair fair also.
I very like that.
Yeah, we'll probably have to have what we need to do is have a kind of post-13
wash-up thing where we talk about all the stuff.
That's the next episode.
My pick for this week is the fanthology from Corfu.
And normally when you say fanthology, it just has a single A,
but in this case it is a fanthology,
which is pronounced exactly the same way, which has two A's,
which is one of these things that's really difficult on a podcast.
And that's because it's not a fanthology of general fan writing,
it's a fanthology of fanfiction,
but it's not fanfiction in the sense of stories such in universes that are written by fans.
It's fanfiction in the sense of fan writing with the fans as fictional characters.
And it turned out, because I didn't think I'd have done any of this,
but I started reading the excellent fanthology
that Sandra Bond has put together for Corfu.
"Guests of Honor" and previous president knows.
"Guests of Honor" knew...
"You took the bond."
Oh, so for people who don't know,
Corfu has the best award.
There's been a lot of talk about honors recently,
but the best honor in fandom without a single doubt
is the past president of the fan writers of America.
Okay, and the great thing about the past president of the Fabrics of America
is that it's never a president.
They just elect every year,
we elect a new past president,
so they don't have any duties whatsoever.
And the newest past president of what is Sandra Bond,
who is in the audience tonight,
she was also guest of honor at Corfu last week.
The fanthology is called "Dangerous Visions."
That's from the extra A in it.
And the great thing about this is it turns out,
when I started reading it,
that it turns out that all the fan writing I've ever done
is in fact fan fiction with an extra A in it,
and I'm not realised because I don't lie.
I just polished my jokes and made me vomit in the vlog.
So, so, so as a newbie to the fanthology,
where could I get my hands on one?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
The spikes holding them up.
You could go onto Amazon.co.uk and buy it there.
I don't know if you say how much does it want Amazon?
It's probably also a past.
Some money.
But remember, when you're searching on dangerous visions,
put in an extra A and put in edited by Sandra Bond.
It is great. Fantastic.
There would also be a link in the service.
And there would be a link across the link in the service.
Did you have a pick, Malcolm?
I think my pick at the moment,
I have two.
One is a new novel that somebody has let me pre-read,
Joseph Elliott Campbell.
And I'm enjoying it very much so far,
but the other is the anthology that's available here at Nelbokan.
Because it is also absolutely fantastic.
I haven't really been able to dig into it.
I might have missed my flight on Friday and come in late.
So, I came in yesterday morning.
But I've had a brief look and it looks amazing.
It's gone.
Some of the stories that were in chat books
from the other 49 never comes.
There's also new stories.
New stories from authors.
So, there's very exciting authors in the anthology.
And I have no idea who I live and I am out of it.
You know Carrie.
Carrie, Carrie, Carrie, Carrie.
Adrian Shikovsky's starting to feel like this.
What?
I think he embags that one of the stories.
Because the embags to chat books were some money
as I found to my benefit on eBay some years ago.
I have a lot of news, but I'm not selling it.
I used to have four of them.
Sick out.
Yeah.
Because it used to be that you couldn't, if you could.
No, it still is.
So, me and his back, you got one of each.
We were not asked.
But, you know, it's fine.
Two things.
So, that's great.
Pics.
Any other questions?
Esther.
Fan favorite Badger the Cat.
Yes or no?
I'm happy.
Yes.
Definitely, yes.
I thought we kind of, you know,
were you mad at us?
Yeah, yes.
I mean, it also goes without question.
Badger is the best cat.
Badger in the best.
Oh, no.
John Coxon, original poet.
Badger is the best cat.
I didn't say bad.
He is.
That's an original album.
Esther is.
She's the best.
All the things we've said is she's telling us thing.
And expecting us to respect.
So, yes.
So, and I for one, don't do a podcast so that people can remember what I say.
So, one of the things about podcasts that have hundreds and hundreds of episodes
is that the audience apparently expect the people on the podcast to remember what they
said.
But if you're the sort of person who does 500 episodes of a podcast,
you're not the sort of person who remembers what they've already said.
Oh, just like Freddy listeners listening who are thinking,
"You're like missed 400 and 56 episodes of "The One of the Dawn."
We have in fact only done 40 episodes.
No, no, I'm just...
Yeah, no.
I know.
Just curious.
Listen, I'd like to say that's what machine learning is for.
Does that have a question?
Does that have a question at the end?
No.
No, no.
Is that a machine learning?
Yes, it's very easy.
You can...
It's very easy to do comments as questions because you say,
"Do you think comment, question mark?"
And it's I've learned this.
I can't tell another comment to it.
You can't.
Okay, so can we have your letter of comment from big name fan and also a book author.
Previous...
Previous TAF winner, Lillian Edwards.
When you get your report, when you're going to get your trip report out, ladies.
Maybe next year.
Sometimes you'll be after on a date.
Anyway, where were you going?
You could go back here almost twice in because this is what my PhD students
got all their comments.
You could build an avatar bot from author to the English if she learns from all of your
characteristics.
Quickly, yes.
Oh, for fuck's sake.
You know, just also like a Barbie talking dog.
Yeah.
You know, people that straight away go.
So you'll say...
I think the cat is the best cat.
How much?
How much opt forward we have to put Jesus.
How... no, actually not going to be... Jesus.
That's good.
I like that.
We just send that into the microphone.
We should have put that much.
Jesus is so...
Cheeses and margaritians.
Yeah, probably.
You know, you're going to have some issues.
And I'll be normalised as fine.
Yeah.
That's it.
So I did tell Mark and Claire that when they all want to feed all the banana wings into an
AI to resurrect them after they're gone.
And after I've gone, probably.
And then what we can do is we can have Claire make all decisions about British fandom
and their absence because she's the only sense of...
Claire has given you a pattington last seven.
Yes.
But I think she's doing it with love.
I hope.
Either that I'm going to get kicked up the backside later.
So, you know, we'll find out.
Two in the next episode.
So any other comments, questions?
Might start.
You said earlier you've formed the live code amazing.
You can't fast forward to the boarding bits.
Is that how we're here this long?
Oh, it's a good point.
And it was a question.
It was?
Yeah.
It's very good.
Sandra Bond.
It was a rhetorical question.
Surely given the state of emptiness of the passage in front of you,
I think the purpose of the beer is to create the boarding bits.
That is what we refer to as a pointing tool.
Sick.
Was that a sick bird?
I think we just got told.
We did get told.
Any more comments, questions?
So from Ms. Claire Brownlee of Britain.
It's been a while since you've done a letter of comment.
I'd like to thank you for asking.
I've taken your couple of people from earlier.
And I would like to ask, what was that, you idiot?
That was the Octa Thought podcast.
And it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
Goodbye from me.
Cover any of you.
If you've been affected by me.
You can buy merch at them.
Thank you very much to Margree for being on the podcast.
Yes.
It was a very good deal.
Thank you.
Keep reading.
It's not going to be worse.
It's not going to be worse than, like, it's not,
this is not going to be a pristine.
We're going to go into Octa Thought though,
as soon as we start.
Do we have a joke?
Where are shadows?
Are you up?
What are you doing?
That is the topic of cinema.
Hello.
How are you?
Well, I'm awake.
Hey!
Are we doing this on Zoom?
I think, I assumed we'd be doing this on Zoom.
Alison thought we'd be doing it on Zoom,
but it's sort of like a lot of effort, doesn't it?
Anyway, I promise we'd shout, "Hi, Liz."
Hi, Liz.
So, Liz.
You can't see this, but we're in the bar.
We should do this.
Welcome to Octa Thought, the podcast of getting pissed.
Yes.
And also, Armin Max.
Did you get an Armin Max for this occasion, Liz?
No, because I had one yesterday.
Wow.
How was it?
Tell us everything.
It was good.
Almondy?
I was expecting more than three words.
Yeah, that's because she's only,
"Have you had any coffee, sweetheart?"
No!
No, no, no.
"Have you had any beer?"
Yeah.
"Would you like?"
"Would send you a coffee or some beer?
"Which would you rather?"
"If you were a..."
Good morning.
"If you were 100 men at Easter Corn
"and Alice and Tex did you saying,
"Are you up winky face?
"What would you do?"
"100 duck size then, that's ridiculous."
I feel we've confused her about to sleep.
[Laughter]
It's a nice thing.
So...
[Laughter]
Sorry, I can't be honest.
I don't know.
I'm texting men because I'm after a duck.
I'm supposed to be really quiet, guys.
[Laughter]
We're not supposed to be really quiet.
Yes, so...
Oh, yeah, I know.
Right, so welcome to Oxford,
the podcast is staying up too late
and drunkenly phoning people from bars.
Welcome to the first one.
I'm John Carson.
I'm Alice and Scott.
[Laughter]
Liz, you're Liz Batty.
This is my Jesus.
[Laughter]
This is quite confusing.
This is where Liz goes.
Jesus.
[Laughter]
So this is actually the first ever
Oxford Liver convention with an audience
and we're making a real good go at it.
Who the audience are?
The audience are Caroline,
Claire, Mark and Spike,
and also two very confused hotel staff and a rugby player.
[Laughter]
Yes.
That is the complete list.
[Laughter]
It's a nice hotel.
There's mushrooms for breakfast.
Yeah, they're just pretty good.
They're just not quite a plus.
We miss you.
We'd love to see you.
We're sad that you're not with us.
Hello, Thomas.
Hi, Alice.
Hi, what's up?
What's up, Adam?
Hello, Liz.
John said you didn't want to be finished.
No, don't touch me something.
Shut my name a lot.
Liz.
And then you were going to do a fact.
Oh, are we not supposed to be having like an actual recording?
I thought we were going to record.
John promised me he had the technology all sorted out.
Which I think we need is recording.
What's up somehow?
Yep, on my eye.
We are using John's eye pad on what's up.
Can you take a photo of this very elaborate recording set
for the chapter?
Yeah, can you smile?
Hang on, you're going to have to take a little bit of a smile.
Lots of good mix.
Hello, I'm doing a grimace, Liz.
Grimace, surely.
That's not what Caroline said.
Just travel in places.
I'm really sorry.
Check, you're all into course.
You almost certainly do not.
Claire is ducking like it's World War 3.
She's in a shelter.
Okay, it'll be just like David.
Not what you're doing this kind of kid.
I'm happy with that.
If I look like David Mitchell.
Yeah, he's married to Victoria Carm Mitchell and that's...
Oh, I do.
Yeah, you do.
Yeah, I'm a homo.
What would I do?
I'd say that.
Liz, what do you do Victoria Carm Mitchell?
It's what she would have wanted.
Yeah, it's got my cake.
What?
Who's your type?
Of the current taskmaster contestants, who is your type?
Good question.
Oh, interesting.
Do you want to say it very well?
Oh, Desiree, yeah.
Fair enough.
Yeah, there is a group consisting of...
I would have gone for Alan Davis,
but I think that says more about me than...
Look, he's just got lots of very nice floppy hair and he's adorable.
So, just a very attentive?
Yes.
And no, she would not be very attentive.
She'd be more aggressive.
More attentive.
Yeah.
Alan would just be lovely and he'd give you woolly slippers when you went to his house.
Oh, David's just got to have a QA for 16 years.
I think we'll see if you miss dressing out.
So, I'm watching Alan Davis.
But he wouldn't wonder it.
Oh, that was weird.
That whole 16- year thing was weird.
So, we miss you.
We are an actual convention with real people.
So, did we have shown it?
So, about...
We do not have show-do's.
Why would we?
It's two fifteen in the morning and I've had so much beer.
15, with the people with polar reads of an hour, I just told.
That's better.
And that was...
That was all the thought-life in the bar,
Yes.
And it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from a bunch of drunken fans.
Yay!
And this.
No, I think Caroline's, I think it was much better.
And that's the end of the episode.
Who's...
Bye.
No.
The theme music for this episode was "Rattle State Railroad" by Brett Van Donzel,
used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beat.
Beep.
(piano music)