Oh to the podcast corner is from me this time.
Hang on, I'm gonna sneeze.
- Well that's the pre-show.
Just Liz refusing to sneeze after promising us a sneeze.
Sneeze Liz, sneeze, sneeze!
- It's there, hang on.
No, it's gone now.
See if, get up.
- If you shall sneeze at someone loudly enough,
they can't sneeze and it's the worst thing.
It's planning to just be every time I try and sneeze
and it is, it should be banned.
But it is hilarious, do it to your loved ones.
They will be so annoyed with you.
Sorry Liz.
(laughing)
- We made Alison cry again.
Yes, okay, well that's the goals of podcast of the year.
(upbeat music)
- Hello everyone and welcome to the very 55th episode
of OctaThorp, the podcast for Science Fiction
and Science Fiction fandom,
which is coming to you on the 14th of April 2022.
I'm John Coxon.
- I'm Alison Scott.
- And I'm Liz Batty.
- We got nominated for a Hugo Award.
- I was good to say,
did we have any news this week guys?
- I don't know, I was too busy
being nominated for a Hugo Award.
(laughing)
It's so exciting.
- Quite nice.
- Very happy.
- Yeah.
- It's very nice.
- Congratulations to everyone else
who was nominated for a Hugo Award,
specifically in the fan cast category.
- It's a really good ballot.
We're really happy to be on the ballot
with the other fan cast
and we'd be very happy to lose to one of them
as we fully expect to.
- Yes, so the other nominees,
or sorry, the other finalists are Be the Serpent,
the Cooed Street podcast, Hugo Girl,
our opinions are correct and well-building for masochists.
Us and Hugo Girl are new to the ballot this year
and we would be very happy to lose to any of the other finalists
but I think we would all be particularly thrilled
to lose to Hugo Girl.
So we recommend everyone goes and listen to them
'cause they are brilliant.
- 'Cause we really like it.
And we all listen to,
now I don't know if we all listen to it.
I listen to a Hugo Girl very regularly.
- We do, we all listen to it.
Especially their most recent episode
which was them opening up all the champagne
and just squealing a lot, which was lovely.
- Haven't heard that yet.
(laughs)
Haven't got around to that.
Shit, we should have opened up all the champagne
and it's squeezed a lot, guys.
- John, can you add some fake champagne popping noises
because it is 10.30, so I feel it's a little bit early
for the fits.
- Yes, witness this Liz.
(popping)
(laughs)
- Okay, so for people who don't have a video on their podcast,
that was John beatboxing champagne opening.
(laughs)
Well, that's the name of the episode.
- We did actually get the email saying
your Hugo finalist at about 11 o'clock at night.
It's quite late.
I was in bed and.
- Was 6 a.m. Bangkok time and we did not ring Liz.
- And it was 6 a.m. Bangkok time
and John and I were on chat going,
"Should we bake? Should we be finalist?
Should we be finalist?"
- See, so the way I found out we had a Hugo nomination
was I looked at my phone
and I had like 97 messages from John and Alison
and I thought, "I either John and Alison had no argument
while I was asleep, or we got an email about Hugo's?"
(laughs)
- That first one was not impossible.
It has happened.
- Oh yeah, I mean, that's why Liz very sensibly
didn't immediately rule it out,
but I'm glad it was the second one.
(laughs)
No, so thank you so much to everyone who dominated us.
It is genuine thrill and we're all very surprised
and excited and we're all going to be in Chicago.
I mean, assuming nothing goes wrong,
we are all planning to be in Chicago for Worldcom.
- Are we? 'Cause Liz was like, "I'm not 100%."
- Oh no.
- And I'm like, "I'm booking flights next week after Easter."
- I'm not 100% yet.
- Chicago sent us a nice thing saying,
"If you're finding it hard to manage the cost
of going to a Worldcom,
then consider applying for our fund
for underprivileged people
and obviously the problem I've got is that
I am dripling in privilege,
but I am not dripping in money, so.
But I have my need to find just about enough money to go,
but obviously I can't, you know,
if you want to support underprivileged people to go to Shikon,
please do that, don't support me.
I can't find the money, but.
- If anyone was thinking of sending Alison some rare emeralds,
then this would be the week.
(laughs)
- Yeah, if we mentioned Alison's rare emeralds collection lately.
If anyone ever sends me vintage emeralds at this point,
they're going straight into the Worldcom bursary fund
for underprivileged people who aren't me.
- This segues very neatly into letters of comment
because lots of listeners wrote to us
to congratulate us for our nomination.
And thank you to everyone who got in touch.
We really appreciate it,
even if we didn't respond to everyone individually.
But yes, thank you so much to everyone
for their kind words.
But let's get into the subject of podcast distracts
because Ali Baker recorded a diss track
based on something Liz and Alison said.
Liz and Alison take it away.
- What's a diss track?
- What do you mean what's a diss track?
It's when a rapper drops a track
that disses another rapper.
- Oh, oh, diss, right.
- I mean, but we were wrong.
And Ali explains why very nicely
in her latest episode of fantasy book swap.
- She thinks we were wrong.
- Well, she doesn't think we're wrong.
She just thinks we, you said that a deadly education
challenged class in Harry Potter.
And I think you said it might have been one
of the first books to do it.
And then she dived into some of the history
about that in her latest podcast episode
because that is her research,
specialism.
So she is a quantifiable expert.
- Yeah.
Okay.
So I think we should say that whenever we veer close
to a topic that one of the three of us is an expert on,
we veer back sharply noticeably
what the weather is like outside of this is window
and what the virus is like.
And I'm not an expert on anything.
So it's quite easy that way, except being old.
- That's not true.
You're an expert on t-shirts, Alison.
- Okay, we do talk about t-shirts quite a lot.
So maybe not then.
- Yeah, but anyway, so yes, a proper academic
has taken us to task for doing a podcast
where we went off on one about her research topic,
which is fine.
- Which is fair 'cause I don't think,
I don't think we ever claim to be giving more
than our own half-hosts on the subject.
- Oh, and it's a wonderful, like, it's more of a verist.
It's brilliant.
I really enjoyed the episode.
It was very good.
And we've not had an entire podcast episode
letter of comment before.
So thank you very much to Ali for that.
- And we will put a link in the show notes.
- We will indeed.
Malcolm Hutcheson wrote in to say,
"John only has one shelf of board games.
Is it a very long shelf?"
Now, I was using the word shelf to mean piece of furniture
on which there are many shelves,
which I appreciate is one of those irregular nouns,
which is deeply unhelpful.
- Yeah, the words you're looking for is bookcase, I believe.
- Well, no, 'cause it's not a bookcase.
- It's a set of shelves.
- It's too deep.
Well, 'cause, and I've got a bookcase behind me,
which does have game content on it,
but most like bookcases are too shallow for board games.
That's why the Calax has been so popular for gamers
because it is deep enough to actually fit board games on.
But I have a bookcase behind me
that has lots of kind of role playing books and stuff on it.
And then I have a set of shelves downstairs
which has all of the actual board games on it.
And so it depends how you count, Malcolm.
I think you should come and see my board game collection
and play some.
It's quite big.
- I just want to say that the look on Liz's face now is,
I want you guys to finish by 11 o'clock
and John is going off on one of the bachelor's shelves.
- No, no, my look was John just out of context saying,
"It's quite big."
(laughing)
Liz, family show.
We also got a note from DC.
DC said that they would like to thank Alice and Scott
and Duncan for the demonstration of the utility
of removing glasses and growing a beard
as an effective disguise.
Duncan also tweeted us saying,
"Aha, let me listen to Octo-Thopcast.
"Ooh, has Alice and committed evil yet?
"Ah, the photo of John is terrifying.
"Curses, Liz made the joke.
"I was about to tweet in the actual podcast."
And he concludes that that was an emotional roller coaster.
And we're sorry for the inadvertent emotional roller coaster,
Duncan.
- We should maybe say this is all about last week's cover art,
which if you haven't seen it,
you should go and look at it.
I can't describe it.
- Nick Gibbons reacted to the GIF of me being very sweaty
at weddings with good Lord.
It's too early for this.
And we would like to sincerely apologise
to anyone for whom this is their first episode
of "
"I've got to talk coming off the back of our
"Hugh-Hugh nomination."
Because if you scroll down far enough on our Twitter,
there is, I'm so sorry, we didn't think that through.
Basically, long story short,
I get very sweaty at weddings.
Let's just draw a discreet veil.
- That's from a long time.
I mean, you need to listen to the last episode.
Although it episode before.
When you guys were expressing some concern
that the first people think people might see
on the Octo-Thopcast was the sweaty John GIF,
or sweaty John, sweaty John GIF.
- This is hard.
Words are hard.
- I think our podcast official should be GIF.
- We're GIF people.
I was like, well, I think that anyone who's first reaction
on hearing the Hugo Ballot is to scroll down
the Twitter piece of the best fan cast category
is probably deserves everything they get.
- Not sure anyone deserves that sweaty John GIF.
(laughing)
- I made it like, it came out.
I was like, is this going to come out well?
I was like, oh.
(laughing)
- Okay, and then finally,
Johnny Badley writes,
he really appreciates the in-depth discussion
of things like how world cons work
as someone who isn't as embedded in fandom.
It's really helpful.
And then followed up with,
is there any way we can donate to the podcast
to help hate for hosting and Weabix?
And the short answer to that is,
we'll all be at Eastcon and we all drink beer.
So if anyone feels like they would like to donate
to the podcast, please do feel free to buy us
one point of beer and we will all share it
with a little straw.
(laughing)
- We have to have an evening in the bar
where we do this with some,
'cause we already have a beer
that we're going to drink together.
We do need to drink a beer with three straws
under our masks, so now.
- Oh.
- Shall I bring three bendy straws to Eastcon?
- Yes.
It is something we've sort of vaguely discussed
after Johnny asked and I think the basic conclusion
is that this podcast does not cost enough to run
and we are not sufficiently unwealth-privileged
that we feel it would be a good use of anyone's money.
So.
- Yeah, full disclosure guys,
this podcast currently mostly paid for
by the occasional adverts for Stowe shirts.
We'll put a link in the show notes.
Who will be at Eastcon?
So one other way you can support the podcast
is to buy stuff from Alison.
Yeah, and we'll put a link so that you can buy more things.
So the I pay for bits and pieces of our hosting so far
and I also do ads occasionally
and every so often somebody buys a sweatshirt
and it all sorts of adverts, so it's fine.
- On the topic of OctaThop merch,
there will be a misprinted OctaThop t-shirt
at the Amaze Balls table at Eastcon.
And Alison, do you want to tell the listeners
about Amaze Balls?
- It's actually we're doing two things,
a t-stiff of the fanfons.
There will be a fanfons table,
which you can need to come and find
in one of the dealers rooms
and it is doing two different enterprises.
The first is a silent auction
and you don't need to be at Eastcon for this.
You can bid online
and there'll be lots of things in the silent auction
which might include the misprinted t-shirt actually.
I don't think it's necessarily gonna be
an Amaze Balls virus.
And then the other thing we're gonna be doing is,
and you also probably don't need to be at Eastcon for this either
because maybe doing a virtual version of it
is you donate money to the fanfons for spins
of a bingo spinner.
And when you spin the bingo spinner,
you get a ball numbered between one and 90.
And we say something like, I don't know,
two little ducks, 22 or something of that kind.
And we give you a prize.
Every single spin wins and spins cost a pound
or six for a fiver.
And some of the prizes are amazing.
That's what's called Amaze Balls.
Some of the prizes are amazing,
but not necessarily in the way you'd want.
And if you'd like to give us your prizes back,
that'll be an extra pound.
(laughs)
I have a variety of things that I'm bringing
to Eastcon for the fanfons.
I've got a tiny little astronaut keychain,
which is very cute and lovely.
And I've also got a hilariously oversized pair
of Dr. Pepper branded underpants.
So, you know, paying that pound to re-donate may or may not
be something you wanna do depending on the prize.
Yes.
Friend of the podcast, Dave Coxon,
and I once wore the Dr. Pepper underpants
because they are large enough that you can fit one human man
in each leg.
And so there is a photo of the two of us
on Insta in these underpants.
We're fully clothed, obviously.
And therefore, in the show notes, yes.
Yes, we will link to it in the show notes
and we'll know what you could win.
And we are going to be recording live at Eastcon.
We've been recording at Monday at 1.30pm.
We are on the programme at 1.30pm in Devere on the Monday.
Oh, the other thing you could do to support the podcast
is vote for conversation 2023 for the Eastcon.
I hope you guys are voting for me.
Yeah, so.
(laughs)
I mean, it's an open vote,
like show of hands on the floor, right?
So Alice and Will know if we voted for her.
It's an open vote, show of hands on the floor, but I don't mind.
People are okay to vote for the other bit.
I don't have a problem with it.
We're basically offering a completely different choice for Eastcon.
So.
Do we know it's an open show of hands?
Because I've never been to a contested recession
and I don't know what they are like.
Back in the day, it was an open show of hands.
And then if it is not obvious which bid is won,
it is then taken to a lobby vote like Parliament.
You actually walk through the door and somebody counts you.
You might very well think that a serpentine
would be a better way to do it and you would be right.
But that's how it's done.
It's done as a show of hands and if it's not obvious,
it's a lobby vote.
And it might even be eyes and nays, but I think it's show of hands.
Because eyes and nays don't aren't public, right?
Well, yeah, but they also privilege people with louder voices,
whereas a hand only privilege people who have two hands.
Do I have a problem with?
Do I have? Yeah, but I mean, obviously we have a...
Yes, you do, Alice, and you have a principled problem.
Are you saying I have loud voice privilege, John?
Does anybody else on this podcast have loud voice privilege?
The entire podcast?
Anyway, I was not...
I was saying other people are free to vote for whatever they want,
but what I'm saying is if John and I vote against Alice,
and she will know.
Yeah, I will know and I won't mind. It's fine.
And also, another way you can support this podcast
at the bidding session is by voting for EasterCon 2024.
I do want to say something about...
I am very excited that the three of us will be at EasterCon together.
It's something I have been hoping to do for a long time,
and it's really good.
And this podcast is dropping on Maundy Thursday,
so lots and lots of people are going to be listening.
Well, being a bit sad, they can't be at EasterCon,
but there's some virtual stuff, and I think we'll be live streamed.
So I think Octa Thought Live is probably going to be live streamed.
Live, Octa Thought Live, yeah.
Yeah, Octa Thought Live, actually live, and also recorded.
So the Hugo Award finalists are out.
Do we think there is a clear influence of the Chinese supporting members
for Ch icon on those nominations?
I confess I can't see anything that I am surprised
is on the ballot from an Anglo-centric perspective.
So my inclination is that it has not necessarily had the big effect
we expected it might.
What do you two think?
The only thing I did wonder about was the Korean film Space Sweepers,
which is not necessarily...
It's a bit of a surprise on the best dramatic presentation.
Ballot is not a huge surprise.
I'm looking forward to watching it because I haven't done that.
The only person I knew was watched it is Fran,
because Fran watches everything.
Well done Fran, but she's my only letterboxed friend who's seen it so far.
I'm sure I'll watch it in the next little bit,
but I didn't see any Chinese.
It looked like it's a really good ballot.
It's full of lovely things, and I'm not just saying that because I'm on it.
I'm going to push back slightly on the Space Sweepers thing
in that Space Sweepers came out on Netflix, right?
I'm not sure you can officially watch Netflix in China.
Oh, that's interesting.
So it probably represents no Chinese influence whatsoever there.
Alissa talks total ballocks again.
Can you believe it, listeners?
Well, I think you may have fallen into the risk of saying, you know,
something which is it is the only kind of non-U.S. nominee, I guess,
non-U.S. or UK possibly.
But I think that just reflects people watching a bit more widely
and not necessarily a particular country's influence.
I think you could well be...
I understand why I also called it out because I do think,
like, I think a lot of Chinese fans do have the ability to watch things
that are not officially available in China.
But I will say that especially Korean science fiction seems
to be having a real moment in Anglo-speaking countries at the moment,
like, 'cause Squid Game, I think, did a lot to promote Korean.
Especially, I suppose not necessarily in books.
I haven't seen much by Korean authors outside of Clark's World,
which has done a lot of Korean translation.
But certainly in terms of, like, film and TV, this interesting.
So yeah, I wonder whether this is the effect of Squid Game,
which I really liked.
I'm looking forward to watching The Movie.
And this year sees the youngest ever Hugo finalist.
Yes.
So congratulations to Laurel Iester, who is nominated in Best Fan Artist,
and is the youngest ever Hugo finalist, the Hugo nerds tell me.
I feel a bit aggrieved about this because back in the day,
when Plochtogot all its nominations,
it was not custom and practice to put everyone who was
a major part of the process of getting the fanzine together
on the list for the Hugo.
So Plochtogot just had the three main editors
and not the rest of the team.
But we were very much a team, and that included two babies and a cat.
One of my children would have been the youngest ever Hugo finalist.
And then we'd have had to argue whether cats can be Hugo finalists.
I think probably they shouldn't be, I think, that was bad.
But we could not have done the fanzine without them.
I think that's everything on Hugo's.
Is that everything on Hugo's?
Yeah, and I think I have any good, very happy,
do we say that pretty already?
Pinnings, we said that several times, I think.
Oh no, I have one more thing, tiny thing.
It's a new category for me, collecting categories.
I'm not as good as Sean and Maguire, who I think has just picked up a sixth.
The Hugo nerds will tell us.
I'm excited to read the fanzine.
I had not realized she had done a fanzine.
It's very rare that something comes up on the fanzine ballot that I had not,
like, any idea about, and so I am excited.
It's also fiction.
Quite unusual for fiction fanzines to get on the ballot.
Yes, no, and it's also very rare that fiction...
Congratulations, Sean and...
And yeah, I think that's a fifth category.
But anyway, so it's my best fan cast as my second category, and I am very excited.
Probably the sixth, isn't it?
Because I bet she's been in every single short fiction and long fiction category.
Oh, no, plus and series.
And series, but and best-related work.
So it's probably seven.
Yeah, no, so she's been nominated in novel novella.
I assume she's been nominated in novel yet, but that is an assumption.
Short story, best-related work, best series, and best fanzine.
Don't do a fan cast, Sean.
She, oh no, she was.
She won for fan cast in the first three years of the categories and all gradients.
She was on SF's Quee cast.
Sean and his clearly tried to get the entire set.
I mean, I respect that.
But no, yes, she won with Paul Cornell and other authors who temporarily escaped me for
SF's Quee cast way back in the start of the fan cast category.
They had a run of wins.
Also, we forgot best graphics story.
So...
So how is that?
Nellie?
I love count.
It's a lot.
Yeah, sure.
And if you're listening, do write in.
But congratulations for your nominations this year, especially for the Wayward Children series,
because I do love those books.
I was going to say on the Hugo's, I think it is nice to see that there are categories
where there are people who have been nominated for who were nominated again and have all done
good work.
But it is nice to see a few new people popping into each category, particularly, I think
there are three first-time nominees in Best Fan Writer this year.
Chris Barkley, Bito Corrala, and Alex Brown, the new people in Fan Artist, the new people
in Fanzine.
As we just said, we are new people in Fancast.
I think it's nice to see a little bit of turnover in some of these categories where you can have
some of the same nominees year after year, and sometimes they're very good work,
but it's nice to see other people getting nominated as well.
I think that's right.
I've to thought, Podcast Corner, I've been listening to Podcasts again.
And the podcast I've been listening to specifically is the Life Writing Podcast,
which comes from the team of Tana Reeve-Doo and Stephen Barnes, who are a husband and wife
writing team, and they have started a podcast where they give writing advice, they have interviews,
they are, and the reason I like it is, one, they have a very good rapport, as you would expect,
because they know each other so well, but that also carries over to their interviews,
where they obviously have great rapport with their interviewees.
And it is very much focused on writing, but I think a lot of the stuff they discuss and the
advice they give kind of applies to writing, but also to your non-writing life, and it's very
applicable to that.
And I would say Stephen Barnes in particular has some very insightful questions.
So I've been listening to that and enjoying that recently.
Cool.
Thank you, Liz.
No, and I think that sounds like a very good idea for a podcast.
So, hurrah.
It does sound good.
I mean, I listened to it because they had an interview with Brian Fuller, who I love of Hannibal,
and Pushing Gaze's, and Star Trek fame.
Yes, yes, fair enough.
In an excellent demonstration of how timely we are, we're going to pick up on the Brandon Sanderson
Kickstarter, which launched a few weeks ago, and which has rapidly become the most funded
project on the platform.
So yes, what do we think about this, Alison and Liz?
Well, first of all, I want to thank Alex Holden.
Mr. Holden makes exceedingly good concertinas for suggesting this topic.
So it's quite a funny Kickstarter video.
I'm sure everybody who listens to this podcast has already heard about it now,
but if you haven't, go and stop the podcast now.
Go watch the Kickstarter video, which is quite funny, and we're going to spoil it now, so then
you can come back.
He basically said, "I have to confess something."
There's a lot of lockdown professionals, and the thing I am confessing is that I accidentally wrote
four extra novels in lockdown.
He actually wrote five, but there are four in the Kickstarter, and the Kickstarter is a new way to
buy novels by Brandon Sanderson, and you can also pay extra money.
If you don't just want a load of novels from Brandon, you can also get a load of extra things,
like I don't know, T-shirts and other merchandise objects, and it's all secret, so you can get like
a Brandon Sanderson subscription box arriving in your post every week month,
I don't think it's a month, and they did $41 million.
I mean, I'm not sure.
I want a subscription box from anyone once a month, and if I think about who I might want one for,
none of the people that come to mind are science fiction authors, so yeah.
But on this topic, if you're interested in an octa-thaw-once-a-month subscription box,
do let us know.
It will contain a piece of weterbicks and a ribbon every month until we run out of weterbicks and
ribbons. Look, you can get different flavours of weterbicks.
Yeah, but we're not going to be putting that level of effort in this and please disregard Liz's
attempt to make this more interesting.
Sorry, I mean, you could get-
You could get different flavours of weterbicks.
Weterbicks comes in two flavours which are weterbicks and abominations.
Okay, so the month's Alison is in charge of the box.
You get original weterbicks only, and the month's Alison is in charge of the box.
Do you get weterbicks abomination?
Liz, do you have any thoughts about this?
Yes, so I thought it was very interesting because I saw the numbers going up on the kickstarter,
but I would never imagine it would get to $41 million.
So I'm just going to set again, because I need to set a few times for it to sink in.
$41 million, but I think it's very interesting.
So Brandon Sanderson has written a very long blog post about it, which we will link to.
But I think some of the main issues are that it's clear that Brandon Sanderson-
it is not just Brandon Sanderson himself getting $1.41 million.
This is Brandon Sanderson essentially using these $41 million to be his own
Brandon Sanderson publishing house in a way.
And it's clear that what he wants is partly to see if they could do this,
but also to show that for him there is a viable option,
you know, should Amazon, which represents the lion's share of his sales, go away.
And also it's to demonstrate to his publishers that actually there is an appetite,
you know, an appetite for buying things in these different formats,
because you know, it is $41 million, but he has 23,000 people who pledged $500,
you know, to get the swag boxes and all the premium hardbacks and the audiobooks and the ebooks.
You know, so clearly there is a significant market of people out there who just want
the ebooks from him, but also a large chunk of people who are happy to pay extra for things like
premium hardcover books and signed premium hardcover books.
And I think it really shows that there is an appetite for books from him.
Okay, I'm going to bring us a box of weirderbicks to sign.
So I think this is really interesting because I think there are, especially in the pandemic,
there is a growing awareness that a lot of the people whose media I consume are very precarious,
and this is something I've been noticing, especially in the podcasting scene,
but I imagine it also extends to authors, which is that like as kind of,
especially in podcasting, as advertising money has been drying up during COVID,
many of them have been moving towards models where you can support them directly.
And I do think that what we're seeing here is a lot of people who are like, well,
Brandon Sanderson is my favorite author by a very long way,
and this is a way that I can both support him and get loads of swag.
I can't get anywhere else into the deal.
And there are quite a few podcasts I support where I'm like, I could not support them.
Like, I don't necessarily need to, but I like supporting them and like getting the exclusives
is a nice kind of thing into the bargain.
So I do wonder how many of the people supporting are just kind of huge fans who are keen to support
him as an independent artist.
I mean, that is true.
Although I would say if you wish, like, if you're picking authors who you wish to support so that
they can continue making a viable living at it, you probably wouldn't start with Brandon Sanderson,
who is quite clear about his sales and so on on the blog posts.
And he's saying that he sells 350,000 copies in week one of his books.
So if you are supporting people, then Brandon Sanderson is probably not at the top of the list
of people who are going to have a problem with the Kickstarter support.
While that is true, I do pre-order.
So like, there are authors I know who are not, who are kind of like mid-list authors who I love
who are on support and I pre-order their books.
But like, so one good example is Dan Moran, I pre-order all his books, but like, he does not
have the ability to do this.
So like, on the one hand, you wouldn't necessarily choose to do it with Sanderson, but on the other
hand, like, it's not like there were 20 Kickstarter's by a bunch of authors and I got to pick which one.
And so that's part of the problem here.
I think...
Except that Sanderson was also slightly surprised by how successful this Kickstarter was.
He was not expecting it to do $41 million and one of the ways they have given back.
And I think this is very meritorious, really, is that they went, there's a video of this too
that we can also put you the show notes.
They went and backed every Kickstarter in the publishing category on Kickstarter,
as a way of saying thank you.
So there are probably, I'm certain that there are a lot of very small authors whose life is
precarious, who got a little bit more money because Braddison D'Sonderson A) went and
supported them, and B) did a video about it so that his 350,000 followers, or however many,
will all have gone and seen all of those other Kickstarter's in the publishing category and they
will also have got some love, I should think.
So I mean, I basically think Braddison D'Sonderson is a jolly good egg.
I was a bit worried that Tor might be very upset by all of this, but apparently Tor are quite thrilled,
I have been told not by the way anyone at Tor.
Tor believes that the people who backed this Kickstarter are often going to go and buy Braddison D'Sonderson's
backlist, which is all on Tor.
- If you are someone who, yeah, if you're publishing things that have Braddison D'Sonderson written on them,
you must have been quite happy that Braddison D'Sonderson was in the news a lot for the last six weeks.
That's gotta be reflecting well on your bottom line as well as on everyone else's.
- I should probably read some Sondison, but I feel like I've always thought everything about it
is maybe think it's the sort of thing I absolutely hate.
- You would hate it, yeah, correct.
- Yeah, okay.
- I won't then, but it seems like a really nice bloke in lots of ways.
- What I hate it, John.
- I don't know.
You like some things, but you don't like other things and I sometimes find it difficult to predict
which edge of the line you'll be on.
- True of most predictions.
- Basically, if you want to read a series of 10 novels which comprise 2 million words,
Alison, then I may have misjudged your taste in literature,
because I think that sounds like what you would like is all of that character development and
plot to be in a tight 40,000 word novella.
And I don't know how you'd achieve that, but I think that's what you'd want.
- I'd want you to not have any extraneous words.
He also has very good advice.
He does stuff about how to write and how to do hard things that is very interesting because he
repudiates the notion that writers are people who cannot do anything else but write,
and he is a big fan of the notion that if you want to be a science fiction writer,
you should sit down and write every day.
And I would endorse that sort of approach to doing anything that is hard.
And I think he's, so I think his advice on how to become good at things is also,
is also quite good.
So clever boy.
And he's also very rich now, which is nice.
I guess he runs a bit organization big enough to have an HR director.
Is that what you said, Liz?
- Yes, he's basically got, I mean, to fulfill this Kickstarter,
he's basically going to have a small publishing outfit that he runs.
So yes, I think the 41 million is, he's going to do well off it,
but it's also going to be split a lot of ways,
I mean, essentially funding a small company from it.
- Well, and also, I think, like, his stated reasons in his blog post
is like to try and reduce the dominance that Amazon has on his career,
as Liz was mentioning earlier.
And there's also the potential that if his publishing venture goes well enough for him,
he might start being able to sort of publish things by kind of other authors.
And so this is potentially very exciting.
And in general, I think it's also quite exciting that the biggest Kickstarter of all time
is for a bunch of books and book-related merchandise in our genre.
That is, I think, a huge thing that I'm very excited about,
because it shows that there's potentially a lot of life there,
and it's just nice to be in a scene that is kind of growing and has enthusiasm.
And I think this Kickstarter shows that those things are true.
And yeah, I think Sanderson increasing the profile of our little slice of life
can only be a good thing, said like a true optimist.
- Yeah, it's particularly good, because some of the other biggest
Kickstarter of all time are for vaporware nonsense.
So, I mean, I'm fairly sure Bradessad and Sanderson will actually deliver on his Kickstarter.
- That is the other thing.
Like, this isn't the laser shaving blade.
I mean, full disclosure, I don't think any of us back the Kickstarter.
I'm just going to buy the ebooks when they come out in the shops.
- Yeah, I thought about buying the e-book one, actually, but I'll probably just get the ebooks.
If I decide I like Bradessad and Sanderson by then, which I probably won't.
- I mean, to be fair, I'll probably just borrow them from the library, but, you know.
- Let's do picks.
- My pick is Arosums Universal Robots, which is, of course, the play from 1921 by Carl Schappec,
that in veg is the word "robots" though the robots in the play are not, in fact,
robots in the way that we normally think about them because they are grown from flesh in a
rather horrible way.
My picks not the play itself, which is problematic in a few ways, but the new Radio 4 production of
it on Radio 4's play for today, I guess, but I'd play for this week anyway, or now I think they
just go, "Well, we've got a podcast that we put plays in it."
But this isn't Octa-Thought podcast corner because radio shows and radio shows and
podcasts and podcasts are very different.
Anyway, it is a Radio 4 production where they have dealt with the problematic nature of this
play by making it a musical comedy.
And it's quite good.
And it's the first episode was "Come to Days ago" and it's on Radio 4, and we will put a link
in the show notes.
And then I think the next one's later today, and I think it might only be a two-part
production, but it's actually very hard to tell on the BBC website whether it's two parts or
seven parts, and they should think about that.
BBC, if you're listening, we could tell you a thing or two about producing audio shows.
Not really.
I think this ego nomination has gone to your head here, Alison.
But I really like it.
Rossims Universal Robots, and it's good stuff.
It's on BBC Sound, so it might be available worldwide.
Yeah, and this is on BBC Sound, so if you have access to that, you can get it there.
My pick is a book, and it may even tie an unexpectedly to our Brandon Sanderson discussion.
So my pick is a book called "Based Notes" by Lara Elaina.
Donne Lee, and it is about Vic, a perfumer who has discovered the secret of making perfumes,
which will perfectly recreate a memory for the person who experienced that memory.
So essentially you sniff this scent and you experience a perfect recreation of a memory.
The catch is that in order to do this, one of the ingredients for the perfume has to be taken
from the dead body of one of the people in the memory.
So it is essentially about Vic, who is, you know, so the protagonist throughout this book is a
serial killer. They have murdered multiple people and will go on to kill more.
So it is quite, you know, it's quite dark, it's quite depressing from that sense.
And I have to enjoy the first part more where it is them meeting a bunch of people and kind of
coming up with a plot for the latest perfume than from the latest stage of the book, which
do involve basically a lot of killing, which escalates as like they've gone closer and closer
to being discovered. But it's also, it's other aspect is it's all set in kind of, it's New York
and it's, you know, Vic is a perfumer and the other people involved, you know, there's a barber,
there's a kind of a bar tender and a tailor. And it is all about the sector of society who are
kind of creative people who on the surface, into making a reasonable living, but really they're
just sort of clinging, clinging on to being able to afford to have this life, to have an apartment,
to be creative. And they are pitted against essentially a large, you know, business corporation
that they get entangled with. And that's why they're making these perfumes, you know. So it's
basically sort of like the precarious millennials and gensette of New York versus the big corporations
who are basically destroying that. So I thought there was a really interesting angle to it. And
it's a very like evocative book. It is full of descriptions of sense and how they are made and
kind of everyone seems to be, you know, a lot of stuff is identified by Cent and it's clear that
Vic has a real passion for perfume outside their other, you know, murderous inclinations. So I
quite enjoyed it. There's a very famous book called Perfume by Patrick Susskind, which is about
somebody who, well, it doesn't have the entire thing of this, but it has some of the features in common
and everyone is kind of like, well, this is a novel that is not like any other novels. So,
but this novel does sound like it might be a novel that's a bit like perfume.
Yeah, so I have not read perfume, just looking up, it does sound like it could be
a little bit similar or inspired by it. Yes. I mean, it's obviously quite different, but I mean,
it feels like, I mean, obviously there's no new under the sun, but perfume is,
it sounds like it might have been one of the antecedents for this book, one of the things that
made the author think that this might be an interesting book to write. Yeah. And the other
thing, when you were talking about it, it did sound like our hero is a creative New York
professional who is clinging onto his lifestyle and is also a serial killer. And that's kind of odd.
I am, can I have to look it up? It sounds cool. The protagonists of bass notes are no pronouns
are ever used for them and their gender is kind of never, you know, it is never explicitly stated.
There's kind of, you know, some comments on, you know, fitting, fitting suits to their shape and
things like that, but it's never explicitly gender. But it's interesting because I noticed that when
Alison replied to me, you said he, I think there's an assumption that serial, I'm very sorry,
that's because historically 99% of serial killers are men. Exactly. I think there's an
assumption, it was interesting that there is an assumption that serial killer novels are always
about men. And in this case, it is, you know, really, really left ambiguous. And it's mentioned
that they present in a very androgynous manner. So I thought that was very interesting.
I had an argument with a friend once, because we read Scalzi's novel where Scalzi uses a similar
trick, it's all in the first person. And the protagonist is never gendered by people they're
talking to, she never know what gender they are. And the character was called Chris. And so my
friends were like, oh, you know, he, this, he, that. And I said, oh, that's interesting, because
like, you know, they're not gender, and they looked at me and they were like, oh, well, but that's
not because we have underlying assumptions, it's because Chris is a boy's name. And I was like,
your girlfriend is literally called Chris. So like, yeah, there is that.
That's quite good. And that's actually really interesting. That makes me want to read it a whole
bunch more. So it's going on the list. That is interesting. Especially it's interesting in the
context of perfume, because for anyone who doesn't know, perfumes are one of the more gender things
in the world, and they're trying to, and have always been, it's not that they kind of went,
or we can sell twice as much perfume if we, if we gender it is always been gendered.
And so they're just trying now trying to find some gender neutral perfumes and doing it, I think,
because you know, then they can sell three times the many perfumes. So they're quite happy with that.
I will link to in the show notes, a regular view on tour.com by Lee Mandela that discusses
some of the gender aspects in more detail. I thought it's very good.
Cool. Thank you very much. Liz, my pick is Moon Knight.
But it's not the Disney series. It is the six issue run, which was written by Warren Ellis,
Declan Shelby, and Jordy Belair back in 2014 and 15. It is volume seven of Moon Knight, and it is
a six issue run that Ellis wrote, and each issue is kind of a standalone story in a larger anthology.
It was my sort of, it was my introduction to the character. I heard about the character first on
the incomparable superhero, superhero tournament that they did one summer, which was nonsense and
very fun, and I enjoyed very much. And Moon Knight got surprisingly far in that tournament.
It made me laugh a lot, so I decided to seek him out. And this little trade paperback is very,
very good. Unfortunately, it is on Amazon, 978 pounds and 99p for the paperback.
But if you're willing to read it in electronic form, it's 3.90. And I recommend reading it
electronically. I mean, apologies to anyone who likes physical books, but you know,
it's not worth 1000, but it's just isn't. But it is definitely worth 3.19, and I would
highly recommend going and looking it up. Is that the bit of Moon Knight that is forming the
plot that they're nicking for the TV show, or is that going to be totally different?
No, it's because it's not a single thread. It's sort of more of an anthology.
Issue seven and onwards of that volume were written by a different author, and that was much more
kind of traditional story. But I thought that was not quite as strong as the earlier bits.
I've put a link in the show notes.
So I can go and get it for 3.90.
Yes, or you can subscribe to Marvel Unlimited. Marvel Unlimited is amazing. You pay $69 a year,
and you get infinite comic comics. I read a lot of comics on Marvel Unlimited.
Yeah, I had Marvel Unlimited for $1, lot of $69. And I basically bazed in comics for about
three weeks and then realised that I was a bit fed up comics and never picked stuff again.
So I need to... It's clearly something I just want to actually take for a month every so often.
That was the Octa Thor podcast, and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me. And it's goodbye from me.
So I feel like you're in the stage of life where you're still going.
If I read two million words, if I read some people I like, and then there's two million words of it,
that's two million words of stuff I like. And I'm in the stage of life where I go.
I have X number of books left in my life and every single one of them has to add value all
of the time. I mean, there are lots of long books. I mean, I don't... I would say I generally don't
like long books, but the expanse. But I mean, I liked Anna Karenina a lot, and I'll talk about
why. And I'll intend you to read War and Peace at some point. That's pretty long.
Because Anna Karenina was so fantastic. My Latin teacher espoused all the things she liked about it,
and she was like, "It's so good because Tolstoy, like you're exploring a convoy." And then he's like,
"Oh, now I'm going to go over here and spend 100 pages telling you about this peasant." And I'm like,
"Oh my God, no, that sounds awful." Tolstoy does go off topic. It is quite true.
You're saying we are the Tolstoy of podcasts? I don't want anyone to think we're comparing
ourselves favorably to Tolstoy. We do a better top podcast than Tolstoy ever did. I'm 99% satisfied.
That's that. This is when you find out there's like,
Wack Cylinders Alison, and he had like a weekly radio show. Weekly Cylinders Show.
Okay, you're at your grasp of history. It's not great, is it? Wack Cylinders were around in the
late 1800s and Tolstoy died in 1910. Okay, so maybe there is Tolstoy, Wack Cylinders, sorry.
Is that did you do a podcast? I mean, write in listeners. If you're an expert in Tolstoy's podcasting
career, please let us know. Tolstoy actually wrote letters by dictating them onto Wack Cylinders
because he found it faster than writing. So he basically, he was the Christopher J. Garcia
of his day. Look, look, look. I've got a link for the show notes. I mean, it's in Russian, but you
know. Well, this is excellent. I wasn't expecting my offhand mention that Tolstoy might have done a
podcast to go this way, but a rah. The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin
McLeod in Competec.com used under a Creative Commons attribution 4.0 license. This podcast will
end at the beep. Beep.
[BLANK_AUDIO]