Oh, she gone again.
Gone again.
I think you should put all the... she's gone again together for the end of the podcast.
Hello everyone and welcome to the 14th episode of Oxford Thore by a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom.
This is the episode for the 17th of September 2020.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
We have had a plethora of letters of comment since the last time we recorded.
Okay, so I've talked to you about plethora before, John.
It's not a word that means many.
It's a word that means too many.
And we haven't really had a plethora of locks.
We have had a sufficiency, a delightful collection of locks.
Many of you have written.
But it's not a plethora because when you have a plethora of courgettes, it is a word that means glott.
Whoa! No one could ever possibly have too many courgettes, Alison.
Have you ever grown courgettes, John?
No.
Right. There we go then.
Yes, we have.
We got one single entirely spherical courgette.
It was magical.
A perfectly round courgette.
I say I grew it.
It's spanyate grow it.
I watched.
Yes. So another year.
So what's your courgettes really?
Once you get the hang of it, you will have a year.
I went to a gig once where the guy stood on stage and said,
"And if you buy a CD, everyone who buys a CD gets a free bag of courgettes."
That's a good deal. That's just a good deal.
I will note that we recorded for, I think, approximately 35 seconds
before we delved into a rabbit hole of courgettes and folk music,
which is pretty good for us, I think.
According to my dictionary app, Alison,
strictly a plethora is not just an abundance of something,
but it is an excessive amount.
However, the new looser sense is now so dominant that it must be regarded
as part of standard English.
Yeah, well, just because your dictionary app isn't...
We're upholding Fowler's standards or whatever.
Hey, I'm a...
I'm a descriptivist. Not a prosperous tourist.
I mean, you know, words change.
I understand that the...
I just don't feel that... I feel that when you use plethora,
quite a lot of people will take the negative meaning
along with the positive one.
Whereas there are other words that have just kind of...
float happily into the language and nobody has a problem with them anymore.
I mean, nobody... people who still complain about the use of the word,
hopefully, to mean, "I hope that I feel...
I feel those people have lost."
But I think those of us who are still arguing about plethora are gonna...
Anyway, we have not in fact had a plethora of locks, so please write in.
We have had a myriad of letters of comment.
Mira's good. That probably means more than four.
Let me double check.
According to my dictionary app,
myriad is... er... a noun.
A countless or extremely great number of people or things.
One, too many lots.
This is a myriad.
Countless.
My dictionary also says that,
although Tiefling classical history, it was a unit of 10,000.
And we have not had that meaning number of locks yet.
We haven't had that many listeners, frankly.
No.
Somebody said on Zoom that they really enjoyed "Octe Thorp"
and waxed poetic about how marvelous it was for some time,
but I can't remember who it was.
Is that a dream you had?
Er... you know, okay, I've been having some weird dreams recently.
Okay.
So if it was you, then please write and tell us,
because telling me that you liked the podcast in Zoom,
while very gratifying, does nothing for my co-host.
We also had a discord, er... mention of comment, I guess.
So you can add that into the myriad pile.
Yay!
Who was our discord mention of comment, Liz?
Our discord mention of comment was from Listen A Chance,
who said "excellent trashing of the MCU".
And this is the sort of comment that means we do not want to pivot
into being an MCU podcast.
We would alienate at least one listener and one co-host.
Thank you very much to Listen A Chance for writing in.
And frankly, we cannot afford to lose any listeners or co-host.
No, no we cannot.
The second letter of comment out of our new five is Mark Plummer,
who felt guilty that he had only written last episode
with a pedantic correction and said
that Octa thought is a really good thing generally.
And he said he agreed with Liz about NASVIC panels
on researching the Golden Age, and he agreed with Alison
about there shouldn't be anything about the NASVIC
in the Wispers Constitution.
And then he said that he was sure he must agree with me
about something, but he can't think what it is.
So thanks, Mark.
That made me feel nice.
Oh, and also he wrote in to correct us because panels
from the NASVIC are available online.
I think I did link them in last episode's show notes,
but basically there are a couple of videos on Vimeo,
which appear to be all of the panels just in what long video.
So we will link those again in the show notes this week.
He thought we were marvelous.
I mean, more people could write to say how good we are
and not argue.
Liz is nodding contentedly.
Yeah, I like all that as a comment that say
you're really good and I agree with you.
Please send them all in.
Lillian writes in and says that no one needs ten minutes for a poo.
Lillian is a thing. I think wrong.
I mean, I think I'll go with nobody should need ten minutes
for their poo.
And quite a lot of people seem to need more time for a poo
than they ought to.
But, you know, don't write in.
I will say that to be honest, I have not made a habit
of timing my bowel movements.
And I think that way lies nothing good and I will not be doing it.
And she also writes in about Gathertown saying
that it's the state of the art right now for virtual drinks.
It seems quite good.
It's based on Jitsi, I think.
Jitsi is doing the underlying bits of the video.
I would like us to practice with Gathertown and High Fidelity,
both of which I quite like.
And it feels like you could have a model where you used Gathertown
for your...
Either Gathertown or High Fidelity for your general
milling about space for a virtual event before
actually putting people into zooms for more serious matters or stuff.
I saw a mention somewhere on Facebook,
and I will try and find out where that zoom was going to let you
choose your own breakout room soon.
Really?
That would be very good.
It was from Tammy Coxen on the Joff Facebook group saying
that you can now create...
Host can create breakout rooms and participants can decide
which breakout room they want to join.
This is a feature that should have been implemented just from a
professional perspective a while back because there are multiple
kind of informal workshops where you do rotate between breakout
rooms and that is a desirable thing to do.
So I am a little bit surprised to take them this long, but I'm
glad that they're now getting around to it.
So she also mentioned zoom fatigue.
I think that is a very real thing.
I have...
I canceled plans yesterday because I was like,
I could spend more time on my computer, like talking to my
friends, or I could sit in the garden and read a book with my
cats and the garden sounded better.
And I think it is tricky.
I am learning that although I crave social interaction,
I also crave time away from screens more than I did pre-lockdown.
And so I am finding that that is an interesting balancing act.
And the way I'm basically doing it is less sort of...
I kind of mostly do one zoom at the weekends usually, but then
like the rest of the weekend is spent doing more physical
things in the real world.
And then during the week I then spent a lot of time on my
computer.
How are you two finding that kind of division?
If I ever run an online convention, I'll want to make sure that
some of the activities require the members to do some things that
aren't just sitting at their computer.
I want to build in physical activity that's a bit like the
pool tournaments or dots tournaments or hanging out at the
garden type things that small, famished conventions have
traditionally had.
So that, I mean November is not the perfect time, but we should
be trying to make sure that some of the activities that the
convention require you to do things that aren't actually at your
desk in order to get the most fun out of the con.
Like, I don't know, scavenger hunt or local...
Or like a show and tell where you tell them on Friday to go out
to the local neighborhood and take some photographs or video of
something of interest and then we'll have a program item where
everyone comes and talks about those things for two minutes each.
It's that sort of... you actually have to physically go and do
a thing that gets you off your backside.
We had a letter of comment from Karen Schafer who wrote to us
about a Liberty puzzle of Barcelona she offered her birthday,
which she completed while listening to our podcast.
She is now very sad because she has finished the puzzle and
run out of octa-thorp.
So we are rectifying one of these problems for you, Karen,
right here.
So, hurrah!
And thank you for listening.
She also assumes there must have been SF conventions of Barcelona
and indeed the 2016 Eurocon was held at Barcelona.
I've put a blog post from Ian Watson who I think was involved
on the committee of that convention in the show notes.
I've also put a link to the Liberty puzzle, Karen did,
which looks beautiful.
It's a wooden jigsaw puzzle and you kind of...
*sings*
Each of the landmarks and kind of people is at its own bit of wood.
So even if you deconstruct the puzzle, you still have like all
of the pieces.
It's really, really beautiful.
Oh, it really is pretty.
It is a very pretty puzzle.
I really like it.
Turn out a 10.
It's beautiful.
I was like, I'm not going to puzzles.
I have got slightly into doing paint by numbers,
which is light painting, but doesn't require me to have any
artistic ability, accept the ability to read a number and
stick within the lines.
And I think it's probably going to take me several hundred hours
to complete it.
So I find it quite a gentle thing to do while listening to
podcasts or watching the TV.
I do do jigsaw puzzles, but I have a strict...
You may not buy another jigsaw puzzle until you have done
all the jigsaw puzzles.
And I also have a lack of space in my not very big house in
which to do jigsaw puzzles.
And I'm kind of looking at the absolute acres of crap piled up
in this room and going, I'm pretty sure there may be
some solutions involved throwing out a lot of this stuff.
And then we would have more space.
Which is actually the nice thing about paint by numbers is
they take much, much, much longer than a jigsaw puzzle,
but take up about the same amount of space as a jigsaw puzzle.
Finally, a letter from Eispania Cheriff,
odd name.
She says that a lot of what we mentioned for tealers is
true of the art show as well, and talks about kind of technical
issues and the huge variability of how art shows have been done
at conventions, and then talks about discoverability and
promotion as well like we did.
And then mentions that FutureCon is coming up September
17th to 20th, and I have put a link to that in the show notes.
And also notes that we might want to add the Octa Torp email
address to our Facebook and Twitter because she couldn't find
it until I told her to check the show notes.
So yes, I don't know who's in charge of those things.
I don't think it's me.
I think Octa thought, well I think I've invited you to be
your own admin, you both to be admins of the Facebook page,
but yeah, I'll put it on the, um, remind me.
I could theoretically do that right now.
And I will put it on the Twitter's.
I told her to put it at the end of the lock so I could ask you
to do it because I didn't want to.
Because I'm a champ.
Um, but yes.
Um, so yeah, thank you very much to everyone who wrote in with locks.
They were lovely.
Um, I do know that obviously we always like hearing that we're
right about everything and they were great.
So if you think that, please do tell us in writing.
Um, and also if you have any more poetry, um, yeah.
I mean, the poems this week were very good, but they were less
rhyme focused than previous poems have been and mostly very
prosy on balance.
That didn't work.
No, I'm not sure that was funny.
Were there any poems?
No, that was his joke.
It was a joke.
Oh, so that was like one of these things that has the accident
of a joke, but not actually the substance of it.
F*** it out.
Excellent.
Jesus.
[Music]
Can I also say that FutureCon looks really good and I already love
them because they list the times of their panel in like seven
time zones and so I do not have to go and get a time zone.
Couldn't hurt it.
Well, I do, but only to work out which one is closest to me so I
can take an hour off.
So I already like that.
I got in trouble of a discord I am a member of because I said,
why don't they just do what my Arkham Horror Convention did,
which is to convert it into the time zone according to your IP
address and I got a shout-out at because apparently that's evil,
but it was very useful and I think more conventions should do it.
It is very useful, but it actually has a very weird, there's a
weird side effect for it, which is, but the NASFIC had an
unofficial connapass like thing of their schedule and what,
you know, connapass is just like a nicely laid out web version of a
program, but the thing it does is it automatically picks up your
time zone, presumably from your IP or whatever, maybe from your
browser and then tries to tell you what items are coming up shortly,
but it doesn't convert the actual time zone.
So what would happen is it would try and show me remaining program
items that were going to happen in my time zone, which because I was
actually looking at schedule where all the times of 12 hours behind
because it was an American one was nothing and then show me nothing.
Yeah, that doesn't, that isn't how I would implement the feature.
No, it was, it was broken in a really weird way, but probably no one
has thought about the problem of what if someone is looking at the con
schedule in a different time zone when it's something that was
basically implemented for physical conventions.
When I started my business, one of the things I discovered very
early on is that in the sort of long lists of things that no tech
companies do very well, it turns out that time zones breaks all
sorts of platforms in all sorts of ways all over the world, all the
time and huge and it turns out that, that and currency conversion
are just vastly more complicated than you would ever believe
possible for something that's just, that looks quite simple, but is also
assuming that the work week runs Monday to Friday isn't actually
true in quite a lot of countries. Yes, we're also assuming that the
weekends, the, the, assuming that the week starts on a Sunday, even that
isn't true in the UK, like, because we start the week on a Monday and the
US starts their week on the Sunday, which is weird, I don't understand
why that is different, but it is. So yeah, there's a lot of assumptions
about time. It is tradition. This is another old people thing, it is
traditional for the week started Sunday in Britain. On Thursday, if you're at
Cambridge University. And all of this stuff, but the thing about time zones
and money is that even, even not allowing for weird assumptions about how
things work that are wrong or not, not universal enough. Time zones, the
business of dealing with time zones breaks websites. They don't cope
with things that are in one day for one for a user and a different
day for the platform. And every time you mention this, people are like,
oh, and it is because most tech companies are run by a bunch of
bros who live in California and haven't really ever lived anywhere else,
especially anywhere else that's more than three time zones away.
There might be some truth to that, but I'm also pretty sure that like
Apple and Google and Microsoft hire quite widely internationally. So I
am wondering to what extent that is quite as true as it might be. I think
like having done some work with time as my day job, it is surprisingly
difficult to do on computers because it's non regular and computers like
nice regular things. It's a similar reason to why translation of language is so
hard because it's working out how to do certain things which are incredibly
difficult and incredibly not strictly logical and computers are bad at that
generally. So it might be that it is also a difficult problem. I will say about
future con that there doesn't seem to be any social plan beyond we have a
discord, so it doesn't address any of the problems you have previously noted
with conventions, Alison, and it probably means I won't attend either because
as mentioned, or previous episodes for me, conventions are predominantly social
spaces. And if a convention has a strong social space like regular parties and
Zoom hangouts, then I'm much more likely to attend than I am if it's a
discord with lots of panels because I don't find that as engaging. Yeah, no, I
agree. So please people go out there and run small conventions that are mostly
focused on creating social spaces for people who are interesting to chat to.
I think that's true, but I think also the problem is if you're explicitly
running a convention where you are trying to say, you know, have two blocks of
panels so that basically the whole world can get to warm up other of those panels.
There then probably isn't a lot of space to do social spaces that would be in a
time zone for everyone and then you have to make a choice about which time zones
is your social time accessible to, you know, if you're doing it on a weekday,
the main at very much point about having social stuff that takes place at 2pm
to a lot of people. I think it is quite tricky. It's the state of mind that says
that having panels is a critical part of having conventions and cannot be
discarded, but having a functioning social space is a nice to have. Now for me,
that's the other way around. Yes, for me too. I have gone to conventions that
have had no programming whatsoever and they've been fun. I mean, and there is
a question about what constitutes a convention with no programming that is
different from a bunch of mates meeting up for a weekend. They are making
assumptions about the core of a convention which are not the assumptions
that are true for me, which is fine because there will be people for whom
those assumptions are true and that's the audience they're appealing to. But I think
as a member of fandom who is not in that audience, I don't think there's any
point of pretending that I am. So clearly there needs to be a primarily
focused convention quite soon. When I was trying to understand why there aren't
Zoom parties happening alongside the panels, because then if I was a
slot where I wasn't bothered about, I'd go into the parties. It doesn't seem
like a difficult problem to solve to me and maybe I'm just not thinking about it
properly, but like you just have parties and then people will be in the parties who
want to be in the parties and people who watch the panels who want to watch the panels.
I think that's fine, but I think this is, it feels like this is in some ways
explicitly pushing back against the trend for conventions to be not more
accessible but less accessible to a lot of people in the world. And so they've chosen
that as the thing they're explicitly going to try and mitigate against with this
comp. Is it your perspective that it wouldn't be possible to do a convention that was
accessible that had accessible social spaces? No, I think my position is that
the vast majority of online events so far have catered primarily to mostly
US time zones and sometimes from European time zones. And what they've done is
decided what we're going to focus on is trying to have something which feels truly
worldwide and their focus is therefore to get a set of panels together which are
running times that are a bit more accessible to people around the world.
And I don't think they're that interested in doing the social space that goes with
them. But I think also when you have probably limited time windows to do things
in, they've decided the best thing to do is to put panels in those time windows
and to have a discord to be their social space. Because for a lot of people I think
discord would work as a social space. I think that's what Alison and I said we
are aware but that is because they're prioritising panels. I think they could
have done an accessible international convention where they prioritise social
space and that would also have worked. And I think the fact they haven't done
that is a valid point to criticise them on. Yeah, no, I agree. Yeah, and also I feel
like it's not impossible to have global party spaces because New Zealand having
although we were quite skeptical about their plan to run parties for three
hours every eight hours, that did actually work perfectly well. And most people,
most places in the world could get to one of those party blocks or a second one if
they were properly into parties or a third one if they were really far more into
parties than was good for them. And I think having a kind of limited length to
the parties also worked quite well because there is a tendency for international
Zoom parties to go on forever in a way that is less fun than you would think
if you're the host. Ask me how I know this. Yeah, I think that is probably fair.
But I think you have said a few times Alison that you think the best model for
this kind of thing is to do sort of five hours of panels and three hours of
social spaces and that allows most people worldwide to access at least two of the
three kind of blocks. And I think in general if I was going to try and do this
kind of thing that is the kind of model I would take. I think BaltaCon kind of did
this but they forgot the parties afterwards and just did the five hours of
programming which was my criticism. That was, I don't think you mean BaltaCon
do you mean reconvene? Yes, I mean reconvene. Yes. And I think it would have been,
I just, yeah, like I said, I think there's not enough. I think these are all
problems that would be soluble if people were trying to solve them. I think my
problem is that they're not. It might be to do with the Zoom fatigue we were
talking about because like if you have like social spaces that are sitting on
your backside in front of the computer it doesn't necessarily feel different to
sitting on your backside in front of like a panel. And I think that is a tricky
thing because at a convention going to the bar, I had there's like a mental
separation to that where it's a space that is set aside for relaxation whereas
obviously if your home office is also the place where you watch your panels and is
also the place where you drink with your friends, that mental separation is much
much harder to come by. I think that is a real problem but I don't know to why
extent it can be fixed. I agree. Doing it off screen today. Do you think the block,
especially for New Zealand though, do you think having blocks of panels and then
blocks of parties made a lot more work for the people running parties? I think
the fact that there was essentially one person in charge of all the parties
is a lot more work for the people running parties and I kind of, there are always
ways that Americans do their world con running that I always look at and go
in Britain we have a model for con running that doesn't work like this and you
know that this is insane guys and people just kind of shrug. I don't think they
didn't really have blocks of parties, panels and then have blocks of parties.
They had programming essentially through the day and into the evening
every day with the evening things not being the sort of lighthearted things
that we'd have in the evening but being more sort of European timed serious
thing. So I found myself on program at eight o'clock in the morning, New Zealand
time and ten o'clock at night New Zealand time one day which is quite hard and
then the parties just slotted into that so they didn't have breaks in the
programming and I think for a world con you might not want to have breaks in
the programming but I think for a smaller convention or a convention that was
more conspicuously global rather than being grounded in New Zealand you might
say you could do round the clock sets of panels and ask but it does make the
job of programming people onto panels even harder than it might be otherwise
because it's all too easy to say that that panel is perfect for that person
but that is at four o'clock in the morning their time. Yeah and like if
anyone was to run a small fanning convention online I think these are the
sorts of things I want to be thinking about because you don't want to make
it so difficult you don't want to plan to do the perfect convention but have that
be such a difficult thing to achieve that you end up burning out before you get
anywhere near it because like that is the problem with a lot of fan activity you
shoot really really high and you end up not be able to get there so you fizzle
but I think there is room for improvement on the formula that is
relatively low hanging I think and I'm hoping I feel like we've settled into a
little bit of a this is how it works and I'm not sure that model of how it works
is actually a thing that really works for me so at this point I'm starting to be
louder about I think there needs to be more innovation here because I don't
think we've solved the problem yet and I think the fact that a lot of these
conventions are looking very very similar means that I'm worried that there are
people that think we have solved the problem if that makes sense maybe I'm being harsh
I think that one of the ways you could do it for a small convention is to not make
it conspicuously global and I think to some extent that's what reconvened it though
it didn't have parties but so if I was running a small fanning convention I would
probably say up front this is a small British fanning convention and of course
we welcome our friends from countries that are not the UK and of course we will try
to do something that are inclusive but primarily the times that we party are
going to be the times that we party and we might call our social spaces in the
morning coffee and if it's like 11 o'clock at night for you that doesn't mean you're not very
welcome but it's a it's a coffee break rather than a party yeah but I think and
maybe that actually gets back to what Liz was saying which is maybe this is very
difficult to do in a way that is international because you do run into those
fundamental clashes between the coffee and beer time zones yeah I will say having
been to kind of international parties which you know basically have continued
through my night and I am now joining in the morning it is fun but it's very
different joining a party when you've just woken up and it's early on in your
eating breakfast and other people are like at the very end of their drinking and it's 3am
the vibe is quite weird yeah cuz I remember you came to Allison's Easter
comparti and I know he was like it was 3am and I had quite a lot of beer and two
pizzas and you were like I mean in coreflakes and I was like Liz you were like
hello John so yeah I think I think that might be I think it depends on your kind
of party idea because that was nice but I did feel like I have missed out on a
nice night of fun party with people on zoom and I can chat to them now but
they're gonna drift off and fall asleep in a heap in a moment I will have so
long over the next day excellent yeah whereas if the EasterCon I have had
breakfast I mean I've had breakfast at EasterCon with people who had still been
partying but that feels different because then there is still a whole
convention for you to go to like I can have breakfast with people who are super
hungover and about to go to bed and I'm about to start the day but that feels
a bit different because I've got a day to start with well maybe that means that
doing this kind of like 3a tower block idea means that that would work
because you'd be like well yes okay I have missed out on this party but in five
hours there will be more parties that are perhaps better situated for me and I
get panels in the interim yes I would I think that would work very well for a
truly global convention that would all not just be truly global in concept but
also would expect to be the sort of size that that that global reach encompasses
I think it's gonna be hard to make that sort of thing work if you're talking
about a couple of hundred people and I think it will probably work a lot better
with a couple of thousand to fill up all those spaces around the clock so that
people didn't discover that there were actually batches of it when the only
people who were awake were in Polynesia I think if you were if I was planning like
a truly global online Worldcon then I think that is a sort of thing I might
think about can I get sufficient people from sufficient different places that we
can really feel like this is global and going all the time
pre-support global globecon here by sending your $10 to Liz Patti
never share a globecon
hahaha yes you heard it here folks yeah Liz Liz said she'd never share a
Worldcon she didn't say she'd never share a globecon
I really like the idea I really like the idea of getting rid of all of Worldcon's
baggage by just launching globecon you know fed up of the waspus constitution
it is it's dangerous I'm not running a business meeting I'm not running he goes
I'm not running a Natsvik you're running the Globos the Globos please please can we have the
Globos I I visited it as like you know in the hitchhikers guide how there's the
party that's been going forever and has now gone into space and goes raiding
other planets to get stuff for their party that's why I see the convention
as it just goes on forever raiding other convention discords I'm getting more and
more hungover oh wow mmm basically I like this I like this plan a lot
that that endless party in fact many of the endless parties in science fiction
has been in my head for the last six months I feel like I may be living it
but raiding other conventions discords is great this is something I don't know if
you two have done a lot of because obviously most fanning conventions have been doing their panels on Zoom
but the gaming convention I've been to have been running their program primarily
on Twitch and the nice thing about that is that when a program item ends you can
raid someone else's twitch channels with the convention has three programming
streams when one ends you can basically just redirect that stream to a stream
that's still going which is actually really cool except for the one time where a serious
D&D actual play that was all full of like drama and character moments was invaded
by drunk people who had just watched the dark room with John Robertson and the vibes
of the two fan bases were quite different I would say it was very funny I suspect it was
less funny for the people who were in the D&D half of the experience
anyway so are you saying that if we were to run a small fanning convention we would want
to do it on Twitch I don't know I don't know how difficult because I think I think
you add overhead doing it that way because with Zoom obviously it merges all
of the panelists video into like a place where you can watch it and you don't have
none of the panelists have to do any tech wrangling for that to occur I think
obviously with Twitch what you need is like you need to have someone who is like taking
all of the video streams and sewing them into a single video stream and then
outputting that to Twitch I have no experience with that I don't know how hard it is
that's probably quite hard okay so not then but but what you seem to be saying that
some that Twitch could be good for some sorts of things and fans are mostly not using
Twitch for their online activity much at the moment though though I do use Twitch
I've used Twitch as a means of displaying a list of who's in the breakout rooms
at the first Thursday meeting because Twitch is actually a very easy way to get
what is on your computer screen onto the internet without very much fuss oh that's a good idea
for those who are brought out in the proverbial screaming heebie-jeebies by discussion of
the dreaded virus you may want to skip to the next chapter which is a better bit
and has Marvin in it but for those of you staying with us then we're going to discuss
a little bit about what the UK's current rise in cases of COVID-19 and
ensuing clamp down back down to it being illegal for more than six people to meet
together what that might imply for EasterCon because obviously if things were just
continually gradually tailing off we might be quite optimistic about EasterCon
but the fact that things are looking like they're getting a little bit worse
makes us a little bit nervous I think so Liz you are our you are OctaThorps
coronavirus correspondent I'm not sure if I want that position or not
you don't have to have coronavirus to do it if that changes your mind
oh that's good that's good um yeah so I think I sort of brought this up because
we haven't heard that much coming out of the 2021 EasterCon so far and when they
talked about the 2021 bid at the 2020 virtual bid session they didn't they were
definitely planning for an in-person convention and I think thinking about
whether they would run a virtual convention if it wasn't possible to run a 2021
EasterCon and I think at the time I thought oh 2021 yeah it's probably okay
like we stamp on the virus it goes down pretty low and then I think it's a case
of can we keep it that way and not have any more how to put this can not have
any more big outbreaks and I was fairly optimistic that you probably could do
that by 2021 but at the moment looking at it kind of six months later the UK
managed to get transmission under control and keep it quite low but never
actually completely like stamp it out and get down to the really super low
levels we've seen in some other countries and currently it doesn't look
like things are going in the right direction it looks like they might be
going up again and we're gonna have to do some kind of partial lockdown or
restriction of socializing kind of bringing back in more social distancing
smaller groups again and based on that it's hard to know where it goes in the
next few months based on the response over the past six months I don't have a
super optimistic view of the UK actually getting to the point where they can get
it down to near zero and then if they do see any outbreaks to have a system which
works fast enough to do testing and contact tracing in order to bring those
back down to zero again and so I'm worried about when the East Ocon might
make the decision to go virtual when they will need to make the decision to go
virtual and if they decide not to go virtual what does the East Ocon actually
look like when you're planning six months out and you're really not sure
how many people you'll be allowed to have in one room yeah I I share Liz's concern
that the UK is not going to be in a position to put a thousand people in a
hotel in a t-star I mean I think it's remarkably unlikely that we will be
able to hold the East Ocon in the way that we're normally expecting to and I
haven't I feel like I don't know why I do this I'm gonna say this thing and then
you can all fall about laughing and then I'll apologize for it part of me
looks to the East Ocon committee for guidance in these troubling times I
expect the East Ocon committee to be proactively out there using their social
media feeds and their means of contact of the community to be keeping us
updated regularly to be letting us know their thinking on what's going on and I
feel like they kind of from the point where we asked at the business meeting
so what what plans have you got to take the convention virtual and they were
kind of like what we haven't really thought about it yet to now I feel like
I've heard almost nothing from them and it may be that I've been ignoring their
their massive publicity campaign about their plans and what they're doing and
what their thinking is so I wanted to see if you guys had heard anything from
them and if I being a bit daft to expect East Ocon the East Ocon committee to have
any greater role in this than just some people who were kind of running a
convention like all the other conventions in progress report one Easter
cog did say that they are continuing to plan for an in-person convention but
they are doing so with a view to how they might make things work in a virtual
world the fact that it's now September and things do not appear to be heading
towards zero and there has not the government have like begun to think
about how certain things can restart but I'd be extremely surprised if if large
conventions with a lot of quite close commingling was a thing that was able to
happen before Easter but I do think the Easter con committees communication up to
this point has been sparse I feel that if I were the chair of next year's
Easter con I would be talking to people okay so John Marshall might not have found
that funny there you go I don't think you can be stopped from talking to people
person so I realize this is a one year bid and one year bids have a very tight
timeframe to get everything up and running even under the best of circumstances
in 2020 is certainly not the best of circumstances and so I can I can
definitely forgive them for maybe not being as communicative or as on top of
things as other Easter cons have been but at the moment they're very quiet and
we that we end up in the same situation but I think it would be a missed
opportunity for people who enjoy this to try and have an enjoyable weekend to
keep us going before we can all actually see each other in person again yeah so
it is time to start thinking about what the options and ideas for an Easter weekend
virtual event would be how that might look if if the current sitting Easter
con committee did not want to run a virtual convention and what we would do
about it if they didn't and when we need them to realistically be telling us
what they're doing before we decide to seize control of the means of Easter
con production and the thing that I think we can all agree on is the current
sitting Easter con committee should show some leadership and should be saying
some things about this if not now then very soon oh and furthermore Rob Jackson
is still planning to run Corflu in Bristol and that's not gonna happen is it
in February well especially not because transatlantic travel won't be possible
by February like even if the UK is completely covid free in a way that means
that we can have a convention so I think I mean it's definitely not going to be
the usual 800 to 1000 person Easter con because that includes a fair number of
overseas or the just who will be unable or willing to do inter-country travel
can we talk very briefly about the magic vaccine which is not going to
exist by Easter because I think people there are a lot of people still out there
going oh vaccine it's going to be an amazing thing but it's not and we
definitely won't have it by Easter. Am I exist by Easter you won't have it by
Easter though. I think what I think is if there is somehow a combination of
situations that means that if a thousand people congregate in Birmingham next
year it won't be a problem from a public health perspective then I will be
delighted and I will enthusiastically attend to these to con as normal but I
think it is also my opinion that the chances of that are vanishingly small
both from the perspective of COVID just giving up and going away and from the
perspective of having a vaccine boy then so sadly I think that is I mean if it
is possible brilliant and I will eat tumble by but my gut feeling is that it's
probably not. It's not possible based on extrapolating from any of the current
responses to the crisis in the UK so I think my question is is there any
situation in which a smaller Easter con or even a hybrid in-person
Easter con, in-person virtual Easter con would be run or is it a case of either
we run something in person that looks a lot like the Easter con we expect maybe
a bit smaller or we just go straight to virtual Easter con. I do feel that
second question is very much something for the committee I mean they might
reasonably say we will run the largest event we are legally allowed to or you
could arrange to run a set of small events in different places. I'm not sure
if things are as they are at present I'm not sure I would be prepared to go to
an in-person con and I mean I speaking here as somebody who went to an actual
COVID safe I think I'm gonna put COVID safe in square quotes because I'm not
sure we really know what constitutes COVID safe but but a music event yesterday
with 30 people at I mean which some some chatting happened where everyone
kind of stood around more than six feet apart with masks on having
conversations and and you could kind of see fans having a party a bit like that
but it still wouldn't be any part of what I think of the Easter con as being
and this was early September rather than February so February I'll put
ignore me Easter because often the weather is very bad at Easter weekend
is not in February no it's not when is you again next year is it April it's not
next weekend either it's early April okay just just I'm definitely not suffering
from confusion ha ha ha name of the con oh god it is at all it is I'm not saying
that the convention committee have to be planning to run a online convention if
COVID hasn't gotten into a manageable stay by then and I'm not saying the
convention I'm not really saying the convention has to do anything I suppose
the only thing I am saying the convention needs to do is communicate what
their plans are openly and transparently with the community because if their
plan isn't to run an Easter con if COVID is not under control it would be
useful for other fans to know that in advance so we can start planning I think
I would say that it is not unusual for the sitting Easter con to have not
communicated clearly and cogently at this stage in the year for the following year
and in fact the Easter con whilst not having a written constitution or even an
unwritten constitution does have custom and practice for what we do in this
situation which is that we sort it out at Novakon obviously we're not having an
over con either but I mean as long as there is something happening over the
Novakon weekend we would be able to at that point take stock of where the Easter
con was at and whether they had communicated cogently about their plans
and if they had not committed to educate cogently about their plans said well it
it falls upon those of us here present to go well what do we want to happen
over the Easter weekend let it let us make it so Spock I think and we have heard
rumors I feel I feel I can feel I can discuss the rumors I've heard rumors that
something will be happening over the Novakon weekend but obviously they are
just rumors so we can't can't say any more here but there are rumors yeah one
of the really strange things about doing a podcast about fandom is that there's
another thing that is only rumors at the moment that I'm desperate to talk about
on the podcast but at some point it will not be rumors and I'll be able to talk
about but that's yeah that is for the podcast you know if you have any good
rumors that we are allowed to talk about please do write to us so we will
allude to them yes we will waggle our eyebrows significantly um so yeah so so
if if something does happen over the Novakon weekend then hopefully this is
something that can be discussed by fandom then um I think so obviously in order
of preference I would like to see covid magically go away and there to be a
proper Easter con with a drunk tobes at it second preference is to have a
smaller Easter con which is you know and appropriate about people for the
covid situation and for there to be a drunk tobes at it and then I think the
third option is I would like there to be a virtual Easter con and I think that
there should be a drunk tobes at it so I think do you think drunk and tobes is
critical to your enjoyment of these two weekend I mean I think to the extent
that Easter con has a constitution that constitution does involve tobes being
drunk I remember Easter cons from before tobes attended them so if there is an
Easter con held and tobes is not at it is it an Easter con this is the sort of
dangerous and uncharted territory that I wish to avoid exploring what if tobes
is at the convention but doesn't drink
I don't I mean well I mean if we're going to talk about fantasy lands I'd
also like to have Easter con on the moon okay so the moon is not in the United
Kingdom and I think although we have stretched this point a few times I'm not
sure we're gonna stretch it to the moon John
here's your thing suppose Easter con went virtual what things would it have to
properly encompass in order to feel like a proper Easter con apart from a drunk
and so I was gonna be my first thing I think the things for me that make it
Easter con at Easter con are good panels with fans on them good panels with pros
on them but not solely pros I think I've seen a lot of conventions where I feel
like most of the programming has been focused around people who are authors
and people who are pros and I understand why because I think that gets people to
attend but I would like to see it Easter con do more with with with you know
the fandom and I think I think Conzeland did that well so I'm not saying that
no one has done that but I think I think that would be good I think there
should be a game component gaming component I don't know how that would
work but I can think of some ways to do it I think there should be a thriving
social space and I think there should be a bid session where people ask
questions about whether or not there will be mushrooms at breakfast Liz what's
an Easter con to you other than the wrong time zone yeah I think if it had
everything you just laid out then it would feel like an Easter con I don't
know I'm not very big on virtual socializing with people I don't already
know well I find that difficult whereas it is much easier an Easter con for like
someone I don't know to come up and join the conversation and get to know
them and have a chat and I find that quite difficult over zoom or discord or
whatever if you could if you had social spaces that were with that kind of six
to eight to ten people consistently that you might have a rounder table in a bar
it is actually quite easy to bring extra people into that and and you make
friends of them over time as we've been seeing on the Internet all all this year
I've made new friends I've there and I think the other thing is that people who
are very very vague acquaintances of mine in March and now my friends purely
because of our interactions over the Internet to an extent that I'm not sure
I would have thought was possible so for me it is all about the social spaces I
mean I understand that there have to be I don't just want program I don't want
just what panels of fans and panels of pros and and I want there to be talks by
interesting people that generate conversations about what they had to say
and why it matters I want there to be extravaganza type events you know that
just I mean not necessarily the disco but you know that are things that other
conventions have not done and I don't know quite how you translate that to
virtual but I you know one of the things about the East con is that it can have
it can do things that no other British Convention has the scale and space to do
and I think that the transition to virtual shouldn't prevent that from
happening and so there's a it's an opportunity to think quite big in terms
of what we can do what we could do at this convention that nobody has tried and
I think I know what my friends to be at it lots and lots of my friends well
that yeah that's fair I think I will say on the subject I think Liz is thing
the thing you said Liz about not necessarily finding it easy to have online
spaces where you socialize with people you don't know very well I think I do
wonder to what extent that changes with the number of these things you attend
because like I would have described myself in a similar situation at the
start of lockdown but having been to a number of first Thursdays where and a
number of boozy mooses where there are quite a few people I don't know I think
I am kind of getting better at that in a in a way and I think Alison's point
about smaller breakout rooms being good for emulating that kind of like you
know these are this is a room and there are like six people in this room and
three of them are people I know really well and two of them are people I've
not met before but like that ratio is not unfavorable and the amount of new
people is not overwhelming I saw his band was in a zoom conversation at one
online con which I think there was about twenty-four people in and I sort of
thought that I don't think I would enjoy I don't think that would work so I
think having a lot of breakout rooms is like the only way to kind of try and
deal with that if that makes sense. Maybe the only way at the moment but we
don't want to solve the problems of six months time with the technology of now
I think we are seeing the virtualization platforms continuing to compete for
market share by generating new features that work and I think I think
Discord is quite likely for a start-off to come up with things that feel more
like a bar and there are definitely people out there trying to do that it's
not just it's not just we're not the only people who want this to work. Yeah I
think it's a probably not specifically me problem but I think I just find it
harder to like follow the ebb and flow of conversation the dynamics of
conversation on zoom and so six might be the maximum I can manage that with and
I think eight to ten is probably more people than I can follow on a zoom so
that makes it a little bit more difficult and I think it's more yeah it just feels
like at a convention you might chat to someone on the first day and then maybe
bump into them again on the third day and have a chat all sort of see them in a
panel and say hello and those kind of repeat exposures may not happen quite so
easily at a virtual convention. Yeah so that we maybe wanting to think about how
we can do that I hate the idea of doing formal ice-breaking events but I think
you may need to do some things that are quite like formal ice-breaking events
in some way and that have some of the same especially for people who find it
harder to make new friends. Maybe that's a thing that I think at a normal
convention I would be a little bit more although I haven't said that maybe that
is a good idea because like you do tend to find the conventions do get very
clicky and like I am very aware even at physical conventions I do tend to spend
the whole time hanging out with people I already know which is I like hanging out
with people I know in the main unless I know them and think they're an idiot but
that doesn't often happen in fandom. But I will say that like I do sometimes
miss the days when I was very new to fandom and most of the people I met were
people I did not know yet because that was quite fun. So maybe maybe that kind
of thing would be a good addition. I don't know. I think this is one of the
reasons why I wish more conventions were trying to solve the problem of online
socializing because I don't think it is a well-solved problem but I equally don't
think that we're going to solve it unless we carry on iterating on the
formula if that makes sense. I think it's definitely something that you could try
at a virtual convention and you know it would be opt-in to that ice breakers if
you want to and if you don't feel that would work for you you don't need to
kind of like sessions for newcomers at conventions in general. How to enjoy your
first virtual Eastercon mandatory for everyone. I think I enjoy getting to know
people through text chat much more than either of you do so that is also more
of an option for me. That was the 14th episode of the UltaThore podcast in
which John Liz and Alison agreed a lot and didn't argue at all. And it's goodbye
from me. And it's goodbye from me. And it's goodbye from me. The theme music for
this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod at Ncompetech.com used under a
Creative Commons attribution 3.0 license.
I have it will not come as a it will not come as a surprise to anyone that the
things I have been doing in lockdown are editing podcasts and playing our
comorbid card game. And do you want to tell us about your new podcast John? I've
got a new podcast Alison and it's when I play Arkham Horror of the card game in a
podcast. Mind blown. I've already got nine listeners. Nine. Smashing. How many of
those listeners are related to you? Well, it's been your refuses to listen and I
haven't told any of my family so I think none. How many of them are in your
Arkham Horror regular Arkham Horror playing group? Oh, I assume I assume they're all
people I don't want discord through Arkham Horror. So yes, that is a fair
comment. But you know, still happy. One of them was me but I only listened up to
point where you like mentioned the spoiler warning for games I haven't played and
then I stopped listening. So not so that counts. Yes, I need to record some more
people can listen to. I'm on it. Oh, sorry. There's a lizard on my wall. Like a
gecko like this big. It's like a little gecko the size of a spider. Yeah, no,
it's literally like about an inch and a half tall but it's just like run behind
my curtain. But that's not really a big problem is it? No, but they go very fast
and it's just suddenly like emerging behind my monitor and I'm like what the
fuck is that? It's a little tiny lizard. Little tiny gecko. They move really fast
and if you surprise them they drop their tails off and the tails keep moving and
it's very freaky. Okay, that's quite freaky. Yeah, yeah, I don't know. So I tried to
trap one and I thought I've gone under the box and I thought oh shit, I've chopped
his tail off with the box. No, it had dropped its tail and left it but they
continue moving. That is the freaky bit. I just got all this by googling after the
fact. Yeah, you see really this is Octa thought the podcast of lizard tails and
other digressions. Where's it gone? It's fucked off now is the problem. Oh, are we
going to get our Arkham Horror playing session in the diary by the way chat? Yeah,
probably. Should we do that after? I have some feedback from somebody which is you
don't have this podcast is now over sound at the very end of the podcast, John.
They don't. That's true. And you need it because if you are listening on a
podcast player that automatically plays the next episode, the after show leads
seamlessly into the cold open and people don't realize they've started listening
to the next episode until it's too late. Alright, how about I'm gonna do the this
podcast is now over noise Liz prepare yourself. This podcast is now over. It's
not often you get to see Allison just completely dumbfounded for what to say.
So I am happy with that result. It isn't it isn't I was kind of thinking of doing
like a little closing beat by blah blah blah. That's sort of that sort of end of
okay yeah for enough you don't think me sexually saying this podcast is now over
is what this podcast will self-destruct in five seconds. Yes, sorry that might be
that might be a cultural reference that is too old. I always worry. This podcast
will end at the beep beep and then the beep yeah