Sorry, I just tried to read and talk the same time.
It went completely wrong.
Hello, everyone, and welcome to the very 54th episode of the Oct.
Podcast, which is coming to you on the 31st of March 2022.
I'm John Coxson.
I'm Alison Scott.
And I'm Liz Batty.
We have a bumper roster of letters of comment this week on account of how I had COVID last week.
And so we only gave you a measly 14 minutes of entertainment.
And thank you to everyone who asked if John was better.
John, are you better?
I appear to be.
You don't sound like you've gargled a load of gravel.
I have a headache and a sore throat, but I think the headache and sore throat are mostly because of the dust this time and not because of the COVID.
Because I think getting reinfected this quickly would be spectacularly unlikely.
Yeah, I had a headache and a dribbly nose and I did an LFT and it was negative.
And I said a headache and dribbly nose and I didn't have to.
It was negative.
And then I went, oh, of course, and took my anti-estamines.
So yeah, that's a sort of thing.
There's a lot of dust in my house now listeners.
This is the experience I have this week and I will probably take an LFT in the middle of recording this podcast, but they will be negative.
So I'm pretty sure I don't have COVID.
You're going to take one mid podcast, although it's positive you're going to stop.
Are you doing an actual play of an LFT?
Is this like a experiment to see whether LFTs are in fact eligible for the best interactive experience Hugo?
That bomb you just heard was Alison putting her foot down listeners.
It wasn't, but I'll remember this.
I actually do lateral flow tests in the middle of octa-thord episodes quite often because
it's finding a time when I can guarantee that I haven't eaten or haven't drunk any coffee in the last half hour.
So because there is no coffee, so in half an hour's time, I would not have had any coffee for half an hour and and 10.
Brilliant.
That is a good plan, actually.
And we also got a lot of comments on Sue Asen's fantastic artwork.
Thank you very much to Sue.
Yeah, we have more fantastic artwork from guest artists in the pipeline.
We are very pleased about that.
Duncan McGregor is very worried what I'm going to do with the picture of him.
And hopefully you'll see that in this episode's artwork as long as I get my finger out.
Excellent.
So we had a letter of comment from one Christopher J Garcia.
And he notes that he can if pressed, it quates everything to genre awards, especially food.
And I'd like you to express Korean barbecue in the context of genre awards, please Chris.
He is in favor of bids having a big website that contains everything you could possibly want to know about the bid, but especially costs.
And my comment on that would be as somebody who's currently working on a bid.
Sometimes the information that you would love to put on the website isn't entirely there yet when you're working on a bid and you probably don't want people to know that.
So the website said to be a collection of the stuff that we know and can talk about and are not still arguing about.
And I think that's fine too.
So you're saying it's better for your website to be missing.
Basically, it's better for your website to be extremely minimalist because otherwise what's not on your website might give away where your committee is still arguing.
I don't think so because I don't think people spot it that well, but I think it is better to be
have limited information on the website than have the website be wrong.
Yes, I would agree with that.
I think that's fair.
But I think sometimes when websites don't have everything you might possibly want, that's why it's because behind the scenes everything you might possibly want is not yet settled.
Yeah, I didn't say the bid sessions, you know, in a bid session, what I want to hear is information which is correct from the bids.
I feel that one should go without saying.
You'd be amazed though.
I think people who have not run bids may not know how much is left, not till the last minute.
But like, there's a lot that you don't know until you know and like you have to bear in mind that the cost curve for a convention, your actual budget and your projected budget can be massively divergent numbers.
And you don't really understand sometimes you don't understand how much money you've got to play with until three weeks before the con.
And so you do there are certain things you're like, we really want to be able to do this.
And if we get enough members, we'll definitely be able to do it.
But we haven't got enough members yet, so we can't announce it yet.
And then what sometimes happens, which is a lovely problem to have, is that you get way more members than you're expecting.
And then suddenly you've got to work out things to spend money on right at the last minute where you hadn't planned to at all.
And so like I do, I appreciate, because this point, but I also appreciate Alison's point that like these things are highly variable, even like right up to the convention.
It can be very difficult to know what's actually going to happen.
And the cost curve for East Cons in particular is while the out of whack at the moment, nobody really knows what it is anymore.
It used to be pretty reliable. And now it's not at all.
Is that to do with Covid or was that happening before Covid, Alison?
I think it is a combination of Covid and the fact that London East Cons are not like non-London East Cons is the two things that primarily drive that.
So essentially in terms of the will you get a massive bunch of members in the last month, the answer seems to be whether you either will or you won't.
Which is not great.
But it is factually correct, so I'm for it.
A website is a lasting thing that people can point to and pillory you if you fail to live up to the promises on it.
So I think in that case we could describe a website as an immutable artifact.
We could certainly describe it as the opposite of a political manifesto.
Oh, satire.
Was that getting a bit political? We can segue from that, but not yet.
Chris also says that because I am a novel, he is going to guess who I am written by.
And his guess is Stephen Baxter, which is awkward because Hispania hates novels written by Stephen Baxter.
So I really hope I'm not because that would be interesting for our marriage.
So try again, Chris, please.
Other listeners may also guess.
Someone called and let me make sure I'm pronouncing their name right.
Liz Batty sent us a lock on our last episode with a picture of a cat.
So if you'd like to see an adorable cat, please go and look at the comments on the Facebook post for that episode.
It is ginger. Lovely.
Did you have a nice holiday Liz?
I did. It was also very noisy cat, but would not come any closer than it is depicted in the photograph.
And in our last episode, Johnny Badly heard John talking about Netrunner in his pick
and is going to send John all his old Netrunner stuff.
So I'd just like to let people know that I collect vintage emeralds.
And if anyone would like to send me some, they'd be very, I'd be very grateful for those.
Big ones better. Thank you.
So listeners, Alison has told that joke four times and it was only in that most recent telling that I actually got it.
So, you know, sometimes repetition is the secret to comedy.
Really?
Yeah. I just, yeah, no. Yeah. I'm quite dense sometimes.
It's why I like rereading the Hitchhiker's Guide.
There are always jokes in there that I didn't get on the first 46 read throughs.
Well, I mean, you do want to keep telling jokes until they land.
I mean, I haven't checked if Liz got it yet, but some people got it on the Facebook group, so it can't be impossible.
We also had a message from Johnny about discos in COVID times.
And whether or not we thought there'd be discos at conventions during COVID.
And whether or not it would be fun to dance in a face mask.
Having caught trains in a face mask and gotten unpleasant these way,
I can't imagine dancing in a face mask is going to be anything like fun.
But I might be wrong.
I don't know how sweaty dancers like to get.
I'm not judging, but I don't know.
I don't know what the plans for the disco are at East con.
East con committee, if you're listening right in.
I do some with a face mask. It's all right.
Interesting.
So maybe the secret is that it's just fine, Johnny, and we just don't need to embrace the sweat.
I mean, I'm going to be, if I'm dancing for an hour, then like, I'm going to be sweaty anyway.
And so the mask doesn't seem to significantly add to that.
I would say more impressive is that like the instructor who is more high energy than I am
and also shouting is wearing a mask throughout.
I think it's pretty impressive.
We may have digressed a bit far, but yeah, I mean, I saw a mask to do exercise and it's okay.
But a disco at a convention isn't exactly doing exercise, is it?
It depends how you dance.
It depends how much you're going at it to mean.
Yeah.
Can't be.
Yeah, I remember my sweatiest moment at Dublin 2019.
It wasn't my sweat.
I stood outside the Glasgow 2024 Kaylee briefly and waited as the
meyasma floated over me from that room.
So they were having a lot of fun and they were getting very sweaty.
Pre-COVID.
Okay, Lee is a very good way of getting very sweaty.
Yeah.
Listener Laurie from the podcast Hugo Girl mentioned that she has now read six
weeks by Malefity and reliked it and is going to try to convince her co-host to
add it to the schedule eventually.
So I look forward to that happening because that sounds ace.
And Laurie also told us that like me, she listens to her own podcast from time to time.
So if you do a podcast and you like to listen back to it, let us know.
Because I kind of think it's a good sign, but it might be that we're just very self-indulgent
or I'm very self-indulgent.
Um, why not both?
We have a live follow-up from inside my house, which is that my wife says there was a dance
at Clockwork Alchemy, which is a steampunk convention in the Bay Area,
where the dance is all the war masks and I will link to...
Well, if it's public, I will link to a Facebook post in the show notes listeners,
although that was more couples dancing.
My steampunk friends say that the steampunk community has embraced masks in a big way,
which shouldn't surprise anyone really.
I saw at Gallifrey 1 several of the cosplays worked masks into the costumes.
So if you're doing like an alien cosplay, you had like a mask that was like the alien's face
and some of those were really, really cool.
[Music]
So since we last recorded, there has been some more discussion of the Chengdu World Con.
There has been a letter asking the World Con community to revoke the site selection of Chengdu
in 2023.
As a reaction to it threats to Taiwan about the Ukraine invasion and also the
weaker genocide, as we discussed previously on this podcast.
And I think it's a very well-meaning effort, but it is more, I think, drawing attention to the Chengdu
World Conbid than actually having much hope that it will be revoked as a site,
because there isn't really any mechanism for that to happen.
But I think it is very nice to kind of raise awareness of it and also the letter does lay out
in very clear and concrete terms the reasons why they feel human rights have been violated
and the site selection should be revoked.
So we're linked to that in the show notes.
The second issue that's also come up is that the guest of honor Sergei Lukianenko
has previously made extremely pro-Russian anti-Ukraine posts on his live journal.
And after the recent Russian invasion of Ukraine, he has also now signed an open letter
supporting the invasion of Ukraine and making other favorable comments about it.
So there's been a lot of discussion and contact with Chengdu and pressure on them,
I think, to try and disinvite him as a guest of honor due to these views.
As yet, I don't think we've heard anything from Chengdu about Lukianenko or about the open letter.
But what I will say is, you know, these views cannot have come as a surprise to them.
You know, the immediate context of the invasion of Ukraine, yes, definitely has,
but it's not like these views were owned and owned before they invited him.
This is something that they're going to have to deal with and it shouldn't have come as a surprise
to them. But so far, they've remained silent on it.
Yeah, I think this is a very good example of how something that I think we discussed
previous to the events of recent times in Europe with a kind of, you know, this is clearly
unacceptable, then became a lot less theoretical very quickly.
I think this is a lesson for conventions who are like, oh, but, you know,
X has this objectionable thing, but it probably won't end up being a problem.
And then you look at Discon with Tony Vyskov and you look at Chengdu with this chap and you think,
oh, no, sometimes these things that you think, oh, we could probably get away with it,
turns out they become giant pains in the arse very quickly.
Yeah, I was also going to say it's one of the things we were discussing about on previous episodes
about, you know, rehabilitation, whether someone's acts in the past should always,
you know, be automatically, oh, you should take those into account.
And in this case, they may have thought, well, he's made comments in the past,
but they were quite a long time ago. Maybe he's not said anything since then, you know,
maybe they could have discussed it with him, what would happen in the future,
but I presume they did not. And now it has become a much more, you know, recent and pressing problem.
And props to Marcin, who was the first person around me who said, oh, no, this guy is a badan,
you know, Chengdu should not have invited him. It's a terrible idea. And he was right.
Yeah, and it was the Polish Eastern European fans who were very much aware of this before I was.
It was not something I was aware of before they raised it after the site section vote.
There has been, so it's worth noting that the guest of honour having objection to all opinions
is not the focus of the open letter. So the two are happening in close proximity to one another,
but are not like necessarily related. Oh, there are letters on Luke and Yanko as well.
So so people have been writing. This sort of thing is why I think that bringing WorldCon to
countries that have not had WorldCon before is great. I think that I did a good thing. I think that
I did not support China as a WorldCon because I had real concerns about various problems with
their human rights record. And that was before they announced their guest of honour, who kind of
didn't make me think that those concerns were things that were being talked about in the Chengdu
organisation very freely. Because I think if a convention had had an idea that there was concerns
about their human right record, they might have invited a different guest of honour who wouldn't
add fuel to that fire. I think that what this shows is there probably does need to be some mechanism
for a bid to need to fill certain human rights criteria before being allowed to be voted. Because
if we can't deselect a bid, it means it's on us to make sure that bids that are selected are appropriate.
And I think that if the end of not doing that is that WorldCon's name gets dragged through the
mud by association, that will be a problem for WorldCon going forward. And so I think that this is all
a lot of these very academic discussions that we were having around Saudi Arabia when they were
bidding are suddenly becoming a lot less academic. And I do think we need to be thinking quite seriously
about where we put these lines in the sand and whether or not there needs to be some sort of
record mechanism or something like that. But I don't know how any of that would work. And it's a very
difficult conversation. I think it's very tempting to go what we need is some, you know, as part of
filing, they need to satisfy these human rights criteria. I think there is a risk that
many bids would not be able to do that in many countries, including many countries that
we are generally comfortable with and it's hard, it would be very hard to draw some lines there.
I also think this might all be a very theoretical argument because I think the world might be
becoming a very complex place in which travelling freely all the way around the world to meet fans
from all over the world becomes very, very difficult over the next few years. That was a bit depressing.
I would say I have seen two concrete suggestions for this. One was using an
it's called the Democracy Index, which comes from the people who published The Economist,
which basically gives every country a ranking as to whether there are full or flawed democracy,
a hybrid regime or an authoritarian regime. And the suggestion was that you should only have
World Cons in regions which are democracies. And there's also an index which basically ranks all
countries as either free or not free, which is I think the Freedom House, Freedom in the World
Index. So there seem to be two concrete suggestions I've seen just because the problem of
how to measure this is very difficult. I would say that both of them sure are coming at this
from a Western perspective. I think they're done by the people who do The Economist and by
US NGO. So they are coming from a certain perspective. And also there's conflicts between them.
There are countries which are ranked as democracies but not free for other reasons. And it also
includes countries that might be controversial but are still democracies under the Democracy
Index. But those are the concrete suggestions I have seen. And I suspect we're going to see
more discussion of this. And I guess the other thing to say is that the Chengdu Wilcon has
obviously a guest shiqin lu, which makes a ton of sense because he's probably the most prominent
Chinese language author outside of China. But he also went asked about his political views on the
one child policy and the re-education camps has been kind of loosely supportive of them. So I
think that's another thing that Chengdu are going to need to be aware of. For instance,
like Netflix are adapting some of his works and I think I've had to distance themselves
from Lou's views. So when I had Sinopticon as one of my picks, one of the things in that is
it's clear that loads of stuff is getting edited in translation because it would not
the things that Chinese SF authors write often do not land well with Western audiences
on all sorts of different fronts. And that certainly happened with Shikson and Lou.
So that economist post ranks the US as only just above a, I might be getting the colour
scale slightly wrong, but it doesn't rank it as a full democracy. So I do think that's like
a reasonable take. I mean, but it does rank China as orange and orange listeners is
not just not just good orange, like angry, actually no, not even orange, more in maroon colour.
And that is bad. I mean, if you've got red, green colour blindness, the world is just shades of
gray. Full democracy, but not the best. Second rank of full democracy. Yeah, better than Spain,
which probably fair. Sweden, Finland, Norway, Germany, Iceland, all complete full democracies,
and Canada. Israel is a flawed democracy by these standards, but I'm still not sure that an Israel
worldcom would be, you know, if that's our ranking, are people going to be happy with that?
I think it's probably better to have some fixed system that is outside of Wussfuss control,
which occasionally yields edge cases I disagree with than it is to try and do it.
Do you see what I mean? Like, at least then it's not, it's not us being wrong. And it's like, no,
we've, we've yoked our star to this carriage, and we're just doing what they say. And sometimes
that might be an edge case that's annoying. But like, certainly looking at this, it reinforces a
lot of my preconceptions about where I would have said to the best democracies in the world are
New Zealand, Scandinavia. I mean, you know, it's not whatever you pick isn't going to be perfect,
but like, I do think that map, but both of these maps, I think you could make an argument
are like relatively sensible, kind of first steps. And it's not the be all and end all here. It is,
you know, a first pass. I mean, you can, we're still going to have votes and people are still
going to choose, and this is still going to be part of how they choose where they would like to see
a worldcom. But it basically would eliminate some sites from being eligible to bid right from the
get-go. I don't see this ratifying in China, guys. Well, I mean, I think the, the ratification in
China is going to be very interesting because of the way Chengdu have structured their memberships.
Chengdu have given us the opportunity to send Liz back into the Wussfuss caves.
To the back constitution, Liz, the Chengdu will come while remaining silent,
other things have released their membership rates. In fact, they release their membership rates,
and then they release their membership rates again with some more instructions because it's
quite a confusing table. But essentially, the way they're structuring it is that you can purchase a
Wussfuss membership, which is, I think what we would normally say is kind of a supporting membership.
And this is automatic if you voted in the 2023 site selection, or you can pay $50 for the Wussfuss
membership. So far, pretty standard. And then you can add an in-person admission, which is free
if you voted in the 2023 site selection. And then there are rates between $30 and $70 for the in-person
admission, or you can purchase online admission, which is between $2 and $10, depending if it's
your first World Coronary student or various other things, which is actually a model that I think
one of the recent constitutional amendments was moving towards where you have kind of a Wussfuss
membership, and then you purchase the in-person admission to the Wilcom on top. But the, the
difference that Chengdu are making is that you don't have to purchase that Wussfuss membership at all.
You can just purchase the in-person admission and attend the convention, but you won't have the
rights to vote in any site selection or Q-Go awards or presumably attend the business meeting on site.
This is quite controversial. Well, in certain circles, it's quite controversial because of the
way the Wussfuss Constitution is written. It says you can't do this. It says you cannot sell an
attending membership without including Wussfuss rights. Except for, I think, day memberships and
children are excluded. So, you can sell a Charles membership or a day membership without including
voting rights, but otherwise Wussfuss membership is key. And I kind of understand why Chengdu don't
want to, but I mean, I don't know why Chengdu don't want to, which is this, that there are other
bits of the Constitution, which say, you know, the supporting membership rate is essentially set
in advance by all the bids in agreement with the Committee of the Wilcom hosting the site selection,
and they all have to kind of agree on the bidding fee, otherwise it defaults to basically the
median of the past three. So, you're never going to manage to set a supporting membership rate,
which is at the moment less than about $50. But the other bit of says that you may not
sell a membership, which includes any Wussfuss voting rights for less than the cost of supporting
membership mentioned in Article 4. So, they're not allowed to sell anything that includes Wussfuss
voting rights for less than $50, which means they can't sell a full attending membership for less
than $50. But obviously, they would like to do that because they would like to have some very cheap
attending membership in order to attract people for whom the cost is prohibitive. And of course,
we are talking about, I think, the first Wilcom being held in a lower middle-income country,
where the idea of paying $120 for membership is prohibitive to many, many people. And so,
they've opted to have this in-person admission, which ranges from $30 for a student to $70 for
someone who's been to multiple Wilcoms, which doesn't include the Wussfuss voting rights,
which gets around that bit, the Constitution. But it also falls foul of the bit about not
having any selling any full attending memberships, which don't include Wussfuss voting rights.
So, there's an interesting point here, which is that one of the decisions I saw about this on some
group on Facebook here or there was someone pointing out that at the moment, if you buy a day
pass to each day of the Wilcom, you don't get Wussfuss voting rights, which is in
contravention of the Constitution. So, existing Wilcoms do already disobey these provisions because
it is possible to just keep buying day passes and never become a Wussfuss voting member.
And I think this is the thing, which is the Constitution is very specific because it says like,
you can't sell a membership that allows attendance and full participation for the
entire duration of the Convention and does not include Wussfuss voting rights.
But if they say that these memberships don't entitle you to go to the Wussfuss business meeting,
it doesn't include full attendance of the Convention and therefore it doesn't need to include Wussfuss
voting rights, which is completely compliant with the Constitution and fine. So, all you need to do
is ban these people from attending the business meeting and jobs are good. I do think that,
in this case, the other problem is that the Constitution is written in a very US-centric way.
Not just US-centric, but anglicpher-centric, I guess.
Yeah, which is to assume that basically everyone attending the Wilcom can definitely afford $50
right. And that is not going to be true if the Wilcom does start branching out to countries which
do have lower levels of income. And like, I'm thinking also of places like India or Brazil or
places like that, if they ever decide they want to vote and bid for a Wilcom, then this may be a
problem. And we probably need to have a think about how to make sure that Wussfuss,
that the intention that the Wilcom is made up of people who form Wussfuss,
matches the reality of what if the Wilcom is held in a country where people don't have a lot of
money and it would be useful to offer a membership to local people, which includes Wussfuss but is
less than a supporting membership, because I think that would be good. And you could definitely
modify the Constitution to allow that. So I think, I mean, I don't know, it might be that
Chengdu haven't spotted this loophole and are just hoping no one notices, but I can see a loophole
in these two that means you can do this and it's fine. But yeah, I think there is a wealth privilege
thing here which probably needs to be addressed. I think you've probably made my point which is
that I'm kind of with Chengdu. I don't know how to do things like the first Wilcom memberships,
that's probably still more than the supporting membership, aren't they? That's the issue,
is that they want to have a very cheap membership for locals and I don't blame them. And I think
they should be encouraged and we should find a way to make that happen. And the probable way to do
this is for Wussfuss just to turn a blind eye, which is the sort of thing that Wussfuss loves to do,
as you know. What if they don't turn a blind eye? What are they going to do? Where are the enforcement
clauses in the Wussfuss Constitution that means anything can be done? There aren't any. So Chengdu
can do what they like. They have the right to host the Wilcom, there's no way of taking that away
from them and there's no enforcement mechanism in the Constitution. So you can do whatever.
Like we have known this, I mean at least since New Zealand, which I would argue flagrantly,
violated the Wussfuss Constitution even though Kevin Sandley disagrees with me,
but we know that you can do whatever you like already. It's fine. But I will also say this is
really interesting because one of the things that has been mooted is that the Hugo Awards would look
very different this year because they'll be loads of Chinese voters. And if all the Chinese voters
have bought super cheap memberships that don't give them Hugo voting, right? It's going to look
basically the same as normal everyone. So yeah, is that good for the Hugo's? What do we think?
Yeah, so I would say a couple of things. Yeah, one is that like I feel that, yeah, essentially
the supporting membership price sort of has locked them in in a way that probably wasn't intended by
the Wussfuss Constitution because it may be that they can run a Wilcom for a lot cheaper than we
can run a Wilcom in the US or the UK or Ireland. I think they're just the sponsorship and membership
and income. It looks very different. I mean, the second argument you can make is that
it's not just holding them in places where the income is lower. It's also, could we possibly
want to hold one in the US or the UK where we ran it with a much lower membership fee and
use a different model where we either made it much cheaper or tried to expand to many more people.
Like it also blocks that kind of thing. Yeah, in terms of the Hugo's, I actually think I probably
will have more to say on Chinese influence on the Hugo nominations once we have the Hugo
nominations in a couple of weeks. That's true. Yeah, hopefully we'll have them by Easter.
That's actually a good point. That's a good point because we know that everyone who
voted for Chengdu did have a supporting membership to discount. So we'll be eligible to nominate.
Sorry, that was the point I was going to make, which is that 2000 Chinese voters already have
a full attending membership of Chengdu and convert to the Hugo's and that is plenty.
Oh, yes. So if you voted at the discount three-type selection for either bid, you are an attending
member of Chengdu, which is kind of magic. A full wuss for attending membership voting rights for
literally your support, your site selection fee. So that was a, in my view, quite a good deal.
Not that I think the chances of my being at Chengdu, at the Chengdu work on are infinitesimal for
multiple reasons, but it's still pretty exciting. And the virtual membership for people who hadn't
noticed is $2 and I really like that. I think that will increase participation, usually, not just in
China. Yeah, I very much like that. What they've been able to do essentially is to reward all the
people who, reward all the people who supported them by paying $50 to vote in a process that might
have seen them get a supporting membership in Winnie-Pager Convention they can never realistically go to.
And so they reward them by saying, well, thank you for that. You can now come to the World
Com and we don't need any extra from you. And then there will also be the, you know, there's probably
many people in like the US and the UK who voted for Winnie-Pag and now have full attending membership
in a Worldcon in China. They probably won't be able to go to or will choose not to go to.
So it does work both ways. Yeah, it means that the, I think the potential for that being, you know,
not just the however many Chinese members who have full attending wisface memberships, but however
many others they might gain, I would imagine that it will now be a lot lower because why pay,
you know, $100 when you could pay $50 if what you really want to do is go to the convention.
And so it is still going to be a very interesting set of nominees and voting for Chengdu and also
the business meeting there is going to be interesting. And that's another thing because we were talking
about the other thing is that a lot of things that will come up for ratification in Chengdu may be
again predominantly people who voted in site selection and the US/other Anglo-fans because,
you know, if a lot of the Chinese members have not bought wisface right. Presumably there won't be
in the business meeting and therefore, yeah, the ratification would be interesting.
Chances of the business meeting having sorted out remote participation by next Worldcon?
Very low, I would say.
Zero. Yeah. Because they're going to require that it's a thing, they're going to require an
amendment to the Constitution despite the fact that obviously attending the member, you could
have told them a commensurate virtually and therefore you should be able to vote virtually, but there we go.
I would, I may have argued this before, but I think the wisface constitution is not,
it's worded in a way that means that if you have the Worldcon in a place that you're attending it,
you should be able to go to the business meeting and if you're attending the Worldcon virtually,
that should mean you get to go to the business meeting virtually and the fact that you can't,
I think, is a flagrant breach of the Constitution, but see also lack of any coherent enforcement
mechanism. I agree.
Right, so shall we talk about the FAN Awards?
Why not? Yes, we should talk about the FAN Awards. Congratulations to everyone who won and congratulate
and thank you very much to the two people who voted for us, one is a Gen Zine and one is a
perzine, both of whose votes were thrown out because the administrator as predicted concluded that we
are not a FAN Zine for the purpose of the FAN Awards. Because we're not published listeners.
For no reason I can tell because we do keep looking at their definition going.
Yeah, yeah. So I think our problem is that we satisfy the definition but we do not quite like a
duck. Yes, when we, when I push the publish podcast button in our podcast software, that is not
publishing. It is different for some reason that I haven't worked out. And it's definitely not just
because they forgot to put the word written in their definition of a FAN Zine. It could just be
written but then I thought but if I did a FAN Zine that was all art and contained no words,
would that count? Oh, and I submit that it would. I mean, I submit that's a graphic novel now,
Alison. No, but it was good. Good people won in various categories. Good things got voted for,
which is nice. There were 66 voters this year and Alison has an observation.
Yeah, so quite a lot of these voters think that the hugos are a bad thing and terrible and don't
reward the right sorts of things. And I am going to say that if you 66 people get on and vote in
the hugos, those of you who have Wilcon memberships, you probably would get some of the things you
like onto the ballot. Because a lot of things that you like just kind of dribble under the
ballot in the FAN categories and yeah, vote. I mean, it's a bit, you know, nominate, it's a bit late
for nomination now but it's not too late to vote. So I find myself, it's interesting because I feel
very much at the time part of the FAN awards community and yet they're kind of persistent
hatred of the hugos. I don't like, I kind of think the hugos are quite a good thing and
not at all bad and it would be good if people who would like them to go to better things voted
for those better things and nominated those better things and talked about those better things.
John is a great fan of talking about the things you like loudly and often in the hopes that people
notice. So I'm going to model that behaviour over the next year. I like Alison. She's good. Liz is
alright too. I was going to say, Liz has just flipped me the bird listeners. Welcome to the
Oxford Mutual Appreciation Society. I am Alison and I like Liz and John.
So, yeah, no, I think and actually you've just said something that massively distills a lot of my
thoughts about Corflu and the FAN awards which are that more and more I find that my perception
of that small slice of fandom is that it defines itself in terms of negativity towards other slices
of fandom that I am also in and although I like going to Corflu's and I like the FAN award,
it is very difficult for me because whenever I interact with them, I am constantly reminded
that there are lots of things I like that I am wrong to like and I find that very difficult
and I think that is why I find it slightly frustrating sometimes. But I would say I was not,
I think the FAN awards went to good winners and I did vote in the FAN awards. I don't know if the
things I voted for won awards. Yeah, well, most of the things I voted for did win
more so than in other. All right, taste maker. No, it's not that it's quite a small constituency
and it's a very, very good, kind of obvious, like portable storage. I think one best
fan of FAN for Stenzine and I have just got portable storage in the post and goodness,
it's amazing. It'll be my pick next time unless something very strange happens.
We can link to the summary of the winners and the full voting breakdown.
We can non-exclusively reveal what won. So, the winners were in order of presentation
the cover for Littlebrook 11 which was drawn by Ulrika O'Brien. Jerry Kalfman was awarded the
Best Letter Hack award. Ulrika O'Brien also took home best fan artist Mark Plummer, friend of the
podcast, took home best fan writer. Best One Shot was Dandrous Visions edited by Sandro Bond,
Rob Jackson and Pat Verzi. Best Verzi was this here, Best Genzine was possible storage and number
one fan face was Nick Fairey. And for those of us who were at the awards ceremony, there was a very
funny bit where the first three awards announced were either Jerry Kalfman or somebody he published
in Littlebrook. So, that was quite amusing. And in general, because Jerry was the MC for the awards.
Good stuff. But yeah, congratulations to all the winners. Jerry Kalfman won Best Letter Hack,
which is great and Mark was second, which is also great. And there are a lot of other letter hacks
in there. But the letter hacks are overwhelmingly male and I don't think that absolutely reflects
the people who are writing to fanzines and I think some women write very good letters to fanzines too
and I would like to see this kind of tacit assumption that all the people who are writing letters to
fanzines are boys be addressed in future voting chaps. This is a...
I would like to say that you could nominate Alison for Best Letter Hack, but my experience is she
only locks fanzines. She's got articles in. If my Lullzine is anything to go by, she's written as
One Lock and it was for her own article, which I thought was very great. Have you sent me a Lullzine
since then? You sent me a Lullzine, but it just reprinted something that you'd already...
Oh, quite possibly. I just thought it was bloody great. I just... I really enjoyed it.
I did get a... I did get one vote for Best Letter Hack, but that was not in fact the letter hacker.
Either of the letter hacks I was thinking of or many of... there are many other great female
letter hacks who are writing letters to fanzines and um and you should look out for it's Claire and Sandra.
[Music]
Okay, so my pick is very science fictional and you'll understand why it kind of...
it breaks a lot of assumptions we have about I think economics like as a science mostly,
but also like some other sciences, which is that I, a millennial, have purchased a house
and my house is great and it is incredibly esf-nal. So, hurrah! It has lots of science fiction in it
listeners and I've just finished setting up my board game shelf and... right, no, sorry, I lie.
I've just set up my games that are books and folders of cards shelf, which is worryingly full
and I hadn't quite appreciated how much stuff I have until I put it all in one place. It's got
my netrunner cards on it, Johnny. So that's good. I have a pick, which is which I am currently
listening to My Real Children by Joe Walton. This is quite an old book and I'm listening to it as
an audiobook for reasons that are really complicated but I'm super enjoying it. It is a book in a
category called Sliding Doors after the movie with Gwyneth Paltrow, which had two totally different
versions of London, none of which neither of which bore any resemblance to reality. I don't know.
The idea that you have a character who makes a choice and worlds spin in different directions
as a result of that choice. My Real Children starts off feeling as if it is going to have almost no
science fiction elements whatsoever but as the world views digress it... the worlds are quite
different and they are quite different in some quite subtle ways and not necessarily in the ways
that you might expect and the obviously our woman has two very different lives in the two
different halves of the novel and I am enjoying it very much. I'm not quite finished yet though
but I'm expecting to carry on enjoying it until the end of about 90% of the way through at the moment.
So that is my pick for this week. My Real Children by Joe Walton, who is a fantastic author.
Just fantastic. I have only read among others but I did thoroughly enjoy it. I read it when it was on
the Hugo Ballot and I did really like it but I have not read any of Joe's other work. So I should
rectify that at some point. I also really really like Farthering and it sequels the small changes
which is kind of a trilogy about a science fictional version of the mithards. I love it.
I've had this audiobook for a very long time but for various reasons I had not read it and I got
to the end of my Hugo nomination reading and went I cannot read any fiction unless I do it by audiobook
because I'm so busy at the moment so I'm doing it as an audiobook. So normally I am
split my reading so the science fiction gets read on e-book or paper and the kind of self-help
books are what I normally do as audiobook because they just kind of wash over me and I don't ever
get any better. I find non-fiction. I find non-fiction content is a lot easier to listen to than fiction.
It just goes in my head better. That's why I like podcasts. I am going to pick. Oh I want to read this.
The Last Graduate by Naomi Novick which is a sequel to a deadly education which Alison has
previously picked as one of her picks. Yes so I read the sequel. I mean I enjoyed a deadly
education but I didn't love it. I just I didn't really get on with the protagonist very much
basically. So a dedication and a last graduate are both set in you know a magical school called
the scholar mants where there are lots of deadly monsters ready every turn to try and kill all the
young young magicians in the school and in the first one. Why most schools? Yeah and in the first one
we see the protagonist go from kind of you know the the outcast who is you know friends with no one
very much just her own thing to kind of you know getting a sort of you know group of friends around
her and making some connections and working out kind of her place in things but because of that in
the first one you see a go from someone who's sort of very prickly and standoffish and you know
connected with no one and I didn't find that particularly fun to read whereas in the second one
it's kind of it picks up immediately. She's basically now got a group of people that she knows and
can trust and it focuses more on basically how this magical school and its structure is basically
and I'm gonna it's not this is not really a spoiler but you know that the magical school is
essentially terrible and people with the most power and privilege and wealth in a magical sense
are gonna do okay and those who don't are probably gonna get eaten by the end of their first year
and the second book definitely is starting to kind of dismantle this and say actually maybe
this system is not that great and actually maybe the whole system of how the magical enclaves
work in the world is not that great and you can see like the protagonist finding her way to a way
where she can do something to change this with the help of the kind of friends and supporters
she now has around her. Now the key thing about this is that the reason she can do this is that she
is an immensely immensely powerful wizard so that also feels a bit like a you know a bit of a sort of
sort of like death ex machina kind of thing that she it only works because she's incredibly
powerful and has an incredibly powerful ally so if you can get with that then it's pretty good.
Is the daughter of an incredibly powerful wizard as well so it's a bit of that going on too?
Yes I mean there's still some things I just like I think the pacing is still a bit off and it kind
of drags a bit in the second half. The first book had some problems with its depictions of like
non-white characters and I think that has improved because it's focusing more on
you know it's focusing more on different aspects of privilege I think so so I felt this one was
was somewhat better but the kind of protagonist is still of mixed heritage which
is basically very rarely mentioned I almost completely forgotten about that and then it kind of
get mentioned about halfway through and I'm like oh yes that was a backstory and also the ending is
like oh yes of course that happened I knew that was going to happen because that's the way you have
to keep the tension going for the third book but other than that I did enjoy it and I will read
the third or which I think has the potential to be a very different sort of story in the way that
the second book leaves it and yeah I enjoyed it. It's also one of those books that you absolutely
like devour like I think I read it over two days or something you just sit down it's very
more rich and you keep turning the pages which is definitely one of Noremeneurvic skills.
I assume that the point about her being a powerful wizard and having a powerful mother
is not in order to effect change to class-based systems in the real world you also need to have
a little bit of privilege to help you along right so like that doesn't seem like a bad point to me.
Yeah yeah but the point is that the reason she is a very powerful wizard who has a very powerful
mother but does not herself have privilege is because her mother explicitly rejected it before
the series of book starts so so she's been kind of she's kind of been set up as an outsider star
you know. Yeah I mean I haven't read the second book yet.
Yes but I mean there's kind of magical power and there's kind of you know there's sort of two
aspects so there's raw magical power and yeah the structural power of how the kind of wizarding
society is structured and she has the former but absolutely does not have the latter and it's how
she kind of teams with people who have the latter essentially. I mean it does feel in in some ways
like a bit of a reposter to Harry Potter where you know magical society is completely broken
and no one seems to be bothered by this. It's very clearly a reaction to Harry Potter.
I quite like the way in the first book and it sounds like in the second book that it is
kind of challenging some of the underlying class assumptions that are in the Harry Potter books
that's good. And which don't get challenged despite the fact that you think that the Harry
Potter novels are setting them up for challenge it turned out that it was much easier and better
for rolling in terms of her success to just kind of perpetrate them perpetuate them.
Yeah so so this is good in that way. That was the Octa thought podcast and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me and it's goodbye from me.
[Music]
I will find a photograph of me to put in the show notes which demonstrates how sweaty I get when I
dance and the answer is very so like I was at a wedding disco and like I'm just so sweaty.
I don't know if you can tell how sweaty I am from the photo but it's a great photo so
it's going in the show notes anyway.
As long as it's a great photo it can go in the show notes I think.
Okay that photo can oh god that photo could go in the show notes that's quite funny photo.
Anyway I think a lot of this should probably go because we're talking nonsense and we're still
on the letters of comment. Did you miss us listeners are you happy we're back we're talking nonsense
and we're still in the letters of comment. I've really missed you guys.
That's not even your wedding is it John? No that is my friend Chris's wedding.
There is a photo of me at a different wedding in which I am sweaty yeah which is this wedding.
You just always tie your tie around your head if you get a bit sweaty.
Obviously why else is it therefore? Spilling ketchup on oh god that's quite intense that is
that is very intense. I look like I've just been working out in the gym in that last one.
That's a proper proper sway mess. You look like you're about to hack a hole in a door with an axe
and stick your head through it John. I was gonna say you look like you should be carrying a big
sword with murderous intent to that one. Huddley you guys might be able to see can you see these
pictures like directly on my Facebook if I just post this link in can you just go through because
there's like a bunch of them from the just got like a you just have like an album of John being
sweaty. So it's a very niche Facebook album. Are you like sending you know paid access links to it?
Oh these are all gold. I know right but I go hard at weddings Liz I when I'm dancing I'm
moving. I'm moving about and I am sweaty. Good thought. There is like not a single photo of you.
I have a dynamic man with dynamic. Even the one where it's just literally your head over
someone else's shoulder. Oh and now you're on a convention panel and you look you look
more sober. I've hit you far. Boo boo. Oh there's one of you as a there's one of you as the pub
boar. Oh yeah no that is fair. I look like I look like the old boy that you'd find in the
members area a cricket ground in that photo. Anyway um we were doing a podcast I think. There's quite a
long digression about sweaty John. I mean that could mostly go. It's not all gold John. You know
you notice I don't know if you've noticed but in the show notes I've updated the name of the
episode to embrace the sweat. So you may be you may be slightly missing everything when my editorial
vision is going on this one which is full sweaty. The theme music for this episode was
Fanfare for Space by Kevin McLeod and Competec.com used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep. Beep.
[BLANK_AUDIO]