Well the issue is that we don't have any show notes because we've been busy.
So if it's less structured than normal...
There, this is not going to be our most structured moment.
Do we actually not have any show notes?
Nope.
We have nothing.
Jesus.
But loads of things happened.
We should introduce ourselves properly.
In case anyone here doesn't know who we are.
But just put your hand up.
Does anyone here not listen to Octa Thorpe?
Interesting.
Okay.
Does anybody here listen to Octa Thorpe who does not yet have a ribbon?
I mean, they're all going to need a ribbon because they're all about to listen to Octa Thorpe
so they all qualify.
But no, you're right Liz.
We should introduce who we are.
Apparently.
Really?
Yeah.
Well we could do that after we do the actual podcast opening.
We could do the podcast opening we always do and then we could do introductions.
That's a good idea.
I'm glad you came up with that Alison.
But I was worried that you wouldn't, you'd do it instead of the opening to the podcast.
Okay, fine.
This is what it's always like, Liz.
Yep.
It's true.
Well no, because usually we're sober.
So, you know, strap in.
Hello everyone and welcome to Octa Thorpe, the podcast of science fiction and science fiction
fandom.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
And for those in the room who have not yet listened, we are a podcast that discusses things
and we are people.
That's a good introduction.
I've nailed it, right?
Yeah.
Do you think they might watch it or who we actually are?
Sorry, I'm John.
I'm a podcaster, self-evidently.
I am also the head of communications for the 2024 EasterCon by day.
Thank you, thank you.
By day, I am a space plasma physicist and by night I play board games.
I'm Alison and I've been struggling because every time I think of a list of all the things
I have to plug, I forget some of them.
But I am director of communications for the 2023 EasterCon conversation, which you sure
all join.
I run a tiny micro business called Stoshirts and you can get T-shirts, stand up and bottle
your T-shirt, John.
You get T-shirts, including the exclusive Oxford Slope T-shirt at eastercon.stoshirts.com
or you wouldn't be able to buy some things from my store if I had any time to spend all
the store this weekend.
I, what else am I doing?
Quite a bit.
Drinking?
What?
Drinking usually.
I've also been drinking in the car anyway.
I'm ready, meet me later because I want to meet everyone at the E-Con every time.
I don't always manage it, but I often do.
I'm Liz, I am the only member of the podcast not currently working on an E-Con committee.
But, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no,
because also you are, I'm the only member not working on a world con bid at the moment,
so, or no an actual seated world con.
Not a world con bid, some of us are working on, well, I'm not actually officially working
on a world con.
I'm working a little bit on my world con.
So Liz is working on a world con, so therefore thinks that that counts as not working on a
Easter con.
I can give it up at any time.
When I'm not working on a world con, I do this podcast with John and Alison, and my
day job is doing genetics of tropical medicine.
And I'm usually in Thailand, by the way, I live in Thailand and therefore I make the
other two podcasts at ungodly times of the morning in order to fit with my time zone.
So yeah, it's a massive novelty to be in the room with them.
Yes.
It is actually really, really nice because we've been in the room, we kind of got some
time together last summer, but we weren't actually doing the podcast.
So this is the first time we've done the podcast live in the three of us in front of an audience.
So that is fantastic.
We just said that if we had shown it.
Probably.
So, yeah, there's been news, there's been an Easter con.
Has everyone enjoyed the Easter con?
Yeah.
And it is the first Easter con since the Easter con in 2019, which was held a long way from
here.
No, sorry, it was held here.
First in person.
First in person Easter con.
That is true.
So yeah, what do we think of this Easter con, peeps?
What have we enjoyed?
We should talk about the building session.
So I have this query, which is it turns out that people can remember when they think
about it for contested Easter cons.
And I was on one of the committees of all four of those bits.
Am I the asshole?
Well, I think I just think I like that statistic and enormous amount.
Thank you for bringing it into my attention.
What were the four bits that were contested, Alison?
So the very first Easter con I was on was Folly con.
And we, at the time, they were great Easter con wars.
There was great ideological split about what the Easter con should be like.
And the other bid, which was 88 in Harrogate, was very much a kind of fancy, all-time fancy
in fans bid.
And we were kind of the, actually, Easter con should be a massive party for everybody type
bid.
How things change?
The following year, that was quite, that we won by miles for lots of reasons.
But then the next year, there was a bid which people didn't think was a very good bid, which
was unopposed.
I won't say what it was, but Chris O'Shea and I ran a spoof bid against it.
And we very nearly ran and just had to go to a lobby vote.
It was only because we stood up before the lobby vote and said, "Do not give us the Easter
con, you horrible people that we lost the lobby vote."
So that was the only other lobby vote that there ever was.
The last year of this year.
So what was, how did you enjoy?
Because I've been going to Easter con since 2007, so yesterday was my first contested bid.
So who here remembers a previous contested bid session they wrapped by show of hands for
the streaming audience and listeners at home?
That's about 10 people, I would say.
So probably about 20 or 30 people who don't.
So it was not full.
It was fun.
I mean, it wasn't...
It was not at all fun.
It was probably fun for people on the 24 bid, which was not contested.
It was not fun.
I mean, it was a thing that we did, but I didn't find it.
I don't really like competitions.
No, it felt very strange because there were essentially two groups of people I like who
are both my friends.
And then I have to pitch which one is, you know, not more my friend, but which one is
giving me the Easter con that I would like to see more.
And inevitably, one group of people I know is going to be disappointed.
And so I do prefer it when they're not contested.
I mean, I guess you can say that it is a good thing if they get contested because it does
kind of force you to up your game a little bit.
You can't just assume that you are going to be voted in.
You do have to put in a lot of effort there to really present what you're going to do
and have a good, you know, a good kind of solid idea of what you want to do.
But on the other hand, I also can't really see any difference between, you know, what
the 2023 bids presented me as contested bids and what the 2024 bid presented me as a very
polished bid that was unopposed.
Yeah, I did feel a little bit like I think it was all very kind of amenable and I know
the bids have talked and that you've discussed about sites and things like that.
But it did feel a bit like I don't like seeing my friends, you know, disagree.
So I feel like sometimes you have to do things that involve competition, that you don't always
get to say, well, we're just going to let things ride on in a steady state and take
what we're offered and that was part of the metafation plan that bid.
Our commissions then had a lot of personal challenges.
Maybe we expected some of them and we didn't expect all of them and it's been, we have
worked incredibly hard.
So it's quite nice to win, I guess.
But there's this, oh, and now we have to run the East con next year.
Okay.
Breathe.
I mean, being contested meant that we've done quite a lot of work that I think if we
were an uncontested bid, we wouldn't have done yet.
Liz did remark that it does mean that she can't take the piss out of East con for the
next two years, but we've reassured her that she can, we'll just pretend she isn't.
Well, yeah, you're always going to get an official response from a director of communications
of the relevant East con, aren't you?
It's not me, we have to say own Brandon on message for two years, John.
Oh.
Only one year for Allison.
That's true.
Yeah, I challenge Allison stay on brand for two minutes.
When we were doing the Q and A for the bid, we have quite a lot of Q and A. So there are
areas where there was like, this is, this is the line and this is not the line and please
try to keep reasonably close to the thing that is the line and not the thing that is
not the line.
But for most things, I was just kind of like, we will do better as a bid if you are reasonably
relaxed and use your own voice to say things that you think are true.
The thing that will keep you on message is that you've been in the team rather than because
you've learned to set up lines.
And it's always worked for me except for the 99,000 times a test.
So the, yeah, no, the lines you set up as the communications person for your convention
should be reflections of the team that is running the convention.
So if you have done that properly, their natural voices should be hearing relatively
close to the lines without too much effort.
And that was certainly the approach we took for our bid.
And so it doesn't matter if people extemporize around a point because it was their thoughts
that shaped our policy anyway.
So that is where our policy came from.
So yeah, this all dreadfully serious.
Sorry, everyone.
Liz, tell the joke.
I don't have any jokes.
I will just say I've checked on Discord and apparently we should repeat audience heckles
so the streaming audience can hear them.
We will repeat all good heckles.
So if we don't repeat it, it's because it was bad heckle.
Yeah, what do we think?
So, what, but what have we enjoyed about Eastacorn?
Because I asked that a while ago and we didn't really actually answer it other than the bid
session.
Well, I was going to say, well, we've, you want an Eastercon and I want an Eastercon.
Liz, have you lost everything this weekend?
I've won by not winning an Eastercon.
But have you lost everything this weekend?
Yeah, I also may have lost something.
I mean, I lost my coat twice.
I lost my jumper like three times.
Liz.
That's what you mean, right?
This is why we need show notes.
Liz, have you lost an award nomination this weekend?
No, we haven't lost the nomination.
Still got the, we will all, it's honour just to be nominated.
And then, and then we were sat in the audience and we were like, yeah.
And then, you know, in our heads, you were like, nah.
It wasn't, didn't mind, didn't mind at all.
Oh, no, I mean, sorry, we didn't mind.
We were completely, it was fine.
Were you very disappointed?
No, not particularly.
I mean, it was nice to be nominated and something good won and it was nice to be in the room
when that happened.
Yes, no, that was true.
Yeah, we were, because, because the thing about the BS event, I mean, thank you everyone
who nominated us on veg for us.
We were very grateful, but it was basically five beautiful swans.
And, and, and then us.
And what were we?
And we were a pedal-o.
[LAUGHTER]
So like, and you might want the pedal-o, the pedal-o is good, you can pedal it, but it
isn't a swan.
But it's ironic and we want to talk about this because we are not eligible for the fan
awards for some reason, but we are eligible for the BSFA awards despite the fact that
in the eligibility criteria for the BSFA awards, it does say it's for a written work
of nonfiction.
Now, this therefore presumably means we were nominated for our show notes.
So thank you all very much for nominating the show notes.
I'm glad you appreciated them.
I spend a lot of time putting the links in.
So thank you all.
So all that fiction.
Surely, fiction.
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah, no, next time we'll be short of fiction.
No, fiction for younger readers.
[LAUGHTER]
We're going to have to stop swearing.
Fuck.
[LAUGHTER]
So the really interesting thing about the BSFA award nomination, well, there's two.
But the first one was that two days before the Eastcon, one Nicholas White, who is the
fangest of honor at this Eastcon, wrote a blog post in which he said, "Well, this is
my favourite of the nonfiction things, and I personally will be astonished if they don't
win by a large margin."
So we want to know is if anyone was in the room, was there some kind of test of Nicholas's
astonishment, should we?
I should say Nicholas is in the audience, and is very embarrassed by this.
[LAUGHTER]
It's like, people were like, because John was in the bar going, "Ha, Bob Beanie's going
to win."
And I was like, "Yeah, no, that makes a lot of sense if you think about who is a member
of the BSFA, but you have to remember that Nicholas White is a professional syphallogist,
and actually goes on to-- so imagine you were on BBC Northern Ireland now, Nicholas."
May I say that I am officially astonished?
[LAUGHTER]
[APPLAUSE]
But it's a pleasure to be here.
Well, and also this was very sneaky, because Nicholas said in that same blog post that one
of the reasons that he nominated us for the award this year was because he was in it last
year, and he's just been in it now, so it was a ruse.
Ha, ha, ha.
So I'm going to go around the room now, reading out all of your names.
[LAUGHTER]
It would take a register.
Hands up everyone who's been very busy this weekend.
Yeah, you could have assumed.
Look at it, me.
Now, you've all made a huge mistake, because if you didn't put your hand up, she now knows
that you're down for volunteering.
No, no, no.
So you could tell the time I'm more experienced senior managers than John.
I know that the people who will work for me in next year are the ones who did put their
hands up, not the ones who didn't.
That's how it works.
Well, the official line of 2024 is that we're bringing new blood into fandom.
So, you know--
Yeah, see, some people--
See, on brand.
Some people's communications directors manage their lives.
[LAUGHTER]
Liz was wrong, though.
It was about-- I think it was about five minutes, not two minutes.
So what an awesome.
[LAUGHTER]
For the people who've got short attention spans, that was before I went off topic random.
So yeah, but no, so convention.
Very good.
Hotel-- kind of slight winkle on the first day, but they handled it well with refunds
for people who had been affected.
I think that was a good response.
I don't think it was a good situation, but I think it is-- it was handled well in the
end.
I feel like there are solutions to cues that are three-hour long cues that do not involve
leaving the people in the three-hour long queue and managing the people who, for whom,
it will be catastrophic if they stand up for three hours, but not all the people for whom
it will be really incredibly irritating.
I feel like you should probably manage those people as well.
On the upside, this hotel's breakfast is really fine.
Yeah, it's good.
I kind of love the breakfast.
And also I got here Thursday, which is why I'm probably a bit more magnanimous about
the hotel queue that we should have sorted.
We should, as a convention, have interspersed ourselves to sort the cues out more than we
were able to, but that's partly because the conventions under volunteered.
Are you going to let Farah speak?
So just to clarify, we did actually try.
We turned up with a trolley to try and take luggage.
We offered to help people who needed access, and only about five accepted.
People-- I don't know why I think oddly enough it was because people were already stressed,
but people were actually refusing assistance.
We can do way better, but I don't want people to walk away thinking we didn't try to offer
assistance.
I don't want to suggest that it was the committee's fault here.
I do know a lot of-- because I used to work for the Department for Work and Pensions,
which used to be called the Department of Social Security.
I know a huge amount about queue-busting that I will bore you with at a bar sometime.
I did have a lot of fun.
I stayed up too late and got drunk.
So that was on Macbrand.
I feel like somebody said to me on about Saturday night that people in general seem more anxious
and strung out on average at this Easter card than normal.
And that has led to lots of-- you know, the concept of microaggression.
I mean, it's led to a lot of microfuckups, where things have just not gone quite as well
as they could because one of the parties in the interaction was strung out and exhausted.
But it was always me and I'm sorry.
But I don't know if that was also your possession.
Yeah, I think so.
I mean, I haven't been to a convention since Easter gone 2018.
I haven't been around this many people, probably for quite a long time.
I think I've forgotten in some ways how to deal with big groups of people and big crowds
and things like that.
So I found it more stressful than it would have been a few years ago.
So Alison and I both went to Corflu and Novricon.
And so because Corflu was only about 40 attendees and then Novricon was about 400, 300, 400.
And obviously this convention is bigger still.
We've kind of had the slow reintroduction, like releasing endangered petaloes into the
wild.
And so I don't think I found it as much of a culture shot.
But I do remember finding Corflu a bit odd and then Novricon a bit odd.
So I do sympathize.
But for me, I think I'd already processed a lot of that prior to this weekend.
Although it is really good to see Liz.
And Liz is a great stunt Liz.
So thank you for being our Liz Liz.
It's been really good to see a lot of people.
Yeah.
So I'm very sorry to all the people who I have seen, but only very, very briefly because
I've been running around an awful lot.
I think one of the things that's happened as we've emerged from isolation is that we
started doing online things.
And now we can do in person things again.
We're all doing all the online things as well.
And that means you're doing twice the things.
And there's kind of a things issue.
Can you give me a cheer if before this weekend you had a wordle streak and at the time that
this is being said, you don't please cheer.
Yeah.
See that?
Because like a lot of my words will streak now, but it's one.
Yeah, that's fair.
So I lost my wordle streak when I moved house and I was like, oh, I'll be able to keep up
with that.
And then the real life was like, no, you won't.
So I was I was I was wondering whether the convention would would would end some wordle
streaks.
And yeah, has anybody lost their duolingo streak?
Yeah, I have done that.
I wasn't going to I was going to renew it, but then I got distracted by beer and conversation
so I didn't.
I looked at my phone and it was about half.
I looked at my phone is about half past 11 and that looked at my phone is about half
past 12 and I was like, oh, no, it's tomorrow.
But yes, don't do your duolingo on the podcast, Alison.
Talk about yourself.
So Liz, yes.
How have you found being back in the UK and how have you found being at your convention
other than stressful?
It's really nice.
I mean, I guess it's the same.
I mean, the same boat was most of you in that I have not seen most of the people here
for three or four years.
And you know, the thing is normally I might come here every couple of years and it'd be
like, oh, I haven't seen any of you for two years, but actually for everyone, everyone
is in the same boat that they haven't seen people for two or three years.
I mean, I am finding it strange that this is, you know, the most people I've been around
without a mask on for probably two years.
That is a little bit strange to me.
I still find kind of how things are going in the UK a little bit weird.
And also I do honestly keep leaving my coat in places because I forget I have a coat.
I haven't carried a jumper around for two years at this point.
What's happened years to the cultural weekend because it's quite hot.
No, it's not.
I feel like we didn't try a little something.
I mean, I'm a little bit hot in here, but I imagine in here is less hot than Bangkok.
Yes.
It's quite nice in here.
No, everyone is sweating in the audience.
Sorry.
It is quite a hot room.
I mean, it's got to be because it's got all these beautiful people in it.
We have kind of talked about the fact that both of our East cons are seated.
I mean, I don't know if we're all we're seated.
Yeah, we're seated.
Yeah.
But some of them might be standing elsewhere.
We don't know.
Yeah, yeah.
Some of the jokes this weekend have been recycled for a very, very long time ago because it
turned out that one of the reasons that the bid session had to be carried over was the
bid session started late yesterday.
And the reason the bid session started late yesterday is that all of the bids were asked
to supply presentations on USB stick by one o'clock.
And it turned out that our USB sticks weren't compatible with the conventions USB stick.
And the solution to this was a very wide range of interestingly shaped dongles.
So we had to stop episode title in the newsletter a decade ago, but I feel like, you know, we
had several different dongles we used to get the presentation.
So it took them forever to get the presentations onto the thing.
And this would be fine if you were the sort of bid that had finalized your presentation
on Thursday rather than say 1259 on Sunday.
You find a nice presentation on Thursday?
I think we swapped out a photo on Saturday.
That was a bit stressful.
I didn't enjoy that.
Yeah, I'll never turn a face John ever again.
Stop gazing at John during the podcast.
I know normally on zoom you can just stay at him.
Oh no.
So someone in the discord asked what I've enjoyed about the con.
And I've really liked the I think the beer's been really good.
I really think that obviously like huge things Martin Hall passed away in between the last
in person East con on this one.
But I think the conventions and a great job of kind of making sure that that will work
well.
And there was initial rumors about cider, but there was lots of cider.
So that's good.
And I've enjoyed the program items I've been to, which admittedly have been not as many
as I'd have liked to go to, but that was lovely.
Really like 90 minute slots with our long program in them because I just really like
having the time to get around.
And also you've been to people in the middle of that slot and being able to chat for 15
minutes is really nice.
And but mostly the people like like yeah, I for me East con is mostly for me it's coming
home and seeing everyone like seeing the family.
And that is that has been the nicest thing and I've really missed that.
So I'm really glad we're here.
And I'm yeah, happy, very happy that we've had that opportunity.
Yeah, I really like I really like the 90 minutes lots.
Although it means I go to slightly fewer program items and I otherwise would because I can't
cram in one an hour.
I think I think the number of people here feels nice.
It feels pleasant.
It doesn't feel like we're crammed in.
I haven't had too many problems getting seats.
I haven't had too many problems getting to the bar in the real L bar.
It feels like this is sort of the right number of people to be rattling around this hotel.
And I don't know how I feel if there are an extra 300, 400 people in this space which
I think it could theoretically take.
So it's going to be interesting to see how that works.
Certainly in terms of things like the economics of Easter cons, you know, is there a point
where they become viable or point where we can have that much space with, you know, that
number of people in and not be sort of crammed into hotels with a thousand people in the
future.
It makes me feel more comfortable.
It just feels nice.
You can wander around and stop for chat at the side of the corridor without blocking
the entire convention behind you, that kind of thing.
I have also been to quite a lot of program.
I went to three guests of honor talks which were all really good.
Actually, there were three guests of one of interviews that were all really good and
all had really good interviewers and guests with lots of thoughtful and interesting things
to say.
And I will now go and buy more of their books if they have books.
And Nicholas, if you do have any merchandise available, let me know.
He's got t-shirts that just say "I'm astonished."
Nicholas White is astonished.
I think there's a...I would say Nicholas White won't say it himself, but he's just taken
his...he finally took his website off dive journal after 109 years.
And that's some street.
So he's now at...from the heart of Europe.eu.
We'll put the link in the show note.
For anyone who'd stopped reading Nicholas because he was on live journal and it was owned by
nefarious Russian influences, he's not there anymore.
He was the last person I was going to live journal for, I think.
So we shouldn't be on live journal.
I shouldn't have set up the ought to thought live journal.
Fair enough.
Instagram are not convinced we're real and that is a sticking point.
I would say I'm discussing it with them, but really I'm just screaming into a void.
Which is often a feeling I have.
Especially, no, that's mean.
I don't feel that when I record ought to thought.
LAUGHTER
So there's a comment not a question in the discord which is future conventions should
have a streaky room where you go to do your streaks.
Ooh, the streak, the streak up.
Every day, the streak up, everyone just goes and does their duolingo and they'll, "Oh,
I like that."
You should do that at 2023.
You heard it here.
Yeah.
And DC has asked an actual question in the discord which is with streaky bacon.
Question rock.
Ahhh.
So obviously the answer to that question panelists is yes.
No.
Do you not like streaky bacon?
No, I don't like streaky bacon.
You and his fan, you can have a very large argument after the panel.
So...
Yeah, when his fan is right and loses rock.
So on zoom I can also just stare at Liz or all the time we're recording.
Just say.
Well, especially when there's a gecko.
So I'm going to suggest we open it up to the audience in the room because we've been
taking comments and questions from the online audience and I feel like we should let our
physical audience say things.
Oh, but before we do that, Alison has reminded me by whispering that we're going to do a
beer of comment.
So we've got a beer of comment listeners who have listened to that episode will remember
that the people at this never happens sent us a beer.
Is anyone on Twitter or Instagram?
This is our photo opportunity for this podcast just saying now.
Christina Lake and I've got some alt text on this if you're kind of just listening to
this.
Christina Lake and Doug Bell sent us a beer from Polly's Brewery called This Never Happened
because their podcast or Christina's and Lillian's and Ian's was called This Never
Happens but they we had a kind of how to keep on podcasting panel yesterday that John
was on and the answer is you keep on podcasting by continuing to podcast and this this never
happens to not.
So this is a beer.
This is not the Instagram opportunity.
I'll tell you you all know when the Instagram opportunity happens.
Yep, we made it we made a promise and some promises can't be unmade.
Apparently.
I argued but.
So the plan was that if we were all managed to be at EasterCon we would share this beer
which we're going to do now.
Okay.
Right.
Can we get three straws over here?
I might take the rest of that beer in a glass if that's alright.
Good, good, good.
It's 13% and it's a quadruple IPA.
So drinking it from a straw is like it's an adventure.
Like it is an opinionated beer.
It's nice but drinking it from a store is a good way to get very drunk.
It's something you get us three tooth glasses please.
You know these ones these little ones.
I'm just going to have mine in this empty my old glass.
Oh no I haven't.
I'm going to use my water glass again.
Great radio.
Right then let's go to questions.
So I think there is a person in the penultimate row with his hand up that is wearing a black
thing.
There we go.
That works.
T-shirt John.
It was James Shields.
Yeah just we were talking about the queuing.
I was very impressed that the Reg desk took the initiative of introducing a badge delivery
service to people waiting in line.
That is good.
That is a good point.
Well done.
That was an excellent point and that was a good idea.
Actually I was really impressed.
I thought oh god look at the checking queue.
I'll go and register thinking registration would have quite a big queue because they had
to check vaccination certificates and things and that was really efficient.
They were really on top of that and I had my badge in five minutes.
So then I went back and stood in the whole queue.
I went to Reg.
I went can I register myself as Stephen Kane and Marianne Kane and Jonathan Kane and they
said do you have the vaccination certificates for all of those people?
I went oh no I do not have the vaccination certificates for any of those people because
I did not bring my phone but then I remembered that my watch has a tiny vaccination certificate
on it.
Thank you to Duncan for posting a picture in the thread on Discord.
I know that I am the only one looking at the camera which I think reflects my general approach
to photographs so that is good.
I think I was kind of making sure I didn't throw the beer across the room.
I was trying to get some beer.
Do we have?
It is really nice look at it.
It is.
Yes no it is lovely.
It is a very strange colour.
Hang on and I have got to log it on untapped.
I had almost forgotten.
Oh we do have to log it on untapped possibly with that photo.
That is a lot of effort.
But.
While they are logging things untapped do we have any more questions from the audience?
Let's go to the person on the end of the front row here first please and then we will come
to the person over here.
Is there a possible code of conduct violation for having a streak up?
I did wonder that when I said it but then I thought oh if we just skate right past it
no one will notice.
But yes we have to call it a streak.
No it is not better.
We call it the being on your phone meet up.
That will work.
This is very nice.
So it is sort of like Tosi.
I see why it is called a milkshake IPA.
It is also very strong.
We did try and get a beer called octa thought.
Because obviously we did.
We are very conceited.
That is I emailed the brewery on and tapped I found that does a beer called octa thought
and they said they stopped making it in 2005.
So if any of you are brewers please do make a beer called octa thought.
By that I mean Dave if you are in the audience still there you are.
I can see you.
But yes Dave home brews.
So this beer is brewed in mould in North Wales.
And I have family who live quite near mould and we went to mould one Saturday afternoon
about 15 years ago quite a while and they have their first ever food festival.
And this food festival is called a taste of mould.
And they only served blue cheese.
They had all sorts of things.
We just thought about the actual local residence had not noticed it was a thing.
So do you have any other questions in the audience?
There is one the person on the front row who is the opposite sides to the person we took
earlier.
So at some events there are perspex panels between each participant in order to prevent
cross contamination with pathogens.
I am wondering if there is a case for opaque perspex panels to stop Alison looking at her
co podcasters.
So basically what you are advocating is that we buy Alison a set of blinkers.
OK so the really strange thing about this is that earlier it was like well obviously
Alison does not zoom she could look at John or look at Liz for as long as she likes.
But in fact when I am on zoom I actually look at me.
I am pathologically unable to drag my eyes away from my own face.
So if I made a zoom with one other person I only look I turn my own self view off but
generally speaking if I am a zoom with two or more other people I just look at me.
So every time I do a hard stare at Alison on the podcast it has been wasted.
No, no because I have seen them and they are very good.
There is nothing better than Liz giving Alison a hard stare.
I feel really bad that because I think it may be right that I have never seen it.
I have seen many of the hard stares that you mentioned.
Have you had any other questions about the podcast you have generally about the Easter
Con or about anything else at all.
Otherwise we will have to go into our reserve show notes that we also haven't written.
Well we haven't done pics.
I wish to pics.
And we have all had loads of time to read and consume science fiction media over the last
two weeks.
So over the last week could be recorded.
It was our previous episode dropped on this Thursday.
This is an early record.
I have a pic.
I could do a pic.
Let's see if we have any questions from the audience.
I think we should take a question from the man with, where dressed entirely and black
apart from his pic socks and who doesn't have any hair and I wasn't supposed to say
man either.
I am not doing very well.
Whose name is Johnny in the front row.
Also is that like a TFL mask?
Like a tube mask?
Your mask is Victoria line, Machette.
Oh my god, that's amazing.
Oh god.
It's not really Machette though because if you made a mask out of Machette it wouldn't
stop your, okay so for people who don't know, Machette.
Hands up if you don't know what Machette is.
Right, so that's enough, right?
Machette is the heavy duty upholstery fabric that is used on buses and trains.
It wears, it has a pile of a number of different lengths and it wears differently which means
it can cope with essentially the way that people behave on Saturday night on the London
Transport Network and each underground line has its own Machette and it turns out, when
we moved into our house, when we worked out last year that we needed a new sofa I was
like, it turns out you'd get a sofa and a post it in a Victorian line Machette and
my husband is a very mild man and person but he beat up that.
I mean I think he's kind of said that I might be able to get like a Machette poof or...
You can get cushions with a Machette.
Yeah, a Machette cushion.
You'll now need to take the Machette mask.
So Johnny is wearing a mask in Victoria line Machette and we'll try and get a picture
of Victoria line Machette into the show notes.
Hey Team Petalo.
So the question I had was how do you feel about the dealer's room, more like a dealer's
happy to oven as a structure, has that been helpful having separate little rooms or difficult
things?
It's a question to me because I have a dealer on.
Overall, the whole idea but I think you've been doing a lot of stuff.
We'll all have a different answer.
Liz, do you want to go first?
Yeah, for me I prefer the dealers to be in one big room because yeah some of the smaller
rooms they've been a bit full and I haven't drifted in so maybe I don't kind of drift
past as many stalls and maybe get pulled in and buy things.
And also I've really not been to many of the dealers kind of, there's sort of a crossroads
of corridors and there are dealers past there and I don't think I even realised they were
kind of dealers quite, are there no dealers?
Okay, far far is taking a head and telling me they're not dealers past there.
Okay yeah, they're somewhere past that.
I don't know what direction because I've got lost a couple of times but basically I
don't think I got to some of the further away dealers so it's just a bit less visible I
guess because I didn't walk past them quite as many times and pop in but actually I've
bought very little from dealers anyway because I have no luggage allowance.
I think yeah so I have, I very confidently brought my suitcase and it was half full of
crap for the van van and I thought brilliant on the way home it will be half empty because
I will have no crap.
And then I somehow very rapidly filled it back up with crap and so I also haven't bought
much from the dealers because I did not really have the room in my suitcase but I quite like
the separate rooms because I like how kind of it breaks up the space and I like kind of
like exploring but I do agree that like if you miss one of the spaces, I think it's
easier to miss one of the spaces than it would be in a larger room so I kind of, I
think there are pros and cons.
I definitely think given the space of this hotel it is, the way it has been done has
used the space in this hotel as well as possible.
I don't think there is a better way to do it in this venue so I do think it's been a
crack and drop generally.
Quite like the little dealers rooms and we managed to kind of get the windows open in
hours so we got some fluid flow of air but I have learnt, I think one of the things about
growing up, if it ever happens, is that you learn things about yourself and the thing
I have learnt about myself about this Eastercon is that I am never ever trading at an Eastercon
again.
If I want to take a dealers table at an Eastercon I am going to get an employee, an elf,
to do it for me because I have not really, I have spent about very little time on my
store, it's one of the things that has made it far harder.
So as I want to eat next week, octa-thop.stoshirts.com or Eastercon.stoshirts.com.
Brilliant, this has already been plugged in the Discord because people have been asking
for the link.
There are also questions which, there is a question in the Discord, one question which
I don't suppose you ask because the answer is obviously never, is when will John stop
flirting with tobes?
I mean I was going to say, I don't think I have ever flirted with tobes, I have just
connected with him, I have just connected with him on the level appropriate to his general
appearance.
And then the panel also, the Discord also says, are you all used to wearing headsets to monitor
your loudness?
And the answer to that is yes.
No?
So I don't think it's, I don't think Liz does.
Do you?
Liz just uses a headset mic so if she turns to look at something in the middle of recording,
the headset will move with her.
Whereas John and I both use mic mics so we know instantly if we've turned away from the
mic and lost our volume.
Yeah, that's true.
So I can't actually hear myself when I'm recording so I don't know what levels it's recording
at.
But I mean I have decided that as we've done like 55 episodes now, there might be something
to this podcasting thing.
Maybe I should buy a microphone and not use the free headset I got four years ago to do
every podcast.
And then John will be excited but then John will have to teach me how to use a microphone.
So you speak into it.
I am also excited.
This convention had a 60 minute, how to use a microphone workshop.
And I was like, well, I mean I'm quite fond of microphones that I quite like the whole
microphone thing but I don't think we need a 60 minute workshop but the one tip is monitor
your ear in ear so that if you are in the habit of turning to look at your co-host, people
can still hear what you're saying.
I hope everyone heard that but it was very funny.
That was a visual joke and the last part of the sentence for the benefit of JT and everybody.
I don't JT left us.
No, I think he's still there.
Oh, thank you.
I just want to say, I think we need to say it anyway.
We probably would have said it.
What I love is you were about to say something for the benefit of JT and then you started
complimenting JT before you did the thing.
It's like you knew what I was like when you started to podcast with me.
So I knew vaguely what you were like but less than I do now.
There was a question at the pop casting panel which is if you knew, if you...
I know I am aware of this.
So Alison said she turned away from the mic and said, can you just, you can't hear me
now or something of that effect?
We've forgotten which is the problem.
Only you had recorded it.
I know, right?
Oh, we didn't do the backup recording.
It was so trustworthy of JT that we haven't got our backup recording yet.
Yes, kind of good.
What's this report?
Ha ha ha ha ha.
For those listening, JT just says, sorry, am I supposed to be recording this and got
a pause break from the audience?
JT, we might need to swap someone out because clearly better spontaneous width than us.
Do we want to do pics?
We've got like seven minutes.
So do we have anything else to say on Easter come?
Maybe before we get to pics.
We exhausted the internet.
Oh yes, please join the 2023 and 2024 Easter Cons.
We would very much like to see everyone there in Telford and a mysterious void that may or
may not be inside time and space.
Okay, so I don't know about the rest of you but I have been in crunch for the Easter
Con for the last seven days.
Oh, and I was like, I've listened to something and it was like, oh, you are, which was my
pick for last week, that's the only thing.
So no, I have not consumed any science fiction or fantasy related content that wasn't directly
related to trying to get something done in time for the Easter Con any time in the last
168 hours.
Oh my God, I have overextended myself.
Anyway, I mean, I'm picking an actual book now.
Are we picking like favorite bits of Easter Con?
You, my view has always been that you can pick whatever you like.
All right, I'm going to pick an actual book and plug it then.
I read The Midnight Bargain by C.L. Polk, which is a kind of fantasy, regency romance in
which, you know, the whole process of kind of the marriage market is complicated by the
fact that people have magic and magic is essentially practiced only by men and women
in a prize, more for their ability to pass magic on to their sons than for their innate
own skills at it.
And it's about two women and one man who kind of end up making changes to this system and
working at how they personally can fit into this system.
And you know, there is a strong romance aspect to it of how can you actually have a romance,
you know, in this situation and how they end up.
And I really enjoyed it.
It was a good kind of pre-Easter Con, you know, fun, interesting read.
So there's your book recommendation for the panel.
Nice.
I, C.L. Polk is at the convention.
Is that right?
No, no, I don't think so.
They are on the Hugo finalist discourse.
So that might be what you're thinking of.
I could be what I think of.
Humblebrag.
That was a humble brag, Alison.
I saw you sneaking that in there.
The great thing about, this is something I'm going to say in the BS FA Awards bit, which
is the great thing about losing the BS FA award is that we had a speech ready at that
these next time we lose an award, which we think is going to be October.
We'll have that speech ready to not use again.
No, it will be September.
And this is something very strange happening at TryCon.
My pick is also a book.
So on the train down to London from Newcastle, it's quite a long train journey.
You could read a full novel.
So I read A Snake Falls to Earth by Darcy Little Badger, which is on the BS FA Ballot and
also on the Load Star Award Ballot.
And it is really great.
It's about a...
It's about girl and a snake.
Because Darcy Little Badger is amazing and she sort of explores Native American...
She writes with a Native American kind of perspective, which I find really interesting.
And I really enjoyed the book.
I thought it was really good.
And I've started reading "Redemptor" by Jordan Ifweku, but I haven't finished it yet.
So I'm not going to pick it.
But I might pick it next time.
"Sleak preview."
We might cut that out.
Yeah, I know we will do.
I think we should probably see if there's anything that...
Is there anyone...
Anyone was hoping that Oxford thought live would be like the bottom of this.
Good.
Funny.
Cajiran.
No, I'm asking the audience.
Oh.
And the Discord audience?
The Discord are...
I would describe the Discord currently as amusing themselves.
And...
I would recommend everyone go and read.
Go and read the Discord because it is very good.
I especially like the people who are commenting in the Discord who are also in the panel.
That is what Discord is so great.
Being able to be the snark for the panel is just so good.
I highly recommend everyone's snark about panels in the Discord.
But in a nice way.
Don't be mean.
Please.
We're very thin-skinned.
Please love us.
Malcolm says he expected more umbs and ahs.
There's something about the editing of this podcast which is that...
Well, I...
Because I had not done a podcast because I realised that editing was a lot of hard work because
you had to take all the umbs and ahs out.
And...
John has helped me understand that's not the case.
You could just leave him in.
Hmm...
John, do you edit out the little awkward silence?
He's just the awkward, the little bits between.
Yeah.
Um...
Well...
Yes, so um...
Sorry everyone, this is uh...
Sausage making.
Um, I have an app called Fairwright.
Um, and Fairwright, what I do is I import me, Alison and Liz um...
As different audio tracks.
And then I cut out anything beneath a certain decibel level um... automatically.
And then it will tighten everything up.
So um, yes, silence is kind of just go uh...
And that's kind of the first step in the editing process.
And it makes it a lot quicker.
Before we finish, we just need to say a big thank you to JT who has worked very
tirelessly to get us streams that we could edit afterwards.
And we really appreciate the work of JT as a whole tech team this weekend because the
business of getting it all um... together with the... with the three streams and the
streaming and everything else has been very hard work.
And thank you very much indeed.
Big cheer everyone.
That was the OctaThought podcast Live and it's goodbye from me.
It's goodbye from me.
And it's goodbye from me.
[Applause]
If you want a ribbon, please come to the front because we have a ribbon.
[Music]
We have had a question from the audience which is I want to know how not the audience
discord which is I want to know how much each of them have had to drink and I believe
that Liz has not had anything to drink.
I mean not today, no.
Oh over the weekend I've gotten that for that.
I have had one pint of mild and then I am on my second pint of mild.
Now I can tell you the amount of units I've had so far this week which is 26 and I didn't
drink before Eastergum so um you know that's good.
But yeah no it's been a good weekend.
The beer's been good.
I've liked the beer.
The stout and the mild and the porter but all very good and the ginger beer and the bitter
and I haven't had the others.
But my seven day total so far.
43.9 listeners which is roughly twice as many as me.
It was good.
I've had a good weekend.
Um I might be alcoholic.
Yeah I don't have a nap for tracking this because as Regulus's will know John and Alice
and like to track things and I just like to flow through life without tracking them but
I reckon that 10 units.
What four point?
Yeah.
I'm pretty restrained.
I kind of reckoned about 10 units prior to getting John's app because I used to go well
I drink.
I don't drink much of the week and then every so often I go to a convention and have a
skinfill.
And it turned out the first part of that was true but the second part was only true for
very large values of skinfill.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod in Competec.com
used under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
(silence)