But it basically turns into me complaining about Disney Plus not being here, which I think I've done on the podcast.
Least once before so many times this yeah, we could like have a checklist at the beginning of the podcast that says this podcast message availability to Disney plus.
What's wrong with the Marvel universe.
Oh, to the Bingo.
We to mix it's also gone dark if you know while we were doing the podcast.
Look, I've been very I've been very good about not noticing that because I have nearly commented like three times.
I know John don't do it.
I literally have not noticed until Liz mentioned it.
Oh God.
Hello everyone and welcome to the 24th episode of Octa's orp, which will be coming out on the 4th of February.
2021.
I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Betty and we are coming to you with some letters of comment.
So first up we have Duncan McGregor who tweeted at us to reassure us that he quite likes discussing convention finances.
So we're glad that it wasn't just Clare, Mark and Alison.
I mean, Liz, obviously we loved it.
One thing he says is that he has been finding that there is he has been finding that lockdown means he's quite screened out or zoomed out.
And so he finds conventions that are very screen heavy, very difficult because it's a lawful lot of screens all at once.
And something I realized is that we don't discuss the more distributed events as much on this podcast.
I noted in my reply to him mainly because they don't go as catastrophically wrong and require our comment.
There is the first Thursday zoom meeting, which happens on the first Thursday of the month and is for the kind of replacement for the physical first Thursday that's held in London.
Sheffield fandom have a regular zoom, which you can find on the anonymous Claire, discord server and on the Sheffield fandom Facebook group.
And there's also a series of panels from Essence of Wonder who are doing kind of weekly weekend panels, which are just a single panel, which you can watch with some interesting topics and whatnot.
Unfortunately, the end of this one of Wonder panels very often conflict with things I already have my calendar.
So I haven't actually gotten to one yet, but they have done some really interesting stuff.
So if anyone out there is in Duncan's boat where they don't want to go to a whole convention worth of screens, but they wouldn't mind kind of dipping their toe in occasionally, then yeah, check the show notes because I put some links.
There's also different sorts of screens.
So I've now seen quite a lot of buzz about running parties or events in Google sheets.
I have been to one of these and it didn't quite work for me, but I think it's an interesting model.
There are also things you can do that are more audio based rather than video based and getting getting your zoom kit out of your study is quite useful as well so that you can kind of sit around in your living room watching watching things, which is something that we're quite familiar with.
I know it's still still screens.
I finally am listening to slightly fewer podcasts because I used to listen to podcasts on my way to work and I no longer leave the house and go to work all the time.
But I find podcasts to be actually quite a nice way of keeping up with people and just listening to people chat about stuff in a way that was sometimes filled by sitting at the back of a convention panel.
And often they're not particularly visual anyway, so I'm quite happy to have that all happen sort of just as an audio thing I can listen to whenever I like.
And the second thing I would like to say is you had a party in Google sheets. Please explain.
They exist. There's a there's been a serious article about doing this. So it's not just amongst our friends.
Explain what it is because at the moment it sounds like you're basically making some sort of flip book out of Google sheets where your color coding each cell to be a pixel and you're like going through the sheets very quickly to simulate video.
And I assume that's not it. But that's the only thing I can think of.
No, but you've correctly identified part of it, which is that how often one of the tabs will be a coloring thing where people are creating collaborative art by filling in the colors of cells, then they do puzzles in places, then they hang out in places.
Because I really like spreadsheets, but I'd not considered trying to have a party in one. Going back to what Alison said about having your zoom rig outside of your study.
I do wonder to what extent people's screen downness is a more to do with kind of worked out.
And I think one of the things I've learned in lockdown is that being able to segregate your workspace from your personal space is very important.
And one way to do that is moving your zooms at your study. I find that I am getting better at context switching as I spend more time doing it.
I'm getting better on the weekends, not thinking about work and I'm getting better during the work.
They are not thinking about leisure products.
But I think there's something to be said for trying to achieve that kind of separation of work, screen time and home screen time and that might also be something to look at.
But having said that is also very possible to be screened out in general.
And I'm glad that our podcast provides a kind of solution to that in some small way.
So glad to hear you're enjoying it still Duncan.
Yeah, I think I'm very aware that while I can have basically a room that is my office for work that I can afford to develop entirely to work and then still have the rest of my flat for non work things.
It is a lot more difficult from a lot of people who cannot segregate their living space like that.
And I think in the early days when I was using one room as kind of my office and bedroom, that was part of the problem because I didn't want to go and sit in there and then watch a convention panel because I'd already been sitting there, you know, working for eight hours.
Yeah.
But I think we are all lucky enough to have a study in the Octa Thorpe team.
I have issues with shared space.
I don't have a room in my own as Virginia Woolf would say.
But it's my own fault because I have a five bedroomed house.
So if we had a act together.
Yes.
Let's move on to Claire Briarley's lock.
So Claire says that Alison will be relieved to know that it was London con in 1957 that the winner of the Fansing Hugo had three editors.
So it's not blocked as fault.
It's science fiction times is fault edited by James V. Tarrasi senior, Ray Van Halton and Frank, our Prieto junior.
I have two things to say about this.
The first is I was just talking about the rockets.
I was literally talking about the trophies.
I knew that there have been more things.
It's the it's the matter of giving away more than one trophy and then three or more trophies.
I think it's a very good job on Facebook that it wasn't really about the trophies or the amount of space on the PowerPoint at all.
It's about invitations to the reception and to the Hugo Losers party and to other events surrounding the Hugo's.
That this is the thing that seems to be the big constraint here.
So it is it is who gets to be in the room where it happens.
Well, and as I think we discovered as I think I said last time, Worldcon's have had a policy of basically saying you can have as many rockets as you like, but above some level we will charge you the cost of the rocket, which I think is an enormously kind of fair and fine way to handle that particular aspect of the thing.
I think I can see where they're coming from in that the Hugo reception. I've been to a couple of Hugo receptions as either an acceptors plus one or I think as a member of the long con committee.
I enjoyed going to them, but I wouldn't say it was necessary for me to have gone to them or the person who I was the guest of the acceptor needed me there for support particularly.
So you probably could cut down the guest list a little bit by just taking a firm align on some of that.
For instance, you often have the committee there. You might have the committee there because some of them are possibly accepting for finalists where there isn't a designated acceptor.
And you could possibly cut that down by having fewer people to do that.
So you just have like one designated acceptor for everyone who is not there in person. But I think that wouldn't make a serious dent in the numbers.
It probably is the fact that you could have an awful lot of nominees who all bring a plus one.
But I'm not sure what the solution is, but I'm not sure the best way is to say where you can only bring two people.
Claire notes that Terry Carr and Ron Elick won a Hugh over Fanac and they decided that they would swap it back and forth at successive World Cons in elaborate and public ways at room parties and thus get to award and receive it over and over again.
And Claire notes that her and Mark intended to follow in their footsteps with their first nova. But obviously anyone who has seen Claire and Mark's enormous nova collection will know that did not quite go entirely to plan.
That's not the reason it didn't go to plan.
But Jimmy, the passing back and forth became no longer necessary at some point along with the nova.
Because they had to remove their no shagging disclaimer from their fad scene.
Well, no, because it also wouldn't make sense to take the truck of 14 novers to every convention.
No, no, no. That's not.
They formed a household. They stopped living in separate households.
But there's no reason that I couldn't present a Spaniard with a rocket at a convention.
That is quitter talk. And if that's why Mark and Claire, if that's genuinely why you didn't do it, shame on you.
You should be. That's not a good enough excuse.
So you're saying that they should have a room party at a convention when we can have conventions in real life. In fact, they could do this on Zoom.
And they should award each other their entire collection of nova.
In fact, we can do this on Zoom and I'm throwing down the gauntlet.
Mark and Claire, you should pass your banana wings, novers, back and forth to each other.
Because they basically be in their two little pods on Zoom and they could move...
They could basically... one of them could move from one room to the other with the nova that had awarded to them.
Then they could reverse the process and it would be funny.
There'd only been different rooms. They just need to be sat next to each other on Zoom and then overpasses from one little Zoom window to the next Zoom window.
Oh, no, that's great. In fact, that's such so good.
I do want to do a bit where we pass the Hugo to each other on Zoom.
I need to sort that out with Mike and Steve. Hang on.
Their separate Zoom webcams are both attached to desktop computers.
I should send them a Mac.
Yes, I'm sure that will go well.
The next logical step in the week of its saga is for Addison to just start sending people computers.
Like, where else do we think this would end up? I think if any of us had thought about it,
we'd have been like, "Allison will definitely start sending just random computers to people."
I've been thinking about it, but what's happened is that Zoom stopped working on these very old Macs.
And I think it is now working again, but you need to do a bit of a "futs with it" and I haven't done that.
But indeed, I have quite a lot of Macs that would run Zoom and I have quite a lot of people who are kind of like,
"I can't go on Zoom because I don't have a computer who can run it."
And yeah, it's a plan.
He'd like the Zoom theory.
Another letter of comment came from Mark Plummer, who also discussed the Hugos.
And he talks quite a lot about the Hugos in general, but he discusses an anecdote at the end of his email,
where he says, "A better example of what it all means was in Spokane.
Somebody was handing out, I voted in the Hugos' ribbons and someone who was there who I didn't know,
but was just a fan who was present, said, "What's a Hugo?"
And he's like, it felt to me that fandom had been saturated in debate about the Hugos since Easter,
especially because this was the year of the puppies,
and then there was someone who was interested enough to be at the World Contour of Join and to attend
and then not to know what the Hugos were.
And so I thought it was a great story because it points out that the Hugos have a disproportionate level of discussion,
but it would be interesting to know what percentage of the people who attend the World Contour know
or the Hugos are, because obviously at the level that they're listening to a podcast about science fiction,
you're probably more likely to know.
But I do wonder if you're just someone who wanders off the street, like, you might not.
I don't have a good feeling for how glued together the two concepts are in the head of the average attendee,
because I'm appreciative I'm at one end of that bell curve.
I could have looked up but have not yet how many people vote in the Hugos each year.
Maybe that would be a useful way of doing this.
Mark also said, and I apologise if you've said this already and I wasn't paying attention.
Is that Mark saying that? Are you, Alison?
Me. Mark also said that the episode was much enhanced for him at least,
because we rarely talked about gaming this time.
Does that mean we need to institute video game corner?
No, I just thought it was funny. I'm saying it for the podcast because I think it's funny.
Moving on to Chris Garcia's Letter of Comment, he says wonderful episode and perhaps the finest use of the...
in podcast history.
And then he says the Hugo thing had a few things that weren't thinged.
And that is very true. He is astute, and that is, I think, a very good point.
He is astute and the world needs stutes.
I just love basically all the phrases in Chris's letters.
I won't read them all out, but I do like him saying this is the corniest of corner cases to go with the few things that weren't thinged.
Yep, yeah. No, he's a wonderful writer. I do love Chris.
Disc on three. Disc on three have announced that they're going to make an announcement,
but they haven't yet announced what the announcement is.
They've been a little bit more specific. They've announced at some point this weekend they'll provide an update on Disc on three.
On the server they sent out to say basically, would you attend a virtual or hybrid or real world convention in August or in December?
And also tell us why they've waited so long to update us.
I was hoping that by weekend they meant they would do it on Saturday, then by the time we record we would have the announcement.
But clearly they meant we'll do it too late in the weekend for OptiTalk to comment on it.
Do they not have any thought for the timing of podcasts?
Well, I think what this clearly shows is that World Concomitites are running scared from our incisive commentary.
Alison, any thoughts?
Those were literally my thoughts. I had two thoughts and it was those two thoughts.
Oh, excellent.
That one was definitely not my thought.
They've deliberately left it till Sunday because if you say this weekend, they're the parable of the unexpected hanging applies and they have to do it now today.
And we will expect it.
And I thought, well, they don't want to do it on Saturday because OptiTalk would trenchantly comment on it and that would be sad.
Fully expecting that as of comment from the Disc on three committee now.
So bring it on, Disc on three, we're ready.
Like a World Concomitite have time to listen to podcasts, John.
Why else do they do whether typing?
I know that I might be in a normally because I think Liz only listens to podcasts when she's not working, but I listen to podcasts while I am working.
So for me, the more productive I am, the more listening I do, which is perhaps not common.
I cannot multitask in that way. If I try and put a podcast on while I'm working and doing anything other than the kind of boring instead of wrote day to entry or something, then I'm just not listening to podcasts at all.
Fair enough.
I have different bits of brain.
And she keeps them in jars listeners. You heard it here first.
I do.
I cannot listen to a podcast if I'm doing anything that involves processing text.
You know, I can't read and listen to a podcast or write and listen to a podcast or anything of that sort, but I can absolutely draw and listen to a podcast.
Yeah.
So, or make badges and listen to a podcast.
I can do those things.
This gone threes hotel is having some issues and the owner of the hotel has filed for bankruptcy because Marriott who operate the hotel have asked them for a lot of money and they have said, we don't have any money.
We're going to file for bankruptcy.
And apparently this is not a new piece of news because we have a link in our show notes linking to a previous discussion of this in various smuffy circles.
But yes, it is something that is a prominent, especially, I think, Maria are having financial difficulties at the moment as well, which might partly be because we're in a global pandemic.
People don't tend to go to hotels.
Yeah.
So my, I would say that I haven't stayed in the world con hotel, the Marriott Walkman Park, but I have stayed in the hotel next door.
And they are two really, really big hotels and they are not in the center of Washington, D.C.
They are like a sort of short metro ride outside the center.
So they're perfectly nice, but I can see why in a time of reduced travel, they might be having serious problems because it is a very big hotel.
And it's not right in the center of D.C.
So it might not be the place that is still getting what little business traffic there is.
[Music]
Capricon and the FilcCon, why parasitic conventions are a great model in virtual times.
Is that what I said? Yeah. So Capricon is next weekend.
Tammy Coxon is the chair and it is a Chicago convention that I think started as a reaction to more traditional literary Chicago conventions.
So it is a convention that has a bit of a party vibe, I believe, and a slightly younger crowd than is maybe normal for our traditional SF conventions.
And one of the things it's got is a Filc track and it's happening next weekend, which is the traditional weekend of the UK FilcCon, which has been running for 32 years.
This is the 33rd one and it was going to be called Long Player, but when they looked and realized they'd have to take it virtual, they changed its name to Long Distance Player.
And they're running it as part of the Filc track at Capricon.
So if you join Capricon, which costs $10, you get a free UK FilcCon.
And if you were only going to the UK FilcCon, then Capricon say, just join us at the free rate because Capricon, and I think this is a brilliant model that we should steal for punctuation to, has two sign up options on their website.
You can either sign up at the $10 rate, three sign up options.
You can sign up at the $10 rate, which is the regular rate.
You can sign up at the free rate if you think it's appropriate for you to do so, or you can sign up at the $25 rate to support the convention.
And I think that's a brilliant model.
And they've said that UK Filc is should sign up at the $0 rate because they'll only be coming into the film, but I'm quite excited to get a little bit of Filking in with the rest of the mix.
And of course the Filking will start earlier in the day than some of the other stuff that's going on at Capricon because they're six hours behind us.
And it all seems like a good thing, and conventions could do this more generally, and thereby become global conventions without having to have to do all the work of making that happen, just by getting people in the other bits of the world to take responsibility for their time zones.
So I was very impressed with all of that.
And it's next weekend, so I will report back in two weeks time.
I do think that the free or $10 or $25 sign up option is very nice.
I mean we did say for Puncuration Con that we would comp your membership if that was a problem, but then there's like a barrier because people have to email you and say, you know, this is a hardship which they may not wish to do, whereas if we just had a button that said free
or button that said a 5a or button that said a 10a and if we have any leftover it's going to charity, then I think it probably would have worked out just as well as it did with just charging up on a 5a.
And then after that, Boscone and there's going to be a fan fund auction.
There is going to be a fan fund auction at Boscone, so if you'll listen to this and you have things the fan fund might like to sell, then please let us know.
And it's going to be the same model that we used at Wilcon where it will be a voice auction on Zoom, work really well.
And people will have to additionally play postage costs from wherever they are unless the donor has agreed to cover them which we'd expect them not to, so you will get your postage costs back.
And yeah, so please donate things, please come to Boscone and bid on them, please support the fan funds, that sort of stuff.
What sort of things would the fund funds like to auction and is there anything that you've been auctioning like in pandemic times that you couldn't do in a regular auction?
I think, well we only have a couple, the auctions are more global, so when you're thinking about things to donate, you can restrict them to particular areas, but if you're prepared to ship them globally then thinking about smaller, lighter things is better.
And obviously virtual things, people can submit things like tuckerizations or things of that sort.
And then finally, we have been, or Alison and I have been at the podcasting panel at the Critical Mass ZoomCon this morning, and we learned about how different people do their podcasts.
The people on the panel were Roman Osansky, Kristin Leleke, myself and Terry Frost were on the panel, and I think it went well.
Gave some software recommendations, gave some microphone recommendations, talked a little bit about podcasting, how much we love the sounds of our own voices, etc.
Hopefully everyone enjoyed it.
I learned a lot of interesting things. I learned that this never happens, has audio issues, because Lillian likes to draw when she podcasts, drum her fingers on the table when she podcasts, and laugh very loudly, none of which thing surprised me at all, but you can see that it would make the editor.
When I also see how it would make the edit harder, because they also record it, Lillian records it on her phone, and I can imagine that her phone is on the desk next to her drawing.
If I draw, my microphone is elevated from my desk, so I suspect it wouldn't come up on the mic, or if it did, it would be quite easy to eliminate, but I think if you're drawing or doing something on your desk next to your microphone, which is also on your desk, yeah, that sounds like a hard edit.
I recorded on my phone when I was on holiday, and it was a bit tricky, because I did have to sit there and be careful not to move or accidentally hit the microphone, plus I had to turn the air conditioning off.
So as a podcast went on, I was getting warmer and warmer, and like, are we done yet? But you know, it's a trade-off, isn't it? Normally I don't record on my phone.
I just stick a headset on and then throw the audio at John and make him deal with it.
But I will say that there is something to be said for recording on your phone, because it does kind of democratise the technology a lot, because obviously like my microphone and stand cost about £200, which was for me a not too insurmountable amount of money.
But like, obviously there are people who do not want to invest that in doing a podcast, and they don't have to. And I think it's worth saying that although I don't envy the edit process, this never happens.
It's not like you can tell really installing, it's very well edited. So yeah, like I think that democratisation of technology is really good.
And it's one of the things that makes podcasting so accessible.
Yeah, I mean, I think it's certainly true that you can record on your phone and it will be fine, it just may have some extraneous noise.
Plenty of professionally produced podcasts that have undertracks under the vocal that make them unlistenable for me.
Thank you very much to Roman for inviting me on the panel.
So the other thing I learnt from this is that some of the podcasters like to have a beer at their side while they're podcasting.
I mean, I would like to, but it is 11.30 in the morning here and I've got to clean the kitchen after I do this. So it seems like a bad thing.
Yeah, no, but if we podcasted at eight in the evening, do you think we'd do it with the beer at our sides? I might have one.
I think Liz would be annoyed. So there's that.
If we podcasted at eight in the evening, I would not have a beer at my side because it would be 3am.
Let's think about the future times when Liz is in the UK for some reason and we're podcasting.
Listen, I have podcasted with a beer, have you not noticed?
It's possible that Liz is more sensible when drinking. I might have one beer.
I can't imagine having a few beers while podcasting.
I can imagine having a couple.
I think I can imagine having as much beer as I can imagine during an Eastercon panel, which is usually I don't want to be absolutely latted.
But if I had one and I get another one at the green room, that seems like an acceptable amount.
I think by the time you're up to like three or four, you might have slightly misjudged. It might be time to calm down.
So yes. And also, I think Roman said he drinks wine and that's dangerous because wine is stronger.
So I've been drinking beer that I get sent by Claire and Mark of Croydon and some of those beers have been as strong as wine, including one they sent me.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
That was called very big moose and was 12% which is basically wine strength.
Yeah, they sent us a 12% one for Christmas as well, which I enjoyed but is not what I choose for podcasting.
I wouldn't have a syrupy Imperial stealth podcasting. I'd have like a 3.8% session pay.
Octa thought the podcast of science fiction fandom and beer.
Yeah. I mean, when I say I'm drinking beer on the podcast, usually I am drinking a cold lager with ice in it.
Whoa. I mean, you didn't tell us you were a heathen list.
This is a hell of a way to find out live on air.
If I was in Thailand, I'd be drinking cold lager with ice in it too.
Exactly. This is the thing I'd always thought was an abomination.
And then I realized when it's very hot, you want a nice cold gin and tonic or you want a sort of cold, quite light lager with optionally some ice in it.
Or sometimes here they will actually like get the beer out of the fridge and put it straight into a glass they've taken out of the freezer.
That's quite good as well.
I can understand that. I think I'm having like those funny, freezable rocks that you put in.
It's just diluting the lager. I'm not sure.
Although I haven't said that. It is very, very hot.
I hope it was a when I went to Mike and Flick's wedding.
The bartender asked me two questions when I ordered my London pride, one of which may be very happy and the other may be very sad.
The first one he asked was, "Would you like ice with that?"
And the manager behind him very quickly tapped him on the shoulder and said, "No, you don't do that. That's not how it works."
But then he said, "Would you like one bottle or two?"
And I was like, "Two bottles of beer, better than one bottle of beer. Thank you."
And then I wandered around with my two bottles of beer and then I had more beer.
And then I nearly spilled some beer on Flick's wedding dress, which would have been a faux pas.
But I didn't. And that's why I'm not dead.
I am thinking about the film Ice Cold in Alex, which I'm going to spoil for you now.
Do we have a spoiler, Clackson?
[Squeaking]
There's the final scene of which involves the hero drinking his ice cold beer.
And the beer in question is, "Calsburg, it's possibly the finest example of product placement in the history of films."
But that's a very good example of somebody drinking a cold beer when they've been quite hot.
Surely it's not as good an example of the product placement in the Italian job, which was for Fiat, bulldringly.
Were they kind of demonstrating what amazing breaks Fiat had?
[Laughing]
They couldn't get Mini to sponsor the movie, but they could get Fiat.
So if you watch the Italian job, every car that is not one of the Minis is a Fiat.
But that's not what you're looking at, so I don't understand what Fiat sponsored the movie.
Like, it's not like you come out of the Italian job thinking, "I want a panda. That's not how it works. You are Mini."
That is strange.
It is very odd.
[Music]
The other thing that fandom has been beginning to discuss over the last fortnight is what we are going to nominate for Hugo's,
or more in the circles I've been moving in, what I need to read to know what I'm going to nominate for Hugo's slash,
what I'm going to read to get a leg up on the eventual finalist's slate.
So the reason this is a good time to discuss this is that Hugo nominations opened four days ago,
and you can nominate Pop Pickers if you're a member of Discone 3, or if you're a member of Conzeland.
And I think if you are, they will have sent you an email because I forgot I was a member of Conzeland,
and so I was quite surprised to get the Hugo nomination to open email. So there you go.
Yay. So I pitched this question to the third row mailing list and Abigail Nussbaum gave me some pointers,
and then when Liz asked Neil Chime-Din, so you know, screw you, Neil.
He doesn't listen to the podcast, so I could say that.
Unless someone dobs me in on the third row Discord, don't you dare hog and watch in you.
Right, so the first--
You're absolutely going to get dopped in for that.
The first book I read for my Hugo reading was The Vanished Birds by Simon Jimenez, which is a fantastic book I would recommend reading,
and I'm currently reading The Doors of Eden by Adrian Tricowski, which was one of the shortlist for the Philip K. Dick award,
and is also very good.
The other books that I'm kind of seriously considering reading are Ministry for the Future by Kim Stanley Robinson,
Pyrdyn Aze by Susanna Clark, Harrow the Ninth by Tamzin Muir, Vagabonds by Harold Jingfang, translated by Ken Liu,
Network Effect by Martha Wells, a deadly education by Naomi Novick, The Once and Future Witches by Alex E Harrow,
and then reluctantly-- because I think it's got a good chance of ending up on the finalist's ballot,
but is my wife reliably informed me that it's very not good-- is The City We Became by N.K. Jemisin.
So, yeah, those are kind of the books that I am imminently intending to read,
because I think there is a fair chance they might end up on the final ballot,
and I'm kind of a book and a half into my reading so far.
Anyone else doing any Hugo reading?
So I will say that I have read The Vanished Birds, which I picked up entirely on the strength of Abigail Nussbaum's glowing review of it,
and I thought it was extremely good as well. It feels to me like a tiny bit like it will appeal to the people who liked books by Becky Chambers,
but it works for me in a way that Becky Chambers books completely do not.
I've also read Pyrdyn Aze by Susanna Clark, which I did like but hasn't stuck with me that much,
but I think it is a very kind of clever and lovely little book, and I'll not be sad to see that on the shortlist.
I'm surprised to hear people not liking the NkGemison because I've liked most of her books,
so I'll probably have to read that myself to decide, but that is already on my list.
And Network Effect is Murderbot, right?
Yeah, Puyo.
So I read the first Murderbot, novella, and when it was nominated for a Hugo a few years ago,
and liked it but never picked up the rest, so maybe now is the time to go and pick up the rest of them.
I will say two things, which is firstly, España also likes NkGemison's work in general,
but the city we became is a novel that has been expanded from a short story,
and basically España felt that it very much did not need to be expanded,
and the expansion added nothing of note, and that is, I can see how that might give you structural problems.
We'll also strongly disagree, or maybe not strongly disagree.
I think the vanished bird is nowhere near as optimistic as Becky Chambers,
so if you're a fan of Becky Chambers because of the term Hope Punk,
then do not read the vanished birds assuming that that is what you're getting,
because you will very much be disappointed, but I still think it is.
It does share a lot of things in common that are not perhaps the inherent optimism of Chambers' work.
Which is say, you are absolutely correct that the vanished birds does not have the sort of hopeful,
optimistic aspects that the Chambers did, but I think the problem was I didn't like the hopeful,
optimistic aspects of it because it felt like it almost forced it into a plopped corner
where everything ended and I only read the first one.
All the episodes ended in a very happy, optimistic way,
and I felt that they often ended too easily or in too quick a resolution.
I'm not saying it's a good thing about Becky Chambers writing,
but I am saying that I suspect an enormous segment of her fanbase
think it is a good feature of her writing.
Yes, and you're right, I probably shouldn't say this is like for people who like Chambers
because they probably won't like it.
No, because I love Becky Chambers and I love the vanished birds
and I think the parallels you've identified are why I love both.
I only started making a note of what I was reading in October,
so I may have read other books, but as far as I can tell,
the only book I have read that is in the running is Piranese
and I enjoyed it a great deal.
I would definitely nominate it in a position of almost complete ignorance,
but I have read a lot of other Hugo nominated and Hugo winning books
and I think I would certainly be happy to see it on the ballot.
The other book I thought might have been a 2020 book turned out to be a late 2019 book,
so that's a bit sad.
I'll probably read some others, but I haven't done yet.
I wanted to pick up a point John made about the NK Gemmerson
maybe being a not very good fix-up to say that that has not stopped books
from winning the best-lobbled Hugo in the past.
Oh no.
Many fine, well, no.
Lots of Hugo winners started out as short stories
and did not gain anything by being expanded to novel length.
It's a very common thing.
And I will also say that España really dislikes the book Flowers for Algonond
because it was expanded from a shorter work and I love that book.
So it might also be that España is more sensitive to the issues that arise as a result of that transition
than other readers.
Do you want to know it's pronounced Algonond or not?
No one I have seen who has read the Gemmerson has said that they think it deserves a nomination.
Had you read the short story of Flowers for Algonond before you read the novel?
No.
Yeah, that's the point, isn't it?
Because you read the short story, you go, "This is fantastic"
and then you read the novel ago, that's the short story but at three times the length.
It's not the point I was trying to make because España has also not read the short story of the Gemmerson.
Ah, so the Gemmerson might be bad even apart from being a fix-up.
Art is subjective.
Our listeners may or may not enjoy the Gemmerson.
All I can do is report the opinions my loved ones have had on it because I have also not read it.
I think that's all for books.
I think that is the kind of level I wanted to discuss books at.
Oh, before we move on.
Listeners, if you have read any books from 2020 or have heard about any books that people are discussing
with a view to nominating, please write in and let us know because I for one would love to read
and get a kind of head start on the eventual shortlist and maybe have some outraged reactions
that things I loved did not end up on the shortlist.
So please do let, get in touch.
I think we should say not just books.
Tell us what you're nominating and why, particularly things that other people might not have thought of
in any category, not just books, so that we can go and check it out while there's still time to nominate.
Yes, that's a good point.
I think it's just that I feel way more informed about TV and movies than I do about books.
I would say specifically I feel a bit under informed about particularly indie games and I do like playing indie games.
So if you have played any particularly good little video games that came out in 2020 that we might like to play with a view to nominate,
then please let us know, particularly because I would like the slate of nominations for the new category to be really, really good.
We should have a discussion about that.
Sorry Mark.
Yeah, I'd just like to mention video games on every podcast we do now.
[laughter]
This is a perfect example of how Mark has engaged with us in a way that has changed our narrative and tone,
thus confirming that we are an interactive experience.
One of the things that's happened as a result of us not spending as much time hanging out with each other this year is that people aren't having as many of those conversations where they go,
"Oh, what are you reading? I'm reading this. It's great. Have you read X? It's brilliant."
And I think that we've not got quite as much of a general buzz going on amongst our friends about what is good.
And so we probably need to do that quite deliberately this year.
One thing about this last year is that we're starting to see fewer blockbusters.
So there are blockbusters, but they're just being kept in mothballs until the theatre's reopened.
And so this might give a chance for more considered and thoughtful drama to be nominated.
This is happening in movies already because the cinemas are closed.
It's not happening so much in TV. At the moment we're still seeing TV that's coming out of the woodwork because it was filmed before everything went tits up.
But over the next year we're going to see this effect in TV as well.
And as I like thoughtful cerebral science fiction, I'm really looking forward to seeing some of it pop up in the nominations
and not always have to compete with some giant explosive superhero thing.
So yeah, I think you're right about blockbuster movies. I actually disagree on TV.
I think the reason we're not seeing... excuse me.
The reason we're not seeing blockbuster movies is because the economics of releasing a blockbuster don't work.
You don't have enough people going to cinemas and you don't have enough subscribers or streaming video.
You can just look at Tenet, which was the only blockbuster that came out and it did not do very well.
You look at how much money Milan made. Sorry, you look at how much money Milan made on Disney Plus.
It didn't make much money. So you can't release these big Tenpole movies and make your money back.
So they're kind of being delayed and delayed and delayed.
With TV, the business model for TV is very much to attract people to streaming services,
which is why we had stuff like the Mandalorian and Star Trek Discovery prior to COVID.
And I don't see a reason why they can't keep filming those,
especially stuff like the Mandalorian, which is a very small number of actors.
And I would expect them to be filming those kind of with very safety restrictions.
I know they're filming Mythic Quest and Ted Lasso seasons in exactly the same way,
just with a lot more masks and hand washing.
So I think it's the problems of making it that are causing the shift.
I think it's the problems of getting people to watch it that it is.
Ha ha ha. And I have picked a tie when Alison must stand.
So I can keep talking about how Alison is wrong about everything.
But Liz.
I think that I could probably argue with you about movies because Warner Brothers have, for instance,
that their states are all going to come out and streaming.
I think some stuff will come out as a lost leader on streaming.
But I was also going to say for TV.
I think I've seen some estimates of how much extra it costs to film with COVID precautions,
and it's somewhere between 20 and 50% extra.
So I do think that means that shows which would be viable pre-COVID are not viable to be filmed
under COVID precautions.
So one example of that was glow on Netflix where they suggested that the problem might be
that you cannot film a wrestling show under COVID precautions without it costing you a lot,
lot extra.
So I think it's also going to depend on the show.
I think while Alison is unable to comment, I could push back a bit on what sort of cerebral
things you would like to see in best romantic presentation short form, because I would know
in the past few years we've had the Expanse, which I think is a cracking piece of space opera.
We've had Watchmen, we've had, you know, a dirty computer and splendor and misery.
I mean, we've had The Good Place, which is basically a comedy about philosophy.
So I think there is some good cerebral stuff already being nominated.
I'm not sure you're going to see a great big shift in the next few years because already
there.
You should probably give Alison the right to reply now.
I'm kind of fine with not getting the right to reply.
But I do, I'm thinking about it while I was standing up.
I'm not sure there is a place for more cerebral movies, though there are still some people
making quite thoughtful films on small budgets and they might have a space.
But most of those people are working in television now, as you say.
And I worry that the Expanse is very good because it's like, this is like five seasons
of it.
I really want somebody to tell me a fantastic science fiction story in an hour or two.
I don't really want to spend 60 hours getting that story.
You watch the Expanse.
It's very good.
Yeah, you may not really be the target audience for television.
[laughter]
I could go on to say that one film that I have heard people saying very good things about,
is Amazons the Vast of Night.
Let me just check the title of that.
The Vast of Night, which is apparently the Vast of Night 2019.
Yes, but I think that was 2019 in film festivals.
And so it counts under the wide release in 2020 and it is 90 minutes long and has six cast
members and is apparently kind of a self-contained kind of slightly old school science fiction
story.
I had not heard of that.
I'll have to watch it.
I think, and perhaps I am off base, but the film I am most, or sorry, not necessarily the
film because obviously Best Dramatic Presentated Long Form takes a variety of forms, long forms.
The thing I am most excited to nominate in Best Dramatic Presentation Long Form is Palm Springs,
the film which I believe is shortly coming to UK streaming but has not been here the two
starring Andy Samberg and Krista Milleotti.
If you haven't seen it, I thoroughly recommend it.
It is fantastic and it is squarely a genre movie so I really hope it gets nominated.
I think it sounds great but there is no way for me to legally watch that film.
So I have not watched it.
Soul, just slipping in there on Disney+ on Christmas Day, cannot fault its genre credentials.
Yet another film that there is no way for me to legally watch.
Do not have Disney+.
Disney+ has not launched in my country and has no estimated launch date yet.
Another thing that I saw in a cinema was Wonder Woman 84, which I don't know whether
we will get nominated.
I really liked Wonder Woman 84 despite the fact that it has some plot points which don't
make a whole bunch sense but I get the impression the internet at large didn't.
It is not the first time I have liked to think and other people haven't but, yep, I don't
know whether that will get nominated.
But it is a film that was famous that came out in 2020 so it may well.
I think that is a film that I could watch actually but I have to go to the cinema.
I assume Hulu is not available in Thailand.
No.
Fair enough.
Hulu is available in the US only as far as I know.
So I expect I can be some of the stuff on Hulu is going to come to start this new Disney
expansion streaming service or something.
And I mean I do expect Disney+ to launch but they basically, Thailand was not in the first
wave or the second wave of launches.
I think we will probably get it sometime in 2021 but it is not here yet.
This is not going to be a problem for the vast majority of the Hugo voting electorate.
No, not.
Although I would guess a surprising number of them will be in Australia and New Zealand
this year.
Yes, yes, possibly.
Good point.
I guess it comes spring on Amazon Prime but not yet.
Ooh.
I can watch it as Amazon Prime.
I knew it was coming to something.
So I think most of our people will not be able to watch it legally.
If it's coming to Amazon Prime then most people will because it will probably be like a worldwide
release on Amazon Prime outside of the US.
I just hope I hope I would strongly encourage people to track a copy down and watch it prior
to nominations.
Hopefully that's on Amazon Prime but yes, I would thoroughly recommend it.
It is a fantastic movie.
I discovered from one of my tech bloggers a website called Letterboxed which everyone else
might have known about for ages but is a place where you list and share your films.
Please add me.
I want friends.
It's a social network for movies.
I have been on it for ages but I've only just started reviewing movies.
Please friend me.
I have no friends there.
I'm feeling very lonely.
One of my 2021 themes is to watch more movies.
So I have been watching a movie every week so far this year and I have been enjoying working
out what I think about them and writing a little bit of a review.
So it's been nice.
I like that it has, I mean obviously I could do this perfectly well in notes.
It's got several different lists so I can keep lists of movies that are available on Amazon
Prime and that are available on Netflix and that are available on Disney+ and that are
available in full on YouTube even though they probably shouldn't be.
That was the 24th episode of the Octa.
The podcast and it's goodbye from me.
I have no games to nominate.
The two who came up I think were Star Wars quadrants and Animal Crossing in previous episodes but
I'll be interested to see if people submit less massive games.
Yeah, I mean I don't have a switch and I'm rubbish at shooty X and games.
You should get a switch which is great.
Not made of money John.
What a playstation this year.
But you live in a country that's not very cheap and you have enough money to buy a switch.
So maybe get a switch Liz.
Yeah let me look at the price of switches in Thailand.
I actually don't know the price of switches in the UK.
Ah no that's fair that's fair.
Please all send 48 switches to Liz.
Please join our new Patreon so that Liz can buy a switch.
I'm just going to give the Nintendo switch has a mere 50% markup in Thailand.
So how much is it in pounds?
About 350.
Ah I mean that's still... I can't remember how much I paid for mine.
That is the Animal Crossing one because I can't find a non-Animal Crossing one which may be cheap.
For enough.
I don't think that's more than your pay for the Animal Crossing one in the UK.
It's 240 quid on August I had to look it up and check.
Oh okay fine.
All right.
Ahh.
This is not a podcast allow me to share with you my method of tracking movies.
This is a spreadsheet.
It is categorized by watch to know what John is having a movie party in Google sheets.
Jesus.
The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by Kevin MacLeod at Encompetech.com
used under a Creative Commons attribution 3.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep.
Beep.