I was going to say I don't think there are any other podcasts for example on the BSFA
best nonfiction long list that we could listen to and it's not a place where I would necessarily
expect them to turn up but that's not a place we can look and find new ones.
I was quite surprised to see a podcast on that list and their mistake.
I mean I'd have been less surprised if it hadn't been us.
It's fair to say.
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 51st episode of Octa the Orp, a broadcast for Science
Fiction and Science Fiction fandom.
This episode is coming to you on the 17th of February 2022.
I'm John Coxen.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty and we have some letters of comment today.
We do have a letter of comment.
It is a letter of comment from Chris Garcia with his congratulations on turning 50.
Only the podcast Chris.
Only the podcast.
And he has he has some thoughts on self-promotion.
As he says he is seen as a ruthless self-promoter because he did a big Chris for TAF campaign
which she says was a lot of fun.
And that's true.
TAF is definitely a thing for which it is not only allowed to campaign and promote yourself
but basically a whole thing of TAF because by promoting yourself for TAF you are just
promoting the TAF race and raising funds for TAF and lifting the whole thing up.
Yeah when I ran for TAF didn't really promote myself because I was very nervous about whether
that was acceptable.
I very nearly didn't win.
But I did win.
I didn't get the most votes but that was fine because I still won.
Yeah he also says he tries to self-promote things from the beginning of the year which
is interesting on the grounds that if people maybe don't remember as well things they read
or watch at the beginning of the year and that he likes to self-promote in the fan categories
because of the required number of votes rules and because we are getting a little bit close
as we mentioned before to sometimes not having a win in those categories.
Although I think then you can mostly promote the categories rather than promote specific
works in those categories.
And he also says side note to Alison that that's not at all how championship boxing works.
I was slightly surprised at the time that I didn't get any comeback on that and nobody
else said and then John used it as the episode title which really I did slightly worry me
but there we go.
I don't know anything about boxing.
Neither do I.
Other than I dislike it.
It should probably not exist as a competitive sport.
We're going to get letters and that's the episode title.
Episode 50 to 75 are just going to be a sequence of opinions on championship boxing expressed
through episode titles of octa-thop.
You heard it here first folks.
Express through the medium of complete ignorance.
Yes also true.
Chris says people are more likely to vote in a category if they have a horse that is in
the race and even if that's just an internet friend who has heard of their zine podcast
fan writing is not only a vote for that thing but to keep the category being awarded.
And I do.
I hadn't thought about it in those terms and I agree that a better way to do this is to
raise the profile of the category overall and Coribula is doing that among others.
But I do see his point that like every vote in a fan category is one vote against that
fan category going away.
I sort of sympathize with that viewpoint a bit.
I sympathize with that viewpoint a lot.
I mean I want everyone who listens to this podcast and who is a member of the member of
the Chico and Wilcon or last year's Wilcon to get on and nominate especially in the fan
categories because I think fan categories are good.
And we could do that by telling you some interesting things that you might like to go
and check out.
I can't remember what the rules on nominations are for the categories to run because there's
a rule on votes.
You have to have a certain percentage of votes as a percentage of the number of ballots
coats cast.
But I don't know is it that you have to have at least five is it like if you've got beneath
some percentage of the nominations you don't appear on the ballot is there a risk there?
Quickly to the Westfus Constitution.
Well no because you said you said about nominating and I know that you did that sort of direct
away from self promotion but now it's like well but is there actually a consideration
here on nominations or is it just on voting?
Oh no but I think good nominations invigorate a category because the thing that makes it
most likely that people won't vote is looking at a category and going I've never heard of
any of these things and why should I care.
But I think that will happen in the fan categories a lot anyway and if fans don't self promote
their works it's more likely to happen.
So I think Chris's point might still stand.
Are we now an ASMR podcast again?
Because we've discussed this in the past John.
No but genuinely like I think that if no fans talk about their projects then there will
be no fan and so I think Chris is right that self promotion may well be one of the important
tools to prevent the fan categories going away because most of the Hugo Electric don't
follow fan works so the only way they're going to is if the fans shout loudly about the fan
works whereas like authors have like publishers marketing houses behind them so even if the
author doesn't self promote they have like an entire team of professionals promoting
them anyway and we don't.
Okay so you thought we were going to get letters about boxing championships?
That's nothing compared to the letters we're going to get about the adequacy of publishers
marketing effects.
Efforts.
But like you see the point I think.
I was too busy being stabbed through the heart by the suggestion that the Hugo voting
community doesn't follow fan works.
I mean some would say that you're not the obvious pick for the idea list on the podcast
but here we are.
I take your point but I do think that you could achieve it by talking about other fan
works that you like rather than necessarily your own.
So generally we should just talk about fan works more.
Which we're doing I think?
Yes.
I like to finish on a nice uncontroversial opinion.
Right I'll let it about that if you dare.
Ali Baker writes to say that she feels extremely icky about self promotion but a problem of
non promotion is that there is then cultural hegemony in the part of SFNF that is her area
of interest which is children's and YA literature.
As far as I remember she says the only books on the load star short list last year were
US books and other international children's book awards are very rarely awarded to non-US
authors.
Raising awareness of brilliant UK based SFF authors can only be positive.
And I think this is another thing that resonated with me because if you do have a situation
in which all the American fan creators and professional creators feel able to talk about
how great they are and none of the Brits do that that will lead to some biases in what
actually ends up on the ballot.
I think it's a good point and I hadn't really thought about it.
So yes thank you Ali that was food for thought.
Historically British fan works only got Hugo's in years when the Worldcon was in Britain
on average.
We got a very long letter of comment from Mark Plummer.
Thank you very much.
Mark says I've been feeling guilty about ignoring opto thought because he has a relentless linearity
that means that he feels the need to listen to the podcast in order and I have a public
service announcement for him and everybody else which is that it is not necessary to
listen to all 51 episodes of opto thought to get the sense of what's going on.
You can just jump in where you are and then you can write to us about what we're doing.
This is not a...
I think we have themes but I don't think we have any sequentiality about us really.
The other two might want to comment here.
I mean there are certain cases where if you write as a letter based on like episode 37
we may have already corrected ourselves in episode 38 if we were completely wrong.
For instance if you are listening to episode 50 you probably shouldn't send us another
letter about how wrong we are about championship boxing.
I mean unless you've heard us be wrong about championship boxing earlier in episode 51 in
which case it's fair game again beeps.
What's more if you are going to do it you could kind of take a place ball approach to
it and do it in a way that has absolutely nothing to do with championship boxing just
telling us about the way in which the laser gun has really affected the way the game went
and that sort of thing.
That's just true.
I think so it's tricky because I think part of the fact that we are a more discursive
podcast which has contributions from our listeners whom we love doesn't mean that there
are like some continuing threads.
We're also topical so you know...
Are we?
A lot of stuff we talked about so many episodes are getting might not make any sense.
We should announce that for those of you not listening on BBC Sounds we will be coming
out on a four week delay so that our topicality makes no sense to anyone.
Mark says yes the TAF free ebooks page is a good thing but so are the TAF free ebooks
that are on that page and for the fan awards you can vote for those that have published
in 2021 which is good point.
They can also be voted for for Hugo's as well but I think only in best related work
where they are not going to make the slightest shadow of an imprint but by all means get
on and vote for the good ones it's good.
He also talked about ties in TAF because there was a tie in 1976 and it but in the
end only one person came.
I think the precedent seems to be send both people if TAF can afford it.
So there was a plan to basically buy a flight that would have enabled both Roy Tacket and
Bill Bowers to come but for some reason that flight fell through and in the end only Roy
Tacket came but like there's no that doesn't really set a precedent and I think Mark is
right that sending both is best and TAF can afford it at the moment.
So we're launching the Octa Thorpe campaign for TAF to be a tie.
If everyone could please coordinate and make TAF a four way tie that would be great.
Sorry TAF administrators this may not be the messaging you wanted.
However he also says one of the things about Anders is that Anders for TAF incidentally is
that while he doesn't necessarily do the high profile jobs he's absolutely the kind
of the person who just volunteers for stuff.
If you're at a convention if you need somebody to move boxes or stack chairs and as a
boxers will immediately pitch in possibly even having done the job before you realize
you needed somebody to help do it.
He in pubs he habitually collects up to empty classes from around the pub and takes them
back for the bar.
Anders for TAF says Mark something which I but not necessarily my co-host hardly a door
and I'll also say something else on TAF which is if you are thinking voting for somebody
else first consider putting out a second because it is a properly organized vote and of course
we'll go for the four way tie which will be very funny and then on self promotion Mark
also raises this distinction between self promotion and signal boosting all of the other
good stuff that is out there and that is the stuff that really sways his thoughts is when
the people that whose opinions he trusts recommend things.
So don't self promote get your mates to promote you instead.
But when I did that on twitter you got really annoyed at me Alice so I'm just saying that
I'm getting mixed messages.
Mark says a couple of things I'd like to pick up on on self promotion which is that he does
say he doesn't see a self promotion to tell people that a new episode of your podcast exists
which is something I mentioned because we kind of wanted to draw.
I wasn't necessarily saying I thought of that self promotion but like I think we wanted
to distinguish between oh hey I did a new thing and I'd like people to know about it
versus oh hey I did a thing and I think you should nominate me for the most prestigious
award in my field which I do think like different concepts that we wanted to make sure we differentiate
between.
But he does say it does seem odd to him that I have to set reminders for myself to do
it but he guesses different people functionally in different ways and yeah I just I don't
know I just I get to the end and I put it up and I'm like aha I've finished this project
but my my work has gone into the world and for me the process of telling people that
has happened doesn't trigger any of the endorphins I get from finishing the project so like I
do need the reminder to be like no you there's a little bit more work you have to do now
which is very kind of ad mini.
So two things here the first is that this might be slightly on topic but I learned that
just a few days ago that one of the key difference between people who are seen as organized and
have their shit together and me is that people in the former group actually conceive of a
project slightly differently so that they think of a project being done at the point
at which you know the dishes have been put away in the cupboard and the and the podcast
has been promoted and the the full set of things have been done and the people who are
seen as scatty and disorganized stop their projects bang at the point where where the
exciting bit is done and don't actually do those last little tidying up bits without
help that was my first point and the second point was I believe that the range of things
for which John sets reminders for him to do is quite large by the standards of normal
human beings.
So on your first point one of the questions they ask you when you get screened for ADHD
is do you have trouble doing all of the tedious little bits at the end of projects and I said
of course I do everyone does who wouldn't and this lock is a very good example of how
that is actually one of the big signs that you might have ADHD.
Who knew?
Mark says wouldn't it be nice if best series was voted on once the series was actually
complete which is very close to my own views and because of course the Expanse won the
best series Hugo before it was finished.
Yeah, my problem with best series is that I would like to give the award once the series
was done.
I don't think that.
And I don't think you could but I take the point absolutely that you don't know when
the series is done because if the series is successful they just do a bit more of it.
See also American TV shows.
See also Sherlock Holmes.
See also Hawkerseye.
Let's not blame America for this like Victorian England ruined series for everyone.
How many views of Mapfugee are there in Hawkerseye's 36 views of Mapfugee?
Jerry Sullivan, TAF administrator extraordinaire.
Much as she is entertained by John's vision of breaking a tight TAF race with a football
match in the gardens of the Hill cool and Metropole in Birmingham.
The only thing in the administrators FAQ, the only allowable exception to the race being
won by simple majority is in the very rare case of a toid race.
And so Jerry agrees with Mark.
That's the best thing to do would be to consult with one's TAF co-administrator and send
BUNF.
Oh, four wait I, four wait I.
And then Jerry wraps up by saying hey I did it, single subject lock.
Thanks so much for the entire podcast.
Thank you very much for your single subject lock.
Jerry it was Grant.
There are some Eastercon updates this week, which means we are back unfortunately to the
dreaded topic of COVID.
Reclamation the 2022 Eastercon have announced the vaccination policy, which is that you
have to be vaccinated and they have announced this well in advance.
So if you are not vaccinated thinking of coming to the convention, you can go and get vaccinated.
They've also opened hotel bookings now.
So obviously they're planning for an in-person convention and you can now book your hotel
and it's all starting to look very much like there might be an in-person Eastercon in 2022.
And so I am then very much thinking, oh should I go to Eastercon in 2022?
Yes, you should.
Yes please.
We're going to drink beer.
There is a slight concern which is that while the UK may be in the process of deciding that
COVID is no longer a thing and so we can just sort of pretend it's not really a thing and
no one will have to wear masks to take any precautions or self-isolate.
I live in a place where you are still required to self-isolate if you have COVID and also
crucially you cannot re-enter the country if you do have COVID and have to currently take
two tests in a week you arrive to check that you have not developed COVID shortly after
arriving.
So my slight concern is that I would go to Eastercon, potentially get COVID, not because
I think anyone at Eastercon will not be trying to be as good as possible to prevent COVID,
but just because this is something that is likely to happen at a large multi-hundred
person event, especially if it involves going through crowded hotels and restaurants where
not everyone is from the convention and not everyone wears masks or is vaccinated.
So in the slight way that I would do that then get a positive test and not be able to
actually go home for a couple of weeks.
So it's tricky.
I mean I also don't want COVID, but you know there's an extra, extra bonus problem if I
do.
And I do wonder whether that will feature in the thoughts of some other overseas visitors
to Eastercon.
Kind of people who usually go to Eastercon.
It would be interesting to hear if you write in and let us know what your thoughts are
on attending Eastercon from overseas, because that could be I think quite illuminating.
I will be going because I don't have to fly to Toyland afterwards, so I just have to go
to Newcastle.
So that's a lot easier.
So I will be going to Eastercon because you know, wild horses wouldn't stop me really.
What is life for if not to actually attend Eastercons in person?
I might be wearing my masks all the time like a good person.
And we don't know what the Eastercon masking plans are yet.
I don't think they need to make a decision yet about that.
I think that's something you might want to make a decision about a little near the time.
But I'm seeing lots of people having kind of thinking out loud on this, not from overseas,
but just from the normal Eastercon community who are attending members, but are kind of
going, I don't know whether I'm ready to go to an Eastercon or not.
So we can clearly have a bunch of people who will go at all costs.
And we have probably some people who definitely won't go.
And I think we've still got a lot of people who are quite in the middle going.
I'm not quite sure how my personal risk profile and the Eastercon match.
And I think there's still quite a lot of falling out to do there.
And as a result of all of that, Eastercon has had somewhat fewer of its regular volunteers
sign up than usual.
So if you're somebody who thinks you might have fun volunteering at an Eastercon, and
that means all of you, because volunteering at an Eastercon is the best fun.
And I know that I'm not doing it this year, but I'm really sorry Phil.
I'm quite busy with all the things.
I'm going to be very, very busy working all weekend at Eastercon, but I'm not necessarily
working for this Eastercon doing it because I'm on the committee, on one of the committees
bidding for next year's Eastercon.
And I'm also looking off the fan fun stuff.
And I'm also touting my, yeah, coming by badges and enamel pins from me.
That's self-emotion, right?
Yeah.
So, yeah, if you'd not sure where you'd like to work, then I think lots of us can make
recommendations.
But I would say that the newsletter is a great place to hang out.
Not quite sure who newsletter head is.
I think a lot of my pals will be working on newsletter as usual.
[Music]
Olga Thorpe podcast corner.
I have been listening to podcasts.
I am going to talk about two podcasts here.
So one of them is not eligible for Best Fan Cast, but I think people should listen to it anyway,
and the other one would be eligible for Best Fan Cast should you wish to nominate it.
So, the first one is a podcast called The Incompraable Game Show.
So there is a podcast network called The Incompraable, which is run by someone I know
through Apple journalism circles and started listening to a while back and has lots of
different shows on.
I'm not going to talk about them all, but what I am going to talk about is The Game Show.
So if you are a fan of panel games and if you are a fan of science fiction, you may enjoy
The Incompraable Game Show because it is mostly panel games about science fiction,
and it is very good.
My favorite is one called Inconceivable, which is hosted by Dan Morrin, who is also an author
and is just amazing.
Really enjoy it.
It's not eligible for Best Fan Cast because they make too much money or a company.
I can't remember.
This is something complicated.
Yeah, this is just demonstrating the problem with Fan vs Pro that we will talk about sometime
because it is obviously professional work.
If we are talking about The Incompraable, though, can I suggest that The Incompraable
600, Episode 600, is it would be a very good place to start with The Incompraable, not the
Game Show, the regular podcast, on account of how it is just seven people talking about
all the books they like for an hour.
And I took lots of notes because many of the books that were recommended were ones that
I like very much.
And so I'm rather assuming that quite a lot of the other books will be as well.
Yes.
Although I warn any people who don't like Becky Chambers, that two of the first round picks
will make your eyes roll.
Yeah, but for anyone who does like Joe Walton, there are two Joe Walton books recommended
on that podcast and several people went, "Oh, you've taken my pick."
I think it's a good episode.
I would recommend that one.
And then the one I'm going to recommend, which is a fan cast, is a podcast called Become
the Tea Pot.
Now this is a podcast by Ian and Ian, my friend Ian and his friend Ian.
And basically my friend Ian has read lots of comics and his friend Ian hasn't.
And so they are on a mission where Ian basically recommends films that have been based on comics
and then they read the comic and they watch the film and they discuss them.
It's really interesting.
It's a really good concept for a show.
They've just wrapped up their second X month.
So both January's, they've been recording, they've done X month and this month was Rhiannuary,
where they watched only X-Men films starring Ryan Reynolds.
And that was very good.
And yeah, no, it's just really interesting to hear the perspective of someone who's super
into comics, talk about these movies and the perspective of someone who's coming to the
comics in the opposite direction, experiencing them for the first time.
Yeah, they do some quite out there ones that I haven't heard of.
Also some that I'm very familiar with.
So Ian really didn't like the old guard, which I've always been a bit of a shame because
I really liked the old guard.
But he makes good points.
I just mostly disagree with him.
And the episode on the League of Extraordinary Gentlemen is bloody brilliant.
They get so grumpy, it's great.
Might listen to that first.
It's also fortnightly and it's also only about 45 minutes.
So if you are a fan of the sort of format of Octo-Thorp, it will suit you down to the
ground.
And then shall we talk about Best Games Hugo?
Best Games Hugo went off and spent some time with the Hugo Awards Study Committee in that
kind of nourishing way that it does.
And it got, I think, quite a good following win there.
I think the Study Committee is minded to be quite enthusiastic and the Study Committee
is, as we know, packed with people who are actually attending business meetings.
So the next stage is for the draft proposal.
The draft proposal is out there on the internet and we are going to link to the tweet, which
includes the proposal itself and also a FAQ.
And it is now the Best Game Hugo.
It's been a bit of time being the best video game Hugo.
And of course the test Hugo was video game.
I think we've talked about this quite a lot on Octo-Thorp before.
So we were basically in favour of it being Best Game and quite a lot of other people took
the same view and so it is currently Best Game.
It's going to go back to for its first round at Chai-Kon and then its second round.
And then if it gets through that then ratification at Chang-Doo so we will see.
So the proposal that will probably come out of the Hugo Awards Study Committee is a modification
to the Constitution of the WUSFS which basically introduces something at 3.2.5 to define what
an interactive work is and then introduces a new award at 3.3.10 called Best Game or Interactive
Work.
So very exciting if like me you want that to be a Best Game Hugo.
And when I say I think it's getting a following wind from the Hugo Awards Study Committee,
I think it's getting a following wind to the extent that it will be the single clear recommendation
for a new Hugo category coming out of the study committee this year, Touchwood, whereas everything
else is kind of hanging around in the soup for another time.
Is that your perception John?
The Study Committee is mindful of not swamping the business meeting with lots of tweaks
to categories so I suspect it will be this and one other and then the rest will be kind
of reported back on for vague comment by interested parties before percolating for another year
as Alison says.
I'm very happy with this both because I strongly support the games Hugo especially because
I think Best Video Game at DC went very well and I will be glad to see that award continue.
I am also glad that it's being expanded to include things that are not video games because
most of my gaming is not primarily in video form but that is it does lead me to often
a world con will introduce a special category prior to a new category being proposed because
it's a good way of testing the waters for that category.
Is this the first time that the category has changed slightly in between the trial category
and the eventually proposed category?
Was for SNURDS please write?
It is a broader category than the one this con ran although I will say given that this
con's category worked very well with the like type of focus I can't see why it wouldn't
work with very slightly expanded focus and I suspect even though I will be mostly nominating
tabletop games I suspect the finalists will mostly be video games in much the same way
that TV dominates best dramatic presentation short form despite the fact that short films
are technically eligible.
I mean I think the better example is that video dominates the best dramatic presentation
categories despite the fact that audio is technically eligible.
Yeah also true.
Because video killed the radio star and if we ever introduce a best audio Hugo prepared
proposal I want to call it video killed the radio star which would not be the stupidest
name for a short name for a whisper's proposal ever.
So I just I've got several comments.
I went and had a look at the list of special categories which have been awarded by previous
world cons and I'm not sure any of them have actually become full categories except for
well I guess it was best all time series which was sort of a precursor to best series but
I guess was never intended to repeat so you wouldn't bother writing the categories such
as it would repeat.
There's also best new author which I guess turned into the astounding award.
Oh there was also most promising new author so who knows.
I think yeah I think I'm generally in favour of expanding the best video game Hugo to be
best game but I think it does give you a very wide range of stuff to cover and I'm not completely
convinced it's going to be dominated by video games because when I look at stuff like the
Nebula award because the Nebula's given award which is called best game writing which they
give us is 2018 and it is not entirely dominated by video games it also ends up with a lot of
sort of interactive fiction in there as well and so I think given that we have you know
venues like Strange Horizons have recently published some more interactive fiction we
might end up with a mix of that plus video game.
The other thing is where do you put critical role?
Dramatic presentation.
What's critical role?
I'm asking for the listeners.
It's an actual play podcast about playing a game.
It's basically a video where people play D&D and every week you, well not I don't
know it's D&D or some other thing but it's basically they play RPGs and you watch them
play their RPG.
BDP.
Yeah it's a dramatic presentation it's definitely not a game.
What if I nominated it in the best game though?
Because it's clearly not.
It would get moved to best presentation unless you had filled your best presentation category
in which case it would be ignored.
I don't think, I don't think because an interactive work is a game narrative or presentation in
which active input or interactive play is an integral component of the work itself.
So the listener or the viewer has to be able to interact with the work in a way that affects
the outcome and my understanding is that critical role does not like in the same way
that Twitch plays Pokemon allow the viewer to actually shape the narrative in any meaningful
way so it is not eligible in the best game or interactive work category.
There is an interesting question here about whether or not something like Twitch plays
Pokemon would be eligible.
I think yes but I think it is such an edge case it's unlikely to actually be tested and
ultimately if the community gets behind something like that why not?
I mean I think it would be interesting to have a fack on that.
I think the answer there would be to trust the voters and say you know if Twitch plays
Pokemon got nominated I think if enough people wanted to nominate and vote for it that seems
fair to me.
But no critical role isn't there's no question the category explicitly excludes non-interactive
work.
The fact that it's interactive for somebody doesn't mean it's interactive for the Hugo
voter.
Like Curb Your Enthusiasm is improv but that's not an interactive work despite the fact
that the actors were interacting with one another.
I mean I think it is I think it's probably an edge case in which I could potentially
read it to say actually this thing I'm watching is a presentation in which people are doing
interactive play and therefore it is should count as an interactive work which is being
filmed.
So I mean I probably wouldn't nominate anyway but I think it will be interesting to see
if anyone does.
I mean I have a bigger problem with the category that more worries me because I think in the
way that Hugo voters are perverse which is that I worry that conventions will find their
way in here because the Hugo voters seem to be desperate to have a Hugo for best convention
thing and you could probably put it in it because what is a convention if not an interactive
experience but it still doesn't feel like what's made by this and I mean if it goes
wrong that you know Wisfuss will correct it in due course.
One and again like no one's nominating conventions for best because I think by the same argument
you could argue that a convention could technically be eligible for best dramatic presentation
because you could argue it is a single improvised play.
Yes and they are but they fall way down the list because best dramatic presentation gets
lots and lots and lots of nominations.
And I think so this category will also get nominations I think which will ensure that
that does not happen.
It might be worth I guess there might be an argument that says that modifying the subclosies
to explicitly exclude active plays is wise but I'd want to see it in action for a couple
of years first because I note that best video game at Discom I don't think anyone nominated
any let's plays of games so I am not minded to think it will be a problem really.
Because of course we are praying in aid let's plays as an evaluation tool for people who
cannot actually play the whole of every game themselves.
Yes.
So yeah.
I wasn't intending to provoke such a strong reaction just to me I think it could be read
as an edge case and I think it will be interesting to see.
I think we should probably go ahead with it as it is because otherwise we'll just argue
for another year about definitions of stuff.
But it will be interesting to see what we end up with and also because it could potentially
be a weird category in which I'm basically comparing a piece of interactive fiction in
which I can choose my own adventure in two or three places with a complete 100 hour video
game.
Oh sorry you could be choosing it with a complete 100 hour video game where you get
to choose the direction of playing all three engagements.
I mean I'm going to be arguing very strongly when this category exists that people should
be casting their nominations and votes for things where the actions that you take influence
the game in a big way quite a lot.
I know that that's only my view and people do like the other sort of thing quite a lot
as well.
Yes.
I mean from my perspective your criticism there is interesting because although I felt
Hades is quite linear isn't it?
It's got ones.
Like you play and you go through the same thing each time and then things happen and
really the only agency you have is who you give presents to and which weapon you pick.
I mean maybe if you play 300 hours this becomes less obviously true but like.
Okay so the thing about Hades is that it it what happens in the game is extremely dependent
on what choices you make but it is certainly true that by the time you get to 300 hours
you've then explored playing Hades for 300 hours is like going through the Sonic game
books till you've explored every single possible strand of it right.
So eventually you do manage to get all of the branches but Hades got a lot of branches.
There are a lot of subplots and interesting weird things that happen and that's part
of what is so good about it.
I felt like I had more minute to minute agency in spirit fairer than I did in Hades which I
suspect is why I preferred spirit fairer to Hades because I got to make choices about
what I did next whereas in Hades it was I go through the dungeon again but I take the
point that like maybe you kind of bounced off Hades didn't you?
I mean I played it for like five hours but yeah like but I will say going back to what
Liz said I would like to recommend a sub stack on interactive fiction and I would like to
quite strongly push back on the idea that a hundred hour video game is somehow inherently
better than a work of an interactive fiction because I do not think this is true.
I at no point said that John.
No you might have to compare the two but I compare the two all the time so you know.
I'm just saying that they are too like they're quite different.
Yeah they're very different.
I do not expect to have to compare you know I do not have to judge this game based on its
interactiveness right.
I mean it's a thing for best game it does not say best interactive parts of a game it's
best game so if I wanted to choose like I don't know street fighter whatever you know
street fighter two or something then I could and I'm not judging that based on its narrative
I'm judging it as a game and so I'm saying something like you know.
Oh yeah yeah.
I have 10 minute mini interactive twine fiction story judged against like a giant AA video
game is a very broad set of things to consider and maybe broader than we consider in most
of the categories and we are now kind of taking those stories out of where you know they now
can't compete in like short story or novel letter anything which you know.
But they weren't anyway.
Well they weren't being nominated but.
I take I take the point but that that if you created a category that short films could
appear in and you were like but now they can't compete in best dramatic presentation short
form I'd be like I mean that is true but given that they're already not represented
there.
This is the hugos do not have to be completely fine grained.
Yeah and it just I it just feels weird to me to create categories that compare enormous
disparate amounts of stuff while we still have kind of all these pretty fine grained
categories saying we're going to compare you know I think it's easier to compare a short
story in a novel letter than to compare like a short piece of interactive fiction with Horizon
Zero Dawn.
I don't think we're ever going to get away from extremely fine grained categories of
written fiction because that's that's where you get started right.
I don't think we're going to remove any hugo categories.
Yeah so let's just start here and then later people might go but the reason I wanted it
to be game and not video game which otherwise we'd talk about.
Yeah I should say I think this is a better way of doing it than best video game I just
do think it's got certain you know awkwardness is to it.
Imagine if we had a hugo category with awkwardness as in it.
But I will also say that the Nebula Award because it is specifically for best game rating will
tend towards that kind of game in a way that I don't think this one will because technically
speaking the interactive fiction you're describing would have been eligible at this con and looking
it down the list of nominations we had Ghost of Tsushima, Sense and Semiosis, Ori and the
Will of the Wisps, Spider-Man Miles Morales, Assassin's Creed Valhalla, Cyberpunk 2077,
the Luminous Underground, Kentucky Route Zero, Half-Life Alyx and Star Wars Squadrons.
Sense and Semiosis is a 10 minute twangay.
No I mean I'm not saying there are none but I am saying the category is clearly not being
dominated by those things so I'm not sure again that that will be a big problem.
The Discon released all their program items online for me to watch.
So some of the recordings that are available if you go and look for them and you log in
in your Discon account you will find them but they have not officially released anything
yet and in the Discord on the 2nd of February they said I know we keep saying soon but we
do mean it so they're coming real soon now maybe even before we release and then they're
going to be available for 30 days so as soon as they're available the next time we do the
podcast we'll tell you but you probably do want to keep checking every couple of weeks
in case they've turned up.
This is the age old problem of like once a convention's finished it's very hard to get
anyone to do anything because a convention's finished.
Well I will also say like I think the majority of the program is up and I would much rather
they waited until it was all up and then start the third day clock than saying well we've
put most of it up and we said it would be 30 days after we announced that so we've
announced it and now there are 30 days and they just never get around to the rest so
I do think this is the right way of doing it and like yeah I'm broadly speaking pro
Discon on this one I'm afraid I'm being very contrary this week.
No I think it's fine I mean I think it is certainly useful for us to say they're there
going to go and get them fill your boots.
Oh yeah because they have an announcement so like if you hadn't realised that there might
be some programming you want to watch in your Discon account.
Yeah so if you went to Discon or had a virtual membership of Discon I would like to go see
their program quite a lot of it is online now but they're still they haven't formally
announced it and they do keep saying that soon and I think what they've got is a few
items where they're just tidying off the loose ends before they do that.
Yes for instance I did not know any of it was there I guess the answer is I probably should
have asked Alison but that feels like a weird way to find out about it.
I'm still on the Discon Discord and it was mentioned on the Discord it just wasn't
so I have been carefully not saying for three months two months yeah there's some stuff
there if you go and look for it because they have not said it in any way publicly but it's
clear that there's a thread in the public questions and answers where it is made clear that is
there now and as far as I'm concerned that means it's fair game for putting on Octoforp
it is there they have not announced it but much of it is there.
Yeah I have not been reading all the Discon Discord channels since Discon finished so
I missed this but I guess I can now watch some replays.
Yes!
So I saw a tweet from Jason Sanford he is running a survey on science fiction fantasy
magazines to see how readers access them and how that may have changed during the pandemic
and apparently he has a survey done very close to the start of the pandemic like just before
so we'll have some interesting data to compare so if anyone wants to go in and fill out his
survey on how they interact with science fiction fantasy magazines we will put it in the show notes.
Thank you very much Liz and then shall we do pics?
Yeah!
Who would like to do their pic first?
So my pic is far from the light of heaven a novel by Tare Thompson which is a it's a stand
loan novel about a colony ship where people are travelling like years to their new colony
and it's basically a ship controlled by AI but of course it has to have a captain on
the essentially just kind of just in case and the captain is always told you know you
won't really need to do anything you're just there just in case and of course what we actually
find out is that she arrives at the planet and everything has gone wrong it's to become
clear that the AI is not functioning in any way the way it should be and that quite a
lot of the colonists are missing.
So it's basically a locked room mystery in space because your locked room is the spaceship
and so she's trying to piece together what has happened during like the journey when
they've all been in cold sleep and you know investigators come up from the colony planet
she's on and it's just all about the mystery kind of unfolding on this on this ship and
how this also interacts with kind of the political situation of the colony planets so the nearby
of the space station that is there for the colony ships and I just think it's a pretty
good stand loan bit of kind of locked room mystery in space.
I think my warm drawback is that I don't actually think the resolution of the mystery is amazing
and you know when it is kind of a locked room mystery it does sort of you know a key bit
is how it was done and it didn't feel entirely satisfying to me but I thought the journey
to get there was very interesting.
So yeah I enjoyed it.
I have not read this it sounds very much like my cup of tea but it does very strongly remind
me of Six Wakes by Merlaffte which was on the Hugo finalist roster in I want to say 2018
but I might be wrong around then and I adored that was also a locked room mystery set on
a spaceship and it had the twist that the opening chapter is from the perspective of
the clone of one of the murder victims waking up with an incomplete memory backup and seeing
their murdered body and that is how the mystery starts and I adored that novel.
I thought it was really great and unlike what you've just said I really liked how the mystery
ended up having been perpetrated.
I thought it was very good.
So there are some reviews on Goodreads that say it is you know there are some similarities
to Six Wakes and some say this is like Six Wakes but not quite as good so it may not
entirely be your cup of tea but yeah I think I would recommend it that there is enough
of interest there in the kind of you know the characters and how this kind of colony system
interacts that I would recommend it.
It also made me remind me a little bit I think it's is it Jack Glass? Jack Glassby
Adam Roberts which is one way you know exactly who the murder is but not how he did it until
later in the book which I also enjoyed.
Ah the sort of like Colombo.
This is one of the books that was recommended to me when I asked for recommendations for
my pals on things that I might want to vote for for the Hugo as a fantastic book of 2021
and then several other people chipped in to say they'd really enjoyed it as well so it's
on my next stop to read list so I'll probably read it by next time maybe so library book
it's another one I've got on paper turns out paper has very small print when did they do
that I'm sure while I was younger it was very easy to read books written on paper and the
print was plenty bigger now.
I don't really have a pick this week on account of having spent most of the two weeks reading
a fat fantasy novel that we're going to talk about next time but I do want to say that I
have listened I've watched episode one of Loki which is I believe a series in the Marvel
Cinematic Universe but I enjoyed it hugely and I want to pick it now because I've been
told by several different people that by the time I get to the end I will not like it
anymore.
Including John so I mean I basically at the first episode is kind of great because it's
got Tom Hiddleston doing Loki in the way I've kind of always wanted him to do it which
is where he is naked is grappling with issues about free will and the fixed state of the
universe and this is all happening because Marvel it turns out that the reason you've
only seen one version of the Earth in the Marvel Cinematic Universe is because there's
a weirdo bunch of time police looking after it and it was all done with an aesthetic which
is kind of brazilish brazilish rather than brazilian but you know and and it's all absolutely
lovely and enormous amounts of the graphic design and cinematography and locations and
everything are just fantastic and if it carries on as good as this I will be absolutely thrilled
but I know it won't which is why I'm picking it now.
I will say the aesthetic stays rock solid throughout like it is an enormously pretty
show and I enjoyed it a great deal.
Well Tom Hiddleston is an enormously pretty actor so you know.
That's fair and I think I will say like there is a chance that you will think it does stick
the landing I don't know it'll be interesting to see.
On the subject of MCU shows I did not pick it as a pick on the pod but a really enjoyed
Hawkeye which I think is my favourite of the MCU series and so yes that's the kind of
the one I loved out of the four of them.
I think Hawkeye is probably my third favourite.
Might be my least favourite but like it is a relatively high floor so being the least
favourite doesn't mean I didn't enjoy it.
If you haven't seen the latest Spider-Man movie I'm about to do a casting spoiler so
you may want to skip to the next chapter which is a good bit and has Marvin in it.
The Spider-Man film went to see it very good movie and I really enjoyed seeing Tom Holland
and Bennett Cumberbatch doing their thing and Zendaya and the other guy whose name I can't
remember because he's not as famous as Zendaya and Tom Holland sorry Ned but really enjoyed
the movie and I thought it was a very good wrap up of the first trilogy of Tom Holland
Spider-Man movies and I also thought it was a good capper for Toby Maguire and Andrew Garfield
in their roles in Spider-Man some very good interactions there and I thought it worked
very well and on the subject of Andrew Garfield I also watched Tic-tic Boom which is not genre
except that it does have a sci-fi rock musical in it in the background called Super Berbia
which I really want to see like now I've seen Tic-tic Boom I absolutely want someone to
stage that I understand that it would not work commercially at all but like oh my god
if anyone does that I want to see it because it looks amazing and it is so good I loved
it I adored it.
Andrew Garfield is amazing in it I mean I have a huge crush on Garfield anyway but he
is just sublime and I really liked kind of witnessing that kind of slice of history it
is a desperately poignant film and I really really really loved it and it is on Netflix
and you put it and you put this on to your letterbox so we all knew how much you liked
it right yep yeah four and a half stars might have been four car over but I definitely
reviewed it yesterday okay maybe I maybe I'm not quite caught up so yes Alison I did
boom if my mic wasn't on a stand I would drop it don't don't don't drop every time
anyone drops a mic I get really really really upset are you a big little Miranda fan because
this is a this is a Miranda project I mean I am I am a big limo Miranda fan except that
none of the music is by him it's directed by him and the staging is very good he directed
it but also he made it happen I'm not sure it's actually produced and directed by but
he is it's all it was his idea of a film limo Miranda directed and was one of the producers
on it but don't go into it thinking it will be limo Miranda songs because it is very much
not it is Jonathan Larson songs and it is amazing no no but it is a passion project by
Miranda so it was on my list because you know no no if what you want is a nice film with
Miranda songs you need to go and watch in camto which I think I had as a bick a couple
of weeks ago but I might not have done and it's got Vanessa Hudgens in who I think is
underused but yeah right now it's it's going way up my list now I just need to talk Stephen
and also they do the thing at the end where they like play video that they have of like
Jonathan Larson so you can see like the matches they got to their kind of locations and characters
and that was quite fun I do like when they do that and the thing that really blew my
mind sorry is I looked it up afterwards because I was like oh Andrew Garfield he's very good
in this and he learned to sing and play piano for the movie and I'm like like because I was
like oh I didn't know he could sing and he couldn't and now he can and he's amazing so
like maybe he'd just never tried maybe I bet I guess but yeah if he gets the oh I think
he's half of the way to an ego so that's good so will it make me cry John yeah make me cry
I'm gonna say you should watch Tom Scott's video about basically decides to record himself
singing and get to singing to help him and a good producer to produce it and he's extremely
good for someone who is clearly very embarrassed about doing it and feels he has no singing
ability so I think yeah if Andrew Garfield had any ability they could probably take him
from zero to really credible pretty quickly and that was the Octa thought podcast and it's
goodbye from me it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me
[Music]
Hades did also win the Nebula and that is because you might or might not think it's linear it
has 300,000 words of voice dialogue oh no the the writing is great like I'm not not
this and the writing is unbelievably good and and a lot of those are in strands that
you won't see unless you take make particular choices so it's it's it's it's quite like
interactive fiction book in that way except eventually if you give enough if you give
enough abrosia and stuff to enough different people you will get all the ending no your
your analogy of the sonic game book I thought was very good because I think I think you are
right that in a lot of ways it's not so much about like the interesting points of the sonic
game book and not when you're rolling dice to do the combats the choices you made that
got you to the combat and I think that Hades the choices that you make outside of the core
gameplay loop are almost the interesting interactive thing which is an interesting way to do a roguelike
yes but the other way that Hades is extremely innovative is that it it provides a setting
in which dying and having to start all over again makes perfect sense which I feel like
games have been looking for for a long time but I'm not sure I would have enjoyed Hades as much
if I couldn't also you know go and smack people up with my big sword yes it's it's beautifully
balanced anyway sorry we're gonna talk about last year's winner now but there's a reason why it
bought over well be Lee no I think that's germane but I think that might be why I have a slightly
different view on this because the part of Hades I found frustrating was I did not find the combat
sufficiently compelling to keep me in the narrative and so I suspect that might be where part of
this is coming from I found I found it made my hand hurt because I was pressing buttons very quickly
and I don't I just I found the combat a bit too frenetic whereas like a lot of the games I like
were fighting in are a bit more that there is also god mode and I was playing on god mode
eventually but basically like Hades is a game where if you press buttons quicker it goes better
for you yeah a lot of video games I like that John no but like Horizon Zero gone Dawn you don't
press buttons quickly you press buttons at the right time in Jedi Fallen Order you press you press
buttons at the right time and so Hades very much felt like that core gameplay loop was it wasn't
a game of working out how to use each weapon elegantly it was a game of pressing buttons incredibly
fast and for me I found that was what really turned me off it because I just I don't there are there
are builds in Hades where you don't need to press any buttons at all as well so one of the reasons
that people like is because there are builds that work for people who cannot press buttons yeah I
think it's this is basically if you play like if you got the point where you play like 20 hours I
think you would have started to get some of these play styles but you really only unlock these kind
of quite later on I finished it but not done all the epilogues but you know once you've unlocked all
the weapons and you start to get all the aspects of the weapons you can start to be like okay this
is a clever way of doing it but now this is my Achilles heel you know you'd have to press the
dash stab button very quickly though it's the old perdido street station got good 500 pages in
argument or indeed Octa sort much better yeah we we only really got good 26 episodes in listeners
no okay so we have gotten a little bit into the weeds swear we are this is one of the um
progressions in the podcast which is if this is the first episode you listen to you might be
surprised that we have all these opinions about video games but if you're Mark Plummer listening
to this thinking why did I pick these episodes to be the ones I listened to Mark the last like 20
episodes very little game content and then you start listening again and it just it's a curse
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud in competec.com
used under a creative Collins attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
Thank you.