[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 78th episode of Octa Thorpe, a podcast for science fiction
and science fiction fandom which is coming to you on the 2nd of March 2023. I'm John Coxon,
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty. And we have some letters of comment. We do. We have a letter of
comment from Andge who says that they got a bit far behind on episodes of Octa Thorpe and then they
just started listening from a recent one instead of trying to listen to the backlog. Hello, welcome
back. Hi Andge. Hi Andge. Hello Andge. We also got a letter of comment from Dave Coxon who talked
about our picks for dramatic presentation short form, said that he's late to the party on The Boys
and he's just about to finish season two but he's loving it for all the reasons I talk about and
more and then he also says he's about to sign up to Apple TV plus again primarily to watch
Severance because of our summary and recommendation. I hope you enjoy Severance Dave is pre-great.
Come Severance stick around for Ted Lasso season three. Yes. On a J. Ted Lasso.
Where's your wrong head? Yes. And we also heard from Chris Dafodj Garcia. He refuses to read the
show notes to which I say boo. They're all beautiful bullet points Chris read the show notes read them
read them now read them and then he also says he bounced off severance but that's likely because
he was watching it on his phone and I'm like yeah maybe maybe I do think Severance is a show
that creates an atmosphere and I do wonder whether if you're watching it on your phone with two
kids running around also listening to the wrestling that atmosphere is harder to create but that might
just be me. He does also give us some recommendations for short films bouncing off our discussion of the
best dramatic presentation short form. Unfortunately I haven't seen any of them. I'll track down and
see if they're on YouTube or anywhere that you can see and put them in the show notes because I
think these are all short films rather than episodes of TV and that's somewhere where I'm very under
under researched. Yes well Chris so we have Chris is very good at short films but also Chris
doesn't read the show notes so Chris we've put all those recommendations in the show notes.
So what I love about Chris's lock is that there are two sentences which we're going to need
clarification on. The first sentence is or the first sorry the first paragraph is the 80s were
the proper time for RPG systems. I've only once run that was the end of the paragraph.
There was no full stop. Chris what have you only once run and then that big spreadsheet has been
incredibly useful. Largely because I forget the months from January through to about October.
I will say that the single best thing I watched last year was
and then that's the end of that paragraph. So Chris write in and tell us what you ran and what the
single best thing you watched last year was because I think you might have been more distracted than
usual on this lock. I am wondering if Chris might dictate his letters of comment to us and the
reason I'm wondering this is that I got back from the from a birthday party very late last night
very drunk. I'd had a fantastic tube journey home and I thought I must write this down my
assumed journey was amazing. It was everything that is great about the London Underground and I
have to write it down and I realized I was incapable of writing so I have dictated it.
So I have like 3000 words of late night dictated text that I have to go back to and see if it
makes any sense at all. I'm not sure strictly speaking the problem here was that you dictated it.
Yeah I was the phrase "a poor workman blames their tools". We also heard from Rave who said that
they're glad the Clark Awards exists but they tend not to use it as a recommendation engine as it
tends to skew more literally than they tend to enjoy and they would definitely have nominated
time and again which is the Ms Marvel time travel episode for BDPSF. I might still like I'm
I'm dithering. I'm dithering Raj and then he's definitely with me on Spock amok he loved
Strangely Worlds and that episode was just brilliant which yes good I'm glad you think so Raj.
Raj also messaged me personally on Maston to express delight that I had not seen ghosts and
tell me I should watch it more. So many many people on Anonymous Square stopped
stopped listening to the podcast in astonishment at the point where they discover that John hadn't
watched ghosts and said John you're one of the lucky 10 000. So yeah today's lucky 10 000.
So have you watched any of it yet? Nope. There you go. Well we've been watching
we've been watching other things. Yeah it's fine but you can save it up for some time when you
want to fail you know lightweight treat it's not it's not gonna it's not gonna change your life
it's just gonna make you laugh I hope you'll watch it now going oh this is the most unfunny
thing ever what were these people talking about?
Chengdu our regular Chengdu segment so Chengdu sent some emails to members
sent several emails to members some of them BCC'd only to me some of them just sent to me
and about 15 other random people some of them which in my inbox some of them in my spam folder
I'm not gonna blame them too hard. That is yeah that I can't let you can blame them for and to
refer the second email did not end up in my spam filter and I'm using Google mail so they probably
worked out how to keep it out of the Google ones. I do think it was a bit naughty just sticking
email addresses in the two line because I now have 15 random people email addresses who are
presuming members of Chengdu. I feel like Worldcon should be a bit better than this but then I don't
know if I was trying to use WeChat mail or something I'd probably make similar errors.
It was CC'd only to 10 people rather than to like the entire Worldcon membership because that
would have been quite funny and then when people started messaging back on reply all saying please
take me off this list. Yeah that is true they didn't send it to 7,000 people whatever they did just
send it obviously doing it in batches and I mean I hope no one was doing it by hand but I
wonder if that's what they were doing and that's why. Oh they were 100% they were 100% doing it by
handle list you know it to be true. What the email actually said was that the 2023 Hugo Awards
nomination page is in final testing expected open by the end of the month and then they will email
as all and there will be a paper ballot as well nominations will run until the end of April 2023
voting begins in May 2023 and will last till August 2023 so it's it's a you know perfectly straight
forward email it's got all the timings in you might want to give you the website it is in two
languages it's pretty good. Yes that does mean listeners that as you're listening to this the end
of the month has come and gone we are recording before the end of the month but you're listening to
it after is it time travel maybe but this might mean it's open now it also might mean it isn't
which is technically always true but is more likely to be notable this time.
By the way you've got two months to do the nominating so probably all right.
Exactly no this is very good and they also released PR1 and successfully sent me an email
about PR1 which was not CC 20 of the people so I think they've you know got the hang of that now.
Yes it's very exciting who read PR1 very briefly.
I read PR1. I did not so what have you can talk about it.
It's it's a very nice PR1 it's got all the stuff you would expect in PR1 in that it's got you know
some quite vague stuff about like generally getting to Chengdu what hotels they've got some
bits about the you know tourism activities you can do there's bits about the food about what
will be going on it is a perfectly fine PR1 it's just that normally PR1 would have been out like
about 10 minutes after you won the vote. No actually that's not true PR0 comes out then
but I mean we've just got PR1 for Glasgow so you can see they're basically running about a year
behind and I think the level of detail is about what I would want you know a year and a half before
the convention. Hmm okay that's fair it is very beautiful and I think given how difficult travel
arrangements are going to be for anyone outside China I feel like I would like them to start
easing into how are you going to get there where are you going to stay what are the practicalities
like though I mean obviously we're grown up so we can work it out for ourselves but I felt a lot
of that was missing I also noticed the recommitment to their guests of honor so this is the official
point every octa thought that we talk about Chengdu where I say Serga Li Kinenko is still a badon.
Confirmed Rotta absolutely I flirted very briefly with the idea of going to China on the way back
from Australia but it's clearly insane and impossible I'm not going to be doing that.
When you said very briefly you mean we had an extensive discussion about it on the podcast that
John then had to trim out I think. But that was a very brief flirt. I've had much longer flirts
than that. There are a few things in here which are interesting firstly I had not realized so in
my tiny little head when someone's a co-chair it means that there are two of them and that is
not the case there are three co-chairs there is he, ji, there is Chen, she and there is Beniello
so I had not realized there were two Chinese co-chairs which maybe everyone else knew but I did not
and then they also have the division list which is really interesting so they have you know some
divisions it's interesting because what we would usually call the wasphus division is actually like
three separate divisions which is kind of weird though as someone has done it that way it might
be the in practice they haven't that's just the way they're reporting it but it's also interesting
that the site selection division is being run by the same person as the program division I guess
because program is famously not a big job so you can just do another job as well I find that a bit
odd because I'd kind of find it reasonable if it was a business meeting that was being done by
the program division person because I can kind of see how you need to do scheduling but site selection
is like there's not a lot in common with program is there it's mostly it seems like maybe even
exhibits would have been made anyway don't understand that very strange and a lot of these don't have
American co-heads which I think we noted before but it's interesting to see and then finally this
just maybe chuckle there is a page on page 35 there is China Visa application service which gives links
for all of the places you can go to get your Chinese Visa to visit China and they have got links for
the United States, Canada, the United Kingdom, France, Germany, Italy, Spain, Netherlands, Australia,
New Zealand, Japan, South Korea, Singapore and Malaysia and they are all the same link and it's
just it just made me giggle I was just like this is a very good page I like this page very much
it makes no sense to me at all but in general these are nitpicks it's very nicely put together
document in general other than being a little bit late is quite nice and good art and my lovely
pictures and just yeah it is very pretty I mean I can kind of see why they've done that I suspect
the visa pages because some places you know for some place if you're applying for a visa they
outsource it and they outsource it to kind of different companies depending on what country you're in
yeah yeah so a lot of the time you don't apply directly for a visa from the government to apply
to a particular company but yeah in this case they could have said you can apply for a visa
like all these countries can apply for a visa at this place and if you're not there we'll probably
figure out where the one is except you can't actually apply for a visa right now can you so
I can understand why they're a bit sketchy on this because I think you can't actually apply for
tourist visa yet but they probably need to have something in about like okay this is how it used
to work in terms of like what documentation you're going to need and what letters you need what
bits of paperwork so you can start putting it together and I mean I like the pictures are lovely
especially all the ones of pandas and tasty food but maybe a bit more of that in terms of divisions
it's interesting because I wonder how much their internal organization is being done in English and
how much is being done in Chinese so I wonder if they have kind of heads of divisions who are also
partly able to be like the public facing ones and then internally maybe they've delegated an awful
lot to internal volunteers who are not necessarily doing everything in English because I just don't
know how they're doing it I'm really interested if anyone worked on the Japanese world con actually
I would be interested to know how that went in terms of like what was your internal like working
language did you do it by division did you do it by area you know what did you do because I'm pretty
sure when I worked on the Helsinki welcome they just kind of defaulted to English for everything
and that worked fine because everyone was bilingual but I don't know if that is the case for Chengdu
so it would be kind of interesting to know how that's going and in some ways it's nice to have like
I do like the idea of having like an art design division which is kind of responsible for making
sure that you know all the divisions have access to all the kind of design elements they need to
have a nice uniform look and styling to everything I kind of like that idea of having like this
putting it at the high level so that everyone can say okay well we need branding for our
program pages or our souvenir book or whatever and they can really be thinking about that in a
joined up way this is one of the reasons why I think I've been advocating for publications and
publicity to merge and become communications for a while because that should be under the purview
of one of those divisions probably under publications because they'll be right in the style guide but
it's not entirely clear which one should have that under their bail work which is why merging them
and because it should clearly be one of them but I agree I think and basically if you read the thing
I ain't quite clear that sponsorship and branding oh no because publicity they also have publicity
I don't understand but yes I think you're entirely right and that ties into things we've been saying
the other thing I noticed about this is that there is a there are 255 rooms on site and then
all of the other hotels are a little way away and I know nothing about public transport in
Chengdu but that wouldn't might have been a thing that when they were telling us about the hotels
they might also have told us about well and but you've got to bear in mind that you know when
ever British Random has done a split site convention it's worked flawlessly and there have been no
teething issues so I'm sure this will be fine yeah and what we mean by split site for Easter
cons for example is often across the road and people still have trouble with it
let's talk about Covid oh we had a few months off and now we're back on it again
it's conversation which is the Easter con that I am doing communications for has released its Covid
policy and um and a day later we kind of tightened up a bit or we clarified what we meant by a
couple of things because people said sure you don't mean this and we had a little conflasm we
went no we don't mean this we mean that so it's there you can read it we'll put a link to the
show notes I'm sure John and Liz don't have anything to say about it so we can move straight on then
so I think it is worth saying that this is obviously an area where you know Alison is working
on the convention and and is part of the communications for the convention and so
you may know is in this segment that me and John talk more and maybe Alison talks a bit less
than usual just because this is one of the first times I think it's come up that we're having a
discussion on the podcast where you know one person is involved in the convention we're
discussing which doesn't hasn't happened that often but it's probably likely to happen more
often as we work on more conventions and certainly there's bits of discussion about maybe shy con
where I had a small role where I would sort of sit on my hands and and not say things so if you're
wondering why Alison is a little bit quieter than usual and me and John are a bit noisier than
usual then that is why. John do you want to go first John just like your first what do you think John
or don't need to start yeah you start you're better at starting than me um I think on this one
I'm I think on this one I'm more in the middle ground than John I don't think it's a very good policy
basically so it's quite a long covid policy um when you compare it to things like maybe Boscon's
covid policy which is much shorter more straightforward it is quite long and I think that's also you
know it's always harder to get people to read and follow and understand the long set of rules but
I just think it kind of undercuts itself quite a lot so I'll say at the start it says it has been
possible for thousands to assemble at conventions like Dragon Meat, Game Expo and Fancy Con without
finding themselves at undue risk but it doesn't actually go on to tell me anything about why they
think those conventions in particular were good at not putting people at undue risk from covid because
I have no idea who at Dragon Meat or Fantasy Con got covid and I don't know if anyone was tracking
that or if anyone really knows so I think without a bit more detail on why they think it is possible
for people to assemble in specialist conference facilities it doesn't really reassure me very
much and then I would also say it kind of undercuts itself a bit which by saying things like
conversation 2023 recommends that you follow national guidelines in respect to vaccination
fine but then says we will not ask about vaccination status so vaccination is important but we won't
ask you to tell us your vaccination status or prove it it says please take a lateral flow test
before leaving home but then just says we will not ask you to show us your test results so it's
important to test but we won't ever check you did it because we don't care about them it just sort of
it's a bit overly complicated I just think you could do a much kind of simpler and more straightforward
one that might be easier to enforce and there's a few other ones basically saying we you know we
encourage members to mask but then saying we won't enforce it anywhere and you have to respect everyone's
choices on it fine just sort of like goes back and forth a bit I think they have clarified the
one about the program one originally said I think that panelists wouldn't be allowed to wear masks
it just now says they're encouraged not to wear masks but then it says you encourage to wear a
mask while attending program items but some items are explicitly tagged as masked optional and you
will not be asked to wear a mask so the other ones are implicitly masks required except they're also
masks optional and then it says that moderators may ask audiences to space themselves and wear
masks if rooms are crowded and if I was a moderator I would really hate being put in the position where
I was having to enforce a covid policy especially one that is kind of as back and forth as this one
so I think even without discussion of like where this sits on my personal spectrum of
feeling safe about covid and attending conventions and the time of covid I just feel it gives quite
a lot of mixed messages and I'm not really clear of whether the convention is really yes we should
wear masks but you know please respect there are a few people who can't wear masks and don't question
them about it or whether like we should wear masks but actually it's okay if you don't wear masks
but sometimes we'll ask you to wear masks but there are masks optional program items it just
doesn't feel like a very satisfactory covid policy to me that was my monologue I don't think there's
much to add to what you said actually Liz this might end up being a very short segment yeah that
basically neatly encapsulates everything I think I think so one of the things I said when the
policy came out in discussions on anonymous Claire if you're not an anonymous Claire let us know and
we'll invite you to that discord was that I found it odd that if I was a panelist on panels that
wanted to mask the original covid policy very much made me feel like the convention didn't want
me to do that and I think that has since been clarified which is good and they were good at the
at the previous east con you had to mask if you were an attendee unless you had a medical reason
not to but panelists were asked not to mask and I was happy with that because it felt like a good
mixture between accessibility and risk but this convention the masking on the part of the
participant seems like it will it will probably be less good just because of the difference in the
policies and so I I think if I am going to be on panels I will probably want to mask for that reason
so I was happy that it was clarified that that was something I could do I do think in general I sort
of wish that all of the things about whether or not these things would be enforced just hadn't been
set out loud because I think a policy where it's like we expect you to mask and then the internal
policy is but we're not going to actually like enforce it very well is probably better than saying
our large you're not going to enforce it very well because it makes you feel much more optional
than maybe the convention committee would like it to be I think there are a couple of bits where
I understand why it ended up that way but it doesn't I feel like it will result in less
masking and less testing and less people who have vaccinated which obviously as as long-time listeners
to the podcast will know makes me a little bit uncomfortable so the other thing I would say is
a aside from my kind of disagreements with how the policy is worded is it it is a bit weaker than
we've seen at previous Eastercons well I guess reclamation is the only one we've fully had in the
covid what covid era but it's weaker than other conventions and what I would say is it's weaker
and I'm not really sure why because I think you know last year it was you must show proof of vaccination
or proof that you're exempt from vaccination and as far as I can tell and I wasn't on the convention
committee so there may have been things I missed that didn't seem to be a massive barrier so unless
there were lots of people who were excluding because they couldn't get vaccinated and couldn't show
proof of not being able to get vaccinated I'm not really sure why we just didn't keep that and for
example I think you could have a very simple policy which was you must be masked when you are
watching program items in program rooms unless you are either on a mask optional item or you have
arranged a special lanyard to show that you don't have to mask which I know a few people had at the
previous Eastercons but not so many that it made me feel like there was a massive unmasked segment
of the audience and then if you've got that in place then I feel a lot happy about saying well
maybe we can have the five participants sitting quite far away who don't have to wear masks
and if the expectation is that you're wearing them in certain areas e.g. the program room and
you know there's a mast only social land which conversation said they'll have then that just
seems a lot easier for like expectations you can expect that if you go in a program room people
will be masked you expect if you go in the bar people will not be masked and it also just seems
like that would be more straightforward and a lot easier to enforce and then moderators can just say
they can just remind people that the policy is that in program you should be masked without it being
them having to make the choice to tell people they have to mask maybe without the convention
feeling like the convention is backing them up on that and I also think you could then write the
policy in half the space and you've more chance people reading it so it feels a bit to me like
this is a policy that is trying to cover all its all its bases and I do accept that you know
science fiction inventions by requiring masking at all are now falling quite far on the end of the
spectrum of covid prevention and covid precautions and I can see that you know we're at the point where
there's no realistic time in sight when we can drop these precautions you know essentially what
we're putting in place now might be what we have to keep in place for conventions for at least the
next few years but I think this one is falling a bit too far on the side of giving people lots of
options and the result will probably be most people are not masked and then that might mean that there
are people who don't attend because they don't feel they will be able to sit in program or they
don't feel that they'll be able to you know walk around conventions bases and decide not to attend
I know that conversation said there will be a hybrid convention but I don't actually know what
their hybrid provision is going to be there is a bit in the most recent newsletter saying you know
they're gonna they're gonna stream things but we don't have a huge amount of kind of concrete
information on that and I feel if they were telling me more to get me excited about the virtual
aspects then that might go alongside you know if there are a few people who say well I can't attend
unless the whole convention is masked which we know is impractical because there will be people
not from the convention in the hotel and the hotel staff and so we know you know we are never going
to be able to have a space where every single person is masked and if that is a barrier to people
then give them something to be excited about on the virtual side and at the moment conversation is
not giving me enough concrete stuff about the virtual side to make me feel excited about it
yeah I do think in hindsight having the covid policy go live at the same time as a lot of news
about the hybrid elements of the convention would have probably been a good idea well firstly
if everyone's discussing the hybrid convention fewer people will be annoyed about the covid policy
so just from a convention self-serving perspective I think that would have been good but I think
also what you said Liz I am annoyed by how like philosophically in the UK like I catch the
Metro and there are people like sneezing and coughing and wiping their noses and they're not
masked and it's like I feel like we had a real chance to adopt a culture where you cared about
not getting other people sick and I feel like that ship has sailed and I'm very distressed that
the wider British public have not decided to move in that direction it's just really annoying when
you see someone who's clearly ill on that trope and they're not masking and it's like well I don't
want your cold like sod off and one of the things I like about science fiction fandom philosophically
is that historically it's always felt like a space to me where we are one of the first groups
to adopt changes that make things better for those who are less enfranchised like science fiction
conventions were among the first events to adopt code of conduct policies science fiction conventions
brought in stuff like panel parity whereas like academic conferences still really haven't done
that and like it does annoy me because although I don't necessarily expect better from the general
public I think I did expect better from science fiction fandom and that makes me a bit sad which
is a very philosophical point but I think it's an inescapable one okay so I thought that was all
very kind of fair and to not kind of weigh off at one end I think the policy does reflect a range
of views we think it reflects it clearly reflects a raise of views in the committee but it also
reflects some of the range of views that we've been told by our members and by staff so we we have
been canvassing for views so we knew that we had really everything from everyone should be
masked at all times no exceptions you know all the way to nobody should be asked to be masked here
in 2023 because covid has gone away covid has not gone away I think it reflects the fact that there's
going to be a lot of people at this convention who are not subject to the policy not just hotel
staff but also other people in the hotel they'll be moving through convention spaces if you're
trying to be in an environment where there aren't unmasked people this isn't the right environment
because there are going to be a lot of unmasked people in the convention hotel and and quite a
lot of unmasked people in the convention space so including you know hotel staff and and people
moving through our space to get to other spaces in the hotel people can and and should reduce their
own risk dramatically by having a having an ff2 ffp2 or fp3 masks and properly wearing it and if
they're worried about risk they should use it consistently including when socializing so one of
things that happened last year is that almost nobody at easter con wore their mask when socializing
and most people at easter con socialized quite a lot so I think that was one of the things that
that caused some people to say well actually you're taking no effective precautions anyway
ignoring the fact there were a portion of the membership who were being extremely careful
people who want to be extremely careful should carry on being extremely careful and they will
reduce their risk very substantial we're trusting our members to be responsible grownups and making
responsible decisions we are saying don't come with symptoms and if anyone's obviously ill I think
that we've told you not to come to the convention and to leave the convention and isolate you will
be able to watch almost all of the convention online so you know that's a major point and you
can do it to the hotel room though though my my tech bunnies will say please if you have got 5g
watch the convention on your 5g rather than using the hotel Wi-Fi because we are slightly
worried that if if lots of people are watching the convention from the hotel room we won't have
the Wi-Fi for it but you know we're not going to change it now so it's probably not perfect I'm
sure it could be better but you know unless there's a major change in the covid situation
before Easter we're not expecting to change the policy we are expecting airflow to do quite a lot
of the heavy lifting for us we have over twice as much convention space as reclamation had last
year and the hiltons are much more modern and better laid out hotel generally in terms of space
and airflow and has recently upgraded all of its filters so we think it's going to be a lot better
and we think airflow does is a lot of what you want here I've said to everyone bring a sweater
because we'll leave doors open wherever we possibly can and and we are giving great funds if you if
as a result of this policy you don't think you can attend the convention we will refund your money
just get in touch but before you ask for a refund do consider whether you might enjoy the
convention online where you have no risk of getting covid any more than all of the rest of the time
in your life is that fair enough I I just I just want to push back a little bit on the idea that I
can take personal responsibility for my own risk by wearing a well-fitting mask because I think
you're then pushing the responsibility back on individuals for what is kind of a collective problem
like yes I could wear a well-fitting mask at all times but what would really help me not get covid
is if other people who have covid also wear a well-fitting mask and that I can't do anything
about and I think it's also you know you can say oh well people were socializing without masks on
but actually when I think back to my Easter con last year I socialized with the same group of
people consistently with masks off but then when I was in program I sat with lots of other people
and kept masks on and they were mostly keeping masks on so I don't think I think we kind of get
this kind of all or nothing oh well if you're going to the bar with that mask on then there's no
point wearing a mask any other time and I'm not sure that is entirely true and also we're saying a
lot of things about airflow and filtering but we've we've all become like armchair experts on airflow
and filtering now but there are kind of specifications for this kind of thing and what kind of filters
you have and what the air turnover is in your spaces and things like that and I think if you had
a bit more detail on that people might be able to be a bit more reassured because you know you
you can say it's got more modern filtering than the previous hotel but what I don't know is whether
you can say and also other conventions which have used this space have had masking policies and had
no case of covid or things like that or you can point to why this one is particularly good and
better I want to say two things I think there is a there is a lack of understanding of probability
distributions among the people having this discussion because if you wear a mask the center of your
probability distribution goes towards lower risk and what that means is that over the course of
a convention every time you wear a mask instead of not wearing a mask you are at lower risk and
so your integrated risk is lower as even if you go to a four-day convention and only wear a mask
for one program item your integrated risk will be lower than if you had not done that and so if
even if you're in the bar unmasked for a little bit you are still much safer masking the rest of the
time and I think people are forgetting that it isn't a binary you get covid or you don't I mean
obviously it is at the end but what it is is it's a risk profile and risk profiles are percentages
not yes no so I do think that's important maths I think I would say that and this is me not the
convention if you attend a science fiction convention where 800 people spend the weekend in a hotel you
are pushing your risk profile way over to the right at that point yes but every time you wear a mask
you're moving it back to the left I will also say I wore a mask most of the time I was socialising
at least calling it other than when I was actively drinking and the reason I remember that is because
one friend did comment on it while I was in the bar and I'm not saying that that friend's name
rhymed with schmallison mott but I'm not saying it didn't either but um but basically I mean we
decided at the last east con that we would probably be going to bed at midnight at the next east
con because it is also true the mask discipline drops substantially after about 11 p.m. midnight
which is basically where everyone is too drunk to make good decisions which um you know there's
probably I mean 100% but I would also like to say and I think this kind of gets to data I'd love
I think it would be a lot easier to have some of these conversations if we had like data which is
like you said you canvas members but I'd love to know like what the percentages are and like what
the sample size was no we didn't do it like that we just asked people what they thought yeah that's
the thing right yeah but where did you ask people what they thought and who did you ask and how did
you like get those people but also one of the things about asking people is that we know that when
we ask people we've got the same half dozen people who are commenting at length every time and we
are not going to make those people happy no you're not but if you did a survey and canvas properly
you could make the argument that it's those six dozen people is the half a dozen people think this
but like 85% of the convention disagree with them or it might turn out that 85% of the people
basically agree with them just are nowhere near as arseholely about it and that's the thing I'd
love to know I'd love to know what percentage of british fandom wants there to be a mask mandate
and what doesn't because if it turns out that I'm in the five percent of wanting one and 95%
of people don't I mean you know I mean I'd be annoyed the same way I'm annoyed about Brexit but
there's nothing I could do about it so I'd get on with things yeah I'm a bit worried that if we
actually said should we just abandon the mask policy we get some score of like 4852 and plunge
all fandom into war that's when it gets that's when it gets tricky I mean I think at some point
we're going to move to not having a mask mandate and so there's there's this question about how slowly
well yeah at some point we are going to do that and that point is in Easter we don't have a mask
mandate so yes obviously at some point we won't have a mask mandate because we don't have a mask
mandate as easy to say these things where they've already happened we are encouraging masking let's
I want to be completely clear we're encouraging a range of behaviors including testing avoiding
the convention if you're sick even if your test shows negative wearing masks whenever you might be
in close proximity with other people and there's a fourth thing and vaccination yeah you know
vaccination I didn't mention earlier but one of the reasons for not saying we'll check your
vaccination state it is that that is one of the things where national guidelines are very clear
they're very clear that you should not be doing it to the extent that they've basically said
oh we only issue covid passes now for people traveling abroad because events shouldn't be doing
this so so we want you to be vaccinated we think everyone should be vaccinated it's quite hard to
get vaccinations now you can't get boosters now if you don't have them already gonna add a couple
of things which is to john's point on the survey fandom is not a democracy and I don't know how many
like policies that we think are good policies and that we accept now like things like code of conduct
how many of them would have generally been you know approved by a majority of the of the fans
no that's that yeah that's a good and the other thing I would say is if you were canvassing opinions
from your members you will have missed out on a segment of people which is the people who aren't
joining your convention until you publish your covid policy because you said you you canvas
people on the covid policy and it would be we're not going to get too deep into weeds on this but
there is like a group of people you're going to miss the opinions of some groups of people
however you do it yeah canvas must have been too strong a word really and to go back to your point
about codes of conduct list I do completely see what you mean but I do think there is an element
here where it's just real tricky right I don't know whether I think it should be democratic or not
I made the point earlier about like wanting sci-fi fandom to do right by the less infantrized and I
do want that be equally I don't want to be a guy who keeps bloviating about an argument years after
he's lost it because I also strongly feel we should be in the EU but that's why I use Brexit as an
example I Brexit is something I feel very very strongly about but equally I have lost the argument
and like at some point I am going to have to be okay with that for my own mental health as much
for anything else
can we do pics yeah I suppose so my pick is pretty sure are you doing you're not doing you've changed
your pick right so it's not 17 different things oh yeah no I'm not doing that all right right
right should I go first yes okay yes my pick is living with ghosts by carrie sparing which is a
great book carrie sparing is one of the east con guests of honor I am trying to read at least one
book by all of them prior to the convention so I started with carrie sparing so this is a great
book it is slow to start I think it lays down the groundwork and I found some of the characters a
bit confusing because everyone has like a diminutive name and a proper name and there was a part of
the novel where I had not entirely resolved whether some people were two characters or one character
but by about page 50 I had got the hang of it so that's good but when it gets going
whole it gets going it's very sexy and very tense sometimes at the same time it's an extraordinarily
sexy book though oh full disclosure carries my mate I think living with ghosts is a very fine
novel so first novel I think but all of carrie's writing is great you should read it all I'm
delighted she's got a new book out of tista we should probably tout it um from Ian Waits and
which is a collection of her Arthurian novellas and I'm really looking forward to that and reading
that as well yes and also it's got a lovely cover what the new one yeah it does but yes that's my
pick good book would highly recommend so I have a slightly left field pick today I am going to
recommend a website called the owl job dot com side note do not just google owl job it has an
urban dictionary meaning so the website the owl job is it's a website with design lessons from the
owl job which is apparently Australia's first ever sightless escape room so it's a whole website
about how they built this escape room deliberately so it was designed to be run either by people
with low vision or for anyone who recited who was running the escape room they had to basically
put on goggles and play it as though they were not cited but it's really interesting it gets into
all the different things you have to do to basically make an escape room work for that group of people
kind of a lot of it's sort of obvious but I never thought about it and a lot of it is really
interesting and like okay you know this is just taking some universal rules of game design but
making sure you apply them in this situation and it was things like having a coherent tactile
language so that when they are feeling their way around the different puzzles they worked out what
was the best arrow shape to have so they could always consistently find an arrow and they tried
a bunch of designs that end up being confusing and they kind of show how they got to this one
design that works and it sounded like a fascinating escape room and I really wish I'd been able to
to try it out but it sounded great and it's essentially there to give the lessons they learned
from this to other people and show them how designing a sightless game uh it's like this escape
room does not have to be any more expensive or particularly difficult than designing any other
escape room you just have to approach it in a slightly different way and I think they hope that
there will be more escape rooms of this type so I think anyone who's interested in game design
would really enjoy this website noise my pick so I haven't really I still not really been doing
anything hopefully I'll be more or less back to normal next time we record I recommend
Spider-man movies or a spider-man movie which is Spider-man far from home I'm never going to cope
with two films which are sequels to or one of which is sequel to the other which are called
Spider-man far from home and Spider-man no way home I think I think that's like poor marketing guys
and you could have done better but anyway Spider-man far from home which I I kind of got to a point
where I was like what do I need I need something that it should be like an action movie but maybe
also a teen rom-com that's what I need and um so yeah it's great for the grief-stricken
distracted because at no point in this movie do you think that any of the kids are in any actual
danger because you know it's a teen rom-com movie so if one of the teams teams got stabbed through
the heart that wouldn't quite fit the vibe it's like glorious candy floss and it has a little bit
of multiverse and it it started to get that sort of sense of oh spider-man is more um more into the
multiverse than most of the Marvel heroes and I quite like getting that sort of sense coming along
in um in the in the mainstream movies and hopefully it'll all fit together in the third one which
we'll watch in the next week or two I should think I know I'm like six years behind on Marvel don't
write I think this is post-blip though so I think we're I'm like I've come to the end of the pre-blip
movies I think apart from the whole Ant-Man set which I probably need to watch soon as well I am
gonna catch up one day have you not watched the first Ant-Man yet no because we watched we had a
choice this time between should we watch the first Ant-Man or should we watch Spider-Man far from home
and we watch Spider-Man far from home should I've watched the first Ant-Man instead oh I think most
people would disagree that you should have done but Ant-Man is like one of my favorite characters in the
MCU so um okay I love them so I have quite a lot of movies as homework for for this fortnight so
just like Michael Pena in every anything I'm like down she's very funny I like funny I do like
in general Marvel is much better when I mean I like the funny bits right I don't like the
superhero fight bits partly because I think if you see them in the if you go see them in the cinema
then massive superhero fight fights are probably a lot of fun um but in in my living room with my
slightly shitty slightly old TV I'm kind of like oh no this is this is not very exciting so so I
like I like the jokes I'm there for the character development of the jokes please mmm that was the
art thought podcast and it's goodbye for me it's goodbye for me and it's goodbye for me
is it Spock amok or is it supposed to be like Spock mok and it rhymes or is this a US UK
difference well but a mock isn't pronounced a mock right is proud so muck it's going to be one
of these things like squirrel girl where you discover having read the entire series that squirrel and
girl rhyme in many parts of the US so it's sort of like squirrel girl which doesn't make any sense
to me but there we go so it's probably spucker muck I did not know no fair enough spark a mark
I think it probably is a US and US British um Spock amok Spock amok rhyme in my English actually
there we go because I say a mock not a muck but it's pronounced a muck because pronunciation is a
it's not a uniform thing and also I might just have learned it off reading books and therefore
just pronounce it wrong possibly like I was 17 before I realized how you say the carver so it
comes from the Portuguese amokko from the Malay amok so I think probably originally it was
pronounced amok but I would not be surprised if there were parts of the world where it rhymes with
Spock but I did say all of this on the last episode and we're just and we're just reiterating it for
no reason did we say all of the last episode and you cut it out would be really boring yes I said
literally out loud I think it's supposed to rhyme but I don't pronounce it to rhyme literally
said that on episode 27 with my words oh I wasn't listening sorry so I'm gonna have to cut all of
this out anyway because this is not interesting enough to revisit uh I did wonder I was like do
they remember that I mentioned that and now I know the answer is no okay so I'm gonna I'm gonna
say I spent I spent the last month in a distracted fog I don't remember anything at the moment
the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin mccloud and competec.com
used under a creative commons attribution 4.0 license this podcast will end at the beep beep
[BLANK_AUDIO]