That's a good point to say you all have access to chat.
We are encouraging you to write things in chat in real time.
The funnier the better.
You get points if you manage to make the panelists laugh.
- Can I pin three people at once,
or can I only pin one person once?
- No, I try that.
- Boo.
- Just turn it onto, it focuses on you when you're speaking,
and I think that will have to work.
- Yes.
- Andrew Hogg says, can I pin three people at once,
title of your sex tape?
(laughing)
- Excellent.
That's gonna be the title of the podcast then,
that's sorted, that is good to get that out the way early.
(dramatic music)
- Hello everyone, welcome to episode three
of the "Octer Thought" podcast, I'm John Coxin.
- I'm Alison Scott, and I'm Liz Bette.
And we are here recording on Zoom on Good Friday,
because we are not Teastacon,
although my Zoom background is the bar at the Hilton Metropolitan,
so I am there in spirit.
But I only have water at the moment, I will get beer later.
- Did we get any feedback on episode two?
It's not been that long, hasn't it?
- No, it turns out that if you only give people about two days,
no one really gives you feedback.
We got some feedback from a listener,
oh, who was it, listener, Alison?
Do you want to read out the feedback from listener, Alison?
- Alison?
- I think you should read out the feedback from,
I just send it to you, didn't I?
- You did send it to me, you sent me a letter,
I'm not sure how Gordian, a Robarussian,
a Robarussian, I could never pronounce that word.
Alison from London writes that the person
who does our new shiny theme music
also has every different sort of graph paper imaginable.
Boxes, triangles, hexagons, asymmetric logarithmic,
knitting charts, polar, Genco Yushi, music staves,
and many, many more.
It's highly configurable and you can make it look exactly
as you like and you can find it at
encompetech.com/graphpaper.
We also got a comment from listener Liz
that said that when she was listening to the podcast
before we released it, I asked a question of her
in the podcast as she responded to it in real life
in her flat, which was most excellent.
We got a comment from listener Andrew who said that
as he was walking up the stairs and fell over,
I said careful at the very moment he had just fallen over.
He accused me of being a witch
and we had feedback from Catherine Crockett
who asked us to do transcripts
and we are looking into doing transcripts at this point.
- I think I'm prepared to say we are going to do transcripts.
I think Liz has followed here.
- Yes, I felt guilty because John does all the recording
and editing, and Alison does all the making nice doegoes
and social media images and I so far do nothing at all,
including listening to the episode in a timely fashion.
So John, can we release it?
So I volunteered to assist with transcripts.
- I think I was lost to the accent this time.
- I think you're putting your contributions
in terms of your excellent opinions, which you vocalize,
which I think is the primary thing that you bring.
Both, but we all bring everything else is gravy on a cake
to continue the excellent metaphors.
How are you two dealing with the fact
that you've got three days of nothingness stretching ahead of you?
- I don't have three days of nothingness.
I seem to have vast numbers of parties.
I've had all of the fun of setting up the technical bits
and pieces for this podcast and planning
for a Zoom party tomorrow night.
And oh no, but I do have a plan for this weekend,
which is that I am going to take my four days
of uninterrupted peace and quiet
and I am going to get legend on pasta, maybe.
- Excellent.
- For the first time ever, I've been playing this game
for six years.
Hashtag not all that good.
- I think it's good to have realistic goals for your weekend
because I could say, you know, I'm going to clean my whole house
and I'm going to make hot cross buns
and I'm going to clean my laundry back.
But really, I'm not, I'm going to play PlayStation.
It's also not a bank holiday weekend for me.
So I just have two days stretching before me
where there would have been an Easter con.
- Fair enough.
It hadn't occurred to me to try and clean the house.
I've mostly been filling my Easter weekend up
with fun things to do.
And so I have assembled quite a lot of fun things.
- Any flat back furniture?
- Ha ha ha, no, no flat back furniture.
I'm not sure whether Ikea's open, but I haven't looked.
Have you guys got any virtual things happening
that are instead of Easter con?
- I don't have any virtual things instead of Easter con,
but I have a virtual thing that are part of Easter con.
The Easter con itself is running,
as far as I know, only one actual program item.
This is important.
I'm sure you guys are all going to be interested,
which is that they're running a virtual business meeting
at 2.45 p.m.
British summertime on Sunday
to choose the 2021 and 2022 Easter cons
and they have had bids for both of them.
So tune in then.
My guests, the details are going to be in email
and on their Facebook pages, so on.
I am holding a party if you know me
and you don't already have an invite to this party,
please get in touch and I'll sort that out.
If you don't know me, then it was like the sort of party
you haven't been used to con.
So you just need to talk to somebody
who's at the Easter con and knows me
and they'll give you the Zoom code.
But if we have over 100 people,
we're going to have to have some kind of corridor thing
going on or a tip jar to get the Zoom large parties extension
or something like that.
And so that's tomorrow night, late.
I think there are other parties happening
as several people have done virtual book launches,
but I don't actually have any diary entries
apart from those three, this to this and then two.
- I've got your room party and I've got the Easter con
and I've got the next session.
John Robertson did a show called Darkroom
at the last Birmingham Easter con.
And this weekend he is doing a 48 hour long darkroom session,
which is on his Twitch and on his Discord server.
And so that starts at 7 p.m. today.
So I will be dipping in and out of that.
I'm not sure I'm going to do the whole 48 hours
because obviously I'm going to come to your party Allison,
but I'm not going to get his sleep apparently.
So that's going to be fun.
- The reports of his show last time
were phenomenal, I didn't get to it.
And people said it was amazing.
So I need to go find more about that and make it happen.
Can we put a link in chat, please?
- There will be a link in the show notes.
I can indeed also put a link in the chat.
- Yes, unless you're very fast with the editing,
I think the 48 hour livestream might be over before then.
- I could be very fast with the editing.
- Yeah, that's what John's going to do this weekend.
- So yeah, so I'm doing that.
And also a podcast I Patreon is doing a panel tomorrow night,
which is actually not strictly speaking SF know,
but it is tabletop game related.
It is not deliberately East con related,
but it is in the same period as East con.
So I'm treating it as part of my East con.
So that'll be good, I hope.
- It looks like we're going to cover kind of the business
of the Easter con,
I've actually picking some more Easter cons.
And we're going to cover the social side
by everyone having Zoom parties.
But are there any actual sort of panel discussions
that anyone has spontaneously brought into being
over the weekend?
What part from this one?
- There's us.
- Yes, other than us.
I mean, I assume the reason there are people listening
is that we are the only available panel type discussion
over the weekend and so they really have no choice.
I just wondering if anything else was going on.
- I'm going to suggest that this is something
that people can do for themselves.
Fine, three people who are interested in the same thing
as you and announce that you're going to run a panel
and stick it on the Facebook group
and people will cover listen to it.
- Yes.
- I think that's a complete plan.
I think start here, get people involved,
tell them once they've listened to one,
they should start another one and the viral spread
is high enough.
I understand so much more about that than I did four weeks ago.
If my viral spread is high enough,
then we will just have everyone in the world
will be involved in the Easter pub panel
by 6 p.m. Monday.
- And I think me and you Liz are doing the game room
on Saturday afternoon, so that will be fun,
but doesn't scale very well.
But obviously if you miss the game room,
there is table top simulator and I don't know.
We were thinking about doing a panel,
but I couldn't think of a good panel topic.
So I ended up not pursuing that
as far as I should have done perhaps,
but I was thinking about trying to do something like that.
And I hope other people will,
but I haven't seen anything yet.
If people know of anything, please post it in the chat.
- It's interesting that the bits of the Easter con
that we have jumped to recreate are kind of all the
frivolous bits around the panels,
but not the actual science fictional discussion so much.
- Yes, that is a fair point.
I don't think if you had asked anyone at Easter con fandom
whether they thought the like one third of the people
who were responsible for doing the only panel
or substitution was me,
they would have guessed that that was correct.
But here we are, it truly is an odd time.
(laughing)
- For me.
- You're clearly very esophanoid serious, Alison.
We all know this secretly.
- I'm famed for it, famed for my dedication
to the art of talking about science fiction.
Right, so the other thing that they did
is that I was gonna be guest of one of this weekend,
which would have been amazing.
And two things happened that Caroline put together
a thank you card for the committee,
which went to them in the end with art by Sue Mason
and 130 signatures quite a lot of them
were actually from couples and families.
So I thought that was pretty phenomenal.
And now of course there's a long thread going,
I never saw the card,
which of course we'd had to virtually circulate
in Starrup Tish's ways,
which is one of these things that is harder than you would think.
And then the other thing was that the,
apparently they've been putting together a Facebook group
for the last week, all about me,
which I thought was very sweet of them.
So I was quite miserable.
I think when we're gonna talk about misery,
I was quite miserable last night in particular.
There was a point about 11 o'clock
when I was kind of getting rid of your bed and thinking,
I shouldn't be in bed, I should be in a bar.
What I should be doing now is I should just be settling in
for maybe three or four hours more of going.
I should really get to bed,
but it's the first night of the Easter card
and I'm not ready to get to bed just yet
because I've just seen all these people have.
And at that point, it really all hit me
and it was just terrible.
So I went to bed anyway.
And then when I got up in the morning,
there was this lovely,
this was full of people being nice about me,
which is lovely because that's not my normal experience
for fandom.
I'd normally, I think,
especially if you're con running,
people are very appreciative,
but people are also very quick to tell you
about everything that you do wrong.
So maybe we should do a little more of that.
Patrick has said that took a lot of conspiring
against you, Alison, don't feel paranoid.
Yeah, it was very sweet.
I thank you all so much.
I really agree.
And I recommend being fangest of honor at an Easter card,
even if it doesn't happen, it's awesome.
Apparently.
I came so close to spilling the beans about that
last week on the podcast.
Really?
You mentioned something else,
which didn't end up in the final edit.
And I asked a bit, I thought,
she doesn't know about the Facebook group yet,
but that would have been a very germane thing
to discuss at this point.
But yes, I didn't want to spoil the surprise.
(laughing)
So you nearly spent the bean.
I'm very slow on the up plate.
So I would not have noticed it.
You could have probably mentioned it quite thoroughly
without me even noticing it.
You could have said it on, of course,
there's a Facebook group.
And I could have got what Facebook group
would you have corrected?
And I'd have got, oh, well, I'm sure I'll see it.
I was blindsided.
I had no clue.
You were all muted and I've stopped all your video
so that we could do the podcast bit
and then we'll have a barbit at the end.
- And then we'll be drinking.
And hopefully my local pub will have delivered my beer by then,
but I don't know.
- That would be amazing.
- It would.
- It would like a delivery from the green room.
- Right there into the lobby of the Metropole.
- Yes, indeed.
I'm looking forward to it.
It's gonna be a porter.
I'm very excited.
That's one of the very big things about doing paddles
is usually that you get beer.
I am bereft of beer at the moment.
So this is very sad.
- It's okay.
I'm paying for every beer I drink this weekend
out of the fivers I'm not spending on points of beer
in the Hilton Metropole Birmingham.
(laughing)
That is fair.
So being the fan guest of Anna doesn't come
with an unlimited beer budget.
- To be fair, they were going to give me a very good podium.
It would have been fine were it not for the fact
that I was going to use it to pay the hotel bill
of my children.
So how are you two coping with the whole,
there's not an Easter come?
- I am quite busy this weekend.
I think I am, I'm gonna miss it.
Obviously it's not the same trying to do everything virtually.
Anna, there are people who I won't see,
who I would normally, who I will dearly miss.
Obviously there is the disco and your room party
which are happening on Saturday night.
So hopefully they will address some of that.
But yeah, it's weird.
It's a big empty thing where there was going
to be a lot of fun and drinking.
I mean, obviously my bank balance is very happy about it,
but I don't know, my mental health, perhaps less so.
- Well, for me it's actually good
because I probably wasn't going to make it in person.
And last year I didn't make it in person.
And what I got was lots of people sending me photos
and sending me videos and sending me gossip.
And it was very fun, but I was in my flat going,
"Hmm, this is a bit less fun when you're not there."
So for me it's actually an upgrade
because I wouldn't have been able to go to the bid session
at all and now I can go to the bid session.
I wouldn't have been able to go to Alice in the room party
and now I possibly can go to Alice in the room party
if I get up very early in the morning
or stay up very late at night in one of those things.
So it's working out pretty well for me,
but I appreciate that is a strange view on it.
But there may be other people who weren't going to make it
in person this year who now also can get
these fringe benefits.
- I really enjoyed OsyCon 4, is it the 2010 Worldcon
was in Australia?
- It was OsyCon 4.
- Despite the fact that I wasn't there,
I was in Wolfenstow and I helped flick from the newsletter.
Flick was in Australia for OsyCon.
And what we did is that when they went to bed
I would pick up all of the outstanding news stories
and write and edit an issue of the newsletter
on my Mac in Wolfenstow because the newsletter system
that we use, it's actually all in the cloud.
The formatted newsletters isn't in the cloud,
but all of the text is.
And I did that and then they get up in the morning
and just do the final edits and print.
And we made loads of jokes about the fact
that I was doing this in Britain
and nobody realized that the fact that we said so repeatedly.
So I did about three or four shifts on the newsletter.
It was actually really, really good fun.
It was, I felt that I was enjoying the convention much more
than I would have done normally a Worldcon
that I couldn't be at.
And I have a very long experience of Worldcon,
so I can't be at, so there we go.
That was a good way to do it.
If I'd had more time, I'd have suggested to persons
that we do a virtual newsletter for concentric.
It's probably not too late actually, but anyway,
I had no promises.
- Not too late.
- I did wonder whether that would be a fan scene
that came out, whether someone would do a virtual newsletter.
And I was sort of tempted to do it.
I sort of thought about it about 6pm yesterday.
I thought I needed probably more notice
than I have given myself to actually achieve anything with this
because I was going to try and do a compilation
of stuff that was happening.
But it would be funny, especially for Conzeland,
it would be fun if someone did a fan scene
that was a newsletter of an increasingly less
and less likely Worldcon that never actually happened.
That could be a very good project, I think.
Conzeland is working very hard to virtualize.
I had Happy Hour yesterday.
And Esther McCallen-Stuert had to run off
because she's part of the Conzeland virtualization effort
and they're having lots of really serious meetings
about how you virtualize a Worldcon
and what sorts of things you do.
I mean, I'm well used to newsletter being very much
an afterthought for these sort of things,
but newsletter is the sort of thing
that if I were running a large virtual convention
and who knows that might happen in the future.
If I were running a large virtual Worldcon,
a convention, I would definitely want to have a newsletter
'cause that's how people find out about.
And it's how you filter the stuff
so that people see what's interesting.
- And it should be entirely PDFs that are left
in random corners of the internet
so that you can't go to a single webpage
and just read them conveniently, right?
That is the newsletter that we have,
that we should try and replicate that where possible.
- You're being very hard.
For the last several years now,
we have actually managed to put the thing
on the website quite quickly.
- I know, I know, I'm joking, I'm joking.
I speak as one who edits newsletters, I speak with love.
- Yes, but yes, that's certainly a thing that we do.
- My newsletters have not been on the internet, Alice,
and like, I have definitely bought the problem
and not bought solution in this particular regard.
I've done nothing.
- It's really complicated because we've got to a stage
in the world where people produce PDF fanzines
that are meant for a fairly small group
of fanzine fans to read.
And if they do that in the wrong way,
those things that are contained in them
can go viral badly.
Now, in general, I think we're okay with newsletters.
We've kind of got the hang of what we cannot put in a newsletter,
but it's only true that in the newsletter,
there are jokes that do not get into the newsletter,
which is just the way of the world now.
And they would have gotten to a newsletter before the end.
And in fact, if you can read all convention newsletters
written by some very witty, witty people
who would not be able to do that now
in that way without getting into terrible, terrible trouble.
- So I would say it may be too late
for you to do a convention newsletter,
but it's definitely not too late for you to do a one-off
spoof convention newsletter of a convention
that's not actually happening.
- Yes, yes.
- I will talk to the person who was going to be running
a newsletter this weekend
and see how they are feeling about.
- Oh, hello.
Spidey has just said that she's technically the green room.
She could have bring me a gin and tonic.
Now this, this is great.
What you need is someone in your house
who is listening to your podcast
who will bring you alcohol.
This is most excellent.
- Hang on.
I have no more moment.
Please bring alcohol.
(laughing)
Listen, the Bridget has given us some feedback
on episode one in chat,
which is Switch Controller also sounds like a sex toy.
- Wait, the green rooms arrived.
Cheers, everyone.
- I'm not sure John heard that.
- I did.
I did.
I heard that the Switch Controller sounds like a sex toy.
It does.
I was very conflicted about whether or not
to leave the end because I was like,
is this the right tone?
And then I decided to embrace it,
make it the title of the episode.
So we've made a clear commitment.
- So what else did we have on the list to do today
apart from talking about the fact we were not a piece to cut?
- We were going to congratulate someone
on the podcast, I believe.
Well, I was anyway.
So congratulations to Hugo nominee Coxon.
- Oh, yes.
That's right.
- Thank you very much.
- Congratulations.
Being a Hugo nominee is awesome.
- It is.
It is.
It is a little pin.
- How many is that now?
- I have two little pins or I will have two little pins.
Or I will.
I have one little pin and assuming Conzeland do little pins,
given that there won't be a Worldcon at all,
which is up in the air, one presumes.
'Cause shipping a bunch of little pins from New Zealand
around the world might not be a good use of their resources.
I don't know.
- Shipping tiny pins around the world is much cheaper
than shipping massive hugas around the world.
- That's true.
That's true.
- So I think it's going to be fine.
I think you'll get your pin.
In respect, I will not win a Hugo
because the raft of other finalists is incredibly strong.
And although I think Journey Planet does great work
and we are definitely in with the chance,
we are also in a position where,
if we lost one of the other finalists,
that would be thoroughly deserved.
But it also occurs to me that if I ever do win a Hugo,
I would want it to be in a year
where the Hugo was not virtue.
I think I would quite like it to be a physical artifact.
So hopefully they do shit massive chunks
of metal around the world.
The really interesting thing will be,
given that the rockets are made in the UK,
will they have the rocket shipped to New Zealand
and then shipped from New Zealand around the world?
Or how will that work?
- I bet they will.
(laughs)
- I don't know.
That's an interesting question.
- They only announced the winners
of the base design competition.
I can't know who they are,
but I think they are New Zealanders.
So yes, they probably will have to ship the rockets
to New Zealand, put the bases on
and then figure out how to dismantle them
and FedEx them back to you.
So that's going to be fun.
- That would be my guess.
- Well, and actually posting the little mini rocket pins
to all the nominees might be better
than the current situation
where they tend to put them in those big envelopes
that you get at registration
and they all get lost in the bottom.
- Yes.
I also hope I get a ribbon.
I don't want to be done out of a Hugo finalist ribbon.
So I hope they send ribbons out as well.
- I've been a Hugo finalist back in the days
when they call them nominees rather than finalists.
I've been a Hugo nominee quite a lot of times
and you would think that I would have carefully stored
all my pins where I could find them,
but I do have a couple.
And then Madrecon did gold ones
because I think it was the 50th Worldcon
or the 50th Hugo's or something.
And so I have that gold pin somewhere.
I did see one of the nominees saying,
"I'm thrilled to be nominated."
But it's so sad that I'm being in a nominated in the year
when I can't be at the Worldcon.
And most of the years I was nominated,
I had tiny children and the Worldcon
who was not in the UK.
And I had years of being nominated
and not being able to go to the Worldcon.
And desperately wanting to go to the Worldcon.
You know, I just wanted the whole Hugo nominees experience.
But this story has had the ending
because in 2005, the Worldcon was in Glasgow
and plucked to won the Best Fanzine Award,
which is as everyone knows, the big one.
- Yes.
It's like Robert Silverberg was saying
when he presented a Hugo at Com Jose, I think it was.
He got the Hugo for Best Fan Writer in the retro Hugo's
and he has put it as proudly as the rest of the Hugo's
on his shelf because it is still a Hugo Award.
But he says he strongly suspects he won it
because he is a famous author,
not because the fan writing he did in that year
was of the highest quality in fandom,
but it's still a Hugo and it still takes a proud place
in his collection.
So yeah, I think Fanzine is a very good one to win.
I don't think I'll ever win it for Fanzine,
but I live in hope that I will,
but the nominees are just so, they're just so strong.
They're just so good.
(laughing)
- So who are the Fanzine nominees this year?
- The Books Bugglers, Galactic Journey, Journey Planet,
Nerds of a Feather Flock Together, Quick Sip Reviews
and the Rec Center.
So that is a strong roster.
- I know lots of Hugo nominees,
lots of people who are Hugo nominees,
it's really nice that so many,
so many people that I know have got the relations,
so that's amazing.
Congratulations to all.
- I think, it's the last year,
Lady Business One and they are not on the ballot,
so I don't know whether they declined their nomination
or I don't know whether they just haven't been active enough
this year to get nominations.
I sort of assume it's the,
I sort of assume that they've declined, but I don't know.
- This is why the most exciting part of the Hugo's for me
every year is the very end of the ceremony
when the people who put the Hugo's together,
at the very end of the thing,
they produce a huge document
that shows exactly what was voted for in everything,
or all the nomination stage, all the finalist stage,
and it is the most fascinating thing.
It tells you who declined things,
where you have a thing where your particular favourite
missed the nomination,
but missed the finalist by one vote and you go,
probably should have voted, and all of that sort of thing.
(laughs)
- I always vote.
I don't always vote in every category,
'cause if I don't feel particularly well informed
that I don't necessarily vote in a category,
'cause I'd rather better informed people make the decision,
but I do always vote in at least one category,
and usually most of them.
- Listen O'Neill says, "stat that,"
which I wholeheartedly concur.
- I mean, he said it more, "shouty,"
that you just did it, which is impressive.
- Sorry, listen O'Neill said, "stat, stat!"
- That is what I wanted.
It's a rare case where you have to tell Alison
to be more "shouty."
(laughs)
- It's just a spot on impression.
I mean, it's like he's in the room.
- I haven't been paying enough attention
to not talking to you two,
and I didn't notice that it was actually hog
that started the stats charm,
so I expect it's supposed to be more like,
"stat, stat, stat, stat, stat, stat, stat, stat, stat, stat,
stat, stat, stat, stat, stat!"
- Right, suspicion.
- Like a statistical Mexican away.
(laughs)
- Yeah, something like that.
- I have just checked, and Lady Business did recute,
say they would decline the nomination
in fanzine before the nominations were announced,
so there you go.
- Excellent.
I mean, excellent research on Liz's part.
I have not.
Don't be an excellent that they recused.
- No, I still think it's a very nice,
I still think it's a nice gesture when, you know,
when it's say, "Okay, we've won, that was great.
"Thank you, please check out everyone else."
- Yeah, I think that's true.
I think obviously, you know, come back to me
when I've won a whole library of hughos, right?
'Cause maybe I'll feel differently
if I ever actually win one.
But I sort of feel like if you've won three times in a row,
that is about at the point where you should start thinking,
is this for the best?
First, fan cast winner one, three times in a row,
and then recused themselves.
It was at the SF Squeecast.
- I don't know, but we'll look it up,
and then he will drop it in seamlessly into the podcast, right?
- Seamlessly, yeah, obviously.
- Now, the retrohugo ballots only attracted 120 nominations,
which don't seem like very many.
We must be getting to the end of retrohugas.
We must be running out of years
for which we could award them.
- So I worked this out,
and there's like another six or something.
We're not as close as I thought we would be.
- The way you've said that makes it sound like
you were hoping it would be closer, Liz.
Do you want to talk about that some more?
- I just, I don't know.
I think maybe the first time I was like,
oh, this is quite a neat idea.
Well, award the hughos for you.
We didn't do it.
We'll go back and look for everything and award them.
And I think it's just been kind of diminishing returns
as evidenced by the number of people
who actually nominate because it takes a long time
to really go and inform yourself
about the potential nominees.
And I think a lot of it is not based on what they did
in that year or where they were in their careers
up to that point.
It's based on kind of the whole of their careers
as we saw it, especially for the fan awards.
So I think, I don't know, we've just reached a point
where maybe it's not worth carrying on to finish them off
when there are only 120 people
who are particularly interested in nominating.
- I'm sure there are more people interested
in nominating than that,
but only 120 actually got to get it onto the balance.
I think I'm not a big fan of O, Lillian.
- You're not a big fan of Lillian.
Is that what you just said?
'Cause that's very mean.
- Welcome, Lillian.
I'm enormous fan of Lillian,
but I have mute Lillian and put a stop to video
along with everyone else who's not up
for the podcast part of this.
And then in a bit, we'll have the bar part of it
and they'll put it back up again.
I'm not a very big fan of the retrohughos.
I've never particularly thought they were a good thing.
I don't think we need more awards than we've got.
And then they have all those inherent problems
that they're not quite doing what they think they're doing.
On the other hand, I do know people whose parents
or grandparents have been awarded retrohughos
who've been absolutely thrilled by that,
that that's been just the most enormous honor for them.
And yeah, that's quite,
I wouldn't personally have invented it.
And if I were running a Worldcon,
which is not a thing that's ever gonna happen,
I would be in the class of people going,
well, we could theoretically award retrohughos,
but we're not gonna do that if at all possible.
- I think it's one of those things where it's a nice idea,
but it would be, it's very difficult to do it well.
I think it's really nice idea to go back to the years
where there were no hughos and award works hughos
for the years that didn't get them.
- Why?
- Because I think it's cool to have a view
of what Worldcon thinks the best work was
in each year that Worldcon existed.
Having said that, I share both of your concerns
that the actual process of doing retrohughos
has not in fact achieved that goal,
because I think people do win,
who are still active in the field for things
that perhaps they weren't really the best.
And I also think that I sort of feel like there is a slant here
where a lot of science fiction fans
and I count myself in this are completionists,
and we don't like seeing an incomplete set.
If you've got a set, it should be a complete set,
and if you don't have a complete set,
what was the point in the set?
And so I think there is an element here
of the completionism being the driving factor,
and I'm not sure completionism is a good enough reason to do it.
I would be more comfortable with it if it was a jury reward
where like 10 people who are very knowledgeable
go away and research and say,
here are the people we think should be given the hughos,
but then that doesn't really drive
with the principle of the hughos being awarded
by the Worldcon fandom.
So I don't know, I don't know that there's a good way
of getting around the problem, and so I am an R.
Equally, I'm quite happy for the people who like it
to keep doing it, and I don't really have to pay attention,
which is usually my view on many things.
So, because I was the people doing it happy,
I don't really mind.
That's not nearly inflammatory enough, is it?
(laughs)
- I tried.
Kent Bloom has said,
do you want to be remembered as the best fanzine except for X?
- I think there are cases where you do have
like the obviously finest thing of the year.
There's much more happens in novels
where people who have one of you novels
take their jaw-dropping novel out of the hughos.
But I think for fanzine, I think for example,
when Plochter won, we were probably the best fanzine
that wasn't answerable.
And you know, A, Plochter, I think I should state now,
Plochter has never been, was never the best fanzine
of the year, not at any time.
That's not what the hughos are not actually awarded
for the best things they're awarded
for the things that people enjoy.
There's a word, there's a form of word.
It's something like the things that you enjoyed
the most over the year and want to see nominated
or something like that.
But I don't think anyone goes now,
oh that award won in a year,
but three fans need to remove themselves from the ballot.
I don't think that's a problem,
except in the case where you have something like,
you know, a film or a movie or a book that looks like
the thing that everyone talked about all year
and then the creators took it off the ballot.
That's a little bit different.
Even then I don't think anyone will remember 10 years later,
they would just go, oh that's what won the hugho
in that year, is it?
So yes, I'm very happy, very proud to have awards
for the best fanzine that wasn't answerable
in 2005 and 2006.
- But you say answerable is the best fanzine,
but certainly I laugh more at Plochter than I do answerable,
but I find out a lot less actual information
about upcoming events in Plochter than I do in answerable.
So it really does depend on what you want.
In some ways, sort of, I think you can make a coherent argument
that answerable is a very, you know, in some ways,
answerable is the best fanzine,
and in some ways it's clearly not.
And I don't know, I don't mind winning.
I think the thing is, if I have a hugho,
I'll be over the bloody moon
and I'm not going to be worried about whether or not
I want it in a year that anyone recused themselves.
And arguably the fact that Father Them and 70 recused
itself in advance means that we don't know whether
it would have been nominated.
Like he said he would recuse himself
so people didn't nominate him, but how do you tell?
I don't know, it's a very hard question,
but I'll be over the moon if I ever win a hugho.
So yes, that is, I think my answer.
- I recommend winning a hugho.
(laughs)
I especially recommend winning a hugho
to convention your app because it's the best thing.
It really is, it was absolutely amazing, loved it.
We'll never have to get it, but it was a lot of fun.
- If anyone's been hearing rattling,
I have now located my hugho pin.
Zoom is very helpfully making it part of the background.
(laughs)
It's very difficult to actually show because it's very thin.
- We can see it.
- And I will put a link in the show notes.
- You know everyone knows what this looks like.
- Not everyone, Tobes doesn't pay attention.
Tobes is in the audience.
Hi Tobes, Tobes has confirmed that he doesn't pay attention
in the chat, but that's a paradox because for him
to have noticed I mentioned that he would have had
to have been paying attention.
So we have ourselves a logic trap on our hands.
- Tobes pays more attention than you think.
(laughs)
- Next is probably audience questions
'cause I'm sure everyone is very keen
to know what we think about things.
- While we're asking for people to write questions,
we will talk about what we're doing to stay sane
in the apocalypse.
What do you do to stay sane in the apocalypse?
- So I have still obstinately not been doing any reading.
I haven't read any of my books.
Since the first episode where I mentioned the book
I was reading, I have been playing an awful lot of board games.
I've been playing a board game,
which I actually have here called Marvel Champions.
It is a great game.
I bought it before the apocalypse,
and it turns out it's very good single player.
So I've been playing that on my own.
And then I've been playing a game called
Arkham Horror of the Card Game with various people,
including my wife, and we played some of that this morning.
Playing PlayStation, watching TV,
watched board knives out and watched that,
and watched Rio window, the Hitchcock movie,
which is really, really good.
So I've been watching more movies.
- Does the house your screen time been?
- My screen time, I would say
about the same as normal actually.
I don't think it's significantly gone up.
- So about 17 hours a day then.
- Well, the thing is, as someone who works in an office
whose job is predominantly making code go, yes,
probably about that, 'cause eight hours a day for work,
and then plus whatever leisure.
But I'm very fortunate in that I have not been furloughed,
and my work does not need me to be anywhere in particular.
I think I am incredibly lucky in that regard,
and it's spannier is also still full time.
So we are both, I think, very lucky.
I'm not really thinking of it as screen time,
because I mean, it is screen time,
but it's also chatting to friends time,
watching people on Zoom and Teams time,
sending WhatsApp messages time.
I mean, so I live alone,
and the furthest I've been since that same morning
is to the car park to collect my groceries
when I'm at a living my grocery.
So if I didn't like spend my screen time chatting to people,
then I literally would not have spoken
to another human being for a week.
So really, the screen time is what is keeping me going.
But yeah, actually I'm doing okay.
I don't seem to have that much free time.
I'm not sure how John is fitting in board games,
and TV, and video games, and books,
because I seem to spend all my time now
hoovering and doing the washing up.
Oh, I did say I would plug,
so I've been doing my daily exercises
in front of the TV to YouTube videos
to a channel called Team Body Projects.
You can go and Google them,
and they have a bunch of free videos on YouTube
of like all levels from beginner
to really quite hard work exercise,
and some of them you can tailor
like high impact, low impact, based on what you want to do.
And they've got someone demonstrating both on screen.
So that's really good.
- After talking about it for about three weeks,
I finally got to the point where I have my dancing mat
plugged into the television.
The amount of tidying up this required
for the living in the living room was quite a lot,
and I have got my PlayStation 2 going,
and I am playing Dancing Stage Fusion,
which is Dance Dance Revolution for people
who don't remember the 90s and the early 2000s,
and it is a game where as the music plays,
you have to move your feet in time with the music.
It's the best thing ever.
I did this because I had been trying now for it.
When Nintendo switched Ring Fit Adventure,
which is a game that you're supposed to play
to get you fit whilst also playing a fantasy game,
came out, I decided I was buying nothing,
and so I did not need this thing.
At the start, at the very beginning of the apocalypse,
before people had realized it was the apocalypse,
I decided I would, after all,
get a copy of Nintendo Switch Ring Fit Adventure
to discover it was unattainable everywhere.
So this is my methadone for the new posh game,
which is an old, but nevertheless excellent game
that will keep you fit.
And I started it yesterday,
so I now have a streak of one consecutive days
of hitting my Apple movement target,
which is not bad, I like five targets,
I don't think it's better than,
'cause otherwise I've just been essentially animating myself
as a slug for a fortnight.
And then I finished playing this game,
got some water, went down to rest,
and stockinformer.com told me that Ring Fit Adventure
was in stock at Amazon from.
So I have a French copy of Ring Fit Adventure,
a wiggy gets read to me in the near future.
- I see various people in the comments
are recommending Beat Saber,
and as I had to go in Dublin this year, it is amazing.
And if I had like the VR headset and everything,
I would be playing that, so.
- That's a lot of money though, isn't it?
You need an actual Oculus Rift thing, or a headset.
I think you could do it on PSVR,
so you could do it for somewhere in the region of 300 to 400 pounds,
I think, but yes, they're still not
in surmountable amount of cash.
Okay, we have a lot of questions.
Patrick McMurray says that he read an article somewhere
which said, "Humanity was failing at apocalypse
on the easy level, what do you think?"
I saw an article that said that we are getting the art
of the coronavirus down to nearly one in several countries,
or at least one within errors.
So I feel pretty optimistic about our reaction
to the apocalypse, you know,
notable edge cases notwithstanding.
What do you two think?
Are we doing well?
How do we know if we're doing well?
But it's your own expert.
- I haven't been thinking of it as an apocalypse,
although maybe that's just because it is better
for my mental health not to assume I am in an apocalypse.
I don't think we're doing amazingly well,
but I don't think we're doing appallingly badly.
I think we're somewhere in the middle.
Like it's taking us a while to make the responses
that we need to make.
And I think we're reacting a bit now
rather than planning ahead for what we're gonna do next.
But we are kind of succeeding in a circumstance
that I'm not sure people had really planned for this.
Like I think people had planned for, you know,
they'd looked at SARS and take an example of SARS,
but SARS was like different in several crucial ways
from the current coronavirus.
And so, you know, maybe you couldn't quite use,
if you're taking that as an example,
maybe you would plan to do things
that wouldn't actually be effective.
But I think we're somewhere in the middle.
We're not doing appallingly.
We're not doing amazingly well.
There are obvious examples of places
which, you know, I just look at what they're doing
and I check my head.
And it's on a macro scale.
Like I see countries doing the wrong thing
and on sort of a micro scale,
you can see, you know, people in niche areas
coming up with the wrong conclusions
and writing bad papers and things like that.
But I think we're sort of the moment on a middle ground.
- Is that the world or the UK?
- Oh, the world mostly.
'Cause I think I'm not quite as okay with how the UK
is doing and it's hard for me to judge
because I can't go out and see what's happening there.
I can't go out and see if there are people around
or kind of get a feel for what's going on with your neighbours.
But then I guess no one can really do that anymore.
- Lillian says, do you think the pandemic
will see a resurgence of fanzines or appers?
And I would like to point out,
I think we started a podcast in reaction
at least partly to the fact
we were gonna have a lot more time on our hands.
And I've been editing my TAFT report.
So I think there is a more fat act happening.
- What do you do, thank you?
- We were planning the podcast well in advance
of lockdown to be fair.
It just happened that the lockdown gave us the impetus
to actually get on with it.
But it's been in trade for a little while.
I seem to be doing quite a lot of fat act at the moment.
But in fact, lots of things for which I like the peace
and quiet of my own normally quiet study
have been very seriously disrupted by the fact
that I now have a husband who is working for full time
in my quiet, peaceful study
and a daughter who is studying for her final term at Oxford
in the peace and quiet of my study
and a son who is playing switch games quite loudly,
very close to the peace and quiet of my study.
And it's actually very hard to get anything done at all.
- That's fair.
- I am currently coming to you from a virtual environment.
So unsuitable for doing a podcast
that I'm not ever going to remove that virtual background.
Oh, but I've bought a green screen.
- You've bought a green screen?
- I've bought a green screen, just a cheap one.
That is definitely something that wouldn't happen
if the apocalypse hadn't, right?
Like, I don't think Zoom and other such
conferencing tools have made green screens
look a lot more sensible than they did three weeks ago.
- When I got the Rotsaw award, it came with money.
And that was very nice.
And I've been using the money for doing
some slightly finished things.
And it struck me that seeing as I seem to be spending
a lot of my time doing fan activity online
buying of green screen was a suitable thing.
I just live in a very beige environment.
So I don't need a green screen.
My environment's very busy.
I have laundry behind me, which helps my acoustics,
but it does make green screens a lot harder
'cause it's all patterns, as you can tell
from my t-shirt choices.
So what did I ask whether the games
I was mentioning were playable online?
And I will put a link in the show notes,
but the short answer is if you get a game called
Tabletop Simulator, you can play many different
board games online.
And the two I mentioned are indeed available through that.
And Nick Upson has asked which book, film,
or other story best predicted the current situation
of behaviours, do you think?
- This is why you probably wouldn't go to us
for your serious science fictional panel, isn't it?
So I'm now thinking about this and I'm not sure.
- But Charlie Strauss did say he had a whole treatment
for a novel that was based on this thing,
but he had this idea that as we know from history,
people do pull together in difficult times
much more than science fiction
tends to predict that they will.
A couple of people have recommended them.
I have been reading "European Auto"
which somebody mentions down the thread
that does indeed it's a bulk-an-ised Europe following
pandemic, so I don't know whether that's how we're going
to end.
It feels to me like Europe's pulling together quite well
with us not in it.
Lily and I asked, should we all dress up for your party?
And I feel like you should dress as you would normally
on the Saturday night of an EasterCon.
Or not as you choose.
Just, I mean, where's something?
It's not a closed optional party.
Where's something unless you want me to stop your video?
- Needless recommended "Song for New Day"
by Sarah Pinska and "Severns" by Lingmar.
I will say that has made me think we probably should work out
which Kim Suni Robinson, three Californians,
we would like to be and see if we can get there.
- Zoe has asked, and I think this is a great question.
Are you all desperately looking for new things
to watch and read or love watching
and reading favourite old stuff?
- I am watching new stuff because I am watching Buffy,
and as Padilla is watching favourite old stuff
because she is watching Buffy.
(laughing)
And so that is how that's happening in my house.
Is Padilla is using this as an opportunity
to get me to watch lots of things?
But I think mostly, I hear for watch so little television
that everything is pretty much due to me,
so that's a hard question.
What about you two?
- I'm watching less television than usual
but that is because we are playing animal crossing
on the switch for almost every waking moment
because there are three of us,
and one of us is a, one of those three people
is an animal crossing completist
which is not a thing I ever realised could happen.
And the other two are animal crossing dilettantes
and keep going.
Could we just get on for 30 minutes in daytime
so we can catch the daytime fish, please?
- I think I'm doing a bit of both.
Like I'll read something new,
but I'm not reading anything, I guess super demanding.
I have gone back to some Terry Pratchett
because that's my comfort read.
- It's a good comfort read, very good.
- This is a statement, I think.
Next live podcast happens with everyone dancing.
(laughing)
- I mean, it won't happen with me dancing.
I'm happy for it to happen with everyone else dancing.
I will be the person not dancing in the middle.
Unless we record a podcast at the disco,
but that seems like it might be
too many podcasts in too short a tie.
Max has recommended Oculus Quest for getting Beat Saber
and Lillian asked,
"Will the pandemic rescue the VR industry
"or will no one ever want to do VR again?"
I don't have VR, so I am spectacularly badly placed
to answer that.
Do I though if you have a VR thing?
- I do not, but I understand that you can get
some sort of fancy set up for your conference room
or meeting room where you sort of get a VR
or some kind of fancy projection of the whole person.
And people were just starting to talk about this
sort of before we all went into
doing video conferences all the time
because I already did a lot of video conferences,
but now I do, only video conferences,
and I think that is gonna become a lot more popular.
I think people will realize that maybe you don't need
to do everything in person,
but maybe it'd be good if you could see
the actual kind of hologram of a person.
- I'm gonna have to find a link to this
weird hologram thing as well.
- I have only ever had the very cheap sorts of VR rigs,
which are the ones where you slot your phone
into a bunch of lenses.
What I do do is, stereo photography.
I have a phone just so that I can look at stereo photos
on it that is not made by Apple
because Apple's never putting a 3D screen on a phone.
And I have used a lot of VR headsets
in order to do 3D stuff.
You know, the stereo realist is 70 years old now, nearly,
and they're a medium format cameras
to look at stereo pictures that are just amazing.
Bridget asks, "Will everyone now want green screen
"color t-shirts with amusing hovering designs on?"
And the answer to that is no.
I also know why it's really difficult to make that happen.
But that's very boring,
and you need to ask me in a bar where,
you know, when there's not 15 people in the room,
just take me into a corner somewhere.
- So, like in the bar, we're about to have.
- Like in the bar we're about to have.
- Excellent.
- Somebody has said also Bridget,
"How can you feed your troubles
"if there's no quadraticale in the shop?"
- I wasn't gonna read that
'cause I can't pronounce that word.
- I can't pronounce that word.
I think that's funny.
- Quadraticale.
- Whoa!
- I can just super-impose that into Alison
and hope no one notices, it'll be fine.
- You can, that's right.
Quadraticale.
- In the shops.
- Yeah.
- And we have one final question, which is,
"Will this encourage us after this
"to travel less and save the planet?"
And that's from Lillian.
I don't know because the thing I'm really missing
is traveling and so I am a little bit
of the opinion that people might actually
decide to get out a bit more
after a few months of enforced isolation.
I could see her going that way.
But if the benefit to the environment is very, very clear,
as a result of the lack of travel,
it might mean that environmental lobbies
have an easier time influencing policymakers in the future.
I don't know.
I think that energy travel is gonna be very popular,
but I think some business travel,
people will start to go, you know what,
now that we've all got video conferencing set up
and we're used to it and we're all familiar with it,
we maybe didn't need to do quite so many trips in person.
I'd be up for a lot of travel rationally as well.
I'd be up for saying, no person is allowed to take
more than 10 journeys a year, sort of term.
You can buy your rationally.
- I mean, I do think like in terms of sort of conferences
and stuff, it's always struck me that a lot of the knowledge
could be acquired remotely without you to go.
The problem, I guess, is the networking
is much easier in person.
So I don't know how that's gonna go.
I don't know whether businesses will react
in one of those ways.
- My response to you, John, would be that
actually virtual conferences are a great leveler
for people who come from countries
where they can't afford to go to conferences regularly.
So they're actually good for that.
Yeah, I completely agree with that.
So that's the end of another thrilling episode of Octa Thought,
the podcast about science fiction and SF fandom.
So it's goodbye from me.
- And it's goodbye from me.
- The music used in this episode was fanfare for space
by Kevin Macloud at incompetech.com,
licensed under a Creative Commons BY 3.0 license.
(dramatic music)
- We should stop and then everyone can have a chat
and a drink.
- I've got a beer with my name on it,
waiting in the fridge.
- Like literally, did you write it on with a pen
and everything?
- No, I just decided I was going to drink it in my head.
- I'm gonna turn off my recording, though, John.
- What?
I'm gonna keep mine on in case I say anything
devilishly witty.
- That's a good plan.
- It seems unlikely.
- I'm gonna stop mine because I'm out of wit.