We have 20 minutes, shall we do some actual topics?
Yes, so...
[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome to the OctaThole podcast, a podcast for Science Fiction and Science Fiction
from Fandom. This episode is coming to you on the 27th of May 2021. I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott and I'm Liz Batty.
And we have some letters of comment for you all in this low energy podcast.
And why is this a low energy podcast, John?
Eurovision because two-thirds of this podcast stayed up to watch Eurovision.
And it turns out that when you watch Eurovision, even if you're not playing a Eurovision drinking
game, you drink.
You do drink.
And the other third of the podcast did not watch Eurovision or do any drinking,
but I did have to unexpectedly work on a Saturday. So I'm tired.
But many normal Eurovision things happened at Eurovision, including my favourite track, Not Winning,
and a lot of people wearing spangly things and...
There was an awful lot of spangle.
A lot of jokes and the British entry cut no points.
And it was compounded by the head of the British jurors saying,
"Oh, I've just said hello in German and Dutch, but I don't know which is which."
Which I think really sums up the UK attitude to Europe and why we got Europoints.
So it's quite interesting because obviously I did not watch Eurovision,
but when I wake up, my Twitch and Facebook feeds are full of Eurovision.
So now I want somebody who's not me, but might be listening to this podcast,
or write a science-fictional story about the intergalactic song contest,
where the broadcasting unions of various federation planets.
Oh, that was nominated for a Hugo two years ago.
It was written by Catherine M. Valente, and it was called Space Opera.
Damn.
Yes, and I read 30 pages of it.
I really enjoyed it, but it was divisive.
You need to read more science fiction on it.
I do. That sounds like the sort of thing I'd really like.
Did it have some aliens on a tricked-out tractor singing about spring?
Basically, yeah.
It was literally Eurovision in space.
If you were not a fan of that style of comedy, you did not get on with it.
I thought it was quite good.
So was it more or less science-fictional than
Fire Saga, the story of Eurovision or whatever it's called?
It's literally set in space.
Yeah, so then yes.
No, I think, because I know Liz said she didn't like it,
I think the thing is with comedy is that the reason comedies don't do well in awards
that do not explicitly recognize comedy is because comedy is far more divisive than non-comedy.
A sense of humor is way more personal than drama or anything else.
So it is, I enjoyed it, but if it doesn't align with your sense of humor,
like you will bounce off it hard.
So yeah, it's like one of those things.
Yeah, I think my issue is that I love how Catherine Blente has an extremely strong
style in all of her novels, and it can be quite different in all of her novels.
But for this one, I read 40 pages and went, "This is trying so hard to have that Douglas Addams
sense of humor that I feel embarrassed to be reading it."
Like it just hit that sort of like, "I cannot read it because it is trying so hard and failing
for me to be funny in this particular way that I just couldn't get further into it."
It was a really strong reaction, and I don't normally have a reaction
that's strong to books actually.
Like sometimes I will stop reading them because I'm a bit bored, but in this case,
I was not bored.
I was just, "Ooh, it triggered something and I could not read any more."
But I did really like Radiance, one of her previous books,
so you should just go and read that one instead.
Anyway, we have letters of comment.
Yeah.
So, and Rosin wrote in to say, "Four minutes into your last episode did Alan Partridge shout
aha in the distance, possibly down into the tunnel that Alison was broadcasting from."
And we did respond to tell her that we did eventually manage to coax Alison out with her tunnel.
But Alison was very happy and we felt a bit bad about it.
I did go back and someone does shout aha in the background at that moment.
So, well noticed, and...
Is that me?
I think it was you, because I didn't notice it while we were recording,
or while I was listening to the edited version for later release.
So, good ears and...
Yeah, that is the sort of thing that we're supposed to pick up whilst editing and say,
"Oi John, you've left us faint aha in."
No.
It's very quiet.
Why would we have done that?
We already got one fewer letter of comment.
Are you saying you left it in deliberately as a comment took?
We would never say things just to get letters of comment, would we?
No, we wouldn't.
We would...
No, obviously not, however, be terrible.
So, Pete Asullivan also tweeted us to say that his concern with a whole weekend of the
Wussfuss business meeting can basically be summarised as the devil makes work for idle hands to do.
And that is a cogent and succinct criticism of our last conversation.
Thank you very much, Peter.
You may have a point.
Yeah, he goes on to say that his directory is that a business meeting with more time
would start trying to micromanage the world calm itself.
And I can see that there's a possibility that would happen.
It just occurs to me that things like at the moment we have kind of the business meeting
will appoint a committee and in theory the committee goes away and deliberates for like a year
or two years and then comes back with a report.
And the question is whether we could take some of that extremely lengthy
deliberations that normally happen over a year or two and maybe fire some of them off
in a weekend in a more concise way, or at least rather than kind of saying a committee will go
and study that, have a meeting which then set up a committee with
you know more of a remit for what they're actually going to do which is doable in a year.
So I just feel some things have kind of gone off to committees and then something which
already takes several years to ratify then spend several years being discussed by committee
and it just gets kind of slower and slower to change anything.
Maybe I'm missing the point of the WISFUS business meeting there.
Well, hang on, I just want to say something in reaction to what Liz said.
Here, the one thing about that is obviously like some committees are going to take a year
because they need to like consult with the community and that's a thing you can't shorten.
But in general like if it's just doing research like I can definitely see that some of those things
could be shortened perhaps. You could definitely shorten consulting with the community if you do
it by saying we're going to have a meeting on the internet on this day and if you want to be
involved this is where you're going to be. But you can't do that with six hours notice, right?
You can't be like we're going to consult with the community and if the community in six hours
could be consulted with that would be great. That's not how community consultations work.
Yeah, so as Spani wrote with two further points on WISFUS, she said it might be worth clarifying
that member of WISFUS and member of WILCON are the same thing and that is quite right it might be.
And I think one of the things I specifically said last time is that I would like to see the
member of WISFUS expanded to be more than merely the member of the seated WILCON.
But that leads into a Spani's second point which is that while she agrees that making the business
meeting easier, better or less mind-numbing to attend is desirable, she is the very of the idea
to opening it up to anyone on the internet with $50 and a grudge. Not a bad point, a fair point.
There are a lot of those people. The fact that it's structured at the moment in a way that means
you have to have a certain level of kind of wealth privilege to make it worth your while attending
does mean that there is a kind of a gatekeeping aspect by saying it is worth pointing out that
that does cut both ways. It may mean that the people who attend are more invested in the good
of the world con than otherwise and that might actually be a good side effect and you would have
to think quite carefully about how to replicate that if you did try and open it up.
So that is I think a very good point. Spani's first point brought to you by a conversation
where she was like sometimes you guys use words and like not everyone will know what the words
mean and I was like that is a good point. I'm wondering whether we should do some sort of
fanist dictionary episode at some point where newer listeners can get up to date on all of our
jargon but if you do ever listen to a say something and you're like oh they're using a word and I
don't really know what it means please do write in because we're not doing it on purpose and we
would very much like to be told when we are being more obtuse than usual. Yes you can also instead
of writing to us you could write to Mr. Google who will probably tell you what the word means
and you might want to include contexts like fanak or science fiction fandom with your word
otherwise you will discover weird things on urban dictionary. Fanak is one of the words that you
might use. Fanak is a portmanteau meaning fan activity the more you know.
But it's then often defined as anything that fans do like watching Eurovision.
I like Spanish letter. I think an episode purely about jargon would be very tedious
but maybe we can have jargon corner. Please write to us listeners and tell us what should be
in jargon corner. We may have too many corners by now but we're virtual we can have as many corners
as we like. We're a dodecahedron of love Liz. Okay so let's be clear here. The dodecahedrons
don't really have corners. You meant dodeca gone. I did mean dodeca gone. A dodecahedron
has vertices. It does. Well this is good and for those who don't know a dodecahedron is a both-sided
solid shape. No it bloody isn't. No it isn't. It doesn't have sides it has faces. What we're hearing
here is a mathematician and a physicist in conversation. All so we have many corners
as we are a mathematical object of indeterminate size. No we've just discussed we don't have any
corners we have vertices. So actually we have dictionary vertex and jargon vertex and poetry
vertex and I will go back and edit all of those in the previous episodes. Octa thought poetry vortex
yes let's have some vertices instead. I think that's the way forward.
Vortices. Maybe this conversation can go down a vortex.
C. Dave wrote in. He's not yet admitted to himself that he's never going to get around to
casting something in resin. You could Dave just to do it. Yeah I believe in you. And also he says
he's never going to ascend a was for business meeting and is unlikely to ever get deep enough
into the weeds to understand all the discussion if he did go but he enjoys listening to the discussion
because his wholebie isn't SFF or fandom it's fandom fandom so yes fandom is a way of life etc.
I would say I am glad that someone is enjoying the wistful spaces being segments because I suspect
many of our audience have reached the end of the we've had a number of letters to that effect.
And so maybe maybe next time will be a wistful free podcast. I also would say that I did go to
a suspicious business meeting and that someone gave me a popcorn smoth ribbon which I treasure
for a person who is a fan of business fandom. That is a very good ribbon. I like that. Popcorn
smoth. Popcorn smoth as in I'm at the business meeting for the popcorn. Oh because they gave
you popcorn or because you were eating popcorn whilst watching wisps. No like in the sense that
when you see drama on the discord or a slack sometimes you just comment with a popcorn emoji
instead of actually arguing. You say I'll get the popcorn. Yeah I don't think it is that I think
it's that they give out popcorn at the wisps business meeting. No no one gave me any popcorn.
Yeah no I mean if they gave out popcorn at the wisps business meeting we would go to the wisps
business meeting. This should be a constitutional amendment. There should always be popcorn at.
I'm pretty sure I've been to a wisps business meeting that had muffins or something. I think in
the US there was coffee and muffins. Yeah yeah yeah there is often snacks, snackage in the European
ones. No snacks. No boo. Buck your ideas up Europe. Yes. So Spike wrote to us to tell us two exciting
things about Winnipeg. Yes. One of which is it's only about a ten-hour drive from Nebraska.
And the second is backman turn overdrive and and you need to know that neither of these quite
hit my excitability threshold Spike. I think I think because because when you say oh such a
such a place as always because it's only ten-hour drive from such such another place that's not
damning with faint praise in the UK that is just a straight-out insult. So it doesn't read to us as
a compliment or as a like double-edged sword just reads as if this place is awful. Because to me
like an hour away is too long. Ten hours is like Scotland. She sends a link to a song by backman
turn overdrive and there and we will put the link to the show notes and she would like us to know
that lead singer is not Chris Garcia because the band would have to have been called Garcia turn
overdrive. I would also like to say that Spike sends me hand instructions for how to find Nebraska
on the map which turns out to be find Winnipeg and then go south. And when she's there with the
instructions I did look at it on a map and I did discover that I have in fact been to Nebraska
despite saying I had never been to Nebraska but I went through it on a train and the train
deliberately I think goes to Nebraska at night because there's nothing very interesting to look
at. Whereas you know it's it spends its days going through Colorado and the Sierra Nevada's which
are much more fun to look at I think than Nebraska. So sorry Nebraska I have been there but I have
absolutely no recollection of it. That is that is fair. I have been looking on a map while we
have been talking and if I drove for 10 hours I could get to the Scottish Highlands. I started
by looking at Aberdeen but Aberdeen is too close and that is a sentence no one has ever said about
Aberdeen before. Is it always there lurking in the back of your mind the threat of Aberdeen?
And for people who don't know the details domestic arrangements of octa thought John lives almost
as fast as it's possible to live and not fall off the bottom of England so it's true.
Right so we we end our letters of comment today with Chris Garcia who says that Winnipeg is pretty
cool actually he likes the conventions and there's a lot of good food around and yeah he
generally seems quite positive. Farah Mendelson wrote to us to tell us that the solution to the
best cat award is the Village Faked Pet Show Award also also used for Children's Baskerades
where you give every cat an award for being best cat at something so Badger is the best
will-con bid-chair cat and Farah's own major Tom who has a Hugo rocket on his nose is quite
obviously best science fiction cat face which gets through to illustrate a cat with a Hugo on his nose.
I like this because then Quentin Alice can clearly be best octa thought podcast cats.
It's true. Yeah but in fact um masquerades and and children's pet displays at Village Fets have
things like the snuggliest cat and the furiest cat and the outchiest cat if one of them has
bitten the judges. Alice is the softest cat but I think Quinn is the fufiest cat.
There we go. Regularists should note that I've met John's cats and I cannot tell them apart
it's all in the ears Liz it's all in the ears. They are both equally soft and fluffy anyway.
It's Banya bought a new phone and as a result of which I can now detect John's cats in photographs
because prior to that I just believe they were kind of black cat-shaped holes in the middle of
zoom meetings and pictures and things but but the new cameras adequate identify it as a cat.
Yes. I assume that's machine learning. Probably probably um and then finally we have Chris Garcia.
Now last episode we said that we did not always go to World Conspiratorism but Chris points out a
very key point which I had not thought of which is that he is a food world conveyor and he votes on
his stomach and actually that is a 10 out of 10 way to vote because um my my my parents get
annoyed with me when we go all holiday because the thing I like best about travel is eating
and they'll be like do you remember this thing that was really good that was something to do with
architectural culture or something. I'll be like no and then they'll be like oh and I'll be like I
do remember that restaurant and they'll be like but but what uh by I bloody love food. Anyone who
has met me will regard my shape and maybe notice that that is not a surprise but yes um and he
talks about some of the good food that he had in Dublin. Yeah what I remember from Dublin is
the donuts. Oh the donuts. The donuts and the pizza at 2am although to be fair the pizza at 2am was the
other side of Dublin were not the other side of Dublin but it was a long way from the convention
center but it was near our Airbnb so we did a lot of pizza or put an image in the chapter art
but it was good and the donuts are applying for a fellowship in Dublin and I would be lying if I
didn't say the donuts had played a role. Alison is honourable. I'm going to be one of the guests of
honour at the Joint Science Fiction Foundation and British Science Fiction Association AGM which is
happening online on the 26th of June. I'm giving a talk um tentatively entitled My Year in Virtual
fandom but I haven't written it yet so if you want to know my writing plan it's that I will not think
about it until about 8am on the 26th of June and then I will cry for three hours.
That is having having worked with Alison on projects that seems reasonable.
It's called Conspire which is a good name, very good name. I think the Science Fiction Foundation
and the British Science Fiction Association are sort of organisations for critical analysis of SF
in the UK would you say? No I don't think so. The Science Fiction Foundation is a charity
which uh basically promotes science fiction and related topics. I should actually find out
what the Science Fiction Foundation's um actual like charitable goal is which I should know because
I have been on the committee of both the Science Fiction Foundation and I mean I don't mean to
I don't mean to contradict you but it's to provide research facilities to investigate
promote usefulness of SF to disseminate information and to preserve for a discriminating
understanding of the nature of so I think it's to be organized for critique like it seems from the
forums I've got on the website it seems very much geared towards academic analysis to me.
I think it's much closer to say academic analysis than criticism. What's the difference between
academic analysis and criticism? That could we could have an entire episode just on that
popcorn? Because I was fascinated by the Hugo finalist who describes themselves as a professional
enthusiast which I think means an uncritical critic. The Science Fiction Foundation also
notably organised the George A. Lecture at EasterCon to promote a science topic an interesting talk
by a scientist to people at the uh EasterCon and I think that's also kind of a key part is kind to
kind of rather than stay in an academic bubble but then try and you know bring this out to the wider
SF fandom. The Science Fiction Foundation definitely has an outreach role and the British Science
Fiction Association no matter how hard it is to tell sometimes is a member association it's a club
and it is a club for science fiction fans but it has the kind of same issues around that as as
you get with other hobbies that that sort of central club never quite accurately reflects the set of
people who are who might be in the club. And spare. It's not all British Science Fiction fans are in
the BSFA by um by a long shot um and I left at the point where I discovered that they were sending
me a lot of paper every month that I didn't want to read. I think they probably stopped sending
people large bunches of paper but I might be wrong about that. No you are I wrote to the
membership secretary to be like how do I get the uh paperless option and now I was met with no
one's ever asked that before as the response which I find incredibly difficult to believe.
That is a lie no one's ever asked the current secretary um paperless option. Yes.
But I think I think when I say they're both um critical organizations I think I think going
on the website that is unfair but I will say that um both of them send paper to do with criticism
to you if you join them. So it it may well be that uh if you're my primary experience with the BSFA
has been receiving their publications and their publications are focused around criticism academic
analysis and reviewing um but going on the website they have also got writing groups and
of participation fund and things like that. So yes I remember at the BSFA very newly um and
and yeah it's been good so far I enjoy vector even though most of it I don't really understand.
I think it's also case that uh so there used to be more than one magazine I think they don't have
matrix anymore it kind of was a sort of news, zine um I had some reviews into lots of media SF
um I think it was kind of going to go online but then never really took off and at this point I'm
not sure what status is. I think kind of vectors academicness sort of varies depending on who is
editing it um and what they're focusing on at the time. I feel it may be more of an academic phase
but I do think some of their recent issues look very interesting. I am not a member but at this
point I would also need very much a paperless option um and like you said I'm not sure that
is currently available. Yeah and and of course they run the BSFA awards they have a
long-standing not quite link with Eastercon um because for a while they ran the Eastercon but
that was a very very long time ago. They do go through more and less critical phases and I think
the BSFA is in a more critical phase at the moment. They used to have a magazine called Focus for
Aspiring Writers. I believe Focus is still going yes. They actually do have in in in times when we
can have actual clubhouse meetings. They do have London meetings at least um where they where
they get an author to do a little talk and then they drink. Yes I did go to number of London
meetings when I was listening to do that and they were good fun. Back in the before times they
they worked out that the way that they could make their AGM Quarat was to combine with the
Science Fiction Foundation and have a un-rata one-day convention into which they included both the
AGMs and some other stuff and that is the that is the thing that is now conspire online. So I
assume that both organizations didn't have their AGM last year but concluded that they needed to
have one this year but I don't know. Traditionally I think they would have one AGM just before
lunch and one AGM just after lunch so that anyone who was not interested in the AGMs could have an
extra long lunch. This is a good plan. Students union at West University used to provide us to
attend the AGM by threatening our society funding if we didn't go.
Okay so fanzines before we wrap up today we're going to have a chat about the humble fanzine
and also in modern times the not so humble fanzine that that was a joke for basically for
Claire and maybe for Alison. So Alison wants to talk about fanzines and I'm going to let her
and then I'm going to interject with thoughts when she has things that I have thoughts about
and Liz is going to also have thoughts but perhaps fewer thoughts because Liz doesn't care as much
about fanzines as we do. Basically correct. I now look like a rabbit caught in headlights and the
reason why is that I had a whole plan for our fanzine episode in which I was going to read
quite a bit of all of the Hugo finalist fanzines and I was also going to read or reread quite a bit
of the sorts of fanzines that I like and think ought to be Hugo finalists and I did neither of these
things. So I am therefore left arguing from a position of almost complete ignorance.
Well maybe this can be like the fanzine fanzine five minutes and we can do a full episode at some
point when you've done it. So I think what I want to do is actually kick off. I think quite a lot
of people who are listening to Octa Thorpe do like the sort of fanzines I like which where and here's
the tiny little rant. What you're actually doing is writing about things in order to set up a dialogue
and discussion with the other people who are reading your fanzine as part of a community
to therefore build interesting thoughts and you have therefore an active letter column and
you you you listen to what your readers have to say and I was very struck yesterday when reading the
um 1700 issues of philosophical transactions which is the Journal of the Royal Society
um which are now all online and clearly people wrote longer letters then but the fact is that
what that was reads much more like a fanzine than than a lot of the Hugo finalist fanzines where I
am not seeing the interplay of of different community views in the way that I would expect
and I know that that interplay does happen it just doesn't I think happen in the pages of fanzines
anymore um or not the pages of fanzines that get regularly nominated for Hugo's. I would like to see
more of the sort of thing I like getting onto the Hugo shortlist and I want to think about how we
can make that happen does that sound like a kickoff rant for a discussion of fanzines?
Yes I have thoughts. Good. So oh sorry press a company except it obviously
except not because yes no I mean so Journey Planet the um fanzine which I um edit as part of a
enormous sort of amorphous blob with many heads and tentacles snap out that was a
a tentacle snapping out listeners tentacle snap out and snare interviews with people and
and things like that but we don't really have a letter column so in that sense um we are not a
fanzine that fulfills Allison's exhortation to uh community dialogue I will say two things here
which I think will probably cause letters the first one is I think and this is an argument
that I've had with people before the traditional fanzine fandom never really developed beyond
PDFs being shared on a website uh with lots of PDFs on it and that is as and and and I don't have a
problem with that being a form of fanzine that people enjoy and want to engage with
but there was I think a very hard kind of edge to the traditional kind of fanzine community who
who progressed and moved with the times and like they went from mimeo to word processors and they
went from kind of printed fanzines to PDFs and then they kind of stopped at PDFs and there is this
disconnect between the community of people who make PDFs and the community of people who are doing
fan writing in more accessible media and I don't have a problem with people preferring PDFs and
wanting to play in that space and then that's brilliant and if that's your bag great but I do
think it is a shame that there is this this real step between the community of people who are doing
that and like the community of people who are doing fan writing everywhere else on the internet
and I think that is something that is not wholly the fault of either camp I am frustrated with both
groups that there is not a gradient in between those I think it's just the way it ended up being
but like it is a shame I think that there are not more people from the fanzine community that I
grew up in making fanzines that are not just PDFs being shared on the internet some notable
exceptions to this include the excellent banana wings which is also available in e-pub formats now
which I think is great I was doing e-pubs before I wrapped up procrastinations and I always thought
they were a very good vehicle for that more kind of traditional fanzine but most fanzines are still
PDFs which are very difficult to read for example on a phone which is where I do most of my reading
of things that are not novels or comics and so banana wings I think does a really good job and
is one of the more innovative players in this space the other one is Alison did a letter fanzine
through email which I think she did two issues of a few years ago I'm definitely doing another one
of those as soon as I finish this you go vote packet and punctuation and get eastbound 2023 sorted
yeah so 2024 look out for issue three and lolzine was inspired by Alison's
zine in that regard but these are zines that come out over email and have more of a traditional
fanzine sensibility in the like lolzine and Alison's zine both had letters of comment
and had that kind of letter column experience but were not doing it in a kind of printed
fanzine way but kind of playing with with with more up-to-date media Chuck Conner did a CD
ROM fanzine which was about 10 or 12 years ago now but it was basically he was sending you a CD
ROM and it had a website on it and you browse the website and I thought that was fantastic and that
was kind of before WordPress and stuff like that got popular and I was like this is really great
and I can see how this is going to be really cool in the future and then no one's really
played with that and lolzine did start trying to do a kind of website based experience but it's
quite hard and maintaining websites is tedious so I do understand why more people do not do that
because it requires an awful lot more consistent effort than making a pdf that you then upload
somewhere does on the other side of the coin I think the people making more modern fanzines are
ignoring that letter column thing but I think part of the reason for that is that there are so
many more places you can have those conversations now than there were when the traditional fanzines
were kind of coming out so in the old days in like the 50s if you wanted to have a conversation
with people you did it in the letter column because you couldn't just tweet at them or text them
but now like I think in a way Twitter is kind of like a worldwide letter column and so I think
part of the reason we're seeing much less engagement in zines themselves is because a lot of that
engagement has been shunted to other platforms and I see why that's happening but I do think it's a
shame because I think there is merit to having a consistent group of commentators and building
that conversation that is more coherent and I think that's something that OctaThork does in that we
have the letter column which we have kind of poached from old style fanzines but is also
something you see in a lot of the tech podcasts that me and Alison kind of formed our opinions on
how podcasts should work by listening to and where you do have this sense of community and
this sense of comment and this building up of relationships with the commentators and the audience
and so I think we're trying to build that kind of coherent conversation in OctaThork but doing it
in a way that isn't a PDF on our website and so sometimes I refer to Lulzine as an episode and
sometimes I refer to OctaThork as an issue and that's because in my head they're both very much
attempts to do the same sort of thing which is to lever more modern styles of communication
but to try and capture that sense of community that the fanzines I read when I was younger kind of
addressed and also if anyone knows Jim DeLiscard, get him to publish another bloody Gerald will you
because that's the third thing that's wrong with fanzines today there's not enough Gerald.
I now of course have many many things to say but that's all we've got time for this week on
OctaThork so it's good oh no we can't you John has to do that bit.
Am I am I not allowed like you know a 30 second rebuttal? I believe you're allowed 90 seconds
which is fine I can do it in 90 seconds I have two responses mostly to John one is that I
hadn't realized that what you were doing when you persuaded us to set up OctaThork was stealthily
reinvigorating your fanzine tradition but well done I do like the regular commenter
commenters who write to us very often thank you very much and if anyone hasn't written
as a letter for a while please write in and tell us how you're doing I'd like to hear from you
and second I think that in a way what is happening in the wider world is maybe something
that fanzines can learn from which is I think people are leaving Twitter a little bit and maybe
moving to platforms like sub stack or other kind of sub stack clones where you can have
something which is a letter which gets emailed to people but you can also have a thriving
comment section under them now I know a lot of sub stack seem to set that up by essentially
having paid subscriptions and then you have special threads for your paid subscribers and
that's maybe not a model to move to but that is it kind of feels like a blog that you email to
people but it does seem to be working in a lot of fields to get people really engaged and
discussing with each other I just want to say I didn't deliberately start OctaThork to try
and reinvigorate my fanzine sensibilities it just sort of accidentally happened when we started
getting layers of comment so it wasn't as insidious as it sounds when you put it like that I didn't
mean to hoodwink anyone but yes yeah yeah I think those are good points and I should also
note file 770 does have a thriving comment section underneath each post and I should
I should not have left file 770 out because I think past 770 is actually the one great the other
great example of a traditional fanzine that did really successfully bridge that cap and Mike
Glyer won several hugos I think in recent years in part because he had successfully managed to do
that please write in tell us if we're wrong please also write in if you haven't written in for a while
we miss you I was going through the old letters of comment of a day and Karen Schafer was messaging
us about her jigsaw's how are your jigsaws Karen we liked hearing about boats so yes we really
do have to wrap up Alison doesn't want to wrap up she is simmering with things she wishes to say
but that is good because it means that when letters of comment come in saying them we will be able to
segue seamlessly into fans these next episode listeners I have gone from comatose to to simmering
in one hour all all that has to happen is that I say wrong things about fandom and they are
some wakes up great quick and on that bombshell it's goodbye from me it's goodbye from me and it's
goodbye from me
gossier turn the turn it over dr-
octa-thorpe beatboxing vertex the theme music for this episode was fanfare for space by kevin
mclowd at incompatec.com used under a creative commons attribution 3.0 license this podcast will
end at the beat beep