There's a joke in here somewhere, but will it be mean?
Make the joke and then we can workshop it to make it funny. That always works.
No, I'm not sure we can, that's the problem. I'm cutting my losses.
No, we don't... we've got a mean joke quota probably and we're going to talk about Locus later, so John's got to be prepared.
[Music]
Hello everyone and welcome to the very 72nd episode of Octothorpe, a podcast for science fiction and science fiction fandom
which is coming to you on the 8th of December 2022. I'm John Coxon.
I'm Alison Scott. And I'm Liz Batty. Alison is cracking up already. We haven't even started.
So we have some letters of comment. Yeah, we got some, we got letters of comment.
We have lots of letters of comment because lots of people gave us suggestions for the Octothorpies.
Yes, yes they did. So we heard from Duncan MacGregor who knows on which side his
bread is buttered because he suggested categories for Best Alison, Best John and Best Liz.
And that would be very flattering obviously but we wouldn't be able to on any account
award them to ourselves and so that would be an incredibly meta category that would lead to a
lot of interesting wrangling. I am immediately recusing myself from the Best Alison category.
Ali Baker, Alison Abramovitz. I suppose there is a risk that like...
There's a risk that I don't win, yes. That would be the great risk but...
Well but there's also a risk that I nominate Alison for Best Liz and vice versa.
In what way am I... In what way am I the Best Alison?
In what way aren't you?
Hmm. I don't know, I feel I want to win Best Liz once and then recuse myself forever.
That does seem reasonable. I don't know if I want to win Best John. There are a number of options
for Best John. Do Jonathans count? We would have to have a serious discussion about eligibility.
No they definitely don't.
Okay and do Alison's spelt with a Y count?
Maybe or Alison's with two L's?
Ali Baker... In a late LoC Ali Baker has just noticed that the FA Cup contains a
women's team called Hashtag United.
And maybe they should be our... and suggests they should be our official sportsball team.
Another suggestion for a Octothorpies category is from Hugo, Girl! which is "Proposal: Best Transatlantic
Podcast Besties (No Reason)" which is thoroughly great.
Awww. Yes. We'll vote for you if you vote for us!
Yeah. Ang emailed us and said "Morning team! I nominate my cats for Best Cats That Are Not Badger."
Which yeah leaves the obvious obvious second category of Best Cats That Are Badger
which much like the Alison, John and Liz categories is going to be an interesting set of nominees.
Yup. I suspect what we will see is Badger will be nominated and then a variety of cats in Badger
cosplays. I mean... Badger is known for being a very large black cat so really anyone who has a
large black cat could nominate it as Best Badger. Or I could buy my cats cat fat suits and put them
in cat fat suits. Yeah your cats are a bit small to be Best Badgers.
John are you cat fat shaming? Not shaming. All cats are very valid in their various sizes but I'm
worried that it would be too obvious that my cats are not Badger to win the award.
I'm kind of going the existence of fat suits is a kind of inherently fat shaming thing
because fat suits only exist because people want to have characters of size being played by
thin actors which is a kind of size-phobic thing to be doing. Sorry I'm sorry for being very very
humourless about this. Agreed in humans but what would you call the cat costume that you could put
a small cat in to make it larger, Alison? What noun is that that every one of our listeners will
understand what I'm getting at? Well probably not a cat suit, yeah? It's pretty much the same as
if we wanted to disguise Alison as me. We wouldn't put her in a fat suit you'd have to be...
Stilts? I'm going in an even worse direction aren't I? Let's give up on this train of thought entirely.
So now I need apparently I need to lose weight and get stilts. I think you can
you can be whatever weight you like to impersonate me but I do think you're a little bit shorter.
I am quite a lot shorter than you, I believe. Digging a lot of holes here aren't I? Anyway,
I think we may have strayed from our topic of cats. Ang says, "Are you going to have the
Octothorpe's Octoversary on the 80th episode or the 88th episode? What better time to
hand out your awards?" and the answer is that we had it on the 64th episode but nobody noticed.
I think it's got to be I think 88 makes more sense to 64 on account of how we're a base 10 culture.
Then why does 88 make sense? Surely 80 would make sense. I'm up for 80. Yeah maybe so maybe 80 should
be our Octoversary. It's complicated isn't it? I mean let's face it it's probably going to be the one
which corresponds with some kind of major event and I think if we calculate it we can probably wiggle
one. You can probably wiggle either 80 or 88 to be at Eastercon right? Uh... pass. I'll do that maths
at some point I promise. I will say that Shut Up and Sit Down have a novel approach to this
where they just put increasingly large decimal points after their episode 99 and 199 so they can
make the round number be a special event. That's why I just listened to podcast episode 199.75.
I'm not sure if that's better. It's an approach. Plokta had an episode 33 and a third rather
33 because it was our long-playing episode and it sounds like our Octoversary episode
should be 88.88 recurring. Ang also notes that she cooked a salmon in a dishwasher at the Novacon
steam room. I'm pretty sure I've read that right. Where did you get the dishwasher from, Ang?
Write in. Curt Phillips wrote us a long letter which he then sent us an email to say he hadn't
worked out how to send us it ino email so he was putting it on the Facebook page. So it's on the
Facebook page. When he says he sent... when he said he sent us an email did he send us an email or
did he sent you an email? Yeah. They may have just have sent me an email. He says, "John talks improbably
fast but with perfect clarity." Curt does say that he didn't miss a single word, he just listened faster.
The great thing about listening to podcast though is that you can listen to them at whatever speed
you like so that if people talk too fast you can slow the podcast down to hear every word [such as 0.8x for editing this transcript — transcript Ed.] and if
people talk too slowly you could speed this podcast up. Only works if we all talk at the same pace as
John though and and then he had a good old whine about the Hugos which you can read on our
Facebook page. And he said, "Your Novacon report was very enjoyable, but I didn't hear mention of a dealers'
room or an art show" and I'm pretty sure I said I spent the whole weekend in the dealers' room when
I wasn't in the bar, because I was trading. Yes. We didn't focus on it – I think you mentioned it in
passing. I hope I didn't cut it out. And there is always an art show at Novacon which is usually
very good. There was an art show which was very nice and he also says "or did you three simply not
peek into them?" and John and Liz didn't peek into those rooms because John and Liz were not at Novacon
I was the only person at Novacon. Mark says "They say science fiction isn't very good at predicting
the future and seemingly neither are science fiction fans. At least so I concluded on listening to
Octothorpe 70 yesterday with its confident assertion that Claire and I were in
Buxton last Thursday." And yes: Claire and Mark never made it to Buxton. Sorry Claire and Mark. So we
lied, listeners. We lied. But we didn't know we were lying, so that makes it better? We lied the episode
before last because by the last episode we knew that they weren't in Buxton but I don't think we
mentioned it so there we go. So this is a LoC on issue 70. I mean to be fair if we did a list of
everyone who wasn't at Novacon that would be the running time of the episode so it is understandable
we didn't but equally... yes. It's a good LoC. I mean, if we did a list of all the times that we are wrong
about something that would probably also make quite a sizable episode by itself. Zing! Liz, do you
want to read the last part of Mark's letter because it deals with your pick? It does, yes, because my
pick of Earthsea inspired Mark to take down a copy from his bookshelf of the Earthsea trilogy which was
at that point the Earthsea trilogy and it seems that he managed to get halfway through chapter seven
of book three and then stop and he might start again. But actually he'll probably wait until it's 40 years
since he stopped and will make a note to write back to Octothorpe at that time which we think
will be episode of Octothorpe 174. So basically, if we're still going Mark will write to us in episode
174 and say he's read Earthsea. Or not. So keep your eyes peeled for that and if you're... I mean I'm
not going to remember that by episode 174 so Mark I hope you will. If you are listening to this
back episode at the point where we have released Octothorpe 174 please pause it here go and listen to
174 and then tell us off if we didn't do it. I wanted to move back to the discussion of using
old receipts as bookmarks and one of the advantages of physical books. I've been thinking... I'm getting
rid of all of my books I don't think this is quite a pick but but I'm getting rid of an awful
lot of books at the moment and one of the things about physical books as opposed to electronic books is
that if you do keep your physical books and you use old tatty bits of paper as bookmarks then you
do have permanent records, as Mark did, of where you gave up on a particular book because your receipts
are still there 40 years later. We've certainly... some of the books that we've taken
down from the shelves have bits of paper in at the point where one or other of us gave up on them.
I'm pretty sure my Kindle also remembers where I was up to and when I last read it. I'm not sure
how you get that information out but I think it does. Another plus point for ebooks.
Listeners please write in with your Python packages that can go through a Kindle library and
work out when you gave up on each book. Thank you very much for writing in Mark. We also heard from
Christopher J. Garcia who says indeed it is gigabytes. In fact it's now closer to 40 gigabytes because
he's found another old thumb drive with copies of Claims Department he'd forgotten about. So you
know noted archivist and curator Christopher J. Garcia showing off his curation and archiving
methods there which is old thumb drives so that's good. Hurrah! I'm not much better, to be fair.
He does also say that I am a bad person for enjoying Voyager. He also says that your
off the cuff method for voting for things is in fact the way that they do draft picks in the
National Basketball Association so I thought that was quite interesting. Yes. Yeah I mean it
seems still seems like a terrible way of picking, say, politicians but I guess if you have like
many many draft picks and you just want to allocate them in some way that is semi-fair that's not a
bad way of doing it. Indeed. Oh and he says he wishes he could go to Novacon one day although as a
guy who knows an incredibly limited amount of Spanish Novacon is a con that shouldn't move.
Yeah they've been making that joke for about 49 years so, you know. I've never heard it. Okay.
It's a generational thing. It's almost like people who are the older members of the community
shouldn't just be like "oh yes, we did that" and they never say it ever again. DC says in regards to
Raj's lock that Raj probably doesn't have to pay more to get a full membership in Glasgow
because they're offering discounted memberships to anyone resident in Scotland. This is not it.
So... and I regret... I regret making this comment on the podcast because a lot of people have written
in to try and guess what I meant. So I was drunk in a Glasgow in 2024 party at Chicon 8 and the
lovely Meg MacDonald collard me and said do you want to pay us £100 to upgrade your Supporting
membership to a Friend membership before the bid session so that when the bid session happens you
will be automatically upgraded to an Attending member and I said "I haven't bought a Supporting
membership yet so I can't upgrade" and Meg very wisely saw that it was better to get 100 quid
out of me then than it was to not do that and just pushed me at the laptop anyway and I filled it in
like a good little drunk boy. So the reason I owe 20 quid to Glasgow is because I didn't have a
Supporting membership before I upgraded that Supporting membership to a Friend membership.
I suspect I am the only person to whom this situation applies so I do apologize for bringing
it up because I think it's caused some confusion! But yes, it is because I was drunk, and it has nothing
to do with whether or not I am in Scotland. To the best of my knowledge. You know how they have like
you know a WSFS membership and then an Attending supplement? Can John have a special Drunken Fuckwit
supplement which is the extra 20 quid you have to pay them now. Can I make Drunken Fuckwit
Supplement the episode title? Because I know I can't but that would be very good. I'm
slightly confused by this because they sold Friend memberships all along to people who didn't
have Pre-Support. Nope they didn't, they stopped in about mid-July. But if you had a Pre-Support
you could still upgrade to a Friend but they let you have the Friend membership
anyway due to some form of wanting £100. I think it's a monetary system known as capitalism.
No some sort of special exception for mates it sounds like because if they wanted £100
they could have done that for everyone. They also could have just waited on...
No I think they wanted to make sure they didn't have a huge influx at the end but I suspect
people in that room in the parties at Chicon was a small enough group that it didn't cause much
extra work. Oh no, that makes perfect sense. Okay, so, if there's a Drunken
Fuckwit supplement that feels like if they have a special Drunken Fuckwit membership then I
can have that for Pemmi-Con can't I?
Beneath Ceaseless Skies has recused from the Hugo Award for Best Semiprozine.
It has won the World Fantasy and British Fantasy Awards and it has been... it has been a finalist for Best Semiprozine
ten times and they have recused themselves from the category. They want to support other indie
zines run by dedicated staff and publishing great and important stories whose work deserves
a Best Semiprozine finalist spot and the corresponding boost in reach and support.
This is great. I think I'm on the record as saying that once you've won in a category more than a
handful of times you need to recuse and let the rest of the genre have its time in the sun – and I'm
looking at you, Uncanny Magazine, when I say that – but I think it had never really occurred to me that
long-time finalists might want to do the same thing and this seems like a really positive move.
Especially long-time finalists in the Best Semiprozine category which seems to be quite static.
It doesn't... it's not a very vibrant category. It doesn't showcase the best work in the field so much as it just
repeatedly rewards the usual suspects and so I guess in categories that are in that bucket
recusing yourself from a finalist state even when you haven't won it is as good as you can do to
sort of try and make that category a bit more vibrant. So yeah, this seems really good. Well
done to Beneath Ceaseless Skies. Do either of you have a hot take on this? I do have a hot take but it's
mean and we've said we're not allowed any mean jokes, so... Why don't you go for it and then John can
cut it out if it is too mean? So my hot take is "Oh, I'm recusing myself from the Best Semiprozine
category where I might have to stand up on stage with 43 people, but please all vote for me
in Best Editor: Short Form" is the actual form of the statement. Beneath Ceaseless Skies have only ever,
I think, nominated themselves with one editor listed in the category so Beneath Ceaseless Skies is
the one where they always do just list Scott Andrews and, you know, not the entire list of
staff. I mean, yeah, there is something in that which is I think it must be really hard to recuse
yourself from something after being nominated so many times and not winning. It must be hard to
say "Actually, it's time to recuse myself anyway" and kind of... you know, you never got to do that bit of
like standing on the stage and getting your spotlight. But they do point out that you can still nominate
Scott Andrews as best editor and you can still nominate kind of all the individual stories in
the magazine in the individual categories so while you're taking the magazine out you can still
nominate its contents and its editor in other categories. So, there is still a chance
that many people associated with the magazine will get kind of a moment of glory in a way
that you probably don't if you recuse yourself from, say, Best Fan Writer then you're
recused from Best Fan Writer – that's it. If Beneath Ceaseless Skies changed editor-in-chief I would not
think it was hypocritical of them to unrecuse themselves as well because I do think that would
be reasonable. Yeah, Liz is right it is just Scott Andrews who is listed under their thing.
The only one in that category! So maybe the actual thought process is "well, clearly everyone else
is a giant hivemind collective and I am just a man so I can be safely nominated in one of the
categories that is just for people and let other hivemind collectives come up in this category".
That is a much more charitable way of looking at it than mine which probably was
going "What is going on here, is there some ego sense?" I don't think I'm that cynical but I
kind of looked this is it is it could this have been a cynical go of what is my best scope of
getting a Hugo clearly this category is not it despite us being very regularly nominated.
Alison, if you've just read the thing on File 770 then I think it is worth you clicking through
and reading the whole statement. Yeah, it's quite a short statement isn't it? Yeah, but it basically
says they've already seen while they've been a finalist their readership has doubled
and they think they've basically got a lot of value out of it. And then, at the end, list a bunch of other
magazines on the 2020 longlist they think deserve a place on the ballot. So, it
really does feel like saying we've had a great success from this here are some other
magazines we think could take our place and enjoy the boosted readership. Oh no, you're
right: I hadn't clicked through, I'm a moron. I had clicked through once but I hadn't clicked through
sufficiently to get to the actual statement. Right, I see, yes. So I think it's very
nice, really. And I think I would find it hard to do myself if I was nominated a lot and I
never quite made it to winning. I think it would be hard to say "actually, don't nominate me
again". So I think I'm going to quickly list... so the ones that he recommends in his statement are
Mermaids Monthly, khōréō (sorry if I've pronounced that wrong), Fireside, Diabolical Plots, The Deadlands
and Giganotasaurus. Fireside's an interesting one because that is not an uncontroversial
recommendation, lately. He's not completely recusing himself from the possibility of winning a Hugo
Award because he's still eligible in another category whereas obviously if we recuse ourselves
for Octothorpe we would not be eligible in any other categories so we would be permanently...
Speak for yourself, sunshine. I mean I would like to say that I did go and look it up because I think
Mermaids Monthly has not published anything since 2021 so I think they're actually not eligible this
year. They basically did 12 issues, and then I'm not sure if a second set of 12 issues has come
out, or if that might happen in 2023, or if it has folded but I do not believe they're eligible next
year unless I have missed something. Interesting. The last thing on their blog is saying "we're about
to launch our 2022 fundraiser" and that was July. Yes, but if you look at their 2022 fundraiser... oh, sorry,
they were, sorry. Yeah, they've got a 2021 fundraiser which didn't make its target so it looks like they
must be launching a new one in 2022 that maybe will run in 2023 that the idea was they were
going to hand it over to new set of editors for the second year and I think that
didn't make its fundraising target and never happened but I don't know whether it's coming back again.
But I didn't want to say too much about that, just that don't nominate them in 2022
because they're not eligible. So Mermaids Monthly were pretty close to making the ballot this year
but didn't quite make it and will not be eligible next year. So keep an eye on them for future years
if they return. Giganotosaurus was last a finalist in 2017, Fireside was last a finalist in 2020.
I don't think the others mentioned in the statement have ever been finalists before but I might be wrong.
So, yes, it would be nice to see some of these categories mixing up a bit and people having a
longer look at the longlist to find things that they want.
Shall we move on to the Locus fundraiser? So, Locus is having what it calls a first
annual crowdfunding campaign. Yes. So for example my pub, my local pub, had a terrible time at the
beginning of the pandemic and it's a very much community pub. It's kind of run as a community
theater, there's a lot of stuff like that. It is the Old Rose and Crown in Walthamstow for anyone
who's listening, and they had a fundraiser to kind of get them over that immediate pandemic-y
hump but there was never any suggestion that... If you're a pub your job is to sell food and drink
to members of the public and theatre tickets in a way that covers your costs, yeah? And if you're
a magazine your job is to sell your magazine to members of the public at a rate that covers the
costs so I wouldn't mind Locus saying "oh god, guys, we're in a bit of a pickle we're having a crowdfunder
to get us over this hump that we find ourselves in", but I feel like the the long-term
goal of a magazine should be to run to break even rather to say "oh and we're going to come back
every year for extra money". It felt a bit odd to me. It's kind of like "yeah, no, we're just going to
be loss-making forever but the authors will support us" and maybe they will? I think this is a really
good argument for why semiprozine is such a tricky category because the difference between a pro
magazine and a semipro magazine is not obvious and I think this blurs it even more. Because obviously,
lots of the semiprozines in the field rely on crowdfunders to happen and I don't think it's
unreasonable to say, you know, "if you like this thing and you want it to keep going throw us some
money". I mean, I don't think it's any more ridiculous than like a pay-what-you-want video game on itch.
I think with more niche stuff and more niche categories it is harder to find the ability to
do that commercially? I mean, I think a pub is a bad example because although I like pubs, I think
especially the old-fashioned community pubs to which you refer... they're very similar and so if one pub
goes out of business there'll be another pub somewhere in your town whereas if Locus goes out of business
there'll be other magazines but there won't be another Locus magazine and so I think there is a
uniqueness to it as well. I mean somewhere in my town if my town is London but not somewhere in my
town if my town is Walthamstow, really. I'm going to say something here which is... as obviously
someone who married someone who lived in the San Francisco area there is a problem which is
San Francisco is rapidly becoming the sort of place where if you are not rich you cannot be
and so that works a lot like if you work for Apple or Google or Facebook or any of these massive
companies where you make a lot of money, living and working in San Francisco is great and hurrah.
But there is a reason that magazines like Macworld have been downsizing their San Francisco
office space and moving to remote workers and that is because having a full-time staff all of whom
live in San Francisco is rapidly going to become untenable. And it's untenable now but in ten years'
time it is going to be worse than it is now. It's a pretty... it's a pretty mean take. You're
basically... because what is your conclusion to this? That they should
move somewhere that is not San Francisco? Or Oakland to be specific? I mean I don't... and I think
that sucks, but I don't see how Locus can remain profitable if it hires six full-time people who
live and work in the Bay Area because I know people who live and work in the Bay Area and they're
moving out and that's because the Bay Area is becoming unlivable and that isn't Locus' fault
but it is true. And it's worse now than it was a decade ago when I met
España and it will be worse in a decade than it is now and so unless Locus have a plan...
Locus can't just stay afloat. Locus will need to find more money because it's getting more
expensive not less and especially with inflation at 10% globally I don't see how this works. And so,
yeah, if they're determined to maintain a staff of six all of whom live in the Bay Area... and it sucks
because I love San Francisco and I think it's part of the death of the area and if we're going to
talk about this we could talk about it and I have really strong and really mournful opinions about
it because I think San Francisco is dying and I think this sort of thing will die because it is
based there. And that's horrible. But it's not unreasonable to try, but equally I don't think
it will work. These funds fulfill three main purposes which are paying people to live and work in the
Bay Area, creating a top-notch print magazine and the overhead for our office space which is
presumably also in the Bay Area. And I'm like, I don't think... Obviously you know I don't believe
in print magazines, I'm just giving away all my text-based documents that's not fundamentally
art-based, so I don't think I believe in any of those three goals. I don't think those three goals
are things that we should be directly supporting. I mean I don't mind if people support them
but somebody's like are you kicking into the Locus Indiegogo the answer is no because you've told me
that you're doing three things that I believe are not good uses for human funds.
I don't really have a problem with print media I mean I don't buy print magazines bu I don't
have a huge problem with it. And especially maintaining a Bay Area office space, I mean... They do say elsewhere
that they basically... I mean I don't know how up-to-date this is but they have a Patreon where they say that
they share some offices in a house in Oakland with lots of other non-profits. So I don't know
how kind of sustainable that is. So my feeling is that yeah the value of Locus is having a news
magazine that covers the field, but that is what I like this is not necessarily tied to it being
in a particular location or producing a print magazine. And what I can't see from this fundraiser
is kind of how sustainable this is? Magazines that fund themselves with an annual Kickstarter: there
are lots of semiprozines that fund themselves with annual Kickstarters in this way. But I assume
they have a goal and that goal is to cover the running expenses of the magazine and it's
usually, their running expenses are more like $20,000 and then they have stretch
goals whereas this is trying to raise $75,000 out of the over $600,000
they need so you know they're saying if they get $75,000 taking
away their subscription and existing revenue, they still need to get $240,000.
That is just such a monumental task to be crowdfunded. What I'm missing here is
how they think in future years they will be on a sustainable level? And can I digress for five
minutes? So, there is a website called Metafilter which I've been reading for many many years and
for many years they've had now an annual fund drive. And what has become clear in the past couple of
years is that they had an annual fund drive which was just about getting them the money they needed to
continue, but it was not sustainable because their other sources of revenue were shrinking. And they
kind of got to this year and went "oh wait, hang on. Our other sources of revenue have been shrinking,
our pool of savings is going down, and actually just asking people for money once a year and getting
a bit is not putting us on a sustainable footing for the future". And so there's lots I
can't get into here but they basically been a change of ownership there's now kind of a community
organization board they've been taking a thorough look at finances, at future funding models, and
this year's fundraising drive has basically said look we've got three models: if we get this much
money we can survive, if we get this much money this is the extra things we can do to make ourselves
more sustainable, and if we get anything above that here's future things we'll do. I'm
sort of looking for something a bit more like that. Are Locus thinking, actually, we can increase
the number of subscriptions, and we can do this kind of fundraising drive? Where we they sell
magazines but they're also selling like a bunch of extra things like you do in any fundraising
auction? Do they think that this is going to get them through every year or are they going to come
back next year? Maybe ad revenues have gone down, subscriptions have increased a bit, the cost of
living has increased a bit and now they actually need $125,000 to survive? They're not
obliged to provide me with their future business plans but when I'm supporting... there's
something is coming and saying "can you help support us for the future?" I like to see
that they have a sustainable plan for the future. Business models change, and Locus is a decade or more
behind. You know, most small special interest magazines have gone fully digital or no longer
exist. Locus has done very well to survive as long as it has with a full-time staff of six
in this space because lots of magazines like that aren't around anymore. Is that true in
our space? Because like Asimov's is still both, right? It's a fiction magazine. This is kind
of a specialist industry magazine. It's difficult because they don't break out their... in the thing
they break it out into paying writers, editors and artists; sustaining issues, website and awards; and
Locus HQ. And Locus HQ is the lowest at 60 grand and paying writers, editors, and artists is 450.
And if you read that you might think "oh, most of their money is going on commissioning content"
but the 450 is where the staff costs for the six full-time staff are. This entire fundraiser would be...
I mean they're asking for $75,000 and if they got rid of their office space that would make up $60,000
of it. But, like, then where you put the Hugos, I guess? No, they were like, "we want to raise a lot of money,
we're going to have an auction". They've got 30 Hugos they'll raise a fair packet.
Oh, that's true. We could bid on them all, and give them out of the inaugural Octothorpies guys
sustaining the issues is in the 130 grand line item and I have no idea how much that costs to do
but I have to be honest I think a Locus magazine that doesn't have an office and doesn't have a
print magazine but does still do what Locus does is way more valuable than a Locus that does have
an office and does have a print magazine but is slowly becoming more and more unviable.
I'd rather see them pivot, and continue. And works remotely. Well, it's tricky right? Because
because like what do you do with the staff? Do you say you move or we fire you? I don't want to have that
conversation with six people I manage. No, no, you say we cannot increase your salary. That's
how this is done. So people go "well we cannot survive in the Bay Area on this salary" and at that point
you go "well, have you considered working working remotely somewhere that is not
in daily commuter range of our offices in Oakland." Many companies have done this, but the
thing is that if a new business started up today to do what Locus does it wouldn't have
an office. Businesses like that don't have offices anymore, if they're new businesses. They only have
offices if they're old businesses, because that's the way these sorts of things used to be done.
Nowadays businesses of this kind work remotely and occasionally hire meeting space. I don't know
how extensive the Locus archives are. I can see that it's something that they are currently preserving
and maybe that needs to be preserved in a library somewhere? But also things like, if you are Locus
you are getting a lot of books delivered to your office so you probably do need some physical
space somewhere. It just doesn't necessarily have to be where it currently is. I mean, review books are
also electronic now. Yeah, but look at like, Scalzi's blog, he still gets a lot of paper books. I don't
know how... Yeah, Langford does too. Yeah, people are still sending paper books as well. I want Locus to
continue, but equally, I have never read Locus and it is not clear to me that the way they are going
about this... Even if they hit their fundraiser this time I would not want to bet money that they
would still exist in five years. Because it doesn't seem like they're making any of the changes they
need to make to be sustainable. So, Locus, hard love, pivot. They're going to have to change a lot or
they're going to die and I don't think they're willing to change a lot so I think they're going
to die? And I don't think that's good but I do think that if you made me bet £10 either way
I wouldn't be betting on them being around in five years. Yeah, I think... see where we are
this time next year because they say they're having an auction and a subscription drive and
potentially they'll get quite a lot of extra subscriptions, which will put them on a good
footing? Because that's what you really need, you need that kind of consistent revenue rather than
people paying you $100 for something cool in an auction. Maybe more
stuff will come out but that's kind of what I'm hoping we'll see over the next year: Exactly
what what the proactive steps are, so that next year isn't actually now we need $100,000
to survive. I'm still not betting you that $10 though. No, me neither.
Shall we do some picks? Picks, picks, picks. What order are we doing this in?
What's happened here, listeners, is Liz and I, last episode, were debating which of us would get to pick
Andor and in order to make this decision easier for us Alison decided to watch the first episode
of Andor so she could pick it too. And so we have a three-way tie and, yeah... And I had a backup
pick in case Liz wanted to pick Andor, and now all is Andor. So obviously I
want to go first because I've only seen the first episode and then if these guys get spoilery I can
just take my headphones off. So I had a couple of things to say about Andor, having watched
exactly one episode. The first is that all of my friends are talking about it, not just John and
Liz but all over the internet people are saying "gosh this series is very good" in a way that I
don't think has happened for the television output of the Star Wars universe before. That it's very
good in terms of what television should be and how it should be and things like that. I know none of
this because I've only seen the first episode. Right from almost the first second you know you're in
the Star Wars universe there's nowhere else you could be there's tons of stuff this is just incredibly
Star Wars-y a bit about it all over the place and I really like that because I like the sense
that they are building a consistent universe here despite the fact that it's enormously diverse
and has all sorts of different things going on, but nevertheless it's... It's all very consistent.
Everyone likes it. You are not wrong! I mean it's true, I... John is the Star Wars fan here I am not
particularly... I mean I like Star Wars but I'm not, like, a fan in the way John is. And I have not in fact
bothered watching any of the other Star Wars TV shows yet. And the internet is loving Andor in a
way I can't remember it loving anything except possibly that time when baby Yoda ate a frog. Yeah. And
even then, that was like a 30 second bit of an episode. Yeah, basically everyone watched it and was like "oh
actually this is what you can do in the Star Wars universe". I think it's the second good TV show in
Star Wars, the first one being Rebels. Rebels is animated so I know a lot of people who just don't
watch animated stuff and you're like "you can watch animated stuff" and they're like "yeah yeah yeah" and they don't.
And also rebels is explicitly aimed at a much younger audience, and it did... And so I think that
is two reasons why it was not widely discussed. In much the same way that the reason that
we didn't get much YA on the Hugo ballot until the Lodestar award was because you don't tend to
nominate stuff aimed at a younger audience in the big serious awards. But Andor is definitely
the first good live-action TV show they've done. I liked Kenobi but it had problems, and one of the
problems it has is it filmed in The Volume. And Andor is filmed uh, in, you know, places. And it
turns out you can do a lot more if you aren't limited to a small circle surrounded by
monitors. Who knew? But yeah, I think one of the senses of place... and I think this goes back to
what Alison was saying about the Star Wars setting. The use of sets and and kind of the use of real
places it makes it feel much more like you're in a place rather than kind of just not, really.
And the Mandalorian feels kind of really insubstantial in a way, and so does Kenobi, that Andor did not.
And the insubstantiality is one of the problems that the prequel trilogy has, that the
original trilogy did not. And I wonder if it comes from over-reliance on this one technique that they
used for the Mandalorian and then carried on using for the other stuff. It feels a lot like sort of,
maybe British 70s TV sci-fi in a good way? I mean someone did a kind of fake 70s opening credits for
Andor which are brilliant. But there's just something about it being, like... there's bits of it set in
in cities, there's bits of it set, you know... they do a lot of walking around hills and in the rain and in
just sort of slightly gloomy-looking remote areas. There's something about that, and there's something
about the fact that the cast is full of British character actors as well. That plus the fact that
Star Wars always had this way of using the technology which has not advanced since the Star Wars of
the 70s. They managed to integrate this... Everything is like giant button-pushing machines like you
find in an abandoned 70s power plant kind of thing. And somehow they integrate all of that and for the
first time it didn't seem to feel like it was deliberately limiting themselves to this
level of technology, it felt like they'd really embraced that and just said "right, this
is our aesthetic for the show and everything's going to make sense". Mmm-mmm. No, exactly. The other thing about
Andor is it is really I thought it got good after episode three I thought the first three episodes...
And I think there is a reason that when the first three episodes dropped on Disney+ it did not
immediately make the sorts of waves that it is making now that it has wrapped up. There are a couple of things
that really kick into high gear after episode three and a couple of annoying narrative devices
that are left behind. And I think first three episodes are setting up the last nine and the last nine
are where the real gold is. Do you think that's fair, Liz? I think so. I think what I will say is that
they dropped the first three episodes together and thereafter it came out week-by-week and I watched
the first three episodes... I didn't watch them all together. I watched one, and then took a break and
watched the next one, and they did not work nearly as well for me as for people who watched the first
three because they do very much form a little kind of mini arc. And that was... I mean the rest of the
season was basically a series of mini arcs and I think that first one works much better as three
episodes together because I didn't feel the episodes had a strong enough episodic structure.
Whereas in the later mini arcs, each episode I think has a much stronger structure even when it's set
into this mini arc. I think also, after I looked at episode three, where I predicted some of the
characters would go is completely not where they went. You know, there were things I was thinking "oh
this is what's going to happen to this person and this person, and nope, completely off." Oh that's good.
That's a good sign. Yeah. Do you mind casting spoilers Alison? I mean I don't mind spoilers, really.
I think our listeners might though. Yeah I'm not going to do any plot spoilers, but Andy Serkis
pops up later in the show and it might be the best performance he's ever given. He is just
amazing in it. Doc Brown or Ben Bailey plays a role which is very good. I didn't recognise him at all!
Like, I've watched him in Taskmaster, I did not realize it was the same person. I thought someone was having
a joke and then they were like no he uses a different name for acting, it's the same person.
What?! Yeah. Yeah. I think he's credited as Ben Bailey, his name's Ben Smith, but he was on Taskmaster as
Doc Brown? So like, I'm very sorry if I get how he is credited wrong but it is all the same man, and I
love that man. He's good man. And one of the reasons why I've been rooting for his character.
There seems to be some scenes of happy natives and I really don't like that. Anyway, onwards.
Yeah, that's the stuff from the first episode about... not Ferrix... Cassian's... Oh, right.
Cassian's background is we are a peaceful untechnological civilization and
I find that very annoying but there we go. I know what you mean about the happy natives thing
Basically there's a line in Rogue One where Cassian says that he's been in this fight since he was
six years old... or is it five years old? But it's like an implausibly young age. And at the time
I assumed that that was hyperbole and in those scenes I don't think he's as young as he says he was
in Rogue One but I think it's basically an attempt to square the circle without just having him
portrayed as an actual child soldier? One of the problems with Star Wars YA media and
kids' media is that Star Wars does actually turn out to have a lot of child soldiers in it because
if you write novels aimed at kids, the kids have to be protagonists, and because it's a story about
war, they end up fighting in a war? And if you think about it too much it gets really awkward really
quickly. But I will say that the happy natives motif does not persist through the entire series.
Can I have a digression where I talk about being old a little bit? Which is that when I was growing
up, which was the 70s, an enormous amount of the cultural touchstones were heavily influenced by
the Second World War and people... And the fact that the creators were people who at the time were
people who had come out of that or been incredibly influenced by the immediate post-war times. It's
true in America as well. And this came up the other day by the fact that I have a
1974 Dad's Army board game which can't go unblurred onto eBay because it has swastikas on the cover
because it's a wartime thing. But everything about the 70s was driven by people's perceptions of the
Second World War, so that there were war stories everywhere. And so Star Wars... That glorifying war
thing was embedded in the first Star Wars movie. And then, of course it's... We've moved away from
that the whole culture has moved away from "all of our stories of war stories or a huge proportion
of our stories of war stories". There's still some of that in the kind of formative much that Star
Wars was developed out of and I think this leads to things like... Because when I was a child there were
an awful lot of stories about child soldiers and there were also an awful lot of child soldiers.
We've changed, I think as a planet. Hopefully for the better. Hopefully we won't go back to a world
where child... Where being a child soldier is glorified. I think you're right and I think
it's tricky because when you read the stories that are aimed at kids, it doesn't seem problematic
because the kids have all the agency, and then you read plot summaries of what happened in
a particular part of Star Wars and it's like then this child was recruited to do this and you're
like "oh no". And it gets a bit... Child spies are another. Yep. You know like Sherlock Holmes had
child spies, child spies are a very big part of literature traditionally. Children are very
excited by the idea of being a child spy and then you actually look at what spies do and you go
"oh, oh no". Or pirates, cabin boys, you know the whole... All of our adventure
literature has this theme running forward through it of pre-teens and young teenage kids doing exciting
grown-up things which are perhaps not that exciting. So I want to call out some other actors just
before we stop talking about Andor. I love Adria Arjona as Bix, she was also – and I don't know if
either of you recognized her – she was Anathema in the TV series Good Omens and she is very different
in both of those, which I think is great testament to how good she is at acting. That's where
I know her from. Yes. I did not recognize her, apparently I don't recognize anyone. Denise Gough is amazing
as Dedra Meero who is just so good. And Genevieve O'Reilly, who was in Revenge of the Sith but
got cut, but plays Mon Mothma, and it's really good to see Mon Mothma being, kind of,
fleshed out given that she just randomly pops up in Return of the Jedi. And it's quite nice to see
that character come back. And there is another I don't want to do... There's a piece of casting
which is a huge spoiler for a plot thing which I'm not going to say out loud, but I thought
that that was good. And also, one last thing, the droid! The droid is the best droid. Best droid. So
it struck me when I was watching Andor that I had just been on a ride called Rise of the
Resistance but you could basically call Andor Rise of the Resistance instead? And it basically
digs into the thing that I for one have always really wanted to see in the Star Wars universe which
is the early days of the resistance. How do you form this resistance movement which
will go on to bem you know, the... The Rebellion. What, John? The Resistance is 30
years later, this is the Rebellion. Yeah, well, this is the Rebellion which goes on to be the
Resistance, right? This is the Rebellion that leads into Rogue One. And this is something... This is the
other reason I really like Rebels because... a lot of the stuff that Andor does to show
the early days of the Rebellion and to show Mon Mothma's role in that, and to kind of highlight
people like Saw Gerrera and how they fit in was done by Rebels, and is being revisited by Andor.
And so a lot of those themes are really cool but it's weird to revisit them with people who haven't
watched Rbels because a lot of it is really... I mean I don't know how much this is conscious but
like a lot of these themes are the same themes. Is Rebels set at roughly the same time? Rebels
is set later but came out earlier? Yeah, but you're basically saying so people who like Andor should
go and watch Rebels even though they are slightly worried about watching animated things which
I would endorse your notion is... You know, go and watch animated things guys, they're good. I
don't know if this one is, but in general. Rebels is aimed at a much younger audience so
is probably not as hard-hitting as Andor but I do... I think it is brilliant, but yeah. I mean I'm
prepared to go and watch Rebels, I just probably was not very aware of it and also
don't remember ever being on any kind of TV service I had access to. I don't know where it was broadcast
in the UK. Ah, no, that is fair. I assume it's on Disney+ now right? It is now, yeah. I also don't
know where it was broadcast Liz. I've only had Disney+ for like a year because I got it a
year later than you did so I have not caught up with everything that was on Disney+. Oh no, yeah, that's
that's fair, that's fair. Anyway, I think... Okay, so I think what I'm saying is I like what Andor does
even if something else has already done it. I think they really lucked out with the fact that they
kind of already had an actress who was Mon Mothma, but who is definitely up to the task of what she
has to do in this one, which is, I don't know... It's very fascinating to watch the contrast
between her, between Stellan Skarsgård's character, and Andor. And I think the only thing I've
seen that I kind of agree with is some criticism that it feels more like a show which is interested
in a wide range of characters, and maybe loses a bit of its focus on Andor, and I think
Diego Luna does a great job of what is sometimes a very kind of underplayed... his role is quite
underplayed, in that he has to do a lot of the heavy lifting. He never gets to do the big kind of like...
Well there's sort of some big scenes and big monologues that other characters get and it
feels like he gets a little bit short-changed on some of that? And has to do a lot just kind of
from his expressions and from us watching him in some ways react to things. So that would be my
one complaint is that sometimes I was a bit more interested in people who were not Andor rather
than Andor. Which I probably shouldn't because it's his TV show. But that's a very minor complaint
really. I think, and maybe I'm wrong... I think that one of the great things about Star Wars is like the
people around the people we care about? Like, I don't think... the original trilogy wouldn't have been
better if it focused more on Luke, and I don't think the sequel trilogy would have been better if
it had focused more on Rey, and arguably I think one of the problems the prequel trilogy has is it focuses
too much on Anakin. And so I think, in actuality, although I see what you mean, I think that's one
of the strengths of Star Wars as a franchise. Is that although it is literally a series of stories
about chosen ones, it doesn't focus on those chosen ones as much as it might. Like the focus is much
less on the chosen one in any of the given movies than it is on the superhero in a Marvel
movie for instance. And I think that is to Star Wars' credit. I will also say I don't understand
how I skipped complimenting Diego Luna's acting, because he is great. Like, so good in this entire
thing. He is so good, he nails it. And so I think you're right there, that in some places he does a
lot with a little but I do wonder whether they knew he would and so they were able to do that. I
wonder if they'd had a lesser actor they would have had to focus it more on Andor because
there wouldn't have been as much there if they hadn't. It might be a, yeah... It might be an
expression of trust in the actor, I guess. We liked Andor, listeners! I haven't liked it yet. I've only
liked a tenth of it, or a twelfth of it. But I am expecting to like the rest. I'm very much looking
forward to watching it. I have had to pause my ongoing Expanse watch in order to fit Andor in.
This does beg a question, and the question it begs is is this better... I would argue this is
probably going to get nominated for Best Long Form... because I don't think there's a standout
episode, I think it's just a very tight 12 episode thing. And I would argue similar about Severance? So
then my question is if this and Severance are on the Long Form ballot, which do you vote for?
Um, Everything Everywhere All At Once. If it was between this and Severance which would you vote for? I've
only seen one episode give me a chance. I think I did say that. Okay. Look, Alison has managed
to watch all of Severance which means by Alison's standards it was extremely compelling because
she's watched it in, you know, under a year. So, I mean it seems like Severance. Oh, yeah, no,
could be argued... What about you, Liz? It's tricky, but I think I would probably go with Andor. But
bear in mind I just literally finished watching Andor, so. I've literally not had a chance... As soon
as I noticed Andor I started watching it and then we were prevented from watching more episodes by
not being at home so we'll see a second ep. Ask me the next time how many episodes I've watched
because it might be 12. I am going to be a bad Star Wars fan. I think I preferred Severance to Andor. If
it was between the two I would vote for Severance. It would be a strange universe if John ends up
voting for something non-Star Wars where I vote for a Star Wars thing, won't it. Yes. Come back in January
when we're going to discuss this in more detail, guys. And that was the Octothorpe podcast. And it's goodbye
from me. It's goodbye from me. And it's goodbye from me.
I have an anti-pick for the logo which I hate with a fiery fiery passion because people talk about
the effective use of negative space and this isn't it. This is how to do something clever with
negative space and therefore make your logo unreadable and stupid. And apparently there was a logo for
this that was released a couple of years ago that looks like a perfectly reasonable logo and now
there's this logo which is unreadable and crap and oh god it's very annoying. I will say I disagree with
Alison on the logo because I correctly read the logo and it says Andor. So I don't think it's
unreadable. Hot take. I quite like the logo. I don't have strong feelings on it, I guess? I'm like a four out of
ten. Yeah, my hot take is I don't care. The theme music for this episode was Fanfare for Space by
Kevin Macleod at incompetech.com used under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 license.
This podcast will end at the beep. Beeeep